<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/9/17 images: 182-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government  JLPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1942.SECRET. .. Copy No.W.P.-(R) W 17.jfflrcA 25, 1942. t(WAR CABINET.REPORT FOR THE MONTH OF FEBRUARY 1942 FOR THEDOMINIONS, INDIA, BURMA AND THE COLONIES, and mandated   TERRITORIES.THE DOMINIONS.Report by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.CANADA.(1) General Position. iPRESS comment during the month on Imperial affairs was marked by an attitude of dejection. The fall of Singapore was regarded as almost inevitable,so that no particular surprise was evinced, at the news of its capture. The pressbad predicted also that Sumatra was likely to go the same way. Much anxietywas shown over the continuing Japanese advances, particularly now that australia is directly threatened. The fact that the Japanese air force, thought,before the war to be weak, had shown itself so effective exercised a depressing effect on the public, and throughout the press there was no optimistic comment on affairs in the Far East. The escape of the German battleships from Brestovershadowed, however, even the bad news from Singapore. Many Canadiannewspapers quoted angry United Kingdom press comment on the incident, but,in general, themselves maintained a reasonable and balanced view. following on all these events, the news of the United Kingdom Cabinet reorganisation waswarmly welcomed; the position of Sir Stafford Cripps, in particular, was thesubject of considerable interest to the Canadian public. Speculation about his political views, particularly in relation to the future status of India, was rife!The earlier change, by which Lord Beaverbrook became Minister of Production,was popular in Canada, and confidence was expressed that he would be able to overcome the difficulties of under-production. -\Dr. Temple&apos;s appointment as Archbishop of Canterbury was regarded as agood one.News from Libya continued to be vaguely disturbing, with cautiousexplanations by the press for the British lack of success. Canadian editors werenoticeably shy of comment on the support which Vichy is thought to have givento General Rommel.Much interest has been shown in the prospect of the establishment of directdiplomatic relations with Russia, and, in general, comment has been friendly,although there was inevitable talk in some quarters of the dangers of Communism,a he general desire appears, however, to be to let bygones be bygones, and friendlypublicity, at times enthusiastic in tone, is given to the continuing news of russian military successes.As a result of the spate of military disasters and the general lack of any outstanding Allied success in the war operations, Canadian opinion has tended to concentrate on domestic issues.   Lively interest was shown in recent bye-elections, where, in Quebec East, Mr. Laurent, the new Minister of Justice,[23603] B
achieved a majority of 3,916 in defeating, much to everyone&apos;s surprise, the anti-conscriptionist candidate, In South York, regarded as a safe Conservative seatMr. Meighen, the recently elected leader of the Conservative Party, was defeated&apos;Press comment on these elections was that they constituted a vote of confidence in Mr. Mackenzie King&apos;s administration and justified him in going ahead withthe plebiscite plan. On the 20th February the Canadian House of Commonspassed the motion to adopt the address-in-reply by a majority of 83 votes. Theway is now open for the introduction of the formal legislation on which&apos; the plebiscite legislation regarding conscription depends.Much difference of opinion exists about Canada&apos;s status on the Allied WarBoards, while some dissension was shown over Canada&apos;s position vis-a-vis theImperial War Cabinet, some sections of the press taking the view that canada is slighted by not being directly represented, others that Canada is shirkino- thequestion of full participation in case the Government might be held to blame forany future disasters which might befall the Imperial and Allied cause.(2) Naval, Military and Air Activities.Enemy submarine activities in the Atlantic extended further westwardduring the month and took place along the Atlantic seaboard from Cape Hatterasnorthwards; since practically all available anti-submarine forces are engagedin convoy duties in the Central Atlantic, only small anti-submarine striking forces have been available in Canadian coastal areas. Corvettes and anti-submarinefitted mine-sweepers from local forces have been used for the protection of canadian coastal convoys, assisted by United States and Canadian air patrols.All Japanese fishing boats on the west coast of Canada, to the number ofmore than 1,100, have now been immobilised. Six have been requisitioned for naval service and are already in commission, and it is intended to requisition anadditional fourteen shortly.It has been decided to organise a Women&apos;s Royal Naval Service.Major-General F. Worthington has been appointed to command the CanadianArmoured Division in Canada.The 1st Canadian Army Tank Brigade was visited by Lord Cranborne, theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs, during the month, and King Peter ii of Yugoslavia visited No. 5 Canadian General Hospital on the 2nd.R.C.A.F. squadrons, working in conjunction with the R.A.F., took part in anumber of offensive operations by day and night, although both operational and non-operational flying was again somewhat curtailed by bad weather.Nos. 405, 408 and 420 Squadrons carried out bombing operations over North-west germany and Brest. In addition, Nos. 401, 403 and 411 Spitfire Squadrons,No. 405 Wellington Squadron, Nos. 408 and 420 Hampden Squadrons and No. 407Hudson Squadron all took part in the attack on enemy warships in the Channelon the 12th February, when No. 408 Squadron were able to press home the attack and No. 401 Squadron claimed two enemy aircraft destroyed and two damaged.Furthermore, No. 402 (Hurricane Bomber) Squadron attacked a formation of enemy destroyers during the latter part of the month and saw direct hits on two destroyers, which were subsequently categorised as one probably sunk and onebadly damaged.COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.(3) General Position.The march of events in the Far East has left the Australian public extremelyanxious, and the fall of Singapore has been a shattering blow, Although anxietyfor the safety of Australia increased rapidly, the attitude of the general public in regard to United Kingdom leadership steadied, and criticism of this countrypractically disappeared now that war is at the very gates of Australia.Australians realise that the war is indivisible, and, as this view has gainedground, an increasing appreciation of the fact that Australia must help herselfand rid herself of complacency was shown. The attacks on Port Darwin, andthe danger of the Allied cause in Java, stimulated tihe entire press to stir the
country to even greater efforts. The week in which Singapore fell, and theGerman battleships escaped, was regarded in Australia as one of the grimmestof the war, comparable with the disaster of Dunkirk. But the general reaction to these events was to maintain the belief in Mr. churchill&apos;s leadership, thoughit was felt that there was evidence of Service weaknesses which required&quot;rigorous&quot; examination and ruthless correction.&quot; The situation in Burmacaused some concern, but the offensive spirit shown by the Allied navies in drivingoft&apos; the Japanese invasion fleet from Bali gave some encouragement to a pessimisticpublic.The United Kingdom Cabinet changes were warmly welcomed, and approval,in particular, of Sir Stafford Crippss appointment was shown. The inclusionof the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs in the War Cabinet gave muchsatisfaction, and, commenting on this, the Sydney Morning Herald, said,&quot; Dominions who do not desire to claim direct representation in the War cabinet will none the less have their views officially presented.&quot; Australian interest inthe question of representation has now largely died down.In the battle for Libya some disappointment was felt over RommelFssuccesses, and the danger of the effect of any considerable reverses in Libya onthe political situation in Egypt was appreciated in Australia.The fact that the United States was not represented on the Pacific Council,and that its Headquarters were in London and not in Washington, gave rise to criticism, some sections of the press tending to regard the Council as &quot; cumber-some &quot; and unwieldy.In view of the situation in which Australia now finds herself, there was ahigh degree of public interest in domestic issues. The Commonwealth government decided to form a Home Guard on the United Kingdom model. The local presshas been full of criticism of A.R.P. and evacuation muddles, and the Laxity ofthe control over enemy aliens, particularly of the many Italians in Queensland,was widely commented on. &quot; Ruthless mobilisation of the nation&apos;s resources &quot;was the cry, and the Cabinefs decision that Australian resources, human andmaterial, were to be completely mobilised was very well received. Pressure wasrenewed for the formation of a National Government, and the Opposition becamerestive at the apparent lack of action by Mr. Curtin&apos;s Government, particulardisapproval being shown at the Government^ vacillation in dealing with theindustrial disturbances which still deter the country&apos;s war effort.(4) Naval, Military and Air Activities.H.M.A.S. Australia is acting as flagship of the Anzac Squadron.H.M.A.S. Canberra was employed on convoy duties in the Indian Ocean, and h.M.A.S. Adelaide, Westralia and Kanimbla have also been engaged in similarduties in Australian waters.H.M.A.S. Perth left for the Netherlands East Indies towards the latter partof the month.Two mine-sweepers and one &apos;&apos; Tribal&apos;&apos; class destroyer were launched duringthe month.Several merchant ships were seriously damaged during the. air raid onDarwin on the 19th February. Two fuel tanks and wharfage facilities were alsobadly damaged.The naval coast-watching organisation in territories to the north-east ofAustralia was continuing to function in certain areas despite japanese occupation; some coast-watchers have taken their tele-radio sets to suitable points in the bush and remained in contact.The Japanese attack on Ambon was strongly resisted by one A.I.F. battalionand the local Dutch troops; it appears that two Japanese cruisers, one submarine and! one destroyer were sunk by coast-defence artillery or mine-fields. After astubborn defence, the troops were forced back into the hills and there has been nocontact with Ambon since.Japanese forces landed in Timor on the 21st February near Koepang andiJJilli. Our forces consisted of one A.I.F. battalion and coastal artillery unitswith some United Kingdom anti-aircraft units at Koepang and one A.I.F.independent company at Dilli. There were some Dutch forces at both places.Apart from the fact that both Koepang and Dilli have been reported occupied byuie enemy, no information concerning our forces has been received.[23603] . B 2
The 8th Division A.I.F. and! R.A.A.F. aircraft were engaged in the fighting in Malaya, the withdrawal to Singapore and the subsequent resistance in the island until the surrender.Fighter and Bomber Squadrons of the R.A.A.F. have earned out routineoperations from the United Kingdom and in the Middle East in co-operation withthe R.A.F. .   .The Royal Australian Air Force units in Australia carried out reconnaisance-reconnaissances throughout the islands to the northward and shipping protectionduties.   Enemy aerdromes at Raboul were also attacked on several occasions.(5) Economic A activities.The Commonwealth Government announced on the 10th February a com-prehensive scheme for the control of sales of investments, profits, wages and prices. The far-reaching Regulations issued for this purpose have proved insome respects highly controversial, and after examination by an all-partycommittee they have since been amended in certain important particulars. the declared object of this new scheme is to bring about a truly total war effortaccompanied by a genuine equality of sacrifice, but it appears that the Regula-tions have been somewhat hastily conceived and may in certain directions proveunworkable.NEW ZEALAND.(6) General Position.As might be expected, the New Zealand press in the early stages of the monthshowed great anxiety about the fate of Singapore. The general attitude appearsto have been that the object of the defenders of Singapore, the Netherlands east indies, and every other defended place in the South-West Pacific must be to contain as large a number of the enemy as is possible until Great Britain and america could muster their forces to regain control of the South-West Pacific.The fall of Singapore, when it came, quickened apprehension in New Zealandover the country&apos;s relative impotence, and an undercurrent of defeatist talk wasnoticed, arising probably from the insidious influence of Tokyo broadcasts, whichhave had a large audience. Criticism of mistakes made by the United Kingdombecame more noticeable than has been the case in the past, and a tendency to askwhat New Zealand may expect from the United Kingdom in return for herunstinted help in the Allied cause was observed. New Zealand opinion seems tohave been that a sufficiently high degree of priority has not been given to theneeds of the South-West Pacific, and it was felt that the importance of the warin the Far East was still not fully appreciated in London. Much admiration was shown for the resistance of the Dutch authorities in the Netherlands East Indies.In view of the graver events nearer to New Zealand, the news of the escape of theGerman battleships excited little comment, although the event was regarded as adisaster. A stream of comment from Australia and the United States about thedefect in the civil administration of Malaya undermined New Zealand&apos;s confi-dence in the British High Command, and, in order to offset this unfortunatetendency, the Prime Minister and Leader of the Opposition both broadcastexpressing confidence in United Kingdom leadership, and urging abstention fromcarping criticism.New Zealand interest in the question of direct representation in an imperial war Cabinet was maintained. The general feeling seems to have been in favourof such representation, though the practical difficulties of giving effect to such astep were fully recognised. The United Kingdom. Cabinet changes accordinglyhad a particularly good press, and the inclusion of the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs in the War Cabinet was duly appreciated. &quot; If satisfactoryliaison can be maintained between Mr. Attlee and the Dominion Government,.andtheir representatives in London^ there is no apparent reason why this should not meet the requirements of the situation for voicing the Dominion&apos;s point of view,&apos;was a typical comment.
In Foreign Affairs interest in the Russian successes has been maintained.In Empire matters, news about India has been prominent, and the general viewappears to be that concessions by the United Kingdom Government would now be wise. .   .With regard to purely domestic issues, the New Zealand Prime Minister was criticised for taking the portfolio of Finance and thus adding considerably to hisalready considerable responsibilities. The Government was taken to task also for not giving more information about New Zealand&apos;s war position, and for notpermitting open debate on the Far Eastern situation.(7) Naval, Military and Air Activities.H.M.N.Z. ships Leander and Achilles were engaged on convoy and escortoperations with the Anzac Squadron.The additional call-up on the 20th January of single men and married menwithout children between the ages of 18 and 46 had as its object the increase ofthe Territorial Force from 35.000 to about 65,000 men. Most of the men thuscalled up for home defence belong to classes previously earmarked for reinforce-ment of the forces overseas. Their enrolment, therefore, points to a modificationof the programme of reinforcements for the Middle East, which has also been affected by the despatch of further troops from New Zealand to Fiji. No further reinforcements from New Zealand for the Middle East are likely to be available atpresent, but it is considered that the second New Zealand Expeditionary Force hassufficient reinforcements for six months, including one period of intense activitynot involving abnormally heavy losses. The effect of the permanent mobilisation of the Territorial Force and National Military Reserve has compelled the Govern-ment to give serious consideration to proposals for economising man-power in industry.A Maori battalion is to be formed for home defence service.Women may now enlist for auxiliary duties in the Army.A further draft of 900 all ranks, to complete the establishment of 8,400, areto be sent to Fiji.The war establishment of the Territorial Force, including former NationalMilitary Reserve units, is 66,376 all ranks; of this number, 41,653 are nowmobilised.The present strength of New Zealand forces serving overseas is 43,313.Casualties to New Zealand personnel of the three Services are as follows -killed 2,378, prisoners of war 4,378, missing 2.452. and wounded 4.080.UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.(8) General Position.The fall of Singapore has done much to destroy the South African attitudeof detachment towards the war, and even the Opposition press now recognises thepossibility of direct attack on South Africa. Attention has also been drawn tothe possibility of Madagascar falling into Japanese hands, thus imperilling the safety of the Union and of the Cape route. The security of Eastern Union ports and of the Cape route is fully realised in South Africa, and consultations are now taking place with regard to increased defence measures. The Opposition pressmaintained an uneasy objectivity in reporting Far Eastern news, though losing-no opportunity of indulging in carping criticism of the Government for havingcontinued in the war.During the month, the pro-Government press took the line that, if the vichy government has helped to supply Rommel&apos;s armies, it should be treated as anunscrupulous enemy and the tolerant policy of drift should immediately be changed. As regards Madagascar, the Opposition press refuses to recognise thepresent position of the island as constituting a danger, though the possibility ofthe Union Government co-operating with the de Gaullist forces to rallyMadagascar has been widely discussed.Much disappointment was shown over Rommel&apos;s success in Libya, and thefeeling that there is little to show for South African losses was expressed.   It is
felt that the two Union divisions in the North constitute a serious drain on SouthAfrican man-power, and, since conscription is not regarded at present as practical politics, the question of arming the natives in order to solve the increasing man-power difficulties has been discussed in the press. Lord Cranborne&apos;s speech onthe Abyssinian Treaty was given a good report in pro-Government newspapersand taken as proof that Great Britain had no imperialistic aims, thoughOpposition papers commented ironically on Abyssinia&apos;s new &quot;freedom.&quot;The announcement of the United Kingdom Cabinet changes was well received; the appointment of Sir Stafford Cripps was of particular interest.Opposition newspapers took the line that the appointment of Sir Stafford Crippssingles him out as the only statesman of outstanding ability after Mr. churchill and as the inevitable successor to the Prime Minister in a Britain which wishes tomaintain relations with a Socialist ally.The Government press pointed out the advantages of closer Dominion repre-sentation in the United Kingdom War Cabinet by the appointment of the deputy prime Minister as Secretary of State for the Dominions.Despite the promulgation of the death penalty for sabotage, telegraph and telephone wires have continued to be cut in the Transvaal, and an attempt wasmade during February to blow up the police headquarters at Pretoria.Opposition dissension continues, and the breach between the various factionsis widening. Dr. Malan referred to the Ossewa Branclwag as an &quot; organisationof gangsters,&quot; and ordered Nationalists in the Cape and Transvaal to resign fromthe organisation. In return, Dr. van Rensburg ordered a boycott of Nationalistnewspapers. Mr. Pirow is trying to embarrass the Government by working up a&quot; Red scare,&quot; but it is not thought that he can do anything to deflect the Govern-ment from their policy of support for Russia, which is regarded as essential forvictory over Germany.(9) Naval, Military and Air Activities.Seaward Defence. There were 49 vessels in commission at the end ofFebruary.The recent publication of full lists of casualties sustained by the two SouthAfrican Divisions in Libya, especially in the fighting at Sicli Rezegh, has emphasised the urgent need of more recruits; a, wide recruiting campaign started at the New Year. It is thought that there must be at least 50,000 loyal south africans of military age ignoring the call to the colours, but it is realised that inmany cases financial considerations are the cause of an unwillingness to join.The implications of Japan&apos;s entry into the war and the danger of a Japaneseattack upon Union ports are fully realised; home defence services are being organised and overhauled and the call for more volunteers to man coastal batteriesis having an encouraging response..The first course for women coast defence personnel recently passed out22 women artillery specialists, who have been posted to batteries; a secoud courseof 50 more women volunteers started early in the year. Reports are favourableas to their standard of efficiency.The South African Air Force almost exactly doubled its strength during1941; its strength at the end of the year was 3,177 officers and 23,477 other ranks.It is still the most popular unit from the recruiting point of view. There is alsoa steady flow of recruits for the Women&apos;s Auxiliary Air Force.(10) Southern Rhodesia.Mr. J. II. Smit, the Minister of Finance in Sir Godfrey Huggins&apos; Govern-ment, recently resigned office and announced in the press his intention to forma new &quot; Democratic &quot; Party. In his letter of resignation he stated that he hadnoticed with regret that Sir G. Huggins was becoming more and more influenced by those of his colleagues with &apos;&apos; extreme left&apos;&apos; tendencies, but there were evidently also more personal considerations involved. Sir G. Huggins subse-quently moved in the Legislative Assembly for a vote of confidence in hisGovernment, the motion being carried by 18 votes to 10. He afterwardsreorganised his Ministry,, distributing his own previous departmental responsibilities to other Ministers, and bringing in one new member(Mr. Danziger) as Minister of Finance.
Discussion of the question of the amalgamation of the RhodesiasNyasaland seems likely to die down, as Sir G. Huggins has now recognised thatit is impossible for His Majesty s Government in the United Kingrom and forthe United Kingdom Parliament to give the necessary consideration to the amalgamation issue in present circumstances. It has been decided in thecircumstances that publication of the Note prepared by Lord Hailey following&apos;his visit to Africa m 1940, on the bearing of native policy on the amalgamationissue should be deferred until due consideration of the problem of amalgamationbecomes practicable. A statement to this effect has been made in the House ofCommons and in Southern Rhodesia.(11) EIRE.Mr. de Valera in his public speeches continues to warn the people of Eireof the dangers threatening them. Speaking at Naas on. the 3rd February, he saidthat &quot; any man would be a fool not to plan for at least four more years of war.&quot;Unless there was something like a miracle, he said, Eire, despite all her efforts,would be forced into conflict. If their country were attacked, the conditions would become largely what they had become on the Continent. &quot; The country would become a cockpit. If one belligerent attacked, it would almost be acertainty that the other would attack, and we ourselves take a hand in it too.&quot;A quarter of a million soldiers were needed, trained to fight to maintain theirliberty.Mr. de Valera then went on to tell the farmers, who formed the majority ofhis audience, that, if they did not produce enough wheat to provide Eire withbread, their whole economy would be upset.There is no doubt that the question of wheat and bread supplies is causinglively anxiety in Eire. Speaking at Eimis on the 27th February, Mr. de Valeraappealed for lower consumption of bread in Eire, and suggested the substitu-tion of potatoes and milk. He said that Eire would be 100,000 tons short between this and next harvest.The price of sugar-beet is also to be increased, and, as a result, the priceof both bread and sugar will be increased after the next harvest.At the beginning of February Mr. Lemass announced that consumers muststill be content with half an ounce of tea each week. He had stated early inJanuary that tea shipments purchased in India had first to be shipped to theUnited States and thence conveyed by Eire ships to Eire.The Devereux murder trial which was concluded during February hasreceived much publicity in the Eire press. Two persons were originally accusedbefore a civil court of the murder of Devereux, a petrol salesman ofMaudlinstown, County Wexford, whose body was found in Tipperary inSeptember 1941, twelve months after he had disappeared. Probably as a resultof intimidation, however, witnesses having first-hand knowledge and who had made signed statements to the police, declined to give evidence in court. the eire Government thereupon entered a &quot;nolle prosequi,&quot; with the result that nojudgment was given. One of the witnesses was arrested, and subsequently legis-lation was passed through the Dail to authorise the production of &quot;voluntaryor lawfully-taken-down statements as evidence even in the absence or against the will of the persons concerned.&quot;Four persons were then charged with the murder before a military court, andthree were convicted while the fourth was acquitted but rearrested immediately.j-Wo of the convicted men have been reprieved and their sentences commuted tohfe imprisonment. In the case of the third man, George Plant, the Eireauthorities have declined to remit the sentence. The victim and. ail the accusedwere members of the I.R.A. Both Devereux and the accused had a police recordw the United Kingdom in connection with a bombing outrage at the beginningof the war.During discussion in the Dail on the legislation connected with the Devereuxcase, Mr. MacEntee admitted that he did not believe that if the I.R.A. washeated with clemency and mercy it would perish because there had grown upround it a set of vested interests fed from sources which could not be described.We cannot,&quot; he said, &quot; give yon precise details as to the extent of this rebellions
conspiracy, but those who control it are desperate, unscrupulous and bloodihardened men who will stop at nothing to enforce their opinions upon theirassociates.&quot; ,;&quot; Mr. Cosgrave described the Government policy for law and order as an absolute failure, and remarked that they had from Government benches mention of organised violence and murder, but the name of the organisation responsiblewas never mentioned. It was the Governments duty, he said, to tell the people that it was a national crime to enrol in this organisation and to inform them ofits name. :Mr. Brennan, the Eire Minister in Washington, delivered to Mr. SimmerWelles a summary of Mr. de Valera&apos;s protest against the landing of UnitedStates troops in Northern Ireland without his being consulted. Mr. Brennanafterwards indicated that Mr. Welles had given him assurances that the presenceof United States troops in Northern Ireland was in no way a threat to Eire.Mr. J. M. Dillon, who was elected Vice-President of the Fine Gael party at its annual meeting, said that he believed an attempt was being made to prisethe people of Eire apart from their traditional alliance with the people of theUnited States. &quot; In my judgment, the German Government is using its policyof terror and threatening our people with an immediate and terrible blitz if weapproach any closer to the United States. That threat is shortly going to takethe form of warning us that, if we do not draw further from America, the blitzwill.come upon us. If in some awful hour our people accept in exchange for theIrish-American alliance any form of co-operation with the Nazi-Fascist Powers&quot;of Europe, it will be merely the introduction of a development which will end in Ireland being turned into a, German Gibraltar in the Atlantic. whatever the United States ask from us for its protection and safety it should get for theasking. If it does not, the name of Eire will become synonymous with disloyaltyand treachery.&quot;Subsequently Mr. Dillon resigned from the Fine Gael party. It had beenapparent for some time that Mr. Dillon held views on Eire&apos;s neutrality that were at variance with those of his part)&apos; as well as the other main parties in the Dail.In his reply to the letter of resignation, Mr. Cosgrave said that he had reluctantlycome to the conclusion that the interests and the usefulness of the party to thecountry would, best be served by accepting the resignation tendered by Mr. Dillon.He admitted that a sense of duty had compelled Mr. Dillon to pursue a particular course in relation to external policy in emergency which he could not in theinterests of the country approve.&apos; In an address to the Cavan County Convention of Fianna Fail, Mr. de Valerareferred once more to the question of partition. He said that, &quot; so far as the26 counties were concerned, they were as free as any State in the world.&apos;Unfortunately, there was a portion of their country cut off, and until that portionwas reunited to the rest of the country no nationalist could say that the nationalobjective had been achieved.&quot; Mr. de Valera stressed the point that the objective was the unity of the whole country and the revival of its language.INDIA.Report by the Secretary of State for India.(12) Political Situation.1. In the political field there were no positive developments. The PrimeMinisters reply to the Sapru appeal was awaited in an atmosphere of expectancy,fostered by the demand from many quarters inside and outside India for adeclaration of India&apos;s independence of Whitehall and the transfer of power toa&apos;.&apos;national Government &quot; and encouraged by the message issued to the indian people by Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek in&apos;which he expressed the hope thatGreat Britain would as speedily as possible give real political power to theIndian people.1&apos; 2. The fall of Singapore and the further advances made by the Japaneseinevitably increased anxieties in India, particularly in the cities and towns of theEastern seaboard.   The spread of anti-war and &apos; defeatist rumours throughout
(13) Indian States. &apos;Though there were no signs of panic there was a general lowering of moralein the States as the result of Japanese successes. The press, however, remainedsteady and loyal.Action had to be taken against the Maharaja of Rewa, the largest State in central India, in view of his suspected complicity in certain murders in the Stateof which details have come to light. He agreed to submit to a Commission ofEnquiry into the charges against him and is being excluded from theadministration and the territory of his State pending further investigationrequired to complete the case to be put before the Commission.(14) Foreign and Frontier Relations.1. Afghanistan. There is little to report from Afghanistan this month.His Majesty&apos;s Minister has paid a visit to India in order to discuss with theGovernment of India questions arising in regard to our general policy inAfghanistan2. North-West Frontier.-The Faqir of Ipi&apos;s present plan of campaignappears to be to work up with the aid of intimidation by hostile gangs oppositionto the construction of defence works in the Khaisora, Shaktu and Tank Zamvalleys. Air action has been necessary on occasions against these gangs and useful co-operation has been received from tribesmen within whose territory thehostiles endeavoured to operate. Otherwise the frontier has remained quiet.100 Mahsuds have been recruited for training as motor transport mechanics.Tribal reaction to the news of the fall of Singapore has been one of disdainthat so grave a reverse should have been suffered at the hands of such foes. Thisblow to our urestige may be expected to have adverse consequences.3. Persian GwZ/.-His Highness Sheikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa,K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrein, died on the 20th February after a stroke. TheAl Khalifa family have agreed without dispute upon the succession of his eldestson, Sheikh Salman, and His Majesty&apos;s Government have therefore decided to accord him formal recognition forthwith. He has issued a proclamationannouncing his assumption of the Rulership. which contains the following,words : &quot; I shall continue to strengthen the proved ties with the British Empireand shall always maintain its friendship.&quot;4. China. General Chiang Kai-shek, accompanied by Mrs. chiang kai-shek -shek, made a visit lasting a fortnight to India, where he was the guest ofthe Viceroy at Delhi. He held a number of useful discussions with the viceroy and Commander-in-Chief. on matters of military and political interest with aview to the closer co-ordination of the efforts&apos; of India and China against japanese attack. His main p re-occupation was with the improvement of communications and the urgent need for us to maintain touch with the Chinese[23603] cthe month, encouraged by Axis broadcasts and by stories circulated by-evacuees.from the overrun territories, caused serious concern. Industrial centres werenot, so far, appreciably affected, but a certain amount of labour unrest in Calcuttagave rise to anxiety, and recruiting suffered. On the other hand, there was an appreciable hardening of opinion against the Japanese partly from realisation of the implications of the fall of Singapore, but largely owing to the visit toIndia of Generalissimo and Madame Chiang Kai-shek. Congress leadersrepeatedly affirmed their condemnation of Japanese and German aggression whileprofessing their helplessness under the present regime to assist the victims of aggression. Neither Congress nor the Moslem League had come forward toco-operate with Government in the war effort, although the League professedwillingness to do so on terms which would render Hindu co-operation unattainable&apos;-even m civil defence matters either party preferred to set up its own organisation for assisting the civilian population rather than co-operate with the authorities
armies and, if this is broken, to re-establish it. Part of his stay was spent ina tour of the Khyber, Poona, Rawalpindi and Lahore and he was favourablyimpressed by what he saw of the Indian army during his tour. He expressed himself as particularly gratified that he was told everything in connection with military matters and was regarded as an equal and an Ally and not as a&quot; backward boy.&quot; The whole visit passed in the most friendly atmosphere andfeelings on all sides were most cordial. The General and his wife and the wholeof their staff were much liked by all who came into contact with them. -In hisfarewell message to the Viceroy, the Generalissimo expressed his satisfaction thatthe result of his visit had been to strengthen co-operation in the fight against thecommon aggressor. .He also saw several Indian political leaders during the course of his visit,including Mr. Gandhi and Mr. Nehru of the Indian Congress Party, andMr. Jinnah of the Moslem League.Following upon the Generalissimo&apos;s visit, it has been announced that theGovernment of India have decided to establish a post to be known as the ChinaRelations Officer in Calcutta. It will be held at the outset by Sir Edward Cook,late Governor of the Bank of Egypt. The functions of this new officer will beto co-ordinate the various activities of the Government of India&apos;s several departments, the Reserve Bank of India and the Governmentof Bengal in matters relating to the common war effort of India and China and to the transportationof supplies to China with the Chinese organisations which have been set up in Calcutta. At the same time the Chinese Government have proposed, and the&quot;Government of India have agreed, that they should appoint a representative withthe title of Commissioner and with the local rank of Minister to the headquarters of the Government of India at Delhi. The Government of India propose toreciprocate by the appointment of an Indian representative at Chunking. Theseappointments should have a valuable effect and emphasise the desire to promote the closest liaison between China and India.. (15) Economic.Current crop prospects in India, The failure of the late rains and the prevalence of unseasonably hot and sultry wTeather during the last quarter of1941 appear to have had adverse effects on the prospects of several of the staplecrops in India. Latest forecasts of the sugar-cane, ground-nut and castor-seedcrops all suggest that the out-turn of these commodities will be considerably lowerduring the current season than last season, the deficiencies amounting to as muchas 30 per cent, in that of castor-seed. In all three cases the out-turn is likely tobe about 20 per cent, below the average of the last five years.On the other hand, the estimated yield of the rice crop is 15 per cent, above that of last season, or slightly higher than the annual average of the pastquinquennium, while the out-turn of the wheat, cotton and sesamum crops is:expected to be about normal, as was the case last year. A feature of the cotton crop, in view of the difficulty in marketing short staple cotton consequent uponthe loss of the Japanese market, is a large increase in the total area under mediumstaple cotton in the Central Provinces.The preliminary acreage forecast of the rape and mustard crop showsan increase of 2 per cent, over last season, but that of the linseed crop indicates adecrease of 3 per cent.Owing to the restriction policy adopted by the Government of Bengal, theall-India acreage under jute in 1941 was 2,132,000 acres compared with,669,000 acres in 1940, and the yield 5,408,000 bales compared with 13,172,000bales (a record). With the Bengal permissible acreage for 1942 increased to morethan double the acreage recorded in 1941, the all-India yield of the crop isexpected to be in the neighbourhood of 10,800,000 bales this year.Nothing to report.(16) Finance.
(17) Military Activities.1. Malayi. The 9th and 11th Divisions, which had been reinforced by,100 men, the 44th and 45th Indian Infantry Brigades were in Singapore whenit-capitulated and must be presumed to be Prisoners of War.2. Burma.-Commander-in-Chief, India, reassumed command of -Burmafrom the 22nd February.Indian forces in Burma now consist of : Headquarters 17th Indian Division.13th Indian Infantry Brigade Group.16th Indian Infantry Brigade Group.46th Indian Infantry Brigade Group.48th Indian Infantry Brigade Group.Six Mountain Batteries R.A.One Indian Anti-Tank Regiment R.A.One Indian Heavy A.A. Battery.One Indian Light A.A. Battery.Five British Infantry Battalions.One Indian Pioneer Battalion.Two Indian Auxiliary Pioneer Battalions28 Squadrons R.A.F.1 Squadron I.A.F.3. Indian Forces Serving Overseas. India has approximately 300,000 men serving overseas. There are Indian troops in the Middle East and East Africa-Aden, Iraq and Iran, Burma and the Indian Ocean Islands. The 4th indian division has been continuously engaged in the recent operations in the western desert. There are also a number of Animal Transport Units in the UnitedKingdom.These forces comprise nine Infantry Divisions, one Armoured Brigade oneMotor Brigade, with the necessary ancillary units, and Line of communication and Base Units and services, and infantry battalions equivalent to those of anotherfive Infantry Divisions.BURMA.Report by the Secretary of State for Burma.(18) Military.The month of February has witnessed the withdrawal of our heavily out-numbered forces from the west bank of the Salween to an area covering Pegu,20 miles west of the Sittang. ,      fA new northern front was opened during the month on the lhai border orthe Southern Shan States.\1. Southern front.The withdrawal over the Salween began on the night of the 31st January-1st February and was completed by the 4th February. By the 12th, Martaban,attacked mainly from the rear, was in enemy hands; two days later Paan telland on the 15th Thaton was evacuated. By the 17th, 17th Indian Division hadtaken up their position on the west of the Bilin river, but were continuouslyforced back by the enemy, and were unable to hold their ground after the 20th,when our troops began withdrawing over the Sittang, some 20 miles west of theBilin. In the ensuing battle severe casualties were inflicted by both sides, butreinforcements by troops hitherto reserved for the defence of the coast line aroundRangoon were insufficient to stem the Japanese advance. On the 23rd, the Sittangrailway bridge was blown up, before, however, the greater part of two Brigades(16th and 46th) had been able to withdraw across the river and rejoin the mambody on the west bank.[23603] c 2
On the 21st, the 7th Armoured Brigade and a detachment of Cameroniansarrived at Rangoon for the reinforcement of the front, and reached the forward area on the 23rd.Some advanced Chinese reinforcements of unknown strength reachedToungoo, some 130 miles north of Rangoon, on the 26th.Throughout the withdrawal our troops have fought well and inflicted heavy casualties on the enemy: the K.O.Y.L.I., the 4/12th F.F.R. and the 7/10thBaluchis having particularly distinguished themselves in five weeks&apos; continuousfighting. The Japanese attack has been remarkable for the excellence of itsground to air communications and for the co-ordination of air with land forces.17th Division concentrated in the area of Pegu to refit by the 27th. Thetroops available in this area were the reorganised 46th and 48th Brigades.7th Armoured Brigade, 1st Bn. Cameronians, 5th Bn. 1st Punjab Regt.. 1st Bn.West Yorks.   The Japanese forces were estimated at 2 Divisions.2. Air.The R.A.F. and A.V.G. continued their spirited fight, taking a heavy toll of japanese raiders. Throughout the month their bombing of enemy concentrationsand forward divisions has greatly heartened our troops.From the 1st to the 8th, the Japanese made frequent raids on Rangoon andMingaladon, but did not resume the attack until the 25th, when, in a raid on the aerodrome, they lost 30 machines for one of ours, and over Rangoon the next daythey lost 22 planes for one R.A.F. machine.&apos; Blenheim aircraft with Thai markings are reported to have raided our forward areas.(19) Internal.Our reverses in Malaya and Burma naturally produced a progressive lowering of civilian morale. Contributory factors were the rapid evacuation of Europeanwomen and the belief that the Japanese would not hurt Burmans or Indians..; As a result of the steps taken by the Governor at the end of January, which included an Ordinance for the control of labour in the port, the labour situationin Rangoon remained at first fairly satisfactory (on 10th February the best 20days&apos; work in the port since hostilities began were reported). An orderly civilianevacuation commenced about the middle of February. The evacuation ofEuropean women to India or Upper Burma was completed. Government Depart-ments were gradually moved to Maymyo. On the 18th, the Rangoon Banksmoved to Mandalay. The Governor remained in Rangoon with a skeleton stafftill the 2nd March. He has since proceeded to Maymyo. As desertions from thepolice made the maintenance of law and order in Rangoon difficult and there was some looting, orders were given to the police and military to shoot looters at sight.On the 24th February Rangoon was placed under military control. All prepara-tions have been made for carrying out the oil denial scheme and other demolitions.Instructions regarding the scorched earth policy generally and special objectives in Burma were sent in January.(20) External.The Governor was unable to leave Rangoon to meet General Chiang Kai-shekon the latter&apos;s passing through Burma to India, but has since met him (on 3rd March) at Laishio. The Generalissimo while in India responded favourablyto a proposal to appoint an Agent of the Government of Burma at Chungking,and this appointment will be made as soon as the formal consent of the ChineseGovernment has been obtained.Work on the road between India and Burma mentioned in last month sreport is being pushed on. It has also been agreed that a road should be constructed from Assam via Myitkyina, in Burma, in link up with the existingBurma Road at Lungling, a little way inside China. The Chinese have offered to undertake the construction of the Burma section of this road with Chineselabour. &apos;    &apos; &quot;\ .. --i-1
THE COLONIAL EMPIRE.Report by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.&apos;: (Note. In this report &quot; Colonies &quot; is used to cover not only the Colonies inthe restricted sense, but also Protectorates and Mandated Territories,and &quot; Colonial Governors &quot; is used to include High Commissioners andthe British Resident, Zanzibar.)Economic Affairs.(21) Production in the Colonies.1. Rubber.Under an agreement with the Rubber Reserve Company of the United States,the Ministry of Supply has become the sole buyer of rubber in Ceylon, and fit,consultation with the East and West African Governments the Ministry is fixingbuying prices for plantation and wild rubber, which it is hoped will encouragemaximum production. Owing, however, to the collection of both types of rubber in these areas having been neglected in recent years, time will be requiredto organise this. The Governments are fully alive to the urgency of the matter;There is at present competitive buying by Empire and United States consumersin these territories, and allied buying policy will have to be co-ordinated.2. Tea.Since December, when supplies from the Netherlands East Indies werethreatened, the export quota from Ceylon has been fixed at a figure which requires the maximum possible production, and this is being attained as far as the labour supply permits.3. Oilseeds.Measures are being taken to bring Colonial sources of supply under bulk purchase arrangements, where such do not already exist. The Ministry of Foodhas now arranged to buy the total output of copra from Fiji and other western pacific islands under the same administration, and a proposal is being consideredthat the Government of India should buy the output from Ceylon.4. Ceylon Graphite.- Negotiations for the purchase of the entire output have not yet been com-pleted, owing to an unexpected revision by the United States of their estimate of requirements. &quot;5. Uganda Cotton.The disposal of this crop, normally readily sold in India, has caused some anxiety, as the Indian market has been upset by the loss of Japan as a buyer fora substantial proportion of the Indian production of short-staple cotton. TheUganda problem may be temporarily solved by the purchase of 15,000 tons bythe Cotton Control, and it is hoped that in a short time the Indian market willhave returned to more normal conditions.6. East Africa.Energetic steps are being taken to develop East Africa as an importantsource of supply of many food-stuffs for the Middle East. The Governor ofIxenya has announced comprehensive plans, including the provision of acreagebonuses, to stimulate the production of maize and wheat in particular.Defence.(22) General.(a) Civil Defence. The civil defence arrangements of the Colonies haveunder review in the light of the experience gained recently in the Far Easterntre of war.   Telegrams were sent to Fiji, Ceylon, Mauritius and Seychelles
requesting up-to-date reports on the present state of civil defence and bringing to their notice the lessons learnt in Malaya and Hong Kong. A special point isbeing made of the importance of taking all possible steps to guard against the flight of labour from essential services under air attack. Similar telegrams arebeing sent to Cyprus, Palestine, Aden and the East African Governors&apos;Conference (for Kenya, Tanganyika and Zanzibar).(b) Position of Civil Governments in event of invasion. Instructions arebeing sent to certain Colonies regarding the course to be adopted by Governors andother civil officers in the event of their territories being invaded. In accordancewith the recent Cabinet decision on this subject (W.M. (42) 14th conclusions minute 7), the instructions state (i) that the Governor, as the representative ofThe King (and any necessary civil government staff), should remain in the colony and establish his headquarters at the most suitable centre in consultation withthe service authorities; and that in the last resort, if the territory is overrun bythe enemy, he and his staff should either evacuate with the military commanderor, if that is not possible, remain with military headquarters; (ii) that Europeanofficers of the civil government in areas of military operations should remain attheir posts as long as they can serve a useful purpose and assist the military; butthat, if and when they can no longer render such service and enemy occupationof their districts is imminent, they should (after completing the duties allotted to them) withdraw by arrangement with the military commander and not remain to face capture unnecessarily. It is being emphasized that, in order to avoid any suggestion of racial discrimination, any instructions issued should be worded soas to apply to all officers in any particular grade&quot;, whether European or non-European.The Governors concerned are also being informed that they have discretion in consultation with the military authorities in applying the above instructions,to conditions in their territories, bearing in mind always that the primaryfunction of the civil government in the circumstances envisaged is to render allpossible assistance to the forces engaged in fighting the enemy,(23) Far East War.(a) Malaya. The Japanese invasion of Singapore Island began on the night of the 8th/9th February, when the enemy landed a considerable force on thenorth-west coast. Further landings were made at different points, and enemy forces established their position and advanced towards the city, which wassubjected to heavy shelling and air bombardment. By the 13th February the citywas closely invested and water supplies were badly damaged. The fall of singapore was announced on the 14th/15th February.(b) Ceylon. Attention has been concentrated on defence measures in Ceylon,and on the civil side particularly in the direction of increasing food reserves.With the interruption of supplies from the chief rice-exporting countries in theFar East, other grains are on order, but in the meantime a drastic scale of ricerationing has been introduced.There has been some movement of Indian labourers from Colombo and thetea and rubber plantations back to India and the Government has taken steps forthe organisation of Government labour units to maintain essential services.Wages have been improved by employing firms in consultation with the Govern-ment and labour unions.(c) Christmas Island (Indian Ocean). The District Officer of ChristinasIsland, which is normally administered from the Straits Settlements, has beenfurnished with cyphers to enable him to communicate direct with the Secretary ofState. The island is important as a source of phosphates, but the export of thiscommodity to Australia has now become impossible owing to shipping difficulties and the plant is being demolished. The majority of Europeans (including all women and children) have been evacuated to Australia. A bombing raid on thewharves by three aircraft was reported by the District Officer on the28th February. Little damage was done; but three Chinese were killed and twoWounded. Telegraphic communication with the island has recently been reported by Cable and Wireless, Limited, to be impossible.; On General wavell&apos;s departure for India the small garrison maintained onthe island was placed under the operational control of the Dutch military head-quarters in Java, to which a British section was attached.
. (d) Cocos-Keeling Islands. These islands are also normally under theadministration of the Straits Settlements, but hitherto no officer of the MalayanCivil Service has been stationed there. One was designated several weeks ago,but it has not yet been possible for him to be taken to Direction Island. personnel of the Ceylon Garrison Artillery are stationed on that island to protect the cablestation. The island will in future be under the operational control of theC-in-C, India, through the G.O.C., Ceylon. The most recent report is that the islands have been shelled by the enemy, but the results are not known,(e) Fiji and Western Pacific (i) Fiji. 133 European women and 128 children have left for neighbouring,; Dominions in response to the Fiji Governments advice that thosewho are able to leave the Colony should do so, and 200 women andchildren are booked to leave by the next opportunity. The governor has been asked to consider whether facilities for evacuation shouldalso be offered to the women and children of non-European races(i.e., Indian and Chinese).(ii) British Solomon Islands. The European civilian population has nowbeen evacuated to Australia with the exception of a few men (mostlyGovernment officers who are remaining to form a skeleton staff).Reports on Individual Colonies.(24) Palestine.. While subversive elements have tried to make capital out of the fall of singapore, the general public took this development calmly and the main pre-occupation remains the question of food supplies. A deputation consisting ofthe Bishop in Jerusalem, Dr. Magnes, and Amin Abdulhadi Bey assured theHigh Commissioner of the support of all right-thinking people in any measure to counter the exploitation of the present difficult supply situation.There were no major political developments among either Jews or Arabsduring the month.Drastic action has been taken by the Police against the Jewish pseudo-political terrorist gang known as the Stern Group, to whose activities a reference was made in last month&apos;s report. Some 80 members of the group have beenrounded up, and the leader was killed while resisting arrest. These measures have restored public confidence. Two wireless transmitters, which formed thegang&apos;s illicit broadcasting station, and a considerable quantity of bomb partshave been seized. The members of the more responsible section of the Jewishpublic have openly supported drastic action for the complete disruption of thegang, but there are indications that the Irgun Zvai Leumi (the Revisionistterrorist organisation) are in sympathy with the Stern group rather than withthe authorities.Taking a leaf out of the Jewish book, the Arabs have started in the press and at recruiting meetings to stress the importance of an increase in the numbersof Arabs joining the fighting forces in relation to the post-war settlement as it affects Palestine. Although perhaps natural, this development has its potentialities-tialities for mischief and is being carefully watched.The circumstances in which S.S. Struma, carrying illegal Jewish immigrants to Palestine, was sunk in the Bosphorus have been fully reported to the Cabinet.(25) Malta.The attacks on Malta from the air which were a feature of the early partof 1941 were resumed in January and have been continued with increasingintensity during February. There were 150 alerts by day and 103 by night duringthe month ending on the 20th January, and 146 by day and 116 by night during91 ft mont,k en4^nS 20th February. Casualties during the same periods Were^lo people killed and 236 seriously injured. Premises demolished or badly damaged numbered 1,364. &apos;The intensification of the raids has caused a good deal of dislocation in thehie of the community. But methods similar to those adopted in this countrytor giving warning are being adopted, and a system whereby business and work
continue unless and until raiders are overhead is being put into operation. Thepolicy of deep shelter construction has much reduced casualties. The standardcover is about 15 feet of rock, and this has so far proved adequate No case ofa shelter having been destroyed by bombs has occurred. There should now beaccommodation in deep shelters for very nearly the whole population of Malta.The necessity for people to remain in the deep shelters for considerableperiods has raised questions regarding the provision for lighting and for dealingwith sanitation, &amp;c. A Committee has been appointed to assist the Governmentin dealing with these problems. .The only convoy to reach Malta since last October arrived during January.The supply situation is causing some anxiety and restrictions on the consumptionof essential commodities have recently been extended.(26) West Indies.The Governor of Barbados reports that he has reviewed the case 6f UlricGrant, who was sentenced in 1937 to ten years&apos; imprisonment for sedition at the-time of the disturbances in Barbados, and that as a result Grant has been released.The internment order made in September 1940 by the Governor of Jamaicaagainst Alexander Bustamante has been suspended. Bustamante has been released subject to certain restrictions on addressing public meetings.(27) East Africa.Progress has been made in East Africa with the programme of increased production of food-stuffs for local needs, and for the requirements of the middle east, for which the Minister of State appealed last November. At the same timeefforts have been made to increase the output of sisal and copper in Tanganyikaand Northern Rhodesia respectively. The conscription of African labour for essential undertakings in Kenya, including agriculture, has been approved, subjectto carefully worked-out safeguards regarding wages, conditions of service, casesof hardship, &amp;c. Similar powers have been taken by the Governments of tanganyika and Northern Rhodesia for the conscription of labour required forthe production of essential foodstuffs. About 150 Europeans, chiefly farmers, areto be released from the East African Forces during the next six months. Asystem of guaranteed prices for certain crops and of bonuses for new acreagebrought into cultivation has been introduced in certain areas.(28) West Africa.Approval has been given in principle for the use of conscription in sierra leone for the formation of a Military Labour Corps to meet the increasing demands of the Service Departments for labour for constructional work in and around Freetown.A consulting engineer is to visit Freetown to advise on the site for the pro-posed deep-water berth. He will also visit the Gambia to advise on the praticability of constructing a deep-water berth at Bathurst.On the 7th January an influential Chief in the French Ivory Coast (theJamanhene of the Brong people) crossed over into the Gold Coast with about750 followers. They had come to seek asylum in British territory for the duration of the war owing to dissatisfaction at the oppressive methods of the VichyAdministration. The interests of these refugees are being looked after by a free french representative, but he, of course, has not been given executive powers overthem. Instructions have been sent to the Acting Chairman of the West AfricanGovernors&apos; Conference that no persons should be encouraged to leave French &quot;WestAfrica for British territory in future unless they can and will give direct assistance to our war effort.



</content>
</cab>
