<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/219/22 images: 732-740</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY GOVERNMENT

^85) 22 C0PY N  79

^Wptember 1985

CABINET

iflP&amp;EEN&apos;S SPEECHES ON THE PROROGATION AND OPENING OF PARLIAMENT &lt;^^emorandum by the Lord President of the Council

The attache^drafts of The Queen&apos;s Speeches on ^^^&quot;Xl^Sessio^have Present Session of Parliament and the Opening of the 1985-86 Session been prepared by T&gt;c$ueen&apos;s Speeches and Future LegiBlatxon Committee (QL) onfcH&gt;asis of the texts suggested by Departments. The draft OpeniS SpeeSySsiect. the legislative programme approved by the Cabinet&apos;on 28  btu^C&lt;85) 7th Conclusions) and subsequenty amended  n 6 June (CC(85) 19^&amp;lusions).    In addition, I &quot; ? ,

in my minute of   7 Sep82Z^hat QL considered that two   u 1 should be added to the f^^jpe (to deal with the conf&quot;&quot;&quot;on of the Proceeds of drug traffici^M scientific experiments on J^8&apos;^ ^at a Salmon Fisheries Bil^^d be substituted for th   Lav Reform Parent and Child)(Scotlan^SOL I have seen no objec&quot;ons to these Proposals and they are accord^g^eflected in the draft Opening Speech.

9        ^. .   ^^cj/Zj miffht be required in the light

2-     Subject to any further dectW^     J ^   **       Cabinet t0

 r developments before the Speeches^r^deliverea, approve the attached drafts.

Privy Council Office 27 September 1985


I o^ATION OF PARLIAMENT 1935

^ QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION O

l  J^Uords^^ State Visits of the Life

^ Duke of Edinburgh and 1 were pleased to rece ^ ^ ^ ^ Madrid

1  ^Utent of Malawi In April and the President of M

Vi it to Portugal in March. I 2-   *e recall with much satisfaction the State   5   ^ Cornmonwealth Heads have also visited Belize, and was in the Bahamas o ^ ^ ^

0f Government Meeting.  Our tour of Commonwealth Caribbean is still in progress.

3     n of the Maldives and of St Vincent

3&gt;   My Government welcomed the decision of t nwealth.

and *e Grenadines to become full members of the

t0 Western defence,

*    ^ Government have maintained Britain&apos;s ^^^^     ements in equipment

Chanced the United Kingdom&apos;s own defences thro g    ^ ^ ^ ^ ** * the regular and reserve forces. They have Pla*e the NATO

^ and promoted Brltish and Western defence interests

5 &apos; sw for agreements on verifiable

&quot;   WY Government have continued to work vigorou y ^ ^ Soviet

control and disarmament, and to seek improved re ^ ^ ^ Geneya

7 n ^d Eastern Europe. They warmly welcomed the p Un.ted

a &apos;0 reach concrete agreements.

  - on of Spain and Portugal

&apos;   ^y Government have signed the Treaty on the Acc*SS* &quot;        d Convention to th  p a   nrt ratified tne uw

q{ ne European Communities, and have signed ana ebleau Agreement

Lonr*. An Act has been passed implementing the   on correction *   future financmg of the European Communities, ***** e British budgetary contribution.

7&lt; n for the victims of the

^ Government share the widespread public concer Ame_-enCV assistance

* They have continued to provide substantial emergen

dlrectly and tnrough the EuroPean Community.


to the Pe Ple

8. My Government have continued fully to honour their undertakings

1 relation

of the Falkland Islands, while taking positive steps to seek more normal with Argentina.  The Sino-British Joint Declaration on Hong Kong was =&gt; &amp; December and an Act consequent upon its terms was passed.  My Governm have reached agreement with Spain on the implementation of the Lisbon concerning Gibraltar.

9. My Government have supported efforts to restore the independent status of Afghanistan. They have urged peaceful change in South Afn early independence of Namibia.

_ premier  f

10. My Government welcomed to the United Kingdom in June trie r

the State Council of the People&apos;s Republic of China.  The great imp r ^

Government attach to their relations with the Countries of South East . ,re

trie visit nci

Asia was marked by the Prime Minister&apos;s visit there in April and by this month of the Indian Prime Minister.

11. Members of the House of Commons .,  - nd dignl &apos;

I thank you for the provision which you have made for the honour a

of the Crown and for the public service.

12. My Lords and Members of the House of Commons flati n

My Government have maintained the policies necessary to bring down

r ^j-jg nati

and sustain economic growth.  Inflation remains low, the output oi ^ peoPie

is at its highest level ever and continues to increase, as does the nu in work.

13. Further steps have been taken to help the unemployed into jo ^ Q^ the Youth Training Scheme and enlarging the Community Programme,

ways, including a reform of the structure of national insurance co

,  f share  w

14. To promote economic efficiency and encourage the spread     - e of

nrofirafn

not least among employees, my Government have continued their p sful

the suc

returning state-owned businesses to the private sector, including public flotation of British Telecommunications.,


15. ^

n Act has been passed to complete the transition of the Trustee Savings

to fun

 wn Pfivate sector status and to permit wide public participation in their

16. An

bus Ct      been Passed t0 increase competition in the provision of local

Com rViC6S in ^reat Britain and to enable the operations of the National Bus Pany to be transferred to the private sector.

of     e^isiation has been enacted to make further provision for the payment

t0 tne National Coal Board and to abolish the British National Oil Corporation.

18.   u .

to Prov.^1Siation nas been enacted to remove the statutory levy on cinema admissions,

the      S f r ^ternative financial assistance for film production and to reduce

regulatorv hi.rw

y ourden on the film and cinema industries.

An A.ct .

 as been passed for the better protection of food and the environment.

20- A

Act h

Service   been passed t0 establish in England and Wales a Crown Prosecution

Crlrninni dependent of the police, and to enable time limits to be imposed on nal Proceedings.

21.  

r* Act h

F,arliament     ^ beSn passed giving the right to vote at Parliamentary and European ^ Proxy  eieCtions to many British citizens resident abroad, and extending postal tlng to electors who cannot reasonably be expected to vote in person.

&apos;22- I

Sislati

kerning       n ^ been passed to establish a comprehensive statutory framework Perception of communications.

23  A

sD     n Act has h

ng event Passed to deal with the problem of drunkenness at designated

Ik,

C^nsidgj-

 vision has b   6 adVance nas been made in the consolidation of our statute law; ^ f r the made t0 aPPly international Conventions on child abduction

Ministration of justice.


.,   H the

25. An Act has been passed to abolish the Greater London Council and County Councils on 1st April 1986 and to transfer most of their functions to borough and district councils.

26. In Northern Ireland, my Government has attached high importance to maintenance of law and order.  They have continued the search for ways m responsibility can be returned to a local administration on a widely accep errirnent basis.  They have sought to develop a solid working relationship with the

of the Republic of Ireland.

e foliovving

27. For Scotland, measures have been passed to introduce a rebate schem ^^q0S, rating revaluation, to establish trustee bodies to manage certain Scottish 1

and to make a number of reforms in Scots law.

a and WaleS&apos;

28. Legislation has been passed to reform insolvency law in Englana   and in Scotland.

of sch oi

29. My Government have published proposals to improve the quality   education, the effectiveness of teachers and the development of higne into the next decade.

al se^rity

30. My Government have conducted a fundamental review of the soc system and published proposals for radical reform.

&apos;   hc retired

31. In addition, my Government have protected the real value oi  &apos;        ( rjghts

_ [oyees

&apos;.pension and other related benefits, and passed an act to improve emp under occupational pension schemes, and to extend statutory sick pay*

32. My Lords and Members of the House of Commons

I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.


QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF PARLIAMENT 1985

My LnrH

I looJp ^5Lind Members of the House of Commons

^jest0^^ With great Pleasure t0 receiving His Highness the Amir of Qatar, their of       S tne King and Queen of Spain and [the President of the Federal Republic any and Frau von Weizsaecker] on State Visits during the next. 12 months.

2. j

t0 ^    S  lool&lt; foward to paying a State Visit to Nepal in February, followed by visits Kon    2eaiand ar&gt;d Australia [and to paying a State Visit to China and visiting Hong   ln ^tober.]

3&quot;   % Gov

of n        Vernment continue to attach the highest importance to the maintenance

Win co      Security and the preservation of peace with freedom and justice. They

the 11   lnUe t0 play a fu^ and active part in the Atlantic Alliance and to enhance united ur- .

teToriSm     lngdom&apos;s own defences.  They will make vigorous efforts to combat internationa My q

neSotiati   Vernrnent wih continue to work for progress in arms control and disarmament and for greater cooperation and trust between East and West.

5&lt; My Govern

CornrnUnit     ment Welcome tne accession of Spain and Portugal to the European

Wor(&lt; f introduce tne necessary legislation.   Within the Community, they

early c-Q^   lrnProved decision taking, strengthened cooperation on foreign policy,

 * the r 0  f tbe common market, improvements in world trade and reform

 mrt1 n Agricultural Policy&gt;

continu theit&quot; underTat&lt;ings to tne people of the Falkland Islands, my Governmen-

t0 discharge t0 .S6et&lt; more norrnai relations with Argentina.   They will also continue to irnPlement        bii^ations t0 tne people of Hong Kong; and will propose provisions

the nati nality arrangements arising from the Sino-British Joint Declaration.

 f Peace and WlU W rk for Peaceful change in South Africa:   for the restoration

^ Iran and Statlility in Lebanon:  and for solutions to the conflict between Iraq

n0ruaJigned     6 Arab/Israel dispute.   They will seek to restore an independent and

&apos;n CyPrus        anistan.  They will support United Nations efforts for a settlement a&gt; and thos

se of the Contadora Group to resolve the tensions in Central America.


, v a constr^ctiVe

8. My Government will give full support to the Commonwealth, and play  ^ ^ role at the United Nations.  They will maintain a substantial aid programme their part in the relief of famine and of other disasters; and encourage inve

in developing countries.

9. Members of the House of Commons

Estimates for the Public Service will be laid before you.

10. My Lords and Members of the House of Commons ron^00&apos;  - a tn secure 3 u

Within the framework of firm monetary and fiscal policies designed to reduction in inflation, my Government will do all in their power to encourag^^^ ^ growth of new jobs.  Firm control of public expenditure will be maintain^ &gt; e^.c^ view to diminishing its share of overall national output and facilitating in the burden of income tax.

ion. 35 3

11. My Government will pursue vigorously their programme of privatise ^ ^our3^

means both of improving the efficiency of the industries concerned, and 0   ^ ^

wider share ownership.   Measures will be introduced to permit the transf Atomic

able *e ^ ufe

assets of the British Gas Corporation to the private sector and to ena struc Energy Authority to operate as a trading fund from 1 April 1986 with a and borrowing powers.

  ish Airp rtS

12. A Bill will be proposed to introduce private capital into the Bn ^apie5&apos; Authority, to require larger local authority airports to be formed into

and to regulate certain airport activities.

mercial

13. My Government will bring forward legislation to introduce com ^erci to my Naval Dockyards, as a significant contribution to encouraging a approach and securing value for money in spending on defence.

a stry oi agrlC ^

14. Legislation will be introduced to facilitate funding by the inau arr3 research, advice and related services; and to implement European

to protect areas of particular environmental sensitivity.


latory framework for the l5    Wes will be introduced to establish a newg competitlveness whilst

f^cial services sector, wh1Ch will enhance its  ttie en y ^ ^ ^^.^ ^ Liberalise hiding greater safeguards for the interests of mve the law governing Building Societies.

i   m the operation of Wages Councils, l6&apos;   Measures will be brought forward to retor ^ ^ ^ Qn sex

t0 **e provisions concerning the payment of wages dlScrimination in employment.

the sale of public sector flats to l7.   Legislation wlu be introduced to encourage ownership and management

their tenants and wider private sector involvement in  f *uncll housing, and to improve the planning system.

t of public sector tenants [l%   F r Scotland, Bills will be introduced to extend t eji   ^ ^ improve

*nd to faCiUtate the private ownership of public sector ^ of saimon

*Sal     arrangements, and to modify and extend the m ^ ^ Qreat

. including strengthening measures to combat uleg

&amp;ritain.

{ to support the security forces

. &quot;   ln Northern Ireland my Government will continue They wiU seek

&quot;Arcing the law and in working for the eradication o ^ ^ fo

acceptable arrangements for the devolution of power ^ ^

Xher their co-operation with the Government at w encouragement 7 b* -de to create and sustain employment, particularly by

the Private sector.

 &apos;   * Bill will be introduced to reform social security.

2l ment of schools and to

pr&quot;   Legislation will be introduced to improve the managem

^ the professional effectiveness of teachers.

^   u prs of the police to prevent

,s   ^sures will be introduced to strengthen the powe v ^

M  ,    t0 modern^ ^d codify the common law pub rf drug

**** and to provide the courts with power to confiscate P 1CklnS and to penalise the handling of such proceeds.


ening h urS&apos;

23. A Bill will be introduced to remove statutory restrictions on shop  P

teCtion oi

24. A Bill will be brought before you to make new provision for the p animals used for experimental or other scientific purposes.

25. Other measures will be laid before you.

26. My Lords and Members of the House of Commons

I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon your counsels.



</content>
</cab>
