<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/3/16 images: 132-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.   (59) 33nd CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 7.Confidential Annex.$AIR STRENGTHS. THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR explained thata mere arithmetical comparison of the kind given in the tables before the War Cabinet would be misleading unlesscertain further considerations were borne in mindoThus, Germany had been forbidden an air force in theyears after the Great War and, when she had decided in1933 to create one, she had been faced with difficultieswhich could not be entirely overcome even by the mostlavish expenditure of money.     As a result of the very rapid expansion on which she had embarked, she sufferedto-day from a serious lack of experienced leaders for hersquadrons and of officers for her staffs.     This rapid   .expansion had moreover created problems throughout thewhole range of equipment.     In order to produce sufficientaircraft for her ambitious programme, Germany had been forced to standardise on the three or four main typeswhich she had available in 1935 and 1936;    and although,as aeroplanes, they were as good as any in the World atthat date, the requirements of fighting in the air hadnot been given that careful thought and practicalexperiment essential in the design of service aircraft.As a result, although Germany had a much greater numberof heavy bombers than we had, her bomber aircraft .suffered from the disadvantage that they were inadequatelyprotected from fighter attack from the rear.     Theirfighters also were less efficient than the present dayBritish aircraft, and carried only four guns whereas theHurricane and Spitfire carried eight.     They were alsoless manoeuvrable and more difficult to land than ours,a factor which was reflected in the small amount of nightflying carried out in the German fighter squadrons owing,it was understood, to the heavy accident rate when such

flights were attempted.     It would be seen from theforegoing that our Hurricane and Spitfire fighters should give a good account of themselves against German bomberswhenever they intercepted them.The German JLir Force had been able to pick itspersonnel from amongst the best in Germany;    and thestandard of mechanics and pilots was undoubtedly high.The system of training laid down was thorough but, owingto the rate of continuous expansion and consequent lackof instructional staff, it was unlikely to have been asgood in practice as would appear from the syllabus of instruction.     Thus, to sum up, the German Air Force,whilst more numerous than the Royal Air Force, was likelyto show the defects of its rapid growth when a heavy strainwas put upon it.As regards reserves, it would be remembered thata considerable proportion of our own bomber reserves werecreated by contracting our first-line strength on mobilisation, i.e., by regarding a number of our peace-time regular units as additional reserves behind, themobilised squadrons.     Such a course, while giving adecreased first-line strength in war, nevertheless ensuredthat a considerable proportion of our reserves werecomplete with crews trained to peace-time regular standards.Germany had been training reserve pilots but it was not thought that she yet had any large number of trainedreserve crews available for her long range bomber force.It should also be noted that, partly as a result of thecontraction of our first-line strength referred to above,the percentage (though not the total number) of our bomber aircraft reserves was considerably greater than in theGerman Air Force.As regards the French Air Force, although it remained the most powerful in Europe after the last war,it had latterly not been, provided with sufficient money to- 2 -

allow for its proper upkeep, including the replacementsof aircraft.     Difficulties had &quot;been experienced with newdesigns, and labour troubles had reduced the output of factories.     As a result, the French Air Force had reached a low level in 1938, when a complete reorganisation hadtaken place.     The effects of this change were now beingfelt and the morale throughout the Force was excellent.Its modern aircraft were, however, mainly fighters becausethese were the types first put into production.     Frenchbomber aircraft were largely of obsolescent types andof doubtful operational value, a fact which underlined theimportance to France of a modification of the AmericanNeutrality Act which would enable her to obtain quickdelivery of the 315 modern bombers on order and now overdueTHE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF then gave an explanation of the figures set out in the table.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL invited attention to thehigh figure of reserves of aircraft maintained for RoyalAir Force bomber squadrons (300% reserves) as comparedwith the scale of reserves maintained by the German bomber force (about 100%).I In reply, itjvas explained by THE CHIEF OF THEAIR STAFF that theBecause germany at the present time&apos; maintained a lower proportion of reserve bombers than we did, it ought not to be taken for granted that she would not increase her reserves at sometime in the future.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY took a seriousview of our first line bomber strength, having regard to- 3 -

the large numbers of new aircraft which had been builtsince the previous April.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said that approximately 2,700 aircraft of an operational type hadbeen delivered to the Royal Air Force since April.These had been used to build reserves behind mobilisablesquadrons.     Others had gone to training units.     Othersagain had been used to make up wastage.     We had in thisperiod made aaeestsi^^afeie- increase in our overseasfirst line strength and we had been compelled to fulfil the more pressing demands for modern aircraft from theDominions and from certain friendly Powers.     As an example of the amount of replacement of obsolescenttypes which had taken place, it should be noted thatnine-tenths of our fighter squadrons had been re-equipped with modern aircraft during the previous twelve months.In reply to a further question, THE CHIEF OFTHE AIR STAFF said that we now had about 4,000 aircraftemployed as trainers.     Many of these had been found from obsolescent first line aircraft which had been replaced by more modern types.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY reiterated his view that there was an undue disparity between the largenumbers of aircraft coming out of the factories and the comparatively small increase in first line squadronsready for action.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF explained that theAir Ministry had embarked upon no less than six expansion schemes.     The first one had been launched in 1934-35,and had been due for completion in March, 1939.     &amp;amoetfesja five other schemes had been launched, each onebigger than the last.     The sixth scheme was due for completion in March, 3r^*e.     The constant change to anew programme before the previous one had been completed

was responsible for a good deal of our present 1difficulties, i Unfortunately it was not possible forthe gigantic machine, which was in course of being built up, to get into full operation exactly at the time we wanted it most.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that it would beunprofitable to carry the discussion as to futurestrengths further until the War Cabinet had had anopportunity of studying an analysis of future productionfigures, which would show the allocation of all types of new aircraft and reserves.THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER said that,although the German figure of bombers was a formidableone, there would be a very rapid wastage of first line strength if they attempted full-scale operations againstwell defended targets.     It was then that theirrelatively smaller proportion of reserves might tellagainst them.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL thought that as soon asair warfare on a large acale commenced, big losses wouldbe suffered on both sides.     For this reason it was ofthe utmost importance that we should develop resources in Canada and the other Dominions to the fullest possible extent.     He understood that the production figures for heavy bombers would tend to go down during a certainperiod in 1940, and enquired whether it might not be preferable to concentrate on producing a larger numberof smaller types of bomber rather than a reduced numberof very heavy bombers.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR replied thatthis question had been carefully considered.     Actualnumbers were apt to be misleading and it should beremembered that the new type of heavy bomber, whichwould go into production in 1940, would carry a greatly

m a( iincreased bomb load and would be more heavily protectedthan the existing types.     It was not strictly true tosay that we were concentrating on heavy bombers, but rather that we were aiming to build up a balanced AirForce.Attention was then invited to the relatively small number of German army co-operation aircraft, and it was suggested that a considerable number of the Germanbomber strength would be employed in co-operation withthe Army if the Germans launched a big offensive on landin the West.Information was also given regarding the Frenchbombers from which it was clear that existing types were of poor performance and small in numbers.     The FrenchGovernment had placed orders in America for a number of bombers and had taken steps to increase their own production.     These measures could not however bear fruitfor some time to come.The War Cabinet   -(i) took note of&quot;the statements showing thepresent air strength of this country andFrance in relation to the estimated air strength of Germany:(ii) took note that the Air Ministry were preparing a further statement showingthe production figures of Great Britain,France and Germany up to (a) 31stDecember, 1939, and (b) 31st March, 1940,showing the estimated rate of productionof aircraft of all types, assuming thatfactories are not hampered by air attack:(iii) invited the Air Ministry to submit afurther Paper showing -(a) the increase which would accrue inthe period covered by this review inthe number of first-line Squadrons(shown separately as to types), andin the numbers of aircraft allocated to reserves and to training:(b) a forecast of the Air personnelsituation over the same period:(iv) invited the Air Ministry to submit aseparate Paper as to German types, in comparison with our own, their dependence on octane fuel, and like matters.-    -------- -        ;       :




</content>
</cab>
