<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/16/0 images: 31-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1947SECRET Copy No.    9III llll 111.11 II IIIIIIIM ^CP. (47) SlWi January, 1947CABINETUNITED NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLY: SECOND PART off first SESSIONREPORT ON TRUSTEESHIP AND SUPPLY OF INFORMATION on non-SELF-GOVERNING territories memorandum by the Secretary of State for the colonies circulate for the information of my colleagues a memorandum on the workof the General Assembly of the United Nations and its Fourth Committee at the-Second Part of its First Session in New York. This Committee deals primarily with the International Trusteeship System (Chapters XII and XIII of the charter) and secondly with any matters arising under Chapter XI (declarationregarding non-self-governing territories). The United Kingdom was normallyrepresented in the Committee by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State&apos;for the Colonies (Mr. Ivor Thomas) with advisers from the Colonial Office and theGovernment of Tanganyika. This Committee also considered on this occasion the future of South-West Africa, but this matter falls outside the scope of this paper.The International Trusteeship system.   The General Assembly approved eight trusteeship agreements in respectof six mandated territories in Tropical Africa, New Guinea and Western Samoa.The Trusteeship Agreements for Tanganyika, Togoland under British MandateI  and Cameroons under British Mandate were approved subject to minor modifica-j  tions which the United Kingdom Delegation was able to accept.  It was necessary to refuse acceptance of one modification proposed in the text of the trusteeship,agreement for Togoland and the Cameroons and of two new articles proposed forall three United Kingdom trusteeship agreements.  Details of these are given ini Annex I to the enclosed memorandum.The work of the Fourth Committee and the Assembly in regard to the trustee-I ship agreements is fully described in Section B of the memorandum and I need!I not here refer to more than a few points of particular importance : (a) The U.S.S.R. and other Members of the Slav Group contested the validity of the trusteeship agreements on technical grounds, but a Resolutionproposed by the U.S.S.R. for disapproval of the agreements wasnegatived in the Assembly by 34 votes to 6, with eleven abstentions.(&amp;) After approval of the eight trusteeship agreements the trusteeship council was established. The countries represented on it areAustralia, Belgium, France, New Zealand and the United kingdom as administering authorities; China, USA. and U.S.S.R. as ex officiomembers not administering trust territories, and Iraq and Mexico a selected members to give the necessary equality between administeringand non-administering States.(c) The Assembly also decided that the first meeting of the trusteeship council should be held not later than 15th of March. The business is likely to include the adoption of Rules of Procedure and the drawing up of the questionnaires which will form the basis of theannual reports to be submitted by the Administering Authorities.[33018]
2To sum up, the work of the Committee and Assembly as regards the Inter-national Trusteeship System was highly satisfactory from the United Kingdompoint of view, although there were difficult moments in the course of debate whencertain dangerous amendments seemed likely to be recommended. A few, indeed,were recommended by the Fourth Committee and had to be rejected by the UnitedKingdom Delegation.Declaration regarding Non-Self-Governing Territories3. A full account of the Committee&apos;s proceedings is given in Section C ofthe enclosed memorandum, from which it will be seen that the general atmospherewas considerably less satisfactory. Apart from the question of South-WestAfrica, two resohitions were passed. The first dealt with the manner in whichthe information transmitted to the Secretary-General by the Colonial powers under Article 73 (e) of the Charter should be handled. It was decided to establish an ad hoc Committee of experts of 16 Member States to meet shortly before theSecond Session of the General Assembly to consider the Secretary-GeneraFssummary and analysis of the material submitted in 1947 and to advise on the pro-cedure to be followed in future years and on the means of ensuring that theadvice, expert knowledge and experience of the Specialised Agencies are used tothe best advantage. The second Resolution originated in the form of a proposal by tlhe Philippine Delegation for a World Conference of Non-Self-Governingpeoples. It passed through many stages as a result of amendments by the Soviet,Ukrainian and Cuban delegations, and in its final form (for the wording of whichthe Cuban Delegation was mainly responsible) it has emerged as a recommendation that the Colonial Powers should themselves call conferences to enable effect to begiven to Chapter XI of the Charter.Throughout the discussion of these Resolutions there was evidence that manyDelegations which have no colonial responsibilities desired to go far beyond theprovisions of the Charter in conferring upon the United Nations a power of super-vision over all colonial territories and even in certain respects a right of initiative in regard to the practical realisation of Chapter XI. I am considering what thepolicy of the United Kingdom should be in regard to the two Resolutions passedby the General Assembly, but I take the view that it would be unfortunate if atthis stage in the United Nations any encouragement were given to the assembly to contravene the provisions of this Chapter of the Charter. We shall maintainthe close collaboration in these matters with the Dominions and other colonial powers which we have built up in the past year. I may add that perhaps the most significant development was the realisation by the United States that their interests in this matter lie with the other Colonial Powers rather than with theirresponsible critics.A. C. J.Colonial Office,\$th January, 1947.
MemorandumTRUSTEESHIP AND INFORMATION ON NON-SELF-GOVERNINGTERRITORIESAppreciation of the Work of the Second Part of the First Session of the.General Assembly of the United NationsA. introductory. Questions relating to trusteeship and the supply of information on non-self-governing territories arise from Chapters XI, XII and XIII of the united nations Charter and fall to the Fourth Committee of the General Assembly.The two aspects of the subject are quite distinct though there was an unfortunatetendency at the General Assembly to blur this distinction.2. Chapter XI contains a general declaration of colonial policy and a specific obligation, in Article 73 (e) to transmit regularly to the Secretary-General, for information purposes, subject to such limitation as security and constitutional considerations may require, statistical and other information ofa technical nature relating to economic, social and educational conditions in the territories for which Members of the United Nations are respectively responsibleother than those territories to which Chapters XII and XIII apply.3. Chapters XII and XIII deal with the International Trusteeship system which is the United Nations analogy of the League of Nations Mandates System.Chapter XII lays down the basic objectives and general nature of the trusteeship system while Chapter XIII deals with the composition, functions and powers ofthe Trusteeship Council which is charged with the supervision of the administra-tion of territories placed under trusteeship.4. In any appreciation of the proceedings of the General Assembly it isconvenient to consider the International Trusteeship System first.B. The International Trusteeship System (Chapters XII and XIII)5. According to Article 77 of the Charter, the International trusteeship system may be applied to territories in any of the following three categories^namely: (a) territories now held under mandate;(b) territories which may be detached from enemy States as a result of theSecond World War; and(c) territories voluntarily placed under the system by States responsible fortheir administration.It is a matter for subsequent agreement as to which territories in these categorieswill be brought under the trusteeship system and upon what terms.6. At the opening of the First Part of the First Session of the general assembly in January 1946, the United Kingdom declared its intention to bringthe three African mandated territories for which it was responsible under the trusteeship system, and to establish Trans-Jordan as an independent State.No statement regarding the future of Palestine could be made at that time.The other Mandatory Powers except France and the Union of South Africastated their intention to bring their mandated territories under trusteeship(France, however, made a subsequent declaration to that effect). In February1946, the General Assembly adopted a Resolution welcoming the intention ofthe United Kingdom to establish Trans-Jordan as an independent State,welcoming the declared intentions of certain of the Mandatory Powers to bringmandated territories under trusteeship, and urging that trusteeship agreements should be presented for approval preferably not later than the Second Part ofthe First Session.7. When the Second Part of the First Session opened in October 1946, theAssembly had before it trusteeship agreements presented by the under-mentionedMember States in respect of the territories indicated :  United Kingdom Tanganyika.Togoland under British Mandate.Cameroons under British Mandate.[33018]
France 1   Togoland under French Mandate.Cameroons under French Mandate.Belgium Ruanda Urundi.Australia New Guinea.New Zealand Western Samoa.In other words trusteeship agreements were presented in respect of all theremaining mandated territories except Palestine (United Kingdom), Nauru(British Empire, administered by Australia), South-West Africa (South Africa),and the Japanese Mandated Islands (at present under United States military administration). Various Delegations notably that of the U.S.S.R., criticizedthe Mandatory Powers concerned for not having also presented trusteeship agree-ments for Palestine, Nauru or South-West Africa. There had been close collaboration throughout between the United Kingdom, France and Belgium asregards the terms of trusteeship for the Mandated Territories in tropical Africa;and also between the United Kingdom and New Zealand as regards WesternSamoa. The agreements for these territories were therefore substantially in similar terms. The Australian draft for New Guinea was in a much shorterform.9. For the detailed examination of the trusteeship agreements the FourthCommittee appointed a Sub-Committee of seventeen members roughly balancedbetween Mandatory and Colonial Powers on the one hand and non-colonial powers on the other hand.   The members were :-This Sub-Committee sat under the Chairmanship of Dr. MacEachen of Uruguaywith Mr. Lisicky, Czechoslovakia, as Rapporteur, these gentlemen being theChairman and Rapporteur respectively of the full Committee. The Secretariatconsisted of Dr. Victor Hoo, Assistant-Secrebary-General (Chinese), Dr. Bunche(United States) and Mr. Anker (Norwegian). Both the officers and the Secre-tariat of this Sub-Committee deserve the highest praise for their efficiency andobjectivity. In particular the Rapporteur&apos;s report was a model of what sucha report should be. The Rapporteur as Delegate of Czechoslovakia showedcommendable impartiality, and his report showed no bias in favour of the Sovietpoint of view.10. The Sub-Committee considered in aggregate 229 proposals for textualamendments of the eight trusteeship agreements put forward either by membersof the Sub-Committee or by other Delegations who were invited to attend theSub-Committee meetings for that limited purpose. (In fact only the delegation of Byelo-Russia availed themselves of this facility.) The discussions in the Sub-Committee were long, complicated and very arduous, and protracted debatestook place on many points. A small number of the suggestions were acceptedeither in full or in a modified form by the States presenting the trusteeship agreements, others were rejected in the Sub-Committee or full Committee andthe.number of suggestions adopted by the full Committee which the MandatoryPower concerned felt unable to accept was remarkably small. The UnitedKingdom refused acceptance of one amendment affecting the text of the Togolandand Cameroons agreements and two suggestions for new articles to be includedin each of the three trusteeship agreements. Annex I contains details of theseproposals. Similar proposals were made in respect of most of the otheragreements and rejected by the Mandatory Power concerned.Australia.Belgium.Canada.China.Czechoslovakia.France.India.Iraq.Mexico.Netherlands.New Zealand.Union of South Africa.United Kingdom.United States.U.S.S.R.Uruguay.Yugoslavia.
11. In the end six of the trusteeship agreements were approved by votes of forty-one in favour, six against (U.S.S.R., Ukraine, Byelo-Russia, Yugoslavia,Liberia and Poland) and five abstentions. The French agreements were approvedby a vote of forty-one in favour, five against and six abstentions, owing to aswitch by the Polish delegate from opposition to abstention, apparently as a gesture towards Franco-Polish friendship. India and Czechoslovakia, whichhad voted against the agreements in the Fourth Committee, abstained in theAssembly.12. The main opposition in the Fourth Committee and in the Assemblyitself came from the Soviet Group, who maintained (i) that the trusteeship agree-ments were invalid because the terms had not been properly agreed upon betweenthe &quot; States directly concerned &quot;as required by Article 79 of the Charter, (ii) that several of them included provision for administration of the Trust territories as integral parts of the territory of the Administering Authority, whereas the charter provides for ultimate self-government or independence, and (iii) thatthe provision for naval, military and air bases outside the control of the security council was in conflict with the Charter. The Soviet Delegation pressed these amendments very strongly, particularly the third, on which they received strong support from India. They went so far as to table a Resolution in PlenaryAssembly, proposing the disapproA^al of the agreements on these three grounds.This, however, was rejected by thirty-four votes to six, with eleven abstentions,and three absentees. Apart from the Soviet group the main opponents of the drafts as presented by the Mandatory Powers were India and to a less extentChina. The Indian Delegation proposed a very large number of amendmentsor additions to the agreements, all of them unacceptable, e.g., that the united nations itself -should be the Administering Authority, and that a time limit for independence or self-government should be fixed in the trusteeship agreements.They took up a great deal of the time of the Sub-Committee and their attitude was most unco-operative.13. The very large majority in favour of approval of the trusteeship agree-ments must be regarded with some caution. Few Delegations outside theMandatory Powers themselves expressed complete satisfaction with the termsof trusteeship presented for approval, and it was only the realisation that theMandatory Powers had. in the last resort a veto, and that failure to approve the trusteeship agreements would&apos; make it impossible to set up the trusteeship council and bring the trusteeship system into operation, which led to this large majority. It is difficult to understand the very luke-warm attitude of the non-Mandatory Powers in the Assembly except on political grounds. The trusteeship agreements, in fact, cover every obligation of the Charter explicitly or implicitly,and Annex I, which describes the only recommendations for amendment adoptedby the full Committee but rejected by the Mandatory Powers, shows clearly that there was very little substance in most of the points pressed upon theMandatory Powers by other Delegations. Nevertheless, we can be well satisfied with the result since the trusteeship agreements in the form in which they were finally approved are completely satisfactory from our point of view.14. After approval of the trusteeship agreements the Assembly proceeded to the election by secret ballot of two members of the Trusteeship Council underArticle 86 (c) for three years each. This number was determined as follows.The Trusteeship Council has to be formed in such a manner that half its member-ship consists of States which administer Trust Territories and half of states which do not. Further, all the &quot; Big Five &quot; are ex dfficio members of the Councilwhether they are Administering Authorities or not. There were thus fiveAdministering Authorities (United Kingdom, France, Australia, Belgium andNew Zealand), of which the first two are also members of the &quot; Big Five.&quot; Thefive non-Administering members had therefore to consist of China, United Statesand U.S.S.R. (the three remaining members of the Big Five) plus two elected members to make the balance. Mexico and Iraq were elected. India came thirdbut with only seven votes. The U.S.S.R., Byelo-Russia, the Ukraine and Yugo-slavia took no part in the election in view of their attitude to the validity of the agreements. The U.S.S.R. has not indicated, however, that she will refuseto take her seat in the Trusteeship Council.15. The Assembly also resolved that the Secretary-General should convenethe first meeting of,the Trusteeship Council not later that 15th March, 1947.It is probable that this meeting will be devoted to formal and organisationalbusiness, in particular the election of a president, the drawing up of Rulesa
of Procedure and the formulation of the questionnaires which will be the basisof- the annual reports to be submitted by the Administering Authorities. DraftRules of Procedure have already been worked out by the Preparatory Commis-sion and these will form the basis of the Trusteeship Council&apos;s discussion oathis subject. In some respects the draft prepared by the Preparatory commission is not very satisfactory from the point of view of the Administering Authorities,notably in the handling of petitions and provision for political surveys, and we hope to secure some improvement in the Council itself. No international dis-cussion has yet taken place in regard to the questionnaires, but the United King-dom Departments concerned have already prepared a draft in consultation withthe Governors of the territories placed under trusteeship which could be tabledat the proper moment. Our immediate task is to select the United kingdom representative for the Trusteeship Council who, according to the terms of the charter, is required to be a specially qualified person. This appointment isunder consideration separately.C. Chapter XI.  Non-Self-Governing Territories not placed under theInternational Trusteeship System16. As stated in paragraph 2 the only specific obligation towards th&amp;United Nations under Chapter XI is the transmission of certain information to the Secretary-General. This obligation is limited by the Charter in threeways, namely- -(a) it is subject to security and constitutional limitations;       , -(b) the material is &quot; for information purposes,&quot; and(c) the material is confined to economic, social and educational conditions and does not cover, for example, political or constitutional matters.17. At the first part of the First Session on 9th February, 1946, the general assembly passed a Resolution which contained the following passage : &quot; The General Assembly requests the Secretary-General to include inhis annual report on the work of the Organisation, as provided for inArticle 98 of the Charter, a statement summarising such information asmay have been transmitted to him by members of the United Nations under.Article 73 (e) of the Charter relating to economic, social and educationalconditions in the territories for which they are responsible other than those to which Chapters XII and XIII apply.&quot;The Secretary-General&apos;s annual report would be placed on the agenda of thefollowing General Assembly and the various sections of it allocated to the appro-priate Committee in this case the Fourth. The Charter does not, however,contemplate that this material should be subject to study and recommendation by the General Assembly in the same manner as the reports submitted on the trust Territories. It is transmitted &quot; for information purposes.&quot; The terms ofreference of the Fourth Committee see page 30 of the Preparatory Commission^Report are as follows : &quot; The Tmsteeship Committee might have the large and clearly-definedtask of considering items pertaining to trusteeship arrangements as set forthunder Article 16 and Chapters XII and XIII of the Charter. This Com-mittee might also consider any matters arising under Chapter XI.&quot;(This passage in the Preparatory Commission^ report was accompanied by afootnote stating that a majority of Delegates, but not the required two-thirds,voted for the introduction of the second sentence into the draft report, but thatagainst this it was contended that it implied an extension of the authority ofthe General Assembly with regard to Chapter XI beyond the limits of the charter.) The procedure proposed by the Resolution of the 9th February would,however, have given the Assembly an opportunity of raising any points of special importance.18. On the 29th June, 1946, the Secretary-General wrote to the Govern-ments of all members of the United Nations drawing attention to this resolution and asking for their views on the definition of territories to which Chapter XIapplies and the nature of the information to be transmitted.19. It was natural, therefore, that the Fourth Committee should wishto discuss the two specific points raised in the Secretary-General&apos;s circular letter and in the replies thereto, and also the date by which the material should be
transmitted. A Sub-Committee of nineteen members* under the chairmanship of Norway, with a Polish Rapporteur, was appointed to consider these questions.Unfortunately, however, early in the proceedings of the Assembly the Secre-tariat, without any consultation with any of the Colonial Powers, had circulatedvarious documents which went considerably beyond these points and contained a number of highly controversial suggestions including a proposal that, in advanceof the Second Session of the General Assembly, the information transmitted bjrthe Member States concerned should be examined by an ad hoc Committee of experts drawn from various- Member States on the analogy of the trusteeship council. The Secretariat officer assigned to this Sub-Committee was,unfortunately, far less objective and impartial than the officers of Sub-Committee 1,a fact which proved to be a considerable embarrassment at all stages. This view was shared by a number of Delegations including the United States. The Secre-tariat documents undoubtedly set the tone of the general discussion, during whichit became clear that many Delegations wished to pervert Chapter XI into some-thing akin to an alternative form of international trusteeship with supervisionby the United Nations over all colonial administration and even in certain circum-stances a right of initiative. The Chinese Delegation went so far as to advocates-cate remission of all this material for study and report by the trusteeship council, which clearly conflicts with the Charter.20. The Indian Delegation, supported by a number of others, urged strongly that information on political matters should also be transmitted. It was pointedout that this went beyond the Charter, but the United Kingdom Delegate observedthat the United Kingdom Government had in the past sent to the Library of theLeague of Nations copies of reports on colonial affairs covering a very wide field(including political and constitutional matters) and were quite willing to sendsuch published documents in future to the United Nations Library as a voluntaryact, over and above the obligation in Article 73 (e). It is perhaps significant that both in the Minutes of the Sub-Committee and in the first draft of theRapporteurs Report of the Sub-Committee&apos;s proceedings this statement wasinaccurately recorded as a promise to include political information in the materialtransmitted to the Secretary-General, and the United Kingdom Delegation hadto ask for corrections to be made. Worse still, the draft Resolution annexed tothe Rapporteurs first draft report contained (without any explanatory comment)a paragraph recommending the inclusion of political information in the materialtransmitted under Article 73 (0), although (a) no vote of the sub-committee to that effect had been taken and (&amp;) it is clearly outside the provisions of the Charter.This was removed, but even so a passage was inserted in the final Report sayingthat the first draft had included this point, which had been deleted on the motion of the United Kingdom Delegation.21. There is, it is to be feared, little doubt that the motives of these Dele-gations arose far more from political considerations than from any genuine desireto promote the well-being of colonial peoples. In the end, despite efforts by allthe Colonial Powers, an ad hoc Committee was appointed consisting of the eightColonial Powers (Australia, Belgium, Denmark, Prance, Netherlands, NewZealand, United Kingdom and United States of America) and eight othermembers (Brazil, China, Cuba, Egypt, India, Philippines, U.S.S.R. andUruguay). In its final form the text of the Resolution setting up this Com-mittee (see Annex II) is relatively harmless, but the trend of the discussionleading up to it and the whole atmosphere of the Assembly towards this question has dangerous implications which will want watching carefully. And we mustbe prepared for a struggle to extend the scope of Chapter XI both in the ad hoc committee and at the Second Session of the Assembly.22. Another proposal relating to Chapter XI, which shows even more clearly the tendency in many quarters to contravene the provisions of the Charter, wastabled by the Philippine Delegation. The Philippine memorandum, covering adraft Resolution, pointed out that there was no organ of the United Nationscharged with the implementation of Chapter XI, and argued that some meansmust be found to enable the peoples of non-self-governing territories to ventilatetheir grievances and give expression to their aspirations.   The draft Resolution,* This sub-committee, known as &quot;Sub-Committee 2&quot; consisted of Argentina, Australia,Belgium, Brazil, China, Cuba, Denmark, Egypt, France, India, Netherlands, New Zealand,;7&quot;v* Philippines, Poland, Union of South Africa, United Kingdom, United States andU.S.S.R. It also considered the Philippine resolution (paragraph 22) and the matter of South-vy est Africa.
therefore, proposed the summoning by the Economic and Social Council of a world Conference of Non-Self-Governing Peoples, without, however, making any reference to the Governments of the responsible Member States or .to theexistence of the colonial Governments. In one of his speeches supporting thisproposal the Philippine Delegate argued that the United Nations would get theColonial Powers&apos; side of the picture through the material transmitted underArticle 73 (e), but would have no means of hearing the peoples&apos; side unless some such machinery was established. Only thus, he said, would the United Nationsbe able to take appropriate decisions for the implementation of Chapter XI.The manner in which this proposal was handled throughout the Assembly pro- jceedings gave rise to considerable criticism and, as it throws such an interestinglight on the general atmosphere of the Assembly on colonial questions, it is described in some detail in Annex III. The final form of the Resolution adoptedby the General Assembly is attached as Annex IV,23. Perhaps the most significant development from the discussion of this resolution was the reaction of the United States Delegation on realising forthe first time that there was serious risk of the General Assembly adopting a Resolution which would have the effect of summoning a Conference of UnitedStates nationals from United States territories such as Alaska, Puerto Ricoand Hawaii behind the back of the United States Government probably on united States soil. Perhaps for the first time the United States began torealise that their interests in such matters lay with the other Colonial Powersrather than with the critics. Unfortunately they still showed a tendency to seek the role of mediator instead of using every effort to secure the defeat of unsatis-factory proposals. They have, however, realised that full and frank collaboration between all the Colonial Powers including themselves will be necessary beforethe next General Assembly. It will be clearly necessary to try to follow a commonline, especially having regard to the fact that the Member States which haveresponsibilities in this field are in a minority of eight against perhaps as many as forty, and that in the present atmosphere of the United Nations politicalprejudice and racial emotion count for very much more than reason and experience. What we have to contend with is the prevailing notion that thereis something inherently reprehensible about the existence of non-self-governing-territories as such and a complete failure to admit that most of the problems which arise in these territories are merely manifestations of the same problems which arise in the critics&apos; own territories but about which their sovereign statusenables them to preserve a discreet silence.Colonial Office, 13th January, 1947.ANNEX INote on the Proposals for Amendment of the United Kingdom trusteeship agreements Recommended by the Fourth Committee but rejected by the United kingdom. The Fourth Committee recommended the deletion of the words inArticle 5 (a) of the draft Trusteeship Agreements for Togoland and Cameroonswhich gave authority to the United Kingdom to administer these areas as integralparts of the Administering Authority&apos;s territory and to apply the laws of the administering Authority. The words in question are reproduced from the mandates for these territories. In the Sub-Committee the United kingdom delegation explained the reasons for the retention of these words. It was not intended to administer Togoland and the Cameroons as integral parts of theUnited Kingdom itself nor, normally, to apply the laws of the United Kingdom,nor had the words any implication of British sovereignty in the territories.The purpose of the words was to enable the territories to be administered asintegral parts of the Gold Coast and Nigeria respectively and to apply to them the laws of the Gold Coast and Nigeria which were made by the local Legisla-tive Councils, on which there were already African majorities. The provisionof the Mandate was not merely permissive : it was obligatory. Our policy incarrying out the Mandate had now reached a stage at which Togoland and the cameroons had been very closely integrated with the Gold Coast and Nigeriarespectively and were embraced in the constitutional machinery of the two territories.&quot; It would be impossible to recede from this policy now and a glance
at the map would show that administration as integral parts of the Gold coast and Nigeria was the only practicable course. So administered, the territoriescould go forward to self-government along with the Gold Coast and Nigeria.In isolation it would be impossible to administer them at all. This argumentconvinced the Sub-sCommittee, who rejected the proposal for amendment by9 votes to 7 with one abstention. In the full Committee, however, where speecheswere limited to four minutes, it was impossible for the United Kingdom Delega-tion to make the case fully and the proposal for amendment was carried by avery narrow margin 16 to 15 with 3 abstentions. In these circumstances, theUnited Kingdom Delegation felt justified in refusing to agree to the proposalfor amendment.2. The next proposal was for the addition to all three trusteeship agree-ments (Tanganyika, Togoland and Cameroons) of a new Article in the following words : -&quot; The Administering Authority shall administer the Trust Territoryon behalf of and solely for the benefit and in the interests of its people,and on the termination of the Trusteeship ali the powers of the authority shall cease and it shall surrender the territories together with all publicproperty then existing, whether movable or immovable, to the peoples whosesovereignty and whose right to self-government or independence shall always be recognised.&quot;The United Kingdom Delegation objected to this Article on various grounds. Inthe first place the question of sovereignty in mandated territories was a highlycomplex problem of international law, which had never been settled authoritative-tively during the last 25 years and could not be settled by a vote of the assembly in the form of an article for inclusion in the trusteeship agreements. One thingwas clear, however, namely, that the Administering Authority itself did not possess sovereignty in the territories concerned. As regards the other provisionsgoverning the ultimate self-government or independence of the territories, these were, in the opinion of the United Kingdom Delegation, either safeguardedin principle by the existing text and by the Charter itself, or were matters of detail which would have to be worked out at the appropriate time in consulta-tion between the Administering Authority and the Trusteeship Council or, ifnecessary, the Assembly as a whole compare the League of Nations&apos; discussionwith regard to the termination of the Iraq Mandate, 1929-1932. This proposal had been rejected in the Sub-Committee by 10 votes to 7 but was carried inthe full Committee by 19 votes to 16 with 2 abstentions. Nevertheless, for thereasons given above, the United Kingdom felt justified in refusing to accept this recommendation.3. The third suggestion (also applying to all three trusteeship agreements)was for the insertion of a new Article in the following words : &quot; This agreement is valid for the period of ten years at the end ofwhich period it may be renewed, with or without amendments, at the discre-tion of the Trusteeship Council.&quot;The United Kingdom Delegation objected to this on two grounds, first that the sense of uncertainty created by such a provision would have an adverse effecton the development of the territories and would make any long-term planningor investment of capital impossible; secondly that it appeared to be contrary tothe Charter since the provisions for revision of trusteeship agreements were laiddown differently in Articles 79 and 85 of the Charter itself (which, incidentally,make the consent of the Administering Authority necessary), and that these provisions were specifically mentioned in the existing texts of the trusteeship agreements. In any case the trusteeship agreements dealt for the most part with broad questions of policy which were not likely to become out of date;and, therefore, the trusteeship agreements were not likely to stand in need offrequent revision. If, however, revision appeared to be necessary this couldbe effected at any time under the provisions of the Charter and of the trusteeship agreements as submitted.The proposal had been rejected in the Sub-Committee by 8 votes to 6 with3 abstentions but was carried in the full Committee by 20 votes to 7 with 8abstentions. For the reasons given, however, the United Kingdom Delegationfelt justified in refusing to accept this recommendation.[33018]c
ANNEX IIResolution on the Transmission of Information under Article 73(e) ofthe CharterThe General Assembly on 9th February, 1946, approved a Resolution oiNon-Self-Governing Peoples. By this Resolution the Secretary-General wasrequested to include in his annual report on the work of the Organisation a state-ment summarising such information as may have been transmitted to him byMembers of the United Nations under Article 73(e) of the Charter relatingto economic, social and educational conditions in the territories for which they iare responsible, other than those to which Chapters XII and XIII apply.The General Assembly notes that information has been transmitted by theGovernments of Australia concerning conditions in Papua; France concerningconditions in French West Africa, French Equatorial Africa, French Somaliland,Madagascar and Dependencies, French Establishments in Oceania, Indo-China,French Establishments in India, New Caledonia and Dependencies, Saint Pierreet Miquelon, Morocco, Tunisia, the New Hebrides under Anglo-French Con-dominium, Martinique, Guadeloupe and Dependencies, French Guiana, andReunion (without prejudice to the future status of these territories); NewZealand concerning conditions in the Cook Islands (without prejudice to anyinterpretation of the expression Non-Self-Governing Territories in view of thefact that the Cook Islands are an integral part of New Zealand); the UnitedKingdom concerning conditions in Barbados, Bermuda, British Guiana, british honduras, Fiji, Gambia, Gibraltar, Leeward Islands, Mauritius, St. Lucia andZanzibar Protectorate; and the United States&quot;concerning conditions in Alaska,American Samoa, Guam, Hawaii, Panama Canal Zone, Puerto Rico and theVirgin Islands.The General Assembly also notes that the following Governments have declared their intention of transmitting information : Belgium on the belgian congo; Denmark on Greenland; the Netherlands on the Netherlands Indies,Surinam and Curacao; New Zealand on the Tokeiau Islands; and the UnitedKingdom on Aden (Colony and Protectorate), Bahamas, Basutoland,Bechuanaland Protectorate, British Somaliland Protectorate, Brunei,Cyprus, Dominica, Falkland Islands, Gold Coast (Colony and Pro-tectorate), Grenada, Hong Kong, Jamaica, Kenya (Colony and Pro-tectorate), Malayan Union, Malta, Nigeria, North Borneo, Northern Rhodesia,Nyasaland, St. Helena and Dependencies, St. Vincent, Sarawak, Seychelles,Sierra Leone, Singapore, Swaziland, Trinidad and Tobago, Uganda Protectorate,and the High Commission territories of the Western Pacific (Gilbert and ElliceIslands Colony, British Solomon Islands Protectorate, Pitcairn Islands).The value of the association of Non-Self-Governing Territories in the workof the Specialised Agencies as a means of attaining the objectives of Chapter XIof the Charter has been stressed.The procedures to be followed by the Organisation in connection with theinformation transmitted by Members regarding Non-Self-Governing Peoples havebeen carefully examined.Therefore the General Assembly : 1. Invites the Members transmitting information to send to the Secretary-General by 30th June of each year the most recent information whichis at their disposal.2. Recommends that the information transmitted in the course of 1947 byMembers of the United Nations under Article 73 (e) of the Chartershould be summarised, analysed and classified by the Secretary-General and included in his report to the Second Session of theGeneral Assembly, in order that in the light of the experience gainedthe General Assembly may be able to decide whether any otherprocedure may be desirable for dealing with such information infuture years.3. Recommends that the Secretary-General communicate to the specialised agencies the information transmitted, with a view to making all relevant data available to their expert and deliberative bodies. 04. Invites the. Secretary-General to convene, some weeks before the openingof the Second Session of the General Assembly, an ad hoc committee composed in equal numbers of representatives of the Members trans-initting information under Article 73 (e) of the Charter and of reprfcsentatives of Members elected, by the General Assembly at this Session,on the basis of an equitable geographical distribution.
5. Invites the Secretary-General to request the Food . and agriculture organisation, the International Labour Organisation, the united nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organisation, and theWorld Health Organisation and the International Trade Organisa-tion, when constituted, to send representatives in an advisory capacity to the meeting of the ad hoc committee.8. Invites the ad hoc committee to examine the Secretary-General&apos;s summaryand analysis of the information transmitted under Article 73 (e) ofthe Charter with a view to aiding the General Assembly in its consideration of this information, and with a view to making recommendations to the General Assembly regarding the proceduresto be followed in the future and the means of ensuring that the advice,expert knowledge and experience of the Specialised Agencies are usedto the best advantage.ANNEX iii the Philippine Proposal for a Conference of Non-Self-Governing PeoplesThe rule of the General Assembly is that items proposed for the agenda shallnormally be communicated to the Members of the United Nations at leastsixty days before the opening of the Session. At the discretion of the Assembly,however, additional items can be added at shorter notice, indeed even after the session has started.The Philippine draft Resolution that the Economic and Social council should convene a world conference of non-self-governing peoples was communi-cated to the Secretariat five minutes before the final closing date fixed by theAssembly for the submission of additional items for the agenda, namely,2nd November, 1946. The Resolution, originating from a State which itselfhas no responsibilities in the field of Chapter XI, was tabled in this mannerwithout any prior consultation with any of the Member States having suchresponsibilities.2. Proposals of this kind for additional items on the Agenda are examined in the first place by the &quot; General Committee,&quot; which advises the PlenaryAssembly whether they should be added to the agenda or not. They then haveto be approved by the Plenary Assembly itself. The United Kingdom, Franceand Belgium all spoke against the inclusion of this item, and, had the UnitedStates followed suit, it is probable that the proposal could have been killed atbirth. Unfortunately, the United States felt unwilling to administer a snub tothe Philippine Delegation and spoke and voted in favour of the inclusion ofthe item on the agenda, although they assured us that they would oppose it on merits when it came up for discussion. The addition of this item to the Agendawas ultimately approved by the General Assembly which, however, appreciatingthat there might be constitutional objections to the proposal on the ground of conflict with the Charter, referred it simultaneously to the Fourth Committee(Trusteeship and Information from non-self-governing territories) and to the sixth Committee (Legal).3. Sub-Committee 2 of the Fourth Committee decided that it was uselessfor them to consider the matter until they had the advice of the Sixth Committeeon the juridical implications. When the item came up in the Sixth Committee,however, the Philippine Delegate, without any prior warning, asked for it tobe postponed. The grounds on which he based this request were that he hadlearnt that there was likely to be objection to the proposal in its present formand that negotiations were, therefore, proceeding privately with certain other delegations with a view to rewriting the proposal in a form which would makeit constitutionally acceptable. The Delegates of the United Kingdom, France,Belgium and the Netherlands strongly opposed this suggestion, which wouldresult in the submission of a new proposal after the closing date fixed by theAssembly. In particular the United Kingdom Delegate (the Attorney-General)objected to the private negotiations, urging that once a Resolution had been included in the agenda the proper place to discuss amendments was in theCommittees and Sub-Committees. The United Kingdom itself, although theprincipal Colonial Power, had not been approached in these private negotiations and Sir Hartley Shawcross demanded to know who were the Delegations with whom the negotiations were proceeding. No answer was given, but it transpiredsubsequently that the French, Belgian or Netherlands Delegations were not being consulted either.   Again, unfortunately, the United States spoke in support of
the Philippine Delegation, and it was decided by a large majority that thePhilippine Delegation should be allowed to take the proposal away and rewrite it,4. It was accordingly rewritten (largely, in fact, by the United states delegation, which had been the Delegation conducting, with this objective, thenegotiations referred to in the preceding paragraph) and came forward again in an entirely different form, whidh several Delegations (notably France andBelgium) maintained ruled it out of order as a new proposal which was too late for inclusion in the Agenda. In its revised form it drew attention to thedesirability of international collaboration, commented favourably upon thedevelopment of the Caribbean Commission and Conferences by the Member states with responsibilities in that area and advocated the extension of this system toother parts of the world.5. The proposal in its revised form came again before the Sixth Committee,whidh decided that there was no juridical objection to it in that form. TheBelgian and French Delegations maintained their objection to the wholeprocedure, refused to take any part in the discussion of the proposal, andabstained from voting.6. The proposal then came back to the Fourth Committee where it wasconsidered in Sub-Committee 2. Various amendments were tabled but in theend it was adopted in its revised form.7. It then came before the full Fourth Committee on a Sunday morning,Speeches were limited to four minutes each. After an entirely inadequatediscussion a Soviet-cum-Ukraine alternative version was adopted which omittedall reference to the Caribbean Commission and reverted in substance to theoriginal Resolution inviting the Economic and Social Council (this time&quot; together with &quot; the Member States concerned) to convene Conferences of non-self-governing peoples.* Every one of the colonial powers, including, this time,the United States, spoke and voted against the amendment, and afterwards madeexpress reservations regarding their jurisdiction in their non-self-governingterritories.8. Finally, tlhe draft Resolution as adopted by the Fourth Committee came before the Plenary Assembly where it was again the subject of controversialdiscussion and amendment. The form of wording in which it was finally passed(Annex IV) had, in fact, been suggested previously by the Delegate of Cuhaand rejected. It was acquiesced in at this stage by the majority of the colonial powers, including the United Kingdom, as representing the least objectionableversion which was likely to be carried and in particular as not involving theimportation of the Economic and Social Council into Chapter XI of the Charter.ANNEX IVResolution on Regional Conferences of Representatives of Non-Self-Governing territories the General Assembly,Considering that the Resolution on Non-Self-Governing Peoples adoptedduring the first part of the first session of the General Assembly draws attentionto the fact that the obligations accepted by Members of the United Nations under chapter XI are already in full force;Recognising the importance of the declaration contained in Chapter XI ofthe Charter, especially as it concerns the peace and security of the world, and thepolitical, economic, social and educational advancement of the peoples of Non-Self-Governing Territories as well as their just treatment and protection againstabuses;Recommends to the Members having or assuming responsibilities for theadministration of non-self-governing territories to convene conferences of rep re-sentatives of non-self-governing peoples chosen or, preferably, elected in such away that the representation of the people will be ensured to the extent that theparticular conditions of the territory concerned permit, in order that the letter and spirit of Chapter XI of the Charter may be accomplished and the wishes and aspirations of the non-self-governing peoples may be expressed.* The other two recommendations of this Sub-Committee (concerning information und&quot;Article 73 (e) and South-West Africa) were also rejected in favour of different resolutions aftysimilar inadequate discussion.


</content>
</cab>
