<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/16/0 images: 154-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE    PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret copy NO.CP. 217th Ja.nu.ary, 19^,-7*CABINETWHEAT PURCHASES IN, TURKEYMemorandum &quot;by the Minister of FoodWith reference to paper CP. (1+7) 13 circulated&quot;by the Secretary of State for. India,  I think it may be helpful for my colleagues when considering this paper tohave &quot;before them the recent correspondence &quot;between theSecretary of State and myself on this subject.      i therefore circulate herewith a copy of the Secretary ofState&apos;s letter dated the l6th December, and a copy of myreply dated 2nd January,  19U/7.(Jo S*Ministry of Food,  S.W. 1.7th January,  1 9^4-7.
ANNEX ,1Gopy of a letter dated 1&apos;6th December from, theSecretary of State for India to the Ministerof Food &quot;Would ydu please refer to your letter of 12th.December in which you suggest that H.M.G.  should divertto the United Kingdom the whole of the 125,000 tons, of wheat which the Ministry of Pood recently purchased in Turkey?2. The objection to this proposal is that His Majests^sGovernment are officially committed to making at least asubstantial part of this wheat available to India.      Whatmakes the position even more awkward is that we have headedthe Government of India off from competing with us in theTurkish wheat market by leading them to suppose that their interests were safe in the hands of the Ministry of Pood.      fappreciate your difficulties in maintaining the bread rationin the United Kingdom,  though these are certainly no greaterthan those of India where the wheat ration in some importantwheat-eating districts has recently had to be cut as low as  ounces a day.      But however acute the United Kingdomfsdifficulties may be,   they could hardly be sufficient to justify a grave breach of faith on the part of H.M.G. and a betrayalof India&apos;s confidence in our honest dealing which would have illconsequences far outweighing the practical value to this country of the quantity of grain involved.3. If H.M.G.  should in fact decide to take the step younow propose,  there would be no hope of avoiding an acrimoniouspublic dispute with India,  since apart from our own officialtelegrams to the Government of India,  the conclusion of anagreement with Turkey for the purchase of about 150,000 tons of grain for India was announced by Reuters from Istanbul as long ago as 10th November.      Whoever was responsible for thatannouncement,  it merely reflected the intentions of all theparties concerned at that time,  including the Ministry of Poodas is shown for example by your Department1s telegramNo. AMAZE X 7928 of 6th November to the British Pood Mission atV/ash.ingto.n.      In the circumstances,  the whole story would come out and I do not see how H.M.G.  could successfully defend,  againstthe criticisms of the Indian public and Government (which wouldbe bitter),  their action in bringing to the United Kingdom allthe wheat  (viz.  125,000 tons)  involved in this transaction.This criticism would inevitably be reflected in Parliament.h. It is wheat which India how needs most acutely and it iswheat which we promised the Government of India to supply.      an offer to provide 2b,,000 tons of Turkish rye,  plus 16,000 tonsof Australian barley which the Government of India are alreadyexpecting to receive as an entirely separate item, would betotally inadequate compensation for the loss of the wheat.      Thebarley which the Ministry of Pood&quot; had previously bought for indian Turkey and Iraq also seems irrelevant in this connection.As you know the Government of India agreed to refrain from buyingbarley themselves either in Iraq or Turkey on the understandingthat barley would be made available to India out of the Ministryof Pood&apos;s purchases in those countries,  after provision  had been
made from Iraq for Palestine&apos;s essential needs.      In fact,none of these items would do anything to mitigate the perfidywith which we should rightly be charged,5* You will no doubt have seen the Government of India&apos;atelegram Ho.  101+26 of 10th December  (copy enclosed) requesting that at least - 25,000 tons of Turkish wheat should &quot;be shippedto them in January and a similar quantity in February.The Government of India appear to have made this request onthe assumption that    they would also be receiving substantial quantities of wheat from Australia during these two months.I enclose a copy of their telegram No.   10337 of 8th Decemberin this connection and I should be grateful for your views onthe validity of - their assumption,  particularly in view of the drought which is understood to have affected the Australianharvest this year.      In any event,  I am quite convinced that50,000 tons of wheat for shipment next January and Februaryplus a further shipment in March is the minimum which would represent a fair settlement of H.M.G.&apos;s commitments to theGovernment of India in respect of the Turkish transaction.They may well claim that the-y are entitled to expect a largerquantity in view of the correspondence we have had with themand particularly of their agreement  to refrain from making anypurchases in Turkey themselves,6.        .      This question is of such importances  especially havingregard to the critical and delicate state of H.M..G.&apos;s presentrelations with Vae Interim Government in India,  that if in thelight of this letter you  still feel unable to accept my views,I must ask that the whole subject should be referred to theCabinet for a final decision.      The case is one of considerableurgency since it is now a month since the contract with theTurks was arranged and we cannot therefore delay any longer in informing the Government -of India what they may expect to get outof it.7. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Prime Ministerto whom I suggest that copies of your reply and of your letterof 12th December should also be sent.(Signed)    PETHIGKThe Rt.   Hon.  John Strachey, M.P.
-8 4 &amp;ANNEX IICopy of Letter dated 2nd January, 19h7from the Minister of Food to  the Secretaryof State for India1* I have received your letter of the 16th instantregarding our recent purchase of 125,000 tons of Turkishwheat.2. While I do appreciate and share your naturalconcern regarding the difficult supply position in india regret that I cannot agree that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentis officially committed to making the whole or any part ofthis quantity available to India.      It would, however, hecorrect to say that I had. hoped this might Toe possible andbut for the grave deterioration that has occurred in the wheatsupply position of the United Kingdom, which must be my firstcare , I would gladly have made arrangements to that end.3* I have no doubt that Reuters&apos;  announcement fromIstanbul may have lent some colour to the belief that thewheat would go to India, but this announcement was notauthorised by me and I do not see how it can be held toimpose an official commitment on His Majesty&apos;s Government.As regards the cable AMAZE X 7928,  to which you also refer,this message was a domestic one meant only to keep my food mission in Washington apprised of our prospects in securingsupplies in certain markets.      At the time this cable was sent it was thought that supplies to the United Kingdom wouldhave been assured from elsewhere and that the purchase of turkish wheat then under negotiation might be made availablefor India.      The message was intended to convey no more thanthat in telegraphic language.      There could clearly have been no  definite commitment to  India at that stage because wheathad not then been bought, and I am informed that no specificcommitment was made.k&apos; When the Turkish wheat was being negotiated for earlyin November,  the forward position of the United -Kingdom and.colonial areas for which T bear procurement responsibility wasgiving me concern, but it was then thought that substantial quantities of wheat and flour would be obtainable fromArgentina and Australia early in 19h7 in addition to such supplies as might become available from the United Statesagainst our uncovered requirements of nearly % million tons.Since then the position has become critical.      I had hoped to buy 500,000 tons in Argentina but this hope has not yetmaterialised.      The most recent information to my Departmentindicates that Australia will have only a very small quantityof wheat for export in 19U7j but I understand that theGovernment of India is making its own enquiries in Australia.5. In so far as  the United States are concerned,   the quantities allotted to the United Kingdom for January areonly 68,000 tons of wheat and 36,000 tons of flour,  and for
the colonies only 314,000. tons of grain sorghums.      Thesequantities may enable us to struggle through until the end.of January,, out our position thereafter will still be sograve that I could not accept the  responsibility of releasingany of the 12 5,000 tons of Turkish wheat for India or anyother destination but the United Kingdom.6. I referred in my letter of the 12th December to thepossibility of having to reduce the bread ration in thiscountry, but my responsibilities do not, unfortunately, endthere;   -indeed if the needs of the United Kingdom could bedivorced from those of the colonies my task would be much easier.-.     I note what you say about the present ration levelin certain of the wheat-eating&apos;districts of India, but I think am correct in saying that the reduced daily ration of 5 ouncesof wheat could at present be supplemented by rice from India&apos;srice producing provinces.      During recent months the total dailyration of all food grains  in our Par Eastern territories hasbeen so low as 6 ounces a day or about one half .of the officialration in India and it has only been possible to maintain thisnear-starvation level by the diversion of about 100,000 tonsof flour that is badly needed now in .the United Kingdom.In the course of the current crop year I expect to have tofind about 720,000 tons of flour in lieu of rice for those far eastern territories apart from the requirements of our othercolonies.7- Even if the whole of this quantity were obtainableit would suffice only to cover minimum consumption requirementson a ship-to-mouth basis. .8. Reluetantly,  therefore, I am compelled to adhere tomy decision in regard to the 125,000 tons of Turkish wheatbut I would ask you to believe that while I do not under-ratethe seriousness of the situation in the wheat-eating provinces of India, the deficit which faces the United Kingdom and ourcolonies is no less serious, and we have not got the internalresources of India.9. A copy of this letter and of my letter of the12th December has been sent to the Prime Minister.      Thesituation is not really one of taking wheat from India for thebenefit of the United Kingdom.  .   It is rather one of equatingIndia&apos;s needs with those of our Far Eastern territories forwhich we have direct procurement responsibility.10. I am very sorry the picture is such&apos;a black one.      Ifit changes for the better - &quot;by, for example, the receipt by us of Argentine supplies - I will let you know at once and will re-consider the destination of some part of the Turkish wheat,if and when the United Kingdom&apos;-s crisis has been surmounted andour bread ration secured.      I don&apos;t see ho?/ I can go further than that to-day.(Signed)    JOHN 8TRACHEYThe Rt. Hon.  The Lord pethick-Lawrence.-Ii-


</content>
</cab>
