<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/16/0 images: 380-382</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)G,?.(47) 36 COPY NO.___^20TH JANUARY,   1947CABINETDESERTERSMemorandum by the Minister of defence i have to reply on Wednesday,  22nd January,  tothe two following Parliamentary Questions:-LIEUT.-COLONEL LIPTON -    To ask the Minister ofDefence, whether he will make an announcementarising from the review by the service departments of the problem of deserters.MR. WILKES -   To ask the Minister of Defence,whether he will now consider proposals for ageneral or selective amnesty for the 13,176,1,500 and 392 deserters for a period of more  thanone year from the Army, R.N.  and R.A.P.respectively,  in view of the fact that policereports indicate that these deserters areresponsible for the increasing gang warfare andhooliganism, as well as the general increase inthe number of crimes of violence.I propose to make a statement on the following lines: -(a) There is a considerable number of deserters in theUnited Kingdom amounting to nearly 20,000 men.      So long as these men remain in a state of desertion,  they are not onlycommitting an offence against military law, for which theyare liable to arrest,  but  since they have no civilian status,they are dependent for food and clothing either upon private   .charity or upon breaches of the law relating to rationing andcontrol of commodities and are in many cases leading an under-ground existence.      The Government has already announced thatthere can be no amnesty to these men,  since this would give them preferential treatment over those who are complying withtheir military obligations, but it is to the advantage and well-being of the men themselves and of the nation as a wholethat they should take steps now Which will enable themeventually to. resume normal lives as free citizens.(b) Those who are now deserters are strongly recommended to surrender at once.      The fact that they are  surrendering -voluntarily and any other mitigating circumstances will betaken into  account when disposing of each particular case.-1-
(c) Those who surrender (other than men who entered onregular engagements) and have had previous service arereminded that they will have their previous service restroedfor the purpose of the release scheme if they servesatisfactorily for a further twelve months.(d) Surrender will eventually lead to the rehabilitation of each man and to restoration of full civil rights and,subject to special rules as regards war gratuity,  to thosebenefits to which his completed term of service entitles him,(e) The general public is reminded of the penalties towhich a person is liable if convicted of the offence ofconcealing a deserted.      The maximum penalty is six months&apos;imprisonment or a fine of  30 (thirty pounds).      employers should satisfy themselves that they are not even unwittinglyassisting deserters to maintain themselves.(f) The Government earnestly requests the co-operationof everyone, especially  relatives, friends and employers ofthe men concerned,   in securing that these men surrender or are traced,  and in ending the social evils which result fromthe existence in the community of numbers, of persons withoutany recognised civil status.The Prime Minister has agreed that this statement should be discussed in Cabinet  tomorrow,  Tuesday,21st January.A. V. A .Ministry of Defence, S.W.  1.,20th January, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
