<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/42/0 images: 74-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of Mis Britannic Majesty^ Gey-smiaaentJPrinted for the Imperial War Cabinet.   November 1918.SECRET.IMPERIAL WAR CABINET, 37.Minutes of the Thirty-seventh Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet, held in London, at10, Downing Street, S.W., on Wednesday, November 20, 1918, at 12noon.., Present :The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,.  Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl curzon of kedleston,  K.G., G.C.S.I.,  G.C.I.E.,1 Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Austen Chamberlain,M.P.The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M., M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Viscount Milner, G.C.B.,G.C.M.G., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Weir, Secretaryof State for the Air Force.The Right Hon. Sir Robert L. Borden,G.C.M.G., K.C., Prime Minister ofCanada.The Right Hon. Sir G. E. Foster,K.C.M.G., Minister of Trade and Com-merce, Canada.The Right Hon. W. M. Hughes, PrimeMinister of Australia.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C., Minister for Defence, Unionof South Africa.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. the Earl of Reading,G.C.B., K.C.V.O., His Majesty&apos;s HighCommissioner and Special ambassador to the United States of America.Major-General F. H. Sykes, C.M.G., Chiefof the Air Staff.Major-General W. Thwaites, C.B.,Director of Military Intelligence.The Right Hon. Sir Ertc Geddes, G.B.E.,K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, G.C.B.*C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff.The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Shipping Controller.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions.Mr. H. C. M. Lambert, C.B., ColonialOffice.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant-Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Wilson, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.[530-16]B
Carrying out ofTerms of armistice.1. THE Director of Military Intelligence reported that the allied armies had now reached the Antwerp-Brussels-Metz line, and theirmarch was progressing satisfactorily. Brussels had been entered onthe previous day.German Ill-treat-ment of british prisoners.2. The Prime Minister drew attention to the German treatmentof British prisoners. It was evident that prisoners were released from German prisons and left to find their own way, without foodor conveyance, back to their own lines. Many of them had,apparently, dropped from fatigue. He suggested that represen-tations should be made immediately to the German Government,through either the Foreign Office or the War Office, to the effectthat, unless the German Government made proper arrangements forthe provision of food and conveyances for our prisoners, we shouldbe obliged to reconsider the plans which we were making for therelief of Germany.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, with regardto the means of communicating this message to Germany, theForeign Office could only communicate through Holland or Spain.He therefore suggested that it would be better for the message to besent by wireless, en elair, to the German Command. Mr. Balfouradded that it must be remembered that the work of relief of germany was being arranged by Allied bodies and not by ourselves alone.It would therefore be necessary to obtain the co-operation of our.Allies in the matter of making representations to Germany. Itwould, however, be possible to tell them that we had been obligedto take immediate action owing to the extreme urgency of theposition of our prisoners.In this connection, Mr. Hughes said that, as we had amplesupplies of food and the Germans had not, it behoved us to send thefood by lorries and/or by train to the camps or/and to meet themen along the roads by which they were travelling to our lines.Mr. Churchill suggested that the War Office should arrange forthe despatch of lorries from our lines in advance of our armies, tomeet and convey our prisoners.Sir Robert Borden suggested that we should combine pressure upon Germany to treat our prisoners properly, with arrangements onour own part to send them food from our lines.The Imperial War Cabinet decided that (a.) The Admiralty, on behalf of the British Government, should send the following W/T message en elair&apos; to the GermanGovernment : &quot; Information reaches His Majesty&apos;s Government ofshocking lack of organisation in release of british prisoners in German territory, and of their return marchon foot, miserably clothed, without food or transport,and with no escort or guides, to the Allied lines, withthe result of lamentable suffering and heavy mortality.His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot tolerate continuation of this cruel treatment, and must insist on adequatearrangements being made, in all above respects, by german authorities with whom responsibility lies.Otherwise we shall be compelled to take this into account in any question of re-victualling Germany or satisfyingrequirements of German population. His Majesty&apos;sGovernment are ready to lend all available assistance byforwarding food, clothing, and transport to prisoners&apos;camps, where they are not otherwise forthcoming, andare addressing Allied Commanders in this sense,&quot;(6.) The War Office should call the attention of Field-marshal sir Douglas Haig to this message, and should direct himto make all possible arrangements to assist the released.   prisoners, by pushing forward food, clothing, transport,
and other relief measures, between the British lines andthe prisoners&apos; camps ; he should make such communica-tions to General Haking as he thinks advisable on thissubject, and should concert with Marshal Foch andGeneral Persking for corresponding action by the Frenchand American armies ;(c.) The Foreign Office should repeat to iiM French Governmentthe message quoted in (a), and should ask them to takecorresponding action;(d.) A statement on the subject should be made in both houses of Parliament that afternoon.Despatch ofBritish fleet to the Baltic.3. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that it wouldbe clear to anyone who had read the recent Foreign office telegrams that a show of force in the Baltic would be most useful.It would help to strengthen the populations of that part of the worldagainst Bolshevism, and might assist British interests there. He wasvery anxious, therefore, that the British fleet should be sent, in viewof the excellent moral effect that would be obtained along the south-east coast of the Baltic. He understood that the Admiralty, owingto technical reasons, were reluctant to send a fleet. The decisiontherefore appeared to be one for the Cabinet.The First Sea Lord pointed out, however, that the onlyreluctance on the part of the Admiralty was one of time, and thefact that the mines must be swept up before the fleet proceeded.The First Lord said that the Admiralty concurred in the pro-posal to send a fleet to the Baltic, provided that the proposals didnot include going to Petrograd and Finland. If the fleet were to goto Petrograd, it would be contrary to the policy of the Cabinet notto fight Bolshevism.The Imperial War Cabinet decided that The Admiralty subject to the above-mentioned proviso as tomines and destination, should make arrangements for thedespatch of a fleet to the Baltic, in consultation with theForeign Office, as may be possible and required.Report on theWork of the RoyalAir Force.4. General Sykes said that there were several points in regardto the recent work of the Air Force which he proposed, if theCabinet concurred, to embody in a Report. Amongst other mattersof interest, there were the movement of the Independent Force tothe north of France, and the taking over by the French of our aerodromes which this Force had occupied. Then there was thecollection of all Our forces in Egypt and the Mediterranean, to beready for purposes which, since the Armistice, were not now required.Again,&quot;there was the question of our police force for Egypt and mesopotamia, and the relieving of certain squadrons, e.g., the australians, who had done such wonderful work in Palestine.The Imperial War Cabinet requested The Chief of the Air Staff to prepare the Paper to which hehad referred.Arrival of Canadian 5. The Prime Minister welcomed Sir Robert Borden and SirEepresentatives.       George Foster.    He said that he had kept Sir Robert informedboth from London and from Versailles, as to the events which had led up to the signing of the Armistice.
preliminary discussion onPeace ConferenceProcedure.6. The Prime Minister said that M. Clemenceau, SignorOrlando, and probably Colonel House, would arrive in London onDecember 1, 1918, and preliminary discussions would begin on 2nd December. It was therefore necessary, between now and 2ndDecember, for the Imperial War Cabinet to come to conclusions on certain questions which had not yet been definitely decided. In the firstpUfce, there was the question as to the Government which should beestablished in places like Mesopotamia. In the second place, there wereeconomic questions, dealingwith the extent towhich it was proposed toput restrictions on the export of raw material to Germany, and for what period the restrictions should be in force. In the third place,there was the q uestion of the representation at the Peace Conference,and it was necessary that the Imperial War Cabinet should putforward its suggestions. In this connection Mr. Lloyd George saidthat M. Clemenceau bad put forward the view that there should be-five representatives of each of the Allied countries at the PeaceConference, but this was only an informal suggestion. It was undoubtedly necessary that there must be permanent delegates, butit appeared desirable that other representatives should be present inorder to discuss problems which particularly affected them.The Imperial War Cabinet deferred further discussion on thisquestion until a later date.Peace Conference.&quot; Freedom of these as.&quot;7. Sir Robert Borden said that one of the questions to bediscussed at the Peace Conference, in which it appeared probable,from information which he had received, that there would be a difference of opinion between the British Government and PresidentWilson, was the Freedom &quot;of the Seas. Undoubtedly PresidentWilson had very strong views on this question, and it would seem desirable that it should be studied from the historical, the strategic,and the political aspects, in order that the Imperial War cabinet might come to a definite decision as to the attitude which it should adopt.t. Mr. Lloyd George, in agreeing with Sir Robert Borden&apos;s sugges-tion, expressed the opinion that it would be advisable that theAdmiralty should prepare a memorandum on the various navalaspects of this question, and that the Law Officers of the Crownshould also prepare a memorandum dealing more particularly withthe historical and the legal side.The Imperial War Cabinet decided to invite (a.) The Law Officers of the Crown to prepare a memorandumdealing with the historical and legal side of the questionof the Freedom of the Seas.(b.) The Admiralty to prepare a full memorandum on thevarious naval aspects of the question of the Freedom ofthe Seas.German Colonies.8. Sir Robert Borden said that there was a still further question on which it was possible the British Government woidd differ fromthe American Government, and; this question was with regard tothe retention of the German colonies. Sir Robert reminded theImperial War Cabinet that he had already suggested by telegramthat&quot; those dominions who were principally interested in thisquestion should put forward their views, using as strong argumentsas possible. This method, in his opinion, was preferable to theclaim for the retention of any German colony being made by theBritish Government.Mr. Lloyd George said that he fully concurred in this proposal,,and that it was most advisable that, when this question came to bediscussed, the case of the German colonies should be fully putforward by the dominions principally concerned.   It was important
to remember that, when the Allies dealt with these questions at thePeace Conference, they would be in a position to dictate their terms to the enemy representatives. Mr. Lloyd George reminded theImperial War Cabinet that he had specifically informed colonel house that the view of the British Government was that none ofthe German colonies should be restored, and that those german colonies which had been captured by colonial troops, with thepossible exception of British East Africa, should be held by thedominions which had captured them.Without prejudice to the further discussion on the question ofAllied Conferences and Peace Conferences mentioned in Minute 6,the Imperial War Cabinet decided that-At the important Allied Conference which should precede the, Peace Conference, India and each self-governing dominionshould be given the fullest opportunity to express theirviews  on  those questions  which  may closely concernthem.The Imperial War Cabinet took particular note of the PrimeMinisters statement that he had, in conversation with colonel House, warned him that the British Governmentcould not consent to the restoration to Germany of any ofthe colonies captured from her, and that the german colonies which had been captured by colonial troops should be retained by those dominions which had capturedthem.Our Attitudetowards theEx-Kaiser.[530-16]9. Lord Curzon explained that, while in Paris, he had had a discussion with M. Clemenceau as to what the attitude of the AlliedGovernments should be towards the ex-Kaiser. Undoubtedly this war had been created by the ex-Kaiser, and its cruelties had been encouraged and certainly not discountenanced by him. In any othersphere of life a criminal would be brought to justice and there wasno reason why the ex-Kaiser should be spared because of his position.In his conversation with Lord Curzon, M. Clemenceau said that theFrench jurists bad not studied this question from the internationalpoint of view, but, undoubtedly, pu public opinion in France was strongly in favour of the trial of the ex-Kaiser. M. Clemenceau shared this opinion, and was anxious to know the view of the British Govern-ment on the matter. M. Clemenceau had contemplated an inter-national tribunal, composed of representatives of the Allied andpossibly of neutral States, but the feasibility of holding such a tribunal must be considered from two points of view: firstly,whether a demand for the person of the ex-Kaiser himself to theDutch Government would be successful; and, secondly, whether,if such a demand failed, it was possible to tiy the ex-Kaiser inhis absence. M! Clemenceau thought that, in such a case, itwould be possible for the trial to take place in the absenceof the accused. With regard to punishment, it might be difficultto proceed as far as execution, but, if found guilty, the ex-Kaisercould be treated as a universal outlaw, so that there woxildbe no land on which he could set his foot. Moreover, this act of justice, taken by means of representatives of all the Allies andthe neutral countries, would be the first step in calling into being a league of Nations. Lord Curzon said that he had seen the Attorney-General that morning, and, in speaking of the question of theconstitution of a tribunal in order to try criminal enemy individuals,had asked him whether his Committee had considered the questionof indicting the ex-Kaiser. The Attorney-General had told him thatthe Committee had not yet approached that question, but that many of the members were in favour of that course, and would put before the War Cabinet proposals for the constitution of a tribunal for this purpose. Lord Curzon reminded the Imperial WarCabinet that action&apos;should be taken at once, as the ex-Kaiser could&apos;       &apos; &apos;   &apos; -   -    &apos; C
now be treated as a prisoner of war, which would not be possible after the Peace Conference had been held.Mr. Lloyd George said that he did not see that it was necessaryto lay down any limit of punishment. If the ex-Kaiser were guilty,he was guilty of a capital offence, for by his action he had recklesslyput to death several millions of people. The Crown Prince was equally a culprit, as lie had been advocating this war for years.Rulers who plunged the civilised world into Avar must be made topay the penalty, and it was undoubtedly no sufficient punishment for them to retire to some neutral country and enjoy a life ofcomfort. The sense of justice in the world would not be satisfieduntil the ex-Kaiser had been brought before a judicial tribunal setup by the Allied Governments. Before that tribunal he could make his defence. Mr. Lloyd George expressed the opinion thatHolland should be informed that so long as she sheltered theex-Kaiser she could not be admitted into any League of Nations.The ex-Kaiser had committed the greatest crime possible againsthumanity, and whilst the German people had suffered much punish-ment by their tremendous losses in the field, neither the ex-Kaisernor any member of his household had even suffered privation.The Prime Minister of Australia expressed the opinion that itwould not be possible to indict a man for making war. At thesame time, it was an indisputable fact that the ex-Kaiser had committed many crimes against international law, and for these hecould be arraigned.The Prime Minister of Canada expressed the opinion that the kaiser could be tried, if at all, only for his crime against humanityin willing and preparing for this war. He eould not be successfullybrought to trial unless an international tribunal was establishedinvested with power to declare criminal the acts of which he hadbeen guilty. It would be futile to undertake his trial while he wassecure in the sanctuary of a neutral country. It was important toconsider whether we could ensure his delivery by the dutch government to the Allied nations. To determine our attitude itwas worth while to consider what we should have done with himif he had surrendered to the British, as Napoleon had done. the reference to the Attorney-GeneraPs Committee should be made asbroad as possible, and the exact phrasing might be left to the PrimeMinister and Lord Reading. They shotild consider the constitutionalpowers of the Kaiser as to declaring war.The Minister of Munitions urged that, on the basis of justice and law, it would be difficult to say that the ex-Kaiser&apos;s guilt was greater than many of his advisers, or greater than that of the Parlia-ment of the nation which supported him in making war. It mightbe that, after an indictment had been laid against the ex-Kaiser, itwould be found that it could not be sustained, and a serious impassewould be created. Mr. Churchill expressed the opinion that thisquestion should be looked at very carefully before the Governmentcommitted itself to any decision.Lord Reading said that it was most desirable that the BritishGovernment should know exactly what it proposed to do, andwhether it was feasible to prosecute the ex-Kaiser at all. He urgedthat legal opinion should be taken as to the charges on which hecould be indicted ; as to what procedure should be followed ; andas to the possibility of his being handed over by the Government of holland for trial.Mr. Chamberlain pointed out that it would be impossible to distinguish between the guilt of the ex-Kaiser and the people who supported him, and that if an international tribunal found theex-Kaiser guilty, there would be a danger to this&apos;country and to ourown people when it had apparently been decided that the ex-Kaise?was alone to be blamed for the war.   His exit from Germany ha-;been so undignified as to be extremely bitter to a great career, an.it would be a serious thing to create a Hohenzollern legend, like tljegend of Napoleon or King Charles.
739The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, alluding to the pointmade by Mr. Lloyd George, that the Crown Prince should also be tried, said that it would be very difficult to prove that the son wasanything but subordinate to his father. Mr. Balfour urged that therewere other cases of men who had committed the greatest cruelties,such as Talaat and Enver, and expressed the hope that such cases would also be considered by the Imperial War Cabinet at some future date.The Prime Minister said that he regretted to find any hesitation in the Imperial War Cabinet with regard to trying the ex-Kaiserfor high treason against humanity. This case was entirely different from that of Napoleon, who not only showed great talent and power,but himself fought with his own troops. The ex-Kaiser was a man of no strength of character, who had shown himself to be a cowardwho ran away at the first hint of trouble.The Imperial War Cabinet decided (a.) To invite the Law Officers of the Crown to examine, fromthe widest point of view, the question of framing chargesagainst the ex-Emperor , of Germany, and/or the ex-Crown Prince: ,(i.) For the crime against humanity of having caused the war; and(ii.) For offences, by one or both, against inter-national law during the war,with a view to bringing forward to one or both theresponsibility for the acts charged ;(6.) To invite the Law Officers of the Crown to consider theconstitution of a tribunal to try the charges framed ;(c.) To invite the Law Officers to examine with the ForeignOffice the practicability of inducing the Dutch Govern-ment to hand over the ex-Emperor and the Crown Princeto such a tribunal for trial.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,November 20, 1918.o


</content>
</cab>
