<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/42/0 images: 132-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Pg^erty of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.].Printed for the Imperial War Cabinet.   December 1918.SECRET.IMPERIAL WAR CABINET, 43.Minutes of a Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet, held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.yon Wednesday, December 18, 1918, at 11*30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Lord President of the Council.The   Right   Hon.    A.   Bonar   Law,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain.The Right Hon. A. J. balfour, O.M.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. W. H. Long, Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The   Right   Hon.   E.    S.   Montagu,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Viscount Milner, G.C.B.,G.C.M.G., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. the Vescount Cave, K.C.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.L.   BoRDKN,Minister   ofThe Right Hon. Sir R.G.C.M.G., K.C., PrimeCanada.The Right Hon. Sir G. Foster, K.C.M.G.,Minister of Finance, Canada.The Right Hon. W. M: Hughes,&quot; PrimeMinister of Australia.The Right Hon. Sir J. Cook, K.C.M.G.,Minister of the Navy, Australia.The Right Hon. W.F. Lloyd, K.C., PrimeMinister of Newfoundland.Major - General His Highness the maharaja Sir Ganga Singh, Bahadur,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., A.D.C., Maharaja ofBikaner.The Hon. Sir S. P. Sinha, Member ofthe Executive Council of the governor of Bengal.General the Right Hon. L. Botha,Prime Minister of the Union of SouthAfrica.The following were also present:The Right Hon. the Earl of Reading,G.C.B., K.C.V.O., His Majesty&apos;s High&quot; Commissioner and Special ambassador to the United States of America.The Right Hon. the Lord Hardinge of penshurst, K.G., G.C.B., G.C.S.I.,G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O., I.S.O.,Permanent Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 3).The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D.,Minister of Reconstruction (for Minute6).The   Right   Hon.   Sir   A.   Stanley,President of theMinutes 6 and 7).&apos;Board of Trade (forThe Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.K.C.B., First Lord of the Admiralty.Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, G.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff.The Right Hon.   Sir L. worthington evans, Bart., Minister of Blockade.The Right Hon. Sir J.. Maclay, Bart.,.Shipping Controller (for Minute 7).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankfy, K.C.B., Secretary.Brigadier-General S. H. Wilson, C.B., C.M.G., Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.[530-21] &quot;B
2Welcome to representatives ofthe Dominions.1. The Prime Minister stated that he wished to extend a welcome to General Botha on his attendance at a meeting of theImperial War Cabinet. His co-operation had always been hoped forduring the war, but as this had proved impossible, the Imperial WarCabinet especially welcomed his assistance at the forthcoming discus-sions on peace questions. He wished also to welcome, on his reappear-ance at the Imperial War Cabinet, the Maharajah of Bikaner andSir S. P. Sinha. India had been a real source of strength to theEmpire throughout the war, and notably this year, when theGovernment had been forced to take troops from Mesopotamia and palestine in order to strengthen those on the Western front. TheGovernment had had to rely increasingly on Indian troops, and these had fought gallantly and with great skill.Naval Co-operation- of the Dominionsand India.Visit of LordJellicoe.2. The Imperial War Cabinet gave their approval to a proposal of the Admiralty that Lord Jellicoe should visit, in an advisory capacity, Australia, New Zealand, Canada, and India, subject ineach case to the consent of the respective Governments. This consenthas already been given.   (G.T.-6494.)Visit of President 3. The Prime  Minister said that a  telegram had just beenWilson. received from Lord Derby (No. 1799) stating that President Wilsonwas willing to forgo his trip to Italy and Belgium in order to visitEngland, and would be ready to come to this country anytime between the 26th December and the commencement of theInter-Allied Conference, which, it was presumed, would be on the6th January. The President would wish to return to France bythe 3rd or 4th January. It was pointed out in the telegram thatthe President might be telegraphed for at any moment to go back to america. In his, -the Prime Minister&apos;^, opinion it would be agreat international misfortune if the President should return tothe United States without visiting England. He hoped therefore weshould make any date that was convenient to the Presidentconvenient to us, and that steps should be taken immediately toprepare the finest possible public reception, preferably&apos; on the26th December, which was a national holiday. In this reception the&apos;navy should take part as well as the army. In view of the changeof plans, no object would now be served by his (the Prime Ministers)going over to France with Mr. Balfour at the end of this week as originally proposed,Lord Beading hoped that nothing would be allowed to stand inthe way of our accepting the date suggested by Colonel House, andthat a reception on an unprecedented scale would be organised forthe President.Lord Hardinge said that, from the standpoint of the ForeignOffice, it was very desirable that President Wilson should visit thiscountry.The Imperial War Cabinet decided that (a.) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should reply to &apos;Lord Derby &apos;s telegram in the sense that we weredelighted at the change of plans ; any date that suitsthe President will suit us from the 26th December tothe 3rd or 4th January, but, from our point of view,the sooner the better. We should be glad to know thedate chosen as soon as possible, as the British publict were most anxious to welcome the President, and pre-reparations would have to be made. In this connection the Imperial War Cabinet would be glad to learn whetherthe President would accept the invitation alreadyextended to him by the King to stay at buckingham palace.   In view of these alterations the Prime Minister
and Mr. Balfour did not propose to carry out theirintended visit to Paris at the end of this week.(o.) The terms of the above telegram should be laid before*e theKing by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.(c.) The necessary intimations of the change of plans shouldbe made by the Foreign Office to M. Clemenceau and sign or Orlando as soon as possible.(d.) Lord Curzon, in consultation with Lord Stamfordham,should be invited to take charge of the arrangementsfor President Wilsons visit, and should assemble thedepartments concerned to draw up a complete programme for the reception of the President, both at the coast andin London.4. The Prime Minister raised the question of arriving at a clear understanding on the main peace issues which would fall to bediscussed with President Wilson during his visit to England. It was important that Mr. Balfour and he himself should be in a positionrightly to interpret the wishes of the Imperial War Cabinet, especially on territorial questions. There had been a number of general dis-cussions on the question of the German colonies, and it was agreedthat they should not be returned to Germany. But were they agreed that the United States should be asked to undertake theguardianship of some unsettled areas like East Africa or Palestine ?Then there was the question of our attitude to the Italian treaties.Were we going to be bound by the Treaty St. Jean de Maurienne ?There was at present a bitter conflict proceeding between the Jugo-Slavs and the Italians with regard to Dalmatia. Similarly, it was important that we should reach some clear understanding as tothe policy which we wished to urge in regard to Russia and constantinople. The freedom of the seas, bhe League of Nations,disarmament, indemnities, economic policy, were other large andvital problems on which attention should be concentrated imme-diately with a view to formulating in general terms proposals to guide the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and himself.Sir Robert Borden suggested it might be possible to classifythe problems into those; of major and those of minor importance.The papers dealing with the former could be studied at once andhe strongly urged that immediate meetings of the Imperial WarCabinet should be held for the purpose of discussing and determiningthese questions as far as possible. It was desirable that the memoranda on freedom of the seas, which the Law Officers and theAdmiralty had been asked to supply, should be circulated at theearliest possible moment. With reference to the German colonies itwas, he thought, generally agreed that they should not be returnedto Germany, and that some of them should be retained by thoseDominions which had conquered them, and to the future safety ofwhich they were essential. He understood that President Wilsonlaid great stress on our not interfering in the internal affairs ofRussia, and wished to apply to that country the principle of self-determination.Mr. Long said that with reference to Togoland and the cameroons arrangements had been come to with France by whichthe greater part of those territories were assigned to France. france might be willing to agree to some small readjustment of the arrange-ments which had been concluded.Mr. Balfour said that he thought the first question which shouldbe put to President Wilson was to ask him whether the UnitedStates were prepared to take some share in dealing with the terri-torial problems of Europe, Asia, and Africa. Were they prepared,for example, to take on the guardianship of Constantinople ? Unfor-unfortunately, while President Wilson would be able to answer those questions in his own name, he would not be able to bind theAmerican Senate.
Mr. Long said it was important to decide whether, when thequestion proposed by Mr. Balfour was put to President Wilson, itwould apply not only to the territories conquered by us, but also tothe territories in which France and Italy were interested. It was important that President Wilson should review the whole questionof territories everywhere, and not only East Africa, which had beenwon by our troops and was full of immense possibilities.Lord Curzon said he presumed the question would be put tothe President in its broadest sense as affecting the whole world,including Constantinople and Armenia, and not only the territories in fahich the British Empire was specially interested. We would,he presumed, ask America if she were ready to depart from hertraditional policy. The President would probably want to do so,but it was very doubtful if the Senate would agree. Lord Curzonhoped that Sir Robert Bordens suggestions would be accepted, andthat the Imperial War Cabinet would from now on sit day by day todiscuss the questions, so that the Prime Minister and Mr. Balfourmight know the views of the Cabinet on each question.Mr. Hughes suggested that we wanted to be in a position to say what line we were going to take as regards President Wilson&apos;sfourteen points.Mr. Chamberlain pointed out that what was jnecessary was thatwe should be clear as to what we wished, and then we could put this to President Wilson. If he suggested that our aims were notcompatible with his fourteen points, our representatives could arguethe question, but we need not raise it.The Prime Minister agreed that what we wanted to do was todiscuss each question in turn until we had got the general view ofthe Cabinet. He did not want to discuss any question with Presi-dent Wilson without knowing in what respect he would have to &quot; puthis foot down,&quot; as once any particular point of view was taken itwould be very difficult to alter it. He earnestly hoped that whenthe Imperial War Cabinet referred to conclusions, it was not meant that he and Mr. Balfour would be given rigid instructions as to whatthey were to say. What he wanted was a series of discussions which would give him and Mr. Balfour a general idea of the viewsheld by the Imperial War Cabinet as regards each question.Mr. Hughes thought we could not entirely ignore PresidentWilson&apos;s fourteen points. He thought we would have to considerthe fourteen points at the same time as other special questions, andthat we would have to make up our minds in what order of pre-cedence we would urge our views on the United States. He asked if the subjects were to be considered by the Imperial War Cabineton the basis of the papers already circulated ?Mr. Balfour hoped that President W7ilson&apos;s fourteen points wouldnot be referred to more than could be possibly helped, as they werenot in his opinion a good basis for a business discussion.The Prime Minister said that when the subjects were being discussed by the Imperial War Cabinet there should be a definiteagenda, which should include questions such as the Freedom of these as, the League of Nations, Disarmament, Indemnities, german colonies, Russia, the agreement with Italy, and possibly certainEconomic Questions. He suggested that the Imperial War cabinet should meet again on Friday, after there had been time to read the papers on the subject, and that on that day suitable subjects fordiscussion would be the League of Nations, Mesopotamia, Palestine,the German colonies, and Russia.Mr. Balfour again reminded the Imperial War Cabinet of whatthe Prime Minister had already said as regards the instructions ofthe Cabinet not being too definite. Difficulties would continuallyarise if they were so, and as an example of what he meant he saidthat we were continually being approached by the representativesof the different Allies (with the exception of America), askingus to back certain claims of theirs, and in view of questions like this arising it would be quite impossible for the Cabinet to tell
the Prime Minister definitely what line he was to take in a discussion which might last for months. There was already a disagreeabletendency among some of our Allies to adopt the system of &quot; log-rolling,&quot; and he had little doubt that certain of our Allies were anxious to support our claims, on condition that we supported theirs.He gave several examples.With regard to the treaty under the terms of which Italy had entered the war, it was suggested that it might be possible to leavethe Italian representatives to be dealt with by those of the UnitedStates, who might perhaps induce Italy to agree to reduce her claims under the treaty, having regard to the fact that Italy was verydependent upon the United States for finance and raw materials.The Prime Minister, however, pointed out that such a course-would - only be a half-hearted proceeding. Italy would know quitewell that if we really pressed for the claims of Italy they would beobtained. It was a question of policy involving the relations of thiscountry in Europe. We were signatories of a bond with Italywhich ought to be honoured, and we had to decide whether we were going to give Italy our whole-hearted support, in which case we might have the Jugo-Slavs against us, or leave Italy in the handsof the United States. We ought not to leave the United States tqpersuade Italy to reduce her claims; if there were any persuasionin this respect it should he applied by us in the form of advice by a friend. It would be wrong to use President Wilson to get us out ofour bargain with Italy. It must be remembered that Italy had foughtthroughout the war with only about one-tenth of the equipment which we and the French had had, and the marvel was how, with hershortage of coal and steel, she had managed to keep her guns fedat all.Mr. Hughes said that it would be helpful if the Foreign office could furnish a memorandum on the subject of our obligations to Italy. -       &apos;The Imperial War Cabinet decided (1.) To commence a systematic discussion of the various questions likely to arise in the forthcoming conversations with President Wilson, commencing with the following questions on Friday, the 20th December, 1918 : The captured German colonies.Mesopotamia.Syria.Palestine.The Italian claims.(2.) That the Secretary should circulate as soon as possible allthe relevant documents.*(3.) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should circulateas soon as possible the Foreign Office section of theGovernment brief on the various questions of foreignpolicy to be discussed at the Peace Conference, andparticularly, with the least possible delay, any relatingto the subjects for discussion on Friday next.5. The Imperial War Cabinet had before them a note by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Paper G.T.-6481) coveringnotes by the Swiss Legation and the French Embassy in regard tothe proposal from the German Government for the appointment of a neutral Commission to enquire into the responsibility for the war.*N6te by /Secretary.-Some of the relevant documents have at one time or another been circulated.   Some, unfortunately, are out of print, and will have to be-&apos; reproduced.   The resolution of the Eastern Committee in regard to Mesopotamia and palestine are not yet available for circulation.   Every effort is being made to hasten the reproduction of these documents. (Initialled)   M. P. A. H.
In the Note by the French Embassy it was stated that M.Pichon proposed to inform the Swiss Minister at Paris that theGerman Note required no reply, the responsibility for the warhaving been long since established incontestably by all the docu-ments. He would be glad to know whether he was in agreement onthis subject with Mr. Balfour.The Imperial War Cabinet decided (a) That the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should reply that His Majesty&apos;s Government were in complete agree-ment with the answer which M. Pichon proposed toreturn to the Swiss Minister at Paris;(b) That the Secretary of State  for. Foreign Affairs should ask the United States Embassy whether they havereceived a similar enquiry and what they proposed to reply.-     6. The Imperial War Cabinet had before them a Joint Memo-randum by the Home Office and [the Ministry of Labour (PaperP. 41) in regard to Labour matters and the Peace Conference.The Imperial War Cabinet decided That the question should be placed among the other itemson the Agenda Paper for the special series of meetingsof the Imperial War Cabinet which were to be held inconnection with questions to be discussed at the PeaceConference.Future Shipping 7. The&apos; Imperial War Cabinet had before them two papers byPolicy. the Ministry of Shipping (Papers G.T.-6472 and G.T.-6482) in regardto the tonnage situation in relation to future shipping policy.It was shown that the armistice had brought with lightningspeed an entire change of conditions. Immediately prior to thearmistice the pressure on shipping was at its maximum: but with the conclusion of the armistice and the cessation of hostilitiesan enormous amount of tonnage had become quickly free, and it was difficult for the moment to utilize it fully,Sir Joseph Maclay said that the United Kingdom was floodedwith foodstuffs. He was told that there was now sufficient wheat in the country to supply our needs until the next harvest. Nodifficulty was anticipated in the carriage of troops. A number ofships had been sent to Australia to bring Australian wheat, which to some extent relieved the position, and every kind of commoditywhich the country &quot;required was being brought freely in andno difficulty was expected with regard to required importations.It must be remembered that other nations, particularly the japanese and Americans, were busily engaged in getting hold of our sea-bornetrade. Sir Joseph Maclay added that, in the interests of national economy, the moment was opportune for the discontinuance of thesystem of general requisition as an essential preliminary for theproper re-establishment of British trade. The power of requisitionwould, however, be retained for use in case of need, and certaintonnage would in any event have to be kept under requisition forsome considerable time. He therefore proposed to complete arrange-ments as rapidly as possible for the substitution of direction andcontrol of shipping by licence in place of control by requisition......On the other hand, it was pointed out that although at thepresent time the machinery of business was no doubt at a standstill,and therefore manufacturers had little to export, it was clear that in ashort, time, say, two or three months, the normal flow of raw materials and exports would begin again. If therefore shipowners were nowtoj have their fleets returned to them to be placed in distant andhighly profitable trades, e.g., China and the Far East, the timeLabour matters and the PeaceConference.
omight soon arrive when we would be faced again with the problemof shortage of tonnage and high freights.Mr. Churchill said that the system of rationing of food,materials, &amp;c, -had been necessary on account of the tonnagesituation. If now shipping was as plentiful as the ShippingController had indicated, not only should shipping but moreespecially food and materials be released from Government control.A case could even be made out for directing more ships to bringmore food.&quot;Lord Reading said that as a result of his recent investigationsinto the problems of revictualling and supply of Allied, neutral, and enemy countries, he had come to the conclusion that the release from Government control of shipping could not be regarded as a problem by itself. The whole question of Government control,whether of shipping, food, or materials, should be treated as one.The Prime Minister suggested that a Committee should be setup to examine the question of the release from Government controlof shipping, and that the Dominions should be represented on theCommittee^The Imperial War Cabinet decided That Sir Joseph Maclay should convene a meeting for thispurpose, which should consist of the following members : Sir Joseph Maclay (Chairman).Lord Reading..   Sir J. Cook.Sir G. E. Foster.Sir A. Stanley.Mr. Churchill.Dr. Addison.Mr. Astor.who should examine the question of the release from Govern-ment control of shipping in relation to food and materials,that in the event, of agreement, the conclusion of theCommittee should be regarded as final, and that only inthe event of a failure to reach agreement should thequestion be referred back to the Imperial War Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,December 18, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
