<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/76/0 images: 22-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HTS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT^ULCJULi copy N0&apos;CABINET    31  (33).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY, April 26th,193 3 9 Q- &quot;t 11 * 0 &amp; * m %AGENDA.1. FOREIGN AFFAIRS.      -      (if required).2. EGYPT:    RESUMPTION OF TREATY NEGOTIATIONS.(Reference Cabinet 50(32), Conclusion 6).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.(CP. 109 (33)    -    already circulated).3. LOCAL GOVERNMENT LAW CONSOLIDATION.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.(CP.  113(33)    -   circulated herewith) .(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.24th April, 1933.
\ SECRET.COPY NO.CABINET    31 (35).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,April 26th, 1953, at 11.0 a.ra.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.    (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M,P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E. ,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, fc.C.S.1.,K.C.V.0.,0.B.E. ,K.C. ,M.P. ,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The. Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E. ,C.M.G.,M.P.; Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.Major The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C. ,M.P. ,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D,S.O.,M.P., Secretary of State for home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, doubt,G.B,E.,C.M.G.,M.P., SecretaryofState for India.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K*G.,M.V.0., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G.B.E.,D.S.O.,D.S.C.,M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Irwin, K.G.,G.C.S.I.,G.C.I.E., President of theBoard of Education,The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,C.B.E.,M,P., Minister of Labour.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works.5olonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B.,G.C.M.G.,............... Secretary.l this  DQOTTltfrWNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&quot;1 S GOVERNMENT) .
1. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that the Japanese, after theoccupation of Jehol, had, for military reasons, beengradually nibbling into China.   A situation had arisen not unlike that which had existed at one time at Shanghai, namely, that the Japanese did not knowhow to stop.   Their movements for defensive purposesled to counter-attacks, and the situation was develop.-ing in such a w^ay that in time there might even bea question of a Japanese occupation of Peking.The Japanese had recently indicated that they wouldlike Sir Miles Lamps on to use the same good officesas he had in the Shanghai affair.   At first Sir miles lampson did not like the idea, and the Secretary ofState had told him not to act without a request fromthe Chinese.   Now that application had been received,and it was difficult to see how we could avoidsanctioning his rendering good offices.   He had accordingly told Sir Miles Lampson that he was willingfor him to do his best, in order to avoid the dangers to which he had alluded.
THE TEXTILETRADE.Japanese Corn-petition .(previous reference:Cabinet 22(33), Con-clusion 4.)FR.3^3$)//.2. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that just before Easter he had seen the Japanese Ambassador, as had been decided at   fthe Meeting referred to in the margin, and had suggested that he should put himself in touch withthe President of the Board of Trade.   mhe ambassador had agreed to this and had asked to associate withhim his Commercial Attache.    Since the Easter Recessthe Ambassador had visited him and spoken of theconsternation of the Japanese Government and Japanesecircles at the action recently taken by the Governmentof India in denouncing their Treaty with Japan,especially without any previous discussion.   He had replied by referring to his previous interview andhad explained that. India&apos;s case was different fromthe one he had then discussed, and that the indian government was not subject to the British Governmentin these matters.The President of the Board of Trade said thatMr. Matsudaira had been to the Board of Trade,accompanied by his Commercial Attache&quot;, and had spokenas to India on the same lines as the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs had just reported.   He had asked if it would be possible for him to see theSecretary of State for India.   The President had replied that he was sure this could be managed, andhad explained that India did not accept dictation inthese matters from the United Kingdom.   On the BritishEmpire position the Ambassador had expressed alarmat the prospect of anything In the nature of wholesaleprohibition,   ^he President had replied that we werenot disposed to take such drastic action as that without prior consultation,, but had dwelt on the seriousness of the situation.    mhe Japanese Commercial
Attache had combated this point of view.   He hadadmitted that, owing to the high rate of exchangeof the yen, they had been able to purchase raw materialsvery cheaply.   Their stocks, however, were becomingexhausted, and the value of the yen had fallen, withthe result that in future their competition would be far less serious.The President of the Board of Trade had thensuggested that the Japanese Government might get together some representative commercial men, and hewould try to do the same here   a subject on whichhe had already sounded the Lancashire industry.   TheCommercial Attache had favoured the idea personallyand had undertaken to commend it to his Government,for whose view, however, he could not at present speak.The President added that he had made a note of this conversation and would communicate it to the Secretaryof State for India.    If the Indian Government desiredany conference between their commercial representatives and those of Japan, he thought that they should be intouch with the Board of Trade.The Secretary of State for India said he wouldtelegraph the facts to India and ascertain the viewsof the Government.
EGYPT *Resumptionof TreatyNegotia-tions.(previous reference:Cabinet 50(32), Con-elusion 6 ,)3.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (C.P4-109(33)) circulating the following Papers:-(l) A brief outline of previous negotia-tions and of modifications in previousoffers entailed by the new draft.(2) A note on the reasons for and againstthe initiation of steps leading up toAnglo-Egyptian negotiations.(3) A note on the points at issue betweenthe Service Departments and the ForeignOffice, on which a decision is required should it be decided to open negotia-tions.(4) A note on the position which it isintended under the Foreign office proposals to secure for the Sudan*(5) The text of the full draft TreatySettlement.The course of action proposed by the Secretary ofState, should the Foreign Office suggestions be approved, was that His Majesty&apos;s High commissioner in Cairo should be instructed (after the necessarycommunication has been made to the Dominions) to openpreliminary discussions with the Egyptian PrimeMinister on the two main points of the location ofthe forces and of the Sudan.   On receipt of the HighCorrmissionerTs report of the result of these conversa-tions it should be possible to decide whether or notto proceed with the negotiation of the draft settle-,ment as a whole.    The Secretary of State emphasised that in his  judgment and in that of his advisersthere was no possibility of securing a Treaty settle-,ment with Egypt on terms less favourable to thatcountry than those contemplated in the Foreign Officedraft.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs made astatement to the Cabinet emphasising the various points in his Memorandum.   The Declaration of Booembe-r,1922, made clear that agreements were to be concluded
on the subject of the four Reserved Points,   Threeattempts had been made, without s&apos;.uccess .    He wasunder constant pressure on the matter.   More favour-able conditions for a settlement than those nowexisting were not likely to occur.    If the presentopportunity was not taken to reach a settlement,relations with Egypt must deteriorate.   There wasno prospect of a Treaty unless agreement was reached on the two main points of the location of the forces and of the Sudan.    That was why he proposed that,after consultation with the -Dominions, the HighCommissioner should be instructed to open preliminary discussions on these two points.Turning to these two points, he pointed out thatsubstantially it was proposed that the position ofthe Sudan should remain as at present.    On thequestion of the location of the troops the alterna-tives were, to withdraw from Cairo and Alexandriaand concentrate east of Long, 32QE., as proposed bythe Foreign Office, or to state that we were notprepared to. remove from the vicinity of Cairo, asdesired by the Defence Departments.    If the latteralternative were adopted he could hold out no hopeof obtaining a Treaty at all.   He elaborated thispoint at some length.    If we were to negotiate at all we must do so with some good cards in our hands.We now had two:    first, that Egypt v/anted to become a member of the League of Nations, their claim towhich was much strengthened by the fact that Iraqhad become a member;    and, second, that they wanted to get rid of the capitulatory system, which was nothing less than a scandal.   Promise of support onthese two points provided a valuable bargainingfactor, but if negotiations were postponed this might
no longer be the case.   He thought, therefore, thatthe High Commissioner should be given the ins.tr.uc-tions which he now proposed.In the course of the discussion the view was strongly supported that if negotiations were to be-undertaken they ought to take place in London andnot in Cairo.   The High Commissioner, even thoughbeginning with a discussion of the two points referred to, might easily be drawn into a discussionof the whole Treaty.    In the atmosphere of Cairo hewould, have every incentive to reach agreement, and itwould be awkward if the Government later on had to throw him over.    It was urged that it would be better to hold the discussions in London, where the ForeignOffice would be in closest touch with the defence departments and other Departments concerned.The Secretary of State for Dominion affairs reminded the Cabinet of the strong interest ofAustralia and New Zealand in this question,    ^heDominions had been informed of the present position.He read a telegram from the Prime Minister of theCommonwealth indicating that the Australian government considered, the present opportunity as favourable asis likely to offer for the resumption of negotiations;agreeing that it is desirable to secure a substantial modification of the terms offered in 1930 as to the location and strength of the British forces in Egypt;favouring the new proposal as to the location ofthose forces, but suggesting the omission of therestriction on their total strength:    and concurringin the United Kingdom Government&apos;? attitude as to theSudan.   No reply had yet been received from NewZealand.
The Secretary of State for War put before theCabinet the advice he had received from the militaryauthorities.    Since the Declaration of 1922 the responsible military advisers of the Government had,without exception, held that the removal of thetroops from Cairo to the banks of the Canal could notbe effected without imperilling the first of the reserved Points of the 1922 Declaration, viz., thesecurity of the communications of the British empire in Egypt.    As mentioned briefly in C.P.-109 (33),Lord Trenchard had expressed the view that althoughtroops disposed as at present constituted the bestdefence of the Canal, yet the same number of troops(ground, air and other services) could defend the canal if stationed in the vicinity, provided that alarge sum. of money were first expended in making thenecessary stations.    Lord Cavan, who was then Chiefof the Imperial General Staff, had not accepted thisview;    neither had any of his successors;    and theCommittee of Imperial Defence had accepted the Reportof the Chiefs of Staff without Lord Trenchard&apos;observations.   He reminded the Cabinet of the circum-stances in which the Chiefs of Staff Committee hadreiterated their views in 1929 and 1930 (C.I.D. PapersHos . 957-B and 1011-B).    He did not suggest that military considerations must necessarily over-ridepolitical expediency.   That was a matter for theCabinet to decide:   but in taking their decision they ought to know what view their military advisers heldof the risks .   The Foreign Office view, as set forth in the Memorandum, was that efi- Egypt bound to thiscountry by a Treaty of Alliance was not in the leastlikely either herself to attack the Canal or toassist any other Power to do so.   The view of the
military authorities, however, was that they couldnot ensure or be responsible for the safety of theSue-?:. Canal against attack from the West if the troops were restricted as now proposed.    In saying this he paid a tribute to the efforts of the Foreign Officeto improve the situation as compared with the 1930negotiations,,    On the political side he recalled thatin 19S2 all we had undertaken to do was to try andreach agreement on the four&quot; Reserved Points,    It couldbe said that if the Egyptians refused the only grounds on which the first of the four Reserved Points couldbe secured, it was their responsibility and not ours.It appeared to him also that the avoidance of an expenditure of  8,000,000 to  10,000,000 by theEgyptian Government and the possibility of there being no British force near Cairo for the protection of theKing of Egypt in case of necessity were considerationsthat ought not to be ignored.The Secretary of State for Air informed the Cabinetthat the Canal Zone East of Long. 320E. suited theRoyal Air Force, but that the air forces must be inthe vicinity of the troops.In the course of the discussion the question was raised as to whether there was any intermediate pointsomewhere between Long. &apos;32D E. and Cairo at which british troops might be,stationed in order to secureour Imperial communications without offending Egyptianopinion, e.g., in the vicinity of the point wherethe Sweet-Water Canal joins the Kile.The Home Secretary, who had served in Egypt duringthe War, emphasised the great importance of controlling the head-waters of the Sweet-Water Canal.   He recalled that it had not been found possible to defend the suez Canal at its edge, and that was why our troops
had had to advance to Gaza,   He -understood thatagainst attack on the Canal from the West the occupa-tion of Cairo was required for similar reasons.There was one point raised by the Home Secretary,and developed by other members of the Cabinet,which was felt to require further consideration.It was recalled that the Indian policy of theGovernment was being attacked on the ground that ourhold on India was being relaxed.    If it became known that we were contemplating withdrawing the forces from Cairo and that this was being done contrary to military advice, the political situation would be aggravated.The Cabinet felt that the position requiiredfurther consideration and that they would like tohave more detailed information on the military aspects of the question, including such points asthe importance of the Sweet-Water Canal;    thearrangements for water-supply in the event of a withdrawal East of Long. 320 E.;    and the possibilityof the troops being stationed at some intermediatepoint.With the assent of the Secretary of State for Warand the Secretary of State for Air, the cabinet agreed  That the Lord President of theCouncil and the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs should discuss the quest-ion with theChiefs of Staff Sub-Committee ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence,with a view to a further Reportbeing prepared by them for theinformation of the Cabinet .
LOCAL GOVERN- 4. ^ke Cabinet had before them a Memorandum byMENT LAWSONS OLID AT ION ,the Minister of Health &apos;C.P,-113 (33)) asking(previous Reference:Cabinet 62(32),  Con-clusion 6 .)Cabinet approval to the introduction in the Houseof Lords of a Pill to consolidate, with minor amendments, the law relating to local governmentin England and Wales,   Copies of the draft bill and of the Report of the Local Government and PublicHealth Consolidation Committee (of which the bill was the outcome) were attached to the Memorandum.The Cabinet agreed:-To approve the introduction in theHouse of Lords of a Bill to consolidate,with minor amendments, the law relatingto Local Government in England and Wales,and the Minister of Health1s suggestionthat the Bill should be referred to aJoint Select Committee of both Houseswith a view to their examining and reporting on the changes in the laweffected by the Bill,
5.     The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed theCabinet that he had seen the representatives of the government-operative Societies on the afternoon of Monday,April 24th.     They had &quot;begun by a statement to theeffect that they found the Chancellor&apos;s proposalsunacceptable, but were prepared to continue negotia-tions, preferably with Officials of the Treasury.They had suggested that this discussion should be onthe basis of their agreeing to submit to taxationthe profits made with non-members and their invest-ment income, but that payments under Schedule &apos;A&apos;should be deducted from the latter.     The chancellor had pointed out that agreement on those lines wouldappear to be a surrender on his part.     He had,however, agreed to discussions between the societies and of Officials of the Treasury on the understandingthat any settlement must be capable of being repre-sented as a fair compromise.     He had told the societies that it would be necessary for him to putdown the Resolution in fairly wide terms, but thatthe Bill would not necessarily conform to the termsof the Resolution.     To that they had not -shown somuch objection as he had anticipated.     They asked if they were expected to produce a fair sum for theTreasury, and he had replied that this was so.They had then asked if the Chancellor would notdispense with a Resolution by the Committee of theHouse of Commons.     He had explained that he attached importance to this.     After the meeting hehad prepared to table a Resolution.     Later, however,the Co-operative Societies&apos; representatives heldanother meeting and sent him a letter covering a
Resolution in which they asked him to withhold tablinga Resolution in the House of Commons, and. pending a reply,suspended their discussions with the TreasuryOfficials.      That would have prevented the Chancellorof the Exchequer from saying that discussions were going on,and consequently in the House of Commonslie had spoken as follows:-!&apos;Some provision will have to he inserted in the Finance Bill and, in due course,I shall ask the Committee to pass aResolution which will enable us to putinto the Finance Bill such provisions asmay ultimately he found expedient.    Inthe meantime, in order not to prejudice the possibility of our arriving at asatisfactory settlement, I am not proposing to table a Resolution to-day.&quot;The Co-operatives had seen Treasury Officialsthis morning and took the view that they could not pay more than  100,000 to  150,000.     The Chancellorof the Exchequer warned the Cabinet that, in thesecircumstances, he would probably have to come back and ask for a decision on the basis that no agreement could, be reached.Some discussion took place as to the Co-operative societies&apos; suggestion that they should be allowed todeduct Schedule &apos;A*  from the taxation of investments,and a suggestion was made that the Chancellor of theExchequer should have prepared an explanation of thispoint for the benefit of those of his colleagues whowere concerned to defend the policy of the Governmenton this point in the country.     The Chancellor of theExchequer warned the Cabinet that he might have to ask them to deal with this question fairly soon.
6.     The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,in accordance with the precedent of recent years,asked his colleagues to agree    that, notwithstanding the urgent need tot economy, the usual officialDinner should he given at the Foreign Office to the diplomatic Corps on the occasion of the King&apos;birthday.     Owing to the incidence of Whitsuntidethe most convenient date would he June $rd.The Cabinet agreed:-That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should arrangefor the usual official Dinnerto the Diplomatic Corps in connectionwith the King&apos;s Birthday,THE KING&apos;birthday.The Secretaryof State forForeign Affairs&apos;Dinner.(previous reference:Cabinet 27(32) ,Conclusion 10).fA
ESPIONAGE.The RecentCoiirt-Martial.7,     The Secretary of State for &quot;War informed theCabinet that the Officer condemned for espionageat the recent Court-Martial had made a fullconfession of the crime of which he was convicted,2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.26th April, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
