<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/76/0 images: 299-321</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JJQJ20CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY15 GOVBRNMEN1:COPY NO,C A B I N E, T    45 (53).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,12th July, 1933, at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1. MONETARY AND ECONOMIC CONFERENCE.  -    (If required).-  (Reference Cabinet 44(33), Conclusion l).2&apos; REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.(Reference Cabinet 44(33), Conclusion 6).Note by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, covering record of conversation between Mr. Henderson, Mr. Thomas andMr. Eden.(CP. 176(33)    -   to be circulated).3. EGYPT:  RESUMPTION OF TREATY NEGOTIATIONS.   - (if ready).(Reference Cabinet 31(33), Conclusion 3).Memoranda by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.(CP.  109(33)    -   already circulated).(CP. 152(33)    -   already circulated) .Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.(CP.  119(33)    -   already circulated).Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.(CP. 124(33)    -   already circulated).4. ARTICLE 21 OF THE UNITED KINGDOM - CANADIAN AGREEMENT(RUSSIAN TIMBER).    &quot;    (If ready).(Reference Cabinet 36(33), Conclusion 12).Memorandum by the President of the Board ofTrade.(CP, 177(33)    -    to be circulated).
5.  ISLE OF MAN CUSTOMS BILL.(Reference Cabinet 40(32), Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer, covering draft Bill.(CP. 178(33)    -   to be circulated).(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.10th July, 1933.
hts DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)gjsC R E T,COPY NO.CABINET    45 (35).Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at 10Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,12th July, 1933, at 11,0 a.m.ADDITIONAL ITEM TO AGENDA.6.  INDIA:    ATTITUDE TO BE ADOPTED TOWARDS MR.  GANDHI.(Reference Cabinet 33(33), Conclusion 7).(Question to be raised &quot;by the Secretaryof State for India).(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.p Whitehall Gardens, S.W.111th July, 1933.
BjajTOCDlAENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .igj^R E T. COPY NO.cabinet    45 (33).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cab inet heldat 10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,12th July, 1933, at 11.0 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister. (In the Chair).le Right Hon.fstaniey Baldwin, M.P. ,Lord President of the Council.Re Right Hon.gfSir John Gilmour, Bt. ,D.S.O. ,fM.P. , Secretary of State forffiorae Affairs.ife Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.He Right Hon.&quot;Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E, ,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for India.He Right Hon.&quot;Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E.,M.O.,M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.He Right Hon.&quot;Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P. ,President of the Board ofTrade.sbs5l^e Right Hon.lord Irwin, K.G. ,G.C.S.I. ,p.C.I.E., President of theJpoard of Education.me Right Hon.IjSir Henry Betterton, Bt. ,WJ.B.E. ,M.P. , Minister ofiLabour.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E. ,Lord Qhancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.X. ,K.C.V.O.,0.B.E.,K.C.,M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K.G.,M.V.O., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G.B.E. ,D.S.O. ,D.S.C ,M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres-Monsell,G.B.E.,M.P,, First Lord of theAdmiralty.Major The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C.,M.P,,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.Major The Right Hon..W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., first commissioner of Works.
THE monetary and ECONOMICCONFERENCE,(previous reference:Cabinet 44(33). Con-elusion 1.)1,   The Prime Minister said he had nothing to add beyond what had been stated in the recentParliamentary Debate.   The pessimism revealed incertain organs of the Press today was unjustified.The decision by the Bureau of the Conference should enable difficulties to be dealt with as they arose.
Deduction andliiTATiofl opLjft Disarmament&quot;jonferenee:(Previous-Reference:Cabinet 44(33), Con-clusion 6.)2. The Cabinet had before them a Note by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (C.P.-176 (:33))circulating for the information of his colleaguesa Memorandum prepared at his request by the Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairsgiving the record of a further discussion withMr Henderson on the procedure the latter proposedto follow in his forthcoming conversations with theFrench, German and Italian Governments on the subjectof Disarmament.   The Secretary of State for Foreignhimself . n. .Affairs/and the Secretary of State for Dominion Affaxrshad also been present.   The nature and object of the conversations had been discussed, and Mr Hendersonhad warned them that the following questions wouldcertainly arise:-(l) ^he extension to the world of theNo-Res ort-to-Force Declaration:(2) The Definition of &quot;Aggression&quot;:and(3) Police Bombing.Mr Henderson intended to proceed to Paris on July 10th,afterwards visiting Berlin and Rome, and would let the Secretary of State know at once if he requiredany assistance.and the manner in which, in his opinion,it could best be given.The Prime Minister pointed out that the three questions referred to above, which Mr Henderson had said were likely to arise, were the exact points which His Majesty&apos;s Government did not want todiscuss at present.mhe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs saidthat was why, as mentioned in the next paragraph ofthe Memorandum, Mr Henderson had been told that -&quot;If, by his conversations, Mr Hendersoncould secure a likely basis for Franco-German agreement, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would be prepared to give
sympathetic consideration to allthese matters, but they were notprepared to make further piecemealconcessions in advance of such aprospective accord&quot;.The attention of the Cabinet was called to astatement made by the Parliamentary Under-Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs in the House of commons during the Debate on July 5, 1933, in the course ofwhich, referring to remarks in a speech by the member for West Birmingham (Sir Austen Chamberlain) on ourreservations in respect of bombing in outlyingdistricts, he had said -&quot;I can assure him that I should feel as strongly as he the terrible responsi-bility of any breakdown of the Confer-ence upon such an issue&quot;.The question was raised as to whether this was consistent with the Cabinet decision in favour ofmaintaining the right of bombing in outlying districts .The Cabinet were reminded that Sir austen chamberlain, who had great influence in the Houseof Commons, had made a powerful speech against theretention of Police-bombing, and it had beenabsolutely impossible for any Minister speaking onbehalf of the Government to avoid an immediate reply .When the speech was read as a whole it would be seenthat the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State hadbeen most careful to bring out how small an issue was this question of Police-bombing compared withthe great political issues that were holding up theConference:    and this point had been emphasised bythe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs ina subsequent speech.The Prime Minister said he was receiving a largenumber of letters enclosing resolutions, and so forth,on the question of Police-bombing, and he felt it wasone which would have to be handled with great discre-tion.
EGYPT .in \*Resumption0f treaty negotiations(previous reference:Cabinet 44(33)? Con-clusion 8.)3. The Cabinet had before them the following documents on the subject of Egypt and the resumptionof Treaty Negotiations, consideration of which had been postponed at the Meeting mentioned in the margin:-A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (CP.-109 (33)),which had been considered by theCabinet on April 26th (Cabinet 31 (33),Conclusion 3):A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor India (CP.-119 (33)) coveringtelegrams exchanged with the Governmentof India on the question of the futurelocation of the British forces in Egypt:A Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee of the Committee of ImperialDefence (CP.-124 (33)) on the military aspect of the Anglo-Egyptian TreatyProposals (1933), submitted in accord-ance with Conclusion 3 of Cabinet 31(33):A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (CP.-152 (33))commenting on the above Report of theChiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.The trend, of the views of the Cabinet, as resultingfrom the discussion of these Papers, may be summed upas follows:-(a) At the present moment it is undesirable to make any communication to the egyptian government on the subject of the proposed treaty negotiations:(b) When the Egyptian Government press for a reply, as no doubt they will when afavourable    opportunity (such as the arrival in Cairo of the High Commissioner) arises,they should be told that our preoccupationsin the coming winter make it impossibleto begin conversations now, but that wedo contemplate doing so some time inthe course of next year:(c) That, in agreeing to negotiations nextyear, notwithstanding the statement ofthe Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs that &quot;there is no prospectwhatever, in my view, of the present or any Egyptian Government acceptingany Treaty which maintains the Britishtroops in or near Cairo&quot; (C .P.-152 (33)),the Cabinet are in no way committed toa decision in favour of removing thetroops from the neighbourhood of Cairo:(d) That whenever a communication on thesubject has to be made to the egyptian government, It would be inadvisable,in the first stage,to warn them of the
special difficulties likely to arise in connection with the Sudan and the stations for the British troops:(e) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should consider thebest time and method for giving effect to the above policy.-5-
VERY SECRET..ADDENDUM. TO CABINET 45 (55)CONCLUSION 3   &quot;EGYPT&quot; .(By instructions from the PrimeMinister the following addendumto the Conclusion on EGYPT hasbeen prepared for record in thestandard file of Cabinet Conclu-sions, a copy being sent to theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs.)*     *     *THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that a personal as well as a political question was raised by the discussion of the proposed treaty with Egypt.    Some people were highly critical ofSir Percy Loraine, the present High Commissioner.In his view these criticisms were not all justified.Sir Percy Loraine had had to succeed Lord Lloyd andchange the policy.    In doing so he had managed, tobecome the target for a certain amount of gossip andcriticism.   But the fact remained that there was this body of criticism,, and in the circumstances he did notthink Sir Percy Loraine was the right man to negotiate a Treaty, &quot;for the reason that he would attract a certainamount of talk and challenge, more particularly in viewof the reactions of Egyptian on Indian policy.   he recalled that Sir Percy Loraine was appointed HighCommissioner in August, 1929, and his five years term,therefore, would, come to an end in the summer of nextyear.    There was no question of renewing his appointmentin Egypt.    If negotiations with a view to a new Treatywere undertaken they could not be&apos;finished before he left.   There was, therefore, strong reason for adopting the view that any conversations or negotiations for aTreaty should, be undertaken not during Sir PercyLorainefs time, but in the time of his successor.
There was no justification for terminating Sir percy loraine&apos;s diplomatic career:   he would be promotedelsewhere according to a time-table.   The question,however, could not be postponed indefinitely, and it-would be necessary promptly to get the best man avail-able to succeed the present High Commissioner.    Inthese circumstances he thought it might be possible to let the Egyptian Government know that we were too busynow and would continue to be too busy during the coming winter to be able to take up thenegotiations beforenext summer.   This would give time for further considera-tion of the question of the location of the troops and would enable Sir Percy Loraine to return to cairo and pack up.   He recalled that one of Lord Lloyd&apos;scomplaints had been that he had been removed without being given a proper opportunity to pack up at Cairo.It had been unfortunate that Sir Percy Loraine had hadto return to England last March in connection with a personal bereavement.   Later, in June, he had had an operation, and his medical advisers discouraged him from returning in the hot weather.   This had ratheraccentuated the criticisms already referred to.Summarising his views, the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs said -(l) Sir Percy Loraine&apos;s time expires next summer;    there is no question of are-appointment;   he would not be ableto complete the negotiations.(2) Consequently the negotiations ought tobe begun by the new High Commissioner,who would see the whole business through.(3) He must do what was right by Sir percy loraine, and would like to consider thequestion of his successor as soon aspossible.    Sir Francis Humphrys, he feared, would not be available, but sir Miles Lamps on might perhaps fill the post.(4) He would propose to tell the egyptian government that the question of the
Treaty could not be dealt with, just nowowing to heavy preoccupation elsewhere,but that we proposed to enter intoconversations next year.The Cabinet were reminded that Sidky Pasha was still indisposed and at the present time was inSwitzerland.The Secretary of State&apos; s plan was cordiallysupported by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and others,but the point was made that by agreeing to postponenegotiations the Cabinet must not be taken as approvingany plan to move the British troops in Cairo.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidhis understanding was that the Cabinet had not reachedany decision on that point, though his own view, as recorded in the Papers before the Cabinet, remainedunaltered, namely, that no Egyptian Government could accept a Treaty which left the British troops in or near Cairo.He pointed out that Sir Percy Loraine said itwould be extremely difficult for him to return to Cairowithout being able to answer the question of whethernegotiations were to be resumed.    It was imperative,therefore, that he should be in a position to give an answer, and the best reply seemed to be that we couldnot handle the question of the Treaty in the presentyear but would take it up next year.   The question aroseas to whether the Egyptian Government should be given a hint that we were doubtful whether we should- be ableto reach agreement or not, in view of the difficultqtiestions raised in connection with the garrison andth e Sudan.THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that if Sir percy loraine said that we could not discuss the Treaty nowbut would take it up next year, that might precipitate
a certain amount of temper both in the case of King Puadand. Sidky Pasha.    If, in addition, he were to warn themthat we were going to be stiff about the troops andthe Sudan, the Egyptians would say that there was not going to be a successful negotiation, and we should beface to face with the consequences of a complete breach.They might apply for membership of the League ofNations, and he did not see how we could expectanything except a complete rejection of our attitude bythe League.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs agreed, and thought we should avoid giving the egyptians a cold douche.The question was raised, as to whether, in thecircumstances, it would not be better to advance thedate of the appointment of Sir Percy Loraine&apos;s successor,and this idea met with considerable support in theCabinet.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs pointed out that, although Sir Percy Loraine&apos;s timeexpired in August,  it would be quite possible to anticipate the appointment of his successor.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the new HighCommissioner must have time to consider these questionscarefully and to size up the situation.    It would notbe right to press him to give his advice prematurely.In the meantime, particularly in the uncertainty ofSidky Pasha&apos;s health, something might happen to put theWafd in power.   He asked if the Egyptians could applynow for membership of the League?THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs thought it might be postponed.   He was anxious to use a promise of British support for such an applicationas an argument in the negotiations.   That was one reason
for speeding matters up.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR was in favourof Sir Percy Loraine not returning to Egypt.   he understood there was a particularly good Charge&apos; d&apos;Affairesthere, and he could carry on until Sir Percy Loraine&apos;ssuccessor was appointed.   As Secretary of State for Warhis main concern was that the troops should not beremoved from Cairo.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS,after pointing out that no Cabinet decision had beenreached on that, reaffirmed his previous position onthe matter.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that his colleagues should look at an earlier Report by the Chiefs of staff committee on the question of the retention of troops in cairo.    In view of the earlier Report he had been rathersurprised at the Report now before the Cabinet.   His own view was that no communication should be made to theEgyptian Government at present.    If Sir Percy Lorainereturned to Egypt we should have to face making somecommunication on the lines suggested by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs.    It would be impossiblefor Sir Percy Loraine to return without being in aposition to make some reply.   It seemed possible,however, that Sir Percy would not return at all.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs thought that in any event he would not return before october.   He added that the present discussion did notappear to involve any immediate action on his part, buthe would consider the question with his advisers in theForeign Office....itehall Gardens, S.W.1,July 12,  1933.
I   ARTICLE 21 OF 4. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by1   (pffE UNITEDp   KINGDOM-CANADIAN the President of the Board of ^rade (C.P.-177 (S3))I   AGREEMENT(RUSSIAN on the question of Russian Timber and the UnitedTIMBER) .Kingdom-Canadian Agreement,Lcle 21 of the Anglo-Canadian Ottawa AgreementLlows :-&quot;This Agreement is made on the expresscondition that, if either Government is satisfied that any preferences herebygranted in respect of any particularclass of commodities are likely to be frustrated in whole or in part by reasonof the creation or maintenance directly or indirectly of prices for such classof commodities through State action onthe part of any foreign country, thatGovernment hereby declares that it will exercise the powers which it now hasor will hereafter take to prohibit the entry from such foreign country directly or indirectly of such commodities intoits country for such time as may benecessary to make effective and tomaintain the preferences hereby granted by it&quot;.Powers for Implementing the above are contained inSection 5 of the Ottawa Agreements Act.   The question before the Cabinet was as to whether action, and,if so, what action, should be taken in respect ofRtissian timber under Section 5 of the Ottawa Agree-ments Act.   The actual points submitted for thedecision of the Cabinet were as follows:-(l) Whether, now that the embargo has beenlifted, the Board of Trade may beaxithorised to request the Import duties advisory Committee to advise them whether the conditions exist in whichaction in regard to Russian timberunder Section 5 of the Ottawa Agree-ments Act would be necessary:(2) Whether evidence should be taken fromSoviet sources in any enquiry undertaken on this matter, and, if so, whether theSoviet representatives may be so informedif they raise the point during thenegotiations .The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairsurged that the Canadian Government as well as theCanadian lumber industry should be afforded an oppor-tunity to give evidence before any Inquiry that was(Previous Art:Reference:Cabinet 36 is as fol(33), Con-clusion 12.)F.R.set up.-6-
In the course of the discussion the importance was emphasised of taking no action which would be detrimental to the building trade or to the miningindustry in procuring pitprops.The question was raised as to what action wouldbe taken if the Import Duties Advisory Committeeadvised that action would be necessary under Section 5of the Ottawa Agreements Act,    It was suggested thatin that event the best plan would be to inform therepresentatives of the Russian Soviet of the positionand to discuss with them as to whether any means couldbe found to implement Article 21 of the Anglo-CanadianOttawa Agreement without excluding all Russian timber.In such conversations the question of an Import Quotamight perhaps arise.    In that event it would almost certainly be necessary to discuss the matter with theCanadian Government, owing to the rigid provisionsof Article 21.The President of the Board of Trade mentioned that the question of quotas was on the agenda-paper for the negotiations in regard to a Trade Agreementwith Russia that had just been reopened.The Cabinet agreed - (a) That the Board of Trade should beauthorised to request the ImportDuties Advisory Committee to advisethem whether the conditions exist in which action in regard to Russiantimber under Section 5 of the ottawa agreements Act would be necessary:(b) That the Import Duties AdvisoryCommittee should take such evidence.   as it might deem desirable, including,if necessary, evidence from Soviets ources.
ipHB ISLE opIan customsBILL.I previous Reference:I Cabinet 40I (32), Oon-I elusion 4.)5, The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Financial Secretary to the Treasury (CP,-178 (33)) ,circulated by direction of the Chancellor o^* theExchequer, covering a draft Isle of Man Customs Bill,an Annual Bill confirming the Customs Resolutions ofthe Manx Legislature and giving effect to certain modifications in Customs Law required for administra-tive and technical reasons.   As the Bill was practicallyformal and would occupy little Parliamentary time,authority was requested to introduce it and proceedwith it at once, subject to any drafting or other minor amendments that might be found necessary.The Cabinet approved the proposals set forth in CP.-178 (33) and summarised above.
INDIA.politicalSituationin.Mr Gandhi.(previous reference:Cabinet 33(33), Con-clusion 7.)ft.6.   ^he secretary of State for India wished tohave the general views of the Cabinet as a backgroundfor his correspondence with the Viceroy on the subjectof a request that Mr Gandhi was likely to make for an interview with the Viceroy,    On the release ofMr Gandhi from prison in a weakened condition after a hunger-strike, a manifesto had been issued,probably by his followers and without his knowledge,in favour of civil disobedience.    Since then opposi-tion to civil disobedience had apparently been growingin Congress circles ,   The Secretary of State had reason to believe that Mr Gandhi was likely to makea request to the Viceroy for an interview.    some three weeks ago he had written to the Viceroy on thesubject, and ten days before the Viceroy had saidthat if he received a request from Mr Gandhi merely for a talk without any conditions he would be preparedto agree.   The Secretary of State had telegraphedhis agreement.   Within the last three days, however,the Viceroy had changed his view and said that hewould not see Mr Gandhi unless civil disobediencewas called off.   The Secretary of State inclined tothe view that that was going too far.    If Mr Gandhiasked the Viceroy to see him and met with a directnegative, he thought this would produce a badreaction among Indians here and also in the other twopolitical Parties that were at present co-operatingwell with the Government in the Joint Select Committee.jThe Secretary of State?s own view was that, if he received this request, the Viceroy should ask forinformation as to the object of the interview.He might make clear that if Mr Gandhi wished eitherto enter into negotiations or to discuss administra-tive questions the interview could not be granted.
If, on the other hand, he wished to discuss Constitu-tional questions, the request might be considered.What the Secretary of State wished to avoid was a purely negative attitude on the part of the Viceroy,or anything which would prevent Mr Gandhi from with-drawing from a position which might have become impossible for him.In the course of the discussion some doubts were expressed as to whether the Viceroy, if he gave an interview, could avoid being drawn into negotiations,which everyone agreed was undesirable.    It wassuggested also that public opinion in this countryinclined to the view that Mr Gandhi.had been ratherfortunate in securing release from prison, and would consider that to allow him the advantage of conversa-tions with the Viceroy would be going too far.On the whole, however, the Cabinet supported theview of the Secretary of State for India that it wouldbe advisable for him to make representations to theViceroy in favour of his not opposing a flat negativeto a request from Mr Gandhi for an interview, and ofaccompanying this by a suggestion that the viceroy should ascertain the purpose of Mr Gandhi&apos;s proposed visit, together with an intimation that he could not enter into negotiations or discuss any administrativequestion, though not unwilling to discuss constitutional questions.    The Cabinet felt, however, that it wouldbe inadvisable to press the Viceroy unduly if he feltstrong objection to the interview.The Secretary of State for India thanked his  col-leagues for their expression of views, and said thatin forwarding the general views of the Cabinet hewould be very careful to avoid any instruction to theViceroy ,
productionof oil promgoal.Hydrogenation.ProposedAgreementwith imperial chemical Indus-tries .(previous references:Cabinet 84(31), Con-clusion 12,)and Cabinet93 (31), Con-elusion 2,)7.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer reminded the Cabinet that conversations had been taking place with Imperial Chemical Industries at intervals forsome time, with a view to their proceeding with alarge-scale experiment for the hydrogenation of coal.These negotiations had now reached a satisfactoryresult.   The Company were prepared to proceed withthe erection of a plant capable of producing 100,000tons per annum of petrol by the hydrogenation ofBritish coal or tar, on certain conditions,   Thescheme would involve a capital cost of  4,000,000.Part of the plant, however, was already in existence,and the new plant required would involve an estimated expenditure of slightly less than  2,500,000.   TheCompany-was willing to undertake this enterprisewithout any cash guarantee, on conditions which wouldinvolve a loss equal to  1,000,000, not of existing,but of anticipated increase in revenue.   The conditioninvolved a guarantee by the Government of a Preferencein respect of light hydrocarbon oils of 4d. a gallonfor a period of ten years from April 1, 1934.    Ifthe Customs Duty for any financial year after March31st, 1935, exceeded 4d. a gallon, and no Excise Dutywas imposed for that year, or if for any year theCustoms Duty exceeded any Excise Duty by more than4d. a gallon, then in respect of each such year theperiod of guarantee would be reduced by three monthsf or each Id. of excess .   mhe Chancellor of theExchequer added that legislation would be requiredto implement the proposed Agreement.   This legislation would have to be drafted at an early date and shown to Imperial Chemical Industries, but need not beintroduced until the autumn.    If the Cabinet approved the proposal he intended to answer a Question on thesubject in the House of Commons in the following week.-11-
In reply to a question lie made clear that this wasnot an Agreement exclusively to the benefit ofImperial Chemical Industries, but would apply to allhome-produced light hydrocarbon oil,^he Cabinet agreed . (a) To approve the arrangement withImperial Chemical Industries as described by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer and set forth above:(b) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should proceed with the action -required to carry out the arrangement,
LEAGUE OPNATIONSASS FT/PLY.British Re-presentationat.(previous reference:Cabinet 42(33), Con-clusion 1.)8. ^he Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that Viscount Cecil of Chelwoodhad an engagement in Canada and had not been able toaccept his invitation to act as one of the delegates of the United Kingdom at the forthcoming meeting ofthe Assembly of the League of Nations.In these circumstances the cabinet approved the suggestion of theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs that the Secretary of theDepartment of Overseas Trade shouldbe included in the United kingdom delegation, his exact status being left &quot;&quot;to the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs in consultationwith the Prime Minister.
NEXT MEETING 9.     The Cabinet, agreed  OF CABINET.That their next Meeting should beheld on WEDNESDAY, JULY 19, 1933,at 11 a.m., at 10 Downing Street!.  .  .2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1July 12, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
