<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/76/0 images: 354-395</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fc! 3 t)pnOUMSNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT&apos;) .C R E T. COPY NO.&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; CABINET    48 (gg) .Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at 10Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,26th July, 1953, at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1. MONETARY AND ECONOMIC CONFERENCE.     - (if required).(Reference Cabinet 47 (33), Conclusion l).2* REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS:    THE french attitude.(Reference Cabinet 45 (33), Conclusion 2).Despatch from His Majesty&apos;s Charge&apos; d&apos;Affaires inParis, with Minute by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office^(CP. 185(33)    -   already circulated) .3.  INDICATIONS OF GERMANY&apos;S DISREGARD OF PART V OFTHE VERSAILLES TREATY.(Reference Cabinet 38 (33), Conclusion 5).Note by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, covering Memorandum prepared in theForeign Office.(CP. 184(53)    -   already circulated).4* RESPONSIBILITY FOR PERSIAN GULF AFFAIRS.(Reference Cabinet 42 (33), Conclusion 4),Memorandum by the Secretary of State for theColonies.(CP. .154(53)    -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.(CP. 156(53)    -   already circulated) .Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.(CP. 165(33)    -   already circulated).5. ESTABLISHMENT OF NEW AIR BASE IN CENTRAL IRAQ.  (If ready).(Reference Cabinet 1 (33) , Conclusion 4).Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committeeof the Committee of Imperial Defence.(CP. 196 (33) -   to be circulated).
Note by the Secretary of State for Air,covering a Memorandum &quot;by the Board ofImperial Airways, Limited.(CP. 110(33)    -   already circulated).7.  COMMERCIAL NEGOTIATIONS WITH FOREIGN COUNTRIES.(Reference Cabinet 27 (33), Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.(CP. 187 (33)    -   already circulated).8.  TRADE NEGOTIATIONS WITH FINLAND.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.(CP. 188(33)    -   already circulated).9. TRADE NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN INDIA AND JAPAN.(Reference Cabinet 22 (33), Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.(CP. 192(33)    -   circulated herewith).10. UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 26 (33), Conclusion l).Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP. 190(33)    -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Minister of Health.(CP. 195(33)    -   circulated herewith).11.  LAND SETTLEMENT (SCOTLAND).(Reference Cabinet 36 (33), Conclusion 9 (e)).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland,covering draft Bill.(CP. 181(33)    -   circulated herewith).Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(CP. 191(33)    -   circulated herewith).12.  PENALTIES FOR ILLEGAL TRAWLING.(Reference Cabinet 18 (33), Conclusion 7).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland.(CP. 183(33) &apos; -   already circulated),13. EXPIRING LAWS CONTINUANCE BILL.(Reference Cabinet 60 (32), Conclusion 9).Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury, covering Draft Bill, circulated by direction of the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(CP. 193(33)    -   already circulated).
14.FUTURE MEETINGS OF THE CABINET.(To be raised by the Prime Minister),TO TAKE NOTE OF:-15.  SITUATION IN MALTA.(Reference Cabinet 44 (33), Conclusion 3).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forthe Colonies.(CP. 194(33)    -    to be circulated).16. TRAINING AND OCCUPATION FOR THE UNEMPLOYEDNEXT WINTER.(Reference Cabinet 42 (33), Conclusion 12).Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP. 189(33)    -    circulated herewith) .(Signed) M.P.A., HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.24th July, 1933.
/ffrrK DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT)gjU? RET. COPY NO.cabinet   48 (35).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,26th July, 1935, at 11.0 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. J.Prime Minister.The Right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt..D.S.O,,M.P., Secretary of State for home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K.G.,M.V.O., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G.B.E.. .D.S.Q. ,D.S.C. ,M.P. ,Minister of Health.Major The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C.,M.P. ,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries,Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,(In the Chair).The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt. ,G.B.BC.M.G..M.P., Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.C.M.G.,M,P., Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Lord Irwin, K.G.,G.C.S.I. ,G.C.I.E., President of theBoard Of Education.The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,C.B.E.,M.P., Minister ofLabour.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., first commissioner of Works.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:-Mr, R.A. Eden, M.C.,M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary,Foreign Office. (For Conclusions 1 to 11)Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B. ,G.C.M.G. ,.......... Secretary.
1. The Prime Minister said that he had nothing toreport beyond the facts already known, namely, thatthe Monetary and Economic Conference was going intorecess on the morrow:    the Bureau was being keptalive:    and arrangements were being made for the continuation of the work of Committees, probablyabout the middle of September,He had been rather concerned as to what should bedone about the Geological Museum,    Sir Maurice Hankeyhad made enquiries from Sir F,E,Smith, and reportedthat the Museum could be kept in its present stateand held available for further meetings of the Confer-ence if the public interest required.   He thought,therefore, that it should be kept for the present available for the use of the Conference.The First Commissioner of Works said he had enquiredas to the heating arrangements, and they were adequate.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Geological Museum should,for the present, be kept availablefor the use of the Monetary andEconomic Conference:(b) That the question should be reopenedin September.
rT*HE MONETARY . 2, The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs0D ECONOMICCONFERENCE. asked to place on record his indebtedness to the(The Commonwealth   Chancellor of the Exchequer for the successfulDelegations .- efforts he had made to reach agreement with theproposed De-claration by.       Dominions as to a Declaration of Policy.   this declaration should have a good psychological effect.
MOTION AKD 3.The Cabinet had before them a Despatch fromRATION OP0ENTS. His Majesty*s Charge&quot; d&apos;Affaires in Paris to theg prench Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, together withtitude,a Minute thereon by the Parliamentary Under-Secretaryevio-us of State for Foreign Affairs (C.P.-185 (33)), on theeference:cabinet 45 subject of the French attitude on Disarmament.    In hisS3), Con-conclusion 2.J Minute the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of Statef-K- pointed out the discouraging nature of the french proposals, which made it clear that no Franco-Germansettlement could be reached upon them, and submitted that if the British Government had a duty in promoting a Franco-German settlement the French offer to discussthe matter further, with a view to finding an accept-able ground for compromise, ought not to be refused,provided Mr Henderson was not opposed to such conversa-tions ,The Lord President of the Council made a generalreport on a meeting of the Ministerial Committee whichhad taken place at the House of Commons on the previous evening, and which had been joined at a later stage bythe Prime Minister,   ^he question under consideration had been as to whether Mr Rendersonfs conversations should be followed by conversations with France.He recalled a recent decision by the ministerial committee (C.P.-167 (33), Appendix), to the effectthat piecemeal decisions should not be taken on thedetails of Disarmament until Mr Henderson&apos;s conversa-tions had shown whether there was any chance of areconciliation between France and Germany.   Thequestions before the Ministerial Committee had been(l) whether to meet the French at all, and (2) whatwas to be said to them?   Most of those present had felt apprehensions lest we should be driven intobargaining and making concessions on points of detail
when the French might be finding it impossible tomake sufficient concessions to reach agreement owingto their uncertainty as to the position in Germany.The general sentiment had been that we ought first to find out whether, in view of the course of events in Germany, the French wanted a Convention, and, if so   how much they were prepared to give to obtain it.Italians .   As to the proper method of approach, ithad been felt that it would be a mistake for us toput pressure on the French to fall into a position where either they felt their security in danger or,alternatively, they might try to drive a bargain with us.   mhe Ministerial Committee had also accepted theview that, whatever might be the prospects of aConvention, we must not be drawn into further commit-ments.    On the whole, therefore, it had been thoughtbetter not to talk to the French immediately, moreespecially as it was known that some of the french ministers and Officials concerned were going on holiday.   The Committee had discussed whether the conversations should be at Paris or Geneva, and theParliamentary Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs had preferred Paris ,   ^he Committee thought the date should be somewhere about September 18th.As mentioned in CP,-185 (33), the French had presettedproposals which were not likely to provide a basis fora Convention acceptable to Germany.    It had been thought, therefore, that we should try and get tothe bottom of what the French thought about thesequestions .The Secretary of State for the Colonies added that by Be^&amp;4sr%4*ig in September we should avoid having togive a written answer to the French Memorandum,-4-
The Chancellor of the Exchequer asked what wasthe purpose of the French in asking to have conversa-tions with us?The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs thought this was due to the difficultythe French had in making up their minds what to do inthe present situation of Germany.   French ministers were probably divided on the subject.    They wanted toput the situation to us and get our reaction.   Theywould probably repeat to us the offers they had madeto Mr Henderson, but were likely to intimate thatthey were not necessarily their last word.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that theform of the conversations appeared likely to be that france would have made the proposals in their Memo-rand urn:   we should reply that we thought theseunlikely to be acceptable to Germany as the basis ofa Convention:    they would then ask us how much furtherthey ought to go:    we might then be driven into makingsuggestions as to whether they should do more, and,if so, what they could do.   Presumably we should nextbe expected to go to the Germans with their proposals.He did not object particularly to such a procedure,because he thought a Disarmament Convention would bethe best outcome of the conversations.   He did feel,however, that France ought not to be pushed by us into;a position of weakness, more particularly as he feltmisgivings as to the attitude of Germany.    It was evident that the French were unwilling to proceedwith disarmament without some period of trial.     Thatappeared not unreasonable.    It had to be recognisedthat the proposal under consideration involved our being put in the position of &quot;honest broker&quot;.-5-
The Prime Minister said it was important for usto avoid being put into a position of taking a moralresponsibility for a situation into which the french had been put through our action, and into whichthey otherwise would not have allowed themselves tobe put.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said the ,Ministerial Committee had been rather opposed to our\being put into the position of &quot;honest broker&quot;.The President of the Board of Education askedwhether the matter was not affected by the questionof German and Austrian aviation, which was also onthe Agenda?The Prime Minister said that that question wouldbe discussed anOn.    Everyone on the previous eveninghad felt that we must be very careful about our conversations with France, though.they were bound tobe held.    Also it must be, made clear that we could undertake no new commitments.    It- had, also been agreedthat the settlement of details was not going.to help.We might, however say to them &quot;Do, you seriouslythinks in present conditions, that it is possible toget a Convention?&quot;    If they said &quot;No&quot; we should try and get at wrhat was in their minds , but without committing ourselves.   The conversations would not open until the.latter half.of September.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairsunderstood that Mr Henderson would be informed of whatwas proposed.The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State saidthat he proposed to see Mr Henderson here in London.The Secretary of State for Air pointed out thatthe Americans had received a similar invitation fromthe French.
The Prime Minister asked whether it was consideredwise to have a joint meeting without any separatemeeting with the French?The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State said the French would probably ask the Americans to be present if Mr Norman Davis was back.The Prime Minister thought that that requiredcons consideration,The Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState pointedout that the Americans toput pressvire on the French than we were.    If Mr Norman....Davis was present we could sit back during this partof the conversations,(mhe Prime Minister instructed theSecretary to make a full minute ofthis discussion for the benefit ofthe Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs and the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State.   The gist of theCabinet*s views was summed up inthe remarks by the Prime Ministersummarised on page 6 and underlined.)
AgSTRO-german relations.F.R4,  The Parliamentary Under Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs informed the Cabinet that since junly German propaganda had been broadcast fromMunich into Austria.      The Austrian Government wasprofoundly distrubed, the more so since the MunichStation was under Government control.      The AustrianMinister had called on the Permanent Under Secretaryof State and himself on July 84th and spokenseriously in regard to the persistent attemptsof Germany to undermine Austrian independence.These attempts had taken three forms:extensive terrorism, dropping seditious leafletsfrom German aeroplanes over Austrian territory,and persistent subversive broadcasting incitingthe Austrian people to resist the present government.      Austrian representations to Berlinhad had no effect.      The Austrian Government weregrateful for the attitude of our Press, but asked us to support them openly and officially.Similar official requests had been made the same day to the French and Italian Governments.The Foreign Office had felt that v, hey must takea grave view of this matter, more especially atthe present time immediately after the signature of the Four Power Pact and in view of Germany&apos;sobligation under Article 80 of the Treaty ofVersailles (recognition of the independence ofAustria).     Both these matters could be brought up under Article XI, Paragraph 2, of the covenant of the League of Nations.      It had been thoughtbetter, however, in the first instance at anyrate, to deal with the matter inthe spirit ofthe Four Power Pact by consultation between the signatory Powers.       After obtaining the Prime-8-
Minister&apos;s authority, therefore, the Foreign office had made representations on the previous day(July 25th) at Paris and Rome with a view tojoint action in Berlin.      No reply had yet beenreceived.The Cabinet then discussed the questionof whether the House of Commons should beinformed of this action.      The advantage of thiscourse would be to anticipate a possiblealarmist Press reaction in Paris and Rome.Such a statement might also prompt the Italiansto take action in the matter.      On the other hand,if the French and Italians refused to co-operate,a public statement might place us in a difficult position and we should be pressed tosay whether we intended to act alone.      Further,the suggestion was made that publication beforeanything had been said to Germany might make itdifficult for the German Government to give afavourable reply.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the action already taken by the Foreign Office inapproaching the French candItalian Governments.(b) That an answer from Paris and rome should be expedited.(e) That the question of whethera statement should be made inParliament should be leftto the Foreign Office who sliouldtake the Prime Minister&apos;instructions as soon as theyheard from Paris and Rome.(d) That the question of whether in the event of a negativeanswer from Paris and Rome, weshould or should not take inde-pendent action could not besettled until the replies had been  received.
THE OBLIGATIONSOP GERMANYUNDER PAR^ VOP THE TREATYOP VERSAILLES .(previous reference:Cabinet 38(S3), Con-elusion 5.)I German request to be allowedto purchaseAircraft forPolicePurposes .4-5.     The Cabinet had before them the following documents relating to re-armament by Germany:-A Note by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (CP.-184 (33))entitled &quot;Indications of Germany&apos;sDisregard of Part V of the Treatyof Versailles&quot;, covering a Memo-randuro   drawn up by the&quot;ForeignOffice after consultation with theWar Office, the A,dmiralty and theAir Ministry  .   After rehearsing theevidence, public and secret, ofGermany&apos;s re-armament measures, theForeign Office Memorandum suggestedthat the British, French and italian governments should make joint repre-sentations to the German&apos;Government,having as their first pivotal point .the published and recognised declara-tions of German officials on thesubject of re-armament.   The Secretaryof State himself was disposed to sound the Italians first of all, as theycould probably put some restraint on berlin and very likely get areassuring declaration made fromthat quarter, although it by nomeans followed that such a reassur-ance ought to be believed:A Memorandum by the Permanent Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office(CP.-198 (33)), describing a new development in Germany since C.P.-184(33) was written.    On July 15th theGerman Air Minister had made a request that, as the British aircraft industry had been allowed to sell five policeaircraft to Austria, Germany shouldbe allowed to purchase 25 to 50similar aircraft for police purposes in Germany, accompanied by an intima-tion that if it was refused the aircraft in question would be bought in France.The statement that British aircraft hadbeen sold to Austria for police purposeswas shown to be untrue.    His Majesty&apos;charge&apos; dTAffaires at Berlin had so informed the German Government, andhad added that there could be   noquestion of the sale of aircraft byBritish firms to the German Governmentfor purposes forbidden by the Paris AirAsreement.   The Memorandum furtherstated that the Belgian, French andItalian Governments had been informed of the German request and of the action that had so far been taken, and hadbeen asked themselves to act similarlyif they were approached.
In view of the events which had taken place       ^since C.P.184 (33) was written (July 14th), theSecretary of State&apos;s proposal to sound the Italiansfirst as to German rearmament was felt no longer to he applicable.      &quot;tfe had already approached theItalians on the matter of German interference withAustria (see previous Conclusion);    and we were onthe point of making somewhat delicate representationsat Rome on the subject of Italian propaganda in Malta.On the whole, therefore, the Cabinet felt it would be advisable not to seek the good offices of Italy inthe first instance.The Secretary of State for Air pointed outthat the question of German rearmament raised inO.P. 184 (33) was closely connected with the Germanrequest to purchase British aircraft for policepurposes dealt with in CP.  198 (33).      The aeroplaneswhich Germany wished to purchase were not militaryaeroplanes and our manufacturers were notifying theAir Ministry that if we refused the orders othercountries vrould accept them.      In this matter, there-fore, a communication had already been made to theBelgian, French and Italian Governments who had beeninformed of our attitude in refusing these orders on the ground that the aeroplanes were required forpurposes forbidden by the Paris Air Agreement and hadbeen asked to act similarly if they were approached.&quot;While approving the action taken by theForeign Office in the matter of air craft for policepurposes as reported in CP.  198 (33), the cabinet agreed  (a)     That on the question of German rearmamentraised in CP.  184 (33) the Foreign office should instruct His Majesty&apos;s ambassador in Berlin to express the concern of HisMajesty&apos;s Government at the indications ofGerman rearmament including, moreparticularly, the question of policeaeroplanes (on the lines suggested onpage 4, section (iii) of CP.  184 (33) )and should express their anxiety on thegeneral question.
That while the above action should, betaken independently, the ForeignOffice should notify the French andItalian Governments.
ERSIAW GULPFutureHespons ibilityfor.(previous reference:Cabinet 44(33), Oon-clusion 7.)6.   The Cabinet had before them once more thefollowing documents&apos; on the subject of Responsibilityfor Persian Gulf Affairs, which were briefly summarised at the head of Conclusion 4 of Cabinet 42 (33):-A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Colonies (CP.-154(33)):A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (CP.-156(33)):A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for India (CP.-165 (33)).The Lord President of the Council who hadbeen invited by the Cabinet to advise them on thisquestion informed his colleagues that after careful consideration he had reached the opinionthat responsibility for Persian Gulf affairs should be transferred from the Colonial Officeto the India Office.      The main objection urgedagainst this course was lest the Indian Reform scheme should eventually weaken our control. &apos;   this appeared to him, however, to be very remote,and agaiast that he had weighed the fact tfratthe India Office had greater experience in the regions affected.      His recommendation to theCabinet, therefore, was that the India office should become the Department responsible forPersian Gulf Affairs.The Cabinet approved the Lord Presidentsproposal that the India Office should undertake the responsibility for persian gulf Affairs in place of the ColonialOffice.
CENTRAL IRAQ,.Establishmentof a new AirBase in.(previous reference:Cabinet 1(S3), Con-clusion 4.)7.    The Cabinet had before them a Report by theChiefs of Staff Sub-Committee of the Committee ofImperial Defence (C.P.-196 (33)), circulated fortheir consideration by direction of the Prime Minister,on the subject of the establishment of a new Air base in Central Iraq in lieu of Hinaidi, from which, underthe terms of the Anglo-Iraq treaty, 1930, the BritishGovernment was obliged to withdraw its forces within five years of the date of the Treaty.   A site forthis purpose had now been provided by the Iraq Govern-ment at Dhibban.   After full consideration of the strategic situation of Dhibban and of the correspond-ence which had. passed between the Secretary of Statefor Air and the Chancellor of the Exchequer (attached as Appendices to the Report) the Chiefs of StaffSub-Committee reached the following conclusions:-(i) We are of the opinion that in itself thetransfer of the Royal Air Force base fromHinaidi to Dhibban, some 50 miles west ofBaghdad, involves no fundamental changein the existing strategical situation;the only difference arising being that theline of communication from the nearestport, e.g.,Basra, is increased by some50 miles,(ii) The Chief of the Air Staff is satisfiedthat communication with the proposed newbase at Dhibban can be adequately main-tained by means of the existing road, andthat, however desirable the advent of a railway may be, on general strategicgrounds, it is not essential from thepoint of view of the maintenance of normalefficient communication with Dhibban.This view we are prepared to accept.(iii) On the wider strategic aspect, however,the Chief of the Imperial General Staffdesires that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentshould be made aware of the opinion of theGeneral Staff, before finally approvingthis project, that the retention of an air base in Central Iraq constitutes^apermanent, serious and definite commitmentagainst our very limited resources.-14-
The Secretary of State for Air informed the Cabinetthat this question arose out of a correspondence betweenthe Chancellor of the Exchequer and himself, as a resulti .of which the former had asked that the Chiefs of staff committee might be consulted   on the strategical positionof the proposed new Air Base at Dhibban.    He emphasised the important of an early decision.     Unless orders weregiven at an early date for material for the buildingsrequired at the new Air Base we should not be in aposition to avacuate. Hinaidi by the date laid down inthe Treaty.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that this wasa very big question and he was not re*assured by theReport of the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee, moreparticularly in view of the opinion of the Chief of theImperial General Staff, summarised in Conclusion (iii)above.&apos;    Once the Air Force was removed from the immediatevicinity of Baghdad we should not have the same guarantee of tranquility and order.     Recent telegrams indicated thegrowth of a feeling in Baghdad hostile to this country.It appeared to him that to locate the Air Base in thedesert a long way from our sea communications violatedthe strategical principle that a Base ought to be secure-.We have no land forces in Iraq to secure the new Base.The alternative to Dhibban appeared to be a Base nearBasra, and the question whether a Base in this regionwouid be safer than at Dhibban was a subject on which hewould like a further Report by the Chiefs of Staff.He asked if it would not be possible to obtain an extensionof the term,provided by the Treaty for the evacuation ofHinaidi, in order that this important point might be investigated at leisure.     His proposal, therefore, was-15-
that no decision should he taken to-day, hut that theCommittee of Imperial Defence should he invited to Reporton the question of an alternative Base to Dhibban.That Report should not he biassed by the fact that Iraq was an Air Force command.The Secretary of State for Air said that all thesequestions had been raised and settled years ago.     TheChief of the Air Staff would prefer to evacuate in thelast resort to the West across the desert rather than toBasra.     The communications across the desert were tending to improve, partly owing to the construction of the oilpipe-line.     He was advised that Dhibban was actuallysafer than Hinaidi.    Sir Francis Humphrys had expressedthe following viewifc-&quot;I wish to emphasise as strongly as I am ablethat the success or failure of the new order ofthings, after Iraq has been admitted to theLeague, will largely depend on the moral influence which the Royal Air Force will continue to exerton a people naturally lawless and averse to thepayment of taxes.     The complete withdrawal of theRoyal Air Force to Shaibah and their refusal totake any hand whatever in the maintenance of lawand order would, in my opinion, inevitably plungethe country into chaos before many years had passed.&quot;(Reference G.I.D. Paper No, 1018-B, Appendix A.September, 1930).He would greatly regret any delay in reaching a decision.Replying to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,he said that the Air Staff would prefer evacuation alonga road rather than along a railway.The Secretary of State for India understood theChancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s anxiety in this matter.The Iraqis had been behaving badly and that naturallycaused nervousness as to any commitment in Iraq.     This,however, was no new commitment.     In the Treaty a Base ofthis kind had always been contemplated.     It had been-16-
assumed that we should withdraw from Hinaidi hut havea Base not far from Baghdad and the negotiations had turned largely on that point.     The Iraqis had wantedus to clear out, hut from the point of view of imperial communications we required an Air Base somewhere nearBaghdad, so this had been included in a Treaty with iraq.     To move to Shaibshnear Basra would mean thatwe could not maintain.our obligations to Iraq, particular-ly in the North of that country,     Basra would tendmore and more to become merely a Naval Base.     he doubted whether a further enquiry was worth while ashe felt sure that the conclusion must be the same as before.The Secretary of State for &quot;War said that thedifficulty was that the experts took a different view.He, therefore, supported the plan of referring thequestion to the Committee of Imperial Defence.     He didnot pretend to be competent to say whether Dhibbanwas the best site but he was dubious about thepossibility of evacuating six hundred miles to the West.The Army would not be able to help the Air Force insuch an operation, and did not relish the idea of sixhundred miles of desert.The Secretary of State for the Colonies urged thatif the question was to go to the Committee of ImperialDefence it should meet before Sir Francis Humphrys had left for Iraq-The Secretary of State for Air drew attention to theview of the Chief of the Air Staff, as set forth inParagraph 12 of CCS.312 (CP. 196(33)), that theconstruction of the pipe-line across the Syrian Desertshowed that        re-re-inforcement   along the route from-17-
Trans-Jordan or the withdrawal of the Forces fromDhibban westwards prevented no insuperable difficulty.The Cabinet agreed:-(a) That the. Committee of Imperial defence should meet in the Prime Minister&apos;room in the House of Commons on Friday,July 28th, at 4.0 p.m. (or immediatelyafter the Cabinet meeting, fixed for.0 p.m.), to consider the site of thefuture Air Base in Iraq including therival claims of Dhibban and Shaibah;(b) That Sir Francis Humphrys should beinvited to attend the meeting;(c) That the Chiefs of Staff of the three defence Services and Sir Francis Humpfcrysshould be informed by the Secretary to theCommittee of Imperial Defence of the natureof the issues on which their advice wawrequired.
/iflTlL air COM-UlCATIOMS OP;HE EMPIRE.(previous reference:Cabinet 11(29), Con-elusion 12.)8,   The Cabinet had before them a Note by theSecretary of State for Air (C.P.-110 (33)), circulated in April last, covering a Memorandum prepared by theBoard of Imperial Airways, Limited, entitled &quot;TheFuture of Civil Air Communications of the Empire&quot;.This Memorandum, written after a recent tour of inspection by Sir Eric Oeddes, the Chairman of theCompany, stated that Sir Eric had been greatly impressed (a) with the keen interest taken by theDominion and Colonial Administrations in the further development of our system of Imperial Air Communica-tions:    (b) with the need for ensuring that that ,development shall, if possible, proceed by means ofa scheme of close co-operation and mutual partnership between the United Kingdom and the Dominions and colonies&apos;,    and (c) with the extreme importance of planning for the future well in advance of the expiry of the existing agreement with Imperial Airways .The Memorandum also summarised the progress achieved by Imperial Airways to date.   The Secretary of Stateagreed broadly with the above points, and believedthat civil air transport, properly handled, wasdestined to be a factor of steadily increasing importance to the British Commonwealth of Nations,not merely commercially but also politically.The Secretary of State for Air said his object in asking for this subject to be placed upon theAgenda Paper of the Cabinet was in order to invitehis colleagues to read the Report during the vacation.On their return he would ask for the appointment ofa small Cabinet Committee to consider the question.He preferred this course to the appointment of a departmental Committee, as the latter plan would only involve hearing the evidence of Sir Eric Geddes-19-
twice.    Imperial Airways had a fine record of achieve-ment and had a right, in his view, to some securityof tenure.   He was not asking for any action until after the Cabinet&apos;s vacation, except that his colleagueshould read the Memorandum,The Cabinet took note of the Secretaryof State for Air&apos;s observations.
COMMERCIALgjOTlATlONSXTH FOREIGN0UNTRIES .(previous reference:Cabinet 27(33), Con-elusion 4.)791-9.  The Cabinet had before them a Note by thePresident of the Board, of Trade (CP,-187 (33)) onthe subject of the programme of future commercial negotiations with foreign countries.    In order thatthe lengthy work of preparation might be put in handforthwith the President asked approval to the followingsuggested programme:-(i) Negotiations to be opened up with, u Esthonia and Latvia in the autumn,and also with Lithuania, subject,&apos;3C5^/Y-       in the case of the last, to the\&apos;]i?b&apos;lcj.       special considerations referred toin the Memorandum attached to thePresident&apos;s Note.(ii) Negotiations to be opened with Polandy, ;s somewhat later in the year, on com-pietion of the preparations whichare now being made.(iii) Preparations for negotiations with spain and Uruguay to be put in handon the understanding that it will notbe possible to begin actual negotiationswith these countries for some months .Iiv) Preparations to be undertaken for negotiations with Egypt in the eventof it being found desirable that such negotiations should be opened.(v) The possibility of negotiations withHolland to be borne in mind, in viewof the present discussions in regardto Japanese competition.(vi) Negotiations with Prance and Germanyto be ruled out, unless unforeseencircumstances arise.The Secretary of State for the Colonies reportedthat there existed a difficulty with Holland which prevented us from giving Preference in West Africa.There was also a rather difficult Treaty affectingthe position in Singapore and Malaya,   Our relationswith Holland were good, and he was anxious, to removethese difficulties.    In the circumstances he wouldlike to ask the President of the Board of Trade toitaeJL^eynegotiations with Holland^xn his list.The Secretary of State for India said he wouldalso be glad if Holland were included in the list,-21-
3mfor somewhat similar reasons.The Prime Minister drew attention to the factthat there would be no negotiations with Prance andGermany for at least six months, unless unforeseencircumstances arose.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the proposals of thePresident of the Board of trade as set forth in C.P.-187 (33) and summarised above:    and(b) That the Secretary of State for theColonies and the Secretary of Statefor India should make representations Kto the President of the Board of Tradewith a view to the inclusion of Hollandin the list.Absent in attendance on the King.
TRADE NEG-OTIA-yI0NS WITHFINLAND .(previous reference:Cabinet 27(53), Con-conclusion 4..)10.The Cabinet had before them a Note by the Presidentof the Board of Trade (C.P.-188 (33)) covering aMemorandum prepared in his Department on the subjectof Trade Negotiations with Finland.   The Presidentasked authority to conclude an Agreement on the lines set out in the Memorandum, subject to a satisfactory settlement of outstanding points, none of which was of major importance.. The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries saidthat a guarantee that the Finnish quota of buttershould not be reduced below a particular quantitymade a difficulty for him.   He had no objection to aguarantee expressed in percentages, but quantitieswere awkward.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the proposals of thePresident of the Board of trade for an Agreement with Finland asset forth in CP.-188 (33):(b) ^hat the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries should make repre-sentations direct to the Presidentof the Board of Trade on the pointreferred to above.
PRADE NEGOTIA-between india and japan.japanes eCommercialCompet it ion.(previous reference:Cabinet m\q(33); Con-clusion I-&amp;.)11.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for India (CP.-192 (33)) onthe question of Trade Negotiations between India and japan, setting forth the course of events following upon the denunciation by His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin April last of the Trade Convention with japan in order that India might be free to take actionagainst Japanese imports.   The Memorandum furtherstated that in the course of conversations at theForeign Office the Japanese Ambassador had requested that any agreement arrived at as the result of Indo-Japanese governmental negotiations should not onlybe negotiated but also signed in India;   but theSecretary of State asked the Cabinet to agree thatany such agreement should be signed in London.   TheJapanese had also asked for an assurance that any agreement come to in India should be final and notbe liable to alteration by authority outside India.The Secretary of State asked for the approval of hiscolleagues to the following reply:-&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government are, underthe Fiscal Autonomy Convention, no longer in a position to dictate the fiscal policyof India.   It is nevertheless the case that they are still, and will continue tobe, responsible for the international relations of India.   While, therefore, it need not be anticipated that the detailsof any trade agreement which, as the resultof the impending discussions, may be come to between the Government of Japan and theGovernment of India will be liable toalteration in London, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment cannot divest themselves ofthe responsibility of considering whetherthe agreement as a whole will affect theinternational relations of India&quot;.The Secretary of State for India made a statement to the Cabinet developing what was set forth in his memorandum.    In the course of this he paid a tribute to Lord Derby for his good offices with the LancashireManufacturers, which had been most helpful in obtainingtheir consent to send representatives to India to-24-
confer with Japanese manufacturers.   He was preparedthat the negotiations should begin in India inSeptember, but so far had been unable to obtain from the Japanese particulars as to the basis of negotiation they desired.   He invited the parliamentary under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to make further representations to the Japanese as to what&apos;in their view should be the basis of negotiation.He then invited the Cabinet to agree that the discus-sion should take place in India, but that the actualAgreement should, be signed in London.This point led to some discussion.    It was pointedout that signature in London would tend to weaken the argument we had used with Japan that this was amatter in which we were unable to exercise any control.The Secretary of State for India pointed out,however, the objection of conveying the impression that some change had taken place in the international status of India and that the responsibility for Indianexternal relations, which rests on His majesty&apos;s government, had been weakened.    He thought there shouSbe no difficulty in explaining to the Japanese thatsignature in India would be a departure from precedent.On the subject of the proposed formula quoted above,attention was drawn to the first sentence, which reads as follows:-&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government are, under the fiscal Autonomy Convention, no longer in a position to dictate the fiscal policy of India&quot;.The Secretary of State for India was asked toconsider whether this was strictly correct, and whetherit would not be advisable to modify that sentence.The Cabinet agreed  
(a) To invite the attention of theParliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs to theSecretary of State for India&apos;invitation to him to approach theJapanese Government once more witha view to ascertaining what basisthey proposed for the forthcoming negotiations in India, in order thatthe date might be fixed as soon asposs ible:(b) To approve the proposal of theSecretary of State for India thatthe negotiation should take placein India but that the signature ofany Agreement which might be reachedshould take place in London:(c) To approve the formula quoted onthe first page of this Conclusionfor presentation to the Japanese-...Ambassador, subject to reconsideration of the terms of the first sentence by.,the Secretary of State for India.(The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs withdrew at this point.)
UNEMPLOYMENTINSURANCE.(previous reference:Cabinet 26(33), Con-clusion 1.)12.    The Cabinet had before them the Report of aCabinet Committee (C .P.-190 (33)) which had been setup at the Meeting mentioned in the margin to re-examinethe scheme submitted to the Cabinet in the third report of the Cabinet Committee on UnemploymentInsurance (CP.-89 (33))  in the light of the cabinet discussion.   As the result of their deliberationsthe Cabinet Committee had reached agreement upon ascheme (which the Secretary of State for Scotland had agreed should also apply to Scotland) the principal features of which were attached as an Appendix to theReport.   The recommendations made to the Cabinet bythe Committee were as follows:-(l) That approval in principle should be givento the Unemployment Assistance Scheme, theprincipal features of which are summarised in the Appendix to the Report.(2) That the Minister of Labour should beauthorised to arrange for the preparationof an Unemployment Bill based on the approvedscheme, but also covering the subject ofunemployment insurance^ for considerate on by the Home Affairs Committee and theCabinet, towards the end of the ParliamentaryRecess .(3) That on the assumption that it will not bepossible to introduce the Bill before thecommencement of the new Parliamentary session in the Autumn, every effort should be madeto secure that as much progress as possiblewill be made with the Bill before the christmas Recess, 1933, and that, in any event, the text of the Bill should bepublished as early in the new Session aspracticable.(4) That the aim should be to bring the newUnemployment Act into operation as from the30th June, 193^ the date on which theUnemployment Insurance Act expires ,(5) that notwithstanding that negotiations with&apos;Local Authorities must take place before theBill is actually introduced, no White paper or other authoritative statement with regardto the proposals to be embodied in the Billshould be published until the Bill itself is ready for introduction.The Cabinet also had before them a Memorandum bythe Minister of Health (C.P.-195 (33)) stating that.
although he accepted the Report of the Committee, hewas not satisfied with one feature of the Scheme,namely, the establishment amongst those in need ofassistance of a separate class of industrial or able-bodied unemployed who are to receive special treatment.In his view this distinction could not be justified by any difference between the claims of that class and other recipients of assistance.     The Ministertherefore suggested that the present recipients of out-door relief should be transferred from the LocalAuthorities to the Commission, but to be administered by the Commission in a department separate from thatadministering the able-bodied, and under separate rules.The Chancellor of the Exchequer after explaining the proposals informed the Cabinet that he agreed withthe Minister of Health in disliking the classification of the unemployed, but he accepted the compromise setforth in the Report.     He wished to record the view thatthe scheme in its present form was well worth undertaking and that he was grateful to the Minister of Labour forhis concessions, but that he did not regard the present scheme as the final stage.      If, as he anticipated, thepresent scheme proved a success, he thought that it wouldbe found necessary to go further on the lines of his original plan.The Minister of Labour accepted the scheme andbelieved it was the best in the present circumstances.He expressed his appreciation of the concessions madeby the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Ministerof Health.     He particularly asked that there shouldbe no disclosure during the Parliamentary recessof the details of the scheme.      If such disclosuretook place,, the Government would be attacked for making public their plan to the-28-
country before announcing it to the House ofCommons, and would he thrown on the defensive,when Parliament met, on the details on the scheme.He hoped to have a draft of the Bill ready bythe end of September.The Minister of Health was less optimisticthan the Chancellor of the Exchequer as to theprospects of some points in the scheme, and heapprehended that part of the scheme would collapsethrough its imperfections.      The classification ofthe unemployed was too arbitary to last..     The dualadministration contemplated was so imperfect as to jeopardise the scheme.    That was why he had felt bound to record his view in CP,  195 (33),&quot; The Prime Minister agreed that the classi-fication was awkward and enquired whether it wasthe only possibility.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explainedthat every possible plan had been explored and thatthe one before the Cabinet had been accepted as a compromise.The Secretary of State for Dominion affairs said that originally he   had been among those opposedto the Minister of Labour and he thought that eventuallyit might be necessary to extend the scheme whenit was successful on the original lines.      He wishedto- record, however,  that the present plan was agood one.      It was one of the biggest unemploymentschemes that had been brought forward and embodiedmany of the best points desired by all parties.
The Cabinet agreed  That the Minister of Labour should arrangefor the preparation of an Unemployment&quot;Bill based on the scheme set forth in cp.  190 (33)5 also covering the subjectof Unemployment Insurance for considerationby the Home Affairs Committee and theCabinet at the end of the Cabinet1svacation, and that all the necessary measures should be taken to this end.
LEMENT     13.  The Cabinet had before them the following documents on the subject of Land Settlement (Scotland)A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statee: for Scotland (C.P.-181 (33)) submitting36 proposals to be financed out of borrowedon- money:    covering a draft Bill:    and asking9(e).) authority to announce the adoption of an enlarged policy of land settlement inScotland as outlined in the Memorandum:A Memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer (CP.-191 (33)) setting forthhis objections to the above proposals,but expressing his anxiety to reach agreement with the Secretary of Statefor Scotland on any proposal for an extended programme of land settlement in Scotland which could be financed outof current Votes .After The Secretary of State for Scotland andthe Chancellor of the Exchequer had developed thepoints of view set forth in their respective memorandathe suggestion was made that the Chancellor of theExchequer&apos;s objection of principle to borrowingmoney for uneconomic development and so burdeningposterity, might be met by including the lossincurred on the scheme for each successive year on the estimates.      In this connection the attentionof the Cabinet was drawn to Section (3) of the draftBill attached to CP.   181 (33).:-&quot;At the end of the financial year ending on the thirty-first day of March in the yearnineteen hundred and thirty-four, and of each subsequent year, the Department shall submit tothe Treasury, in such form as the Treasury mayprescribe, a statement of the loss (if any)which has been reasonably or necessarilyincurred by the Department during the year sofar as such loss relates to expenditure out of loans under this section, and the amount of suchloss, tothe extent approved by the Treasury,shall be paid out of moneys provided by   &apos;Parliament. &quot;  &quot;&quot;&quot;This, it was suggested, seemed to indicatethat the plan proposed was already incorporated inthe Bill.The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that31.
3?this attention had not been drawn specifically tothis point and he asked for further time to considerit,The Cabinet agreed  To re-examine the question after theirvacation.
ILLEGAL 14. The Cabinet postponed consideration of theTRAWLING.  Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ScotlandPenaltiesfor. (C.P.-183 (33)) on the prevalence of illegal trawlingby British vessels off the coasts of Scotland, and(previous reference:       instructed the Secretary to keep it on the Agenda.Cabinet 47(33), Con-clusion 9 .)pr- &apos;
fHB EXPIRING]0S CONTINU-0CE BILL.1933.(previous reference:Cabinet 60(32)    C on-clusion 9,)h&quot;R.a.15.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Financial Secretary to the Treasury (CP,-193(33)), circulated by direction of the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer, asking authority to introduce, beforethe adjournment of Parliament, the Expiring laws continuance Bill, 19 33, in the form of a draft attached to the Memorandum,    It was necessary thatthe Bill should become law by December 31, 1933.The draft Bill had been agreed by all the Departmentsconcerned, subject to decisions of the Cabinet as tothe action to be taken in respect of the Dyestuffs(Import Regulation) Act, 1920, and the inclusion inthe Bill of the Unemployment (Relief Works) Act, 1920,and Sections 1 and 4 of the Public Works FacilitiesAct, 1930.The Minister of Health explained the difficultyon the latter point.The Cabinet agreed  To postpone consideration of thequestion for the present, but theSecretary was instructed to keep it on the Agenda of the Cabinet,
MALTA.ItalianPropaganda.(previous reference:Cabinet 44(33), Con-cIns ion 3.)ft16. The Cabinet took note of a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (CP.-194 (33))circulating copies of two secret communications hehad received from the Governor of Malta on the recentsituation in that Island.
TRAINIMG AND - 17. The Cabinet took note of a Memorandum by theOCCUPATION FORTHE UNEMPLOYED     Minister of Labour (C.P.-189 (33)) outlining theNEXT WINTER,efforts being made to provide training and occupation(Previous for the unemployed next winter *Reference:Cabinet 42(33), Con-clusion 12.)
(previous reference:Cabinet 47&apos;55), Con-conclusion 7,)gpGES&apos; SALARIES.     18. The Lord Chancellor informed the Cabinet that everything had been in train for carrying out thedecision of the Cabinet referred to in the marginin respect of Judges&apos;  Salaries, but the matter had now been complicated by a speech made by a prominentCivil Servant in which he had used some phrase to theeffect that everyone had accepted- the economy cutsand that the Judges were the only people &quot;squealing&quot;.The Judges had taken umbrage at this speech and askedleave to publish a Memorandum that they had sent tothe Prime Minister two years ago.The Secretary of State for War said he thought the judges&apos; wish was that the Cabinet should publish theMemorandum, as otherwise they would feel const-rainedto do so.The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed the Cabinetthat the Official in question had expressed the greatestregret for his remarks and had no idea that they were liable to be reported.    mhe Chancellor had takenappropriate action.The Prime Minister said that the Judges&apos; memorandum had been communicated confidentially.   He himself hadno objection to its publication, but he doubted ifthey were justified in publishing without the consentof all the signatories.    If the Judges ascertained that all the signatories were willing, he would raiseno objection.The Cabinet accepted the PrimeMinister&apos;s view,
NEXT MEETING- 19. The Chancellor of the Exchequer communicatedOP CABINET *  to the Cabinet the general lines of a proposal he wasTHE NEW CUNARD inclined to favour for financing, the construction ofLINER.the new Cunard liner by the Government.   He did not(Previous feel, however, that the question could be discussedReference:Cabinet 36       in detail in the absence of the President of the(33), Con-clusion 9(a) ,)Board of Trade.The Cabinet agreed  That a Special Meeting should beheld on FRIDAY, JULY 28th, in thePRIME MINISTER&apos;S ROOM AT.THE HOUSEOF COMMONS, at 3 p.m., for consider-ation of the following questions:-(l) THE NEW CUNARD LINER.(2)  FUTURE MEETINGS OF THECABINET .s      *       *2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,July 26, 1933,

</content>
</cab>
