<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/48/21 images: 204-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.    102It is issued for the personal use of......\Sj&amp;uZZ&amp;Uy.TOP SECRET Copy No......13.5W.M.(44)173rd CONCLUSIONS; MINUTE 2Confideatial Annex(21st December, 1944 - 5.30 p.m. )GREECE(previous reference:(44) 171 stConclusions,Minute 1)THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS said&apos;. .that the Greek Ambassador had now informed us that atelegram from M. Papandreou advising the King in favourof a Regency had been received the previous day.      It       .was not clear whether the advice was that of M. Papandreoualone or that of the Greek Government.     The War cabinet might - see advantage in steps being taken to make contact with the King and to ascertain whether he had, in fact,received further information from Athens as to thesituation, and if so what his reaction was.The War Cabinet first considered the arguments for and against a further approach to the King of Greeceat this stage.The following points&apos; were made in discussion -    . -(a) It was for consideration whether it would not bebetter to postpone any approach to the King for two orthree days longer.      In any event, to bring immediatepressure on him to decide in any particular sense wouldbe open to objection, on the grounds that, we wereinterfering in Greek internal politics.(b) It was suggested, on the- other hand, that it wasvery important that the War Cabinet should have thefullest and most up-to-date information as to develop-ments in the Greek situation.     The latest indicationswere (Athens Telegram No. 669) that we might be gettingnear the point at which.a ne.. situation would arise.      It .would be undesirable that that point should be reachedwithout the War Cabinet having a clear view- as to thepolicy it proposed to adopt.     There need be no questionof bringing any pressure to bear on the King infavourof a particular course -at this stage, nor was it necessarythat the approach to His Majesty should be at the highest level.After-further discussion, the War Cabinet -Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs to send an emissary to ascertain from the King of greece v/hat advice he had received and what his information was as to the political situation in greece, without putting any pressure on His majesty in. favour of any course&apos; of action.A discussion followed on the question of a Regencyand of the suitability of Archbishop Damaskinos for appointment asmade -sole Regent.?he following points were(a) Could the risk be excluded that the Archbish*pyif appointed sole. Regent, might become a dictator?     His

strong opposition to serving as a member of a Regen.cy.Council was suspicious, while an Archbishop as dictatorwould be no more popular in this country than a Kxng forcedon Greece against the will of the people.     The.Archbishop,once installed in power as sole Regent might quite wellset up a puppet Prime Minister.(b) It was urged, on the other hand, that if the archbishop was appointed by the King there would be noquestion of his being a dictator.      He would have been formally appointed by the Greek Crown, which would beplacing its power in commission;   but if the Archbishopbehaved contrary to expectation it would be open to theCrown to cancel his appointment.     In vie v. of the fact thatthe King was in this country, it whs essential that thereshould be someone with whom we could deal in Athens,  and-on whom we could rely to bring about the formation of abroad-based Government.      The Archbishop was put forward as the one person likely to be able to fill this role.(c) There was-no evidence that the Archbishop had LeftWing,&apos; or indeed any, political leanings.      His reluctance to serVe on, or as a member of, a Regency Council wasunderstandable given, the nature of the Council of whichit had been suggested that he might bee -me a member.(d) Was the present unhappy situation in Athens beingprolonged because of the fear that, surrender-by E.L.A.S.would be followed by -the establishment with our support ofa Government of the Right which would indulge in reprisals,and that the Royalists would endeavour to&apos; manoeuvre us into a position in which our continued support would be forthcoming for them?     It was generally agreed that it was essential to avoid any suggestion of this nature, but the-point was made that on the available evidence the risk of a&quot;White Terror&quot; Was small, given the extent to which military equipment appeared to be in the hands of B.L.A.S. and the &quot;Left&quot;.(e) The suggestion was made that there would be advantage in a United Nations guarantee for a fair and free election in Greece.(f) It was suggested that there w:-s no need for Britishtroops to stay in Greece until elections had been held.But we ought to leave our troops there long enough toenable a.broad-based Government to raise a Police force which could maintain order and put down terrorism.After further discussion, the War Cabinet -Decided to await the outcome of the further enquiries no?/ to be made of the King of Greece asto the information&apos; avail able tohim on.the position-.- in Athens, before resuming the discussion.




</content>
</cab>
