<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/111/0 images: 647-649</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^LXhin Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government;,!*Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1920.AIR STAFF MEMORANDUM ON THE AIR FORCE AS AN ALLEGED CAUSE OF THE LOSS OF POPULARITY OF THE MESOPOTAMIA CIVIL ADMINISTRATION.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues a Memorandum which has been prepared by the Chief of the Air Staff on the subject of a telegram, dated the 12th August^from  the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. Having misused the Air Forces by petty pinprick operations in direct contrariness to the Air Ministry Memorandum of June ISwfyhe I , Civil Commissioner now turns round and blames the Air Force for the very results which the Air Ministry had foreseen would follow from his policy.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.August 27, 1920.The Air Staff has had under consideration a telegram from the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, of the 12th August, in which he details the &quot;reasons underlying the loss by the civil administration of that degree of popularity which it first enjoyed.&quot; Among these reasons the statement is made in paragraph 12 ; &quot; The use of aeroplanes against recalcitrants.&quot; The Air Staff cannot let this statement remain on record unchallenged. The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, in making this allegation has executed a surprising change of front; in his previous remarks from September 1918 till the recent disturbance-bances he was an enthusiastic advocate of the use of aircraft, as may be seen from the quotations below: &quot;.....the existence of such a force (Royal Air Force) can scarcely fail to exert a powerful influence in support of British policy and of peace in the whole of Middle East.&quot;September 1918,&quot; The moral effect of flights over distant areas not readily accessible to troops, whether or not accompanied by dropping of bombs, has had an excellent effect whenever resorted to.&quot;November 1918.&quot; I have every confidence in ability of Royal Air Force to lend powerful aid to civil power in maintenance of order in Mesopotamia and in North-West Persia without the intervention of troops. They should be in a position in future to do for us on land in Middle East what the Navy have done for us in Persian Gulf in past.&quot;&quot; Our experience in Mesopotamia and in North-West Persia does not bear out the view that discrimination between innocent and guilty is more difficult when carried out by Royal Air Force than by troops, and I have little doubt that it will prove far less costly than our present methods.&quot;&quot; Experience shows that effective discrimination can be exercised, and there is less risk of complications on the way to and from the scene of action, and greater moral effect. The attitude of tribes is : 4 We are not afraid of your troops. Guns cannot reach us : but we cannot fight against your aircraft.&apos; In point^ of fact the advent of the aeroplanes and their active participation against the tribes had an important and, in my opinion, determining effect on the position, and within six weeks from their arrival (I speak from memory) opposition to our troops was at an end.&quot; [4212]
Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1920.p. p. 179$AIR STAFF MEMORANDUM ON THE AIR FORCE AS AN ALLEGED CAUSE OF THE LOSS OF POPULARITY OF THE MESOPOTAMIA CIVIL ADMINISTRATION.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues a Memorandum which has been prepared by the Chief of the Air Staff on the subject of a telegram, dated the 12th AugustffTrom the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. Having misused the Air Forces by petty pinprick operations in direct contrariness to the Air Ministry Memorandum of June 192(j,uihe ^ Civil Commissioner now turns round and blames the Air Force for the very results which the Air Ministry had foreseen would follow from his policy.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.August 27, 1920.The Air Staff has had under consideration a telegram from the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, of the 12th August, in which he details the &quot;reasons underlying the loss by the civil administration of that degree of popularity which it first enjoyed.&quot; Among these reasons the statement is made in paragraph 12 : &quot; The use of aeroplanes against recalcitrants.&quot; Thy Air Staff cannot let this statement remain on record unchallenged. The Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, in making this allegation has executed a surprising change of front; in his previous remarks from September 1918 till the recent disturbance-bances he was an enthusiastic advocate of the use of aircraft, as may be seen from the quotations below: &quot;.....the existeuce of such a force (Royal Air Force) can scarcely fail to exert a powerful influence in support of British policy and of peace in the whole of Middle East.&quot;September 1918.&quot; The moral effect of flights over distant areas not readily accessible to troops, whether or not accompanied by dropping of bombs, has had an excellent effect whenever resorted to.&quot;November 1918.&quot; I have every confidence in ability of Royal Air Force to lend powerful aid to civil power in maintenance of order in Mesopotamia and in North-West Persia without the intervention of troops. They should be in a position in future to do for us on land in Middle East what the Navy have done for us in Persian Gulf in past.&quot;&quot; Our experience in Mesopotamia and in North-West Persia does not bear out the view that discrimination between innocent and guilty is more difficult when carried out by Royal Air Force than by troops, and I have little doubt that it will prove far less costly than our present methods.&quot;&quot; Experience shows that effective discrimination can be exercised, and there is less risk of complications on the way to and from the scene of action, and greater moral effect. The attitude of tribes is: 1 We are not afraid of your troops. Guns cannot reach us : but we cannot fight against your aircraft.&apos; In point of fact the advent of the aeroplanes and their active participation against the tribes had an important and, in my opinion, determining effect on the position, and within six weeks from their arrival (I speak from memory) opposition to our troops was at an end.&quot; [4212]
&quot; Aeroplanes could then co-operate with local levies, disperse hostile gatherings, and generally assist the Persian Government to maintain order at a far less cost and with less military and political liability than troops. This point of view has been specifically endorsed by Sir P. Cox, His Majesty&apos;s Minister, Tehran.&quot;      )April 1919.&quot;Troops other than the E.A.F. have only been twice used since the armistice in the Baghdad or Basrah vilayets in actual combat with malcontent inhabitants otherwise than on the frontier. The B.A.F., on the other hand, have been used on about twelve different occasions, always with a considerable degree of success.&quot;May 1920.Many other telegrams expressing similar views have been received in addition to the foregoing.The Air ,Staff considers that an explanation of the apparent failure of the Air Force to exert the influence that they claim it to possess will be found not in the use of aeroplanes, but in their misuse. &quot; The ultimate basis of a government is force &quot; (to quote again from the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad), and in their memorandum on the application of air power to hold Mesopotamia the Air Staff laid considerable stress on &quot; strong and continuous action from the air&quot; if the Air Force was to hold effective control. They have protested frequently against the policy of detachments, which by dissipating air power prevents effective action being taken. In fact the Air Staff, in a memorandum of June 1920, referred specifically to the danger-of a policy of &quot;pin pricks &quot; in the following words : &quot; But it is not alone on account of the danger of haste in its application and the ensuing departure from British tradition that these small air detachments are unsatisfactory, but because of their inefficiency for the purpose ot enforcing respect. Aircraft depend to a great extent on the moral effect they create; this is at present considerably owing to. ignorance in the native mind. If they are constantly used for petty operations which cause no great material damage and cannot, owing to the smallness of the unit, be long sustained, respect will change to annoyance and contempt. If this should ever come about the reinspiring of the natives with proper respect for the air arm will be a long and expensive task. It follows, therefore, that when air operations are resorted to, they should be carried out in a strength sufficient to inflict severe punishment and in numbers adequate to sustain the attack for as long a period as may be necessary.&quot; It will be realised then that aircraft cannot be too rapidly sent to show themselves in an area of potential disturbances, and by their mere presence will often induce the natives to return to peaceful ways. Should, however, the second phase arrive when force must be resorted to, the &apos; facility&apos; of aircraft must not be permitted to lead to their despatch without adequate thought and in insufficient strength ; the time for &apos; bluff&apos; has passed.&quot;;. . It is regrettable that circumstances should so soon have shown the correctness of these views.  ,, .. .;.,,...f;; v In preparing this Memorandum the,Air Staff realise that the last telegram of the Civil Commissioner has been sent in a time of grave anxiety and possible depression, but they are unwilling to allow it to remain on record as a considered guide to the possibilities of aircraft correctly used to assist the civil power in disturbed and unsettled countries. &apos;,H. TRENCHAKD,Chief of the Air Staff.August 1920.

</content>
</cab>
