<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/111/0 images: 756-757</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
p 1 8 43^^TO\document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government7SECRET.THE CABINET.REINFORCEMENTS FOR MESOPOTAMIA.In the absence of the Secretary of State for War the following memorandum, containing proposals for reinforcing Mesopotamia, of whose nature Mr. Churchill is cognizant, is circulated by- the General Staff.9th September, 1920.MEMORANDUM BY THE GENERAL STAFF, WAR OFFICE.1. The present situation in Mesopotamia and India demands careful consideration of the extent of our military resources, particularly as regards British troops, in the event of further calls for reinforcements.At our request India is providing reinforcements amounting to 3 British and 17 Indian infantry battalions, with auxiliary troops and services, although by so doing India is of opinion that considerable risks to herself are incurred, for the following main reasons: (a.) British troops in India are some 9,000 short of complement, and units arecomposed of young soldiers backward in training. (6.) Indian troops, the majority of which have been serving since the Armisticeunder active service conditions, are deficient in training, and are composedto a great extent of young recruits, (c.) Despatch of these reinforcements will be unpopular amongst the troops and inIndia generally, entailing as it will (i.) Delay in demobilization, (ii.) Curtailment of leave, (iii.) Upsetting the programme of reliefs.2. India has agreed with great reluctance to sending the three British battalions mentioned above, and presses for their early replacement. The necessity of such replacement cannot be denied, yet it is of great importance that an adequate complement of white troops should be allotted to our forces in Mesopotamia, not only for military, but also for political reasons. The Indian troops in that&apos; country are reported to be suffering from a sense of injustice on account of their long detention overseas, and a feeling has arisen among them that they are being exploited for the advantage of British troops.3. Our many commitments in the United Kingdom, Europe, Egypt, &amp;c, already exhaust our available resources in British troops and there is no prospect under our present voluntary system of providing further troops to meet the possible requirements of both Mesopotamia and India.In these circumstances, it becomes necessary to consider other possible sources, from which white troops could be obtained, and the suggestion has been made that thy Dominions of Canada, Australia and New Zealand could afford some measure of military assistance during the present period of strain. Such assistance might take either the direct form of sending troops to Mesopotamia or the indirect form of&quot; relieving British troops in India or elsewhere so as to free the latter for service in Mesopotamia.As an illustration of this indirect assistance, it is sufficient to indicate the following possible measures: (a.) Australia might be asked to replace the three battalions sent to Mesopotamiafrom India, or to send a brigade to Mesopotamia itself. (6.) Canada might be asked to relieve the British battalion in the West Indies, (c.) New Zealand might be asked to relieve the British battalion at Singapore.(B2.)/381)   100  9/20  HAS, Ltd.   8540wo
4. It is realized that the Dominion Governments may not be in a position to spare troops from their permanent forces for the purposes indicated, but it is hoped that they might be able to raise such troops on a voluntary basis from personnel with previous war experience. Possibly a nucleus of staff arid hjgher ranks could be provided from the permanent forces.All expenses in connection with these tr-troops would presumably have to be borne by the British Exchequer, unless the Dominions concerned voluntarily expressed a desire to contribute, in view of the Imperial na!ture off the task.5. In order to ascertain whether the Dominions would be likely to respond to the suggestion, it is now desired to obtain the sanction of His Majesty&apos;s Government to the Governments of Australia, Canada and New Zealand being approached on the matter. They would be informed of the existing situation and of the nature and extent b&apos;f the aid which would be most acceptable should they   agree to render assistance.

</content>
</cab>
