<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/131 images: 744-749</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
g E C. R ,E T.l-^.lQl(4l). 15131ST NOVEMBER, 1941,MANPOWEREMPLOYMENT OP WOMEN BY. GOVERNME NT DEPARTMENTS,Memorandum by the Lord President off, ^the Council.It Mobile young women are needed for the Servioesauxiliary to the fighting Forces,     And,  in view of theextent to which new factories have been sited in areasdistant from centres of population, large numbers of mobilewomen are also needed for the munitions industries/   The great---fl.ior.ity of mobile women are already in employment of somek^-ndo    A large measure of substitution will therefore benecessary.,    Mobile women will have to be dravn mrsyOxm industries and occupations in the urban areas, where their places couldbe taken by immobile women who could do their work while still living in their own homes,20 In this process of substitution GovernmentDepartments must play their part,,       This does not mean that vital Government Departments are to be put on the same footing as less essential industries, which are required togive up women for the Services and the munitions industrieswithout any assurance that other women will be found to take their place.    It means merely that Government Offices in areas where immobile women are available must, like other importantenterprises in. such areas, make their contribution towardsthe process of substitution by releasing young mobile women,who could work away from their homes,  as fast as suitablesubstitutes are made available from-among the other womenmainly older women, who cannot work away from their homes,30 The contribution which Departments are asked tomake is to release a proportion of the young women in the20-30 age group who are engaged on clerical work for which no special qualifications are required.    There are in theCivil Service about 130,000 women in clerical grades, nearlylOpjooo being temporary staff; and it is known that,  in someCOPY no war    CAB MET

Departments at any rate, more than 50 per cent,  of these are inthe 20-30 age group.      If, from among such large numbers, none of the young mobile women are made available for work away fromtheir homes - and if, further,  it is seen that Departmentscontinue to recruit young mobile women for work of this kind -the Ministry of Labour will clearly find difficulty in pressingthis process of substitution upon commerce and industry.      Itmust he practicable for Departments to release some proportionof these young women - no doubt with inconvenience, but with no substantial loss of efficiency - as older women become available and are trailed to take their place,It should be noted that the proposal does not apply to staff with technical qualifications, e. it.   typists, shorthand-writers and machine operators.       In addition,  clerical staff engaged on&quot;specially confidential work or in sections carryingon vital work (e.g.5   in the War Registry at the Admiralty) can be excluded from the scheme &quot;by arrangements made in agreementbetween the Treasury,  the Ministry of Labour and the department concerned.4. A scheme for the release of a proportion of these womenclerical officers was formulated by the Treasury and was approved in principle by all Departments except the three service departments.      The position has been discussed by the lord president&apos;s Committee, in consultation with the three service ministers.      As a result,  the Service Ministers are prepared toaccept a scheme on the following lines:-(a) Departments will not be expected to release clerical staff while their clerical grades remain substantially belowcomplement.      Until a Department has been brought up to its proper complement,  the first call on new entrants in the clericalgrades must be to fill existing vacancies in those grades.Departments will continue to be free to move staff fromone part of the country to another to fill vacancies, but this practice, necessary for flexibility of administration, will notbe used unreasonably in such a way as tc defeat the whole objectof the present proposals.(b) No mobile women between 19. and 30 will in future be recruited for clerical work in Government Departments if suitableimmobile or older women are available.      Continued recruitment of women of this age-group to certain special strffs,  such asthe War Registry at the Admiralty, will be a matter fordiscussion under the arrangements described at (d) below.(c) Subject to  (a) above, Departments will prcceed to release mobile women between 20 and 30 in the clerical gradesto the maximum of their ability,  as older or immobile women aremade available by the Mir. is try  of Labour to tike  their place.The numbers to be released will vary according to theneeds of the Department and the extent to which dilution ofpermanent staff has already taken place.      All Departments shouldbe able to arrange for the eventual release of at least 10 percent,  of the numbers in. the 20-50 age group.      And in Departmentswhere the numbers employed are large and the work is less

directly related to the war effort the proportion to hereleased should he substantially higher,  in some cases as muchas 50 per cent,  of those in this age group^(d) Differences or difficulties arising out of theapplication of the principles laid down in (a; - (c),  forexample,  the determination of special categories of work whichmay require special treatment, will he the subject of consultation between representatives of the Treasury,  theMinistry of Labour and the Department concerned.This procedure will preserve a measure of flexibility inthe application of the scheme, particularly as regards the exclusion of staffs engaged on specially confidential or vitalwork,  as mentioned in paragraph 3 above.(e) All temporary  &apos;en clerks below the age of 30 willbe recruited solely through the local offices of the Ministryof Labour.At the same time the Ministry of Labour will instruct their local offices that,  so far as it is at all possible forthem to do so,  they must meet demands by Departments for staff to fill authorised establishments:    that these demands shouldbe met wherever practicable by the provision of suitable olderor immobile women, or part-time women employed on half-shifts,but that where this is not practicable younger or mobile womenmust be supplied.(f) The Service Departments will not seek to defeat the objects of this scheme by employing women in their uniformedServices to do civil clerical work previously done by youngwomen released under the scheme.In certain cases, where shortage of staff is acute,  it maybe necessary to have recourse to such an expedient, either tomeet an emergency or as a temporary arrangement.      But, whereService Departments see that in any particular case the releaseof civil staff will inevitably result in the employment, or increased employment, of uniformed women,  they will discuss thematter in advance with the Treasury and the Ministry of Labour.5. My Committee recevv&quot;-&apos;end that a scheme on these lines bebrought into operation without delay.(Intlid.)    tJ .A.G*eat George Street, S.W.1.31st NOVEMBER,  1941.


</content>
</cab>
