<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/237/0 images: 130-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property  oi His Britannic Majesty&apos;s  Government.]                 Printed for the Cabinet.  January 1933.                                                            Copy No.CABINET.Reduction of Pay of Indian Services.       MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY  OF STATE FOR INDIA.   The Government of India&apos;s Budget estimates for  1933-34 are of necessity subjectto the qualification that, owing to general economic  uncertainty, any estimate mustbe  more than  usually  conjectural.   Apart  from  this,  the  Budget  situation is complicated by the fact, that the two most important and  contentious questions underconsideration, viz. that of the reimposifcion of the  cut in pay of the Services&apos;8 andthat of an excise duty on matches, affect  not  only the general  Budget of the CentralGovernment but also the Budgets of  the Provincial Governments, while the questionof pay-cuts affects in addition the separate Budget of the Railways.   In the table appended is set out the surplus or deficit position of the respectiveBudgets on  various  hypotheses,  the  figure in the case  of the Provinces being theaggregate deficit of those Provinces  which in the  absence  of a subvention (e.g. fromthe proceeds of the match excise) would be in deficit,  those Provinces  in which a surplus is anticipated being left out of  account  since  their surpluses will  not beavailable  towards  meeting deficits elsewhere.  The  figures given show  the effect of complete remission, partial  remission, and full rcimposition  of the  cut.  Those forpartial  remission assume that the cut should now be one of 5 per cent.,  and thatcertain income tax concessions by which the  burden of the original cut was mitigatedshould not be renewed.                            (All figures in  Rs. lakhs.)          Pay-cut wholly remitted and Income Tax Concession  not renewed.         Central revenues -      ...  Deficit    59         Railways-                                       9,20         Provinces in deficit!    -      -       -     ,,    4,56 (or 2,20 if match                                                               excise distributed).           Pay-cut half remitted and Income Tax Concession not renewed.         Central revenues-      ...  Surplus  36         Railways-       -                        Deficit  8,10         Provinces in deficit^    -       -           ,,    3,78 (or 1,4S if match                                                               excise distributed).           Pay-cut wholly reimposed and- Income Tax Concession renewed.         Central revenues-      ...  Surplus  91         Railways        -                       Deficit  7,00         Provinces in deficit^                        ,,    3,13 (or 83 if match                                                               excise distributed).   It will be seen that on the basis of the  present  estimates the Central Governmentwould show a surplus of  Rs. 91  lakhs if the full cut were reimposed as  at  present ;while  this surplus would be  reduced to Rs.  36 lakhs if a  5  per cent,  cut  were imposed,  the income-tax concession  being withdrawn, and there would be a deficit of Rs.  59 lakhs if no  cut were reimposed.   As regards the Provinces,  even  ifthe full cut in pay were maintained, a number of Provincial budgets would  show ahaggregate deficit of Us. 3,13 lakhs, which would  be substantially increased  by  anyremission of the pay-cuts.  To meet  this situation, and especially since a number ofProvinces have  already accumulated deficits, the  Finance  Member of tho Goverhor-GeneraPs Council has proiwsed the imposition of an excise duty on matches.  Sucha duty, to be successful, requires some arrangement  between  British India and the   * Jt will bo remeitiburod that a special Act, expiring- at. tho end of March this year, had to bo passed in tho autumn of 1931 to enable the All-India Services to bo cut.   t Excluding&apos; Madras and Puniiib with a combined surplus of 56.   X  Kxeludinir Madras, United tYovineos and Punjab, with a combined surplus of 96.   5 Excluding Madras, United Provinces, Punjab, and  Bihar and  Orissa, with a combined surplusof 1,49.      102S    60  1.33SECRET.CP. 14 (33).
Indian States ;  and, as the result of provisional negotiations, it is contemplated thatof the net anticipated  proceeds of: about Us. 3,00 lakhs,  Rs. 70  lakhs  approximatelywould be;allocated to the States in  consideration of their adhesion to the arrangementso that about Rs. 2,30 lakhs would be available for British India, the suggestion being that the  latter amount  should be  distributed as a  subvention from the CentralCovernment to those  Provincial Governments that are  in need of assistance.  Theaggregate cost  to all the Provinces  of a total or partial remission  of the pay-cuts isestimated for 1933-34 as Us. 2,36 lakhs and Rs. 1,18 lakhs  respectively, so that theaggregate cost  to the deficit Provinces would be somewhat loss than these figures.  Itwill be  seen therefore  that even  if the proceeds  of the match tax in  ils lirst vearshould be substantially less than the figure of Rs.  3,00 lakhs quoted above, they should suffice to enable the proposed subvention to the Provinces to counterbalance a partialremission of the pay-cuts, and  perhaps in addition to leave a  balance available forfurther assistance  in  the most difficult cases, notably that of ,Bengal, where in anycase a deficit of  about Rs. 2,00 lakhs is  anticipated.  E ven with assistance from amatch tax and  a 5 per cent,  pay-cut, several Provincial Budgets will show substantialdeficits,  and the serious railway  deficit,  which will be  reduced by no less thanRs. 1,10 lakhs  if a 5 per cent, pay-cut is adopted,  will involve a further inroad on theRailway Depreciation Fund, a process which cannot lie continued  indefinitely.    The proposal  to impose a match excise duty for next year is opposed  by themajority of  the  Governor-GeneraTs Council on  the  ground that  it  would  excitecriticism as being a tax on  the poorest classes to  provide  money  for  restoring the pay of officials  and would thus  have serious  reactions throughout the country.    As regards the cuts  in pay, the  Government of India (with the exception of theArmy Member) are unanimous in urging that, in view of the financial position, theyshould be reimposed in full.    In  the  light  of the  situation thus  disclosed,  t  have  reached, though with great reluctance, the  conclusion that  acquiescence  in the continuance of some cut in pay for another year from the 1st April next is  unavoidable.   In  reaching this conclusion  have given the utmost possible weight to the point of view of  the Services thatthere should be a complete restoration of the cut.   Following on  the  statements i made in introducing the temporary Abatements Measure in the House of Commons inthe autumn of  1931, I have recently stated in reply to Service representations on thesxibject that I had no intention of agreeing to the  continuance of the cut in the pay ofofficers appointed by me beyond the 31st March 1933 unless 1 was  satisfied that thefinancial situation in India rendered such  a  course unavoidable.   I  am being pressed by the Government of India to  reimpose the cut of 10 per cent, in full, and 1 recognisethat from xthe  purely  financial point  of  view there  is  much to be  said  for thiscourse,  especially in view  of  the  fact that even if the whole  cut were  continued the Railway deficit would  amount to  Rs.  7 crores, a  figure which is  increased hyRs. 1  crore by  the remission of half the cut.  1 have discussed with the Governmentof India the question as to whether the  full  cut  could be  continued in the case  of theCommercial 1 Apartments if reduction was allowed in the case of the administrative services, but I  have felt  obliged to  accept the contention of  the Government of india that the objections against this course render its adoption undesirable.   As, however,the budget of  the Central  Government  will show a  small surplus with a partialremission of the cut and  as the credit position, both in London and in India,  has been much  improved  in the  last  18  months, andv should render it possible to finance the Railway deficit without  excessive strain, I feel  that a continuance  of the  wholecut for a further year can hardly be described as Unavoidable.  In response, therefore,to my strong  representations  that legislation for complete  reimposition  would beregarded as inconsistent with pledges given and would not commend itsel f to Parliament,the Government of India (including  tho Army  Member) have  reluctantly acquiesced in a reduction  of the cut from 10 per cent, to 5 per cent., it  being understood that thespecial income  tax concession would not be renewed.  The Finance Member, however,still adheres to the view  that the cut should be retained in its entirety.   vApart from the question of  honouring the pledges thus given to existing membersof the Services, I am  convinced that a continuance of the cut  at the  full rate of10  per cent, for another year would be most unwise from  a political  point  of viewhere.   The reality of the safeguards in the new  constitution  will be judged by  theway in  which the existing  service safeguards  are  implemented.  Moreover,  theopinion is very generally held  in this country that  the effectiveness of the proposedsafeguards  in  the new  constitution  will largely  depend  on the maintenance of a
strong European  element in  the Indian  Civil Service and  Indian  Police  Service.Full expression is certain to he given to such opinion  in  the course of the discussions on  the  White  Paper, and, if nothing is done before its  appearance to lighten theburden  of the Services, the probable unfortunate results  on  recruitment and  onpremature retirement are sure to be stressed.  This is an aspect of the Indian Servicesquestion to which the Government of  this country must pay special attention as theGovernment  of India are naturally more  immediately  concerned with the  politicalreaction  in India  to  a restoration of  even part of the  cut in  view of the  financial situation as revealed in the estimates given above.    The  fact  that on  this occasion the cut  in  pay will be  5  per cent, instead of10  per  cent, and will be for a period  of one year only, should convince the Servicesthat Government  is in earnest in meeting their claims for relief ; while on the otherhand the money that the 5 per cent, cut will  bring in both to the Central and Provincialrevenues should,  if combined with the imposition  of a match tax, convince financialopinion in India and  elsewhere that due regard is being paid to the financial situation,and this latter consideration is particularly important  on the eve of a constitutional change.    If the opening months of the new financial  year  should  proved  uncxpectedlyprosperous, I will certainly hold  myself free to consider whether oven  this half cutcould not be restored  before 31st March 1934.    My colleagues, the Secretaries of  State for War and  Air, may like  to  know  thatI would  propose in  the case of British service officers to apply mutatis  mutandis  thesame arrangements for relief in  regard to  the 5 per cent, cut  as have been  agreedupon for the present cut of 10 per cent.    If my colleagues agree with my view that the partial continuance of the cut is unavoidable, it will bo  necessary, as  in 1931, to pass a measure through Parliamenttaking power,  in the case of statutorily protected officers,&quot;8 to  make  the necessaryabatement from  pay up  to but  not exceeding 5 per cent,  and limited in its operation to  the 31st March 1934.   The text of the Bill on the previous occasion  was  verybrief and I  am  told that on this occasion  it can  be  still shorter just  one clausealtering the maximum  amount  of the cut  and the date of operation given  in the expiring Act.    Match Excise. It is  in  any  case  highly desirable that the resources  of thoseProvinces which are  in a  deficit  position should be fortified;  and  this need is emphasised by the fact that their deficits  will be aggravated  by a decision to remiteven half of  the existing pay cut.  I   propose therefore to inform the Government ofIndia that this tax should be included in their Finance Bill, and that proposals shouldbe submitted  to the Legislature for  the  allocation to Provincial Governments (andto  Indian States so far as necessary) of  the estimated  proceeds.  It  does  notnecessarily  follow  that,  if  this  portion  of  the  Finance  Bill is  rejected  by theLegislature,  the  XDrocedure of  &quot;certification&quot; will  be used  to pass  it  into  law.That is a question that can only properly be  decided if  and when the occasion arises.    * The statutorily protected officers are those appointed by the Secretary of State in Council before thecommencement of the Government of India Act, 1919,  but it is generally agreed that it is impossible to cut the pay of all the rest of the services in India and exempt these officers.India Office,  27th January 1933.S. 11.

</content>
</cab>
