<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/3/0 images: 166-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET.Copy No.CP. (45) 224.IWi October, 1945.CABINET.HOUSING.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.IN replying to the motion for next Wednesday it will be necessary to make ageneral statement of our policy on housing and of the action which has been taken and is in contemplation.2.   I should propose to deal with three main points : (1) emergency action for the months immediately ahead;(2) the house building programme in its various aspects and the actionintended to be taken by the Government to secure the execution of theprogramme speedily and at a reasonable cost;&apos;&apos;3) the legislation and the regulations which the Government intend.3.   For the emergency action two regulations are required : (1) For the emergency use of occupied houses.To provide for waiving restrictive covenants and the operation of rent restriction provisions where owners respond to the Governmentappeal to take in lodgers.   This is in draft.(2) To prevent the change of use from residential to non-residential.4. The legislation required for the housing programme comprises thefollowing : (1) A Miscellaneous Housing Bill to include : (i) Building Materials. To authorise the Treasury to finance fromthe Consolidated Fund (i.c, by borrowing), the purchase by theMinistry of Works of building materials and components,including prefabricated bouses, and the preparation of sites anderection of houses by the Ministry of Works on behalf of LocalAuthorities.(ii) The control of the selling price of houses built under licence-Toprovide that houses built privately under a licence limitingtheir size and selling price should not within a period of fouryears be re-sold at a higher price,(iii) Advances on purchase of houses. To amend to  1,200 the figureof  800 under the Small Dwellings Acquisition Acts and section 91 (4) of the Housing Act, 1936, which is the maximumvalue of a house for which advances may be made by the localauthority.(2) A acquisition of Land Bill.To provide a new and uniform procedure for acquiring land which localauthorities can already be authorised to acquire compulsorily. In particular to substitute a quicker procedure of Ministers Order for Provisional Order.The Bill will also contain provision on the lines of the Housing (temporary accommodation) Act. 1944, facilitating quicker entry and subsequentacquisition. From the housing point of view it would be satisfactory for meto have this provision applicable to housing only and included in a Housing-Instructions to Parliamentary Counsel are being prepared.[30697]b
Bill, but it is not likely that this would be satisfactory to other Departmentswho would be left with less expeditious powers of acquisition for the services for which they were concerned. It therefore seems necessary to have aseparate Bill to enable local authorities to acquire land for all purposes bythe same procedure as applies to the acquisition of land under the Housing(Temporary Accommodation) Act.(3) Control of Furnished Lettings.(4) Housing, Financial Provisions.I have considered whether the legislation required can be included ina single Bill. I have come to the conclusion that this is not practicable. Ifthe Acquisition of Land Bill is intended to be applicable to all purposes for which local authorities have powers of compulsory acquisition it is not suitable for inclusion in a Housing Bill. The proposals for control offurnished lettings properly form part of rent restriction legislation and cannot be conveniently included in a Housing Bill. The proposals for financial assistance to local authorities must be agreed with the chancellor and must then be the subject of discussion with the Associations of LocalAuthorities. I am satisfied that this legislation will have a much smootherpassage in the House if we carry the Associations with us and that therewill be a much better chance of doing this if we allow ample time for consultation and discussion. The Associations have been assured that thelegislation when passed is intended to be retrospective, and our defermentof this legislation has the goodwill of the Associations. This legislation should include a number of other items in addition to the proposals forsubsidy for houses built after the war and will properly constitute a separate bill. I ask for approval in principle to the legislation indicated above and suggest that reference should be made in the Debate to these Bills as legisla-tion which the Government intend to promote on the basis that the miscellaneous Housing Bill, the Acquisition of Land Bill and the Controlof Furnished Lettings would be marked for early introduction, and that forthe reasons indicated&quot; above a somewhat later date for the Housing financial provisions Rill will be indicated, but it should be as early as effectiveconsultation with the Associations of Local Authorities permits.5. Emergency action means in effect the best use of accommodation which already exists. Neither new houses nor elaborate conversion can make muchcontribution towards this winter&apos;s needs.The additional action suggested is (1) to prevent a diminution in the existing pool Of housing accommodation.For this purpose I suggest a Defence Regulation to prohibit the con-version of residential accommodation to other purposes without theconsent of the housing authority;(2) to secure the fullest possible use of spare accommodation in occupiedhouses by (a) an appeal to householders who have spare accommodation in their houses to make it available to persons with no home of theirown;(&amp;) a Defence Regulation to exempt arrangements made in this way from the provisions of the Rent Restriction Acts and from therequirements of covenants attached to a house which might otherwise prevent such arrangements and to give powers toLocal Authorities to make such minimum essential works asmay be necessary and to provide necessary fittings, furnitureor equipment;(c) where necessary, the use of requisitioning powers to make spareaccommodation available.6. I propose that Local Authorities should be invited to make this appealin their districts, with the backing of the Government, and that it should extendboth to furnished and to unfurnished accommodation. Householders who are willing to help in this way will be invited to register with the local authoritystating the amount of the accommodation available and the terms. Once accom-modation is registered (which will depend on the acceptance of the terms by thelocal authority), the protection of the tenancy which would otherwise result underthe Rent Restriction Act would be waived (so that the householder need not beafraid of being unable to bring the arrangement to an end) and covenants whichwould also prevent sub-letting would also be waived.
&apos; T.he Minister of Fuel and Power has advised me that there will be oTeatdifficulty m the provision of gas and electrical appliances. The powers to LocalAuthorities to provide equipment will necessarily be limited by this fact, andthe aim must, therefore, be primarily to secure accommodation which can be used as it stands. I am aware that appeals of this kind have already been made by-some authorities and I hope that resort to compulsory powers will not be necessarvin order to induce householders with spare accommodation to offer it. I think,however, that we must be prepared to use compulsory powers in the exceptionalcase of unreasonable refusal to make accommodation available. The powers would take the form of requisitioning the property as a whole and allowing thepresent occupant to retain a specified amount of accommodation.I should propose at once to consult the representatives of local authoritiesand thereafter to launch the appeal.7.   The new building programme should, I suggest, consist of (1) Temporary houses.-! should refer to this as a stop-gap, to be carried through as quickly as possible, but to be limited to the number ofhouses already allocated to Local Authorities. I propose that theWhite Paper which has been prepared should be laid before the debate.(2) Permanent houses built by Local Authorities, I should refer to the programmes submitted by the Local Authorities and the progress made towards their execution and the steps which are being taken to accelerate progress.(3) Permanent houses of non-traditional types. I should refer to the research and experiments which have been carried out, and to the action whichI have taken to promote arrangements for the construction ofhouses which have been approved as a result of this research. I haveissued a Circular to Local Authorities in which I have indicated thearrangements which the Government intend to make as may benecessary for bulk orders and for control of prices in order to assistLocal Authorities. I have given Local Authorities full particulars of the systems and advised them where prototypes can be seen. Ihave requested Local Authorities to let me know within the&apos;next monthhow many houses of the various types they wish to order. the types of which particulars are given are (i) B.I.S.F., Braithwaite, Hill, Howard and Pressed Steel.   All ofthese are steel or steel-framed systems,(ii) Easiform, Airey and Orlit.   These are concrete houses.(4) Houses erected by private persons under licence, I should refer to thearrangements in operation, to the conditions attached to licences andto my proposal to introduce legislation to provide that houses builtunder licence should not within a period of years (I suggest 4 years for this purpose) be sold or let at a figure higher than that approved at the time the licence was issued.8. I should stress the importance of getting a substantial output of new houses under way. Particularly in London war damage repair must continue forsome time to occupy a substantial proportion of our building force. But elaborateconversion should not be encouraged until new building is under way.9. I have considered to what extent other agencies than Local Authoritiescan be used in our programme of new house building :-(1) Housing Associations can play their part in collaboration with LocalAuthorities when they have the machinery and the financial resources to do so But all experience suggests that their total contribution in numbers can only be a small one. Building Societies are, of course,financial agencies only and do not themselves build houses. If theywere prepared to form a Housing Association which aimed at a contribution to the provision of houses for letting I would certainlyconsider how we could best co-operate, but so far they have felt unableto act in this way. .,, .(2) Direct building by the Government must be either in agreement with oxs        in default of the Local Authority.   Before the Government embarked on such operations it would be necessary to be clear on what terms theywere to proceed, e.g., in regard to the acquisition of land, the building[30697] B 2
of houses by contract or direct labour, the ownership and management of the houses and the selection of tenants. To introduce the questionof direct building by the Government would certainly arousecontroversy with local authorities on whom Parliament has imposedthe statutory responsibility. I have every reason to think that mostLocal Authorities will build as many houses as they can with thebuilding resources available in the district. I cannot but think that,apart from the difficulties which would be involved in working outarrangements for building large numbers of houses in small groups bya central organisation, an announcement of. direct building by theGovernment would be a deterrent to progress by confusing the minds of Local Authorities and leading them to delay their own proposals.I suggest that, having announced our intentions to look to theLocal Authorities for the production of houses, we should throw our full weight into this campaign, and concentrate on making themaximum building resources available to them. I am taking action to stimulate their progress and to give all possible technical assistance tothose authorities who are insufficiently equipped in this way.(3) The increased use of agencies which cater for the erection of houses forsale raises a question of policy. In my view our first object must beto build houses for letting to the lower-income groups. Power has beengiven to Local Authorities to issue licences for the erection of houses by other persons, where such building will not interfere with themaximum output of houses by the Local Authority. But in my view the building of such houses at the present time, when labour and materials are in short supply, must be controlled, and I, therefore, donot propose that at the present time it should be stimulated by anylegislative proposals for granting financial assistance : nor am Isatisfied that at the present time, when priority in obtaining a homepossesses such a high value, it would be right to introduce special legislation to give financial assistance to those who are able to obtain a measure of priority for themselves by their ability to purchasea house.0 I do propose that we should introduce legislation to extend themaximum value of houses in respect of which advances may be madeunder the Housing Act and the Small Dwellings Acquisition Actsfrom  800 to  1,200, and I should encourage Local Authorities to use these powers in order to give to the purchasers of houses the benefitof the lower rates of interest at which Local Authorities can lend, ascompared with the Building Societies.10. I should refer to the special needs of rural housing and their importancein relation to food production. The proposals for subsidy for the erection of new houses by Rural District Councils, which, in consultation with the Secretary ofState for Scotland and the Minister of Agriculture, I am discussing with theChancellor and on which I intend to consult the Associations of Local Authorities,will continue to make a special provision for rural areas which will take accountof rental levels and financial resources. In our arrangements for the execution ofthe programme we shall do all that is possible to make the fullest use of the smallbuilders by whom such houses have been built in the past, and I shall explore every means of supplementing this supply by alternative methods of construction. Themain difficulty in the rapid provision of houses in the rural districts is the shortageof building labour. There are one or two systems of non-traditional buildingwhich I hope will prove specially suitable for rural areas, and I intend to pressupon the rural authorities the adoption of these forms of building and to workout arrangements in consultation with those for facilitating their erection andfor providing the necessary technical guidance. I am assured of the full supportof the Rural District Councils&apos; Association in a vigorous campaign for housebuilding, and it is particularly in these areas where I believe that my officers willbe able to expedite progress by technical assistance in planning.This shortage of rural building labour is a special reason for deferring thequestion of financial assistance towards the reconditioning of rural houses until we are satisfied that the programme for the building of new houses is well underway I have asked my Central Housing Advisory Committee to report to me onthe possibility of carrying out reconditioning of cottages without prejudice to theprogramme of new building, and I propose to bring the question of remtroductionof the Housing (Rural Workers) Acts again before my colleagues when I receivethe Committee&apos;s report.
11. An effective control of costs must be stressed as essential to success. Ihave no intention of securing an illusory reduction by cutting down standards, butI propose to reject tenders which seem to me unreasonably high.The Government are doing everything possible to&apos; ensure that building materials and components are produced in sufficient quantities and in due timeto meet the requirements of the Building Programme, and this is the function inthe main of the Ministries of Works and Supply, as production authorities. Theywill first consider whether there is sufficient, capacity, &amp;c, in the industries eori-cerned to produce the quantities required at the due time, and when sufficientproduction will not be forthcoming substitutes will have to be considered. Ifthere is sufficient capacity in an industry to produce the quantities required, theProduction Authority will consider whether any special steps are necessary toensure that the quantities are produced in clue time and at a reasonable price. Insome cases no special steps may be needed; in others it will be necessary to enterinto production agreements or to place bulk orders. The Government will do their best to ensure that the prices of materials and components are fair and reasonable; control is exercised over selling prices and it will continue as long asis necessary.12. Hitherto responsibility for a number of building components and fittingswhich are engineering products has rested with the Board of Trade except that,when these components and fittings were required for incorporation in temporary houses, the orders were placed by the Ministry of Works in consultation with theBoard of Trade. These arrangements have now been simplified. Responsibilityfor engineering components and fittings has been transferred to the Ministry ofSupply; and this Ministry will now place the necessary orders when thesecomponents and fittings are required for incorporation in temporary houses orfor other building services undertaken by the Ministry of Works. The Ministryof Supply will also undertake all progress and inspection work in connection withthe production of these engineering components and fittings. Under these new arrangements, advantage will be taken of the extensive war-time experience ofthe Ministry of Supply in the engineering field.We intend to plan the whole of the engineering side of the building-component industry and to direct it, if necessary, by means of price control andblanket orders, so that, wherever possible, standardised components may phaseto meet demands for the following items so far as included in the government building programme :  (i) temporary and prefabricated permanent houses;(ii) bomb damage repair and flat conversion schemes;(iii) brick-built housing schemes for public authorities;(iv) erection of houses by private persons under licence;(v) maintenance of existing property.A. B.Ministry of Health, S.W. 1,l$tti October, 1945.


</content>
</cab>
