<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/3/0 images: 206-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET.CP. (45) 231.16th October, 1945.CABINET.NATIONAL HEALTH SERVICE.The Hospital Services.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.THE Lord President of the Council does not, in his paper on the future ofthe hospital services (OP. (45) 227), dispute seriously my contention that theway to make these services efficient is to centralise responsibility for them. Hisdoubts about my proposals relate to their possible repercussions and political consequences, particularly in the field of local government. I had naturally con-sidered very fully the difficulties which the Lord President foresees and I am convinced they can be overcome. In any case, they must, I suggest, be judgedagainst the difficulties to my mind far greater of any other scheme.2. There are three paramount objections to any scheme less radical thanmine.First, it is, I repeat, impossible to pay from 70 per cent, to 90 per cent, of theexpenditure of voluntary hospitals out of public funds and leave them underindependent management. The effect of this upon our own people would, Ibelieve, be much more serious than the political consequences, which the lord president fears, of my own proposals.If it be argued that control could be exercised by handing the voluntary hospitals over to the local authorities (whether to joint boards or to individual authorities) instead of to the State, the reply is that such an alternative wouldrouse a tornado compared with any passing thunderstorm my scheme may provoke.Second, any scheme which leaves responsibility for the hospital service with local authorities must be unequal in its operation. This would be unjust to thepublic, who will pay equal contributions.Third, it is a hard fact that, as was stated in my earlier paper, neither of theexisting hospital systems is adequate. It solves nothing to put the one under theother, or even to adapt the detailed form of either or both of them locally. A new,and different, system altogether is the only remedy.3. I gather that the Lord President is in favour of a return to the JointHospital Boards of the White Paper. I do not believe this to be practicable.Apart from the constitutional objections to joint boards, the scheme had the gravedisadvantage of splitting the health service in half, leaving hospital services tobe administered by the boards and other health services by individual authorities;it was a scheme that had no friends. Moreover, it left the voluntary hospitalsunder independent management. If my proposals are not accepted, I think theonly alternative is to leave the hospitals with their present owners and providefor joint area planning on the lines proposed by Mr. Willink. But neitherMr. Willink&apos;s, nor any other local government, scheme will give us a fully efficientservice or overcome the fundamental objections cited in the preceding paragraph.4. What then, in comparison with these objections, are the difficulties inthe way of centralisation ?  The Lord President cites four  (i) The concentration of too much power in the hands of one Minister.(ii) The danger of weakening local government.(iii) The political consequences.(iv) Delay.5. The danger of concentrating police powers in one Minister is obvious,but I am sure the Lord President will not press this analogy. There can be noGestapo of hospital orderlies. A centralised service must, indeed, be planned soas to avoid rigidity. That is why I have proposed that the hospital service shallbe administered locally by Regional Boards and District Committees. But I donot think that there is, in this proposal, the dilemma suggested in paragraph 2of the Lord President^ paper.   The Boards and Committees are not designed[30708]Copy No. b9
as a. sop to local authorities. Nor are they in any sense analogous to the joint boards of the White Paper. They will be the agents (though not, I hope, in anyderogatory sense the creatures) of my Department, and the extent to which power is delegated to them will not affect the local authorities as such. Yet it isprecisely by the selection of the right men and women to serve on these bodiesthat I hope to be able to give them substantial executive powers, subject to a broadfinancial control, and so prevent rigidity. Admittedly, this is a field in whichthere is room for development in the technique of government, but the problems that will arise should not be incapable of solution.6. I agree with the Lord President that if we make the hospital and clinicservices a national responsibility we shall be accused of weakening local govern-ment.   But is the accusation just?It is the common practice of local authorities to resist strenuously anydiminution of their powers and at the same time to complain of the burden onthe rates and demand ever-increasing subsidies from the Exchequer. In 1914the ratepayers paid for all purposes  71 millions, when Exchequer grants were 22-^ millions. In 1939 the ratepayers paid  191 millions, while exchequer grants amounted to  147 millions. Under Mr. WillkuYs scheme, local authorities would bear 50 per cent of the cost of the health services they administered, but no more than 31 per cent, of the cost of the new health service as a whole. Hasnot the time come to say plainly to local authorities that there is a limit to theamount of money which the Exchequer is willing to give them to spend, andthat there must now be a rationalisation of local government services to ensure a sensible distribution both of function and cost as between local authoritiesand the State? In short, it is not a haphazard whittling down of the powersof local authorities that we contemplate, but their proper rationalisation. Thereis no fear that there will be any shortage of work for the local authorities to do.Housing and town and country planning, education, police, water and sewerage,highways, the environmental (as distinct from personal) health services, andthe many other functions they will continue to exercise, all expanding in impor-tance and cost, will surely provide ample scope for the education in democracyupon the importance of which I am in full agreement with the Lord President.7. If my scheme for a national hospital service is sound, I do not believewe need fear the political consequences. The Lord President is good enough to describe the scheme as &apos;&apos; imaginative.&apos;&apos; Is not that exactly what we were returnedto be ? Even though we did not put this precise proposal in our manifesto, itaccords with its spirit. Also its proposed system of new regional agencies maywell be a pointer to a future regional reorganisation in local government itself,with which we are in sympathy. That there will be opposition, even violentopposition, in some quarters, I do not deny. That it will lose us votes in the municipal elections I doubt; for I believe that, if the scheme is properly presented,it will have the support of a great majority of the medical profession, of themore far-seeing local government opinion and even of the wiser heads in the voluntary hospital world, who realise that the time when hospitals should be organised as (charities has gone.8. Of delay I am, indeed, afraid. The present state of uncertainty cannotbe allowed to continue, and a national health service is essential to our social insurance plans; and on both these grounds we need a Bill this .Session. Thismeans an early decision, so that I can give the instructions to my Departmentwithout which their planning cannot proceed. But a decision :to adopt my proposals would not mean conducting the whole series of negotiations all over again.Once assured of the full support of my colleagues, I could make clear that theprinciples of the new scheme are settled, and many of the details needingdiscussion would not have to be dealt with in the Bill itself, which would probablybe simpler. There may be more argument on the Bilhs second reading but, unless we are faced with deliberate obstruction, there should be less in Committee.9. In short, I believe that we have now the chance to put into effect a schemewhich would make our hospital and health services the admiration of the world.It is a chance which, in any one field of administration, comes but once, perhaps,in a generation. Given the support of my colleagues, and, not least, of the lord president, who has such powerful influence in the local government world, the thing can be done now.   If it is not done now, it will not be done in our time.A. B.Ministry of Health, S.W. 1,16th October, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
