<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/3/0 images: 254-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET.Copy No.64CP. (45) 240.20th October, 1945.CABINET.REPATRIATION OF GERMANS TO GERMANY FROM THE UNIONOF SOUTH AFRICA AND THE MANDATED TERRITORY OFSOUTH-WEST AFRICA.Memorandum by the Secretary oe State for Dominion Affairs.1. On the 3rd September the High Commissioner for the Union of SouthAfrica informed me that the Union Government felt strongly that they could not allow their country once again to be exposed to the dangers shown by experience to be inherent in the existence of a large German community in South-WestAfrica and of individual Germans in the Union who would stop at nothing to advance the interests of Germany. Before, however, formulating their policy,the Union Government asked for the comments of the United Kingdom Govern-ment as to the possibility of repatriating such Germans to Germany.2. In reply to my request for an estimate of the number involved, the HighCommissioner sent me the information at Annex I, which indicates that upwards of 7,000 Germans would be involved, consisting of 6,000 persons, with dependants,out of a total of 10,000 Germans in South-West Africa, and over 1,000 Germanresidents from the Union (this latter figure excludes dependants).3. As the High Commissioner pressed for an indication of the practicalpossibilities of shipping these numbers, I informed him, after consultation withthe Ministry of War Transport, that, political questions apart, there was no chance of it being practicable before the middle of 1946 to make available thenecessary shipping and that, even then, the feasibility of doing so would need tobe considered in relation to the other calls at the time on our shipping resources.I added that important political issues might be involved in the Union Govern-ments proposal and that we counted on them not to take any decisions, withouthearing further from us, which would have repercussions for the United KingdomGovernment.4. I have now received from the High Commissioner the letter of the11th October at Annex II in which he emphasises that the Union government do not wish to repatriate all Germans in South-West Africa and the Union butonly those who are inimical to the safety of the Mandated Territory and theUnion.   He presses that the United Kingdom Government should (a) arrange for the repatriation from South Africa during the next fewmonths of a few individuals who may be regarded as particularlyundesirable;(b) agree to give facilities for large-scale repatriation during the middle.of 1946.He also urges that *(c) the Union Government should be in a position to make a public announce-ment that undesirable German elements will be repatriated at a not too distant date.5. In the meantime it has been reported in the press that, as a result of discussions between the Union Government and a delegation from South-WestAfrica, a commission is to be appointed by the Union Government to weed outundesirables, who would be classified as prohibited immigrants and repatriates;also that former German citizens of South-West Africa claiming dual nationality,who were away from the territory at the outbreak of war, will not be permitted to return.[30732]b
6. The United Kingdom High Commissioner in South Africa has reportedthat there is widespread feeling in the Union that all Germans in the territory should be repatriated, but that repatriation of large farmers would raise economic difficulties and also the question of compensation. He comments, further, that theNationalist party in the Union would oppose compulsory repatriation and that,as this party polled some 40 per cent, of the votes at the general election (albeitwithout winning a single seat) the political aspect in the Union cannot be ignored.7. I should mention that the South African Delegation at the San FranciscoConference gave notice of the Union Governments intention to raise later thequestion of terminating the mandate and incorporating South-West Africa inthe Union. The Union Government have not yet taken any further formal step,and their intention need not affect the decision on their present proposal to repatriate Germans..8. The question of the Germans in South-West Africa has given troubleintermittently between the wars, mainly over their nationality (see Annex III),but I understand that all those whom the Union Government now desire to repatriate are regarded by them as enemy nationals and have ceased to possessBritish or South African nationality if they ever had it. In any case, if we agreeto the principle of transfer, we can stipulate that nobody should be transferredwho can establish a claim to British or South African nationality.9. The South African proposal may at first sight be repugnant, and seemunduly hard on settlers who have been established in the mandated territory forupwards of a generation. But it is undeniable that they have intrigued againstthe Union, and the Union Government should have little difficulty in justifyingto world opinion a policy of large-scale repatriation. Having acquiesced, as we did in subscribing to the Potsdam decision (Annex IV), in a policy of transfer from Poland, Czechoslovakia and Hungary, we should be on weak ground in resisting the application of the same policy to the Germans in South and South-West Africa.10. I realise that the military authorities in the Western zones of germany are already confronted with a difficult problem in securing accommodation forthe refugees from Eastern Germany, and I should not wish to support anyproposal which would aggravate their difficulties. But I understand that thenumber liable to transfer under the Potsdam Declaration is of the order of14 millions and that the present influx into the British zone is at the rate of5,000 a week. It could hardly be contended that another 7,000 would make theposition very much worse. The exact dates of transfer and the detailed arrange-ments generally should of course be worked out between the Union authoritiesand the British military authorities concerned. Transfer would be facilitatedif it were to the British zone in the first place, since sea transport could be usedall the way to Hamburg, and arrangements could be made much more easilybetween the South African and British authorities direct, than if the UnitedStates and French (and possibly Soviet) authorities also had to be brought in.11. The Union Government are entitled, under the mandate, to administerSouth-West Africa, as an integral part of the Union, and, if they decide to expelundesirable Germans, we cannot, in the last resort, prevent their taking andannouncing such a decision. We could, if we wished to do so, at the cost of friction with the Union Government, refuse to facilitate the transfer, by with-holding the shipping which is under our control. This would, I think, be unjustified-fiable. On the contrary, the removal of undesirable Germans from South-WestAfrica and the Union, once it has been effected, should not only strengthen thehands of the Union Government against potential hostile intrigue, but wouldalso remove one focus of anti-British feeling; and, if we facilitate their removal,we shall strengthen those in South Africa who support the British connection.12.   I therefore ask my colleagues to authorise me (1) to inform the Union Government that the United Kingdom government agree in principle to (a), (&amp;) and (c) in paragraph 4 above on theunderstanding that (i) (in the words of the Potsdam Declaration) any transfers that takeplace should be effected in an orderly and humane manner;(ii) nobody should be transferred who can establish a claim to british or South African nationality;
(iii) the detailed arrangements should be worked out by the Unionauthorities in consultation with the Minister of War Transport,as to shipping, and the British Military authorities, as toreception and accommodation in Germany.A.Dominions Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1,20th October, 1945.ANNEX I.Extract from Letter from the High Commissioner for the Union ofSouth Africa to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,14th September, 1945.THE position in South-West Africa is that out of a total of nearly 10,000German nationals, the number interned or under control with their dependants is nearly 6,000. In South Africa, according to the figures we have, it was necessaryto intern during the war nearly 1,500 German residents (this figure excludesdependants).In South-West Africa the Germans constitute a homogeneous communitywhich has in the past been powerfully organised in an attempt to form almost aState within a State. If war had broken out in 1938 for instance, there is little doubt that the German community would at that time have been well placed to seize control of the Mandated Territory and it was only afterwards that measures were taken by the Government (the despatch of a special police contingent, &amp;c.)to prevent the execution of the coup which the Germans had been planningSimilarly in the Union, the presence of a fairly substantial German population has for years been a serious embarrassment to the Government. Naturally,numbers of them before the war engaged in espionage and endeavoured to fomentdisaffection between the English and Afrikaans-speaking sections of the popula-tion. Should they remain in the Union their presence will inevitably continueto be a source of friction between the two sections of the population andtherefore a potential danger to the State should circumstances similar to thoseobtaining in 1939 recur. Indeed their treatment is already becoming a subjectof considerable political controversy and it is for this reason that my Governmentare anxious to have the views of the United Kingdom Government on the practicalaspects as distinct from the political aspects of their repatriation.On the political side I appreciate that as the United Kingdom Governmenthave for instance called upon the Czechoslovak Government to stop the repatri-ation of Sudeten Deutsch into an overcrowded and ill-nourished Germany, it wouldbe difficult for them to consent to provide facilities for the repatriation at thisstage of Germans from South Africa. I shall not fail to represent such consider-ations to my Government but before doing so I should like to have a statement on the practical difficulties involved.ANNEX II.Letter from High Commissioner for the Union of South Africa to theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs, 11th October, 1945.My dear Secretary of State,Repatriation of Germans from the Union and South-West Africa.I telegraphed to my Government the views expressed in your letter of the5th October, and also conveyed a clear indication of the political considerations which would make it difficult for the United Kingdom Government (in view,for instance, of the strong protests they have made against deportation of germans from territories under Polish and Czech administration) to provide facilities forthe repatriation of Germans from the Union and South-West Africa.2. My Government have now stated, however, that they cannot agree thatEastern European countries, for example, should have a stronger claim to deportGermans than have countries of the British Commonwealth, simply because the[30732] B 2
former are more vocal in their demands, and sometimes show a tendency tounilateral action.3. My Government cannot view with equanimity the possibility of a futurerecrudescence of the troubles of the immediate pre-war and war period engenderedby the presence in South-West Africa of a strong German pro-Nazi elementrepresenting approximately one-third of the total European population. We haveno desire to repatriate all Germans in South-West Africa, many of whom can nodoubt still be made good citizens, but we must in the interests and safety both ofthe Mandated Territory and of the Union itself, insist upon arrangements beingmade for the deportation of those elements which are inimical to that safety.And what has been said of undesirable elements in South-West Africa applieswith equal force to similar but fewer elements in the Union.4. In view of the considerations stressed above, I should be grateful if you would examine the possibilities of (a) arranging for the repatriation from South Africa during the next fewmonths of a few individuals who may be regarded as particularlyundesirable.(&amp;) agreeing that facilities would be given for the large-scale repatriationdesired by my Government during the summer of 1946.5. In the latter connection I understand the difficulty of giving a specificundertaking at this stage to provide the shipping that would be necessary. Onthe other hand it seems desirable that my Government should be in a position tomake a public announcement that undesirable German elements will be repatriatedat a not too distant date which, for practical reasons, should not I think be later than the summer of 1946.Yours sincerely,G.   HEATON NICHOLLS.ANNEX III.Nationality of Germans in South-West Africa.THE former German colony of German South-West Africa surrendered to south African forces in 1915 and was assigned to the Union of South Africa asa &quot; C &quot;Mandate in 1920. This Mandate permitted the administration of theterritory as an integral part of the Union and it has been so administered.2. In 1921 the Union Government announced their decision to legislate sothat the Germans in South-West Africa would automatically receive british nationality unless they opted to the contrary. This led to considerable discussionwith the Permanent Mandates Commission of the League of Nations, and theCouncil of the League, but eventually, in 1923, the Council adopted a resolution which took note of the Union Governments intention and, in view of the specialcircumstances, raised no objection.3. The question was settled as between the Union and Germany by an exchange of letters between General Smuts and representatives of the GermanGovernment in October 1923 (Treaty Series (19241, No. 27). Under this it wasagreed that &quot; the policy of the Union Government is to accept the Germans ofSouth-West Africa as part of the people, with the same privileges and the sameresponsibilities as the other citizens.&quot; In return the German Government,&quot; recognising that the future of South-West Africa is now bound up with theUnion of South Africa and that it would be a wise policy for the Germannationals in that Territory to throw in their lot with South Africans,&quot; undertook to use their influence to induce their nationals to accept Union citizenship undera general naturalisation law of the Union and not to opt out of such citizenship.Under this agreement, the Union Government agreed upon certain privilegesfor the Germans in South-West Africa, including the free use of the Germanlanguage and financial assistance for a period to German schools. The agree-ment provided that Germans in South-West Africa and their children wouldnot be liable in any circumstances for military service against the Reich for aperiod of 30 years.4. As a result of this agreement the Union in 1924 passed a law (No. 30of 1924) whereby Germans in South-West Africa who did not opt to. retainGerman nationality were to,be deemed to have become naturalised British subjects
and entitled in the Union or South-West Africa to the privileges of Britishsubjects, as well as being subject to their obligations. (This Act was not regarded as conferring British nationality upon the persons concerned outsidethe Union or South-West Africa).5. Until the rise of Hitlerism in Germany it appeared that a fair proportionof the German population had become reconciled to South African rule but,as Hitler&apos;s power and propaganda increased, the majority of the local Germansdeveloped a more exclusive and arrogant demeanour towards all other races.Genuine efforts were made by the Afrikaans population and the local Administra-tion to break down this social and racial exclusiveness, but this policy failed.The Germans insisted on having their own schools throughout the Territory andeven forbade their children to play with non-Germans, Shortly before theoutbreak of war the German Consul at Windhoek organised what was practicallya Gestapo, warning any Germans who showed loyalty to the Administrationthat it would be the worse for their families and relatives in Germany if theydid not swear allegiance to the Nazi cause. In September 1939 the UnionGovernment sent into the Territory police and armed forces, who seized theGerman Consulate and discovered an elaborate organisation of military characterthroughout the German community provided with weapons, either locally made or smuggled into the country. As a result over 1,400 South-West AfricanGermans were interned. In 1942 an Act was passed by the Union Parliament(No. 35 of 1942) cancelling the naturalisation conferred on the Germans by thelegislation described in the previous paragraph.Dominions Office, l$th October, 1945.ANNEX IV.Potsdam Agreement of 2nd August, 1945, on Orderly Transfers of GermanPopulations.THE Conference reached the following agreement on the removal of germans from Poland, Czechoslovakia and Hungary : &apos;The Three Governments, having considered the question in all its aspects,recognise that the transfer to Germany of German populations, or elementsthereof, remaining in Poland, Czechoslovakia, and Hungary will have to beundertaken. They agree that any transfers that take place should be effected in an orderly and humane manner.Since the influx of a large number of Germans into Germany would increasethe burden already resting on the occupying authorities, they consider that theAllied Control Council in Germany should in the first instance examine theproblem with special regard to the question of the equitable distribution of theseGermans among the several zones of occupation. They are accordingly instructingtheir respective representatives on the Control Council to report to their Govern-ments as soon as possible the extent to which such persons have already enteredGermany from Poland, Czechoslovakia and Hungary, and to submit an estimateof the time and rate at which further transfers could be carried out, having regardto the present situation in Germany.The Czechoslovak Government, the Polish Provisional Government and theControl Council in Hungary are at the same time being informed of the above,and are being requested meanwhile to suspend further expulsions pending the examination by the Governments concerned of the report from their representa-tives on the Control Council.


</content>
</cab>
