<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/3/0 images: 274-277</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET. Copy No. 58CP. (45) 242.26th October, 1945.CABINET.ATTITUDE OF GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTS TOWARDSORGANISATIONS MATERIALLY INFLUENCED or controlled BY A POLITICAL  PARTY.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.1. Ministers and Departments are from time to time asked for some kindof support or assistance by organisations which, although ostensibly non-party,are known to be under the influence or control of the Communist Party. Thequestion for decision is whether the policy laid down by the Coalition Govern-ment should be maintained and, if not, what modification in it should be made.2. In 1942 the War Cabinet decided that international organisations that were materially influenced or directed or in practice controlled by a political party or were being run to serve the interests of a political party should not begiven official support (W.M. (42) 72nd Conclusions, Minute 9), and ministers were asked to consult the Home Secretary when any occasion arose which seemed likely to come within this decision. The Cabinet decision referred in terms toyouth organisations, but the principle laid down has been applied to other organisations which have come within the terms of the decision. These other organisations have included the National Council for British Soviet Unity,which is in practice controlled by the Communist Party.3. The only organisations which have in fact come within the terms ofthe Cabinet decision have been those influenced or controlled by the Communists.It is the policy of the Communist Party to penetrate existing organisations orto create new ones in such a way that while the organisation appears to be arespectable non-party body they usually have an impressive list of patronsdrawn from all parties the actual control is in the hands of a few under-coverCommunists or Communist sympathisers in key positions in the secretariat.These bodies are ostensibly devoted to some popular cause a number of them were formed in 1941 and 1942 to exploit the current admiration and symapathy for Russia-but they are intended, in fact, to act as &quot;transmission belts&quot; to carryCommunist propaganda to people with whom the Communist Party is not normally in touch but who can be reached by apparently non-party organisations.These bodies not merely enable the Party to reach further with its propagandathan it could do openly, but also enable it to mobilise support for its demands on certain points among people who would not support Communist policy if they recognised it as such.4. The success of these satellite organisations depends to a large extent ontheir appearance of respectability and their prestige with the public. Both areenhanced by anything which suggests official support, such as the presence ofMinisters at the meetings of the organisations. The presence of a Minister at ameeting not merely tends to increase an organisation^ influence, but lends tothe speeches and resolutions some of which express the Communist Party line -the appearance of official approval. The satellite organisations accordingly makea practice of inviting Ministers to speak at or send messages to their principalfunctions. They also ask from time to time for other forms of assistance whichmay appear to imply Government support, e.g.t for Ministry of Informationspeakers at public meetings, for the help of that Ministry in organisingexhibitions, or for grants of public money, for example, to youth organisations.[30741]
Home Office, S.W. 1,26th October, 19455. It is for consideration whether the policy laid down by the coalition government is applicable in present circumstances. The general ground onwhich it was felt undesirable to do anything which might assist the CommunistParty to extend its influence and particularly its insidious under-cover influencewas that, although after the German attack on the Soviet Union the. Partysupported the Coalition and did everything possible to give itself the appearance of a constitutional party, there was reason to believe that its leaders.,had notabandoned the long-term policy of establishing a Communist regime by violentrevolution. This is still the case and as long as there remain men in influentialpositions in the Communist Party whose aim is violent revolution I think it wouldbe wrong for the Government to assist the Party&apos;s activities. The position has changed to some extent since 1942, however, in that the satellite organisations which were then seeking to establish themselves among the public have by nowearned such reputation as they are ever likely to en j oy, and the form of assistance which merely tends to increase their prestige is no longer of such value to them.J. C. E.



</content>
</cab>
