<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/16 images: 182-189</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet. November 1939.10 ^IBllyJSSI^f.SR.. MxOSS, AE3B ,&amp;Etf.is requested that -$pedal care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 82 (80).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, November 14, 1939, at 11 - 30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Air Chief Marshal, Sir Cyril X.. N.Newall, Chief -of the- Air-Staff. :Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval/Staff. -General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.:;SM:l$Bt^^Major-General H. L. Ismay.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.[20329]
WAR CABINET-- 8SContents.No. Subject. Page.1     The Air Situation     ...      ...      ... - 1112     The Naval Situation ...      ............     ... Ill3     The Military Situation       ......      ...      ...... Ill4     The German Air Force       ............     ... 112Evidence as to morale.5     The Netherlands and Belgium       ......      ...... 112Imports of oil and other raw materials.6     Air Policy      ..................      ... 113
The Air Situation. (Previous Reference W.M. (39) 81st Conclusions, Minute 1.)

1. The Secretary of State for Air informed the War Cabinet that the principal and ? on the previous day had been a German raid on three of our cruisers and the R.A.F. Depot Ship Manila, stationed in the Shetlands. No damage had been done, and no casualties had been inflicted on the enemy. There had been slight air activity over the North Sea.

One interception had been made by our Fighters, as a result of which it was thought that a German flying-boat had been disabled East of Felixstowe.

Coastal Command activities included an attack, the previous morning, on a submarine 65 miles North-east of Scapa. Two bombs were dropped, but no results were seen.

The War. Cabinet took note of the above statement.

The Naval Situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 81st Conclusions, Minute 2.)

2. The First Lord of the Admiralty informed the War Cabinet of the present situation as regards the Fleet. H.M.S. Newcastle had returned with 57 of the crew of the German S.S. Parana  which had been scuttled by her crew to avoid capture.

As previously mentioned by the Secretary of State for Air, the Northern Patrol Cruisers had been attacked in the Shetlands by one aircraft, which had dropped bombs, without obtaining any hits.

A U-boat had laid a minefield opposite the entrance to the Thames Estuary. As a result, H.M.S. Adventure had suffered extensive damage underneath. There were twelve dead, an unknown number of missing and 37 injured cases. As reported the previous day, H.M.S., Blanche had been sunk in the same minefield with1 dead and 6 missing. S.S. Ponzano, and S.S.Matra (8,000 tons) of the Brocklebank Line, had also both struck mines in the same area. There was reason to believe that this serious damage had been inflicted by a type of magnetic mine, which was likely to prove a great vexation.

The Chief of Naval Staff said that experiments had been carried out with a magnetic sweep which had yielded promising results at the time, but which could not, as yet, be regarded as entirely satisfactory. Other experiments were in hand, but we were handicapped by not having so far been able to secure one of these magnetic mines.

Continuing, the First Lord of the Admiralty said that the trawler Cresswell had been sunk by U-41, 18 miles off the Western Hebrides. The crew had been taken on board the submarine and had been transferred later to another trawler. The U-boat crew had stated that they had sunk a 10,000-ton tanker on the 12th November, but of this we had no confirmation.

The S.S. Sirdhana (8,000 tons) had struck a British mine just outside Singapore, with some casualties amongst the Asiatic passengers. The Secretary of State for War mentioned that all the military personnel on board had been saved.

S.S. Dearpool, previously reported ashore off the Humber, was still there despite the efforts to refloat her.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.

The Military Situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 8ist vicinity Conclusions, Minute 8.)

3. The Secretary of State for War informed the War Cabinet that there had been no change either, in the number or the disposition of the German Divisions on the Western Front.

There had been considerable German wireless activity in the vicinity of the Dutch frontier, but this was considered to be bogus and intended to deceive.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.


Evidence as-lbmorale.(previous reference:W.M, (89) 81stConclusions,Minute 6.)Ailjjjgjfljj^fj^     : 4^-Mhe SecretaryIfifteen to twenty German, (aircjiaf t at Soesterbergj,1 i&amp;id-l toflown there by deserters. V   &apos;, &quot;    ;The Secretary of State for Foreign Affafafe said that hed,mentioned the matter to the Dutch Minister On the previous day\The latter thought this might be a distorted verkioh of the presenceof three of four German aircraft which had beeh forced to land in holland; but he would make enquiries.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.ali-3 KFoSSiQEfesifisw&amp; Mgtam.Imports of oiland other rawmaterials.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 76thConclusions,Minute 8.)5. The Minister without Portfolio said that the Ministry ofEconomic Warfare had raised a question which required immediate decision by the War Cabinet. When it had seemed that an invasion of the Low Countries by Germany might be imminent; it had beehdecided, as a temporary measure, to &quot;slow down the supplies of oiland other raw materials to Holland and Belgium. The Dutch and belgians were now asking for the release of certain ships, includingnine oil tankers seven vessels, carrying 74,000 tons, being destined for Holland, and two, carrying 12,000 tons, for Belgium. against their release it might be said that neither Belgium nor Holland wasin immediate need of this oil their present reserves being respec-tively three months&apos; and six months&apos; supply. Moreover, we had reason to be extremely dissatisfied with the guarantees given by theNetherlands Government, which they had not the administrativemeans to enforce properly. Nevertheless, the fact remained thatthese ships would have been allowed to proceed had it not been forthe recent alarm, and it would therefore be difficult to justify their continued retention now that the cause for this appeared to bepassing.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the WarCabinet would be seeing the record of a conversation which he had had on the previous evening with the Netherlands Minister, whoseinformation was that the situation in Holland was much less tense.He had been left with the impression that the Netherlands minister was still anxious, but did not regard a German invasion asimminent, and that, in any case, the danger for the next few daysseemed to have lessened.. He therefore did not feel that we shouldbe justified in continuing to withhold these vessels on the plea thatthey might fall into German hands.The^ First Lord of the Admiralty was inclined to favour afurther delay, on the ground that we were dissatisfied with theDutch guarantees.The Minister Without Portfolio said that in any event four outof -the nine vessels would continue? to be delayed, as their paperswere not in order. Lord Cadman, moreover, had emphasised theneed for allowing these to proceed and discharge owing to theshortage of tanker capacity. .... hThe Minister for Co-ordination of Defence was in favour of-allowing. the vessels, whose, papers were in crier, m. prcossa.- -The - War&apos;-Cabinet agreed:-(il) that ocfc?.ca Boald te taken.
mdmr^^iom ^^Mm^mS^m^ WarCabinet, on the. 9th November,, to -slow down supplies-. of;oil and other maw: materials.to Holland and,Belgiumfor the next few days. -6.  The War Cabinet had before them the following Papers:-A Report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee making recommendations on the policy which should govern our air action in the event of a German invasion of Belgium, or of holland; but in the latter case only if the Belgians intervenedand asked for our assistance (Paper W.P. (39) 118).A Report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee on the policywhich should govern our air action in the event of a german invasion of Holland, if Belgium should not intervene or call for assistance (Paper W.P. (39) 122).The War Cabinet was also given an oral account of thediscussion which had taken place the previous evening at a meetingof the Military Co-ordination Committee, at Which various alternative courses of action by the Royal Air Force had been fullyexamined.The ensuing discussion is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet :-(1) Took note of the recommendations of the Chiefs of staff committee, contained in their two Reports, but agreedthat it was not possible to authorise in advance of theevent any specific policy for the employment of the mainAir Striking Force, and that the decision must be takenby the War Cabinet, in the light of the facts existingat the time.(2) Agreed that the considerations set out in these two Reports,together with the judgment formed upon them by theWar Cabinet, should be explained to the FrenchGovernment at an early meeting of the Supreme WarCouncil, to be held, if possible, in London.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to instruct His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Paris to put thisproposal to the French Government.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,November 14, 1939.(previous reference:W.M. (89) 81stConclusions,Minute 10.)




</content>
</cab>
