<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/36/17 images: 188-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1943.SECRET.W.M. (43)149th Conclusions.Copy No.WAR CABINET 149 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers-Room, House of Commons, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 2nd November, 1943. at12 15 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Item 3).The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma(Item 3).The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,.Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Item 3).The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of State.Mr. Duncan Sandys, M.P., joint parliamentary Secretary, Ministryof Supply (Items 1-2).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.minute no.1Contents.Subject.German Long-Range RocketMoscow Conference       ........Shipping   ....Indian grain requirements.Page134134134[26369-2]
German Long- 1.   The War Cabinet considered whether it would be desirableRange Rocket, to give information to Parliament in Secret Session regarding the(Previous enquiries made as to the reports of a German long-range rocket.Reference: Th   w     Cabinet-W.M. (43) 132ndConclusions, Decided that the balance of advantage lay against this minute 3.) course.                                                              jMoscowConference.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 148thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Prime Minister drew the attention of the War Cabinetto the opening sentence of the declaration of the four nations on general security, which ran as follows : &quot; The Governments of the United States, the UnitedKingdom, the U.S.S.E. and China: United in their determination, in accordance with the declaration by theUnited Nations of the 1st January, 1942, and subsequentdeclarations, to continue hostilities against those axis power with which they respectively are at war until such powers have laid down their arms on the basis of. unconditional surrender;&quot;The Prime Minister thought that the words in italics were of great significance.Further particulars in regard to one matter arising from the moscow Conference are recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.Shipping.Indian GrainRequirements.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 131stConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for India (W.P. (43) 493) regarding an offer ofthe Canadian Government to make available to India, as a free gift,up to 100,000 tons of wheat, if arrangements could be made to shipthis from ports in Western Canada.The Secretary of State for India said that he had discussed this matter with the High Commissioner for Canada. He under-stood that the Canadian Government were anxious to publish their offer at once, even though it might not be possible to arrange for more than a small proportion of the wheat to be shipped in thenear future. He himself believed that an announcement of this offer would have a favourable effect on public opinion in India; and, asit seemed likely that India would be short of food for some considerable time, there would probably be later opportunities to transport to India the balance which could not be shipped in thenear future.&apos;The Minister of War Transport pointed out that, from thepoint of view of shipping, it would be most uneconomical to drawfrom Canada food grains for India. The voyage-time was over two months, as compared with a voyage of three to four weeks from australia, where there was surplus wheat available. Moreover,shipping could be worked into position to lift wheat from Australiamuch more easily than from Canada; and it was clear that, if weattempted to lift any substantial proportion of this wheat from canada, we should have to ask the Americans for further shippingassistance.In discussion it was suggested that, if the Canadian offer were accepted, additional wheat might be sent to India from Australiaand a corresponding amount of the Canadian wheat brought to thiscountry. It was recognised that it would be necessary to consult theAustralian Government before any such arrangement was made. Itwas pointed out, however, that, even under such an arrangement as this, no effective addition could be made to Indian supplies of wheatwithout an additional drain on Anglo-American shipping resources.The Prime Minister said that in present circumstances it wouldbe unjustifiable to impose any additional strain on our shipping
Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,2nd November, 1943.resources (especially if that involved seeking further shippingassistance from the Americans) for the sake of the whollyuneconomic project of shipping wheat from Canada to India. Hewould be prepared to send a personal message to the Prime Ministerof Canada explaining our attitude on this matter and urging himnot to publish the offer made by the Canadian Government.The War Cabinet-(1) Endorsed the view expressed by the Prime Minister and invited him to send a personal message to the PrimeMinister of Canada on the lines indicated above. TheMinister of War Transport undertook to furnish a draft which might serve as a basis for the Prime Ministersmessage.(2) Took note that the Secretary of State for India would bring before the War Cabinet, at an early meeting, the questionof sending further supplies of food grains to India,possibly from Australia.

HOST secret no CIRCULATION,v/,ivu ( 45) 149th conclusions()NS ,-. MINUTEIIG onf i de nt i a!1 RRecord(2nd November, 1943- 6.0 p.m.)THE PRIME MINISTER said that after the Meeting held the previous night, he had further considered the questionwhether it was desirable to inform the House of Commons, in secret Session,  of the chain of events connected with theLong Range Rocket.     While he had not changed his view asto our attitude towards the risk involved, he had changedhis mind as to the desirability of informing parliament in Secret Session.      If Parliament were informed, theywould ask what action they were called upon to take.    Therewas in fact no action which the Government required from parliament,     Moreover, Parliament might ask why thissecret had been communicated to them when the Government hadnot disclosed various other perils,  e.g.  that at one timeseven of our battleships had been undergoing repairs, orthe degree of danger with which we had been faced at oneperiod of the U-boat war,A further point was that Members would begin to wonderwhether they should inform their wives or families, orwhether they were entitled to use this information tosuggest that they should move out of London.     They might even come to feel that by being given this information,but not being able to act on it,  they were being put ina false position.     On the whole he thought that the best plan was not to inform the House- of Commons.     If the riskmaterialised,  the House could be told that the question of informing them had been very carefully Considered,  and thatthe Government had been on the point of informing the Housebut had finally decided against this course,The Prime Minister added that the Paymaster-Generalfelt that, since he (the Prime Minister) acted in a numberof scientific matters on his advice,  it should be placed on record that he remained sceptical of the risk involved.THE PRIME MINISTER then said that this decision wouldnot affect the action which we had already decided upon inthe operational field;    full reconnaissance would continue tobe carried out,  together with the attacks on certain object-ives which had already been decided upon.     As regardsproductive establishments in this country, the Prime minister thought that if in a particular case all our capacity waslocated in one centre in the London area,  it would bedesirable that part of it should be moved.     Apart from suchspecial cases,  however, he thought that there should be no interference with the productive capacity.THE MINISTER OP AIRCRAFT PRODUCTION mentioned thecase of Platinum, in regard to which we depended on onesingle centre in the London area.     He added that SO percent,  of our radio capacity was in the London area,  and thatit was proposed to deal with this situation by moving the radio stores out of London.      This had already been con-templated on other grounds.The Ministers expresthe Prime Minister&apos;ssed general agreement withview, which was: endorsed.Offices of the vTar Cabinet, S.W.I.




</content>
</cab>
