<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/11/46 images: 450-465</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.M OS rS E 0&quot;R*E T.V/.P. (40) 566. COPY NO,        -tf1QTH SEPTEMBER,  1940.TELEGRAMS EXCHANGED WITH HISMAJESTY&apos;S MINISTER IN STOCKHOLM.Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The annexed exchange of telegrams with HisMajesty&apos;s Minister in Stockholm is circulated for theinformation of the War Cabinet, together with a draft reply to telegram No.  1016.It will be seen that the offer reaching usthrough this source is essentially the same as thatmade to us recently through the King of Sweden, and thedraft reply follows the same line that we adopted onthat occasion.(initialled)    H.Foreign Office.10TH SEPTEMBER,  1940.

1*     Your telegram No. 1,016, you should returna reply to the intermediary as follows .     His Majesty&apos;s Government did not enter this war for selfish aims, hut for large and general purposesaffecting the freedom and independence of many states in Europe.     Their position was defined at length towardsGerman peace offers in the maturely--considered statement made hy Mr. Chamberlain, then Prime Minister, in the Houseof Commons on october  .12, 1959.     Nothing that has happened since then has led His Majesty&apos;s Government torecede in any way from the principles and resolves whichwere then so clearly set forth.   On the contrary, theintention of all the peoples of the British Empire to prosecute the war has &quot;been strengthened by the manyhorrible crimes committed hy the ruleirs of Nazi Germanyagainst the smaller States on her borders, and by theindiscriminate bombing of London without the slightestrelation to military objectives.     His Majesty&apos;sGovernment do not wish to prolong the war for a daylonger than is necessary.     It therefore lies with theGerman Government to make proposals by which the wrongsthat Germany has inflicted upon other nations may beredressed/

redressed^    Moreover, It would be necessary,, before any such proposals could be considered, that effectiveguarantees by deeds not words should be forthcoming from Germany which would ensure in a general peace therestoration of freedom to France, and to the othercountries which have been deprived of it, as well asthe security of Great Britain and the British Empire0

(Stockholm) a9th September, 1940o9th September^ 1940*10th September, 1940.imniiimmmmIMMEDIATE.Following for Sir A, Cadogan,PERSONAL AMD SECRET,Your telegram No. 726cI duly informed the intermediary on 7th Septemberthat I would not see Yfeissauer end that in any case the interview seemed to me useless in view of the publicly.&quot;declared attitude of his Majesty5s Government.A few hours later the intermediary in whosetrustworthiness and disinterested [grp. undec.] I have full confidence&apos; returned in a state of excitement and said he was convinced that the matter was of the first importance and that Weissauer was acting at the instigation of Hitlerin person.     Only two men in Germany knew of his mission.Following were the main points of the proposal:I.     World to be divided into two economic spheres,one continental, organized by Germany,  the other maritimeand colonial organized by the British Empire and2.     Political independence of European countriesnow occupied by Germany to be restored Including &quot;a P0lishState&quot; but excluding Czechoslovakia^,     Economic divisionof Europe must however be brought to an endT3.     British Empire to retain all ccolonies and suchmandates as are needed for its political ifuid militaryinterests.     Germany possibly to receive some compensationelsewhere.4.     Questions concerning the Mediterranean, egypt and French, Belgian and Dutch colonies to biS open to discussion,,This was the &quot;last chance&quot; and the alternative to peace was the continuance of the war on an intensifiedscale; special mention was made here of the loass toGreat Britain of Egypt, the Middle East and ultimately &quot;India.I gave the intermediary no encouragement whatsoeverto believe that I should have any message for hin&amp; buthe has since twice returnee to the charge obviousJ-yat Weissauerls instigation and informed me that Weissauerhas/Decypher.     Mr. Mallet:D*     7*50 p.m.Rw     1*40 a.m*No. 1016,

2ohas decided to prolong his stay here until 12th Septemberas he is desperately anxious not to return empty-handed..He would stay here longer if it were any use.     Any talks,he said, could continue for the present through a neutralpersonage.I have reported all this more fully in personal letters to you and I have no reason to expect that the proposals are of interest to His Majesty&apos;s Government.     At thesame time since the date of departure of the hag is uncertain,   I have ventured to telegraph this summary incase you may wish me to make a further move before Weissauerleaves.     His final remark to the intermediary was thatthe absence of any message from ;r: would be taken in Berlinas a definite refusal.

(C...9598/G)SPEGIi\L DISTRIBUTION AND WAR CABINET.To:     SWEDEN.Cypher telegram to Mr. Mallet, (Stockholm)eForeign Office.     6th September, 1940o     7o00 p.m.No, 726 eoooooooooMOST IMMEDIATE.MOST SECRET.Your telegram No. 1011oYou should not yourself meet Weissauer, in view ofobvious danger of misconstruction,,Moreover it would be quite useless for you to do so,as you oould not enter into discussion and could onlyreceive message from him, which it is always open to.himto pass to you through President of High Court or anyother channel.     Attitude of His Majesty&quot;&apos;s Government hasbeen made quite plain in reply to King of Sweden - see my telegram No* 660 - in which we emphasised necessity of words being effectively guaranteed by deeds0

SPECIAL DISTRIBUTION AND WAR CABINgr ^From:   SWISH0Decypher,       Mr,&apos;Mallet,   (Stockholm),,5th September, 1940.D.      8o05 poffio 5th September, 1940,Ro     12,20 army 6th September, 1940.No. 1011,ggggggggggMOST IMMEDIATE.Most Secret.President of High Court of Appeal of Sweden came to see meto-day. He said he was not a politician and hesitated to makefollowing proposal.Dr. Ludvig Weissauer, a Berlin barrister about 40 years oldintroduced to him on a previous visit to Stockholm last month by the Finnish Minister at Berlin as a man with very importantconnexions, had just been to ask him to arrange for me to meet him very secretly in order to have a purely unofficial and non-committal talk on the subject of peace-..    Weissauer isunderstood to be a direct secret emissary of Hitler and as suchvisited Finland last month and saw the Prime Minister and field marshal.    He is believed also to have been employed in thepast on missions to China and the United States0    He told the judge that he wished conversations,, if they took place, to be known to nobody but His majesty s Government and Hitler to whom he intimated that he would report direct.,    Talks could&apos;begin atonce and proceed for so long as seemed useful or could cease afterthe first meeting,,    Judge might be present in order to avoid any suggestion oi trickery0    Weissauer realised that peace mightnox yet be attainable &quot;but nevertheless felt that conversationwould be useful *    He felt that the attempt at mediation by Kingsand Pope were too conspicuous a form of approach to offer hope ofresult.The.Judge tells me [group un.de] personally in Finland andhis sentiments on the subject of Scandinavia had made a favourableimpression in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs here.     The swedish government do not however know about his present approach to me,I told the Judge that I could see no useful purpose in the suggested meeting in view of the express views of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment on continuing the war. He begged me not to refuseat least to hear what Weissauer had to say and pointed out that my refusal to meet him would certainly be reported to Hitler.Finally I asked for time to reflect before deciding0 He asked me to decide at the latest by Saturday mcrningoPlease telegraph most immediately whether I may meet Weissauer.I should of course say nothing to encourage him but it might be ofInterest to listens




</content>
</cab>
