<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/54/38 images: 320-325</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1944.The circulation of this paper has tojeen strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of..........rTx^ .^r*^............................TOP secret copy No.W.P. (44) 488.1st September, 1944.WAR CABINET.MAN-POWER REQUIREMENTS FOR THE SERVICES-JULY TO DECEMBER 1944.Note by the Minister of Labour and National Service.1. On the 12th July the War Cabinet approved intakes into each of thethree Services and transfers between Services during July and August proposedby the Chancellor of the Exchequer, and also provisional allocations for all three services combined for September to December (WP. (44) 375 and W.M. (44)90th Conclusions).Jidy and Aiigust.2.   The allocations and achievements in July and August were as follows : Service.Allocation.Achievement.Surplus (4-)Deficit (-)Men.Royal NavyArmy ...R.A.F....W.R.N.S.A.T.S. ...W.A.A.F.New IntakeTransfers of serving personnel to ArmyNew IntakeCall-up from R.A F. DeferredService ListTransfers from Navy and R.A.F.Total       ...       ...   -   ...New IntakeTransfers to Army4-   5,391 -  6,200	4-   5,391 -   6,430	4-     2304- 32,329 4-   6,000 4- 11,200	4- 38,758 4-   3,619 4- 11,660	4-   6,429 -   2,381 4-     4604- 49.529	4- 54,037	4-   4,5084-   6,230 &apos;   -   5,000	4-   6,230 -  5,230	4-     230New IntakeNew IntakeNew IntakeTotalWomen.4- 1,6994- 4,3074- 1,4244-   7,4304- 1,5784- 2,5174-   2,015- 121- 1,7904-     5914-   6,110-   1,320Six Months July to December.3.   The total call-up for the second half of 1944 for all three Services was fixed at 123,000 men and 17,500 women (including the Women&apos;s Nursing Services).These numbers were approved after consideration of the maximum number that[28131]
could be made available under existing arrangements. It does not now look asif it will be possible to produce more than 15,500 women for all the Women&apos;services, including nursing. The War Cabinet have already approved an intake of 9,700 men and women into the R.A.F. and W.A.A.F. in the second half ofthe year (8.200 men and 1,500 women). The following Table shows the demandsnow put forward, the allocations already approved, the intakes achieved in july and August, and the balances that can be made available in September toDecember.  Inter-Service transfers have been excluded from the figures : 	Demands for half-year.	Allocation already approved.	Intakes July and August.	Balances that can be made available in Sept-Dec.Royal Navy ... Army R.A.F.        ...       ...... Total    ......... W.R.N.S.......... A.T.S.......... W.A.A.F......... Nursing   Services   and .V.A.D. Total   ...      ......	36,391 117,31 7 8,200	Men. \   114,800 i 8,200	,7 r;fto    f       5,391 4&apos;&apos;&apos;68  (   42,377 6,230	1      67,032 1,970	161,968 5,078 18,517 1,500 2,347	123.000 Women. j     15,000 1,500 1,000	53,998 4 095  !     1,578 -i,uyo I     2,517 2,015 1,018	69,002 J        7,390 Nil 982	27,442	17,500	7,128	8,3724. It will be seen that the question to be considered for the periodSeptember to December is the allocation of 67.032 men and 7,390 women betiveenthe Navy and the Army. 6,400 of the men are due to be found for the Army fromthe R.A.F. Deferred Service List, as only 3,600 were obtained from that sourcein July and August out of the 10.000 already)- approved by the War Cabinet(W.P. (44) 375. paragraph 12 (a), and W.M. (44) 90th Conclusions). This leavesjust over 60.000 men available from other sources for the Navy and the Army.5. As regards the Women&apos;s Nursing Services, it will be possible to find1.000 more than the number allocated for the second half-year, and this should enable the intake of Nursing Officers and V.A.D. into the Army to be raised to1,773 for the half-year, on the assumption that further intakes into the nursing services of the Navy and R.A.F., which for July and August amounted to 227.are not required.Summary of Man-power  Budget for 1944.6.   The man-power budget for 1944 may be summarised as follows :  	Intakes and net Increases.	Supply (cuts).Services intakes from civilian sources Number to be drawn from the non-industrial popula-tion Number to be drawn from industry Estimated decline in industrial populaiion Civil Defence        ...       ...      .... Industry  Group I  ... Group II ... Group III Totals         ...       ...............	341,620 41,020 300,000 175,000 -4-    13,000 -1-    75,000 4-   31,000	- 50,000 - 418,000 - 95,000	594,000	503,000
There is thus a deficiency of 31,000 even assuming that the full cut of 50,000in Civil Defence is achieved by the end of the year.The figure for intakes into the Services included in the foregoing statement is made up of the actual intakes in the first half of the year, together with the allocations already approved for the second half, with the addition of 1,000 forWomen&apos;s Nursing Services.The inclusion of a net increase of 13,000 in Group I (munitions industries)is on account of the increases that have already occurred in the section working for non-Supply Government Departments, export and home market. figures in Groups II and III are on the basis of the latest proposals for these industries.E. B.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,1st September, 1944.




</content>
</cab>
