<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/49/0 images: 18-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
No. /ALLIED MARITIME TRANSPORT COUNCIL.REPORT OF ACTION TAKEN MARCH 15TH TO APRIL 15TH 1918.I have the honour to submit to the Council the following report as to action taken since the last meeting by the permanent organisation in execution of the Council&apos;s decisions and in pursuance of their general duty of assisting in the allocation and the most advantageous use of Allied tonnage by co-operative action, together with a further note as to other recent events and action which affect the work of the Council.This report is merely a statement of facts designed primarily to show the way in which the decisions of the Council at the last Meeting have in fact been carried out.Separate Memoranda are being produced with regard to matters requiring consideration and decision by the Council at its next Meetings.J. A. SALTER.Secretary of the Council.(1) The Supply of Coal to Italy and Prance.The Council decided that 600,000 tons were to be sent to Italy during the month, March 15th-April 15th, 150,000 tons being British coal by long searonte, 100,000 tons British coal via Blaye and 350,000 tons French coal. 270,000 tons of the above quantities were to go by rail to Italy and 180,000 by rail to South France and thence by sea. An amount of British coal equivalent to what France sent to Italy in the month was (with due allowance for quality) to be shipped in replacement in about six weeks from March 15th.The execution of the above plan was seriously interfered with by the German offensive, which had the following two results : (a) The recall of Allied troops from Italy interfered with the passage of French coal. This was originally estimated at 2,000-2,500 tons a day reduction for about a fortnight. This in itself would have reduced the 350,000 tons to about 310,000 tons. It was decided, however, and as the event proved rightly, to provide for the supply of French coal falling considerably below this figure. 100,000 tons of British coal destined for Gibraltar and the Mediterranean were consequently diverted to Italy, British and French Atlantic liners, &amp;c, being sent to Gibraltar in replacement.(6) The advance of the Germans to within short distance of the Amiens-Montdidier line and the use of that line for the movement of Allied troops very seriously reduced the railage of coal from the Bruay Mines to Paris and other places south of Amiens. The situation so resulting has been closely examined (see separate memorandum).Coal to Italy and Replacement Coal to France.Plan. Execution.1. 150,000 tons British coal by long sea-route from Shipped in  Tons.United Kingdom.   (March 15-April 15.) British ships - 210,251Italian ships -  43,489*2. 100,000 tons British coal via Blaye       -      -      - Quantity sent - 135,120*3. 350,000 tons French coal.   (March 15-April 15)  - ,, 229,853Total - 618,713o   (33) as 5212   pk 1 &amp; 3   150   4/18   e&amp;s a
2Plan.Execution.4. 350,000 tons of British coal (to be shipped March 15-April 30). Ad-justments so far as the French coal sent from March 15 April 15 was less or more than 350,000, and as the quality differed from that of the British coal.*5. Of the 450,000 tons in 2 and 3 above, 270,000 was to go by rail all the way, 180,000 was to go by short sea-route from Marseilles or other S. French ports.The amount shipped in small British vessels, requisitioned and added to the French Coal Se rvice, was 213,544 tons up to 15th April. A further quantity of 85,000 tons has been arranged for and should be shipped by the end of April. In addition to this total quantity of about 300,000 tons, a large quantity of additional coal has been carried to France in British vessels directed into the French coal trade from various sources, including the French general cargo trade. It is not possible at present to state exactly the amount of additional coal so carried, but these vessels- should operate as a substantial help towards meeting the further problem resulting from the German offensive.262,688 tons sent by rail, 102,285 tons sent by short sea-routes.* The figures given under heads 2, 3, and 5 above, represent the amounts of British aud French coal sent by rail or by the short searroutes. from France to Italy during the mouth to April: 15th, as shown by daily reports, sent from Paris to London. It is understood that these figures have yet to be agreed by the Franco-Italian Committee in Paris, and though approximately correct must be for the moment regarded as provisional.The net result was that there was shipped and consigned to Italy during the month March 15-April 15, 618,713 tons of coal, 388,860 tons being British coal and 229,853 tons being French coal, as compared with the plan of 600,000 tons, of which 250,000 tons were to have been British and 350,000 tons French.The execution of the above plan was approved by the Council conditionally upon American Dutch tonnage, being provided to compensate for loss, of Atlantic imports. It did not prove possible to obtain this tonnage, but it was decided to proceed with the general plan (with the modifications indicated above), notwithstanding the loss of this assistance.The Committee 9$ representatives of the Italian Government, of the French Ministry of Public Works, and of the French Ministry of Munitions, which M. Loucheur was asked by the Council to establish, has. now been set up in Paris, and consists of the following representatives : -Lieut. Lazzerim -      -      -   Mission Militaire, Italienne. -    M. Ulrich - Chief Service ExecutionTechnique Transports voieferree.Capitaine Barrillon   -      -   Service Central Exploitation ports Maritime. Capitaine Bletry       -      -   Chief Service Central et Combustibles au MinistereArmement.Lieut. Oudot (Secretary)    -   4,eme Bureau, Etat-Major.Communications have been made to the Swiss Government regarding the use of the Simplon route, but it has not yet been found possible to make arrangements for the use of this route into Italy.(2) Other Action and Events.(a) Development of Executive Machinery and Permanent Staff.The co-ordination of the several national divisions has been effected by the appointment of a number of committees.   Details, as to the arrangements are given in
Appendix I. It is Loped that the staffs of the different divisions will be housed together in Lancaster House. in May. In the. meanti me the arrangements to.co-ordinate action have been working satisfactorily, though .subject tto the inconvenience of the several divisions being situated in different parts of London. .(b) Consideration of Provisional Balance Sheet.Several discussions have taken place as to the way in which the deficit of ten million tons of imports, shown in the balance sheet, could be met. .-It Jias not been possible to produce a scheme covering this deficit for two reasons :-(i) The machinery for obtaining allied criticism of &quot;the different classes of-importsthrough, the Executive is not yet complete :(see separate ^memorandum), and the different national requirements need more prolonged examination than has so far been practicable.(ii) It has not been possible to bring the American tonnage requirements, bothforimports and the American military supply programme, under review,and the American Government has now announced that plans must be made on the assumption that no further assistance will be available from the tonnage under American control for imports into Allied countries this year. It has not been possible to make a scheme providing for the whole deficit to be borne by the three European Allies, in view of the extremely drastic character of the measures which would be required and the fact that no material is at present available for the close comparison of the European and the American situations. The resulting position is set out more fully in a separate memorandum. In the meantime it may be remarked that the deficit, as previously shown, has been relieved &quot;by the acquisition of Dutch tonnage and by a fall in the submarine losses, while, on the other hand, the results of the German offensive, which cannot at present be measured, will affect the deficit in the opposite direction.(c) Arrangements have been made for six Italian fast passenger liners of small cargo-carrying capacity, which were formerly bringing footstuffs from the United States to Genoa, to be transferred for service between America and France for the conveyance of American troops, compensation being given to Italy by the allocation of extra British tonnage for the conveyance of food cargoes. This has resulted in a substantial economy of tonnage, and has also the further advantage of putting an end to the heavy calls upon bunker stocks at Gibraltar made by the vessels in question, which being fast passenger vessels have consumed coal altogether out of proportion to their caig^carrying -capacity.Steps are being taken to discontinue the arrangement under which French ships in the Eastern Mediterranean have been coaled by means of coal conveyed to Bizerta mainly in British vessels, and then transhipped into smaller French vessels for conveyance to Fleet Bases at Milo, Salonica, &amp;c, this transhipment being a source of serious delay. It is proposed to arrange to send the coal direct from the United Kingdom to the Fleet, and by this means and by the use of hulks at the Fleet Bases (to obviate the detention of vessels there) a -considerable saving of tonnage will, it. is anticipated, be effected. Mr. Trinder was asked to visit Paris, on behalf of the Tonnage Committee, and reports that there is a good prospect of the scheme being put into operation.(e) Arrangements have been made for Great Britain to put into the nitrate trade a number of neutral vessels not available in the war zone, with some British vessels unsuitable for Atlantic work. As the nitrate carried in these vessels would, if brought to Europe, have to be transhipped at a North American port, negotiations are proceeding with the American Government for the nitrate in question to be supplied for American consumption in exchange for the equivalent amount of American tonnage for the carriage of nitrate direct from Chile to Europe.(/) Negotiations have been In progress for the use of a number of large French passenger vessels for trooping purposes. The necessity for at once carrying a large number of men from North Africa has delayed this arrangement being put into force, but it is hoped that a number of the vessels in question will be availablefor American trooping purposes m May.,($.) The American Shipping Board have reported that owing to the intended restriction of the United States Imports from South America, it would be possible for
them to allot certain additional vessels on Trans-Atlantic service, if cerrain arrauge-nients conld be made -with regard to the coal supply of Brazil, and the Argentine, and the employment of the Franco-Brazilian tonnage in the following route United Kingdom-Brazil-U.S.A.-France. A plan to use allied tonnage for this purpose is now being worked out, and it is hoped to give effect to it as the Brazilian tonnage becomes available.. (7?,) In addition a number of individual arrangements, e.g., exchanges involving the use of single ships or the supply by one ally to another as commodities at a particular port, have also been effected.The above arrangements have for the most part been carried out, either through the Tonnage Committee or through the officials of the different shipping organisations in London. . . ,(i) The memorandum with regard to the relation of the Council and of the Staff to the Executive, which the Secretary was instructed to prepare, is being circulated separately.(j) The memorandum sent by the Council to the Supreme War Council with regard to the allocation of Dutch tonnage for European imports avas considered by the latter Council, which passed a resalution to the following effect: &quot;As the French Government have agreed not to* discontinue the transport of 350,000 tons of French coal into Italy by the 15th April 1918, the Supreme War Council are of opinion that the Dutch shipping in American ports should be used, in the first place, for the indispensable requirements of the American Military Programme.&quot;Further representations were made to &apos;,he American Government as to the import-ance of allotting 70,000 tons of this tonnage in compensation for the loss of Atlantic imports resulting from the Italian coal arrangements. It has not, howrever, proved possible to obtain any part of the tonnage for this purpose.appendix.NOTE AS TO PERMANENT ORGANISATION.The permanent organisation consists of four National Divisions who will be housed together in Lancaster House with the exception of the British Division, the greater part of which must remain in the Ministry of Shipping.The work of these four National Divisions is co-ordinated by one Main Committee which generally supervises the w^ork of the whole Allied organisation, and three Sub-Committees dealing respectively with Tonnage, Imports, and Statistics, which, subject to the general supervision of the Main Executive Committee, co-ordinate the work of the several Divisions in detail.1. Main Executive Committee.The main Committee consists of the following heads of the several National Divisions : Mr. J. A. Salter (Chairman), M. Monnet (France). Professor Attolico (Italy). Mr. G. Ptublee (U.S.A.).The main Committee may be generally described as the Executive of the Council.. Its general responsibilities are to secure the necessary Executive action to give effect to decisions by the Council, to prepare information relevant to any question that the Council may desire to consider at any future meeting, to suggest definite proposals for the approval of the Council, and in general to take such. Executive action as is desirable and practicable, in pursuance of the general duty of assistiug in the allocation and most advantageous use of Allied tonnage by co-operative action.
2. Tonnage Sub-Committee.M. Revillon (France).Lieut. Farina (Italy). .&apos; Mr. Shearman (U.S.A.). Mr. Browett (Great Britain).Functions: (a) To arrange for the due execution of any decision of the Council involvingthe co-operative use or programming of tonnage. (6) To obtain and make available for general use statements showing theamount and disposition of the tonnage under the control of each Ally.(c) To examine proposals made by any country with a view to securing a moreadvantageous use of tonnage under the control of any ally (whether by the better disposition, routing, or more co-operative use of the tonnage or the better assignment of cargoes in relation to import programmes), and so far as possible to arrange that agreed improvements shall be carried into effect.(d) To report to the Main Committee as to the clue performance of the aboveduties.3. Imports Sub-Committee.M. Halgouet (France). Professor Attolico (Italy). Mr. Morrow (U.S.A.).Functions: (a) To arrange for the due execution of any decision of the Council as toImport programmes, by communication as may be necessary with the respective Executives or through the National Divisions avith the respective Governments.(b) To obtain (whether through the Executives or otherwise) and make availablefor general use statements showing in detail the import requirements (with sources of origin, &amp;c.) of the different countries, with such further information as may be desirable in order to show the relative necessity of the different requirements.(c) To examine the import programmes as so obtained, whether through theExecutives or otherwise, and to ascertain in what directions reductions - can be made most equitably as between the different countries and with least injury to the prosecution of the avar. (cZ) To report to the Main Committee as to the due performance of the aboA^e duties.4. Statistical Sub-Committee.M. Seitert (France). Signor Pardo (Italv). Mr. J. A. Field (ILS.A.). Mr. PalinElderton.Functions:  (a) To propose appropriate and uniform methods for collecting and investigatingdata bearing on the work of the Allied Maritime Transport Council.(b) To examine and pass all data and statistical conclusions based thereon.(c) To keep record of all actions under (a) and (b).(d) To arrange for records to be kept showing the extent to which any decisionsof the Council as to allocation of tonnage or re-arrangement of supplies which are being complied with, and for that purpose consider statistical principles which are forming the basis of such a record.(e) For the due performance of the above duties, the Sub-Committee will keepconstantly in contact with the Tonnage and Imports Sub-Committees, and provide such statistical information and assistance as those Sub-Committees may require ; and ay ill report to the Main Committee.

</content>
</cab>
