<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/49/0 images: 157-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the property of the Secretary of State for India. Military Secret. 720 fFrom Viceroy, Army Department, 2ord April 1918. (Received 6 p.m., 24th.)5242. Reference to Premiers message of 2nd April pressing for further assistance from India in prosecution of war. Following is communicated for Prime Ministers information : 1. We fully realise gravity of military situation. We understand that main efforts should be directed to furnishing men and material for the defence of India and in neighbouring theatres of war. We believe this object can best be attained by enlisting the co-operation of India&apos;s Princes and peoples, and for this purpose Viceroy has convened a meeting of representatives of all classes at Delhi on 27th April.2. As an earnest of co-operation we have already received offers of assistance from various sources, including His Highness the Nizam, the Maharajas of Kashmir and Patiala, and various influential Associations and individuals in British India, both European and Indian. We will inform you later of the result of meeting at Delhi.3. Turning to our military situation evidence reaches us that German-Turkish influence is penetrating eastwards through Persia and the Caucasus, and we believe attack on India would greatly assist enemy aims in Palestine, and if successful would compel relinquishment of Mesopotamia.The new and dangerous factor in the situation is the spread of German-Turkish power over Russia which may result in enemy access to Russian railheads on northern border of Afghanistan. The arrival of even a small enemy force in this region would probably encourage the anti-British party in Afghanistan to such an extent as to give the Amir no choice save that of joining the enemy or losing his throne.India would then be confronted with a general conflagration on her North-West Frontiers, in which the tribes would join and would have to defend those frontiers, both on the Khyber and on Quetta front. Our first task, therefore, is to put ourselves in a position to ensure success in these theatres as far as may be, since otherwise we cannot maintain internal security or continue despatch of supplies and men overseas.4. With respect to lndia&apos;s war efforts. It is sufficient to say she has already supplied and maintained forces in all theatres on a scale far exceeding what had previously been laid down as her probable share even in an Imperial war.At present moment we have as many infantry battalions serving overseas alone as there were in India at the beginning of the war. To meet recent calls we are adding to forces in Egypt 27 Indian battalions which will release British battalions for France. In addition, our reserves of men and recruiting prospects based on last year&apos;s actuals should enable us to complete a programme which includes not only two mounted brigades and three infantry divisions, but also formation of nine extra battalions. During 12 months ending with 31st March, we recruited approximately 276,000 combatants against 113,000 in corresponding year ending 31st March 1917. But. we now aim at raising our combatant recruitment for the 12 months beginning from 1st April to 500,000, and if we succeed, this will produce an additional 100 battalions besides meeting all wastage demands. These new battalions should all be effective during campaigning season 1919-1920. The success of our recruiting campaign will, however, depend very materially on the decision to grant a large number of King&apos;s commissions to Indians.We have already addressed you separately regarding this (see our Army Department telegram No. 5176, dated 21st April), and press for an early acceptance of our proposals. We desire to point out in this connection that though a yield of 500,000 men may seem small as compared with total population of India, it is a large figure as compared with much more limited
-capacity of the lighting sections of the population. While we shall make every effort to tap fresh sources, you will, of course, realise that recruitment of unsuitable material would be merely a waste of energy and money.6..We have already supplied from our medical establishments 1,910 officers for military employment and 800 other civil officers, and although we do not anticipate being able to obtain many more medical officers will supply as many more civil officers for military service as is possible with clue regard to internal security of country.7. We hope also to raise some battalions for internal,security purposes from our police forces. Further, we have met large demands for labour corps and can recruit more men for service in these corps wherever required.8. In so far as the additional forces we are raising are not required for the defence of our own frontiers, they will be a general reserve for use wherever needed in Imperial interests.9. With regard to material resources our Munitions Board is doing a]l it can to utilise and expand to the fullest extent local sources of supply and manufacture; we believe, however, that our output could be largely increased if His Majesty&apos;s Government were in a position to give further assistance in following directions : (a) By meeting as fully and promptly as possible all demands from United Kingdom and urging on American Government necessity for meeting similar demands from America for machinery required to increase our manufacturing resources in case of articles, raw material of which is available in India. A case in point is plant required for Tatas plate rolling mills where shortage of steel plates is causing serious anxiety. We fully appreciate the fact that His Majesty&apos;? Government have already rejected this proposal but we would earnestly press for its reconsideration. His Majesty&apos;s Government may rest assured that Indian Munitions Board has for past year rigidly limited all demands to what is essential for Army use and for contributing to civil industries.(6) By meeting promptly and fully all demands for replacement of articles not manufactured in India and essential for maintenance of such industries and of forces in field.(c) By arranging for regular direct freight between West Coast of Americaand India.(d) By sparing, where necessary, limited numbers of skilled personnelor technical experts for further development of manufacturing capacity.10. Our difficulties in the matter of railways are well known to you. Our resources in this direction have been already largely devoted to prosecution of the Avar. We have supplied a large quantity of stock and materials for military railways overseas which have been entirely equipped with personnel, engines and rolling stock drawn from Indian railways. Indeed, we have already pulled up some lines to furnish rails. Incidentally our passenger service for ordinary traffic was long-ago reduced by more than a million train miles monthly, fares increased and concessions withdrawn. Traffic Controller has been appointed, wagons pooled . and whole traffic of railways brought under single control. Traffic Priority Committee, on which Army and Munitions Board are strongly represented, has been constituted. In spite of depleted personnel and absence of necessary supplies, Indian railways have succeeded in carrying more than experts ever thought possible. Strain has been enormously increased by cessation of sea-borne coal traffic. Nevertheless, they have dealt with abnormal coal, troops, and military stores traffic, and have conveyed to the ports all wheat and other grain required overseas. This last-mentioned traffic has amounted to 354,000 tons in a single month, and the coal traffic to an average of 1,400,000 tons a month. We hope to be able to continue to meet this strain though stock gradually deteriorating, but it will be practically impossible to augment our efforts unless assistance can be given from England.   If colliers to carry coal
to Bombay could be supplied, and a second tanker to bring oil fuel from Persian Gulf to Bombay or Karachi, and if 100 engines and 5,000 wagons asked for in the Army Departments telegram No. 3453, dated 16th March, could be sent, our powers for co-operation would be greatly strengthened.11. It must also be realised that our difficulties with regard to railways nniy be at any moment gravely increased in the event of untoward develop-ments upon our frontiers. These would impose an additional strain very difficult to meet.12. As regards foodstuffs we have placed practically the whole surplus of Indians wheat production at disposal of United Kingdom and Allies, allowing internal prices to rise to level beyond which it Avould be dangerous to go without incurring grave risk of serious internal trouble. We have supplied Royal Commission Avith 1,500,000 tons of wheat in 1917-1.8, at cost consider-ably below world prices, and hope to supply 1,800,000 tons or more in current year. Our Wheat Commissioner has supplied 700,000 tons of other grain in past year for military purposes in Egypt and Salonika, and is continuing to meet all demands of Director of Army Contracts. We are also supplying all grains required by Forces in Mesopotamia, Persian Gulf, Aden and East Africa, rice and flour for Egypt, and flour for Salonika, in addition to requirements of civil population in Mesopotamia. We are examining further scheme designed to enable us to increase exportable surplus of wheat, and, while unable to furnish precise details, we hope to be able to raise total available surplus for export to 2,000,000 tons. We can also supply considerably larger quantities of rice from Burma for Royal Commission if freight can be provided.13. Lastly, as regards finance, we are most anxious to co-operate effectively. Our difficulty is, however, to make definite promise in view of position as regards inconvertibility. You are already aware of the grave difficulties inconvertibility is likely to entail, involving among other matters run on Savings Banks deposits, serious prejudice to Loan prospects, and inadvisability of adding to taxation while our credit is disturbed, and people would be unsettled by, and in many cases resentful of, stoppage of cash payment.We must also conserve our resources to meet military eventualities previously mentioned, which would entail heavy drain upon Indian finances. But later on, if dangers referred to pass away, we hope to consider, in consultation with our Legislative Council, what addition to the 100,000,000L contribution made last year, or what other form of financial assistance, may be practicable.14. We should be glad to be informed if there is any other way in which Indian resources can be profitably and promptly utilised, as we are very anxious to render all possible assistance to the Empire in this crisis.15. In the meantime it is very important that no publicity should be given to proposals outlined above, as they will form subject matter for discussion and endorsement at Delhi Conference.

</content>
</cab>
