<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/49/0 images: 304-305</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[JmiB DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRTgAgglO MA0E5TYTS GOVERMEMT)sj ore t.0.T. 4363. T7AR   CABINET.M EKOBAOU M, dated 17 til April, 1918, submitted by the HES7SPAPER C0U7BR3IICS, representing the LOBDflW &amp; PK0VI1ICIAI PRESS regarding certain Proposals qf the WAR ALMS COMMITTEE,There is a serious shortage in paper, which is likely to grpw more acute.   See accompanying Memorandum   submitted to War Cabinet.The Government is now the largest consumer of paper and paper-making materials.   Government Departments must economise. Each Department alleges that it uses only.s comparatively small amount of paper..   That may be true, but the aggregate is very considerable.3. The&apos;newspapers are of opinion that the publications issuedby the War Aims Committee are in most cases unnecessary, and that they improperly divert paper from the- newspapers.   In the opinion of the Press the different supplements and other * publications have only a slight value for propaganda purposes. The matter is only a feeble imitation of that which appears in almost every newspaper end periodical.   The newspapers consider that the Committee should confine their literary operations to producing matter which does not appear elsewhere in an extended or striking form.   For example, it would be desirable to reproduce on small posters and leaflets some of the vivid letters describing the sufferings of our prisoners of war.4. Reference may also be made to the series of picturesissued by the Committee of some of the men responsible for the conduct of the war in Allied Countries.   Publicity of this sort is absolutely worthless for propaganda purposes and is a waste1 of paber and labour.   In view of the shortage of material, a more careful selection should be made of the matter to be published.5. The Government admit that the Press is an essential partof the organization for carrying on the War.   That being&apos; so, the Government must choose between tho Press, the value of which has been proved, and publications suoh as those of the War Aims Committee which are of uncertain value.6. The Press would strongly oppose the establishment by theV/ar Aims Committee of a clearing house such as that described in the memorandum which has been furnished to me.   All matter intended for the Press generally should be issued through the Press Bureau, the Directors of which are best able to judge from day to day what metter can be assimilated by the newspapers end what should bo held over,V. The Press prefer to remain in touch with the differentGovernment Departments, but steps should be taken to curtail the operations of the various publicity staffs,   k mess of useless matter is now bein^ prepared in different departments, much of which finds its way into tho westepaper basket.
As pointed out by the Directors of the Bureau, official notices should bo condensed.   The staffs should be released and the men employed for other purposes.The Press do not went Government Departments to epitomise Blue Books and other documents on their behalf. The suggested clearing house would only result in further confusion and in tho employment of more highly paid officials. There is an idea that the Press want to be spoon-fed; they want nothing of the sort,   They desire facilities to obtain information and to write it up in their own way. Most of the matter issued by Government Departments is quite unsuitable for reproduction in the newspapers -The creation of a clearing house would further tend to stereotype the information supplied to the press and would offer no guarantee for the mitigation of the evils complained of, vis, over-staffed publicity departments engaged in the production of useless and unappetising material.    Humorous protests have already been made regarding &quot;dud,T articles issued by various departments.After numerous and emphatic representations, arrangements have now been made whereby the Admiralty, the War Office, and the Ministry of Munitions are affording   facilities for the preparation of suitable material.   The establishment of the suggested clearing house would be a re-actionary measure calculated to accentuate and perpetuate the abuses against which the Press has been vigorously protesting for the past three years.   A rigid comb-out in the various publicity, departments is urgently required.    There is an impression in certain Government Departments that the Press is avid for articles.    That is quite inaccurate.    The Press wants news, and Editors want facilities for writing up matter in their own way.Heedless to say, the Newspapers are most anxious to . assist the Committee to make their operations effective, but the newspapers think, rightly or wrongly, that the Committee are   wasting a considerable amount of valuable labour and material.   Vfe believe that far better results could be secured by a wiser selection and more economic methods.

</content>
</cab>
