<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/49/0 images: 414-414</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3/3603. WAR CABINBT. jjfDespatch of Amerioan Troops.Memorandum hy the Secretary of State for War.I circulate the agreement reached between General Perching and myself as to the despatch from the United States of American troops,,T,..: - Milner.v   &apos;A*29th April, 1918,) /c2 ,    ^^^^It is agreed between the Secretary of State for War, representing the British Government, and General Pershing, representing the American Government, that for the present American troops be sent over in the following order;IA* That only the infantry, machine guns, engineers, and signal troops of American divisions and the headquarters of divisions and brigades be sent over in British and American shipping during May for training and service with the British army in Prance up to six divisions, and that any shipping in excess of that required for these troops be utilised to transport troops necessary to make these divisions complete. The training and service of these troops will be oarried out in accordance with plans already agreed upon between Sir Douglas Haig and General Pershing, with a view at an early date of building up Amarican divisions^B, That the American personnel of the artillery of these divisions and such corps troops as may be required to build up American oorps organisations follow immediately thereafter,! and that the American artillery personnel be trained with French material and join its proper divisions as soon as thoroughly trained.C. If, when the program outlined in paragraphs A. and B. is completed, the military situation makes advisable the further shipment of infantry etcetera of American divisions, then all the British and American shipping available for transport of troops shall be used for that purpose under such arrangement as will insure immediate aid to the Allies, and at the same time provide at the earliest moment for bringing over Amerioan artillery and other necessary units to complete I the organisation of American divisions and corps.   Provided that the combatant troops mentioned in A and B be followed by such servioe of the rear and other troops as may be considered necessary by the American Commander-in-Chief*D.That it is contemplated American divisions and corps when trained and organised shall be utilised under the Americsnl Comnander-in-Chief, in an American group,E. That the American Commander-in-Chief shall allot American troops to the French or British for training or train them with  &quot;American units at his discretion, with the understanding that troops already transported by British shipping or included in the six divisions mentioned in paragraph A are to be trained with the British Army, details as to rations, equipment and transport to be determined by special agreement.(Sgd.)     MILKER.London, (SgdO     JOHN J. PERSHING.April, 24,1918, General, U,S, Array,

</content>
</cab>
