<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/49/0 images: 422-425</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
RESTRICTIONS ON TRAVELLING BY RAILWAY. l&amp;^yfP^----------/&quot;*n% i&quot; &apos; -t   \&apos;; f-fr&quot;&apos;&quot;&quot;\ ^f-\f?s GbverniT)^ni \.Memorandum b-Vjjjjgj^-residenj^oj^-jbhe;;Boa,Td      Trade.T r^he Railways of Great Britain now find themselves in a very serious position and drastic steps must be taken to reduce travel on the Railways.     In addition to the      very heavy demands that have been made upon them for the provision of locomotives, rolling stock, materials, and men for military purposes abroad; and the fact that St has been impossible for the Companies to maintain their stock in efficient order, the mass of traffic, both Govern-ment and civilian, which has been thrown upon the railways has been enormous.     Coming on the top of this, recent further demands on the carrying capacity of the railways have been made owing to the diversion to the railways of traffic which formerly went coast-wi se.I have had a eerie?;&apos; of Conferences with the Railway iSxecu-tive Committee and as a result of these Conferences I have to put to the War Cabinet the following proposals the adoption of whichis in my opinion necessary and which may have to be augmentedlater on if the situation does not improve.An amendment of Defence of the Realm Regulation 7B, of whicha copy is attached; has been made and under the powers of thatRegulation I propose to authorise the Railway Executive Committeeto take the following steps:-(1)   To discontinue the issue or renewal of all seasontickets which are issued at special reduced rates except scholars&apos; , apprentices&apos;j and privilege season tickets issued by the Railway Companies to their employees.   This proposal covers the issue or renewal of season tickets at specially low rates to members of the family of a season ticket holder and may also affect the special cheap military tickets which are issued to Officers who are not, at the time being, on active service although they may be engaged on some form of &apos;military duty.Before, however, dealing further with the military tickets I propose to arrange that the War Office shall be consulted.(2)   To discontinue the issue of any new season or trader&apos;s ^ ^ ticketshis is witn\n^ printers\^Dnd will^bV^sent as^aopn as available.
tickets, which are applied for for the first time, between London and places situated outside a radius of 12 miles from Charing Cross, except in cases where it is shown that work of National importance is being under-taken by the applicant.     This restriction may have to be applied to other districts later on,I may exp3.ain that the object this proposal has inview is to reduce the very large number of season tickets covering comparatively lengthy journeys, which has recently been issued as a result partly of the migration of certain classes of the population from London to places outside the Metropolis.(3)   To discontinue the renewal of any season or trader&apos;s ticket between London and places situated outside a radius of 12 miles from Charing Cross which were taken out for the first time since the 1st January 1917, except in cases in which it is shown that work of national importance is being undertaken by the holder of the ticket.(4)   To discontinue the issue of season tickets for periods of less than 6 months in cases in which the tickets cover journeys over 12 miles and the applicants have not pre-viously held season tickets.(5)   To discontinue giving refunds in respect of season tickets which have not expired and \?hich the holder desires to surrender to the company in return for an allowance in respect of the unexpired period,This proposal will not apply in the case of the death of the holder of the ticket or in the case of a holder being called up for Government service, and is a necessary corollary to (4).(6)   To increase the price of season tickets by 10 per cent, in the case of tickets covering distances up to 12 miles, and 20 per cent, in the case of tickets covering distances of over 12 miles.The effect of the 50$ increase in ordinary fares which was imposed as from the lat January 1917, has been to induce people to take season tickets who in the past had bought ordinary tickets as occasion required, and the further result has been that people, more especially those living at some distance from London, have travelled to and from London more frequently than they did in the past as, being holders of a season ticket, their extra journeys cost them nothing.There
There is a further consideration in connection with season tickets, and that is, that while the railway companies were inde-pendent they issued season tickets at very unrovunerative rates and in present circumstances I Co not feel justified in allowing this unremunerative arrangement to he continued.     The very large increases in wages which have he.en granted to railway employees , amounting, since the recent increase of 4/- a week, to something around  45,000,000 a year, seems to me to make it neOessaiy to revise the existing season ticket arrangements, and to do seme-thing towards bringing- an increased       revenue from the railways under Government control into the Exchequer.     This is the ground for the last proposal stated above.I have considered, with the Railway Executive Committee, the question of introducing a system under which no one       should be able to travel by railway without a permit.   It may be that a permit system will become necessary, but it is surrounded with difficulties and complications, and the Railway Executive Commit-tee do not think that they are at present in a position to under-take to administer the system.The question of an increase in goods and cartage rates has also been considered, but I am not in a position, at the moment, to put forward any proposals on this subject.A. H. STAHLSY.29th April, 1918.
ittnendment of Regulation 7 B.for prescribing the conditions on which tickets may be issued and passengers carried either generally or in specified localities or for journeys exceeding specified distances and for enabling pribrity to be given on rail-ways to any passengers or classes of passengers and for enabling railway companies to refuse to carry passengers, and to refuse access to stations or trains in order to give priority to other passengers, and to remove passengers obtaining such access without authority.for removing any statutory or other obligation to issue season tickets and f6i* limiting the number of such tickets that may be issued by prescribing the persons to whom or the conditions on which such tickets may be issued or renewed subject to such exceptions as may be provided for in the order.for the calling in and cancellation of season tickets o  any description.for restricting or prohibiting through bookingfacilities\ and the issue of return tickets, railwayfor enabling/coapsnies to refuse to accept goods for carriage by raili where other means of transport exist, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the order.Add to paragraph 3 *or pert of a railway or to any particular locality*.

</content>
</cab>
