<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/33/26 images: 162-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet. February 1943.SECRET.26th Conclusions.cow no.  50TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure die. secrecy of this dopnmentWAR CABINET 26 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Monday, February 8, 1943, at 5-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,.Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Right Hon. $. M. Bruce, Repre-sentalive of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury (Items 5-6).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNav^ 1-3).The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Item 4).The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of Aircraft-Production.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (/terns 1-3).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Joint Parliamentary Secretaryto the Treasury (Items 5-6).Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-3).  .General Sir, Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff (Items 1-3).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Lieutenant^General Sir Hastings Ismay.C Mr-..: :Ngrm an &apos; Brook.::Mr;:L.-F./BuRGis..:1:025038-1]b

forJabmet.FebruaryiI943.CotofNO.m, (48)(n uoncrasionsTO BE KEPT IINDMR L^OK ANDKEYIt is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 26 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,. S.W. 1, on Monday, February 8, 1943, at 5- 30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce^ Repre-sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury (Items 5-6).Admiral of the  Fleet  Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief of.Naval Staff (Items 1-3).The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Colonel   the   Right   Hon.  oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Item 4).The Right Hon. Sir James GriGG,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-3).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P , Joipt Parliamentary Secretaryto the Treasury (Items 5^-6).Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal,  Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-3).General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff (Items 1-21).i Secretariat.-;;SirvEpWARD&apos;-B^Mr.-Norman Brook.-..-Mf. L. F. - Burgis. ...
WAR CABINET 26(43).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....      ....      ....      ....    91Air Operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean Theatre.Tunisia. vThe Pacific.Naval Operations:. Atlantic Convoy.Mediterranean.Pacific..  Military Operations:       -Tunisia. ;;Libya.Russia.2      Foreign Affairs................      ....      ....      ....    91Poles in U.S.S.R,Fighting French.Italy.3      Prisoners of War       ....      ....      ....      ....      ........    924      Jamaica.........      ....       ...      ....      ....      ....      ...     92Constitutional Reform.5      Parliament      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    93Beveridge Report.6      Parliament      ....      ....   .. ....      ....      ....      ....      .....    93Request that a serving officer should address an unofficialCommittee of Members.
91VSM. 28(43).Emali Militaryand Air      &apos;Operations.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 21stConclusions,Minute 2.)Air Operations.Home Theatre.mediterranean theatre.  ,Tunisia..The Pacific.naval operations.atlantic convoy.Mediterranean.The Pacific.MilitaryOperations.Tunisia.Libya.Russia.1.   The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of thePa8t Bomber Command had carried out raids on Cologne, Hamburg,Tn^HLoSitwice). 2,180 tons of bombs had been dropped^Sm^STSa^UA July. Coastal Command hadS toeprying attacks on U-boats Enemy losses haaVbeenisdestroved 6 probably destroyed and 7 damaged. Our losses? naaoeenTlgLvsl 38 bo4ers ana 7 Coastal Command aircraft.In the Mediterranean our aircraft had attacked one U-boat and damaged 10 merchant ships, 5 schooners and 1 destroyer.In Tunisia Allied air activity had increased whilst the enemy&apos;seffort had fallen off. Ports and airfields had been attacked.During an attack by the Japanese against Wau aerodrome theAllies claimed to have destroyed 26 enemy aircraft for no loss..    Shipping losses for the previous week, including belatedreports, amounted to 107,000 tons.Several ships had been lost in a slow homeward-bound atlantic convoy which had been attacked by U-boats at the end of theprevious week.  One U-boat had been destroyed.In the Mediterranean two enemy merchant ships and several small craft had been sunk. We had lost the minelayer Welshman,a Canadian corvette and a trawler.There were indications that the Japanese meant to make a determined attempt to reinforce Guadalcanal.The Tunisian front had now been organised under the command of General Anderson. The Axis had been endeavouring to securethe line of hills stretching south from Pont du Fahs.The 8th Army&apos;s forward line now coincided with the line of theTunisian frontier. It looked as though Rommel intended to try tohold the Mareth Line.In the Voronezh area two severe Russian thrusts had succeeded in cutting the main north and south railway through Kursk.Russian forces in this area had penetrated beyond the mostadvanced line held the previous winter.Towards the Don Basin the Donetz River had been crossed intwo places. The German divisions left in the bridgehead formedround the Taman peninsula were in an unenviable position. TheGermans had tried to establish an ice road across the Kerch Straits,but it was doubtful whether they would succeed..   The War Cabinet-   -Took note of these statements.2. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that difficulties were arising between the Russians and the Poles. Thelatter had informed us that the Soviet Government were nowvirtually refusing to recognise the Polish nationality of any Polishcitizen now in Soviet Russia. The Poles feared that this declara-tion might be a prelude to a refusal to allow the Poles in russia to continue to receive the food supplies Which were being sent fromthe United States. All this might be expected to have a bad, effecton the morale of the Polish troops in the Middle East whose familieswere still in Russia.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that hethought: the Poles would be bound to make some prptest in thismatter. It was for consideration whether this country and theUnited States should not take the matter up with the Russians&apos;\ Government He was considering communicating with the UnitedStates,Government on this matter.Fighting The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he hadFrench. had a very satisfactory interview with M. Massigli, who had assumed the post of Commissioner for Foreign Affairs on the French:      National Committee;[25038-1]Foreign Affairs.Poles inTJ.S.S.R.
taly. &apos; 1 The.changes in the Italian Government were thought to be dueto the desire to eliminate some members of-:&apos;that&apos; Guyernment/whpse&apos;&apos;*&apos;&apos;,&quot;/ loyalty to the Axis was suspeet. &apos; So -far as&apos; Count Ciano wa&amp; con-; cerned, the reason ;might be Mussolini&apos;s desire to keep control ofK&apos;&apos;ix - foreign affairs Under&apos;his(own&apos; hand.&apos;  The War Cabinet- &apos;    1     &apos;  &apos;&apos;;Took note of these statements.Prisoners ofWar.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 24thConclusions,   &apos;Minute 1.)3. At their meeting on the 5th February the War Cabinet had agreed that the Canadian&apos;Government should be asked to concur inthe terms of a revised draft telegram to Berne which had beenprepared with a, view to meeting their wishes.The War Cabinet now had before them an exchange of telegrams (Nbs. 25 and 26, dated the 5th February, from theDominions Office, and No. 21, dated the 7th February, from Canada)from which it appeared that the Canadian Government nowConcurred in the terms of the revised draft telegram.The War Cabinet were informed that the Prime Minister had seen these telegrams, and approved the terms of the proposedtelegram to Berne.The War Cabinet- .(1) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to telegraph to His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Berne in theterms of the revised draft.;(2) Asked the Secretary of State for War to arrange for theimmediate issue of the orders mentioned in that telegram.(3) Agreed that the terms of the communication to the. swiss government should not be publicly announced until therehad been a reasonable opportunity for the GermanGovernment to consider it. *Jamaica.constitutional reform.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 25thConclusions,Minute 5.)..4. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (W.P. (43) 49) seeking authorityto communicate to the Governor of Jamaica, for discussion with theLegislative Council, proposals for the reform of the JamaicanConstitution.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that this question had been under discussion for some time, but no progress had beenmade, largely because there had been no measure of agreement inJamaica. Towards the end of last year, however, he had receiveda memorandum setting out proposals for certain constitutional changes, which were put forward by representatives of all shades ofpolitical opinion in the Island. He was prepared to accept thesubstance of the proposals made in this memorandum; and, afterconsultation with the Governor, he believed that there was areasonable prospect that they would command a considerable-measure of support in the Island. The submission of these proposal?offered an opportunity of bringing to an end a controversy of longstanding which, unless it were;resolved, was likely to provokeserious trouble in Jamaica at the end of the war, if not earlier.After a short discussion, the War Cabinet -Endorsed the proposals put forward in W.P. (43) 49 and authorised the Secretary of State for the Colonies tocommunicate them to the Governor of Jamaica fordiscussion with the Legislative Council.
ant.beveridge report.(previous reference:mm. (43) 2istConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The War Cabinet were informed that the ReconstructionPriorities Committee would be in a position to submit, fordiscussion by the War Cabinet later in the week, their reoommen-dations on all the main proposals in the Beveridge Report. If these recommendations were accepted, the Government spokesmen wouldbe able to make some positive contribution in the forthcoming debate in the House of Commons.In these circumstances, it was agreed that the Debate shouldtake place during the following week, as provisionally arranged. Itwould be desirable that it should be taken on a specific Motion,tabled either by the Government or by representatives of the main political Parties. It was, perhaps, preferable that the debate should be held on a Government Motion, but a final decision on thispoint could not be reached until the Reconstruction priorities committee had concluded their discussions. It was the general desire of the House that three days should be allowed for this Debate.The War Cabinefs conclusions were as follows : (1) The Leader of the House should announce, on the following day, that this Debate would be held on the 16th-^18 th February, and. might add that, in the usualstatement on Business on the 11th February, he wouldmake a further announcement regarding the form whichthe Debate would take.(2) The Reconstruction Priorities Committee, at their meetingon the following day, would consider whether the debate should be held on the basis of a Government Motion, and,if so, the terms of that Motion; and would include a recommendation on this point in the Report which theywere submitting for consideration by the War Cabinetlater in the week.Parliament.Request that aServing officers should addressan unofficialCommittee ofMembers.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 19thConclusions,itmute 3.)6. The Secretary of State for War said that Lord Salisburywas Chairman of an unofficial Committee which comprisedMembers of both Houses and interested itself in a wide range of subjects. It was understood that a number of serving Officers had addressed it. Now, however, for the first time, the Committee had sent an official request to a Department-the War Office that aserving Officer should address them, the subject being the system ofco-operation between air and land forces which had been worked outin the Middle East. It was for consideration whether this request should be acceded to.In discussion, it was pointed out that serving Officers also hadoccasion to address Members of Parliament who came round to seedemonstrations at Service or Supply Establishments. It was felt,however, that a line could be drawn between technical discussions and explanations, which were permissible, and addresses to bodiescomprising Members of both Houses and other persons- in political life, which were likely to deal with controversial issues of policy.The latter was not the function of serving Officers or Civil Servants,and should be discouraged.The Secretary of State for Air said that he had refused severalrequests from the Air Committee that the Air Officers Commariding-in-Chief should be allowed to address them.The War Cabinet accordingly^-Invited the Secretary of State for War. to inform lord salisbury that this request could not be acceded to, since itwas incompatible with the duties of serving Officers to, address meetings of this character.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,February 8, 1943.




</content>
</cab>
