<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/55/9 images: 172-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Cls. c^/L*J\   Iffff^t^ this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  September 1944.o4iSECRET.(       W.P. (44) 509.8th September, 1944.Copy No.    30WAR CABINET.RE ALLOCATION OF MAN-POWER BETWEEN CIVILIAN EMPLOY-MENTS DURING THE INTERIM PERIOD BETWEEN the defeat OF GERMANY AND THE DEFEAT OF JAPAN.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service.THE White Paper on Reallocation of Man-Power between the Armed forces and Civilian Employment in the Interim Period between the defeat of Germanyand the defeat of Japan has been approved by the War Cabinet (W.M. (44)113th Conclusions, Minute 2 (1)). I circulate herewith a parallel memorandum in the form of a draft White Paper on Reallocation of Man-Power betweenCivilian Employments. I had hoped to consult industry through the medium ofthe Joint Consultative Committee before submitting the scheme to my colleagues,but I have been held up pending the publication of the scheme for the Reallocationof Man-Power between the Forces and Civilian Employment. The matter isnow becoming very urgent in view of the favourable development of the war situation, and, in order to save time, I ask for general approval of the. proposals set out in the document attached on the understanding that they may be. subjectto modification after discussion with the Joint Consultative Committee, which takes place on the 19th September. I shall, of course, submit a final draft forapproval as soon as my consultations with industry have been completed.E. B.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,8th September, 1944.REALLOCATION OF MAN-POWER BETWEEN CIVILIAN EMPLOY-MENTS DURING THE INTERIM PERIOD BETWEEN the defeat OF GERMANY AND THE DEFEAT OF JAPAN.I. Introduction.1. In the White Paper on Reallocation of Man-Power between the armed forces and Civilian Employment (Cmd. 6548) it is pointed out that no generaldemobilisation either of the Armed Forces or of War Industry can take place inthe interim period and that the problem during that period will be one ofreallocation of man-power between the Forces and Industry in order best toprovide for the requirements of the situation. That Paper described the Govern-menfs plans for the release of men and women from the Armed Forces during the interim period. In this Paper are set out the Governments plans for the redistribution of man-power during the same period within civilian employments.2.   The interim period is likely to be one of severe readjustment.   Many(      difficult problems will arise and many conflicting interests will need to be reconciled.   Industry itself will be the subject of considerable changes.   Theproduction required for carrying on the war against Japan must be fully main-tained, but this will permit of a substantial reduction in munitions and equipment[28188] * b
for the Armed Forces: within the reduced total there will be changes of emphasisas between different products. Manufacturers who will wish to restart as soonas possible their civilian production in preparation for post-war trade must expect to find their activities restricted, in some cases severely, according to theimportance of the product and the extent of our resources. As was emphasised inthe White Paper on Employment Policy (Cmd. 6527). a start must be made withrestoring our export trade. There must be a great expansion in building activity,especially for the purpose of rehousing our citizens. It must be made possibleto turn over some of our capacity to the production of civilian goods which in normal times are regarded as sheer necessities, but of which in the past few yearswe have, because of the needs of war production, had to go grievously short. Also,much of our industry is in need of re-equipment if it is to produce efficiently inthe post-war period. The task will be to ensure that our limited resources are concentrated first upon those munitions required for the Armed Forces, and,second, upon those products which are most important to national recovery and toan improvement in the standards not of those people who can pay the highestprices but of the community as a tchole.3. As regards resources of man-power, substantial numbers of men andwomen willbe released from the Armed Forces and Civil Defence, the majorityof whom will be available for. and will require, civilian employment. At the sametime some industries and establishments will be able to release labour, most ofwhom will need employment and should be steered to the employments where their services are most required in the national interest; many other industries and establishments which have had their labour forces depleted during the war will need to have their labour forces built up. Many employers will wish to make a start with building up their permanent labour force for the post-war period, but some of these employers will be engaged on work which is not for the time being of the first importance. As regards workers, many of them, on account of age orof exhaustion after years of severe strain, will wish and be entitled to retire from work altogether. Others will wish to take the earliest opportunity of gettingthemselves settled in permanent employment, a desire which may in many casesnot be compatible with the need to employ them in the work carrying the highest priority for the time being. Finally, there is little doubt that throughout theperiod under consideration the minimum man-power requirements, on a basis not of luxury but for essential purposes, will be substantially in excess of the totalresources.4. It is thus clear that, in order to avoid the risk of serious dislocation andthe dissipation of our resources on objects of secondary importance and to ensure,so far as practicable, the production of necessities rather than luxuries, thereallocation of man-power during this period must be undertaken on a plannedbasis involving in some measure a continuance of control over industry and labour.As stated in the White Paper on Employment Policy &quot; In order to direct the efforts of industry towards the right tasks inthe right order, it will be necessary to establish certain broad priorities andto enforce them for a time by means of the issue of licences, the allocation of raw materials and some measure of control over the labour and staff required for industry.&quot;In the man-power sphere the aim must be, while seeking to mitigate the severity of the existing labour controls and while paying such regard as is possible tothe natural desires of workers to seek work where they please and of employers to engage labour freely, to ensure that the available resources of man-power areemployed in the places where, and on the tasks in which, they are most needed inthe national interest.II. Principles Governing Reallocation.Men and Women Released or Transferred from the Armed Forces.Class A (Men and rvomen released under age and length of service).5. During the period in which they are on paid leave following release fromthe Armed Forces these men and women will not be subject to the current labour controls, and will be allowed to exercise their reinstatement rights and go back-to their former employment, restart their businesses or undertake further education and training.   The Employment Exchanges will give every assistance
to these men and women; in offering employment to them they will have regardto current priorities. At the end of the period of paid leave following release from the Armed Forces, they will be treated in the same way as other workers,and it will then be open to the Exchanges, in appropriate cases and where necessary, to direct those who are still unemployed or become unemployed andare available for work to jobs in accordance Avith existing priorities and underthe usual safeguards for appeal. Those who have obtained a job during their period of leave will not be withdrawn from these jobs.Class B (Men and women released for Reconstruction employments).6. These men and women will be directed to work in the employments forwhich they have been released, their reinstatement rights being preserved duringthe period that the direction remains current. They may be given permission or required to move from one job to another within the reconstruction employment,but if they leave that employment they will be recalled to the Forces.Other men and women released after the end of the war in Europe.7. The majority of these will probably have been discharged on medical grounds, while others will have been released on compassionate grounds. Theywill be treated as Class A men and women so far as reinstatement and placingin employment is concerned.Men and women released before the end of the war in Europe.(a) Men and women released on industrial grounds.8. These are analogous to Class B releases and their treatment willcorrespond as closely as possible to that of the latter. They have been released from the Armed Forces for some particular kind of work and they will be requiredto remain on such work so long as they are needed, their reinstatement rights, ifany, being preserved in the meantime.(b)&apos;31 en and tvomen released on other than industrial grounds.9. These will be mainly men and women discharged on medical grounds orreleased on compassionate grounds. They are analogous to those referred to inparagraph 7 above and their treatment will be as nearly as possible similar.From a date as near to the end of the European war as possible they will be given  an opportunity to exercise their reinstatement rights, if any, to start their ownbusinesses or to undertake further education and training.Disabled Persons.10. In the case of disabled persons who are handicapped by their disabilityin relation to employment, the primary object will be to find them employment which will result in their satisfactory and, so far as possible, permanentresettlement in employment of the kind they wish to follow. They will not berequired to take, or to remain in, employment on the grounds of its immediateimportance if this does not also serve towards their permanent resettlement.Persons released from Civil Defence.11. These persons will be regarded as available for placing in employmentin accordance with the current priorities and subject to the current rules for industrial workers. This means that they will become subject to the currentlabour controls immediately on discharge except that those possessingreinstatement rights will be allowed to exercise them.Persons engaged in Civilian Employment (other than those who have been released from the Armed Forces or Civil Defence).General Principles of Redistribution.12. It has already been pointed out that the period with which theseproposals are concerned is likely to be a period of stringency of man-power. Agoverning consideration must therefore be the needs of essential production, andall persons in the country must continue to be regarded as available to make theirappropriate contribution to the life and work of the nation.13. There will be available for the export and civilian goods industries andthe basic industries an inflow, of man-power from the Armed Forces, from Civil[28188] b 2
Defence and, on balance, from the munitions industries. At the same time, as has been indicated above (paragraph 3), substantial numbers of men and womenwill be wanting to leave industry to go home, whilst others will want to leave theirpresent war jobs and either go back to their normal employment or to some other employment offering prospects of permanency. Others again, especially if theyhave been away from home for a long time, will wish to return to employment neartheir homes. It is an aim of the Government&apos;s reallocation policy, as set out inthis paper, to meet these wishes, especially a wish to return home, so far as is consistent with due regard for the general national interest.14. It is not possible to allow release to be determined purely by the occurrence of redundancy since that would result in certain classes of thecommunity being released from some industries and establishments while the sameclasses were retained in other industries and establishments. There are certainclasses of persons who, on personal grounds, have a claim for specially sympathetictreatment in the matter of release for the purpose of retiring from industry, andthese must be given an overriding priority. These classes must also be given a first priority of release for transfer to work nearer to their homes if they do not wish to retire from industary. There is a further class that has a claim to first priority of release for transfer to work nearer home, namely, those persons whohave been working away from home for three years or more. These priority classeswill, unless in any exceptional case there are very strong production reasons tothe contrary, be allowed to retire from industry or be released for transfer towork nearer home irrespective of the work on which they are engaged or whetherthey are redundant. It will obviously not be possible to effect all these releasesimmediately the war in Europe ends, but it is hoped to be able to effect the bulkof them within about one month.15. When these priority classes have been released the position will be thatcertain establishments, mainly in the munitions industries, will still haveredundant. labour, while other establishments in all industries, includingmunitions, will be requiring labour, and the problem, therefore, becomes one of transfer of labour with some of the vacancies of greater importance than others.In this redistribution of labour an order of priority of discharge or release for transfer must be operated, and it is proposed that, apart from call-up for theForces, the two main classes to be released first should be those needed for priorityvacancies and those who have worked away from home for more than one year andwant to return. The detailed proposals are set out in the following paragraphs : Retirement from employment on personal grounds.16. On application the following classes of persons (called Class K) will begiven permission, if they so desire, to leave their jobs and retire from industryimmediately the %var in Europe ends irrespective of the production on which theyare engaged: - (1) Women (married or single) with household responsibilities and womenwishing to join, or preparing to join, their husbands on release fromthe Forces.(2) Other women over 45.(3) Men over 60.This list will be kept under constant review and extended, as the situationrequires, in close association with the list suggested in paragraph 18 below.Special consideration will also be given to cases of men and women who wish to retire from employment and have good reason for doing so, but are not for thetime being within Class K.Transfer to other tcork or back home.17. Those in Class K who do not want to retire from industry but wish totransfer to other employment or to work nearer home, together with those whohave worked away from home for three years or more and want to obtain worknearer home, will be given first priority of release for transfer irrespective of thetvork on which they are engaged or whether they are redundant.Redistribution of labour arising from redundancy.18. As regards those establishments with a surplus of labour after personsin Class K and those who have worked away from home for three years of more
have been released, the surplus will of course have to be discharged. Where a factory closes down as a whole on a given date no question of the order of discharge arises. In most cases, however, the reduction of the redundant labour force will take the form of discharge over a period for which a priority order of selection for transfer is necessary, if the aim of the Governments policy as statedin paragraph 13 above is to be achieved. The order of priority, which has been determined partly on grounds of the national interest and partly on personalgrounds, is as follows :-A. For call-up for the Forces Men aged 18-27, both dates inclusive.B. For transfer to other employment (1) Those who are needed for priority vacancies.(2) Those who have worked away from home for less than three but more than one year and want to return, in order of their lengthof absence from home.(3) Other releases in accordance in accordance with current practice,e.g., as determined by industrial agreements.This order of priority is not to be regarded as determined once and for all. Asin the case of the list in paragraph 16 it will be kept under review and extended or modified as the situation requires. Persons who have special cause on otherpersonnel grounds will be entitled to apply for release in the ordinary way.19. In applying this order of priority the Ministry of Labour will beentitled as at present first to withdraw redundant men required for the forces and redundant workers needed for priority vacancies. As regards men for theForces it is proposed that men in the 10 years age range from 18 to 27 inclusiveshould be liable for calling up. Men up to 25 years of age wall be called up first and those in the age range 25 to 27 will only be called up if there are not sufficientmen in the lower age ranges to meet requirements. In selecting workers for release for transfer to priority vacancies on the occurrence of redundancy it isproposed to follow existing selection procedure, which includes consultation withrepresentatives of the employers and workers. For the purpose of identifyingfor early release the remaining workers w^ho have served away from home for more than one year and who want to return, the co-operation of employers and workers will be needed. Employers and workers affected will, of course, as atpresent, be entitled to appeal against decisions of the National Service Officer.20. The workers released in this way will be redistributed in accordancewith current labour priorities. .4 major objective will be to retransfer as many persons as possible back to their homes; accordingly, those released will be trans-ferred to work as near to their homes as practicable.Redistribution of labour not arising from redundancy.21. The redistribution of labour from establishments having a surplus isonly a part of the problem o f reallocation. Within the industries and establish-ments needing to maintain or increase their labour force there are bound to be widespread applications for transfer from persons outside Class K and thosewho have been away from home for more than three years, particularly from thosewho wish to move nearer to their homes. Accordingly, as and when substitutescan be provided from the &quot; surplus &quot; industries, from releases from the Forces orfrom fresh entrants into employment, the priority order of release in para-graph 18 above will be applied to these cases.22. Again, in some eases it will probably be necessary to secure thetransfer of workers from their existing employment, even though they are notredundant, to other work where their services are more needed in the national interest. Here again the objective of moving persons nearer to their homes willbe borne in mind.Registration for Employment or National Service.23. Young men and women. Young men and young women reaching theage^ of registration for Employment or National Service will continue to be registered as at present. Their cases will be reviewed in order to ensure that theyare engaged on those activities in which they are most needed in the national interest.  Young men will remain liable to service in the Armed Forces and will
be subject to the current arrangements regarding call-up, deferment, exemp-tion. &amp;c. Those not required for the Armed Forces and who are otherwise avail-able will be required to take or to continue in work or to take training, inaccordance with the current labour priorities.24. Women will not be called up for the Forces, although they will (pro-bably) be permitted to volunteer. It will, however, be necessary to retain largenumbers of women in industry for some time and it is most desirable to relieve the older women amongst them as soon as possible. Accordingly, young women who are available in accordance with the current rules will be required to take orto continue in employment, or to take training in accordance with the currentlabour priorities; butthe present i&apos;ule under which women are not sent away from home under the age of 19 will be maintained.25. The position will be reviewed from time to time in the light of any decisions which may be taken affecting the policy of further education and with aview to relaxing restrictions. The position of those young people returning fromthe Forces, who have the first claim to resume their education, must, however, be safeguarded.Transfers from home.26. As a major objective of the redistribution of man-power is to get as many persons as possible back home, it is obvious that it will only be where thereis no other method of providing the necessary man-power that persons will besent away from home. It is not proposed to transfer persons out of their Regionunless this cannot be avoided. Accordingly, transfers away from home will onlybe made where there is no alternative, and in these cases every effort will be madeto avoid sending persons a long distance from home.III. Labour Controls in the Interim Period.27. &apos; The preceding sections of this Paper set out the considerations govern-ing the reallocation of man-power during the interim period and the principles on which reallocation will be applied. The aim will be to effect the necessaryredistribution of man-power as far as possible on a voluntary basis and tonarrow the field of compulsion to the strictest limits. It is clear, however, that ina problem of readjustment so intricate as we shall be faced with, it may benecessary to require some persons to remain at their existing jobs and others tomove from their existing jobs to other jobs, and that if the process of redistribution-tion of labour is to be effected in a fair and orderly nmnner and in order toensure that essential industries and services are to be manned up in accordancewith the agreed standards, the Government must retain a substantial measure ofcontrol over the movement of labour. The Governments proposals under this head are set out below.Directions tinder Recjidation 58a.28. One of the main foundations of control over the movement of labour isthe power of direction under Defence Regulations 58a, under which, broadly, theMinister of Labour and National Service has power to direct any person to anyjob in the United Kingdom at the rate for the job. While it is essential that theGovernment should during the interim period possess this power in the background to be exercised if necessary, it is intended to dispense with its use toa great extent by using instead the much more limited powers of the Control of engagement Order (see paragraph 30); in fact, it is hoped to dispense with its use completely at an early date. Its use will be limited to directing persons toessential work of the highest urgency. In any case, as has happened during thewar, it is not anticipated that it will be necessary to exercise the power of direction except possibly in a small minority of cases, and every care will be takento ensure that it is applied with the greatest discrimination.The Essential Work Orders..29. The material provisions of these Orders relating to control over themovement of labour forbid a worker leaving scheduled employment and forbid an employer terminating the engagement of a worker in scheduled employment without the permission of the National Service Officer. These Orders have provedinvaluable during the war in achieving an effective stabilisation in the labour force of particular industries and establishments, and the Government consider
it essential that the provisions of the Orders shall be retained during the interim period. It does not follow that the Orders will continue to apply to the sameindustries as are now covered. Those industries will have to be reviewed in orderto see whether they continue to require the protection of the Orders. Otherindustries of increasing importance in the interim period may have to be brought within the application of the Orders. Relaxations will have to be made in thecase of certain classes of persons. Thus, in accordance with the principle set outin paragraph 16 above, arrangements will be made for the following classes tobe released without question : (1) Women (married or single) with household responsibilities and womenwishing to join, or preparing to join, their husbands on release fromthe Forces.(2) Other women over 45.(3) Men over 60.- 30. In addition, in accordance with the principles laid down inparagraphs 12-14 it will be a chief objective in the administration of the Ordersthat persons who have been long away from home shall have the earliest possible opportunity of transferring to work near their homes.The Control of Employment (Directed Persons) Order.31. Similar considerations apply to this Order, the effect of which, combined with the power of direction, is that a person directed to a particular job maynot, without the consent of the National Service Officer, leave that job and maynot be dismissed by the employer from that job for such period as is specified inthe direction. It will be necessary to retain this Order, but it will be administeredwith due regard to the considerations, so far as they are appropriate, discussed inconnection with the Essential Work Orders.Control of Engagements.32. The object here is to ensure that engagements of certain specified classesof persons are controlled by the Ministry of Labour and National Service by providing that they may be made only through the Employment Exchanges or approved Agencies. This is effected at present through a number of Orders,namely : (1) The Restriction on Engagement Order for men which applies to men ofall ages, but in a limited number of industries only building and civil engineering, general engineering, the installation, maintenance and repair of electrical equipment.(2) The Essential Work Orders applying to coalmining, shipbuilding and ship-repairing, the Merchant Navy, port transport and ScottishAgriculture.(3) The Control of Engagement Order-for Women applying to women betweenthe ages of 18 and 40.In addition, there has been a very detailed control of the employment of all menof military age through the individual deferment system.33. Control over engagements during the interim period broadly on theselines is essential if any serious attempt is to be made to distribute labour during that period on a planned basis in accordance with agreed priorities and therelative needs of essential industries and services. The control over the engage-ment of men provided by the Restriction on Engagement Order and certain specialEssential Work Orders&quot;has covered the main industries which are important forwar production. In the interim period many civilian goods industries will haveto have their labour force built up to meet die needs of expanding production,while much important wartime production will no longer be expanding and willeven be contracting in certain cases. It will be necessary to adjust the area ofcontrol to accord with the requirements of the new situation and with the aim of achieving over the new area roughly the same effect as at present. It will be especially necessary to make that control effective if, as is proposed in para-graph 28, the power of direction is to be used sparingly or is dispensed with at anearly date. At the same time, it is the Government&apos;s desire both to give to employers as much freedom in the engagement of workers as is possible, and alsoto ease the position of as many classes of workers as possible, especially those in
the older age groups, and it is thought that it will be possible to dispense withcontrol over the engagements of men over the age of 50. Accordingly it is pro-posed to replace the above provisions by a single Control of Engagement Ordercovering all employments, but limited in the case of men to those aged 18 to 50and in the case of women to those aged 18 to 40.Juveniles.34. The effect of the proposal in paragraph 33 above will be to free certainjuveniles, i.e., boys and girls under 18. from the limited degree of control to whichthey have been subjected during the war. Special considerations apply tojuveniles and the war-time controls, in so far as they have applied to juveniles,have been administered in such a way as to ensure that, while leaving them a widefreedom of choice, juveniles have been engaged in employment which whileassisting the war effort so far as practicable has also offered opportunities for a career. Experience has shown the value to the juvenile of a limited control of engagement administered in this way. The question must, however, be considered in relation to the whole problem of juvenile employment and a separate scheme isbeing worked out in consultation with the interests concerned, the paramountobject of which will be to assist juveniles to the maximum extent possible in the choice of employment with a view to giving them the best opportunities for apermanent and progressive career in life with due regard to individual aptitudes.Registration for Employment Orders.35. The continuance of these Orders will be necessary so as to provide forthe identification of the workers concerned. In particular it may be necessary tohold special registrations of particular classes of persons or of persons engagedin or having experience of particular industries or occupations. It is not proposedto take any action under these Orders in connection with the classes of personswhich are included in Class K.Notice of Termination of Employment Order.36.   It is not proposed to continue this Order.



</content>
</cab>
