<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 196-200</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUM&amp;JT  U TEE imW*  W  HIM  BUiAMIC  IffJLuSWfc  GOVMSiilMT.)C.P.-25S4.(COUKGIL JXOTi&amp;flT     1E8J.C A B I H E T.Copy 1(0,AlPO-MitEM&apos; (tf THE J^&amp;Ua Oi? TH  i-iilil*UiJSBT           Memorandum    the^ueoretary-jenerait     The Council of the league of hations and r the provisionsof article EE of the Covenant ana those oi the Constitution ofthe Permanent Mandates commission, approved bjr the council anDecember 1st, 1920, it to appoint the Members of this Commission,The documents to whicn the ambers of the council may wish torefer in ohoosing the ^mbeis of the oommis&amp;ion are annexed tothis Memorandum.1.E.3.4.     .he^ are as follows    The Constitution of the Permanent Mandates Commission;    The recommendations to tie Council regarding the Mandates    Commission adopted by the Assembly on December 18th, 1920;    The resolutions concerning the Mandates Commission, adopted    by philanthropic and other organisations and addressed to    the Council or to the secretariat;    Letters and statements addressed to the Council or to the    beoretariat by various governments and organisations,    presenting the names and qualifioations of suggested    Candidates;     The Constitution of the Permanent Mandates Commissionprovides that it shall consist of 9 Members, the majority ofwhom shall be nationals of non-mandatory powers.     The Mandatory lowers are                BELGIUM                131; IT IEMI IBS                AUSTRALIA                SOUTH AFRICA                HBW ZEALAND                mam                JAPANr Already circulated as C.P.2281.*- hot  reproduced.
     Not more than four Members of the Commission may be chosenfrom among the nationals of these Powers.  The others may benationals cf any non-mandatory lower.  The Constitution doesnot exclude the appointment of several Members nationals of thesame i/fcate, nor the appointment of the national of a state nota Member of the league.  Nothing in the Constitution preventsthe appointment, as recommended by the Assembly, of at least one women.     The Constitution provides that &quot;all the ambers of theCommission shall be selected for their personal merits andcompetence.  They shall not hold any office which puts themin a position of direct dependence on their Governments whileMembers of the Commission.&quot;  It was understood from thepreliminary discussions that this clause excluded theappointment of any civil or military servant of any Governmenteven one of the non-mandatory Powers, but not the appointmentof such officials, as professors at a otate University, who could not be said to occupy a position of direot dependence on their Governments.     The Council decided  that, in no oase, could a Memberof the Commission be regarded as representing the vtate ofwhich he was a citizen or subject.
   &apos;  Having in mind the non-national character of the Membersof the Commission the Gou/icil decided that the constitution should provide for a dulj authorised representative of each MandatoryPower to participate in the discussion oi the report which he will present in the name of his Government.     The Commission, acting in concert with the duly authorisedrepresentatives of all the Mandatory lowers is to hold a plenary meeting,to examine the reports as a whole and any other matters connected with mandates^ which in tho opinion of the commission should be submitted by the Oounoil to the Ambers of the League.     The work of the Commission, as defined in the Covenantand in the constitution, is:-1,   To receive and to examine the annual reports which the     .  Mandatory Powers are to render to the Council       concerning the territories committed to their charge;2.   To present to the Council a statement on t-e reports of       the Mandatory lowers.  It shall annex to each report       not only its own observations but also those of the       duly authorised representative of the lower, which       issued the report, if the representative so desires;3*   To hold annually a plenary meeting at Geneva, with all       the duly authorised representatives of the Mandatory       Powers to oonsider all the reports as a whole and any       general conclusions to be drawn from them;4.   To lay before the representatives of the Mandatory lowers       at the meeting, if the commission so desires, any       matters connected with mandates which in their opinion       should be iRiibmitted by the Council to the Mandatery       Powers, and to the other states Members of the League;5.   To summon, if necessary, teohnioal experts to act in an       advisory capacity ior all questions relating to the       observance of the Mandates;6.   To regulate its own procedure subject to the approval of       the Council.     The Coinmisslon is to consider all the annual reportsrendered to the Council by the ^xandatories and must therefore- 3 -
 meet at least once a year,  Although it&apos; would be premature to fis  the date for the fiitt meeting jet as this  should take place before the next  session of the Assembly,  ii would seem advisable that the Commission be appointed as soon as possible.      The following re com/rend at ion to the Council was passed by the  Assembly:           &quot;That the Mandatories should be asked to           &quot;present to the Commission a report on the           &quot;recent administration of the territories           &quot;now confided to  their care.&quot; The Council is oalled upon  to determine whether or not it will adopt this recommendation.        bhouu. the Council decide, to do so, it will be necessary for a formal request in this sense to be addressed to the Mandatory  lowers, and the Commission will have to meet for the examination of these reports when presented,  further the Commission will, at its first meeting, frame its rules or procedure for submission to the  council          It is therefore suggested t at the Commission should be convoked at least 6 v&apos;eeks or a month before the dated fixed for the Assembly,           The date of the convocation should be communicated to the  Mandatories, so that they will be aware of it when preparing the rerorts.                                  V                          - 4 -Whitehall Gardens, o.&apos;ul., 3rd February, 1921.
       COlvfivL^DAT 101Tb  TO THL  C0U1J0IL,  ADOPTED BY TE&amp;  AbbEkBlY,              AT  EPb  MliETIM HELD  ON  aATUEDAY.                18th  December  1920,(morning).        U) KEOOm^DAJIOllo  gggARDIgg THIS MAJDJIT^ COlvflvlIbblON.     1.   The Members of the Commission should not he dismissedwithout the assent of the majority  of the Assembly.     2,   The Commission should contain at least one woman.     3.   The mandatories should be asked to  present to theCommission a report on the recent  administration of  the territoriesnow confided to their care.

</content>
</cab>
