<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 202-203</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

SECRET

?.2526.

CABINET.

GRANTS IN AID OF UNIVERSITY EDUCATION.

Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.



With reference to my memorandum (C.P.2388) on the question of the provision to be made next year for grants in aid of University education, I circulate herewith to the Cabinet a letter which I have received from the President of the Board of Education.



                                                   (Intld.) A.C.



Treasury, S.W.

2nd. February, 1921.




                                                                  Board of Education,

                                                                    Whitehall, S.W.1.

                                                                  6th January, 1921.

My dear Chamberlain,

        

       I hope that the Cabinet Committee on Finance will not find it necessary to curtail the provision which it is proposed to make next year for grants in aid of University Education and that at any rate before a decision is taken I may be heard in support of your proposal for a non-recurrent sum of £500,000 to assist Universities in meeting the grievance of those of their senior members who are precluded from profiting to the full by the benefits of the Federated Universities Superannuation Scheme. Apart from the services of the persons who will be benefited under the proposal (and these include men who have rendered incomparable services in the field of Science, both Puro and Applied), the expenditure of this sum will be a mean of arresting the very strong and I think dangerous current of opinion in the Universities in favour of their comprehension under the Teachers&apos; Superannuation Act. If the older teachers are specially provided for, the younger teachers in Universities will be eventually as well off under the Federated Scheme which is contributory as they would be under the Teachers&apos; Superannuation Scheme which is non-contributory, and consequently once the grievance of the older teachers is removed the case for coming under the Superannuation Act disappears. Now I think it most important, and here I know that you agree with me, that the Universities should not come under this Act. It would be fatal to their autonomy if they did, and it would also involve the State in an expenditure far greater than the non-recurrent contribution which you are proposing to the Cabinet. On the double ground, therefore, of economy and of academic advantage I trust that you will succeed in persuading our Colleagues to allow your original proposal to stand.





                                                      Yours Sincerely,

                                                        (Sd.) H.A.L. FISHER



The Right Hon.

J.Austen Chamberlain, M.P.





</content>
</cab>
