<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 247-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCTJICTT IS TH7&quot; PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT Air &quot;10 MAJT;STY*S GOVERNMENT) I CRFT,!.P, 2537.           o A B -i r ; T .PROPOSALS PQR CONTINUING THE v&apos;OM OP ESTABLISHING            TRADE BOARDS *    (Note &quot;by the Chancellor of the Exchequer).      With reference to the Minister of labourfs Memorandum(C4P.25\2l), relative to the further establishment  of  trade boards, I oiroulate  to the cabinet the fallowing  oerres-pondenoe which has recently passed between the Ministry ofLabour and the Treasury on this subjeot.  My views on theproposals are set out in the -Treasury letter dated l4thJanuary, 19JS1.                              (intld.)  A.C,asury chambers, 4th February,  1921.
1.1285/1920.                                             20th  December,  1920. Sir,      1.  I am directed by the Minister of Labour to refer to previous correspondence between this Department and the Treasury relative to:temporary staff requirements for parrying out the provisions of the Trade &quot;^oaras acts. (Treasury letters dated 29th December, 1919,  No.53674/19, and 26th March, 1920,  Ncl2045/2O) and in particular to Their Loraships&apos; letter of the 3rd December 192o (51,8811), and to submit for Their lordships favourable consideration the following proposals.      2.  in Connection with the programme for the establishment of Trace Boards which was drawn up by sir Robert Korne in November 1919, and approved by the cabinet, a full progress report was furnished to Their Lordships on the 5th November, 1920.  An amended oopy of  this report, &quot;corrected up to the loth. Deaembe-r, 1920,  is enclosed, showing the-&quot;progress mace at that date in the oarrying out of the programme.          in addition to the information given in the previous report there has been added a section (D) showing trai.es in re- gard to  which representations have been received to the effect that, owin;:, to the lack of adequate machinery for the effective regulation of wa^es, investigation is necessary,&apos; but. in which  it has not  yet been practicable to carry investigation very far.   It may be observed that the investigation work which has already  been carried  out has revealed to the Minister further traces, not specifically mentioned in sir Robert Harness report to the Cabinet that appear prima facie to be trades which  call for the applica- tion of  the Trade Boards Acts.           1% is anticipated that  the  sum of  20,000 already sanctioned by Their Lordships will at the present rate of expendi- ture probably be exhausted by the end of pebruary, 1921.  It is estimated that at that date 44 Trade Boards will have be*-.n estab- lished since November 1919  (Great Britain 20, England and Wales 9,  Scotland 5, irelanu lo); that  special Orders will have been issued,  and Traae Boards will be  in  course  of establishment in 5 traues,  whilst statutory Notice of Intention to apply the Acts will have been published in-respect  of 8 further  trades.          Further, it is anticipated  that on the  same  date there will &quot;be  about 92 trades in  which  investigation  remains to be under- taken or completed  in order  to carry  out the programme designed by  sir Robert H&amp;rne,  This  programme, it is considered,  cannot be  completed before  31.12.21. at  the  earliest.      3.   in the light of  the experience  gained  in  the course of the year as to the  complexity of  the  work invclved,  the Minister considers the progress made witv  the  programme  satisfactory, but it  will  be apporent  from  the  facts  given above,  that  a  censidera- . ble volume of work  still  remains  to  be  accomplished  and  that it will not be possible, under the present limited sanction, to com- plete  the work of establishing Trade  Boards in  the  various trades to  which, in  the Ministers  opinion,  the  application of  the Trade Boards Acts is imperative  for  the reasons  stated in  sir Robert Herne*s  memorandum  to  the  Cabinet.  It may  be mentioned  that tradesSecretary,H.M,  Treasury,   Whitehall,  s.W. 1.
at present &quot;being investigate^, induce nany&apos;Distributive Traces,and that the Minister is pledged to apply the  Acts  as  speedilyas possible to all the main Distributive  Trades.  In these cir-oumstances the Minister has no alternative but tc ask  for anextension of the existing sanction (with  the modifications setout below) for a further periid of 12 months.   He conaideres thatthis proposal reoeivee weighty support  from the additionalexperienoe gained in the last year of the value cf  Trade boards in securing and maintaining industrial  stability  in a  time ofgreat unrest.    4.  I am to state that, with a view to the co-ordination ofthe intelligence trOrk cf the Department generally and  io ihe most economical use of the staff available for the  duties of investi-gation fur Trade Boards and other purposes, the Minister haetransferred the control of the Trade Boards temporary  Investiga-tion staff tc the Assistant secretary in  charge of  the Intelli-gence Division.  The advantage cf this  measure in the  generalscheme cf the Department will be apparent, but owin^ to thedemands made upon this service it Is impossible to  Bay whether any direct saving will immediately result.                                                                 *    6*  in submitting this proposal for an extensicn of theexisting sanction authorised in Their Lordships4  letter abcvereferred to and modified as regards rates of pay  by the Z0foBonus increase sanctioned in Sir Malcolm  Ramsay*e letter of the28th October, 192C,  No.35.1760, the Minister desires me to requestTheir lordships* authority to pay the rates of salary  approved for men investigators and Heads of Groups in cases  ^aere menInvestigators are employed in substitution for women.  The numberof posts in which substitution has been effected  is 5  in all,which is not likely to increase.  The Minister has  received re-presentations from the Temporary staff  Association  drawing attention to the fact that certain men  investigators are being paid at the lower rate approved for women for  identical duties,and he feels that, although in fact there has  been  a differentia-tion in the duties the position is not  a satisfactory  one.    6.  The Minister considers also that  a similar  differentia-tion of salary as betv/een men and women efficers  should be adoptedin the case of the trvc posts of supervisor, approved for womenat an inclusive rate of  500 p.a. plus  the additional  ZC% Bonusand I am to request that you will move  Their Lordships toauthorise payment of salary at the rate tf  700 P*a. inclusivewhere a male  officer is appointed to either  cf these  posts,one of which it has already been found  necessary  to fill by atemporary male officer.    7.  with regard tc temporary/- Administrative  Staff, I am tostate that the experience gained during tho  current year hasshown that the 5 posts sanctioned are  quite inadequate to dealwith the large  volume of administrative  work  which follows thecompletion of investigation and precedes  the initial meeting ofa Trade Board, and further that the rate  of pay offered,  350p,a. inclusive, is not sufficient to enable the Department tosecure and retain the type of man with  the necessary experience and ability.        I am accordingly to request that Their lordships m&amp;be pleased to sanction an addition of  3 temporary administrativeposts, making 8 in all, and an increase In the inclusive rateuf remuneration, raising it tc  450 P*a.
     8,  A statement of.the? total estimated cost of these  pro-posals is annexed.                                     . I-     9.  in-Tier of the imminent; expiry of the present sanction for the Trace Boards temporary staff. T&apos; am to request ,that you &apos;will 1)t good enough to move&apos;Their Lordships to give considera-tion to these proposals at an early date.                     I have the honour to he,  Sir,                             Your obedient Servant,                          (Signed)  A,wh  WATSON-
TRACT! BOARDS TEMPORARY ITOSTIGATIC1 AlfD, AD?I&quot;INISTRATIVE                      STAPP,   Existing  sanction(X. 26/3/20,,Fo. 12045/20.)present ProposalsEstimatedcost over12 months.Administrative officers at              420 P*a.K&quot;oman supervisor at  600 p*a-eads of Groups (men)$  300- 400 p.m. plus  T.rar Bonus.[eads of Groups (women)il  360 P*m.investigating officers (men) :  360 p.m.nvestigating officers         (women)Q  300 p.a.                              8 Administrative Officers    7 U  450 P.a.           3150    10  300- ft00 P*m*      Plus har Bonus         600 1 supervisor (Man at       700 p.a.              700 3 Heads of Groups(men  1 0  300- 400 p.-.    plus Yfar Bonus.           600  2.0  420 p.a.              840. 1 Head ef Group^ woman)    0  360 p.a.              36035 Investigations Officers ...  O  360 p.m. (Men)        12600 7 investigating Officers            (women)    $  300 P-a.             2109Clerical-Staff (say)20950 400024950.JC inclusive salaries throughout increased by 20$  Treasury letter 28/10/20, E. 1760./ 1 Head of Group  300- 400 plus war bonus&apos;  transferred to Administrative Section.
Treasury Chambers.-   14th January,  1921..Sir,.     I have laic, before the Lords Commissioners of HisMajesty s Treasury Mr. Watson&apos;s letter of the 20th ultimo(E.1.1265/1920) submitting proposals for the extendedapplication of the Trade Boards Acts,  1909 ahd 1918,. and forthe retention of the temporary staff at present engaged on work in connection with those Acts and for the engagement ofadditional temporary staff,- the total  cost of the proposalsover a period of 12 months bein.-s estimated at  24,6&apos; 50.     in reply i am directed to request you to inform theMinister of Labour that My Lords consider that the applica-tion cf the Trade Boards Acts to traces to which they dcnot at present apply falls within the  Cabinet decisionannounced in the House of commons on the  9th ultimo,and within Treasury Circular Fo,65/20  of the 17th ultimobased thereon,, and I am accordingly to request that thecourse indicated in that circular may  be followed shouldyour Department desire to obtain fresh authority from theCabinet for these proposals.-     In this connection, but subject to such further representations as may be made by the  Minister of Labour,.I am to offer the following observations.     1.  On the last occasion when the extension of theTrade ^crds Acts was considered and approved by theCabinet, on the 26th November, 1919, the proposal beforethe c&amp;binet was for the estabjd Bhrnart  of some 100 trade boards, the completion of the bulk of  the work beingcontemplated within one year at a cost 4 1/2 temporary staff estimated at  20,000*  My Lords  understand thatthis bum is expected T.O be exhausted by the end of&apos;February next, and They observe that in addition W the prolongation of the work for a further period of IS monthsit is also proposed to apply the Acts to Traces not included in the original list.     2.  Apart from the extension of the scheme thenapproved in time, cost and subject matter, liy Lords attacheven more importance to the change which has taken place inthe economic situation since November 1919.&apos;  A principalfactor, in the then decision was the fear that unorganisedtraces, without the guidance of a r. to fixed by a trade board, would fix a flat minimum wage unrelated to actualpractice or to bhe ability of the trade to bear it.My Lords consider that there is at the present time no serious danger of this occurrin?;,-     3.  it appears to Their Lordships that the presentneed  of industry is not the fixing of wa^es but the finding of work, - and They deplore the rD.sk of aggravatingunemployment which the estaKi: ehmcnt of further trade boards mf &amp;ht in the pie Bent juncture product-!;, while evenapart frun rurh i?sk. the erpeura^ur-e involved in theprelim:n?ir insert: gat.i ons, W.H. the L-vbPecuent estab--li  hmeiii. of a board; by adding to the financial burdenof the c ommun: i-:,. at. large, contributes in itself to restrict employment.
     4,  if, notwithstanding,  a further extension  of  trade boards is  aesirec,  Their lordships would he  glad  toreceive an indication oi the nature of the traces  to  whichthe Minister of Labour considers that the Acts should befurther extended.  It Y/ill be remembered that in origintrade boards, as established, by the Act of 1909, were confined to what were popularly described as  sweatedtrades, namely &quot;travailleur:.es in which the rate of wages  pre-vailing in any branch of the trade is exceptionally lowas compared with that in other employments&quot;.   The  powersof the Minister of labour under the Act of 1918 extend to trades in vhich no effective machinery exists for  the efficient regulation of wages; throughout the  trade ana towhich he is accordingly of opinion that,  having regard to therates of wages prevailing in the trade, it is expedient that the Act of 1909 should apply.  Prom the  listsenclosed in the 1 tter under reply of traees  for whichboards have either been established or are contemplated, thelow paid nature of a trade appears to be no longer the criterion, and My Lords would be glad to receive informa-tion on this subject, as They are apprehensive that withoutany precise criterion the expenditure upon staff engagedin the investigation of trades may prove very indefinite.     5.  Assuming a further extension of trade boardsto be in itself desirable, it appears to Their Lordshipsthat such an extension cannot be considered essentialto trace at the present moment.  It is of course,  onlyin comparatively few traces that such boards  EXI3T, andtheir introduction into further traues appears to  Their .Lordships, assuming its eventual desirability,  to  beessentially one of those reforms described in theCabinet decision above referred to as desirable in them-selves but for the initiation of which the present time is not opportune.  My Lords accordingly,  as intinatedabove, regret th;.t in the absence of a further aecisionof His Majesty1 s Government upon the question of policy involved, They are not prepared to sanction theadditional expenditure proposed.  In order however togive the Board reasonable time for further consideration,Their Lordships are willing that the existing temporary staff should be retained not later than the 31st march next, provided that savings on the Vote are available tomeet that cost.                 I am,                      Sir,                          Your obedient servant.(Sgda)   G,L.  BARSTOW.

</content>
</cab>
