<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 303-330</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FOR OFFICIAL  USE  ONLY.Vol.  Ill, No.  6.  5.2.21.[This  Document is the  Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]mtMINISTRY  OF  LABOUR.WEEKLY REPORT.5TH FEBRUARY, 1921.PART  I.-THE LABOUR  SITUATION.PART  II.-THE  WORK OF  THE MINISTRYPREPARED BY  INTELLIGENCE DIVISION.CONTENTS.PART  1.-THE LABOUR SITUATION.WEEK  ENDING THE 1ST FEBRUARY, 1921.THE GENERAL SITUATION-   General Survey of the Week   The Unemployment PositionFEATURES OF THE WEEK-   Unemployment   ......   General Topics    ......   Control of IndustryPAGE 122 123123125126FEATURES OF THE WEEK continued.   Trade Union TopicsNEGOTIATIONS AND DISPUTES-   Demands and Negotiations   Strikes and Lock-Outs   Settlements and AgreementsPAGE 127128129130PART.II.-THE  WORK OF THE MINISTRY.    WEEK ENDING THE 29TH JANUARY, 1921.INDUSTRIAL relations DEPARTMENT-     PAGE   Engineering,  Shipbuilding  and  Allied     Trades  ...............131   Woodworking and Furnishing  ......  131   Building and Works of Construction   ...  132   Quarrying...............  133   Food and Drink  ...  &apos;.........  133   Pottery, Rubber and Glass    ......  133   Textiles............    ...  134   Leather and Boots and Shoes   ......  135   Mining -  ...............  135   Public Authorities  and Public Utility     Services...............135   Government Departments.........  136   Miscellaneous Trades     .........  137   Professional Workers    .........  138   General   ............    ...  138GENERAL DEPARTMENT  Trade Boards    Proceedings...............  139   (B 16930T)  1050  2/21  H &amp; S Ltd.GENERAL DEPARTMENT continued.          PAGE   Fixing and Variation of Minimum Rates     of Wages...............140   Establishment and Amendment of Trade     Boards   ...   ............  140EMPLOYMENT AND INSURANCE DEPARTMENT    Employment Exchanges......    ...  140   Local Employment Committees ...    ...  143   Out-of-work  Donation  and Unemploy-     ment Insurance Benefit......  143   Juvenile Branch  ............  143APPOINTMENTS AND CIVIL LIABILITIES DEPART-,  MENT    Appointments    ............   Business and Professional TrainingTRAINING DEPARTMENT-   Industrial Training     ......144144
PART I-THE  LABOUR  SITUATION.THE   GENERAL  SITUATION.General Survey of the Week.    The most important labour event of the week has been the special Trades Union andLabour Conference at the Kingsway Hall, London,  on the 27th January, to consider thereport of the Joint Committee on Unemployment, appointed by the Parliamentary Com-mittee of the Trades Union Congress and the Labour Party Executive, on the 11th January.The conference may be said to  have proceeded  &quot; according to plan.&quot;  The  resolutionssubmitted, full particulars  of which are given below,  were passed unanimously, aftercomparatively little discussion ; and the conference then adjourned until the 23rd February,to enable the  executives of the trade unions to ascertain, in the meantime, the views  ofthe rank and file on  the steps to be taken to secure the adoption of the committee&apos;s recom-mendations.   The speeches  made at the conference were, generally speaking, moderate andrestrained ; but the opinion is widely held that some kind of action may be taken when theadjourned conference meets again.   Certain unions  are  already reported to be arranging for a ballot  of their members on the question of the adoption of a &quot; down tools &quot; policy,in the event of the Government refusing to accede to the demands of the conference.    Other trade union conferences, which may have important results, have also been held.during the week.  The  executive committee  of the  Miners&apos; Federation  of Great Britainmet on the 26th January, and this meeting was followed by a special delegate  conferenceof the Federation, on the  26th,  27th and 28th, which  discussed  a variety of importanttopics.*  A  special  delegate conference of the  Amalgamated Engineering  Union washeld at the  Central  Hall, Westminster,  on the  27th  and 28th January, when  the refusal of the  engineering employers to  concede an advance in wages was discussed.  The con-ference also considered the unemployment position, and authorised the executive committeeto make a further levy, if necessary, for the relief of unemployed members.   At each  ofthese conferences the Labour policy on unemployment was discussed and endorsed.    The representatives of  the International Snipping  Federation and the InternationalSeamen&apos;s Federation concluded, on the 26th January, their conference at Brussels on thequestion of hours of labour  on board ship.  It was decided to entrust  the examinationof the technical details to two commissions, one  of  which will deal with the deck andengine-room staffs, and the other with the general service staffs.   These  commissions willmeet within 30 days and prepare a report, which will be submitted to a new  conference,to be convened by the Director of the International Labour Office.   The conference justconcluded is of special interest in view of the fact  that it is the first example of twointernational  organisations,  representing employers   and employed  in  a particular industry, meeting with  a view to arriving at  an agreement  on conditions of work.    The general  industrial situation remains  quiet.  A crisis is said  to be imminenton the railways in consequence of the difference  between the Amalgamated engineering union  and the National Union of Railwaymen,  which is now the only obstacle to theprogress of negotiations on the question of shopmen&apos;s wages and conditions of work.  Jointconferences of the executives of the  two unions were held cn the  25th and 26th january and the 1st February, with a view to adjusting  the difference between the unions.   ASpecial General Meeting of the National Union has been called for the 3rd February to receive    * For the conclusions of the conference on the wages negotiations with the Mining Association of GreatBritain, see below, under Negotiations and Disputes; for their  decisions on Labour unemployment policy,see below, under Unemployment;  for their  resolution on the amendment of the Workmen&apos;s.  CompensationAct, see below, under General Topics; and  for their decision with  regard to the joint  agreement with theAmalgamated Engineering Union, see below, under Trade  Union  Topics.  The resolution of  the  executive of the Miners&apos; Federation with regard to the de-control  of  the mining  industry is  dealt with below, under control of Industry.
General  Situation-continued.a report on the shopmen&apos;s position, and to decide on the policy to be pursued.   The Courtof Inquiry appointed by the Minister to inquire into the causes and circumstances of thedispute between the employers and workpeople in the Tramway  Industry  sat on the26th,  27th  and 28th January, and will resume their sittings on the 2nd February.  TheSecretary for Mines announces that the amount of the wages advance payable to collieryworkers, under the strike settlement of November last,  will be reduced for the month ofFebruary.   Particulars of the reduction are given on page 130 below.    The National Federation of Building  Trades Operatives have cdled a  conferenceof the executives of the  affiliated unions  for the 3rd February to decide upon a reply tothe Governments proposals for the admission of not less than 50,000 ex-Service men intothe building industry.  It is  anticipated  that these proposals will be rejected, and  thatcounter-proposals will be made by the Federation.The Unemployment Position.    Statistics. The number of H.M. Forces and merchant seamen out-of-work donation  .policies lodged in the United Kingdom on the 21st January was 324,318 of which 307,276were lodged by men and 442 by women totally unemployed, and 16,451 by men and 149 by women working short time.  On the 14th January there were 314,703 policies lodged, ofwhich 298,963  were lodged by men and 542 by women totally unemployed, and 15,113 by men and 85 by women working short time.    On the 21st January in the United Kingdom 1,221,757 unemployment books remainedlodged under the Unemployment Insurance Act, of which 345,009 were lodged by men and274,754 by women totally unemployed, and 226,585 by men and 375,409 by women workingshort  time.   An increase, on the previous week, of 71,716 totally unemployed, and 31,001working short time.   The total on the live register of all Employment Exchanges in theUnited Kingdom  on the 28th January was 1,059,800.  The above are  advance figuresprovided by the Employment Department and are subject to revision.    A full analysis of the unemployment position will be found on page 140.FEATURES  OF   THE  WEEK.Unemployment.    Labour Policy. A special delegate conference of the Labour Party and the TradesUnion Congress was held on the 27th January at the Kingsway Hall, London, to considerthe report on unemployment of the joint sub-committee appointed by the parliamentary committee of the Trades Union Congress and the National Executive of the Labour Party.The conference, which was presided over by Mr. E. L. Poulton, was Of similar type to thatcalled at the time of the Polish crisis when the Council of Action was formed ;  that is tosay, it was a meeting  of the full executives, or their representatives,  of the trade unions and local Labour organisations, and was, therefore, in a position not merely to recommenda policy for adoption, but also to authorise action to secure its adoption.  The form assumed by  the conference may, therefore, be regarded as an indication  that Labour will do its best to ensure that the remedies and measures recommended, of which the principal is auniversal scheme of maintenance, applicable to workers on short time, as well as to personstotally unemployed, are actually put into  operation.   The atmosphere of the conference,however, was anything but bellicose.  There was no opposition to the proposal to adjourndiscussion of active  measures until&apos;the 23rd February, when the conference reassembles,and none of the speeches, excepting that of Mr.  Neil Maclean, advocated the  adoptionof other than constitutional methods.    The findings of the sub-committee* were embodied in the first resolution on the agenda,which declared that the conference endorsed and accepted the report.  In the absence ofMr. Clynes, Mr. Frank Hodges  proposed  the resolution, in a forcible speech dealing^at great length with the proposals contained  in the report.  He stated emphatically that theconference would refuse to accept the view that  the best way to restore  the industrialbalance was by means of a reduction of wages.  Mr. Ben Turner, in seconding the resolution,advocated peaceable methods to obtain the  consent of the  Government to the  measures proposed.  The resolution was carried unanimously.               * See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 5*, 29th January, p. 99.(B 16930T)Q2
    Mr. J. H. Thomas, M.P., moved the second resolution, which proposed that the reporttogether with the first resolution, should be communicated  to the  Prime Minister  forthe consideration of the Cabinet; sent to every member of the House of Commons; andtransmitted to the trade unions and  local Labour Parties for such action as they may think fit,  and, in particular, with the suggestion that they should take steps to bring theproposals  before  the members  of Parliament for their several  constituencies, either  byinviting them to  attend conferences, or to address  public meetings on the subject, or  bydeputation, or otherwise.    The Parliamentary Labour Party  are requested to bring the matter before the Houseof Commons at the beginning of the session, unless the  Government have in the meantimetakensatisfactory action &quot; ; and the conference stands adjourned until the 23rd february to enable  the executives of the trade  unions to take the opinion of their members withregard to  further steps. Mr. Thomas  laid great stress on the  efforts that could be made before the adjourned meeting to secure the adoption of Labour&apos;s proposals without havingrecourse to direct action.  Mr.  A.  A.  Purcell seconded the  resolution, and Mr.  RobertWilliams  followed with an unusually moderate  speech.   The resolution was  carriedunanimously  without alteration or amendment.    A request which  was made  during the proceedings, that the conference should receive a deputation  from the London  District Council of Unemployed Organisations, was refused,on the ground that the unemployed were fully represented by the conference.    The resolutions on the agenda of  the conference were fully discussed at the nationaldelegate conference of  the Miners&apos;  Federation of Great Britain on the previous day, andit was unanimously decided to  support them.    A special meeting  of the executive council of the National Union of Boot and  ShoeOperatives was held on  the 27th January, and it was decided that a ballot of the members should be  taken on the following declaration: &quot; That we support the policy for dealing withthe question  of unemployment as  stated in  the resolutions passed at the joint LabourConference on the 27th January.  Further,  we declare  that  we empower the  executive of the union  to act in  our  behalf in any action that may be  thought necessary,  even ifsuch action may mean a stoppage of  one day  as  a demonstration for the enforcement of the same.&quot;    Relief of  Unemployment. Nothing of importance  is reported.  As  was stated lastweek, the  opposition  to the Government^ short-time scheme ended in a decision to await the announcement of the general Labour policy on  this question; and short-time workinghas now been introduced  in Government establishments.    Specific proposals for dealing with unemployment in Scotland were put forward by adeputation from the  Scottish Central  Committee on Unemployment who were receivedby the Minister of Labour and  the Secretary of State for Scotland on the 27th January.The  comnlittee  asked  that permanent machinery for  dealing with unemployment inScotland snould be created, and suggested a national committee of an advisory character,whose  function would  he to co-ordinate and  regulate  undertakings which would absorbnumbers of the unemployed. Dr. Macnamara and  Mr. Munro replied, the latter statingthat he was disposed  to favour the establishment of such a committee, provided that  its functions were of a purely advisory character.   The general  situation in Scotland was discussed  at some length.    Effect on Trade Unions. There are some further indications of the serious effect oi theunemployment situation upon  trade  unions  in the textile industry.  The Preston  Cardand Blowing  Room and Ring Spinners&apos; Association, who suspended benefits to membersat the beginning  of the year,  have now  been obliged to secede from the AmalgamatedAssociation of Card and Blowing Room Operatives, and to suspend, temporarily, all their activities.   The executive council of the Yorkshire Cotton Operatives&apos; Association reduced their scale of payment  when the proportion of members drawing benefits reached 75 percent,  of  the  total, and  have  now recommended total suspension.   It is  anticipatedthat there will be a wages crisis in Jane when the  existing agreement terminates; fundswill be needed then, and members are therefore asked to do the best they can on thepayments  which they now receive under the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, and fromthe Cotton Reconstruction  Board..-This recommendation was endorsed at  a  specialdelegate meeting  on  the 22nd  January, only one branch voting against it.  It was also decided that unemployed members should pay a penny per week to the Association to keepthemselves in full benefit.   This is also to apply to  members working less than 20 hours a,week, while all members working a full week have  agreed to pay a levy of Qd. a week toa special relief fund for cases of extreme hardship.
   * This decision of the Government was communicated on the 7th January by the Secretary of State foHome Affairs to a deputation of the executive committee of the Miners&apos; Federation.   t See p. 124. above.  General Topics.      Workmen&apos;s  Compensation Act. The  national  delegate  conference  of  the Miners&apos;  Federation of Great Britain, at their meeting on the 28th January, discussed the decision  of the Government that it would not he possible to introduce into Parliament in the 1921  session a Bill  to amend the Workmens Compensation Act, 1906.*  The miners  desire  such legislation  in order to bring into effect  the recommendations presented last July  by the Departmental Committee, under the chairmanship of Mr. Holman Gregory, K.C.,  M.P.,  appointed  by the Secretary of State for Home Affairs in May, 1919, to inquire into  the system of compensation for injuries to workmen.  The miners&apos; conference passed a  resolution protesting against the decision of the  Government, and urging the Parliamentary  Committee of the Trades Union Congress, the National Executive of the Labour Party, the  Parliamentary Labour Party, and the local Labour Parties, to bring all possible  pressure  to bear with a view to securing an immediate  reversal  of the Governments decision.  It  was further decided that, in the event of this not taking place, the Parliamentary Committee  of the Trades Union Congress, and the National Executive of the Labour Party, should  be asked to bring the whole  question before the adjourned  joint delegate  conference,  which is to be held under their auspices on the 23rd February to review the unemploy-  ment  position.!      Trade Boards Acts. The  protests of  various employers against the  working of the  Trade Boards  Acts have given rise  to criticisms from various employees&apos; associations.  The January number of the Dundee Jute and Flax  Workers&apos;  Guide contains a reply to  the  statements,  recorded in last week&apos;s Report,  of Mr.  David Douglas, who  acted as  spokesman for a  deputation from  the  Aberdeen Chamber of Commerce received by the  Minister during his recent visit to that city.  In this reply, it is stated that any opposition  to Trade Boards on the part of employees is based on the belief that the minimum rates  of wages set up by the Boards are  too low, and not, as in Mr. Douglas&apos;s opinion, because  they are too high.  That this is also the view of  other employees is borne out by the action  of the Scottish Federation of  the  Shop Assistants&apos;  Union, who have adopted proposals.  for a minimum rate of wages for men and women employed in the grocery trade, which  are considerably in excess of the rates proposed by the Grocery Trade Board, while the  latter  are in turn criticised by the employers and by the Grocers&apos; Chamber of  Trade as  being  far too high.      The proposal to institute a Trade Board for the baking industry is strongly  opposed  by the National  Association of Master Bakers, Confectioners and Caterers, as it is held  that the establishment of a high minimum rate of wages tends to create  unemployment,  and that &quot; bureaucratic interference &quot; is not in the best interests of the trade.      Building Guilds. The movement for  the establishment of a  National Guild uniting  the two existing organisations, and for a system of inter-control  between the new body&apos;  and the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives, has advanced a step further  during the week.  Two meetings between representatives  of the guilds  and the Emer-  gency Committee of the Federation have been held, one in  Manchester, and one in London.  In both cases, the board of directors of the guild met the Committee, and, after discussion,  the latter were authorised to investigate the position of the guilds from the point of view  of the operatives. So far, the chief  consideration  has been the nature of  the relation  between  the guilds and the Federation ;   and it is not  certain to what  extent  the  scheme  to  co-ordinate the  work of the  London  and   Manchester organisations  has  advanced.      The first conference of Scottish Guild Committees  was held on the 22nd January in  Glasgow.  Mr. S. G.  Hobson,  secretary of  the Manchester Guild, presided, and  40 dele-  gates attended from different districts throughout Scotland.  Two resolutions were carried,  the first providing that a Regional Council be formed for Scotland to co-ordinate the work  of the committees there; the second stating &quot; that, having regard to the attack made upon  the Building Guilds by the Ministry of Health  and the master builders, this conference of  Scottish Building Guilds, having before it^the result of guild building in England, particu-  larly in South Wales,  Lancashire  and Yorkshire, where  the Building Guild are  erecting  artisan houses at  150 per house cheaper than the master builders in the same localities,  and realising that this result is in part due to the security of employment obtained by the
system of &apos; continuous pay,&apos; urges upon the Government the necessity of recognising thiscontinuous pay as an economic charge upon the building industry, and in no sense asremuneration.&quot;  Mr.  John Winning was appointed  regional officer  for Scotland.    In connection with the &quot; attack &quot; alleged to have  been made on  the guilds by theMinistry of Health, an official statement was recently made to the effect that  no furtherguild  contracts  would be sanctioned  unless the terms  of  contract were revised.   As aresult of representations put forward by the guilds, the Minister has agreed that an  addi-tional 6 contracts may be undertaken to bring the number up to that originally sanctioned,namely 20,  only 14  of  these having  received sanction at the  time  when the official announcement was made.    Labour and Ireland. It is reported that miners employed at Giffnoch Colliery, Glasgow,carried out a one-day strike on the 25th January, as a protest against  the GovernmentsIrish policy.  At a mass meeting of the men, a resolution was passed calling upon theLanarkshire County Miners&apos; Union  to organise, as a further protest, a 48-hour stoppage of work.    The  dispute referred to in last week&apos;s issue  of  this Report,  between the executivecouncil  of the  Amalgamated  Society of Carpenters, Cabinet Makers  and Joiners, andcertain members of the Belfast branch, still continues; and a meeting of delegates repre-senting trade unions  connected with the shipbuilding  industry  was held, on the  26thJanuary, to discuss  the report  of  the  sub-committee appointed by the parliamentary committee of the Trades Union Congress to inquire into the dispute.  A small committee,consisting of representatives of the unions,  was appointed to act with the sub-committee,with a view to bringing about an agreement.  The question is also reported to  have beentaken up by the Amalgamated Engineering Union, and was discussed at a recent meetingof the National Committee.   There was some  disagreement as to the best methods ofsolving the problem, but a  resolution was passed recommending that a committee of fiveshould be appointed to meet  the expelled members of the carpenters&apos; union  in Belfastto discuss the situation, and endeavour to find some means of settlement.  This  committeeis to consist of two members of the  executive council of the union, two  from the national committee, and one from the  organising district delegates.  The  question of legal action is still being considered by  the Belfast branch ;  and the executive council of the Amalga-mated Society have been severely criticised by some of the branches on account of theirattitude with regard to the situation.    International Miners&apos; Federation. A meeting of the Executive  Council was held inLondon on the  24th and 25th January, under  the  chairmanship of  Mr. Robert Smillie.Delegates were  present  from  France,  Belgium, Holland,  Germany, Hungary, Austria,Czechoslovakia,  Poland,  and  Great Britain.  A resolution  was passed  noting  that  over-time had been  imposed on  German miners &quot; in direct opposition to  the decisions of theWashington Labour Convention,&quot; while food supplies were inadequate; and the miners in all countries  were called  upon to  suppress overtime, on the ground that if &quot; productionfalls below the world&apos;s demand, it should only be made good by improving the technique of production, and not by the extension of the working day.&quot;  The Council also decidedthat the  International Labour Office should be called upon to &quot; set  up an international control Board, for the sharing and exchange of all raw materials indispensable for therestoration of all countries.&quot;    The  Council declared that the  only effective method of restoring national industries and international commerce was  by international co-operation, with a view to  stabilisingthe rates of exchange.  It  was  decided that copies  of the resolutions passed  should be forwarded to the heads of  the Governments  of the  Allies  at the Conference then being held at Paris.Control of Industry.    Mining Industry. The executive of the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain met onthe 26th January to  consider a communication made by  the President of the Board ofTrade with regard to the question of de-controlling the mining industry.  It was resolved to inform the President that, after giving full consideration to his statement, the executivecould not acquiesce in any proposal for the de-control of  the coal trade until the  coal-owners&apos; and the miners&apos;  representatives were able to present to the  Government a  plan,jointly agreed upon,  for the  national  control of the industry, which  would  effectivelytake the place of the present arrangements.  This decision was conveyed by a deputation to the  Secretary for Mines  on the 27th January.
 Trade Union Topics.     Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain and the Amalgamated Engineering  Union. The national delegate conference of the Miners&apos; Federation discussed, at their meeting on the  28th January,  the proposed  working  agreement between the Federation and  the Amalgamated  Engineering Union  with regard  to the position of members  of  the latter union employed in  or about collieries.*  Under the proposed  agreement, the members of the  Amalgamated  Engineering Union will be controlled by the miners&apos; associations in so far as industrial questions are concerned.  In the case of mining disputes, for example, members of the  Amalgamated Engineering  Union will tender  notices  simultaneously with the miners, either nationally or locally, and will be officially supported in such action by their executive.  The engineers will also be included in all applications for improvement of wages and conditions of service put forward by the Miners&apos;  Federation.   In addition to their own trade union cards, they  will be granted cards  of membership of the district associations, who are  members of the Miners&apos;  Federation.  A joint sub-committee of the  two organisations will adjudicate  when any questions  arise on the interpretation of the  agreement.     This agreement  was  ratified  by  the miners&apos;  delegate conference;  it  had  already received the sanction  of  the Amalgamated Engineering Union.   It  will be  subject to review  after the lapse of  12 months.     Amalgamated Society  of Woodworkers. The relation of this society to the proposed &quot;General  Combination of  Ship  Constructional and Engineering Workers,&quot;  which is shortly to supersede the Engineering  and Shipbuilding  Trades Federation,! and to  the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives, has been under consideration;  and it has been decided, with regard  to  the latter,  that payments shall  only  be  made  for members of the Amalgamated  Society who are employed in the  building industry.   No additional  levy will be made to assist in financing the proposed General Combination, but  an amount equal to  6d. per quarter for each member engaged in the shipbuilding and  engineering industries  will be paid into the general funds.  The Council of the General Combination will also have power,  in certain circumstances,  to ask for a levy of not more than Qd. per week from each member coming, within their jurisdiction ;  such circumstances would be a partial strike  or lock-out  in any area, or an excessive number of members involved in a  dispute.  In such an event,  members  of the Amalgamated  Society who would be affected would receive their ordinary trade privileges from their own Union, and, in addition, from  the  Combination, orders on a local  co-operative stores for necessaries,pro rata to the number of  dependants.    * Friction between the Amalgamated Society of Engineers and the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation onthis demarcation question became acute in the early  months  of last  year, and the Amalgamated Societycommenced an action in the Chancery Division (Rosser and Jones v. Hawkins) against a local official of the SouthWales Miners&apos; Federation,  The. action, however, was withdrawn before hearing, and efforts were made tosecure a national demarcation agreement.   Meetings  took place on the 8th June and the 14th July last,between the  executives  of the Amalgamated  Society and of the Miners&apos; Federation of  Great Britain,at which a preliminary working agreement was reached.  The scheme outlined above appears to be basedupon the proposals put forward at the first of the joint conferences by the Amalgamated Society of Engineers.Further particulars will be found in the Report, New Series, No. 21, 19th June, 1920, p. 712, and Vol. II,No.  4, 24th July, p. 134.    t See this Report, Vol. II, No. 24, 11th December,  p. 656;    This question of the continuance of the statutory control of the finance of the industry,including  the regulation of the  distribution  of profits  and the determination  of  wagesquestions, should not be confused with the control of the price and. distribution of coal.The Mines Department of the Board of Trade announced, on the 1st February, that on and from  the 1st March next the regulation of the pit-head prices and the control  of the domestic distribution of coal would  cease;  hut the President of the  Board of Trade, onthe same day, announced that the control of finance, while it was not being taken  off onthe 1st March along with these other controls, would be taken off as soon as it was prac-ticable to  do so.
NEGOTIATIONS  AND  DISPUTES. Demands and Negotiations.     Engineers (National). It will be recalled that the joint conference of representativesof the Amalgamated Engineering Union and the Engineering and the National Employers&apos;Federations, which was resumed at York on the 8th December, reached a deadlock  onthe wages question, consequent upon the request of the representatives of the Federationsthat consideration should be adjourned for six months.*   The employers had accompaniedtheir proposal for the postponement of the wages demand with an undertaking on their part to maintain the existing rates in the meantime.   The executive of the union, however,had felt themselves unable to agree to this course upon their own responsibility, in viewof the acute feeling prevailing in some of the districts.  A national conference of delegates of the union met in London on the 27th January to consider the position, and adopted thefollowing resolution;            &quot; That this conference empowers the Executive Committee and Council immediately to open       negotiations with the employers&apos; federation for the consolidation of wages; further, to press for the       Qd. per hour at the earliest favourable opportunity; also to get into touch with the other unions       in the engineering industry and endeavour to secure united  action with the object of obtaining our       claim in accordance with the application.&quot;     The other unions referred to in this resolution are the Federation of Engineering and shipbuilding Trades and the  National Federation of General Workers.   The position is complicated by the fact that the  Federation  of Engineering  and Shipbuilding  Tradesagreed with the Engineering and the National Employers&apos; Federations on the 16th december to adjourn  the consideration of the claim for a wages increase for  six months, while  onthe other hand, on the 21st January, the Shipbuilding Employers&apos; Federation not onlyrejected the wages claim put forward by the Federation but refused to agree to a proposalfor the stabilisation of wages  for six months.f     Railway Vehicle Building and  Repairing Operatives  (Midlands). The  complexities of organisations in the railway vehicle building and repairing  industry  have produced a considerable  amount of unrest  in the  Midlands.  A large number of  railway vehiclebuilding  and repairing  firms are  in the  Engineering and the  National  Employers&apos;Federations. The majority of the remaining firms are members of the wagon builders&apos;and the wagon  repairers&apos; associations, who  are represented  in wages negotiations by aJoint Wages Board.  In the past, the custom has been for the Engineering and the NationalEmployers&apos;  Federations to take the initiative with regard to wages agreements, and theJoint Wages Board  have followed.   A new  precedent, which reversed the position, was created by the agreement made by the Joint Wages Board last  August with the Amalga-mated Society of Railway Vehicle Builders, Wheelwrights, Carpenters   and Mechanics,under which the members of the  union obtained 53s. Qd., plus 26s. 6d., plus 12J per cent.a week, making 90s. in all.   The present strained situation in the Midlands arose out  ofthe fact that neither the Engineering and the National Employers&apos; Federations nor theJoint Wages Board have made agreements with any  of the other unions having members in the industry,  among which unions are the  Amalgamated Engineering Union, the Amal-gamated Union of Shipbuilding,  Engineering and Constructional Workers, the Amalga-mated  Society  of  Woodcutting   Machinists,   and  the Workers&apos; Union.    Although      * See this Report, Vol. II, No. 25,18th December, p. 682.      t See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 1,1st January,  p. 8 ; and No. 5, 29th January, p. 102.    Trade Union Amalgamations. The following further amalgamations are reported:            Monmouthshire and South W ales Colliery Enginemen, Stokers and Surface Craftsmen&apos;s Association-       It was announced at a meeting of this Association, on the 28th January, that the amalgamation of       the association with the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation would take effect as from the 29th January.       A ballot of the members of the Federation,  which had previously  been taken, resulted in 102,648       votes in favour of amalgamation, and 73,738 against.           United^ Operative Plumbers and Domestic Engineers&apos; Association. The amalgamation of the       Scottish Operative Plumbers&apos; Association with the above association has now been completed, and       is to take effect as from the  1st January.
Negotiations  and Disputes-continued.negotiations have been in progress between the latter unions, represented by the Birming-ham Joint Committee of Engineering Trade Unions, and the Joint Wages Board.  but when the Joint Committee, in an endeavour to establish for their  members rates higherthan those accepted by the Amalgamated  Society of Kail way Vehicle Builders, Wheel-wrights, Carpenters  and Mechanics, refused to consider a suggestion of similar rates, theJoint Wages Board decided  that a settlement should be  postponed until the present negotiations between the Engineering and the National Employers&apos; Federations and theengineering trade  unions over  the unions&apos; national  claims  had  reached  a  definite conclusion^  As a  result of this  attitude, drastic action has been under  contemplationby the Birmingham Joint Committee to  enforce their demands.     Warehousemen (Liverpool). A situation of considerable  interest has arisen in Liver-pool out of the proposal of the United Trades Association to reduce their warehousemen&apos;rates.   Last May the association, acting on the assumption that employers at other portswould take the same line, agreed  to operate the recommendations  of the Dockers&apos; Courtof Inquiry.   As their assumption, however, has apparently not been realised, the asso-ciation recently put forward a suggestion to the National Warehouse and General Workers&apos;Union, now merged in the National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers, that thenormal minimum rate of 16s. a day should be paid  only to labourers casually employed,and that the wages of permanent men, in consideration of the constancy of their employ-ment,  should be reduced by from 2s. to 4s. a day.  This suggestion was rejected by theunion on the ground that the agreement was national.    A new factor has come into the situation with, the decision of  the men employed by messrs. Pelling, Stanley  and Co., Ltd., wholesale provision merchants, who are membersof the association, to accept a reduction from  4 8s. a week to  3  13s. 6d. in preference to discharge.  The National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers, in alarm lest this action may result in the breaking  away of all the firms who constitute the  United TradesAssociation  from the payment of the &quot; dockers&apos; minimum,&quot; not only propose to expelthe men concerned from the union unless they reverse this decision, but are  also approach-ing the transport unions with a view to obtaining their aid in boycotting the firm, j    Coke Workers (National). At the meeting of the executive of the Miners&apos; federation on the 26th January, attention was called to the report that the National Coke Owners&apos;Association, through their  local  managers,  had adopted the proceeding  of  asking theworkmen locally to abrogate the war-wage agreement without either  consulting the officials of the National Union of Cokemen and Bye-product Workers or intimating their intentionto the Miners&apos;  Federation.   As the latter  body,  in conjunction with the Government,made the war-wage  agreement upon a national  basis,  the secretary, Mr. F. Hodges, was instructed to call the attention of the  Government to the  attitude of the coke  owners&apos;association, and to request the wor.kmen&apos;s organisations to resist the local attempts whichwere being made to set the agreement aside.   In this connection should be noted thereport that the  Yorkshire Coking and Chemical Co., Ltd., Glass Houghton, have dischargedmembers  of the National Union  of  Cokemen and Bye-product  Workers who refused toaccept a reduction in wages.  It is understood that the men&apos;s action has been governed by the instructions issued by the Miners&apos;  Federation.Strikes and Lock-Outs.    Plumbers and Heating and Domestic Engineers (Manchester). In connection with thedemarcation  dispute between the-National Union of Operative Heating  and DomesticEngineers and the United Operative Plumbers and Domestic Engineers&apos; Association overthe installation of a central heating water supply on the Blackley, Gorton Mount andMount Road Estates, at Manchester, both  parties have agreed  to  accept  an inquiry bythe Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union  Congress.  The Parliamentary Com-mittee have appointed Messrs. Poulton, Sexton and Purcell to  hold the inquiry, and ameeting was to have been  held  on the 31st January. J  No further information is yet available.  In consequence  of this dispute, there has been a strike of plumbers in the manchester housing scheme since the 7th November, 1920.    * In this connection, it will  be remembered  that the Joint Committee of Engineering Trade Unions,representing these  same unions, and the Joint Wages Board were parties to  the application of the fonnerfor an advance of 6d. per hour  on time rates, with an equivalent advance in piece rates an applicationfor the same advance as  was put forward in the engineering and foundry trades at the last periodic hearingbefore the Industrial Court.   In both cases the claim was  not conceded, the case of the Joint Committeeand the Joint Wages Board being covered by Industrial Court Award No. 424, issued the 31st July, 1920.    f See also p. 139 below.           $See this Report, Vol. II, No. 26, 25th December, p. 705.    (B16930T)                                                               R
 Negotiations and Disputes-continued, Settlements and Agreements.     Goal Miners (National). The agreement between the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain, the Mining Association of Great Britain, and the Government, which terminated the national Goal strike in November last year, referred in its preamble to the &quot; necessity of setting up machinery for regulating wages in the coal trade so as to get rid of present anomalies and provide against future difficulties,&quot; and one of the main provisions of the agreement was that the Mining Association and the Miners&apos; Federation should &quot; proceed forthwith to prepare a  scheme for submission to the Government at the earliest possible moment, and not later  than the 31st March, for the regulation of wages in the industry, having regard, among  other considerations, to the profits of the  industry and to the principle upon  which any surplus profits are to be dealt with.&quot;     The progress of the negotiations between the owners and the miners with regard to the preparation of this scheme  was reviewed on the 27th  and  28th January  by the national delegate conference of the Miners&apos; Federation.  On the 27th, the conference received a report presented  by Mr. Hodges  and supplemented by Mr. Smillie.  On the 28th, it was decided that a  questionnaire should be  drafted by the executive committee, embodying the main questions of principle upon which the delegate conference required guidance from their constituents, and which had to be settled before further useful progress could be made by the executive committee with the negotiations.  This questionnaire will be  circulated to the district associations, and a further national delegate conference will be  held for the purpose of hearing the reports from  the districts  and of arriving at decisions on the questions of principle.   It may be assumed that the local  decisions will be taken by the  various delegate conferences of the district associations, and that there will be no ballot  of the rank and file.    The questions  which are  to  be submitted for  discussion appear to  be,  firstly, whether, upon  the consolidation of the present  numerous items  which  make up the miners&apos;  earnings, the  &quot; bonus&quot; additional to  the  standard  earnings,   which,  it is proposed,  will vary according to  the financial  prosperity  of  the  industry,  should take the form of  a flat rate,  or  a  percentage  rate  calculated upon  the  standard earnings ; secondly, whether the miners are willing to accept the principle of a guaranteed minimum profit for the  owners ; and thirdly, whether the miners are in favour of wages control by a national wages  board or by district wages boards.  The last question is, of course, one which has occasioned much controversy within the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain for a considerable period.    Meanwhile, in  accordance with the provisions of the second part  of the agreement which terminated the national coal strike, it was announced on the  31st January that forthe four weeks from that date the amount of the wages advance payable to colliery workersunder the settlement would  be  Is.  Qd.  per shift for persons over 18 years of age,  with corresponding amounts  for persons under that age.  This figure of Is.  Qd. compares  with an advance of 2s.  a shift which was paid from the resumption of work to the 3rd January, and a sum of 3s. 6d. which was  paid from the 3rd to the 31st January.*    Pig-iron Operatives (Scotland). The  Scottish  Iron  Masters&apos;  Association  and  theIron and Steel Trades Confederation have agreed to accept the revised sliding scale drawnup by the joint sliding  scale committee at  their meetings on the 23rd December and the 10th January, to  operate from the 1st February.    [Other  disputes, negotiations and settlements are referred to in the Industrial RelationsDepartments section of the Report, pages  131 to 139.]* See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 2, 8th January, p. 27.
PART   II.-THE  WORK  OF   THE   MINISTRY.INDUSTRIAL  RELATIONS  DEPARTMENT.              ENGINEERING,  SHIPBUILDING AND  ALLIED  TRADES.    Railway Electrical Shopmen (London District).-Application was made to the industrial court for an interpretation, on certain questions arising out of Award No. 542.*  It wasdecided that, although it might be inferred that the Court drew a distinction between two separate classes of workpeople, it was the intention of the Court that the distinction shouldlie between two classes of work and not between two separate bodies of workmen.   Thefact that a workman might be entitled to different rates of pay according as he was engaged on one class of work or another was not lost sight of, and was deemed to be in conformitywith a frequent trade practice.  The decision must  be read as laying down a special ratefor men when engaged on the  installation of new plant and other similar work ordinarilydone by electrical  contractors.  The special rate would not apply when the men were engaged on other classes of work, as, for example, maintenance and repair.  In all casesthe  question of the application of this rate is largely one of degree.  Where the work is substantial it should be regarded as coming  within the category of work ordinarily doneby electrical contractors ;  where the work is not substantial, or is of recurring frequency,it should be regarded as of that class of work which is payable at the rates provided by theagreement of January, 1920.   (Award No.  603.)    Shipbuilding Trade Joint Council. On the  19th January tne trade unions represented on the councils for Government industrial establishments decided to withdraw, as a protest against the introduction of short time in Government industrial  establishments without previous discussion.  When the Shipbuilding Trade Joint Council met on the following day, the trade union representatives intimated this decision  and withdrew.  No business was transacted.                      WOODWORKING  AND  FURNISHING.    Packing-Case Makers (London). Negotiations between the National Union of PackingCase Makers and representatives of  Messrs.  P. Keevil &amp; Sons, Ltd.,f were opened on the17th January, the firm offering to retain the  men at wages reduced by 25 per cent.   this offer was unanimously refused.   It is understood that the union organiser is communicating with the secretary of the National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers, who appearto have a number of members employed at the firm&apos;s Liverpool establishment.    Saivmilkng (Scotland). At a preliminary  conference between representatives of theScottish Timber Merchants and Sawmillers&apos; Association and the Amalgamated Society ofWoodcutting Machinists, held to discuss a draft agreement respecting working conditions,the trade union representatives refused to accept the employers&apos; proposal that any questionwhich could not be settled by the proposed special Joint Committee should be referred  tothe Industrial Court.  The society&apos;s oiganiser explained that his society were not opposedto the principle of arbitration,  but desired to have a free hand in the matter of procedure and were unwilling to he deprived of the right  to strike.  A further conference, however,will be held within  the next few days.    Bobbin and Shuttle Making (Scotland). During the hearing of a claim for increases of wages, the attention of the Industrial Court was directed to the fact that the indian government have established a bobbin factory at Bareilly, to demonstrate that bobbinscan be made successfully in India  and to  train Indian labour in the technique of theindustry.  It was stated that the trade is faced with severe competition from Japan, andthat competition from Sweden, which was  suspended during the war, has revived.    The Court decided that the weekly rates paid to higher skilled men, lesser skilled menand labourers should be increased by 4s., and that  the claims in respect of women, boysand girls had not been established.   (Award No. 608.)(B 16930T)* See this Report, Vol. II, No. 23, 4th December, p. 636.f See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 4, 22nd January, p. 77.
                     BUILDING  AND WORKS OF  CONSTRUCTION.      Demand for Grade IV Rates (Bridport). About 100  operatives at Bridport have  threatened to cease work if their rates of wages are not advanced from Is. Sd. and Is. 5d.  for tradesmen and labourers,  respectively, to Grade IV rates under the South-Western  Area Scheme, namely, Is. lOjcZ. and Is. l\d., respectively.   At the request of the operatives&apos;  federation, the Chief Conciliation Officer secured a suspension of the strike notices, pending  the result of  a meeting of the  employers, at which  an officer of the department was to be  present.      Building. The Management and Costs  Committee of  the Joint Industrial Council  met on the 27th and 28th  January and discussed  further the scheme for providing 30s.  per week unemployment pay in addition to the State benefit of 15s.   It was decided that  the  next  meeting should discuss reports  from the Ministry of Labour regarding the  estimated cost of abolishing waiting days under the Act, and for the payment of time  lost  owing to stress of weather. The committee  also  considered  what measures were  necessary for the regularisation of the demands for  building work.     Building Resettlement Committee. The committee met on tne 27tn January to consider  the position arising out of the replies from the  unions to the Adult Apprenticeship Scheme.  As it was clear from the reports received that the scheme has not received any substantial  degree of support from the trade unions, it was decided that a report should be drawn up  by a sub-committee, to be  presented to the Council at their  next meeting, on the 10th February, outlining the view of the Committee that  the reception of the Adult Apprentice- ship Scheme has  been prejudiced by the Governments scheme for the  absorption of 50,000 ex-Service men into the industry.     It was decided to request the secretary of the Scottish Board of Health to agree to the principle  that representatives  of the committee should be appointed to the  Scottish committee to  inquire into the high cost of  house building.     Plumbers (Aberdeen). The Aberdeen Corporation, when inviting tenders for work in connection  with the housing  scheme, stipulated  that  the terms  of the Government Interrupted  Apprenticeship Scheme  should  be  observed.   In  consequence   of this stipulation, the master plumbers refused to tender and the Corporation employed operative plumbers direct.     The master  plumbers declared that the operatives,  in working for the Corporation, were contravening an agreement that operative plumbers should only work for members of the master plumbers&apos; federation, and as a result  the plumbers on  the housing scheme ceased  work.    A local officer of the department arranged  a conference of representatives of the Town Council and the masters and operatives on the 11th  January.   When the facts of the case were  revealed, the operatives appeared to  be anxious that the local employers should accept the conditions regarding  the apprenticeship scheme.  If  the employers would agree to do so, the operatives were prepared to agree to resume work immediately, but if they refused, the operatives threatened to call upon the  local association to abrogate the rule under which they were compelled  to work only for members of the local master plumbers&apos; association,  and to declare the  dispute with the  Corporation at an end.  It appears that if the employers  accept the  apprenticeship scheme,  the Town  Council will again request the members of the masters&apos; association to tender for the houses not yet completed.  The employers agreed to place the result of these deliberations before a meeting of their associa- tion, and further consideration  was postponed until the result could  be known.    Painters (Scotland).-A  claim was made before the Industrial Court for  a  levelling up of wages and  certain overtime and lodging allowances.  On the evidence, particularly as regards the practice of the past, the Court held the view that the claim of the painters to general equality, in respect of wages, with other skilled sections of  the building trades, had been established, and in these circumstances decided that the rate for Grade A towns should be that laid down in the building trades scheme.  With regard to overtime, it was decided that time-and-a-half should be paid from ordinary stopping time until  starting time next morning.  Work on Sundays should be paid for at  double rates.  This is not to affect the present practice by which work done by men on  lodging allowances is paid for at ordinary rates up to 54  hours.  The claim for the allowance  of 21s. a week was established.  (Award No. 605.)    Imported  Joinery-An.  interesting point  was raised  by a deputation  representingSwedish joinery manufacturers which Sir David Shackleton received on the 26th January,    For some  years joinery manufactured in Sweden has been imported, and no difficulty
 with regard to its fixing has been experienced hitherto.  Recently, however, the Amalga- mated Society of Carpenters,  Cabinet Makers and Joiners  and the General  Union of Operative  Carpenters and Joiners have objected  to  the  fixing of the  joinery by their members, on the ground that it is manufactured by  piece-work, and that their rules do not permit this practice.     At a job at Barrow-in-Furness,  Messrs. W. Gradwell  &amp; Co., Ltd., public works con- tractors,  who had taken delivery of doors supplied by a Swedish firm, were asked by the Amalgamated Society,  on the  4th  November, 1920, to  state  where the  doors were manufactured, and whether they were made under  trade union  conditions.   On being informed that the doors were  imported from Sweden, the general secretary of the union issued  orders  that members should  not fix the doors, on the ground that the Swedish firm is &quot; a piece-work shop and therefore  does not conform to  trade conditions  as  we understand such.&quot;  It was not until the 20th January that the firm were able to arrange with the  local branch of the union to get the doors fixed as a special concession and without prejudice.  Joinery supplied to the Leyland Construction Co., Ltd., Leyland, Lancashire, is still under  embargo.     The  question appears to have had its origin at an international conference of  wood- workers  held  at  Brussels  and Amsterdam  in December, 1919, at  which the general secretary was present.  In his  report of the meetings, he stated:            &quot; The most startling information which we obtained was from the Scandinavian delegates        which was to the effect that, although organised in Sweden, Denmark and Norway, all joinery and        woodwork in general is made on the piece-work system. We informed them that, in the event of any        stuff coming from their countries, we would have to very seriously consider whether we could fix        such stuff or not, as piece-work was a principle to which we were deadly opposed.&quot;     The  claim that imported joinery must be made under conditions which satisfy not only trade  union practice in the country of manufacture, but also British trade  union practice,  is  entirely new, and the matter is receiving the consideration of the department.                                    QUARRYING.     Freestone. The  Yorkshire Area District Council (Freestone Section) of the  Joint Industrial Council met on the 21st December.  It was reported that the Executive Com- mittee  had not yet been called together to  consider the question of grading.  According to notice  given, the employers made application for a reduction of wages.   The employees opposed the consideration of the application, arguing that the notice was not in order, as three months&apos; notice had been given instead of four.  It was agreed, after discussion, that the employers should withdraw their application and renew it during January for consideration at the next Council meeting.                               FOOD  AND DRINK.     Bakers (South Wales). The majority of the men at  Swansea resumed work on the 24th January  under the same conditions  as before the strike,  on the understanding that a joint conference should be  held under the chairmanship of the Mayor of Swansea.     Sugar Refining. At a meeting of the Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee, on the 28th January, a demand was made for an all-round increase of 10s. per week in wages, together wuth double time for  week-end work and  time-and-a-third for night-shift  work. The employers stated that they were unable to grant any increase at the present  time, and that  they must wait the coming  of de-control before any alteration in wages should be considered,  at all.   It  might  then have to be a decrease rather than an increase.   The workers then withdrew their demand until  de-control  should  become operative.    Fishing Industry (Grimsby). The owners have so  far declined to alter their decision as to a conference.  An officer from headquarters has gone to Grimsby with the object of arranging  a  conference, if at all possible.  The threatened strike commenced on the 28thJanuary.  According  to  the Press  reports  the local  dockers&apos;  union have decided notto coal vessels with non-unionist crews.                          POTTERY, RUBBER AND GLASS.    Pottery. The Executive,  General Purposes,  and  Finance Committee of the joint industrial  Council met on the 27th January.   It was agreed that local members of Parlia-
 ment should be requested to press for the inclusion of the following safeguards in  the proposed Bill dealing with the marking of pottery :            That all imported pottery, white or decorated, shall he marked indelibly with the country of origin;       any goods not so marked to be liable to confiscation.           That all imported pottery should be certified by a Consul who should be of British nationality.           That the certificate of the country of origin should be similar to those at present in use for out-       Colonial markings.     It was decided to form a committee to consider the advisability of contracting out of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920,  and in the event of an affirmative decision, to submit a special scheme.     India Rubber Workers:  Reduction of Wages. The Redferns Rubber Works, Ltd., Hyde, near Manchester,  manufacturers of  india  rubber soles and heels, discharged 32 employees in December last,  owing to slackness of trade.  On the 10th January eight of these were re-engaged on a  revised price-list  which showed A reduction on previous earnings.  After working for a week, they were ordered by their union, the Amalgamated Society of India  Rubber, Cable  and Asbestos Workers,  to  withdraw7 their labour, and several of them did so.  At a joint conference held under the auspices of the department, the firm  agreed to reinstate the strikers but submitted that increased output and reduced rates were necessary to enable  them to  meet  competition.  They  produced facts and figures which induced the  union to accept  a reduction in wages together with an increased rate of production.  The new terms were accepted unanimously by a mass meeting of the men on the 24TH January. The number of moulds per charge is increased from 36 to 40, the number of  charges per shift remaining unchanged.    The weekly wages are reduced from  5  6s. Od. to  4 17s. 6d.    Glass. The Joint Industrial Council  met on the 26th January.   The final report of the sub-committee appointed to deal with the Women and Young Persons Act was received, and a vote of thanks was passed to the members of the committee for the great services they had rendered to the industry.    An interim report was received from the Anti-Dumping Sub-Committee, and the policy adopted by the sub-committee was approved, three of the general labour unions abstaining from voting.  A  wages application  from the National Union of General Workers was ruled out of order, and the matter was referred to the  appropriate Sectional Council.  It was agreed to take no action with regard to the Ministers letter on short time.   &apos; On the 27th January, Sic Philip Lloyd-Graeme, M.P.,  Parliamentary Secretary to the Board of Trade, received  a deputation from  the Anti-Dumping Sub-Committee.  The deputation maintained that unless some measures were taken to stabilise exchanges, it would be impossible for the industry to continue to meet foreign competition ; the inclusion of essential illuminating glass in the Key Industries Bill was also asked for.  Sir Philip replied that it was the intention of the Government to introduce  legislation dealing with key industries, dumping and exchanges at an early date.  With regaid to  key industries, the Government could not publish a schedule in advance of the Bill.  With regard TO dumping and exchanges, the information supplied by tne Council was most valuable.                                      TEXTILES.    Wool (and Allied) Textiles. By resolution of the Emergency  Committee of the Joint Industrial Council, in  consequence of the fall of the  cost-of-living index number from 175 to 165, the cost-of-living  wages of the  employees are to be reduced  proportionately as from the pay-day in the week ending the 4TH February, and for the pay-week precedingthat date.  The amount of the  reduction is approximately  from 2s. to 2s.  (id. a week for women, and from 2s. %d.  to 4s. 6d. for men.    A  further special  meeting of the Industrial  Council was held in Bradford  on the28th January to consider the report of the sub-committee appointed to draft a contracting- out scheme under the Unemployment Insurance Act.   A scheme prepared by the sub-committee was accepted by the  Council, and referred to the constituent associations  forconsideration and  report.   A further resolution was passed  that the scheme shoud bebrought into operation at the earliest possible date, on the understanding that the Govern-ment should give the scheme the necessary financial backing and support.  consideration was given to proposals to remedy the present inconvenience occasioned by queues ATthe Exchanges, and there was some discussion as to  the  possibility of extending thepractice  of paving unemployment benefit to operatives at the manufacturers&apos; premises.
It was not possible to reach agreement, and the question was referred back to the sub-committee for further consideration.                        LEATHER AND  BOOTS  AND SHOES.    Leather Manufacture  (Irthlingborough). Messrs. Hatton, Shaw &amp;  Co. gave a week&apos;notice to their employees on the 3rd January, and, before the expiration of the  notices,offered to re-engage them at rates involving a reduction of 20 per cent.  On the advice of their union the men refused to accept  the lower rates, and work stopped on the 10thJanuary.  The Chief Conciliation Officer,  Birmingham, is in touch,  and negotiations are proceeding.   The firm allege that the reductions  are  consequent  on a reorganisation ofwork which will not result in decreased earnings.                                      MINING.    Lead:  Proposed Reduction  of Wages-The Miners&apos; Federation have now agreed toaccept arbitration on the question of the reduction  of wages proposed by the Wanlockheadand Leadhills Lead Mining Companies.   They have refused to allow their members toaccept any  reduction without  arbitration.  The  directors of the companies, however,have  refused arbitration  on the ground  that  the great losses  being  incurred render areduction of wages essential at  once, and they have notified a reduction of 25 per cent.as from the 28th January.    On the 26th January Sir David Shacldeton interviewed representatives of the miners,headed by Mr.  R. Smilfie, to suggest that they should ask their  members to remain atwork  pending negotiations.   On the  27th January he saw Mr.  Felix  Wilson, a  directorof the Leadhills Co., Ltd., with a view to securing the postponement of the notices.   TheChief Conciliation Officer, Glasgow,  interviewed the  chairman of the  directors of  theWanlockhead Mining Co., Ltd., to the same end.  These attempts  were  unsuccessful,and work ceased on the 28th January.  Further conferences are to take place.             PUBLIC AUTHORITIES AND PUBLIC UTILITY  SERVICES.    Electricity Supply. The District Joint Industrial Council for the East Midland Areamet on the 27th January.   It  was decided that  the  time was inopportune to  proceedwith a proposal from the trade  union side for  the revision of the minimum rates in thebasis  rates schedule.  Rates were agreed, to be  included in the existing schedule, forswitchboard and  sub-station attendants.    The Gloucester  Corporation having declined to accept the schedule of salaries andconditions of employment recommended by the National Joint  Board of Employers and staff  Members for technical staffs, the Electrical  Power Engineers&apos; Association  decidedto withdraw their members in the employment of the  Corporation on the 29th January,unless a settlement was arrived at.   A conference of representatives of the  corporation and of the Association was held at Gloucester on the 28th January, under the chairmanship of an  officer of the department.  The representatives of the Corporation submitted certainterms, and the representatives of the Association agreed to recommend the terms  to their executive and to suspend the notices.    A similar  situation  arose  at Wolverhampton,  the  Electrical  Power  Engineers&apos;Association  having decided to  withdraw  their members  on the  1st February unless asettlement was reached.  There is also a difference between the Corporation and  theNational Association of Local Government Officers.  At the request of the department aconference will be held at Wolverhampton on the  31st January.    Local Authorities&apos; Administrative,  Technical and Clerical Services (England and Wales). The National Council met on  the 27th  January.  After  a discussion which  arose fromrepresentations made by  the employers&apos;  associations  regarding the relationship of  theNational Council  to  the Provincial Councils,  the powers of the  latter, and the areas forwhich it is proposed to set up Provincial Councils, the following resolution was passed :-.          &quot; THAT THE PROPOSALS OF THE THREE EMPLOYERS&apos; ASSOCIATIONS BE REFERRED TO  A SUB-COMMITTEE, WITH       INSTRUCTIONS  TO DRAW UP A CONSIDERED REPLY FOR SUBMISSION TO THE NEXT MEETING OF THE  NATIONAL       COUNCIL, SUCH REPLY TO MAKE IT  CLEAR THAT THE NATIONAL COUNCIL DESIRES THAT PROVINCIAL COUNCILS SHOULD       BE BROUGHT INTO EXISTENCE AT ONCE, WITH AUTHORITY TO  SETTLE SCALES OF SALARY FOR THEIR RESPECTIVE AREAS,       SUBJECT TO THE RIGHT OF APPEAL IN CASE OF DIFFERENCE TO  THE NATIONAL COUNCIL.&quot;    A conference  of representatives of the local authorities and staff  associations concerned,held at Reading on the 28th January, to consider a resolution passed at an early conference
                          GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTS.    National Council for the Administrative and Legal Departments ojthe Civil Service. The10th meeting of the National Council was held on the 28th January, Sir Malcolm Ramsay,K.C.B., in the chair.to the effect that a Provincial Council be formed for the South Midland Area, was adjourned  Jpending a settlement of the difficulties that have arisen on the National Council.    At a conference of  representatives of local authorities in the counties of Denbigh,Flint, Carnarvon, Merioneth, Montgomery and Anglesey, and representatives of the staff associations concerned, on the 28th January, it was resolved that a Provincial council should be formed forthwith, to which local authorities in the area be strongly recommended to become parties.  It was decided to hold a further meeting at an early date, after therepresentatives had consulted their authorities.    Local Authorities&apos; Non-Trading Services, Manual Workers (England and Wales). Theannual meeting of the National Council was held on the 28th January, when officers were elected for the year.  As a result of requests from various Provincial Councils, the national council decided that a conference of representatives of all the Provincial Councils and  ofthe members of the National Council should be convened.    The  Provincial Council for the Eastern Counties met on the 27th January.  It wasagreed that consideration of the grading scheme should be adjourned until the 17th Februaryin order that the representatives of the local authorities might consult them on the proposalsof the trade union side.    Tramways Industry Dispute. The Court of Inquiry set up under the Industrial courts act to inquire into the  dispute between the  two sides of the National Joint IndustrialCouncil for the Tramways Industry held their first  sitting on the 26th January. Mr. E.Bevin, of the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation, opened the case for the employees,basing his claim chiefly on the cost of living, and the low standard of life forced uponemployees called upon to do responsible work.  On the 27th and 28th January the case for  the employees  was again dealt with, witnesses being  called in support of the  claim.   ICross-examination by the  employers&apos; side consisted  mainly of  endeavours to weaken the evidence regarding the responsibility of the work  and the effects of the spread-over,or split duty, system, of working hours.  Family budgets were submitted, and employees andtheir wives called upon to support them.    Waterworks Undertakings. The District Council for No. 6 Area, comprising Gloucester-shire, Oxfordshire,  Buckinghamshire,  Berkshire, Wiltshire  and Hampshire,  met on the24th January.  A scheme  was adopted for  grading  undertakings  in the area into  fourclasses, namely, Grade A,  rural districts;  Grade  B,  towns and urban districts with a census population under 40,000 ;  Grade C, towns with a census population above 40,000and under 100,000;  and Grade D, towns with  a census population of 100,000 and over.Minimum rates of pay were laid down appropriate  to ten classes of workmen within eachgrade, the minimum  rates  to  be  inclusive of emoluments other  than holidays.  It wasdecided that the scheme be  operative as from the first pay-day following the 1st January.    The  Midland District Council met on the 28th January at Birmingham, and  dealtwith several differences between unions and undertakings  which had  been considered and reported upon by the Appeals Committee.    Corporation Employees (Sunderland). A claim was made before the Industrial Courtthat the  Civil  Service scale of bonus should  be applied to  the administrative, technical   jand clerical staff.   The amount ot war bonus had been the subject of negotiation on variousdates up to November, 1919.   The bonuses  were  at  first limited to officers on salariesnot exceeding 40s. a week, but this Kmit had been extended to  salaries of  250 a year.In addition to the bonuses, a revision of salaries had  been made,  applying to all salarieswhether  under  250 a vear or not.   The last settlement took effect as from November,1919, and under that settlement all bonuses, paid specifically as  such, were merged msalaries.   In August, 1920, the  Corporation considered a claim for a further revision, anda committee recommended a bonus of 10 per cent, on all salaries as revised under  thelast settlement, up to  500 a year, and a certain revision of salaries over  500 a year.   Thiswas not  acceptable to the association and was never formally approved by the Council.    The Court arrived at the conclusion that the recommendation made by the committeeof the Corporation was  one that  should  be accepted and confirmed by the Corporation.(Award No. 600.)
     The final report of the Committee on the organisation of the Civil Service was received,and it was agreed  that the report should  be printed.  This report  recorded, inter alia,disagreement in regard to the basis for the calculation of overtime, and the Council tookformal note of this disagreement.  A further disagreement on the Cost-of-Living Committeein regard to the pay of temporary clerical classes was also formally recorded.     The Council agreed to set up a standing committee to examine and report from timeto time on any questions of general principle not covered by the recommendations of the interim  Report of  the  Re-organisation Committee which may emerge in the course of applying the revised  scheme  of re-organisation throughout the Civil Service ;  a seriesof committees to consider certain  classes  of  professional,  technical,  and scientific civilservants, the exact scope  and constitution  of these committees being  left over for settle-ment between the secretaries;  and also a  special committee to elucidate the conditions,and the consequences of those conditions, which constitutionally underlie the applicationof the Whitley procedure to the Civil Service.     On the question of a receipt stamp for  wages, the official side stated that, while there appeared to be serious difficulties in waiving the requirements of a stamp, no final decisionhad been arrived at.  The official side were unable to accept certain amendments proposedfrom the staff side in regard to the arrangements for the remuneration of officers appointedto acting rank, embodied in. Treasury  Circular B. 1668, 9th  October, 1920.     As regards travelling and subsistence allowances, the official side stated that they had considered the memorandum circulated by the staff side and  were making further inquiries.The importance of an early settlement was  emphasised.     The Council were unable to agree to a proposal that disciplinary entries on an officersrecord should be expunged after a fixed period of approved service.   It was stated that,both for promotion and superannuation, it was the practice to disregard minor offencesafter a certain number of years of approved service, but the official side felt that the ultimatediscretion must be  left to the head of the  department or the  Treasury.     The Council considered a proposal to set up a grade committee to consider the applica-tion to staff clerks of the Re-organisation  Committee&apos;s report  and the AssimilationAgreement.   No agreement was reached.     As regards the  communication of Treasury circulars to  the staff, the chairman statedthat it was already  the practice of the Treasury to send to the  staff side secretaries of theNational Council copies of Treasury Circulars of general interest,  and that in future thesecirculars might be published or circulated on  condition that they were reproduced in full.     In answer to questions from the staff side, the official side made a general statement as to progress in dealing with the departmental schemes of  re-organisation, and indicated that, while they were not  yet in a position  to make any definite suggestions in regard tothe method of dealing with the allocation of particular border-line  classes as between theindustrial or  administrative  Councils,  they  hoped that an agreed procedure would result from informal consultations which were taking place  between  the  secretaries.     EM. Stationery  Office.-Th.e quarterly meeting  of the Industrial Council was heldon the 25th January.  The question of short time was not discussed.   Among the matters dealt with was a threatened strike at Harrow, where members of  the National Union ofBookbinding, Machine-Printing and Paper  Workers had handed in notices on account ofthe discharge and alleged victimisation of a man who was the  father of the chapel.  Themen&apos;s action  was entirely unauthorised by the union, and was condemned by them on theground that recourse should first have been had to the Industrial Council.  It was arranged that further discussion should take place between the men concerned, the union representa-tives and the Controller, with a view to the  withdrawal of the notices.                             MISCELLANEOUS TRADES.    Co-operative Workers-The Southern Section of  the Co-operative Union, Ltd., andthe National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers have agreed that the dispute betweenthem shall be referred to the Industrial Court.  Some difficulty arose on the constitutionof the Court, but it was agreed that if the  Minister could so constitute the Court that all its members were members of the legal profession, the union would withdraw their objection.Another  difficulty arose owing to the result of the voting of the District Councils of theHours and Wages Board, as only 37 voted  for arbitration while  36 voted against it, and36 remained  neutral.  The Council at first  considered that, in view of these figures, theyhad no power to go to arbitration, but it was decided that  the matter should be referred by the Council, and efforts made to persuade the District Councils  to  fall into line.  Anysocieties which remain obdurate can withdraw at the date of. hearing.    (B 16930T)                                                                S
Industrial  Relations  Department continual.    iron mongers (Scotland). For  several months  last year the  National AmalgamatedUnion of  Shop Assistants, Warehouseman and Clerks were attempting to negotiate withthe iron mongers&apos; Federated Association for Aberdeen, Banff, and Kincardine with a viewto the adoption of a scale of wages and improved rates.  At the request of the union theChief Conciliation Officer, Glasgow, communicated with the association on the matter.The union desired that the claim  should be referred  to arbitration,  but the employers were not  willing to agree to this proposal, nor were they prepared to discuss the matter with the union or with any third party.  Mr. John Turner and Mr. Hoffman visited thedepartment to discuss the position.  It was explained that a Court of Inquiry would notappear to be appropriate in the circumstances, and Mr. Turner announced his intentionof going further into the matter with the Scottish officials of the union.    Shop Assistants  (London). Representatives  of  the National  Amalgamated  Unionof Shop Assistants, Warehousemen  and Clerks called, with reference to the claim made onbehalf of  the union&apos;s members employed by the chief  London firms, for the adoption ofthe terms of Award No.  594.   They requested that the department should endeavour toarrange a conference, or  that efforts should again be made to have the  claim referred to arbitration.  If the employers  refused both  suggestions, the union desired that a Courtof Inquiry should be set up.   They put forward,  as grounds for the inquiry, that shop.assistants throughout the war had not received advances to compensate for the increased cost of living.  It was finally agreed that the union would officially inform the departmentof the deadlock with the firms in question, and the department would consider what action could usefully be taken.                              PROFESSIONAL WORKERS.    Bank Officers&apos; Guild (Lancashire). In accordance with the ballot of the North-Westerndistrict of the guild, which resulted in an 82 per cent, majority in favour of the establish-ment of a district Whitley Council, the guild have  approached the seven largest banks inLancashire with a proposal that the question of setting up such  a council should be dis-cussed.  They have also  written to the Minister asking for the departments help in  thematter.    Insurance Workers. The strike of insurance  officials  in the service of the GeneralAccident, Fire and Life  Corporation continues.   In accordance  with the promise madeto the deputation of  non-manual workers on the 19th  January, the directors of the Cor-poration have been invited to discuss the situation with  the Minister.                                      GENERAL.                                                                           a    Short Time. Further  action  by  Joint  Industrial Councils  and  Interim industrial reconstruction  Committees in connection with the letter from the department datedthe 31st December, 1920, on the subject of short time,* is as follows :        ... .  flour milling, The Executive Committee of the Joint Industrial Council, on the 19th January,       re-affirmed the resolution passed at a meeting of the National Council on the 15th April, 1920, that       in cases of a stoppage or period  of slackness the joint works committee shall endeavour to arrange       the method of employment; in mills without works committees the trade union representative shall       be called in, and a similar endeavour made to arrange the method of employment; and failing an       agreement, the employer shall be at liberty to  give  any  of his employees one week s notice.   The       Committee added to  this resolution: &quot; So long as the manufacture and/or distribution of flour is       affected by Government orders, the Committee recommends to the constituents of both sides and to       the Flour Mills Control Committee that the amount  of wages payable to an employee is not to be       diminished by more than two-elevenths of the standard weekly pay.&quot;           Glass. The Council decided to take no action, but  it was stated that the whole question of       unemployment and its prevention is receiving the most earnest consideration of every section of the       industry.           Surgical Instruments.-T&apos;he Council decided to take no action.           Insurance Committees. The Council decided to take no action, as the employees represented       by the Council are not  affected  by trade depression.           Hosiery, The paragraph inserted on p. 110  of this Report last week,  through  an  error.in       reproduction, needs correction.   It should read  as follows: &quot; The Council decided  to take no       action, as the general -adoption of short time during periods of trade depression was an established       custom in the industry.&quot;    Expiration  of the  Wages  (Temporary Regulation)  Acts. The Industrial  Court havenotified the  department  that it is not proposed to proceed further with the  outstandingcases  referred under the Wages  (Temporary  Regulation) Act subsequent to the 30thSeptember last, having regard to the decision, on appeal, of Mr. Justice Roche that, with                               * See also pp. 134, 137 and  139.
GENERAL   DEPARTMENT.                               TRADE  BOARDS.                                   PROCEEDINGS.     Boot and Shoe Repairing Trade Board (Great Britain). The Lancashire and Cheshire and the Yorkshire District  Trade.Committees considered the suggestions of the  Board for the variation of minimum rates  of wages.  In both cases the workers&apos; representatives recommended certain increases, while the employers&apos; representatives considered that the time was not opportune for any changes to be made in minimum rates.   The Committees considered and approved the Board&apos;s proposals for the  variation  of the minimum rates for apprentices.     Jute Trade Board (Great Britain).-The Board agreed to inform the Minister that his suggestions  in respect of working short  time were already in general operation in the trade.   They also recommended that, in view of the exceptionally large number of women employed in the industry, the employment of disabled ex-Service men to the extent of 5 per cent,  of male operatives should.be  sufficient to enable a firm to qualify under the National Scheme for the Employment of Disabled Ex-Service Men.     The report from the Skilled Workers&apos; Committee, that it was at present inadvisable to consider  the question of substituting a scheme of payments based  on occupations or jobs for the minimum rates based on ages and sex,  was adopted.  The Board resolved to give notice of proposal to fix general minimum piece-rates for hessian weavers.     Stamped or  Pressed Metal Wares Trade Board  (Great Britain). Thev Special  Scope Committee,  after consultation with representatives  of the Ministry, and with  representa- tives of various metal trades, resolved to recommend to the Board that their next meeting be held on the 16th February, when a  statement in regard to the  progress made by the Ministry towards any amendments of the definition of the trade should be made.     Tobacco Trade Board (Great Britain). The Administrative Committee agreed to inform the Board that the representatives of workers were in favour of a piece-work basis  time-rate being fixed for male and female workers, but that the representatives of employersdissented from this view.  It was also agreed to inform the Minister that short time was(u 1C930T)* See p. 129 above,S2 the expiration, on the 30th September last, of the provisions of the Wages (Temporary Regulation) Acts,  as  continued by the  Industrial  Courts Act, 1919,  the jurisdiction of Local Munitions Tribunals in complaints  under that Act ceased on that date.  The parties to the differences in question, and the chairmen of the Local Munitions Tribunals reporting the cases to the Minister, have been informed accordingly.     Warehousemen :  Reduction of Wages  (Liverpool). A deputation from the  United Trades Association of  Liverpool was received on the 22nd January.  The association had sought an interview in regard to a proposed reduction of wages of warehousemen in Liver-pool.  At the present  time the men are paid in accordance with the  agreement arrivedat by the Negotiating Committee, following the Court of Inquiry  into  the Wages andConditions of Employment of Dock Labour.    The employers contended that only in  Liverpool are men engaged  in warehousingpaid the dockers&apos; rate, and that they have paid under a misapprehension as to the applica-bility of the agreement.  They sought a decision from the Minister as to whether theywere bound by it, and inquired what would be the possible procedure of  the Ministry inthe event of a  strike  in Liverpool,  which might affect the whole port and have  serious results.    They  were informed that  the  Minister  could not decide the matter, and  the usualmethods of conciliation and the steps which might be taken in the event of a stoppagetaking place, were  outlined. *    [Reference  to matters  of interest  in connection with Industrial  Relations will be foundalso on pages 122 to  130 and  140.]
General  Department-continued.adopted to a considerable extent by employers in the trade, but that this method was not considered by the representatives of workers to be a satisfactory solution of the problemof unemployment.            FIXING  AND  VARIATION OF MINIMUM  RATES OF  WAGES.     Cotton Waste Reclamation  Trade Board (Great Britain). The Minister has made anOrder, dated the 26th January, confirming general minimum time-rates and overtime ratesfor male and female  workers, and has specified the 31st January as the date from whichthese rates shall become effective.           The general minimum time rates are Is. 4fd!. per hour for male workers, 21 years of age and       over; and 9JflL per hour for female workers in England and Wales, and 8fd. per hour for female workers       in Scotland, 18 years of age and over,  lower  rates are fixed for younger workers.           The overtime rates fixed for  male and female workers are, for the first two hours of overtime       in any week, excluding Sunday, time-and-a-quarter; for overtime after the first two hours in any       week, excluding Sunday, time-and-a-half; and  for all time worked on Sunday, double time.           For the purpose of these overtime rates the Board have declared the normal number of hours       of work in any  week to be 48.     Flax and Hemp Trade Board (Ireland). The Minister has made an  Order, dated  the21st January, confirming general minimum time-rates for certain classes of female workers,and has specified the  24th January  as the date  from, which these rates are effective.           The general minimum time-rates for female  workers vary according to the operations performed,       and according as the worker is employed within a radius of 10 statute  miles from the City Centre,       Belfast, within the County of Cork, or in areas other than those specified.   The rates for doffers,       drawers,  rovers and spreaders, and carders, in  the preparing branch of the trade,  range from hi.       to 8\d. per hour ; those for doffers, layers, piecers, and spinners, and twisters, in the spinning branch       of the trade, range from h\d. to 8 cZ. per hour ; those for machine yarn driers, reelers and wet winders       and hank winders range from l\d. to 8f   per hour.  For all the other  female workers employed in       branches of the trade other than the weaving branch, the rates range from Q\d. to Id. per hour, with       lower rates for workers under 18  years of age.             ESTABLISHMENT AND AMENDMENT  OF TRADE  BOARDS.     New Boards. The Minister has issued a Notice of Intention to make a  Special Orderapplying the Trade Boards Acts to the lace warehousing and finishing trade.     [Reference to matters  of  interest in connection with  Trade Boards will also  be found on page 125.]EMPLOYMENT  AND  INSURANCE   DEPARTMENT.                             EMPLOYMENT  EXCHANGES.The  Unemployment  Position.     The following table shows  the work of the Exchanges  in  respect  of  registrationsvacancies, and placings during the week ending the 21st January  : 	Men.	Women.	Boys.	Girls.	Total.Registrations  On live register at beginning of week ... ... Fresh applications............... On live register at end of week......... Vacancies  Carried forward at beginning of week ... Fresh notifications............... Carried forward at end of week......... Placings ...... ......	603,631 96,678 643,683 18,169 10,607 16,780 9,155	238,333 44,658 258,469 26,092 7,360 25,854 4,354	41,407 8,977 44,611 1,774 1,303 1,554 1,306	47,393 11,419 5,666 3,455 1,593 2,986 1,296	930,764 161,732 998,429 49,490 20,863 47,174 16,111
Men&apos;s Employment.    General Outlook. While  a  more optimistic  tone  is observed in some districts, thereports  generally indicate  a  further decline  in  industrial activity  and a corresponding increase in unemployment and under-employment.   There is no general evidence that any improvement is to be looked  for in the near future.    Shipbuilding and Allied Trades. Reports from the Clyde indicate that unemployment is increasing, mainly as a result of the joiners&apos; strike.  On the Tyne and Wear,  largenumbers of workmen are  being paid  off each, week  as contracts  are finished.  In theHebburn district alone, the number of employees at work is estimated to be 1,000 less than during the week  preceding Christmas.    On the Tees the position is unchanged.  Whilethe situation  generally is regarded as very uncertain,  it is expected that the reductionin the price of steel will improve  matters, especially  if followed by a settlement of thejoiners&apos;  dispute.   It is reported that inquiries by shipowners are fairly numerous, and assuch inquiries usually result  in orders, increased production may be expected as soon asthe financial and labour markets are steadier.    From  South Wales, it is reported that  there  is  a decided improvement at Barry,where large numbers of men have been absorbed in  ship-repair work during the week.The position at  Bute Docks  is slightly better ;  and at Newport and Swansea, thoughbusiness is not so brisk as is usual at this time of the year, the position is certainly improving.    The situation on the Mersey is distinctly unpromising.   Ships normally sent there for repairs are being diverted to  the Continent and Ireland.  Little repair work is thereforecoming to the yards, and further reductions in shipyard staffs may  be expected.    Iron and Steel Trade-in the iron and steel industry, Sheffield report a further increasein short-time working, but in the South Wales district the position  is regarded as a littleeasier, particularly at Ebbw Vale, where a considerable number of workpeople are expectedto re-start  at the local steel works.    Textile and Clothing Trades. Reports from the North-Western Division indicate nochange in the cotton trade.    With regard to the  lace industry the optimistic tone reported last week  is still main-tained.  During  the recent sales a considerable amount  of lace has been disposed of, andit is confidently believed that increased activity may be looked for in the near future.A more hopeful feeling also  obtains in regard to the boot  and shoe trade, particularly among manufacturers catering for the public demand for a cheap and serviceable boot.    The position in regard to  the woollen textile trade  has undergone no change, and  whilethe hosiery trade  has shown a slight upward tendency, there  is no evidence as yet that theposition reached will be  maintained.    Building Trades. The London (Central) Exchange for the Building Trades reportincreased activity, particularly in regard to firms engaged in decorating work.   Bricklayersand slaters are still in urgent  demand and very difficult to obtain.  As further illustratingthe extent  of the present depression, and  the  variety  of trades affected, in the North-Western Division, it is now reported that there is a distinct slackening in trades hithertounaffected, notably in the building trade, which is apparently influenced by the anticipatedearly  fall in the price of building material, and in the glass  industry, which  is said  to becurtailing production owing to lack of orders.    Transport. Middlesbrough report  that with the settlement of the strike of tug-boatmen, which has been in  progress for ten weeks, an improvement in the transport industry of the port may  be  looked for.  On the other hand at Liverpool,  many large sea-going vessels are  laid up  owing to  shortage  of freights, and in consequence transport work isslack, and many seamen are idle.    Labour Reductions. In addition to  the  difficulties mentioned above, Peterboroughreport that the  English Clock  and Gramophone  Co.,  Huntingdon, have closed  down,and 150 workpeople  have been discharged.  At Scunthorpe, Messrs.  A. Cross &amp;  Sons,Ltd.,  basic slag manufacturers,  employing about 148 men, have closed down indefinitely.The Appleby Iron  Co.,  Ltd., Scunthorpe,  also  ceased  production  entirely  on the 22ndJanuary.    At York, Messrs. Rowntree  &amp; Co., Ltd.,  are discharging 100 men this week, and 300more  are being placed on short time.*  From Airdrie, it is reported that the DarngavilCoal Co. have closed one of  their  pits, owing to the  coal being practically  worked out;200 miners are affected.                    * See this Report Vol. Ill, No. 3, 15th January, page 45.
  Women&apos;s Employment.      General Situation. Reports  indicate little  change.   In some cases factories which  were closed are now reported to be working part time, but against this must be set the fact  that other factories are closing down.      Increased registers are shown throughout all divisions, the heaviest rises being in the  London and South-Eastern Division, where they have increased by  nearly 5,000;  in the  North-Western,  Yorkshire and East  Midlands, West Midlands and  Ireland Divisions,  in each of which there have been increases of approximately 3,000; and in Scotland, where  there has been an increase of approximately 2,000.   These figures do not include short-  time workers.     Local Reports. In the North-Western Division the  cotton industry continues in a  very critical condition, and every other industry throughout the division is also  suffering from the effects of the depression.  At Accrington several large mills are now closing down entirely for one week or more.   At Rochdale there is almost universal under-employment in the cotton trade.  In other cases reports have been received stating that full time is being worked.   At  Bury one firm  of cotton manufacturers  have  resumed full-time employment for a period, affecting approximately 500 workpeople.     At Denton the hatting industry remains depressed.  A firm of leather dressers in the area have closed down, and there is much unemployment amongst all classes  of factory workers in Liverpool, as well as in the tailoring and other sewing trades.   The paper industry in Glossop is also depressed.     Depression in the textile and clothing centres is again reported from the Yorkshire and East Midlands  Division.   Depression continues  in the  lace-making towns, Basford, Beeston, Nottingham, and Long Eaton and at Derby  in hosiery, lace, corset, and boot  and shoe manufacture.     At Hebden Bridge  a more hopeful note is reported from the cotton trade, but it is said it will be some  time before full time is resumed.  Leeds, however, report that many firms are starting work for a  few days a week.     The position in  the engineering  trades in the West Midlands Division appears to be steadily growing worse, and the leather, rubber and clothing trades are also depressed. The boom in the pottery trade appears to be definitely over.  At Longton it is stated that unemployment  is increasing rapidly among women in this industry, and at  Stoke-on- Trent pottery workers are continuing  on short  time.  Many of  these who had deferred claiming benefit, hoping that employment would be  more regular after the holidays,  are now doing so.   Birmingham  report large increases in the  live  register and a decrease in the numbers of vacancies notified.     There is little change in the general situation in the South Midlands and  Eastern Division.  Northampton report a slight improvement  in the boot and shoe trade.  Abnor- mal unemployment, however, continues in  this town.  Leicester report that  900 fresh claims to unemployment insurance benefit have been made  this week.  At Kettering there are  practically no  openings for women in boot and shoe manufacture and  wholesale clothing.     The London and South-Eastern Division report  increases  rather than abatement in unemployment among factory  workers in  London.  At  Bermondsey,  for example,  the live register is nearly 3,000, and, including short-time workers, those claiming unemploy- ment insurance benefit are over  4,000.  At East Ham and Enfield the  live register is over 1,200. At Poplar the register is increased owing to the fact that the Hayes Cocoa Co., Ltd., Bromley, have closed down, affecting approximately  1,000 workpeople.  At Whiter chapel the live register stands at over 5,000;  at Tottenham it is nearly 2,000,  and at Walham Green over 1,000.  A  slight revival in  the dressmaking and millinery trades is reported from Great Marlborough Street.    The situation in the South-Western  Division is unchanged.  The staple clothing industries remain depressed, and the most serious unemployment in the division is reported from  Bristol  and Gloucester.   At  the  former Exchange there are approximately 1,400 women on the live register, in addition to 3,600 short-time  workers.   At Gloucester there are 653 women on the live register and  189 short-time workers.  The numbers of married women registering,  owing to the partial or  total unemployment of their husbands, is increasing.  At Swindon there are nearly 400 workers on the register owing to depressionin the tailoring  and  shirt-making industries.  The glove-making industry is depressedboth at Yeovil and Barnstaple.
    The situation in Wales shows little change.  Although unemployment is increasingin such towns as Cardiff, Llanelly, and Swansea, it is not serious compared with that inother parts of the country.    The clothing trade continues to be slack in the Northern Division, and there is slacknessin the ropery industry  at various centres, such as Dunston-on-Tyne, Hebburn-on-Tyneand Willington Quay.    In Scotland a  considerable amount  of short time and depression continues  in  the textile, calico  printing, hosiery, tailoring, linen,  flax,  rubber  and jute  trades.   Heavyunemployment continues to be reported from the Exchanges in the Glasgow area,  and atEdinburgh the live register now stands at over 1,000.                     LOCAL  EMPLOYMENT  COMMITTEES.    Employment. Committees generally  continue to show much activity in approachinglocal authorities with a view to commencing relief works in their respective areas.  Torquayreport that as a direct result of their deputation to the Corporation, 30 men have already begun work.  East Ham have asked the department to urge the Disposals Board to releasefor the purposes of manufacture all wool which is being held up in  various London docks.In connection with  the Governments  short-time arrangements in H.M.  Dockyards  and naval Establishments, the Portsmouth Committee have arranged to assist the authoritiesin selecting the applicants  for employment in the Portsmouth Yards.  For this purpose they propose to form rota  committees from their members, with the addition of such members of the Dockyards Committee as are not already members of the employment committees.    Out-of-Work Donation  and  Unemployment  Insurance. I he Paddington  Committee,being of opinion that the only work capable of absorbing unskilled  women in any numberis domestic  service,  suggest  that the Minister  should issue a&apos;) order to the effect thatunemployed women  who will not accept positions as domestic servants should be ineligibleforthwith  for  further unemployment  benefit.    High Wycombe  also make a  similarsuggestion.    General. The Paddington Committee propose to circulate  a resolution that, in theiropinion, Exchanges  are understaffed, with the  result that considerable overtime has tobe performed, while a large number of unemployed clerks could be engaged to  relieve the pressure.  The  department  have  replied  that  additional temporary assistance is engaged where necessary and practicable.     OUT-OF-WORK DONATION, AND  UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BENEFIT.    Out-of-Work Donation. Returns by the Finance Department, according to information received at the Claims  and Record Office, Kew, for  the week  ending the 20th January,show 320,645 payments to policy-holders, involving an amount  of  298,919 18s. Id.     Unemployment  Insurance. The number of payments of unemployment insurance benefit during the  week ending 14th January was 708,003,  involving an  amount of 335,087 Is. lid.                               JUVENILE ^BRANCH.    Training in Agriculture. The Plymouth Juvenile Advisory  Committee, in continuanceof their efforts in connection with juvenile agricultural labour, have recently appointedmembers  to confer  with representatives of the Tavistock farmers.  While  it was  con-sidered impossible to indenture lads under a scheme of apprenticeship, it was agreed  that definite training, after three months&apos; probation, was necessary.   It was accordingly deciaedto submit (suggestions for  a scheme of training to  the farmers.  The necessity  for the adequate supervision of boys placed in this work was poiated out, and it was stated thatthis  would be done through the juvenile representative on the local Employment Com-mittee&apos;s area sub-committee.  This subject was  also discussed at a meeting  of the  Educa-tion Committee of the Farmers&apos; Union, at which representatives of the Kent education committee attended.  Opinion was  divided as to the practicability of  sending  lads asapprentices on farms, but the principle of an apprenticeship scheme was finally approved.    Domestic Service. Considerable  interest has been shown in the question of domestic service at Ipswich,  where  the Juvenile Advisory Committee have drawn up a standardof minimum conditions for juveniles placed in  this  occupation in the area.  In order to
APPOINTMENTS  AND  TRAINING.     APPOINTMENTS AND  CIVIL LIABILITIES DEPARTMENT,                                APPOINTMENTS.    Statistics. During the week ending the 21st January, the Appointments Departmentplaced 415  candidates for appointments, bringing the total number of candidates knownto have been placed to  48,860.  Of these, 6,629 have been placed through the  agency of the departments  Interviewing Boards.  Applications were registered  from 850 ex-Service men and 26 civilians.  The number of  candidates  available for  appointmentson the 21st January  was 10,720 ex-Service men  and 1,413 civilians.  At the same date,069 &quot; live &quot; vacancies were at the disposal of the department, 475 having been registeredduring the week.                     BUSINESS AND PROFESSIONAL TRAINING.    Maintenance and  Training Grants Scheme. During the week ending the 21st January,the Appointments Department received 15 applications  for training under this scheme,of which 11 were for training  of the type provided by the department.  Deductingcancellations and withdrawals, 28,212  applications for training of this  type  have beenreceived in all, and 49,734 for the types provided  by  other Government departments.The  Interviewing Boards have dealt to date with 27,687 applications,  of which 23,206have been recommended.  The Grants Committee,  dealing with applications so recom-mended, have received 22,113 applications, and sanctioned grants in 18,297 cases.    Of the  223 candidates who were successful in the Final Examination of the institute of Chartered Accountants of England and Wales, held in November last, 103 were traineesunder the Training Grants Scheme of the Ministry of Labour, including the winners of the institute Prize, the W. B. Peat Gold Medal and Prize,  and  the 1st Class Certificate ofMerit, and the 3rd and  4th Class Certificates of Merit.    Business Training Scheme. During the week ending the 21st January the Appoint-ments Department received 156 applications for training  under this scheme, bringing thetotal number of  applications to  1,957,  of which 401 have since  been cancelled.  Grantshave been sanctioned in 343  cases.  At  the same date  314 &quot; live &quot; training vacancieswere at the disposal of the department, 56 having been  registered during the week.    Training of Disabled Officers under Pensions Warrant. The Appointments Departmenthave dealt with a total of 1,007 cases, in 465 of which the training sanctioned is providedby the Appointments Department and in the remainder by other Government departments.Candidates accepted by the Ministry of Labour have completed their training in 261 cases,and abandoned training  in 45; 142 are still in training,  and  17  are awaiting training.encourage girls to take up this calling, a meeting of girls leaving school has been held,which was well attended both by the girls and by their parents.  A musical programme was arranged, and during the interval two addresses were given on the subject of domestic service.    Trade Schools (Swansea). -The serious position of young girls, formerly employed asdressmaking and tailoring apprentices  and improvers, has been engaging the  attentionof the Swansea Juvenile E nploy/nent Committee.  A resolution has  been passed inviting the Education Committee to consider the advisability  of establishing a trade school lorthe training of young persons in these trades.    [Reference to matters of interest to the Employment and Insurance  Department will alsobe found on pages 123, 124, 132, 134 and 146 to 148.]
                                      145   a5.2.21.                          TRAINING DEPARTMENT.                             INDUSTRIAL  TRAINING. Disabled and Other Ex-Service Men.     Statistics. On the 25th January, 25,063 men were in training, as against 25,069 on the  18th January, and 24,932 on the 28th December.   The number oi men placed in training during the week was 573.  There were 16,083 men awaiting training, the corres- ponding totals for the 18th  January and the  28th December being 16,145 and 16,034 respectively.  The number of men whose  training had  been  completed since  the  1st August, 1919, was 24,723, the totals for the 18th January and the 28th December being 24,144 and  22,998, respectively.     At the  close of the year, just under 3,000  men were receiving institutional training in various branches of the building trades,  the majority in Government Instructional Factories.   Of these nearly half were carpenters and joiners  and a fifth bricklayers.  At the present time the number of men in training in the building trade is considerably higher than that for any other  trade group.     Exhibitions, -It has  now been ascertained that over  100 worth of baskets were sold at the Ex-Service Men&apos;s Carnival at the White City, a very welcome result financially, as at least  one of  the basket-making factories had  accumulated a large   stock and was experiencing considerable difficulty in its disposal.     At the  Tailor and Cutter Exhibition, held on the 20th January, the  exhibits shown by ex-Service men reached a very high  standard.  Members of the trade admitted that the intensive system adopted in the training centres had produced  much better results than any obtained under the normal system of apprenticeship.  The gold medals in the three classes were won respectively by Aberdeen, Rathbone Place and Harlesden.     The Minister, accompanied by Mrs. Macnamara, visited the Radnor Road Factory, Bristol, on the 21st January, when he opened the new extension.  The opportunity was taken to provide an exhibition of the work of the men in training, who  were to be seen carrying on their trades  as usual, the actual working spaces being railed off.  Visitors, who were very numerous,  were thus enabled to see the men at work in the various processes in each of the different stages of production.  The  exhibition appears to have caused an excellent impression, and was the subject  of highly favourable comments in the  local newspapers.          5     Hostels, Canteens and Welfare In addition to the group of hostels at Birtley,  there are 11 individual hostels  under the Ministry&apos;s supervision.  Attached to non-residential factories are seven  canteens under the  Ministry&apos;s  management,  and, in addition, the Ministry have equipped  canteens  at Garrison Lane,  Birmingham, and  Forbesfield, Aberdeen.     In  addition there are now five factories in which hostel and canteen accommodation is combined.  In one instance, at Luton, the canteen has been  equipped by the Ministry but is managed under contract by Messrs. Slaters, Ltd.     In  the majority of the newer factories, mess-rooms are being installed in preference to canteens.   Proposals have been submitted in 25 cases, and 11 mess-rooms are already in working order or about to he opened.   These rooms are not infrequently used as recreation centres.     The authority for establishing welfare facilities is  being widely utilised; pianos, billiard  tables,  etc., are provided, and indoor and outdoor  games are organised.   The management of welfare work is vested in a Welfare Committee containing representatives of the men.  Welfare funds are supplemented by subscriptions from  the  men and other sources, and by  the allocation of fines for unpunctuality.     Government Instructional Factories. The number of men in Government Instructional Factories has now reached a total of approximately 9,700, an increase  of between 500 and  600 in about three weeks, and it is practically certain that the number will exceed 10,000 within the next week or two.    In  all the factories acquired by the department, work has now started,  with the exception of the Old Kent Road Factory.   There is good  reason to believe that this factory  will  come on to the active list in about a month&apos;s time.    National Trade Advisory Committees: 4 Boat  Building.-A  meeting was  held  atWinchester on the 20th January, with the result that a Local Advisory Panel was formed,  (B  16930T)                                                                T
 Appointments and  Training-continued. the secretary being the manager of the Portsmouth Employment Exchange.   A scheme of training, as drawn up by the department, was agreed to by the committee, and it is hoped to start training 20 men, to be increased eventually to 50, at Salisbury Court.  The panel in question will advise and adjudicate on matters connected  with training  in the areas of Portsmouth,  Southampton, the Isle of Wight, the Medway and the Upper Thames.     National  Trade Advisory Committees :  Glass. A meeting of the committee was held on the 25th January.  Consideration was given to resolutions from the Leeds and London Local Technical Advisory Committees that the period of training should  be extended in the bench section of the trade.  It was resolved to recommend  that the present period of training of  13 weeks in a technical school or Government Instructional Factory, and 39 weeks in  a  workshop of an employer, should be extended to 39 weeks in a  Government Instructional Factory or technical school, and  39 weeks in the workshop of  an employer.     A resolution passed by the London  Local Technical Advisory Committee respecting the free importation of glassware was considered, and it was unanimously resolved that if the free importation of glassware continues it would be futile to approve of further disabled ex-Service men being passed for training; but that the committee are prepared to continue to afford every facility for the absorption of these men, if the  industry can be protected.  A resolution was also passed that, in view of the continued unemployment in the glass trade, intensified by the free importation of glassware, the committee considered it inadvisable for any further men to be placed in training.     National  Trade Advisory Committee: Bespoke Tailoring. A meeting of the National Trade Advisory Committee was held on the 20th January, when the question of retail and bulk disposal of the products of training classes was again discussed.  The Wholesale Clothiers&apos; Federation have agreed to consider  how stocks accumulated in centres can be disposed of on advantageous terms without embarrassing the trade, and a  summary of the necessary  information is to be supplied to  the Federation.    Local Technical Advisory Committees: Wholesale Tailoring. The Bristol Committee have  decided to admit no more men into training in the area owing to the depressed state of trade.  They  have spared no pains in  the past to give every man a good start in the industry, both employers and journeymen making considerable sacrifices to this end. Apprenticeships Interrupted by Service.    Statistics.-^  to the  26th  January  agreements had been received at  headquarters in respect of 45,487 apprentices under the 41 schemes approved.   Grants had been sanc- tioned in respect of  43,500 apprentices, employed by 17,318 employers.  The total  number of agreements lapsed on expiration of the  appropriate period  of training, or by  mutual agreement between  the parties,  is now 17,332.    Applications. Difficulty, probably due to trade depression, is reported in providing for unmated apprentices in the South-West of England, one of the  areas in which they are most numerous.  Local  headquarters report that more than 100 are still unprovided for, and they are now finding it very hard to induce employers to bring any  of these menunder the  scheme.   Local headquarters  for the London  and South-Eastern  area  also reported recently that  at  the moment there is no marked progress in placing unmated apprentices.    In the  South-Western  area, certain  apprentices did not make application beforethe closing date, because they then were in employment at reasonable wages.   Havingrecently been  dismissed owing to trade depression, they now  desire to come under the scheme.  They appear,  however, to have  been fully aware of its existence before the closing date, and thus do not seem to be entitled to have their applications accepted.   An apprentice in the London and South-Eastern area was demobilised in 1916 but has only recently made application.  He  has been undergoing hospital treatment for a paralysed arm,  and  has  only  been pronounced fit  to resume his pre-war employment within the last few weeks.  He appears, therefore, to come within the provisions  for special cases, and Ms pre-war  employer is prepared to  bring him under the scheme.    Acceptance or Non-Acceptance. A firm of printers in the Yorkshire and East Midlands area persisted  in refusing to bring two apprentices under the scheme,  till after it had been closed.  Subsequently they became liable, under an arrangement within the  industry, topay them five-sixths of the prescribed rate, &quot;the amount provided in the printing  schemefor the second half of renewed apprenticeship,  and desired therefore to bring them under
the scheme.   Their applications were refused.  They have ceased to employ one of theapprentices, who has completed his training, but nevertheless claim State grant for thewhole period since his return from the Forces.   They also threaten to dismiss the otherapprentice, unless he is accepted under the scheme.  The trade union concerned have,however,  taken action to  prevent this apprentice being discharged.    Non-Observance of Conditions. Local headquarters for the South-Western area reportthat the  prevalence  of unemployment is leading an increasing number of employers toattempt  to evade  their  obligations  under the  scheme.  Certain firms, indeed, haveapproached the department to assist in, or countenance, the dismissal of the apprentices.    The  executive  of the Amalgamated  Engineering Union have agreed to legal pro-ceedings to secure for the 17 apprentices of Messrs. John Lewis  &amp; Sons, Ltd., Aberdeen,engineers, the wages  due  to them under their agreements.  The cases are causing great interest locally among employers,  and especially  among other engineering firms whohave  carried out their agreements.   The matter could not be dealt with through the local employment  Committee,  owing to the unwillingness of other local employers to sit injudgment upon the  firm.    Termination of Agreements. A recent return from Scotland shows that 4,266 appren-tices, or about 37 per cent, of those accepted,  had terminated their training by the endof 1920.  The percentage  is much the same in  the rest  of the United Kingdom.   There.were  about 7,300 apprentices, employed by 2,765 firms, still in training in Scotland atthe close  of the year.     Unemployment. There is further evidence,  apart  from   increasing  demands  forinstitutional  training, of  the growing effects of unemployment  upon apprentices underthe scheme.   At Leicester, for instance, the British  Shoe Machinery Co.,  Ltd., areemploying their 80 returned apprentices, along with their other  workpeople, in alternateweeks only.  In this firm, however, apprentices under the scheme are  regarded  as beingindentured ;  and, since indentured apprentices are presumed to be employed continuously,they  may claim payment for the  weeks during which they are idle.  At Southampton,Messrs. J. I. Thornycroft &amp; Co., Ltd., engineers and shipbuilders, have temporarily sus-pended 30 apprentices under the scheme.    Institutional Training. In Scotland,  more firms are  being compelled to put theirapprentices on  short time,  and are inquiring whether technical classes can be arranged for them. Such provision  is becoming a matter of difficulty,  owing to the  increasing numbers  to be dealt with ;  but local headquarters hope to be able to make the necessary arrangements at the  Paisley Technical College,  where the Principal has throughout giventhe department every possible assistance.   In the London area, also, the increasing appli-cations by engineering apprentices for whole-time  institutional  training have exhaustedthe available  facilities, and the more recent applicants have not yet been provided for.To meet  the  need, local  headquarters have approached the Borough Polytechnic,  who-have agreed to provide a special whole-time course, if a minimum of 20 apprentices canbe secured.General Training.     Apprenticeship :  Building-The action of the Midland District Council of the BuildingTrades&apos; Federation, in circulating their branches in favour of the scheme, is regarded bylocal headquarters as an  important step  in advance, as the branches are most loyal totheir district organiser and unwilling to take action without his instructions.  At Rugby,in spite of some ill-feeling caused by the strike in the autumn,  and at Leamington, both employers and  operatives favour the adoption of the scheme, and joint conferences arebeing held.  At West Bromwich the employers, though less favourable, have consented to meet the operatives ; at Walsall, the scheme is being considered in detail; at Nuneaton,the employers have definitely adopted it, and the operatives are also favourable.   progress is also reported at  Shrewsbury and Redditch.  On the other  hand,  the  employers atBlackheath, Birmingham, have definitely  rejected the scheme, fearing undue interferenceby the operatives ; and an unfavourable attitude is being adopted by both sides at Wolver-hampton and by the employers in the Potteries.    Apprenticeship :  Engineering. At Broadheath, Cheshire, several important firms arein favour of all lads working through a schedule of processes, thus preventing their retentionon repetition work ; a six months&apos; period of probation in cases of indentured apprenticeship;the promotion of unskilled boy labourers,  wherever  possible and  after a period of trial, to
5.2.21,148trade apprenticeships;  and the provision of improved facilities for technical training,which at present are very inadequate.  There is  not the  same agreement  in regard toattendance at the day continuation school, which will soon be opened in  the  locality,some firms preferring the establishment of works schools.     Apprenticeship:  Printing. At Preston a number of firms concur  in the view thatboys should only be apprenticed to employers who can guarantee adequate training,  as,under existing conditions, many are not fully efficient after completing an apprenticeship,and some have to leave the trade.   They also believe that where an apprentice attendsa technical school until the age of 16, the maximum term of apprenticeship should befive years.  One employer indeed advocates a general reduction from seven to five years,and also the holding of trade examinations,  one at the end of the third year,  and theother at the close, of apprenticeship.   In South  Wales,  again, the employers  desire areduction in the term from seven to four or five years, but this is opposed by the operatives,who fear a  flood of apprentices  and  consequent  unemployment.   A general dearth ofbookbinders&apos;  apprentices is  reported in the West  Midlands, owing  to the higher  wagesobtainable in other industries, and the  reluctance of parents and boys  to bind themselves for a number of years.  In London, attention is  drawn to the liability of workers  in thetrade to lung diseases and chest complaints, and  to the strain upon the eyes  in monotypework; while stereotypers, who are  healthier in these respects, are somewhat liable to lead poisoning.    There is considerable evidence that the industry would welcome a definite  national scheme on the lines  of the building industry.  Both employers and operatives in  SouthWales have  expressed willingness to consider proposals to  this effect, and an importantNorth of  England firm  are also prepared to co-operate.   The readiness of employers inthis and other industries to discuss the problem with officers of the department is indi-cative of a revival of interest in the question of training and a realisation of its importance for  the  future of industry.    [Reference to matters  of interest to the Appointments and Training  Departments willalso be found on pages 132, 143 and  144.]

</content>
</cab>
