<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 404-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s  Government.secret.CP.  2563.                               THE  CABINET.THE  POSITION  IN  GERMAN  AUSTRIA.       MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.    The  enclosed memorandum  has been  given me by the Master of Sempill who inconnection with Air Force work has been for a long time in Vienna since the end ofthe war.  It seems to me to state the facts with terseness.                                                                   w. s.  c.  THE WAR OFFICE,    fO&amp;  February, 1921.  A BRIEF STATEMENT CONCERNING THE PRESENT  POSITION  IN  GERMAN AUSTRIA.    The present position of German Austria  is a tragedy.   There  may be aspects ofthe tragedy, however,  which are fraught with  vast consequences, not only  for theconstellation of  Central and South-Central Europe,  but also for the peace of Europe.                             I. Austria Bankrupt.    German Austria as it stands cannot endure long.   It  is of no use to speak of coming bankruptcy.  In modern states no sudden crash can take place.   Paper money is floated and the currency goes down towards  vanishing point in value.   That hasalready happened in Austria.  Where there is much wealth in the form of wood, ironand  water-power,  not  to  speak  of lesser  agricultural  and industrials  values, the purchasing power  of money can never  reach zero point.    Austria is  neverthelessbankrupt.   She is a beggar  in  Europe;  a prey to  the profiteers many of themforeigners who abound in an impoverished country.                 II. The Possibilities for  the Future of Austria.    For reasons to be given later, German Austria cannot  be saved by large creditsfrom foreign powers.  As a unit, surrounded as she is, she is an economic impossibility.    Austria must, therefore, change at least her economic status  if she  is to endure.    There are,  roughly, two possibilities, both  of which  are  being canvassed at themoment.   One, that she should  change both her political  and economic  status,  byentering  the German  Reich, as a confederate state.  This is the &quot; Anschluss  anDeutschland &quot;  policy, which finds many adherents both in Vienna and Berlin. Theother is the building up of  a Zoll-Verein,  or Customs Union, between Austria and someof  its  neighbours.   That  such a  Customs  Union might   develop into a  PoliticalConfederation  is obvious.   At the moment the idea of a Confederation the so-calledDanube Confederation would not find favour in many circles. Let us keep, therefore,to the strict minimum alternative, a Customs Union.           *    The  &quot; Anschluss an  Deutschland&quot; policy  would  make for a  greater  Germany,would arouse every suspicion of the French, would frighten  the Czech  Government toan almost incredible degree and so awaken no  little opposition.    The Customs Union policy would probably be favoured by the French as the onlyfeasible alternative.   It too would be disliked  by the Czech  Government, which wouldcry out against  a &quot; reconstruction &quot; of old Austria.    One  or the  other of  these  policies,  whatever be  the likes  or  dislikes  ofneighbouring states, must, however, be followed.  The Treaty  with Austria was inmany ways defective.   Whatever  be the sentiments of the  Entente  Governmentconcerning honour, prestige, change  of policy, or mercy, Austria, as it  stands, cannotlast.  Thus, Austria must either join Germany or else join in a larger Customs Union.    (21/88) 100 2/21  H&amp;S, Ltd  8955wo
                     III. The Internal Conditions of Austria.     (a.) Political. The elections in October resulted in a majority for the conservative and  Bourgeois parties.   The  Socialists, however, enjoy a  large  and very powerfulminority.   The  members are  112 the total  of the Coalition and 85 respectively.This menacing minority of 85 really rule the country.  On its side and at its ordersstand:      (1.) The  Army of  Austria, which in  many ways  is  little  better than a lied           Guard,  and     (2.) The whole of the organized Socialist workmen in the industrial centres, who           are adequately armed.     A word of each of these supports      (1.) The Army. The Army is through  and through  given up for the most part toSocialism  of the extreme type.   Many of  the  soldiers want nothing better than  a soviet Republic.  They canvassed with red bands and red cockades  in the  last elections.This Army is worth little or nothing in cause of law and order.   If given a command the  soldiers  debate the question of obedience.  They  are open to  every  bribery.Recently when the Danube was flooded, some battalions were given orders to assibt the civilians.  They debated and refused on the ground that it was not work for a soldier.On other occasions they demanded extraordinary pay for any special work, and in caseof refusal, openly disobeyed.     The army costs the State some  5 milliard  kroneh per  annum.  One private  cansometimes  cost  between 70 and 80 thousands kronen per annum  in pay alone.  Thearmy is thus very expensive, and except in  cause  of extreme socialism, on  the  wholeworthless.     (2.) The Workmen Battalions. The workmen are armed and brigaded  in largenumbers.   Battalions have their officers, non-commissioned  officers, &amp;c, all elected by themselves.  They are armed with rifles and  guns with machine-guns belonging to oldAustria with fiammenwerfcr in large  numbers and grenades.   They parade openly.They are very numerous.             In Vienna there are perhaps     ...    ...  100,000  (circa).             In Wiener Neustadt and surroundings  ...   40,000    ,,             In Upper  Austria  ...     ...     ..     ...    LI,000    ,,             In Salzburg......     .........     2,000    ,,             In Styria   ...     ...     ...     ...    ...    30,000    ,,             In Tyrol   ......     .........     1,000    ,,     These workmen&apos;s battalions, devoted to extremist measures, have large dep6ts ofarms in Vienna, Wiener Neustadt, Steyr,  Linz,  Wels,  Klagenfurt, &amp;c.  When  theCommission tried to disarm the people, the depots were emptied, as each man  took hisarms or the machine-guns home.     Against this doable-armed menace the Conservative  majority in  the AustrianParliament is powerless.  If any unpopular law were passed, then strikes  in  rapid suc-cession would be organized, so as to impede the public life in every way.  Many instanceshave already occurred.   The International Secretary  of Bolshevism who was  expelled.from Amsterdam flourishes in Vienna.   The influence of this office is pernicious.  TheGovernment  is, however, powerless, as railways,  factories,  transport, &amp;c. indeed allthe public services are at the mercy  of the extremists and agitators.   Indeed manywell-informed people think that these people would strangle  Austria  by a succession of strikes if the Foreign Powers decided to give large credits to the present conservative government.  They want  to wait for the  spring, when they hope that the  RussianBolsheviks may be again active and thus give them a chance.  This is a real danger.In a desperate country extremists are apt to pursue wild and  terrible policies.  Thesemen see nothing to  lose  and everything to win by securing everything  in their hands.The  powerlessness of the Government to remedy the disastrous state of things  is thecapital  fact of the situation.   There is a persistent effort on the  part of  the Socialistsagainst the recuperation  or reconstruction of Austria.   They want  to keep the groundwell  prepared  for  extreme  measures.   Their  arms and battalions are a  direct and immediate  menace.     (b.) Economic situation. The economic situation  is characterized by the absenceof production and the inability to purchase raw materials.     Production when it  occurs is so  dear owing to excessive wages and depreciatedcurrency that articles cannot compete with the European market price.    This  has been
 foimd  in  connection with  motor industry at  Steyr.  All textile  industries are  at  a standstill; there  is no  raw  material and labour charges an  impossible competitively impossible-price.     -Export of cattle would be possible, but owing to difference in  money-value  in the adjoining  countries, is in practice impossible.   Customs officers are bribed and cattle in large numbers are driven over the frontiers into Bavaria or Italy.   Thus, for a certain period  between 1,000 and 2,000 head of cattle were driven each week over the frontier into Bavaria.   The length of the frontier was about I 5 miles.   It was also  a propitious spot for this smuggling.  Customs officers are either bribed or terrorized.  Soldiers  were placed  there ;  they were found  to smuggle themselves, as well  as to take bribes;  they were therefore recalled.   Price per kilo, live, weight, in Bavaria is 25 marks, in Austria 37 kronen.     Apart from this inducement to illicit traffic, the export problem .is  difficult.  The country has not the right shape and the railways are constructed for old Austria.  There is only a single line from Innsbruck to Bregenz.  The congestion of the railways, due to want of coal, the defective management and the inherent difficulties, make export difficult.     The actual value of the kronen makes  import practically impossible.   The Govern- ment must buy commodities like flour and sell them  at  25 per cent, of the cost price, meeting or not meeting the remaining 75  per cent, as best  as they can.  Once again this economic situation cannot  be  improved.    Austria  as .an independent economic unit is  not possible.  The minor  improvements that are obviously possible are impeded by the  armed force of the Socialists, Communist and other extremists.     (c.) The financial situation. Little need be added on  this score.  The burden of  , State finance is  impossibly  heavy.  The  Government,  owing to depreciation  of  a bankrupt  currency, must purchase  certain machinery and many footstuffs, like  flour and sugar.  Much of the cost must be borne by the  State,  as only wealthy people, profiteers and foreigners can afford the excessive prices.     The army, as already stated, costs an enormous sum, and  is nothing more than  a burden.     The railways are  overstaffed by old  Austrian officials, who are thus given work and a means of livelihood.  The actual  Government cannot  touch this situation;  any change would immediately call forth an organized railway and transport strike.     One other item in the  financial situation is a scandal for the Entente peoples. Foreigners prey on Austria  to  an  almost incredible  degree.  The members  of the Relief Commission traffic in  goods and money, speculate  on the  Exchange and  buy goods and  shares from impoverished people  who need  immediate cash for food.   These foreigners  by  speculation and by  their lavish style of living  raise prices.  Vultures preying on dead bodies could not be more revolting.     Briefly, the financial burden on the State is far beyond its capacity, the economic situation is characterized by paralysis, and the political conditions are weighted against decency and  order by the  Bed Guard,  styled an Army,  and armed battalions of workmen.                            IV. The possible remedies.     The present year will probably decide the fate of the countries that border Russia to the west and south-west, and among  others of Austria and Czecho-Slovakia.   The hopes of extremists in both countries are set for the coming spring and summer.  From the preceding  statement the danger in Austria is clear. ,    (a.) I consider, therefore, that  it is a  matter of immediate and  urgent necessity that the Austrian army the &quot;  Red  Guard&quot; should  be disbanded.   This must  and can  only be done by the pressure  of the  Entente.   Moreover,  far  better that  the pressure came from England, as the reputation of Great Britain  stands honourably high in the defeated countries, while  every action  of the French  is not without cause  open to grave  suspicion.   The French, too, are hated bitterly.     Austria cannot be left utterly without  an  army.  It would therefore be advisable to use the Civilian Guard or Mnwohnerwehr, which certainly stand for decency, law and order.   It is, of course,  suspected of  being  a monarchic instrument.  None can expect the people  of  Tyrol to be Republicans.  But their chief object is  the maintainance of order.   They are, therefore, a very valuable asset to the peace of Europe.   This Civilian Guard could be utilized for the few necessary military services of the Staie.    The question is briefly this.  Do the Entente Powers want to  see conservative or extremists  troops in the armies of the countries bordering Russia ?   This particularlyin view  of  the possibilities of the spring and summer.
    (b.) Without doubt  the workmens battalions should be  disbanded and the armsseized.   If this  were done  by an  Entente Commission, which would put itself in contact with  the right  persons, the quantity  of arms seized  would  be surprising.Obviously, too, the ammunition and arms  factories should be placed under adequatesurveillance.   It is foolish to allow tracks of gunpowder to be laid across Europe.    (c.) England ought  to make up her  mind  at once to help  in the formation of a customs Union between Austria and Hungary.    Here,  probably,  the  great difficulty would  be found in the question  of WesternHungary, which is to be ceded to Austria.   As the people in Western Hungary do not want  to join  Austria, this difficulty might  surely  be met by  the  declaration  of a plebiscite.  Let the people themselves decide.    Moreover, England might well try to relax at least the stringency of the Customsregulations between Austria and Czecho-Slovakia. Czecho-Slovakia will certainly resist.But let her be shown her alternative.  Austria bankrupt and without hope  will, if noCustoms Union be formed, certainly join Germany.  Germany  down on the borders ofCzecho-Slovakia,  where 3i  million  Germans,  owing to unjust and  foolish treatment,form a solid, discontented  and aggressive minority, might  bring the inevitable day when  the Germans will override all Czech resistance, dangerously near.   In any caseCzecho-Slovakia must in this and other ways  be taught to be reasonable.   The lessonwill not be  easy.    Above all, in these things, let England take the lead and not France.   For many,if France suggested a scheme which would make Austria flourish beyond all expectations,the scheme would be  mistrusted and hated, because it came from France.  For Englandthere  is a great respect and an assurance of decent treatment.    If these facts and suggestions  prove  of  value they have been put together very carefully after consulting many outstanding people I shall be pleased  to deal with them more fully either in a subsequent memorandum or by word of mouth  early  in February

</content>
</cab>
