<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 457-460</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                 /     /     -isrs u)OmPNT IS THE PROPERTY 0^ HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT).JET.                        CABINET,. 2568 *    E?!0?? S TH&quot; GENERAL OFFICER CO ^commanding-IN^CHIEF ON            THF SITUATION:IN J^LAND FOR,THE week ENDING                         FEBRUARY 5thA, 1931.        (Circulated by the Secretary.of State for v-far).   GENERAL SITUATION,     There has been increased activity on the part of the rebelsluring the past week as anticipated In my last reports     tt is most marked in Dublin City where the bombing of Military?r Police Vehicles is now almost of daily occurrence.     There has also been an increase since last week in the numberit outrages committed in the Martial Lato Area, but this  I consideris chiefly due to the necessity imposed on the rebel leaders of attempting to show that even under Martial Law, the Irish Republicanirmy is capable of holding its own against the forces of the Crou/n,md in order to preserve its moral which is in serious danger  of beinglowered by the successes achieved by the troops and police In  manyif the recent encounters and the undoubtedly high rebel  casualties.?o this extent the Military, situation has undoubtedly improved.     In spite of reoent captures the Irish Republican Army still seemsto be well supplied with arms and ammunition and it would appear thatsome source of supply still exists outside Ireland.   Reports  have seen received from responsible officers which make it evident  that,although a perfunctory examination of passengers&apos; baggage is made atlie ports of embarkation in Great Britain, no steps are  taken  to ensurehat arms and ammunition are not carried on the person.   Until this isone the influx cf pistols and ammunition will continue  to flow intoIreland; and possibly In increasing quanit^y.   Some time which might bnore profitably employed is. at present wasted in searching the baggageif Military and Naval officers in uniform or in possession of  permits.OPERATIONS. 0/1/21.  Some shots were fired at a sentry at New Barracks, Limerick,         There were no casualties. 50/1/21.  An Armoured Motor tender with Auxiliary RIC. was fired on in DUDTTPJ   the fire was returned.  yOne cadet was wounded and one ivilian  killed, 5I/I/21.  The County Inspector RIC * at Mallow, County Cork, was fired ^anbTslightly wounded.  His wife, who was with him, was fatally ousded. 1/2/21.   ^our constables were fired on at Drimoleague, County Corkj toe was killed and pnother wounded.  The fire was returned but it is Jot believed that the rebels, who numbered about ten, sufferedjasualties.         A Military lorry was bombed in Dublin.  There were no casualties.         A &quot;ilitary lorry was &amp;mfonsfted in Dublin.  There were noasuaTties   11n   A lorry with Auxiliary Police was ambushed in Dublin.  Noi3sualtie3 resulted,                                 -I-
 21V  A large party of rebels were engaged by police near Roscarberry, &apos;ty Cork..  Six Sinn Feiners were seen to fall and were carried away heir comrades who were pursued until they escape4 under cover of ness-  There were no police casualties and no arrests were effected. tel.  Two police lorries wove ambushed near Pallas Green, County. - pick.;  Nine policemen were Allied and two dangerously wounded.  . [e were no rebel casualties, fcl.  The police barrack at Rathcormac, County Cork, was attacked &quot;Half an hour when the&apos; atl-aoK was driven off.  There were no ce casualties and the rebel casualties are unknown.      An Officer of the Royal Fusiliers was attacked by three TFans at Kenmare,, County. Kerry. * He fired six&quot; shots and wounded . or.&apos;his assailants who is new in custody..  The off leer-escaped . injured. &quot; &apos;21During a search in&quot; Kilbrittain, County Cork, Area$one ^Tn was shot dead while escaping and twenty rebels were arrested^J21.  A, Corporal of the Military Foot Police was murdered in a  .c house In Dublin. 81.  Two Military lorries were bombed in&apos;Camdeh Street, Dublin, as suit pf fire by the troops five civilians were wounded. . The same lorries were, again attacked when about to enter Portobello Barracks one officer and two civilians were wounded. - Two revolvers and two is were subsequently picked up at the scene of this second attack.., 210  The GHQ.. Vail lorry on its return journey from Kingstown was icled with bombs and revolver fire in Merrion Square, Dublin, . Fire continued against the lorry In Clare Street and Nassau Street. . It lelieved that the bombs in Merrion Square were thrown by persons red in female costumes..   As a result of these two attacks seven Hans have been admitted to Hospital and nine are in custody. 5/1/21.&quot;The property of.nine civilians was destroyed as a punish- I for the ambush of police lorries near to Pallas Green on Feb. .3rd.-, Wly  A.police constable was fired on and wounded by a shot gunr&quot;public house in Emly, County Limerick.-pi.  A party of armed civilians were seen in a field west of cnagree, County Cork*  Fire was opened on them and three civilian falties occurred, further details of this incident are awaited.. I INTERNMENT OF MEMBFRS OF Tff? I*R.A.    The undermentioned number of members of the I.R.A. have been        recommended for Internment&apos; up to Febry.- 7th,. 1921..       BRIGADE.                                   NTJMBRR..  Inf.,  Bden   (Belfast)                             98.. Londonderry Brigade.-.;                              55..  Infantry 3de.  jAthlone)                          138*.  Infantry Bde,&apos; (Curragh)                          112..[Gtelway Brigade.                                   177&apos;.,\ Infantry Bde.&apos; (Fermoy)                           176.. &apos; Infantry Bde-  (Cork)                            171. i Infantry Bdea: (Limerick)                         117. Kerry  Brigade                                     50... Dublin District                           .       7$fl..                                                         1857..
f362   BHIGADE            1                            NUMBER.1st Division                                       1525th Division                                       4276th Division                                       614Dublin District                                    V63       1857MQilBBRS OF THE I.R.A IffiOOiiLEHDED FOR INTBEHMKNlP BY           RAKES:  Febxy. 7th, 1921.Brigade Commandants&apos;                                15Brigo.de staff  .              i                       36Battalion Ceirimandants                               46Battalion Staff    ;       -                         98Company Office-reV-    &apos;    &quot;&apos;                        780Other ranks &amp; ranks unknown                        ft82       1857RESULTS OF COURTS MARTIAL.I     77&apos; civilians have boon tried by Courts Martial during theweek,  cf whom 62 were convicted and sentenced as under and 15were acquitted.          &quot;-&quot;  v&apos;&quot;;                    &apos;,(a) a Attacks on Military &amp; Polioe.1 to death, commuted to P.S. for life.1 to 15 years P*S*i tc io  &quot;    ,T    &apos;,&apos;  &quot;      -  &apos; &quot;  ;2 to 7    w    w1 to 5    &quot;    &quot;2 -go 2 years with H-*L.(b) o B ir.gJ^ PoBHession of Arms &amp; Ammunition.1 to 15 years P*.St&apos; &apos;    ...........6 tc 5    &quot;    w4 to 5 &apos;   TV    &apos;&quot;1 to 18 months with H*L. o1 to 12   n      &quot;    &quot;1 to 9    TT      &quot;    TT -1 to 6    &quot;    without H.L.2 to 2    &quot; .      &quot;     &quot;1 to 84 days HoL. (not Confirmed, released).1 fined  50 or C months without H.L.1 fined  15 &quot;  6 days       Tt      &quot;1 fined 50/- or  2 months without H.L.1 forfeit arms etc. found.(c)c Illegal Drilling.1 to 1 year with H*L.1 to 6 months with  H.L.(d). Being  in possession of seditious  literature,or  I.R.A.  Uniform.7 to 3 years P.S.1 to 2 years with H.L. (not confirmed)1  to 1 year with H.L.  (not confirmed)1  to 21 months without H.L.1  to 12 months    &quot;      &quot;1  t o 9     TT       &quot;      &quot;3.  to 9     &quot;    with H.L.1 to 6     &quot;       &quot;    &quot;1  to 6     &quot;    without H.L.
(&amp;)o oontinuedo1 to 3 months without H*L* (GoOeCo-in-C* reraittod sentence                                                 -1/2/21.)1 to 112 days with ILL.1 to  56  &quot;     &quot;    &quot;1 to   1 month without H*L*1 to  14 days     &quot;     &quot;(e). Ijisce llano qus of fence Sr1 to 5 years P*S*2 to 1 year with Kc.L02 fined  0 or 2 months without ILL.1   &quot;    2  &quot; 1 month     &quot;     &quot;1   &quot;   10/- or 14 days   &quot;     &quot;(f)0 ff^od by Military Court in iiartial Law Area.-?e2.S-S1LS-?-cn of armg &amp; ammunition.1 to death.  Executed 1/2/21*(Sgd)    C ^ILJLMACRJJ JJY.0 o mman ding-in-Oh i e f,  IRELANDG.,H :v-Jreland o0/9/ 0*1

</content>
</cab>
