<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/119/0 images: 824-831</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
D(AMl5SE0KSP.To be destroyed when replacedby a subsequent number.95 91 STLf TgjjT ADMIRALTY-i ii St.)Zku 6o_Ig February, 1031.Issued by the Naval Intellicence Division, Naval Staff,Admiralty, for the information of Recipients only.PISTRIB^IHN.Sont by All British Routo to :-CopiesOopiesBoard of Admiralty..........Seo. (NaviSec ^SoArS.,A.S.F.) .... 3Duty Oaptain.....................    1The Cabinet (0.I.D,).............   40Sec., Navy Boards fc-olbourne ......Director Naval Service, Ottawa ...P.A.N.A*0*.........Head of Naval Section, ParisNaval Repre s ent atlve,League of Nations ..... 5 * * *V1111.........Ooitimanders^iri-ChiGfThe Nore .........Portsmouth t o (. t .PlymouthSC^tlSyHd     *.fcc*44J&apos;W. ApproachesAtlantic ..........N.A. k V/.I, .MediterraneanChina *..**..East Indies .Africa * * e l ..Si Americat tt ku mi........WlM.....V.A.Cj 1st Battle SquadronY.A.CUj 2nd Battle Squadron10  Admiralty Naval StaffI.D.................OcD................P*&apos;D.................Tr.D................Intelligence 0f.fi oersS.I.O. 3 -MediterraneanChina ........East Indies ..S. America ...N. America ...D. L.0.1 s *-PortsmouthChatham .............. -Dsvonport.............Roaytti ......Hull.................Liverpool i............Queenstovm............Gibraltar .............Malta .................Colombo...............Singapore.............Shanghai ..Wellington11111211iillV; A. 0., Re serve L^u ^ ^ r.........R.A*, Battle Orurlf?^ Sara:!:&apos;;&apos;on ....H-.A., 1st Battle Squadron .*......H.A. 9 2nd Battle Sciudror.R*A. , 1st Li^it Cruiser Sou&amp;rtreiv.R.A., 2nd Li $it Cruiser f^^i-idron..R.A., 3rd Li gat Cruiser $ruadron..R.A., Gth Li $it Cruiser Scriadron..R.A., Mediterranean ....R*A., Yanj^so ........ 0.. 0..R* A. (D) .........a *  * * *,Op^modore., Austra?ian JLqq^Ofimodore, New Zealand * * * .0.0., H.M.S. 11 Malaya&quot; . -........ *.TOTAL (Distributed byCopying Branch)1   i   i   *   6* * - . c .11111111I111111188Cape TownBermuda ..AscensionLiaison I.Or, Melbourn...L-, 0,, Koi:i  KongK..L. 0., Cairo.............N.V. 0., Ifete VideoN.V.C., Oallao18321111111111111111111111111.11TOTAL   (I. D,Distribution)
m &quot; -    562To bo rl3stro73d when replacedby a subsequent number.sgcgT adiiiraltyVfSSKLY INTHTLICRNC::   gggiAgT.(7.1.S.)No. 6*   For tho weak enUng lgtli February 1921.PART   I.   NAVAL HTDLLIG^IOE.GRTAT BRITAIN.Principal Move lQnta of H.   Ships.6th February.   II Subrrarine Flotilla arrived Gibraltar.9th February.   1st Battle Squadron and 3rd Destroyer flotillasailed from Arosa Bay and arrived Vigo.2nd Battle Squadron and 4th Destroyer Flotillaarrived Arosa Bay from Gibraltar.H.:.&apos;.:.S. &quot;Queen Elizabeth11 arrived Gibraltarfrom Arosa 3ay.10th February. Battle Cruiser Squadron, 1-1.1.1. S. 3 &quot;Toolston&quot;&apos;      and &quot;l?yriariu arrived Gibraltar from Vigo.11th February. H..&apos;...S* &quot;Dauntless11 sailed from Devonport tojoin 1st Lii^kit Cruiser Squadron.1-1.1/1.S. &quot;Assistance&quot; arrived Gibraltar fromArosa Bay.1st Li?ht Cruiser Squadron arrived PontaDolgada from Payal.P R 0 G R A M1st li $it Cruiser    Ponta Delgada, Azores, 11th-15 thSquadron.        February. Funohal 17thM28th February.H,M.Ss. &quot;Delhi&quot;, &quot;Danae&quot;, and &quot;Dragon&quot;)- Teneriffe, 1st - 6 th Liar oh, Las Palmas, 1 Gibral-6th - 10th Llarch. )   tarH.M.SS. &quot;Dauntless&quot; and &quot;Dunodin&quot; - )12th -Las Palmas, 1st - 5th L&amp;rch, Oasa Blanca, )17th6 th - 11th Maroh. )March.h0m.S. &quot;Caroline&quot;*   Due Penang 7th March with theCommandor-inr-Chief, Fast Indies.H.M.3. &quot;Undaunted&quot;.   To convey relief orsws for,&quot;Sikh&quot;, &quot;Shark&quot;, &quot;Cornflower&quot; and &quot;Senator&quot; to Malta.   LeavesSheerness 16th February, Gibraltar 22nd,February, Ualta 27thFebruary - 2nd Liar eh,   Gibraltar 6th - 7th iforon, Devonport12th-13th Ivlarch, Sheerness 14th - arch.   Rejoins Nora Reserve.E.&apos;1jI.S. &quot;Carnarvon&quot;.   Aranoi Bay 10th -21st February.Malta 23rd February - 7th Liaroh.   Algiers 10th - 19th March.Gibraltar 2lT?t-28th : aroh. Vicro 30th ;:arch-8th April. Arrivesin England 11th April.   To pay off on arrival.H.M.S. &quot;Temeraire&quot;.   Gibraltar 3nd-16th February,Alicante 17th-21st February. Cannes 22nd Feb.-1st March. Ville-franche lst-7th March. Leghorn 7th-llth &quot;larch. Castellamare 12 th-18th i/iaroh. Syracuse 18th-22nd March, i/lalta .23rd March-6th Aoril.Alters 8th-15th April. Gibraltar 17th^21st April. Portsmouth25th April.   To pay off on arrival.
m      0      MMovements of H.      Ships in tho Baltic.- .         . .       . ,,    .         .   n   . . .     -   -   i i ..........--        ---- - -    i ,.........H.;.i. Ships &quot;Castor11 and &quot;Yfryneck&quot; vd.ll leave Copenhagenfor Danzisr on the 13th February and will also visit Llbau ifoircmstanoos permit.H.&amp;S* &quot;Cordelia11 will proceed to Copenhagen viathe Kiel Canal and call at Heligoland en route, sailing aspreviously arranged on or about tho &apos; 5th .&quot;iarch,TROOPSHIP   ITOvXTCTS.The &quot;Bremen11 is due in United Kingdom about the20th February with details from Hons: Kong.   After dischargeshe will bo release! from Transport Service.   The &quot;Teutonic&quot;sailed on the 8th February with I&amp;litary details for theMediterranean, and the aField i\ arshallB left on tho 11thwith troops for Bombay.RUSSIA.Moscow Y//t reports that Kopel has been appointed tocommand the Baltic Fleet in succession to Raskolnikoffo(Kopel is not known, but a Lieutenant Kopev was formerly inthe Baltic Imperial Fleet).A report has been received which states that thepresent efficiency of the Soviet Baltic Fleet is low andthat effective ships generally are not ready for immediateservice:.   Submarine batteries, (numbers not known, probablythose from submarines under repair), have been taken foruse with the electric train now being experimented withbetween Petrograd and luOscow.Press reports unrest amongst naval personnel atKronstadt and that military had been sent from Moscow torestore order.,    Also that the revival of religious feelingis causing the Soviet authorities anxiety^   On St.Andrew aday, (patron Saint of the Russian Navy)5 bluejackets fromKronstadt proceeded to Petrograd and requested the Metropolistan Benjamin to go to Kronstadt to conduct special services.This was done an-&apos; services held in the Cathedral and onboard of all the larger ships., &quot;the attitude of the sailors andpopulation being most reverent.    The Metropolitan was escortedback to Petrograd with much ceremony and loaded with presentsof foodstuffs from the sailors.It is reported that the Executive of the IIIInternational has at its disposal 13 sailing ships whichtravel between Petrograd, Riga and Stettin and then back&apos; toPetrograd.   The ships are used for carrying literature,foreign ooirniunists and Bolshevik s.s. agents.   Furthersupplies of Soviet gold ar - reported to have been shippedon&quot; January 2Ota and 27th in the Ssthonian S^So &quot;Kalovipoog&quot;and Swedish 3*3* a!Hgil&quot; from Reval to Stockholm.iOn the 12th February information was received fromNaval Control, Berlin, that the &quot;3ubotnikHs sailed fromStettin on the 10th instant, for Swineimndo.   It was notpossible to examine cargo owing to obstruction by RussianShipping Agents and by the Police.   As cargo is very highlysuspicious, German Government has been asked to dotaiJa thevessel at Swinemv-nde until the matter has been cleared up.
5*MNETHERLANDS.The Dutch minelayer &quot;l^/dra&quot; was SW&amp; on the 10thFebruary in collision witft T.B* No. 3, during ninnt torpedopractices without linhts.ITALYIt has been decided that an Italian Vice AcLiiralshall be President of the Naval Inter-Allied Commission ofControl for Kvrigary, subjsot to the approval of the Oon-ferencs of Ambassadors.Tie 3.Sb &quot;Dnieper&quot;, latsly belongng to GeneralWrenRel1 g forces., entered Rotterdam in December 1920.   TheItalj.cn -! II Uaneo di Roma&quot; has filed a claim for  37,553 inrespect of k&apos;sv oargo.It is also stated that the Soviet Government haveentorod^a claim for this ship, on the grounds that all\7r&amp;ngol&apos;s property belongs to the Russian Republic.BLACK    SEA., It is understood that the French are sellingWr&amp;ngbl s ships, now at Bizerta, and are probably applyingtrie proceeds to the relief of the refugees.ARABIA.The French Admiral Thomine visited Joddah   10thFebruary.FRANCS.The Atlantic Division consisting of the cruisers&quot;Marseillaise1 flying the flag of Rear-Admiral Pugliesi Conti)&quot;Oueydon&apos;1 and the sloop &quot;Couc;/8 whilst on passage from. Brestto Cherbourg carried out exercises in conjunction with thesutcarine flol,: 7. la and air craft of Cherbourg.   The submarineflotilla&apos;s attaol: wa3 successful but the air attach was afailure owing to the aeroplane developing engine trouble andhaving to return to the aerodrome before the attack wascarried out.The cruiser &quot;Cassard&quot; left Rochefort on 3rd Februaryto relieve the ^Jurien de la Graviere&quot; as flagship of theSyrian Division.V/hllst exercising off Toulon the submarine HNsroideBmet with a serious accident.   On diving, a vontilator wasleft open, and the engine room was flooded; tho en-Tines beingbadly damaged.
PERSIA.It is re-norted that bolshevik Diplomatio Missionto Persia, consisting of 50 persons, has left Moscow.SSTHQNIA.Reports received state t^at military stores arecontinually passing through Ssthonia from Germany toRussia.    This proceeding is rendered simn?e hy thecorruption of Ssthoniari customs.    The waggons are sealedat Reval and cross   the frontier at Narva without beingohooked.LATVIA.Hosoow W/T stntes t,^at t^e American Government hasasked Latvia to consent to allow 100,000 Russians,whomAmerica intends to deport in the near future. to &quot;passthrough her territory to Soviet Russia.RUSSIA.According to press from Paris, Moscow W/T reportspeace between Poland and Soviet Russia was signed onFebruary 9th,Conversations continue in Paris as to the fate ofWrangel1s refugees.     At present the  French are apparentlycontinuing to feed them., without having rescinded theirdeoision to   hand them over to a Russian Committee on 1stFebruary.The arrangement into which we entered with theJugo-Slav Government regarding Deni-kin&apos;s refugees wasworking satisfactorily until the French dumped 5,000 ofWrangeHs refugees at Cattaro, leaving the Jugo-SlavGovernment to bear the expense 0^ them.    This has made thelatter Government very restive about the whole question ofrefugees, but the foreign Office does not anticipateserious difficulties so far as Great Britain is concerned.H.1&apos;. Consul at Bizerta reports that a considerablenumber of Russians brought to Bizerta from the Crimea havejoined the French Ronelfin Legion.georgia.   Georgia has replied to the Rolshevik note, thechief points in the reply are1.   Consent to release of all non-Georgian agitators providedthat they 1 save Georgia immediately, but refusal toacknowledge the legal existence of the communist party whichseeks to destroy t^e independence of Georgia.PART   IT.General  .Intelllgonoe.
5663.   Refusal to discuss the demand for tbe dismissal oftbe Georgian commission -it Batoum and denial of the rightof the looal sailor1 s union there  to hoist the Red flag,7i\   Refusal to pay compensation for s.s. &quot;Principe&quot; whiohescaped from Poti.4.   Consent to allow supply trains to run from Azerbaijanto Armenia to prevent Armenia from starving, but refusalto allow oil trains so long as the Georgian oil trains arenot returned.5.   Consent to treat the Bolshevik mission on tbe camefooting as other missions, provided tbe former behave asdo the latter and observe Internationa] usages.6.   With reference to the   demand that the bolshevikRepresentative shall partake in the negotiations for tbesettlement of the Georgia-Armenian frontier on an equalfooting with the Georgian and Armenian representatives,Georgia enquires whether t/osoor regards Armenian as partof the Russian republic or as an independent State.     Ifthe former, Georgia accepts the suggestion;   if tbe latter,the question does not   arise.7BKMARK.Danish Press makes an official announcement thatHi?&apos;. King Christian and Queen Alexandrina will visit theFaroe Islands, Iceland and Greenland at the end of June.The Royal visit, to Iceland was arranged last summer buthad to be postponed.TTBTgy.The   British G.O.C. in. 0. Constantinople, has beeninformed that it is impossible for us to join tbe Greeks in.anv offensive action, in view of our invitation to tbe.Turkish Nationalist leaders to take part in the LondonConference.It is reported that a Greek offensive, tbe allegedobject of which is to forestall a Turkish attack, isimminent., It is obvious that military operations undertakenby either side must be intended to influence proceedings atthe forthcoming London Conference.The Turkish Central Government propose to send aDelegation to the London Conference on 0,1st &quot;February,whether the Angora Government agree to send representativesor not.    Tbe latter were reported as leaving Angora on7th February and to be proceeding to  England via Adaliaand Brindisi.It is thougbt possible that an understandingbetween tbe two delegations might be arrived at even inLondon.
567PCOTJGAL.The Government resigned on 12th February,principally owing to dissensions amongst its members.Senhor ^into will probably be asked to reconstructhis Cabinet.It is reported that Bolshevik Commissars, whohave hitherto displayed moderation, are gradually beingdisplaced by Russians or Terrorist Armenians.ARABIA..Hodeidah has been occupied by Idrisi, and hisrepresent at ji;e.  laid JJust&amp;fa, has taken over oharge ofinternal adidnist ration from  local oommittees, to whomFazluddin had handed it.    So far, no disturbances havebeen reported.ABYSS TNT AThe Abyssinian Government intends sending apunitive expedition against Fohammed Wad Mahraud shortly,and has asked for the assistance of the Soudan Governmentto prevent his esoape into Soudan Government territory.The necessary steps for co-operation in this matter havebeen arranged.BELGIUM.Belgian Congo.Passengers arriving from the Congo by the BelgianMail state that the rebellion which arose at Yanku hasspread &quot;with great rapidity to praotically all the provincesof Kole and Loto and to certain tribes in the province ofLod^a.The rebels wish to avoid the payment of taxes.All commerce is suspended in the affected regions.SPAIN.Spanish Morocco.According to the press the Spanish positions atSheshouan were attacked on 4th February by rebels.    Theattack was repulsed;   the Spanish oasualties including fivekilled.
568Switzerland,The Swiss Government has refused to allow thepassage of the League&apos;of Nations troops through SwissTerritory to supervise the Plebiscite in Lithuania.This decision has aroused great controversy.     In GermanSwitzerland the general opinion is that the Government :lsright in refusing, while in French Switzerland the opinionis that the Government is wrong, as the troops   are bo:&apos;.;igsent to maintain peace and for policing purposes, and noiifor purposes of war.SYRIA.In the Aleppo region Hachem. Bey continues hisguerilla operations.    He is now reported as being atSifre (15 miles S.E. of Aleppo).     It. is unofficiallyreported that ITu-jim Bey, in spite of being subsidised bythe French to guarantee the security of that part of theprovince of Aleppo, has gone ove1&quot; to Hachem!s side.    Thesituation in the area W. and q.W. of Aleppo is very muchquieter.    The making of trouble arrears&quot; to be strictIjlimited to the people in direct touch with the rebels inthe Xosseir mountains or the Kemalists.French troops oaytured Aintab oh 9th February,after a siege lasting nearly nine months1.

</content>
</cab>
