<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/113/0 images: 297-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret;Printed for the Cabinet.   May J 963 I ^ t&apos;.fW.iC&apos;Y Jot) -)%    &apos;bvt\0?-j\--x&apos;       ilitc. cJApsyjyi&amp;Siltt 7nXl&quot;r&apos;  ;;tt?. ih^iU     ^C. (63) 78 Copy No: 1 &apos;5 2fc0^.-;Wj^,l?&apos;f^!fi^ -0 !W 0*,? .:o!;&quot;&apos;:&quot;M.: L&apos;!:;::W;f&apos;/;&apos;:-&apos;&apos;flui.j;i?y.u3&apos;5     J :ii&apos;5)VhV.:;So !0 2f&apos;lt3tCJ&apos;j &apos;?j -Jil! rhiW rtWfttj vM;% ^n-.vmr-Ja^n;L,o;;; CABINETFEDERATION OF RHODESIA AND NYASALAND&apos;: ^UNITED KINGDOM LEGISLATION: , Memorandum by the First Secretary of StateIt is now necessary to introduce at an early date a Bill furnishing her majesty&apos;s, Government -with the requisite enabling powers for Her Majesty toprovide by Order in Council for changes in the Constitutional arrangements in central Africa, as at present laid down, under the Rhodesia; and NyasalandFederation. Act, ,1953, by the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland. (Constitution)Order,in Council, 1953, ,, ; - .2. It has been apparent since Her Majesty&apos;s Governments decision ofpolicy regarding Nyasaland last December that legislation enabling provision tobe made for the secession of Nyasaland from the Federation would have to. been acted before the end of the Summer Recess, if that process was to be completedor brought near to completion (as is politically necessary) before the end of 1963.3. No Order in Council providing for Nyasaland&apos;s secession could however be made without providing also for consequential alterations in the relationship between Northern and Southern Rhodesia (which would be of a substantial kindeven on the assumption that something like the present Federal Constitution wereto continue). The Bill would therefore have to cover this contingency also. Itwas clear, however; that the enactment at this stage of a Bill providing merely for consequential amendment of the existing Constitution to accommodate thewithdrawal of Nyasaland would not be politically tolerable in Central Africa. Itwas not therefore possible to determine the scope and content of the Bill untilbroad decisions of policy had been reached on the future of the two; remainingterritories.4. Her Majesty&apos;s Governments statement of 29th March, 1963, established the principle of secession for the other two territories and created a new situationin which a major change in the relationship of the Central African territories,involving the dismantling of the present Federal Constitution, is generally seen tobe inevitable. The way is therefore now open for the Bill to provide for the1 secessionof any territory, for the dissolution of the Federation, and for any transitional andconsequential arrangements that may be needed. It should also authorise themaking of constitutional provision (so far as this may prove necessary andacceptable) for any new relationship that may be evolved&quot; between the territories in accordance with Her Majesty&apos;s Governments declared policy of seeking to bringabout an orderly and direct transition to a new relationship.5. I had hoped that, if it had proved possible to mount by mid-May thefurther discussions which I am still seeking, they might have produced at least abroad political understanding with the other Governments on how the problemsof dissolution and future association should best be handled. The enabling bill could then have been framed on that basis. The inception of these talks has,however, been delayed by the stand taken by the Southern Rhodesia and federal governments on the question of Southern Rhodesia&apos;s independence, and sincetime does not allow us to await the outcome of the present negotiations with the
- Governments and the opening of any; conference (which; could not now take place before mid-June at the earliest), there is no alternative but Tor &quot;Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment to proceed at once with the preparation of a Bill covering all thecontingencies with which we may be faced.     ,    ?&apos;,A.*-n-6. There are many uncertainties still to be resolved. We are not yet, forinstance,Jn a position to judge whether  l-j &apos;(i) discussions can be initiated on the basis of considering ;;pw forxns. of relationship pari passu with the problems of dissolving the Federation,of whether we shall have-to concentrate on the minimum requirements ofsecuring an orderly dissolution of the Federation, allowing at least forthe time being the prospect of a continued association to recede.(ii) How far it will be possible to bring back the consideration of the problemsof Nyasaland&apos;s secession into the context of a general dissolution; or what links it will be possible to establish between Nyasaland and the rhodesias. ,(iii) Whether Nyasaland will have to be allowed to withdraw from theFederation before the Federal Constitution can be formally dissolved.(iv) Whether, or at what stage in the transitional arrangements, prior to the dissolution of the Federation the Federal Government should cease to exist and be replaced by some temporary authority.7. . Thus the nature and timing of the actions which Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentmay find.it necessary to take and to provide for by Order in Council under theproposed enabling Act, depends on the progress of events which cannotimmediately be foreseen. But the powers available must be broad enough to giveHer Majesty&apos;s Government full freedom of action, if they are to retain the initiative in the difficult months ahead.8. I therefore seek the agreement of my colleagues to ask parliamentary counsel to prepare, for introduction and passage through Parliament before the recess, a Bill enabling provision to be made by Order in Council for (i) the secession of any.territory from the present Federation;(ii) the dissolution of the Federation;(iii) the making of any transitional and consequential arrangements that maybe required;(iv) the introduction of constitutional provisions (so far as may be necessary and acceptable) for any new form of relationship between the territories.I would, of course, inform the Federal and Territorial Governments of her majesty&apos;s Governments intentions, and it would be desirable to provide them withopportunity for comment on the contents of the Bill before its enactment.R. A. B.Office of the First Secretary of State, S.W.1,, 6th May, 1963.


</content>
</cab>
