<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/113/0 images: 329-334</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COPY NO.52Recent events have made it necessary to review our policy to-wards India.2.     Since Independence in 1947, India has consistently pursued apolicy of non-alignment and sought to build up solidarity among the afro-Asian nations.    But this did not prevent China from attacking herlast autumn;  and when this occurred most of the Afro-Asian cotxntriessat firmly on the fence and hesitated to alienate China by any expression of sympathy for India.    On the other hand, the United Kingdom andthe United States instantly answered India&apos;s call for help and starteddispatching much needed military equipment within a few hours.3.      This positive response from the West, coupled with the negativereactions of her fellow Afro-Asians, made a deep and enduringimpression upon the mind of the Indian people who feel that they havediscovered which are the friends upon whom they can rely..4.     Unfortunately the circumstances which had led to this improve-ment in our relations with India have caused an appreciable deterioration in our relations with Pakistan, which lives in fear, real or imaginary,of Indian aggression, and consequently views with suspicion military aid to India from the West.    That is why we have made strenuous efforts in recent months to encourage India and Pakistan to settle their differences and, in particular, their long-standing dispute over Kashmir.Last December, we persuaded them to start negotiations and, thesehaving now reached complete deadlock, we have urged them to acceptthe good offices of some impartial mediator.    The Indian Governmenthave accepted this proposal in principle, and the Government of Pakistanare considering it.5.     The president  of Pakistan, President Ayub, has throughout been pressing us to make further military aid to India conditional upon asettlement of the Kashmir   dispute, since he is convinced that onlythe threat to deny India weapons will induce her to make worthwhileconcessions to Pakistan.    On his side, the Prime Minister of India,Mr. Nehru, has repeatedly asked to be assured that there is no connection between Western aid and the Kashmir   negotiations.-1-CABINETMILITARY AID FOR india memorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations and Secretary of State for the Colonies
6.     The United States Foreign Secretary, Mr. Dean Rusk, and Ihave stated our position clearly to both President Ayub and Mr. Nehru.We have explained that we wished to strengthen India&apos;s defences both because of our friendship with her and because we do not want to seethe further expansion of Communist power.    We could not thereforeagree with the Pakistan suggestion that military aid to India shouldbe made dependent upon a settlement of the Kashmir   dispute.    Onthe other hand, we could equally not accept the Indian view that thetwo problems are entirely unconnected.    In assessing India&apos;military needs, the United Kingdom and the United States have toconsider whether, on account of this dispute, India is justified indeploying for defence against Pakistan substantial forces which could make an important contribution to her defence against China.    nor can we ignore the anxiety caused in Pakistan by a serious change inthe balance of military power in the sub-continent, and the consequentdanger of stimulating a ruinous arms race between two countries whose limited resources are sorely needed for economic development.Therefore, while military aid to India is not conditional upon asettlement in Kashmir,    the continuance of this dispute is bound to affect the attitude of the United States and the United Kingdom, who do not want to see their relations with Pakistan needlessly embittered,and will make it more difficult for them to justify to their taxpayersthe expenditure involved.7.     V/hile the solution of the Kashmir   problem would be very valuable, and while this is probably the most propitious moment to try and achieve it, there is a much more important issue to beconsidered, namely the future orientation of India in world affairs.8.     Nehru&apos;s policy of non-alignment having been severlyundermined by the Chinese attack, it might now be possible, by ajudicious exploitation of India&apos;s need for military support, to bringher fully over on to the Western side.    This will not be easy.    Butin view of the profound effect it could have, not only on our relationswith India, but on the attitude of neutral countries throughout theworld, no effort should be spared to achieve this result.9.     Although an early renewal of Chinese aggression is not expected, it is generally felt that China will continue to haveexpansionist ambitions, and that India must be in a position todefend herself if attacked again.10.     The Indian Goverment have worked out their military require-ments to meet the Chinese threat (and to maintain their guard againstPakistan).    They have estimated the cost to be of the order of 2,400 million over three years;  and they intend to ask the UnitedStates and ourselves to provide the foreign exchange element ofthis total, amounting to about  600 million.    V/hile suggestingcertain reductions, the United Kingdom and United States militaryadvice is that, if the objective is to enable India single-handed tomeet an all-out invasion by China, the Indian Governmenfs estimateof requirements is not excessive.    On the other hand, the Indianshave been warned that they have no hope of getting military aid fromthe West on anything like this scale.-2-
11.     Thus, faced with the certain prospect of a very large short-fall in their defence budget, the more realistic members of theIndian Government (including the Minister of Defence Production,Mr. Krishnamachari) are beginning to realise that, in an age whereeven the nuclear powers find it necessary to have allies, India cannothope, all on her own, to build up an adequate defence against China;they reluctantly realise that it may not be altogether a coincidencethat none of the countries that are linked by defence pacts to theUnited States and the United Kingdom have in fact been attacked.12.     After an interval, Indian political opinion may have ripenedsufficiently to allow the Government to conclude some form ofmilitary alliance with the West, if the latter should offer it to them.But six months is too short a time to move from complete neutralityto complete commitment.    In any case we and the United States would find it difficult to enter into a formal alliance with India so long as astate of threatened war continues between her and Pakistan.13.     However, the United States and the United Kingdom are con-sidering a possible solution half-way between alliance and neutrality.The idea is based on an earlier proposal of Nehru&apos;s who, at theheight of the Chinese advance last autumn, appealed to Kennedy tosend United States fighter squadrons to protect India&apos;s cities and sorelease the Indian Air Force to tackle the invaders on the frontier.14.     But, although this idea originated with the Indians, there are some signs that they are less keen on it now and would much prefer to be supplied with three supersonic fighter squadrons of their own.The main reason for this change is that they realise that a defencearrangement of this kind would constitute an important military link with the West and would be generally regarded as a thinly veiledabandonment of India&apos;s traditional policy of non-alignment.    On theother hand, from our point of view, it is precisely this consideration which is the principal attraction of the scheme.    It also has theadvantage of being mUch less objectionable to Pakistan than thesupply of aircraft to the Indian Air Force.15.     It seems that the president  of the United States, president kennedy and Mr. Rusk favour this plan;  and they are likely to propose that the United Kingdom and the United States should under-take to despatch three fighter squadrons (two American and one british) to help defend Indian cities in the event of war.    In peace-time, joint air exercises with the Indian Air Force would be carriedout.    We would of course have to ensure that our intervention couldbe invoked only in the event of unprovoked aggression by China on a scale which made outside help necessary, and that we would be the judges of that necessity.    We might also feel it necessary to insist that the Indians should first settle their disputed frontier with China;but the Indian Government might regard this as an unacceptablehumiliation.16.     In return, we could no doubt obtain unrestricted overflyingand staging rights to the Far East, in peace and war, which incertain circumstances might be of considerable value.-3-
17.     At first I had some doubts about the wisdom of accepting a commitment of this nature;  and I said so at the Nassau conference.I would much prefer the conclusion of a defence pact with India on thenormal lines.    But it is unlikely that the Indians would feel able tomake such a radical change of policy in one step.    It is also clearthat the United States Administration are reluctant to assume any new military commitment of a kind which would require Senateapproval.    Therefore, in the light of my recent talks in Delhi with indian Ministers and with Mr. Rusk, I have come round to the viewthat the offer of an Anglo American &quot;air umbrella&quot; would, from the standpoint of Western interest, be the safest and most advantageouscourse.18.     In the event of a major invasion by China, we and the UnitedStates could not stand by and see India, or large parts of it, con-quered by the Communist forces.    Therefore, provided we do notencourage the Indians to provoke the Chinese (for example by trying to retake the mountain area recently lost in Ladakh), and provided it is left with us to decide whether our intervention is necessary, theproposal to provide air cover for Indian cities in the event of needwould not really involve us in any serious commitment, beyond what we would in any case feel obliged to do.    On the other hand, this plan offers four very important advantages:-(a) This practical demonstration of Western interest inthe preservation of India&apos;s independence would inevitably have a certain deterrent effect upon China.(b) A decision by India to rely upon Anglo american military forces for her defence would represent a major and irrevocable step on the road fromneutrality to We stern alignment.(c) India&apos;s increased military dependence upon theWest and the consequential increase of Westerninfluence would be reassuring to Pakistan.(d) The partial abandonment by India of the policy ofnon-alignment, of which she has been the foremostchampion, could not fail to provide food for thought to all the other neutral nations.19.     Whether or not it is decided to provide the &quot;air umbrella1&apos;,it would on financial grounds be altogether out of the question for theVIest to give India three supersonic fighter squadrons which, withradar and ancillary equipment, would cost about  85 million.20.     With regard to India&apos;s other requirements, the United Statesfeel that we shall have to provide some further military aid, thoughon an infinitely more modest scale than anything they are hoping forin Delhi.    The United States and the United Kingdom (with the help of small contributions from Australia and Canada) have already sentor promised to send military equipment of about  20 million each.It is understood that the United States Department of Defense willsuggest that we and they should offer to finance further arms forIndia to the value of another  10 million to  20 million each..4-
21.     The amount we can afford to pay is a matter for considerationamong ourselves and with the Americans.    In view of the size&apos; oftheir requirements, anything less than the total proposed by theUnited States would be regarded by the Indians as derisory.   However,it is questionable whether we should continue to be asked to share the burden equally with the United States.    I also feel that anyfurther military aid should have certain strings attached.    Forexample, we might insist that, in so far as our aid releases foreign exchange for the purchase abroad of additional military equipment,that should be bought from the United Kingdom and the United States.22.     The Indian Minister of Defence Production is going to washington in a few days&apos; time to discuss this matter, and is coming to London on his way home.    There is, therefore, very little timeto concert a common line with the United States before they commit themselves in their talks with the Indians.D.S.Commonwealth Relations Office, S. W. 1.13th May, 1963.-5-


</content>
</cab>
