<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/113/0 images: 355-358</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
\ CABINETEXPORT OF MILITARY EQUIPMENT TO SOUTH AFRICAwMemorandum by the Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster GeneralThe Strategic Exports Committee has before it three applications for export licences for arms to South Africa. Although the value of the items, details ofwhich are given below, is small, the nature of the arms and their possible use inthe case of internal disturbance makes it desirable that we should seek the guidanceof the Cabinet. It would also be helpful if in the light of the present situation theCabinet would indicate whether any changes are desirable in the policy governing the supply of arms to South Africa.2. At present we are authorising the export to South Africa of military equipment of a kind not associated with the suppression of civil disturbances. all exports are being strictly scrutinised from this point of view and three border-linecases have been submitted to the Ministerial Committee on Strategic Exports for decision. These are as follows:(i) 10,000 rounds of 7-62-mm. &quot; standard &quot; ammunition for F.N. rifles (value 850). This is specially manufactured ammunition used for testingpurposes and would enable the South Africans to test the quality of theirown production line. The quantity is small, and while the ammunitioncould be used for shooting rioters, it would be much cheaper for theSouth Africans to buy the ordinary ammunition from Belgium for thispurpose. The Committee was generally of the view that licences shouldbe issued for this ammunition.(ii) 2,400 rounds of 77-mm. high explosive ammunition for use with Comettanks (value  40,000 delivery not to take place for about two years).This ammunition might be used in civil disturbances, e.g., for reducingbuildings, but it is essentially a normal defence requirement of theSouth African army. Moreover, South Africa has been supplied with20-pounder high explosive ammunition for use in Centurion tanks and manufacturing licences have been negotiated for both 77-mm. and20-pounder ammunition. Again the general view of the Committeewas that the export should be authorised.(iii) 3,500 -38 Smith and Wesson revolvers.   This request presents moredifficulty. Not only are these weapons probably destined for the SouthAfrican police, but they are of lease-lend origin and could not be exported without the consent of the United States Authorities. TheSouth African Embassy were approached informally about thepossibility of withdrawing this order but when their Ambassador called on the Foreign Secretary on 17th May he said that his government felt that by withdrawing it they would be admitting by implication that the arms were required for oppression. He was, however, askedto consider again our request that the order should be withdrawn.It seems likely that the request may be pressed, and it may be that theSouth Africans regard this as a test case. The Strategic ExportsCommittee were, on the information before them, divided in view onthe issue of a licence.Printed for the Cabinet. May 1963C. (63) 87 Copy No.    5 221st May, 1963
3. In accordance with present policies licences should be issued in cases (i)and (ii) above. I ask the Cabinet to confirm that they should issue. On present policies a licence would be likely to be refused if the request in (iii) is maintained.The Cabinet will, however, wish to weigh against the inevitable row which theissue of a licence will produce the effect on our relations with South Africa whicha refusal, particularly in present circumstances, would be likely to provoke.J. A. B.-C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,20th May, 1963.

Printed for the Cabinet.   MayC. (63) 88Copy No.52SECRET	CABINET	DER ACT, 19360,(65) 88- rni Bin inrfli i/im in   iii i  iiThe Bill referred to willhe circulated later.Cabinet Office, S.W.I.21st May, 1963or the Home department i.minute 3) the Cabinet consideredjancaster and myself (C. (63) 70c Order Act, 1936. As a result,Attorney-General the possibilitythe penalties for offences underend that section to include theing to racial hatred. I attach aSe purposes.chancellor, the Chancellor of thetland, the Attorney-General andrhnet desires that legislation beble.sort might be secured by meansy Mr. Iremonger.  We are allItle of Mr. Iremonger&apos;s Bill is so the way for other far-rangingihave seen Mr. Iremonger and!of his dropping the present Billraft. He would support this newnt Bill. I have also seen at hisim several other government that, while penalties under theimendment of Section 5 as anconcept of race did not appearSECRETSession would have no prospectber. We are committed to ane is general agreement.  It may___^      __________________.....if ore, and having regard to the differences of opinion on our own side of the House, I am disposed to stand by myoriginal suggestion that we should go ahead with a Bill doing no more than increasepenalties. This would have to be a Government measure.(u As the Cabinet know, we are committed to making a statement beforeWhitsun (Hansard, 2nd May, column 1318). I suggest that this should follow theline of the draft statement appended to my previous paper.H. B.Home Office, S.W. 1,21st May, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
