<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/113/0 images: 470-474</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot; DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(63) 9427th May, 1963COPY NO. JtiLCABINETMILITARY AID TO INDIANote by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations and Secretary of State for the colonies circulate, at Annex, as background to the Cabinet&apos;s discussionof this subject tomorrow, the attached account received from theUnited States Government of their discussions with Mr. Krishnamachari,Indian Minister of Defence Co-ordination.D.S.Commonwealth Relations Office, S. W. 1.27th May, 1963
1&apos;     Air Defense.    United States side indicated that it was prepared to supply India with mobile radar, and associated communica-tions and support equipment, and it had under urgent considerationpossibility of sending air defense aircraft squadrons to India on training exercises along lines of joint report of Commonwealth/UnitedStates Air Defense Mission.    Since we believed it important thatthis action should be carried out in conjunction with the UnitedKingdom and Commonwealth countries, we planned to consult urgentlywith them before making formal approach to Government of India.United States side indicated that in any event it would offer to train Indian personnel in immediate future in operation of appropriateradar types.    United States side further indicated that it was exploringbest manner of meeting minimum long-term Indian radar needs on basis of delivery in approximately 12-18 months, and that itexpected to carry out such delivery in this time frame on approximatescale of six installations, three in western sector and three in easternsector.Indian side indicated that proposed training exercises wouldbe acceptable to Government of India provided they were accompaniedby proposed measures leading to an increased Indian radar capabilityand provided further that training exercises were joint in characterwith Indian personnel participating.Indian side expressed continued desire for early delivery ofsupersonic all-weather interceptor aircraft.    United States sideindicated that it considered such a requirement to have lower prioritythan many other measures for strengthening of IndiaTs defenses and,in particular, additional measures to improve combat effectiveness ofexisting aircraft types.2&apos;     Air Ground Support and Bombing Operations.    United Statesside noted that United Kingdom was taking steps to improve mainten-ance and supply situation of existing combat aircraft.    United Statesindicated its willingness to dispatch small planning team to India toassist in framing proper requirements for combat air ordnance, andalso indicated that United States was receptive to receiving IndianAir Force personnel in United States training schools for low levelnavigation and bombing training.    United States side expressed desireto confer promptly with United Kingdom as to whether either of theseelements of assistance could better be performed by United Kingdom.2&apos;     Air Transport.    This problem was canvassed intensively, withparticular regard to need to improve Indian air-lift capability toLadakh area over next eighteen months.    Following measures were discussed:-(a)    Various projects for jet-engine augmentation of C-119s.    Itwas agreed that this problem should be pursued urgently.    In light ofunavailability of additional J-34-WE36 engines, such as were nowinstalled on twenty-three C-119s, it was provisional view of UnitedStates side that Indian plan to employ Orpheus 701 engines deserved
priority attention in lieu of other possibilities.     United States sideoffered to make available appropriate technicians from FairchildCompany to assist Indian Air Force in carrying out this modificationrapidly and effectively.(b) Maintenance of C-119s.    United States side stressed importanceof improving maintenance and serviceability rate of C-119 fleet, whichwas being augmented by additional aircraft being delivered under Nassauprogram, United States side offered to receive Indian personnel for training in United States maintenance and supply methods in UnitedStates, and.to send a team of United States Air Force specialists toassist Indian Air Force on ground.(c) Utilisation of AN-12s. It was agreed that Indian Air Force would seek to maximise utilisation of existing AN-12 aircraft. India;::, Bide notedcertain limitations of this aircraft.    It was agreed that completionof second runway at Leh, to accommodate AN-12s, was a continuingpriority project.(d) Srinagar-Leh road.    It was agreed that measures to improveSrinagar-Leh road (covered under paragraph 4 below) were in important part of problem and equally deserved continuing high priority.After reviewing possible effect of these measures, United States sidefelt that there was no firm basis for a conclusion at present whetherexisting C-130 operation should be continued beyond presently proposedexpiration date of August, or whether C-130 operations would berequired during next winter.    United States side also noted thatoutright transfer of C-130 aircraft, to meet Indian request for one squadron, would present significant funding and availability problems.However, United States side undertook to continue to study this problemso that it could decide by early July whether to retain C-130s in Indiaafter August and by early Fall whether C-130s would be required during the coming winter.    United States side undertook to fulfillIndia&apos;s requirement for transport to Ladakh if, after India hadenergetically pursued the measures noted above, a substantial needremained.4.     Roads.     It was agreed that this problem deserved high priorityattention, and United States side indicated that it was prepared to carryforward whatever seemed reasonably needed by way of constructionequipment and spare parts to assist.    Indian side put forward certainplans for border road construction and these plans were noted with interest on United States side.    United States side indicated that itwould be guided by recommendations of team now in India, and thatit was prepared to supplement this team or to send additional teams ofthese would be useful in surveying situation in other areas.5&apos;     Communications.    It was agreed that this requirement tooshould be given high priority attention, and United States sideindicated that United States military supply mission, India, was preparing requirements that would then be urgently considered for support.&apos;0,      Training and advisory assistance.     Indian side indicated its willingness to receive United States training and advisory groups in selected fields as might be agreed on a case by case basis.    Apartfrom examples already indicated above, United States generally-2-
offered to send teams to advise in connection with logistics andmaintenance problems of both Indian Army and Indian Air Force, andfurther undertook to explore assistance in area of defense productionplanning on lines of paragraph eight.    United States side indicated that Indian desires for proposed training assistance should becommunicated through USMSMI in New Delhi.7&apos;      Vehicles.    United States side expressed interest in status of Indian production plans for basic &quot;3-ton&quot; and &quot;1-ton&quot; vehicles.Indian side indicated that production of &quot;3-ton&quot; vehicles was atsubstantial levels already and probably would be increased to satisfactory levels over next 18 months.    Picture in respect to&quot;1-ton&quot; vehicle production was more uncertain.    United Statesside expressed view that this was an area in which maximum Indianproduction was desirable and feasible, and should have economic benefits while meeting military requirements.    United States sideexpressed willingness to look into assistance possibilities in this area as Indian plans were further developed.8.       Defense produce t.ion.   United States side indicated it was urgently studying the question of defense production assistance infield of weapons and ammunition, with particular regard to questionof furnishing production equipment from St. Louis Ordnance Plant(small arms ammunition).    It was hoped that early decisions couldbe reached as to priority areas for such assistance.    United Statesside further undertook to provide, through a private consulting firmif desired, continuing planning advice to Government of India withreference to its defense production reqtxirements.    Such advisersv/ould work in close co-operation with United States military supplymission, India, but would submit their advice directly to indian government.United States side put forward possible conceptual basis forcomputing ammunition requirements, using a 16-division force goalfwith appropriate brigade and corps troops, according to a graduatedscale providing for: (A) 90-day supply, at agreed combat rates,for six mountain divisions and the accompanying two corps (i. e. ,those units likely to have extended supply lines and to be engagedin intensive combat);  (B) 60-day combat supply for an additionalsix standard divisions and two corps (i. e. , those units likely to beemployed at an early stage of fighting); (C) 30-day supply forremaining divisions and brigades and for training purposes.Comment on planning basis:  We accept a 16 division Indianforce level as a reasonable figure for planning purposes.   We have left unspecified extent and pace of our support to this force level as well as whether we would support all 16 divisions.    We continueto have in mind that our program should proceed by stages either by picking up additional divisions for over-all NAP support or bysingling out key areas which should be supported,    11In discussing ammunition production within this planning basis with TTK, we made clear that it involved a calculated risk withunderlying assumption that in event of hostilities sustained over periodof 2-3 months, world in general and United States in particular would be bound to take an active part in supplying additional ammunition andprobably going considerably further.    We did not ask him categoricallyto accept proposed planning basis, and noted that we recognised it hadmajor political implications since it required that India forego, at least for short-term, goal of self-sufficiency in defense production.-3-


</content>
</cab>
