<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/203/7 images: 59-60</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DQCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government copy no cp(78) 8218 July 1978CABINETA WINTER FUEL SCHEME FOR 1978-79Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Industry8 00 U1. This paper reports discussion in the Ministerial Committee onEconomic and Industrial Policy (El) about a further winter fuel scheme.2. A special scheme to help people in low income groups to meet theirelectricity bills has operated in the winters of 1976-77 and 1977-78.    It has provided help for the 3.2 million recipients of Supplementary Benefit (SB)and Family Income Supplement (FIS).    The 1976-77 scheme provided a discount of 25 per cent on one winter quarter&apos;s electricity board bill. The1977-78 scheme provided a flat rate payment of  5 in addition to a 25 per centdiscount on electririty bills of over  20.    This modification was producedto provide some help to tenants who do not receive electricity board billsbecause they pay their landlords for their electricity, and who are thereforeexcluded from the 1976-77 scheme.    Because of increases in electricityGriffs expected by next winter, the cost might rise to about  30 million, of^hich 70 per cent would fall in 1978-79 and the remainder in 1979-80.3- There is great pressure to continue the help which has been given tolow income consumers, many of whom still have the greatest difficulty incoping with high fuel bills.    However, the existing scheme has been criticised, because it involves payments to non-householders (such as young^employed school leavers who receive  5 payment).    There is no practicable*ay of excluding them, however.    Any selective scheme has to operate by *ing existing categories, such as the SB and FIS recipients.    Inevitably it isro*gh and ready, and causes complaints from those who are excluded.4- In the longer term, something more sophisticated is needed. WorkQn this is continuing, as part of a study of energy prices agreed by Ministers8ome months ago.    This study will take full account of the criticisms whichWe been made of the temporary schemes of the past two years. Meanwhile,*e have to decide whether the existing scheme should continue for next winter,if so, what modifications should be made.    The Prime Minister hadalready indicated, in reply to a supplementary question from Mrs i
4 May, that &quot;I will ask my Rt Hon Friend the Secretary of State for Energyto come forward with new proposals on how he plans to handle next winter&quot;.There is however no provision for this in the public expenditure survey, andits cost would fall as a claim upon the Contingency Reserve.    The chief secretary, Treasury, has circulated a separate paper (CP(78) 81) about this.5* El considered a number of alternative ways of improving the coverageof the scheme.    It concluded that there was only one practical alternative:to extend the 25 per cent discount element (but not the  5 cash) to the recipients of rate rebate.    The cost of this extension would be about 45 million.    This would confine the assistance to those recipients of raterebate with electricity bills of more than  20.    Since it is estimated that less than half of the three million recipients of rent rebate will fall into this category, it could considerably reduce the burden on local authorities, andchannel the money that would go tc this better off group to those actuallyfeeing the problem of high electricity bills.    It does however depend on theco-operation of the local authorities, who have not yet been approached. Ifthey are to be consulted, an early announcement, before the House rises,xs needed.    It was the view of El that, subject to Cabinet consideration ofthe Contingency Reserve point, this option was to be preferred to a straightrepetition of last year*s scheme.There remains the problem of legislative cover.    The two previousschemes have rested upon the powers of the Appropriation Act.    This is appropriate only for temporary schemes of limited duration.    If we repeatthis for a third year, we risk considerable criticism.    El therefore considered that a short and non-controversial Bill should be introduced earlyln the next Session of Parliament to convey statutory powers (in general terms, so that it could not be amended, with the detail to follow in a statutory instrument).    We should make clear our intention to introduce legislation when we announce the continuation of the scheme.    This shouldbe done before the House rises for the Summer Recess.I therefore propose:a. that there should be a further winter fuel scheme in 1978-79;b. that the discount element of the scheme should be extended tothe recipients of rate rebate;c. that statutory powers for the scheme should be taken in egislation at the beginning of the new Session.E G V Department of Industry18 July 1978

</content>
</cab>
