<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/116/0 images: 104-105</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DQCDHENT IS 3H33 PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GrOYERIIMBNT.CABINET.KEMORAHDUH BY TH3 MINISTER OF LABOUR. ig.TEP,JJIQHAIi LABOUR ORGANISATION.SooretC7?.     1.   In continuation of my Memorandum 0.P.2115 with regardto the interpretation of Artiole 405 of the Treaty of Versailles (Labour Clauses) it appears desirable that the attention of the Cabinet should be drawn to the speeohes (extracts from whioh are attached) made by the Home Secretary in the House of Commons and Lord On slow in the House of Lords in the Debate on the women and Young Persons (Employment in Lead Processes) Bill.    As the Cabinet are aware, that Bill has been lntroduoed in oonsequenoe of a Hecommendation adopted by the International Labour Conference held at Washington last year.Tho argument used by the Home Secretary and Lord Onslow in supporting the Bill follows that adopted by the International Labour Oonferenoe and it will be seen from my previous memoran-dum that it Involves considerations which merit the attention of the Cabinet.2.    Whatever may be the correct interpretation of Artiole 405, it appears to be desirable that there should be some central o-ordinatlng authority to secure that that interpretation is adopted with respeot to all the Recommendations and Conventions of International Labour Conferences, and I note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer in his memorandum CP. 2170 proposes that the Ministry of Labour should be entrusted with the general responsibility for International Labour Work.30th November,1920.(Signed)   T..J. MiCNAMARA.Minister of Labour.
Extract from tho spoeoh of the Home secretary in the House of Commons on 1st November, on the Second Reading of the Women and young persons (Employment in Lead processes)-Bill.&quot;It is essential that we shall, as soon as possible, carry out the obligationc under which we rest to the labour organisations (sic) of the Leaguo of Nations to have all these matters laid before Parliament and passed into law (Parliamentary Rebates House of Commons, Volume 124, No.129, Column 101). xtraot from Lord OnslowTs speech in tho House of Lords on the second reading debate on the same Bill.&quot;Under Article 405 of that Treaty each Government is required to bring the recommendation adopted by the LabourConference before parliament for action .....    IhoBill of which I move the second Reading carries out the full recommendations, but so far as this country is concerned we are oomplying, and more than complying, already with tho recommendations in all the important lead industries,   it is, however, necessary that wo should pass the Bill as soon as possible in order to carry out our obligations to tho Labour Organisation of the League of Nations&quot;, (parliamentary Debates, House of Lords,Volume 42, do.92,Column  21/2).

</content>
</cab>
