<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/116/0 images: 239-243</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
?HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPEBTY OE HIS BRITANNIC MAJF;STYTS GOVGLWMBHT;.,.)IflDENTIALo Cony No.0 A BINE To 1^2241^ &apos;LEAGUE   Og? r NATIONS;H3POHT OFTEE STgOIAL COMMISSION ON TYPHUS in report   OF-MMB professeur The Ma&amp;sen, Director of the State Serum Institute, Copenhagen-Le Sehatour Dr. Pettevin, Dir0.0tear adjoint Co 11Exfi 0e Intornatioral d rHyglene &apos; pub 11 cure. Paris.-.35i*o Po Nomian White, C.I.E., Medical Commissions Typhus Commission. League of Nations0invited by. the Cornell oi the League of Nations to proceed at once to Poland and to present in person a Report to the Assembly as to the exact epidemic in Poland aOur Commission entrusted with the ,tasi. of studying existing sanitary conditions in Poland with special reference to the prevalence of typhus fever and cholera arrived in Warsaw on the 1st and 4th of November,,In view of the limited time at our disposal anything in the nature of a comprehensive investigation was out of the question,lie mud therefore to limit our inquiry to a small.number of representative places which we submitted to as full investigation as possible.The two areas visited were the northern part of the eastern territories (as represented by the towns of Lida, Grodno and Wolkowysk) and Galicia,. where we visited .Lemberg, 2 oil lew, Nadworna,  urahi, B oh or 0 da 3 any,, Stanislawow, Cracow, v/adowioe, Sue ha and Sskopaneo   In both cases we travelled by &quot;railway to the chief centres from which we motored to smaller towns and villages in the neighbourh00d A resume of our observations concerning typhus and. cholera respectively is given belowBI,, TYPHUS EEVEBThe area visited in the northern part, of the eastern territory is poor and has suffered heavily as a result of the war which has been waged there almost incessantly since -ri914,   The retreat of. the Bolshevik forces had taken^ pla c e- 1 -
place only a few weeks before the t irne of our vis$t.   The destruction   of a la rare number&apos; of houses, especially in the villages&apos;, has brought about an almost: incredible aiiount of overcrowding.   In one place we aww the entire population of a village whioh had been completely destroyed., and which had formerly consisted, of a hundred hbuses;v herded together &apos;in a single building which was itself in ah advanced state of disrepair.Bo c ul s it ions have impoverished the&apos;&apos;6ountry.   Information sriven uaby the local authorities ind icates&apos; that-&apos; f cod reservos for the winter are nonexistent.   The number of&apos;horses and cattle are reduced to a cuarter of the pre-war standard.Strictly speaking this part of the -country&apos; has never possessed a sanitary organisation.   Before the war there was no zenistvosin these districts and the element of organisation    &apos;; insufficient in number which hud been created by the Polish Government had been evacuated or&apos;-destroyed&apos;during the course of the recent military operations; at the time of our visit these were in course of reconstruction.In spite of the impossibility oi obtaining ejaidemlolo/pical statisical data of any value it is Imwaa that typhus existed in endemic formin this part of- the country;, - &quot;Although tho time of our visit did ntt oo-inoide with the season of maximum incidence of typhus fever, we saw stiff i ci eat to indicate that the disease is extremely widespread and. of a severe type.In the towns, hospitals that had only been re-opened a few days already contained typhus &quot;patients.   ;:.t Grodno, for example, the epidemic hospital, which had&quot;been re-opened three weeks previously, contained 150 patients,1 Suffering&apos;from either typhus or relapsing fever, in addition &quot;to which a further 70 typhus patients were accommodated in an annexe.In the villages, typhus cases&apos;were found in large numbers, sometimes in ever;, house visited.   On oneopcasion we found in a sinerlo house eight patients In various -stages of the disease in addition to two bodies of persons who had died. of typhus, one on the day of our visit, the other the orevious&apos; evening.In Eastern Galicia, as&apos;in the area described above, warlike operations which have Continued - with slight Intermissions since 1914 almost up to date, have&apos; be&apos;Cn responsible for-very extensive destruction of dwellings.&apos;;&apos; The resulting conditions of poverty and overcrowding are By$cially favourable to the propagation of epidemic&apos; d-i-seaso notably t3?phus fever*The sanitary orgahisati oh&apos;, evacuated &apos; or &quot;destroyed during the course of the recent oampalra is .In process of reaonsfruo-tion, but at the moment -it -is- impossible to obtain statistical data, re ardi&amp;K: the present prevalence of typhus fever.   As en example of the--lack of information wo may cite our experience at /Juraki,&apos;   This^&apos;small village In the Boboroaczany district had reported no Cases &apos;of-typhus to the sanitary -authorities-: ; ail the same, half-an-hour&apos; s ;hoxise to house inquiry in a&quot; portion of the village resulted in the discovery of iwo typhus patients in one house,&quot; three In another, five in a third, and in a fourth we found ail&apos;the occupants convalescent from n recent- attack of the&apos;disease.At
At the present time typhus is not prevailing in  astern Galioia in the acute farm in whioh it prevailed last spring. Nevertheless, the disease Is very widespread and we found cases in every.place visited, thoudi in most instances few in number.   Before the war typhus fever was endemic in a few well-defined areas 0/ Galicia; to-day the whole oi S;.stern Galicia must bo regarded as an endemic focus of the disease.The results of the personal observations that we,have been able to mate do not permit of an opinion as to the course of typhus favor in Poland   or the dangers that are likely to accrue to other countries.:   Abundant information concerning those matters is contained in the publications of the Polish Ministry of Health; in the reports made in 1019 to the league of Red Cross Societies by M.M. Buchanan, Cummins, Castollani and Wisbeck, and in 1920 by.Dr. Ohodzko to the London Conference; in the reports of Medecin principal Gsuthier, Director of the Health Service of the French Mill lt&amp;s*y Kiss ion. etc,Here we would direct attention to the fact that the years 1919 and 1920 were both characterised by extremely severe epidemics..   The number of cases notified. - it is hardly necessary to point out. that such figures are only an actual numbers very much below the actual numbers - were most numerous in 1919 in the months of April and May when 34&apos;, 87b and 34,807 oases respectively   were reported, and in 1920 in Pebrusrv, 27,984 cases.In June, 19 20, the last month for which statistics are available, 3,550 cases were notified in Oonsrresa Poland, 1,795 in bestern Galicia, and 5.850 in eastern Galicia; those figures concern the civil population only.   The incidence of tho disease in the army of tho interior varied in different cantonments between 0..01 and 0.60 per coat.  (Lwow) with a mean, incidence of 0.09 per cent, In prisoners camps the typhus incidence amounted to 1.30 per cent.The reports indicate that typhus is very unequally distributed in Poland,    The north-western districts are practically free from the disease, as is also the district of ?oson; the southern and eastern districts are most seriously affected.V.q may conclude that though typhus may not exist at the present time in the form of an acute epMemic (the present is the season of low incidence of the disease) it is very widespread throughout large areas notably In the south, and the east.   The areas we visited Eire infected to a degree of which official documents give no indication-It is impossible to frame a forecast of the future course of an epidemic of disease, not endemic over wide areas, but our knowledge of the epidemiology of typhus,enables us &quot;to foresee that seasonal outbreaks will continue to occur the gravity of which will be chiefly determined by all social and
noanc. economic conditions which axe likely to oroate a stater of physical depre-alon among, the population submitted oa^Kpoaad.. to infection.   In any case its persistence institutes a permanent danger to tho rest of Poland and for all other countries.In countries with a high standard of personal hygiene there is not much to fear in the way oi 02:tensive outbreaks ox typhus fever.   But oven in such countries there aro groups of individuals and communitios whero lack oi cleanliness presents all the conditions necessary *ior tbft spread oi the disec.se,  &quot;pie re^rt of the League of llocl Cross&apos;Sociotioa rightly calls attention to the. recent 0 pi domic&apos; iii &quot;Holland as a case in point.The eradication of typhus in the aroas described a; ears to us therefore to be a question of international importance. Its continued prevalence constitutes a standing menace to other countries according to the Intercity&apos;of the epidemic. Measures taken at the frontiers of other countries can diminish the danger but they cannot obviate i^&apos; altogether.The measures necessary for the eradication of the disease havo been studied ana defined, notably at the Conference In London,The Polish Government are alive to tho urgency oi the work to be accomplished.   She organisation that they have created to fight epidemic disease, notably typhus fever, is excellent and has already achieved results that do them much credit.   But the material at their disposal is altogether inadequate for the intensive and extended campaign that it is necessary to wage without dolay.II.   OhOLSEA.,At the end of September cholera appealed in territory reoccupied by the Polish forces in the&quot;neighbourhood of Lida and Grodno.   Previously there had been a large incidence of this disease in Soviet Bussia,   Thus an official Soviet statement dated August 30, 1920, reported extensive prevalence of cholera in parts of Soviet territory adjacent to tho Russo-Po*ish armistice line as well as in other p^rts of Russia.   In the first six months oi 19 20 5,675.cases of cholera were notified in Russia.   By the middle of Cctober, IS20, soldiers and prisoners of ./ar had carried infection to various parts of Poland.    Up to date (November 17, 19 0) 21 foci of infection have been reportod and new foci are still being discovered.    In Poland proper reverted c*ses number 299 in addition to which 119 carriers have been discovered. Of the 299 cases 3oycivilians; the great majority of the remainder were prisoners of war.      In adtition to the above, 461 cases of cholera have beon notified in the eastern territory now under Polish military administration; oi these 100 were civilians.The occurrence oi cholera cases in 21 widely separated places in Poland, their very hiAh carrier rato, and the extremely defective nature of rust of the water supplies combine to make the situation full oi danger.   ,ji unpleasantfact
fact in this connection is the very high incicion.ee of enteric or typhoifi fever now prevailing in raost parts of ^oland. Cholera and typhoid fever are propagated in k similar manner, the one to the other,The Polish Haalth Administration Is alive to the clangers of tho situation; inoculation with a cholera vaccine is being widely carried out.   The whole army and all the prisoners of war luvo now been inoculated as well c.a large numbers of tho civil population.On our tour of inspection we encountered cholera at Li&amp;e, Warsaw, ivadowice, and Zakopane.At v/adowice we inspected the prisoners? camp,   At the time of our visit there were 4^500 prisoners of -war in very poor condition.   The Polish authorities are obviously finding it extremely difficult to provide adequate food and clothing for their prisoners.   There were CJ0 cholera cases in tho prisoners&apos; hospital at wadowice as well as 80 cases of relapsing-icver and 36 of typhus.We are informed that there are 80,000 prisoners of war in Poland at the present time,. Half of these are in prisoners camps, the remainder being scattered about the country in working parties.   The presence of this large number of prisoners of war with very enfeebled power of resistenee to disease is a most unwelcome complication of the elroady sufficiently difficult health problems of Poland.COKCIUfclONS,we are of opinion that it is both necessary and urgent to afford effective material&quot;assistance to Poland in her struggle against epidemic disease, especially against typhus fever,;e recommend that the League of hations render this assistance on the basi3 elaborated by. the London Conference and by the Council Meeting at liome.m, POTTEVIH,-. Th.kALSM,. ..&quot;jp. ,mm:M, white. , Whitehall Gardens, ^,w,l, December 6th,. 1$20.

</content>
</cab>
