<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/116/0 images: 267-268</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty &apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.  December 1920.SECRET.C.P.-2247.AGRICULTURE BILL.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.IT is necessary to draw urgent attention to the serious liability which Part I of the Agriculture Bill, now before the House of Locrds, appears likely, in the light of the present tendency of prices, to impose upon the Exchequer.The Bill guarantees minimum prices for wheat and oats based upon the following figures for the year 1919, which is regarded as the standard year : Wheat 68/- per customary quarter, or64/9 per statutory quarter. Oats    46/- per customary quarter, or42/8 per statutory quarter.These figures are subject to adjustment in each year according as the cost of production is found to be greater or less than that of the standard year. The first year in which the guarantees operate is 1921 and the first payments under them would fall to be made in April 1922.It is in regard to oats that immediate and serious liability appears likely to arise. From enquiries which have been made it is believed that the guaranteed price for 1921 is likely to be not less than 51/- per statutory quarter. The average &quot; Gazette &quot; price is steadily falling, and was 48/4 for the last week of November and 45/6 for the first week of December. It would seem probable that in 1921 it will be at least 10/- a quarter below the price guaranteed by the Bill. According to the figures given in the White Paper (Cmd. 741) this would mean a payment in 1922-3 to the farmers on the basis of the 1919 acreage of  12,280,000. If, as would seem quite possible, the prospect of the subsidy induces farmers next year to sow oats on land now under wheat the subsidy may well amount to  1.5,000,000. For this payment the taxpayer may get not more but actually less home produced food for human consumption.As regards wheat the prospect is less immediately serious. It is thought that the guaranteed price for 1921 may be found to be about 80/- per quarter, and so far as can be foreseen at the moment the market price may perhaps not be expected to fall below that figure in that year; but in future years, especially if and when Russia comes into the market, the price may well fall to 70/- a quarter. This would apparently involve a subsidy in respect of wheat of about  8,000,000 a year, and it will thus be seen that the total liability under the Bill in future years may amount to anything from  20 to  30 million a year.From the Parliamentary discussions upon the Bill it- is apparent that that measure of Government control which accompanies the guarantees is very unpopular with the farmers, and it would seem very doubtful if the scheme will induce them in fact to increase the total acreage under cereals, or at least the acreage under wheat.At the Cabinet discussion on the 19th May last the question of the inclusion of oats in the guarantee was considered. Its inclusion is understood to be based partly on the ground of the part which it pkys in the rotation of crops, but also because it was thought that its exclusion would be regarded by Scottish and Irish farmers as making the Bill unduly favourable to the English farmers, who grow nine-tenths of the wheat produced in the United Kingdom.If it is now too late to reconsider the whole question, it might at least be considered whether the guaranteed minimum for oats is not too high. The figures in &quot; The Corn Production Act, 1917,&quot; for 1921-2, are for wheat 45/- a quarter and for oats 24/- a, quarter and a much larger increase proportionately is thus given to the latter in the present Bill. According to the Royal Commission on Agriculture, the proposed minimum guarantee represents something less than the average bare cost[50721
2of production in 1918-9. Even so, it would no doubt give a considerable margin of profit to the more efficient or more fortunately situated farmers, and, in fact, the figure appears to be based upon the maximum prices ruling in 1918 with a deduction for profit. It would appear evident in the light of present circumstances that for oats at least too high a guarantee is being offered. The liability in respect of this crop is much the most serious of the total subsidy, for oats about 30 per cent, would go to Ireland and 22 per cent, to Scotland.(Initialled)       A. C.Treasury, S.W.,December 6, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
