<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/116/0 images: 283-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOOTMfT 13 TEB- ROBERT? OF HIS BRITAMIC MAJBSTT13 GOTONMKNC A B I H B.jj--PggMgS COTCg Off IggHATIQHiL JUSTICE.   &apos;Copy of Uoto from tho Un&amp;er-Socrctary of Stato for Foreign Affairs to the Secretary, Cabinet, December 6th, 1920.* * *(Previous Papers : Boo. B.EJ). - 9, 10, 23. 32. 33, 34:- 1902, 1905, 1956. 1962,1974, 2010, 2188 and2189.)(W,2766/241/98). Immediate,Iho Under Secrotary of Stato for foreign Affairs presents hie compliments to the Secretary to tho Cabinet, and ie directed by. Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit, herewith, copy of a letter from Sir Co Hurst asking: for His Lordshipfs views on two alternative methods for creating the Permanent Court of International Justice provided for by . Article 14 of tho Covenant of tho league of Nations-Sir C. Hurst points out that Mr. Balfour may shortly be called upon to express an opinion on this question. 2.     In Lord Curzonr8 opinion the establishment of an International Court of Justico should bo the subject of an international Convention, which should contain a olauso stipulating that the Convention will not becono operative until it has been ratified by at least two-thirds of the total number of tho morbers of the League. 3*    Lord Curzon desiros the matter to be laid before the Cabinet in order that appropriate instructions  -may bo sent to Mr. Balfour as soon as possible.Foreign Office, S.j5M,December 6th7 1920.
Office of the British Dole^atloa,^Hotel Beau Hivago,Gonova.1st December, 1920.Sir.I am re-quested by !&amp;* Balf our to ash: that you will bring to Lord Curzon&apos;s notice a question which is likely to arise in the near future with regard to tho scheme for the creation of a Permanent Court of International Justice.Ihe scheme has been under detailed considerationby a sub-o omit tee of lawyers, and in all probability areport will be ready for submission to the Assembly in thecourse of the next few days recommending the adoption--of a plan difforing in no essential particular from that acceptedby the Council of the League at Brussels.The question will then arise as to whether the scheme should be embodied in a Convention between the lowers to*bo signed by plenipotentiaries and ratified in due course, or whether the Court should be brought into being nerely by an Act of tho Assembly based on the inherent powers of the delegates to tho Assembly to taice decisions on items duly inserted in the Agenda, and requiring no subsequentHconfirm-ation or ratification by their GovernnentScMr, Balfour is advised that the acceptance of the scheme by HoMoGovernment will not entail legislation,.nor will it. entail a direct money vote; tho expenses of the Court will become part of the general expenses of the league and will not therefore do more than increase an already existing vote. From the legal point of view&quot;therefore it would bo possible to adopt the plan of establishing the Court by the decision or Act of tho Assembly, if it should be thought expedient to do so.he Undor Secretary of Stato, ^Foreign office a\/&apos; S .   . a 1 oIt
It is clear that this plan would have groat advantages pvor a Convention Iron tho point of vie?/ of the rapidity with which tho Court can ho cet up.   Many of the dolcg&amp;teo to the Assembly are not provided with full powers and cannot obtain them boforo tho end of tho Assembly.   The Convention would probably thorefore havo to ronain u/pen for signature for a period of two or throe months, and would then havo to await ratification,.  In tho case of Po.wor3 which thought it necessary to obtain the approval of their Parliaments before ratification, sono considerable delay might ensuo and it is even possible that in sono cases such ratification might never bo deposited,Cortain advantages undoubtedly attend the establishment of the Court by means of a Convention,   It would facilitate the a&amp;heeion of tho United States even if they do not join the League r,Fm-thermnore, cor tain members of the Leaguo are undoubted-ly finding- that their share of the cost of the League involves so heavy a payment that they will hesitate to accept without further authority a scheme which must add considerably to the expenses of the LoaguooI am to add that tho French and Italian Governments are believed to attach importance to the adoption of a Convention as the node of establishing the Court., but no official statement of tho views, of these Governments has yet been made.,As MTo Balfour nay be called upon to express a definite opinion upon the question at an early date ho would be glad to have the assistance of Lord Curzon*s views as soon as possiblenI anYour obedient Servant(Signed). C3CIL JuB.HURSTc

</content>
</cab>
