<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/116/0 images: 340-346</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the PropertyMofCirculated by the Secretary of State for India. cSECRET. ^I circulate a Note by the Financial Department of the India Office on Indian Military Expenditure.Q    &apos; -     , &quot; E. S. M.&quot;O^7th December 1920.OA I&apos;    INDIAN MILITARY EXPENDITURE.^        Some Financial Considerations arising from the Esh^rCommittee^ Report.The net expenditure on the military services in India budgeted for the current financial: year 1920-21 was 40,000,000/. on a basis of 11 = Rs. .15. This figure-is arrived, at as follows : -  millions at;Expenditure :  Ks. d-Mr. Bs. 15 ^ i.India -        -        -  .47-4 31*0England       -        -    -- 9&apos;9Total        -        -        -        - 41.5India  -        -        -1-8 V2England       -        -      &apos;3Total -        - -        -15Net expenditure     - 40 &quot;0On a basis of Rs. 10    11. the figures would work out as follows: Expenditure: India -        -        -        -  47&apos;4England      -        -        -        -    9-9Rs. crores or   millions.- Total        -        -        -        -        -  57;3 ipts: India -        -        -        -    j.&quot;8England -        -        -        -      &quot;net expenditure     -        -        -        -  55*2Since the Budget was framed various additional liabilities have come forward, and it seems probable that the military bill for the year is not likely to fall much, if at all, short of 60,000,0OOL It is no doubt the case that this figure includes a great deal of abnormal expenditure on the operations on the North-West Frontier. Oh the other hand, it does not include provision for many very expensive measures of reform contemplated by the Esher Committee, and present indications are that the discon-tinuanceof.military operations will not be accompanied by any material lightening of the present burden of the cost of the army in India, and, indeed, that this burden is likely to become even heavier than it is at present.2. It is relevant to note (the reference is to the figures on a Rs. 15 11. basis) that the figure of 40,00(),000Z. budgeted for in the current year compares as follows with the cost of the military services in earlier years :   millions.   millions.1909-01 - - - 19-1 1915-16 - - - 22-31910-11 - - - 19-3 1916-17 - - - 25-01911-12 - - - 19-6 1917-18 - - -&apos;.29-()1912-13 - - - 19-6 1918-19 - -    &quot;  - 44-.51913-14 - - - 19-9 1919-20 (revised) - - 52&quot;91914-15 - - - 20-4 2858     100  12.20                             A
Taking the revenues of the Government of India as a whole (Imperial and Provincial combined), these were estimated to amount in the current year to. 134*8 millions (or  .133*3 millions less military receipts),&quot;and the expenditure on military services thus absorbs 30 per cent, of the total. If we take the revenues net, as is done in the explanatory memorandum presented by the Secretary of State to Parliament (page 4), they amount to 95,000,000/. only, the percentage thus standing at over 40. If account be taken of Imperial transactions only the percentage will be even more striking, and the complete separation of the provincial budgets from the Imperial Budget under the Reforms Scheme will lend added prominence to the facts.3. &apos;.nie whole matter is one on which it may be expected that under the reforms the attention of the Legislative Assembly will be focussed in the very early future. Even in the course of the general discussion on the Budget for the current year, while military operations were still continuing, it was severely commented on. by many speakers. I need only refer to Mr. Iiailey&apos;s remarks in replying to them (vide pages 1.18, et seq., of Financial Statement volume for 1920-21) :-&quot; I come now to a more important head, the head of military expenditure. I am, I think, correct in saying that the proposals in the Budget received support from the Hon. Mir Asacl Ali, the Hon. Rampal Singh, and from the Hon. Mr. Redcli; but they have been criticised, and criticised strongly, in other directions. The Hon. Maharaja of Kasim Bazar, Sir Fazulbhoy Currimbhoy, Mr. Bonarjea, Sir Gangadhar Chitnavis, the Hon. Pandit, Mr. Patel, Mr. Sauna, all criticised the provision which we have made under this head. I tried in ray Financial Statement to explain, as fully as possible, what were , the components of that expenditure. I. ventured on a prophesy (and in doing so I seemed to have caused a good of apprehension to some members of this Council) that it would be, perhaps, impossible for us ever to reduce our expenditure to the pre-war level.&quot;4. In resolution IV. of the first group of recommendations of the Brussels Financial Conference it was stated: &quot; The statements presented to the Conference (by the various countries) show . that, on an average, some 20 per cent, of the national expenditure is still being devoted to the maintenance of armaments and the preparations for war.   The Conference desires to affirm with the utmost emphasis that the world cannot afford this expenditure.&quot;It is remarkable that, on the basis of the statistics presented to the Conference1by the countries supplying the necessary infor-i The calculations exclude expenditure  mat;on tjie percentage for India (35*7) is thethe railways, posts, and telegraph   -, . ,    ;     -,i   ,i c ,i r-  r-(.ua        J    1 b 1    highest with the exception of those oi Japan(47*9), and Greece (37*0), comparing, for example, with 16&apos;8 for the United Kingdom, 22* 1 for Italy, 11&apos;2 for France, and 0&apos;6 for Canada. .(Flie details in tables at pages 9 and 18 of &quot;Public Finance and Analysis of Expenditure and Revenue,&quot; published as Appendix I. to Paper IV. of the preliminary documents for the Brussels Financial Conference.)5. In view of what is said above it is important to consider what will be the position of expenditure on defence under the Reforms Scheme. Section 67a (3) (v) (c) of the Government of India Act provides that:  &quot;The proposals of the Governor-General in Council for the appropriation of revenue or moneys relating to the following heads of expenditure shall not be submitted to the vote of the Legislative Assembly, nor shall they be open to discussion of either Chamber at the time when the annual statement is under discussion, unless the Governor-General otherwise directs (v) expenditure classified by the order of the Governor-General in Council as (c) defence.&quot;Though, however, defence expenditure will not be subject to the vote, and though direct resolutions on the subject may he ruled out, there is little doubt that it will be impossible to prevent the matter forming the subject of free comment and criticism during the course of the general, discussion of the Budget as at present. For under 46 of the rules of legislative business discussion of the Budget with commence with aon services
general discussion in which &quot; the Assembly shall be at liberty to discuss, the Budget as a whole or any question of principle involved therein.&quot;6. Apart from this, when the Budget does not balance the question of additional taxation will arise, and this will require to be submitted to the vote in the ordinary way, and there will be great danger of an adverse vote if the elected majority in the Assembly take the view that the taxation is necessitated by a level of military expen-diture which is in their opinion too high. There is little doubt that even the continuance of the present scale of military expenditure will be scrutinised with great jealousy, entrenching, as it does, on the resources available for the reduction of the contributions payable by the provinces to the Central Government, and thus restricting the revenues and the activities of the popular Governments in the provinces.It is true that where the necessary taxation is not voted, the provisions of section 671? of the Government of India Act will be applicable, and that it will be open to the Governor-General to certify under that section that the passage of the taxation Bill &quot; is essential for the safety, tranquillity, or interests of British India,&quot; and so to secure its enactment. But the application of this procedure to taxation, proposals is drastic and undesirable, and habitual recourse to it would be out of the question, meaning, as it would, a real breakdown of the essential character of the Reforms Scheme.Moreover, as an incidental but very practical matter, though the responsibility for employing the provisions of section 67b is personal to the Governor-General, it is almost unthinkable that he should act under this section without consulting, and if &apos; possible obtaining the concurrence of, his Executive Council. The matter is one in which it is improbable that he would be able to carry with him the three Iudian members of his Executive Council against the clearly expressed views of the Legis-lative Assembly, and consequently the employment of this section for the purpose could hardly fail to result in a Cabinet crisis.7. It is necessary also to emphasise the fact that the next few years must inevitably be a period of great strain on the finances of the Government of India. Apart from the already heavy burden of military expenditure, the Central Govern-ment is, under the Reforms Scheme, passing on to the provinces at once nearly 9 crores of annual revenue, and will further have to face insistent claims from them for the progressive reduction of the annual contributions, amounting to nearly 10 crores, which it is necessary for her to take from them at the outset of the Reforms towards creating approximate equilibrium in her finances. At the same time she has to deal with a top-heavy load of floating and short-term debt, for which an early provision of adequate sinking fund arrangements is essential. On the other side her. revenues must now inevitably commence to feel the reaction from the artificial prosperity which accompanied war conditions. The Customs duties will be affected by the decline in import values resulting from (a) the effect on imports of a weak exchange and (b) the general fall in the prices of imported commodities. The taxes on income, in spite of the tightening up of the administration which is in progress, will feel the result of greatly contracted profits of trade and industry. Slack trade will also affect the railway earnings, and these latter will also be encroached on alike by the steadily increasing cost of the administration of the railways and by the cost of making good the arrears in the matter of current upkeep and maintenance into which these inevitably fell during the war. It has indeed already been intimated by the Government of India that a substantial increase of taxation will be necessary to balance their budget for next year. In fact, in India, no less than in the United Kingdom, a point has been reached when economy in every branch of the administration is essential. But while a parallel may be drawn between the position in India and England on its financial and economic side, there is a radical difference in its political aspect. In England the high level of taxation is, it is true, causing a good deal of squealing and agitation for economy on the part of Government. In India, where taxation is not imposed by the representatives of the people, a high level of taxation maintained for purposes which India strongly argues are not in India&apos;s best interests, forms a ready weapon for the extremist agitator in his campaign for fomenting racial hatred and can only form a grave political danger.8. This minute is not intended to deal with, the separate large question of India&apos;s liability in respect of Imperial defence as a whole or with such matters as the adjust-ments (important as these may be) in respect of expenditure incurred for purposes other than the direct defence of India.   Consequently the calculations made in the 2853 A 2
earlier paragraphs do not take account of expenditure incurred on behalf oE the Imperial Government for such purposes as the equipment and despatch of troops for external garrisons or depots for their maintenance. It is assumed that India will be fully recouped for any expenditure of the kind to which she may be put; aud if there were any question of her being required to accept any expenditure beyond that necessitated by her own supposed needs, the position would be more serious still.9. In making the above remarks i must not be understood to be attempting to minimise the importance of adequate provision fer defence expenditure, recognising as I do that this is the first duty of any Government worthy of the name. Nor do I wish to suggest that it is practicable to revert to the pre-war scale of military expenditure, or anything like it. But it would be foolish and dangerous to lose sight of this aspect of the question on which insufficient stress seems to have been laid by the Esher Committee. And it is of great importance that we should know how, we really stand in the matter of military expenditure before sanctioning piecemeal large schemes of unknown cost.10. What the Esher Committee actually say on the subject is as follows: &quot; (5) In submitting our recommendations, we have borne in mind that many of them will entail increased expenditure. We are aware that the present cost of the army in India (1920-21) is already double the pre-war cost. We have, therefore, been actuated throughout by due regard for economy, but we have not refrained from recommending relatively costly measures, where we are satisfied that these are essential to the contentment and better administration of the army.&quot; (6) Our proposals will further increase the annual cost of the army in India, but although the immediate effect of adopting them will be to set up a higher standard of normal expenditure, we do not contemplate the probability of this standard being increased, at least for some years to come, above what can be met from the normal growth of Indian revenues. It is admitted that the first concern of any Government should be defence from external aggression, and the maintenance of internal tranquillity. With the prospect of industrial and agricultural development in India, the revival of trade, and the disappearance of freight difficulties, it is hoped that the revenues of India may expand sufficiently to enable the needs of the army to be satisfied without detriment to other claims.&quot; (7) Fresh standards have been set up; existing services require reorganisa-tion, and new services have to be developed and equipped. There is much leeway too, to be made up in improving accommodation in conformity with modern requirements. All these will involve heavy initial expenditure. We venture to suggest that it might be advantageous from the point of view both of finance and of military administration, to adopt a system somewhat on the following lines : &quot; (a) The military authorities should first prepare a programme, showing the capital expenditure entailed by measures such as those indicated above.&quot; (b) The Government of India would thus be in a position to gauge their liabilities, and to decide to what extent they could be met, and over what period the programme should be spread; and could proceed to obtain the Secretary of State&apos;s sanction, where necessary, to the expenditure involved.&quot; (c) The Government of India might then arrange to give a definite allotment (over and above the sum required for the ordinary yearly upkeep of the army) towards the carrying out of this programme of special expenditure. This allotment should be expressed in terms of a total sum, to be spread&apos;over a fixed number of years. Lapses in the yearly allotment should be carried forward into the following year&apos;s budget, and remain at the disposal of the military authorities for the carrying out of this programme. Within the amount of the special provision, the military authorities should have a free hand in deciding to which of the measures in the programme priority should be given. The accounts relating to the expenditure on these measures should pro forma be maintained separately.
earlier paragraphs do not take account of expenditure incurred on behalf of the Imperial Government for such purposes as the equipment and despatch of troops for external garrisons or depots for their maintenance. It is assumed that India will be fully recouped for any expenditure of the kind to which she may be put; aud if there were any question of her being required to accept any expenditure beyond that, necessitated by her own supposed needs, the position would be more serious still.9. In making the above remarks I must not be understood to be attempting to minimise the importance of adequate provision fer defence expenditure, recognising as I do that this is the first duty of any Government worthy of the name. Nor do I wish to suggest that it is practicable to revert to the pre-war scale of military expenditure, or anything like it. But it would be foolish and dangerous to lose sight of this aspect of the question on which insufficient stress seems to have been laid by the Esher Committee. And it is of great importance that we should know how we really stand in the matter of military expenditure before sanctioning piecemeal large schemes of unknown cost.10. What the Esher Committee actually say on the subject is as follows :--&quot; (5) In submitting our recommendations, we have borne in mind that many of them will entail increased expenditure. We are aware that the present cost of the army in India (1920-21) is already double the pre-war cost. We have, therefore, been actuated throughout by due regard for economy, but we have not refrained from recommending relatively costly measures, where we are satisfied that these are essential to the contentment and better administration, of the army.&quot; (6) Our proposals will further increase the annual cost of the army in India, but although the immediate effect of adopting them will be to set up a higher standard of normal expenditure, we do not contemplate the probability of this standard being increased, at least for some years to come, above what can be met from the normal growth of Indian revenues. It is admitted that the first concern of any Government should be defence from external aggression, and the maintenance of internal tranquillity. With the prospect of industrial and agricultural development in India, the revival of trade, and the disappearance of freight difficulties, it is hoped that the revenues of India may expand sufficiently to enable the needs of the army to be satisfied without detriment to other claims.&quot; (7) Fresh standards have been set up; existing services require reorganisa-tion, and new services have to be developed and equipped. There is much leeway too, to be made up in improving accommodation in conformity with modern requirements. All these will involve heavy initial expenditure. We venture to suggest that it might be advantageous from the point of view both of finance and of military administration, to adopt a system somewhat on the following lines : &quot; (a) The military authorities should first prepare a programme, showing the capital expenditure entailed by measures such as those indicated above.&quot; (b) The Government of India would thus be in a position to gauge their liabilities, and to decide to what extent they could be met, and over what period the programme should be spread; and could proceed to obtain the Secretary of State&apos;s sanction, where necessary, to the expenditure involved.&quot; (c) The Government of India might then arrange to give a definite allotment (over and above the sum required for the ordinary yearly upkeep of the army) towards the carrying out of this programme of special expenditure. This allotment should be expressed in terms of a total sum, to be spread &quot;over a fixed number of years. Lapses in the yearly allotment should be carried forward into the following year&apos;s budget, and remain at the disposal of the military authorities for the carrying out of this programme. Within the amount of the special provision, the military authorities should have a free hand in deciding to which of the measures in the programme priority should be given. The accounts relating to the expenditure on these measures should pro forma be maintained separately.
&quot; (d) Subject to these conditions, the military authorities should, be required to work strictly to the annual budget provision for the upkeep of the army, except in so far as this may prove impossible owing to unforeseen causes, such as military operations, or increases in the cost of foodstuffs, &amp;c, occurring in the course of the financial rear.&quot;11. 1 am doubtful about the desirability of a definite and cast-iron programme of individual measures to be accepted for execution over a period of years. Circum-stances and ideas are liable to change, as was recognised in the orders discontinuing the old &quot; schedule &quot; system, vide in this connection the Secretary of State&apos;s Despatch, Military, No. 61, dated 30th September 1920. That Despatch suggested a system of &quot;history sheets&quot; for individual measures. What seems to be required is, in fact, not a formal programme for several, years ahead, but collective data as to important measures whose adoption from time to time as funds permit is considered to be desirable. These projects can then be pruned or added to as the circumstances of the time appear to require. But the formulation of a list of such projects (with estimates -of cost) and its periodical revision elastic though such list may be is essential if the Government of India are to be in a position to frame even an approximate estimate of their prospective liabilities. Subject to this qualification the general idea underlying the proposals of the Esher Committee is, in my view, in the main sound, and, indeed, in giving evidence before the Committee about a year ago, I ventured, to suggest something on these lines.12. At the same time I cannot but feel that, in stopping short at these recom-mendations, the Committee has perhaps unavoidably failed to take a sufficiently comprehensive view of the problem as a whole, while it is also unfortunate that it has not been able to furnish even a rough estimate of the cost of its various proposals. For a full consideration of the matter we require a statement of the organisation-considered to be necessary as a permanent arrangement for the defence of India with its approximate annual cost (A) on the present basis of pay equipment, &amp;c.,&apos;ui addition to the cost (B) of the individual measures of improvement recommended by the Esher Committee. I do not pretend that the recurring cost of the permanent organisation, or (A), can be fixed at an immutable figure ; and I may observe that such a calculation made in the Government of india&apos;s No. .1 special Despatch of March 191.9, and its accompaniments was unfortunately out of date before it came under consideration. But to proceed without such data is not merely unbusinesslike but must inevitably, for the reasons already given, result at no very distant date in grave embarrassment to the Government of India&apos;s finances and react most prejudicially on the whole-administration.- 13. What is liable to happen in practice is that, when the resources of the &quot;Government are already stretched almost to breaking point in meeting the amount asked for in order to meet current military requirements, demands will come along for additional funds for further projects on grounds of their primary importance or urgency, which it is impossible to gainsay. Neither the financial authorities, nor, in fact, the Government as a whole, can ever really be in a position to assess the relative urgency of various military requirements, such as the construction of a frontier road, the increase in the reserve of transport or supplies, the construction of new cauton-ments or the improvement of hospitals. And the most that can be done is, having due regard to the position of the country&apos;s finances as a whole on the one hand, and on the other the urgency as a whole of the requirements put forward by the military authorities, to state the total, annual amount that the revenues of the country can afford. Within this amount, and subject to the general control of the Government of India and the Secretary of State on grounds of policy, by far the most satisfactory course seems to be that it should rest within the discretion of the military authorities to assign to the measures of reform which they have on the anvil such precedence inter se as the circumstances of the time seem to them to demand, and to take these measures up in that order. This arrangement, however, presupposes a preliminary determination of the vital factor (A) referred to above, namely, the basic permanent, organisation and its cost. To allow for the undertaking of essential new measures, it is clear that there must be an adequate margin between the cost of (A) and the amount which the Government of India expect to be able to find from year to year for the -military services ; and. if the importance of the various new measures or schemes in contemplation is such that they must unquestionably be proceeded with forthwith, or in the early future, a reconsideration of the factor (A) will then, it is submitted, inevitably be forced upon us.
14. We expect to receive from the Government of India before the end of the-year their views on the proposals in Parts III. IX. of the Esher Committee&apos;? Report. The Special Committee of the India Council has suggested that &quot; the Government of &apos;* India be asked to supply the Secretary of Slate as soon, as possible with an &quot; approximate estimate, however rough, of the total cost of the Esher Committees *&apos; recommendations, and to state their general views as to the extent to which and &quot; the manner in which it will be possible to finance the expenditure involved.&quot; In a telegram dated 8th October the Government of India had previously been asked to let the Secretary of State &quot; have their proposals us to the provision of funds to carry out those recommendations which may be finally approved.&quot; It is to be hoped that they will take the opportunity of going into the problem as a whole, and it may be as well to give them a hint that this will before long become inevitable. Meanwhile, the matter is of such importance that I have thought it desirable to bring it to-notice here in anticipation of anything that the Government of India may have to say on the subject.

</content>
</cab>
