<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/11/0 images: 25-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 17(53)							9th March, 1953



		1.	Egypt : Defence Negotiations.          [Enter Slim, SLl. 

								W.Strang.



P.M.	No. 518. – assurance.



Slim	Adhere to Case A. in principle – principle being tht. depots &amp; installations are under Br. control.  Under B. they are not.  And impracticable to put Br. officers &amp; men under command of E. offrs. in a base – pilfering etc.

	This is safeguarded in latest tel. 523.

	Ready to concede on no. &amp; on depots we hand to Egyptians.



P.M.	A.E. has managed to achieve minimum conditions.

	We are not on a slippery slope.

	Horrible business.  But can’t go on with 80.000 men &amp; £50M. p.a. indefinitely.



	Shock to public opinion.  “Phased departure” fr. E. as fr. Sudan.



J.S.	V. strong feeling in Party.



O.L.	Para.1 of log 5 – not satisfied until we had x/. in 523.



Slim	Cafferty may lead U.S. delegation.



P.M.	I wish the 2 soldiers to lead.  Slim anyway will lead for us.



Slim	May come down to pull betwn. us and U.S. delegn. on what constitutes a working base.  Bedell seems to have a low view, on this.

	Supposing Hull is content with eg. base under E. control in peace – Mil. consns. : also pol. need to be able to say we have achieved our aim &amp; not merely “scuttled.”



P.M.	Doms. esp. A., will attach v. gt. importance to our actg. with U.S. in this.



Al.	Must decide first what is necessary in base, peace &amp; war : before Slim or Hull goes.  



P.M. 	Send 2/3 men to do this specifically – and tell Slim/Hull there and us here.  



Al. 	Get firm Anglo/U.S. understandg. on this before we start.  



P.M. 	Not throwing away £200M. on threat.



J.S.	Treaty doesn’t expire until ’56.  Party will say we are condong. breach of it.

	No reason why we shdn’t have stood it out until ’56.



P.M.	Sympathise, as you know, with that.  But reasons i) wd. we be any better off after paying £50M. p.a. for another 3 years.



Sw.	P.M. promised Menzies early informn. about outcome.

P.M.	Await A.E.’s longer message.  Then draft on basis of that.



Sw.	Must also tell other old Doms., before announcement.



Slim.	Stressed need for handling all 5 proposals as a package.

	Have U.S. accepted that?



P.M.	Let me have a note on your desiderata, wh. I can convey to Ike.

	Incldg. point tht. any diffces. betwn. you &amp; Hull shall not be communicated to Egyptians.



</content>
</cab>
