<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/11/0 images: 28-28</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 20(53)							17th March, 1953



		1.	Parliament.					[Enter B.H.



H.C.	Business for next week.

	Date of Budget – will be announced.  14/4.

	Recess dates : 2/4 to 14/4 (H.C.)





		2.	Germany : Former Nazis.



A.E.	Adenauer told U.S. &amp; Fr. tht. he approved our action &amp; is willing to bring procdgs. in German courts.  Hasn’t announced it yet.





		3.	Washington Mission.



R.A.B.	a)  Economic Talks.



	Good tht. we went early.  Have put these issues in front of their minds.

	They have put in hand urgent review (under Len Douglas) by N.A.C.

	Financg. their overseas surplus, if they mean to give less aid.  We urged them to do so by increased trade.  But their pol. diffies. are great because they haven’t come to grips with Congress – will Executive master Legislature?  Doubt if any move will be made this summer, twds. “good creditor” policies.  They may take some admin. steps first e.g. on customs.



	Humphrey was v. friendly.  Asked me to rept. how we cd. improve our trade with dollar area.  Want to send him memo. v. soon – workg. on it with B/T.  Want to include lowering of tariffs, export credit policies.

	Then either U.S. will follow our plan (incldg. convertibility) havg. first assured themselves of trade pattern wh. wd. support convertibility : or they will produce alternatives of their own.  We did impress them with size &amp; importance of sterling area.

	W’in 6 months there may be developmt.

	In Canada Ministers promised to put gt. pressure on U.S. to get moving.



A.E.	Endorse statement – in particular, need for caution.  Attitude of Congress.



	b) Political Talks.



A.E.	Persian Oil.  U.S. have endorsed our proposals &amp; told Persians so.

	New firmness is v. welcome.

	But U.S. are concerned at spare tankers available,  wh. may carry oil to be sold at prices below world-price.  They disagree with A.I.O.C. tht. this isn’t a problem. – &amp; say A.I.O.C. have bn. wrong before.



	Suggest Dpts. look into this at once.  We may have to take action.



P.M.	Let F.O. circulate memo. on history of Rose Marie (?)



A.E.	Egypt.  U.S. agreed to joint approach : put Hull into it : agreed basis.

	But Prs. insisted tht. U.S. must be invited, by Egyptian as well as U.K. Govts.  E. won’t give the invitn.  Have told U.S. we can’t accept E. attitude.  Interim fr. R.M. suggest U.S. won’t bring pressure to get in.



P.M	Can’t ask Slim to wait for more than 2/3 days.  If E. delay. we shall have to choose someone else.



Sw.	Ship sailing 26/3.  Some grumbles developing in Australian Govt.



A.E.	If  U.S. won’t push in, we shall have to say we won’t talk evacuation alone.  Then deadlock for some time.  Can’t see early prospect of talks.

	Told U.S. Amb. this a.m. tht. we wdn’t talk on evacuation alone.  Shall repeat it formally when U.S. attitude is cleared.

	Report of Neguib’s interview with Caffery.  Clear tht. N. and Fawzi were over-ruled by Cabinet.  N.’s posn. is less strong evidently.



P.M.	U.S. can’t go back on merits of policy which they accepted.  We can afford to wait.  Our posn. is stronger.



	Sudan.



A.E.	Tel. fr. Howe.  Nominees.  {Mergani Magadi} does want Nequib’s nominee.

	V. annoying.  We shall have to concede it.  Bad for Commn.



P.M.	Bad tht. Govr. shd. resist first and then have to give way.



A.E.	Suggest M/State shd. go out and have a look round.



P.M.	Yes : Howe hasn’t been v. clever – or strong.





		4.	Shooting down of Lincoln Bomber.



P.M.	Read statement to be made in H/C. this p.m.



A.E.	Agree.



H.C.	Why was training flight so close to frontier?

	Can’t they be stopped?



P.M.	100 sorties in this area per week – no interference previously.

	

Sal.	Final sentence gives R. excuse for saying tht. in last resort we shd. shoot : and this justifies their action.

P.M.	I could omit final sentence.  Don’t wish to do so.  Will consider.



W.	Whatever you say, they will twist it.  Leave it as it was.

		and by adopting







		5.	Hungary : M. Sanders.



A.E.	I find Templer’s arguments compelling.



P.M.	So do I.  Risk of a Chinese Joan of Arc.

							[Enter C.I.G.S., Dawson., 						C.N.S.		

		6.	Trucial Sheikhdoms.			[J.T. and de L.



A.E.	As in memo.



Sw.	Tell old Doms. as before.  Consider posn. of Asiatic Doms.



A.E.	Tell U.S. – not consult them.



C.I.G.S.	400 Levies there : 12 R.A.F. cars &amp; squadrons can support, if needed.



A.E.	Let mil. give us date when they will be ready.

							  [Exit C.O.S. and J.P.L.T.



		7.	Silverman M.P.  Visit to U.S.A.



A.E.	Silverman refused U.S. visa.  Made repns. to U.S. They won’t reverse their decision unless I will say his visit is of vital importance to Anglo-U.S. relations.  I won’t.





		8.	Comm. Economic Conference (resumed).



R.A.B.	Can’t tell Europeans details of a plan.  Tell them our objectives.  Extend E.P.U.  Get them to agree to means of modifying E.P.U. if new U.S. initiative.

	Will have to renew E.P.U.  Get Eur. to try to work out a wider system with us, and be ready to move into it by agreemt. when U.S. are ready.

	Draper will be here on Thursday. Can discuss broadly with him.

	Then memo. for Cab. on Friday.  Can take it with Tourists etc.





		10.	Flood Damage.



A.F.	Statement.  Approved subject to amendment.



R.A.B.	All Exchequer liability.  Now up to £30/40 m. – not counting l.a. expenditure.  Is it really a national disaster.  If so, we must pay up – makg. all these concessions.  £8-10 m. when I left and Fund to £4 m.  £ for £ for addn. of Lynmouth.  Liability has trebled since I left.  Now equals Dankwerts.



M.F.	It is a disaster unprecedented in our history.

	Also pol. pressures are v. strong.



R.A.B.	Para. 13. 2nd alternative goes too far (“in full”).

	Accept H.M.’s general approach : but shall not want to prejudice general settlement.



T.D.	If l.a.’s included at this stage must include all River Bds. (para.12).



M-F.	Para.12 affects only l.a.’s in special diffy.  Any diffies. can be discussed betwn. T.D. &amp; R.A.B./M.F.





		12.	Farm Price Review.



T.D.	Farmers seeking to see Ministers.  Want settlement to-morrow.

	Eggs.  Recommend 4/= no concession.  New and important principle. 

	Believe this price will be profitable to farmers.

	Fixed Commodities.  Offered £14.6M., against £16.9M. envisaged by Cabinet.  Diffces. Remain’g. are milk (we have gone to ½d. meat (3/= per cwt.) &amp; wool.  They ask for ¾d. and 4/=.



	Milk : they will take ½d. in end.  They have a case on wool.

	No cost to Ty.  Bd’s funds are satisfy.  Cost wd. be £800.000 above the £14.6M.  Price guaranteed now 4/6D. : shd. leave £1½M. in fund.

	Market price is rising : now around 4/4D.  Prefer to [raise not reduce] wool rather than mutton.  Agreed.



	Meat.  I cd. give 1/= w’in limits.  But wd. raise row over milk.

	Better stick to it.

	I’m for taking a stand on this.



		Approved.  	M/L. to be consulted on method qua c/living.



</content>
</cab>
