<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/11/0 images: 34-34</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 26(53).				14th April, 1953.



	1.	Egypt.



P.M.	We hoped for Anglo-U.S. foursome – mil. and civil.  U.S. not

		invited to join.

		What next?  Cd. not keep Slim back fr. Australia.

		Brought Brian Robertson home for conversations, and he

		will go instead.

	A.E. wd. prob. have preferred informal approach behind scenes to

		get as many diffies out of way before any public appearance of

		parley.  I believe E. wd. try to get us on run.  I attach

		importce. to formal mtg. &amp; also to mil. participn.  That wd. link

		with U.S. if they join later …….

	talks due to start 27/4.  Announcemt. on 16/4.

	Tel. to Eisenhower.



			General approval.



P.M.	I have made no change in policy.  But I have made a change in

		method.

	Can’t carry A.E. with me on every detail while he is ill.

	Must be allowed to assume responsibility alone.

	One point not to be overlooked.  Mght. accept 3 or 4.000 vice 7.000

		for base.  But I want them to be in uniform &amp; with personal

		arms – so tht. they cdn’t be arrested by police :  cdn’t be 

		molested w’out constituting an act of war.





	2.	Sudan.



H.M.	Tels. re propaganda.  E. does it:  Sud. Govt. doesn’t:  who does the

		counter-propaganda.



S.Ll.	Want to do this:  am going to ask for money for it.

	Blatant E. propaganda helps us a bit.  We must do it covertly.

		Govr. Genl. won’t lend himself to it.  But Prov. Govrs. wd.





	3.	Surrender of Firearms.



M.F.	Many illegally held.  Likely tht. large nos. wd. be surrendered – view

		Police.  Wdn’t. affect good citizen with firearm cert. or those who

		wd. welcome chance to give up firearms they hold improperly.



P.M.	Mention tht. people needing them for protection may apply for 

		certificate.



O.L.	Police will have to let up a little on this.



Sim.	Agree.  Police policy will have to be changed.



O.L.	Must say we hope more favourable consn. will be given to these

		applns.



			Memo. approved.





	4.	House of Lords Reform.



Sal.	Various alternatives.  Now prefer extending Scottish system to

		E &amp; W.  But how wd. you ensure tht. some Labour

		hereditary Peers get elected?  Cd make P.C.’s automatic :

		cd. require only propn. of votes cd. go to own Party.

	Hereditary Peers cd. opt (only once) for H/C. if he so preferred.

	There wd. be life Peers as well – 50% of total membership.

	Exeter’s plan to exclude non-attenders : Sim. has declared it

		unconstitutional.

	Simon’s plan no good because leaves all backwoodsmen in.



P.M.	Use of Prerogative for extraordinary creation?



Sal.	New Peers wdn’t sit except if elected to sit by their fellows.

		Mght. have to make some exceptions e.g. for new

		Ministers.



P.M.	That wdn’t cover 1911 case.



Sal.	But Parlt. Act – that no longer arises.



Sal.	Doubt if it shd. be covered.  I believe H/C. shd. be able to over-ride

		H/L. in last analysis.

	Must get on.  For Simon is pressing to go on with his Bill.

		Don’t wish to have to vote him down.



P.M.	Delaying power shd. be put back to 2 years.  That is a duty of

		Tory Party.



Sal.	V. provocative to go the full 2 years.  Might invite reversal.



			Agreed:    Cab. Cttee. to examine.

			                 L.P., Simonds, Woolton, Swinton, M.F., H.C.,

			                          and M/H., M/Supply with power to co-opt

			                          e.g. L. Boyd.





	5.	Commonwealth Membership.



P.M.	Cttee. to give preliminary consideration – as composed by Swinton.

	Wd. it help if initial work was done by the 3 Junior Ministers?

Sw.	Wd. prefer Cttee. to meet first:  to settle general principles.

		Then we cd. use Junior Ministers to work out detail.

	Must have secret consultns. soon with 3 older Doms.



Sal.	Prefer Swinton to take Chair.  I will sit under him.



O.L.	Not impossible to find a mezzanine floor:  believe we cd.

		persuade Africans to accept.



</content>
</cab>
