<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/11/0 images: 82-82</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 80(53).				18th December, 1953.



	1.	Egypt.		[Exit Watkinson.



P.M.	Tory M.P.’s shd. not accept Nequib’s hospitality while he is 

		abusing us.

	They shd. be restrained.  The other side can go – they are v. this

		country anyhow except when in office.  Play it quietly.



B.H.	W’house Mtg. last night – suggested measures stronger than

		argument e.g. spkg. in country, writing to Press, etc.,  This is

		rumour :  but partly confirmed by what W. said to me this a.m.

		W. believes this is “not v. the Govt.”  Only 1 of them at mtg.

		suggested taking motion off Paper.  Possibility of their

		voting v. Govt., if opportunity arises, is crystallising.

		They wd. have abstained last night, if there had bn a Division.



Al.	The mtg. for “expln.” was a flop.



A.E.	They don’t want to understand.



B.H.	4 or 5 of our side intendg. to go to Egypt.



P.M.	They shd. be told by Ch. Whip, on my behalf, they shd. not accept N.’s

		hospitality.  They cd. go at their own expense.



A.E.	Right if we can stop them all.  Don’t try &amp; fail.

	Boothby wants to go :  shall tell him he can go alone at own expense

		i.e. not with the gang.



P.M.	Prospect wh. I don’t like is :  agreemt., then phased w’drawal under

		E. sneers.  Want a positive plan of re-deployment, regardless of 

		E. views.



A.E.	1724 Cairo. indicates E. have a plan to make diffies. for us before end

		of year – e.g. non-aggression pact with R., or attacks on us in

		Zone.  The first wd. give them neutrality posn., in wh. they wd. 

		say tht. wasn’t open to them to conclude agreemt. contemplatg

		our return in a war with R.  3rd. poss. is measures v. B. subjects

		in E.  If they did that, we shd. bring talks to an end &amp; stand on

		’36 Treaty.

	They may intend this merely to make U.S. flesh creep.

	M’while we take no fresh initiative.

					[Exit  B.H.



	2.	Civil Supply.



R.A.B.	Genl. warning only at this stage.  Consultns. with Dpts. are to come.

	Want substantial cuts before publn. of Estimates so tht. we can present

		a balanced Budget.  Defence – Housing (no. is exceeding 

		target at high subsidy cost to Ty.).

	Can make a saving this year on Stockpiling &amp; C. Defence - &amp; begin

		to shift emphasis in housing to repairs vice new constn.

	Ask for genl. support of Cabt.



W.	Can we examine stock-piles.  V. large figure.  £145 M. is total now.

		Cost of stockpiling wood e.g. is 10% of value because storage

		and turnover.  We are to be putting £33 M. into stock (all

		materials) next year.  All v. a rather remote risk.

	Pause before going further in this direction.



P.M.	Valuable :  but cdn’t it be offset v. Nat. Debt?



RAB.	We cd. save quite a bit on stock-piling.



MF.	Will do my best on C.D. – examining it with Minl. Cttee.



*P.M.	Call on colleagues to support R.A.B. in his effort

			to economy.



RAB.	Interest (in Budget) on Nat. Debt is over £500 M.  Can’t lightly add

		to it.



*P.M.	Duty of every spending Dpt. is to reduce it’s expenditure.





	3.	Food Prices.



Ll.G.	Price increases appd. – to bring total to £220 M.  But now it will be 

		higher.



R.A.B.	Approve Feb. 21 as date for this :  smaller measures viz., butter,

		cheese, beef.

	Leave bread &amp; milk to a later Cabinet, after my return.



Ll.G.	Shall we add pork now – with the minor measures.

		Agreed:   i)    Add pork to butter, cheese &amp; beef.

			       ii)   P’pone bread &amp; milk until RAB returns.



W.	35 pay claims (£300 M.) over next 3 months.



Sw.	i) means only .86.



Ll.G.	And 1d. off eggs will bring it down .5.





	4.	Agricultural Policy.



R.A.B.	Divergency of view betwn Dpts.  Need official examinn. – then 

		reference to F. &amp; A. Cttee.

P.T.	May B/T. come in, at offl. Cttee. because related to imports policy.



Ll.G.	Welcome that.



H.C.	How are talks on Meat Marketg going?



T.D.	Slow :  not hostile :  not v. f’coming.

	They have put in their plan for eggs.

	Campaign in country has waned.  Waitg. for Ministers to make a 

		mistake.



H.C.	Can we accelerate it.  Shd. be ready to bring it in to Price Review.



Ll.G.	Larger families are beginning to consume less e.g. milk.  While

		pensioners are doing well.



Watk.	The allowances are going on television sets, pools etc.,

	Wage claims’ll turn on food prices.  And, after rlways, strike

		threat will be used more lightly.



Sal.	Wd. it make diffce. if farm allowances were paid to wife.



Watk.	It wd. – if it were feasible.



Sw.	Cd. we not produce family budget – in popular style.



R.A.B.	Yes – we will do it.  Viz., to show how much is spent on cigarettes

		etc., as well as food.

				[Exit  Ll.G.



	5.	Teachers’ Superannuation.



F.H.	Fund has bn. in deficit for years.  No review since ’25.  Bad 

		history : originally they were promised non-contriby. pensions.	L.a.’s will agree to 6% - they give that to other employees.

	Teachers are opposed, as always.  They claim tht. it isn’t a fund :

		carried in Budget :  &amp; we are still drawing in more than we pay		out.  No other scheme where rate is varied during service.

	Burnham Cttee. is now reportg.  Shall have to accept its award –

		almost at once.  Cd. be said this (with salary increase) is good

		time to announce increased pension contn.  I agree, if we are

		going to do it at all.

	Saving = £2.3 M.  Agree we can’t p’pone for ever getting into good

		actuarial state.

	But will be v. controversial.  And awkward fr. angle of recruitg

		teachers.  Shall be addg. minor changes they like, but they

		will be ignored.



W.	Discussed at length in H.A. Cttee.  Concluded tht. for reasons of 

		economy alone (not actuarial propriety)  we shd. do it –

		&amp; announce at same time as increase of salary.



J.S.	Endorse F.H.’s view.  Controversial :  unpopular :  but saves £2½ M.

		Must do it now, if at all.



R.A.B.	Posn. of fund – £102 M.  By Mar. ’54 deficiency will have grown to

		£190 M.

	Burnham award will add £8 M. to Ed. Estimates, wh. continue to rise.

	Tax relief will reduce burden on individual, wh. isn’t v. heavy.



M.F.	Got to be done.

			Approved :  as in memo.





	6.	Town &amp; Country Planning Act.



H.M.	Original plan :  State to buy d. rights for £300 M., paid in bonds.

		to recoup, they wd. levy dev. charge.

	We abandoned that.  Decided to leave d. rights with owners :  no

		d. charge :  on restraint of developmt. we are to pay compensn.

		based, not on current value, but on admitted claim under 

		earlier scheme.

	How are these paymts. to be financed?  Ty. say :  fr. annual Votes,

		puttg. into Estimates our guess at amount needed in a given 

		year.

			                 I wd. prefer to charge it 	to Cons. Fund.

		Practical reason :  Bill will pass at end/summer : back-log must

		be paid off soon.  Shd. have to put £25 M. into 	Estimates for ’54.

		There must be big pay-off in 1st. 2 years because of b’log :  prob. 

		£25 M. in ’54 and £35 M. in ’55.  After that the bill will be 

		compar. small.  If we work quickly, as we shd., even more may 

		be needed – and after Suppl. period is over no means of paying it 

		all.  Wd. swell Estimates in unfair way – not really proper to 

		1954/55.

			                 Political reason :  we have damped down 

		controversy on land values.  Risk we shd. revive it by our

		decn. to abandon purchase of d. rights.  Avoided that because 

		desire to damnify l’lord. was balanced by dislike of d. charge.

		Also thght planning shd. not be frustrated by compensn.  Will

		be said tht. this has bn. brght back – revive the old pol. battle on

		land values.

	Argument v. me :  improper to pay w’out assent of Parlt.  Shd. not

		borrow for this.  improper to pay w’out assent of Parlt.  Shd.

		not borrow for this.  But many other such things are paid fr.

		Cons. Fund.  Also top limit is fixed.  Initial £60 M. – then 

		v. small.

	Compromise wd. be to ask Parlt. to vote special fund of £100 M. &amp;

		finance it by annual write-off – as we did with pre-fabs.

		That wd. reduce cost above/line :  also wd. carry it as at any

		rate a quasi-capital commitmt.  Amortise it over period.

RAB.	1)	Need to Submit to Parly. scrutiny &amp; vote sums wh. yield no 

			revenue.

 	2)	Paymt. will involve discretion – and by l.a.’s.  Exchequer money.

			Shd. not be w’drawn fr. Parly. scrutiny.

		Orthodox finance demands that this shd. be taken on Votes.

		I dissented fr. Minister’s plan.  Wanted to keep element of

		d. charge.

	Pol. arguments.  The one way to revive the old controversy wd. be to

		tell Parlt.

…. rest not heard …





	7.	Indian Commissioner in E. Africa.



O.L.	As in memo.



Sw.	Support O.L.  Action quite contrary to agreemt. of Govt. of India on

		transfer of power tht. Commr. in Africa wd. take no part at all

		in local politics.



A.E.	Agree – no alternative.

	Awkward for F.O.  Others wd. like to do it to us.

                  i)	But is 14 day time-limit safe?  A bit short.  Savours of ultimatum.

                  ii)	In written commn. to Nehru, more facts the better:  at least newsreports

		of what Pant has said.



Sw.	On ii) must be careful of some of our sources.

		4 specific instances in memo.



A.E.	Give dates &amp; papers for these.



Sw.	Wd. prefer to leave substantn. to 2nd. round – tho’ must be ready for it





	8.	

CLOSED UNDER THE



FREEDOM OF INFORMATION



ACT 2000



</content>
</cab>
