<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/193/0 images: 32-32</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.Printed for the Cabinet, February, 1928.SECRET.CP. 57 (28)THE CABINET.INDIANIZATION OF THE INDIAN ARMY.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR  WAR ON THE FORM OF COMMISSION TO BE GIVEN TO INDIAN CADETS.In order that no aspect of this question may be overlooked, I draw the attention of my colleagues to the following considerations : 1. King&apos;s Regulations compel the senior combatant officer, including those of His Majesty&apos;s Indian Forces, to take command over all British troops in any station or detachmeut. If an Indian with a King&apos;s Commission is the senior officer present he will take command whether it be as senior subaltern or as senior colonel. Sooner or later a British officer or soldier may refuse to obey a lawful command given in such circumstances and the results may well be disastrous. The regulations should be amended so as to exclude Indians from exercising command over British Army personnel.2. Indians holding King&apos;s Commissions are on the same roster for court-martial duty as British officers. If, when their turn comes, the accused is a British officer or soldier, they must either be allowed to serve or be excluded on one pretext or another. Either course will inevitably lead to difficulties.3. A Dominion Commission is the equivalent of a King&apos;s Commission in that the regulations give a holder of the former no power of command over British troops or of the latter over Dominion troops. If it is necessary to give power of command, local rank is usually given to the British or Dominion officer concerned. It is only logical that the Indian Cadet from Sandhurst should be given &quot;the same type of commission as is now given to New Zealand Cadets, who also go to Sandhurst. At present the Indian with a King&apos;s Commission is automatically given power of command over British troops, whereas the New Zealand officer is not unless it is required for some special reason.4. While I place the above on record I do not press that the commissions to be given in future should at once be altered from King&apos;s Commissions to Dominion Commissions. I think the change should be made if Indianization succeeds and Indian officers are sent out from Sandhurst; if the experiment in Indianization does not succeed the dangers and inconveniences to be expected from the present system will not arise.5. Sir William Birdwood would meet with great difficulties in the Assembly if an announcement were now made of a change in the commissions, and 1 am content to wait a few years until we know wdiat are the prospects of the present plan for Indianization.L. W.-E.The War Office,22nd February, 1928.Copt No. 3 ()(B28/17)   100   2/28   W.O.P.   3G60

</content>
</cab>
