<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/193/0 images: 33-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AjjERICAN DRAFT OF All ARBITRATION TREATY TO REPLACE TH? ANGLO-A^h JC.-.N ARBITRATION TREATYof 1908.Despatch from Sir Austen Chamberlain to Sir E. Howard (&quot;&apos;ashinp:ton).CABINET.COPY NOS J  CRET.D.P. 58 (28)(Circulated by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs).
NORTH AMERICA. February 23, 1928.CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1.[A 1285/154/45] No. 1.Sir Austen Chamberlain to Sir E. Howard (Washington).(No. 2(52.)Sir, Foreign Oj)icc, February 23, 1928.AS I informed your Excellency in my telegram No. 30 of the 20th January last. His Majesty&apos;s Government have been giving very careful consideration to the terms of the draft arbitration treaty which was communicated to you by Mr. Kellogg on the 29th December last. The new text raises points of some diilieulfcy, prominent among which is the danger that, under its terms, the future exercise of our belligerent rights at sea may one clay be seriously restricted by an arbitral decision embodying the views upon this question of the continental school of international jurists. A further difficulty is presented by the stipulation in the American draft that the &quot; special agreement&quot; which is to embody the terms of reference and other essential points relating to a dispute must in each case be subject to the assent of the United States Senate. This provision, which appeared also in the Root-Bryce treaty, assumes a greater importance in the present treaty owing to the absence of any clause excluding from its scope matters which affect &quot; the vital interests, the independence or the honour&quot; of the contracting parties. If disputes involving &quot; vital interests&quot; (other than those specifically excluded) are in future to become a proper subject for arbitration between the Empire and the United States, it would seem important that the facilities for the reference of a dispute to arbitration should be equal on both sides. As the draft stands, however, the United States Senate has the power a power which experience shows it may be expected to exercise inexorably to prevent a recourse to arbitration on a dispute involving some vital American interest, irrespective of any obligations assumed under the treaty and irrespective of the opinion of the American Administration of the day. Moreover the assent of the Senate must presumably be signified by a majority of two-thirds of the Senators present  a provision which finds no counterpart in British parliamentary institutions.I will not conceal from your Excellency that our difficulties in dealing with these and other points raised by the American draft have not been diminished by Mr. Kellogg&apos;s method of springing important proposals upon the world not only without any previous consultation with His Majesty&apos;s Government but to the accompaniment of the maximum possible publicity. Such a method is only fully comprehensible if Mr. Kellogg is primarily preoccupied by the effect of his proposals on the American electorate and only in a lesser degree inspired by the desire to conclude, with the minimum of friction, an arbitration treaty satisfactory to all contracting parties.The method adopted by Mr. Kellogg in this case is precisely similar to that by which the idea of Geneva Naval Conference was launched by the United States Government, although criticism of the &quot; lack of preparation &quot; which preceded that conference has not yet died down cither here or in America. In the present case His Majesty&apos;s Government had an even greater right to expect some measure of consideration from the United States Government seeing that it was only last summer that Mr. Hough ton, as reported in my despatch No. 915 of the 5th July last, enquired on behalf of his Government whether His Majesty&apos;s Government would be prepared to renew the Root-Bryce treaty in its existing form. Since that date we have been proceeding on the not unnatural assumption that the United States Government desired a renewal of the treaty on the old terms. An earlier hint of the real intentions of the United States Government would clearly have been of the utmost value to His Majesty&apos;s Government, particularly when it is remembored that the Franco-American treaty was due for renewal this month and that the Franco-American negotiations could not but exercise an influence on those in which we are about to engage with the United States Government.I write the above for your Excollency&apos;s information only as it is undesirable that you should discuss with Mr. Kellogg the terms or the implications of the &apos; [377 z-1]
draft arbitration treaty until I am in a position to give you more definite instruc-tions as to the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Governments in Great Britain and in the Dominions. Should you however feel&apos;that you yourself, speaking personally and without instructions, could usefully draw Mr. Kellogg&apos;s attention to the difficulties created by treating in this public way problems having so profound an effect on international relations, your Excellency is authorised to mention the subject to the Secretary of State.I am, &amp;c.AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN.

</content>
</cab>
