<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/193/0 images: 68-96</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Properly of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, j Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1928.Copy No.    ^0TO BE KEPT UNDER  LOCK AND  KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.CABINET.RATING REFORM.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.1 CIRCULATE to my colleagues the chapter in the &quot;Liberal Yellow Book &apos;* on Rating, together with comments upon it made by the Treasury, which I endorse. The Liberal diagnosis of the evils is strikingly similar to that contained in the various Treasury papers on the subject, although both sets of studies have proceeded in absolute isolation. The resources of the Ministry of Health and the Treasury have achieved a more precise, elaborate and refined statement of the evils than was possible to unofficial investigators. Nevertheless, apart from its partisanship, the Rating chapter of the l&apos;ello\v Book is a creditable and valuable contribution to a most urgent social and administrative problem.When we leave diagnosis and come to remedies it will. I think, be seen that the proposals now before the Cabinet are immensely superior to those of the Yellow Book. First, they concentrate the relief upon the producers instead of dissipating it over the whole area of the rates. By this means they give a relief of two-thirds instead of one-third to the manufacturers, and they give complete relief to the farmers, instead of a comparatively small modification of the existing burden. Secondly, they avoid the measureless evils which would follow from the Central Government taking upon itself the direct and continuous care of able-bodied unemployed and unemployables and their families.   Such a plan of reopening uncovenantedMOST SECRET. CP. 66 (28).
benefit on an unlimited scale, paid for by the Exchequer, would make the House of Commons a continuous cockpit of Poplarism; and the Government of the day would either spend Hoods of public money pandering to Socialist sentiment, or else would be abused with many lively instances as harsh towards suffering. Thirdly, we provide adequate securities for economy in local administration and inducements to good housekeeping, which protect the Exchequer from undue demands. Fourthly, we provide a coherent and progressive scheme for readjusting the rate burden in accordance with the movements of population and of labour, and ensure an ever closer approximation between the needs and the resources of any given area at any given time. Fifthly, the Liberal proposal makes no suggestion for finance, except that  m 40 should be cut from national defence, thus mutilating all three fighting services and rendering them incapable of discharging their minimum functions. Or alternatively, or in addition, they propose large increases of direct taxation on Death Duties and Supertax, which would certainly be extremely detrimental to the prosperity and saving power of the nation already flagging under its burdens. We, on the other hand, meet the cost of our reforms by a proposal which, apart from its justice and comparative painlessness, claims the powerful support of the Mining and Railway interests.March 1st. 1928.W. S. C.
&quot; BRITAIN&apos;S INDUSTRIAL FUTURE.&quot;Notes on Chapter XXXI REFORM  OF  THE  RATING  SYSTEMfThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] MOST SECRET.
2(1) The first three pages of this Chapter present a somewhat less complete indictment of the present system of rating industry than that con-tained in CP. 8 (28). It does not bring out the fundamental causes of rate inequalities, viz., the growth of transport facilities and the development of the company system of ownership which have led to a considerable degree of segregation of the population into rich and poor communities; the latter mainly industrial with high social needs and exceptionally high rates, the former largely residential or commercial with smaller social needs and medium or low rates. Nor does the Chapter show how the system exercises a constant pressure towards the actual removal of industries to new areas with all the economic loss and suffering involved.
CHAPTER XXXI REFORM OF THE RATING SYSTEM 1.   The Disastrous Effects of the Present System (h) On Industry and business on tiie test of the injury done to industry it is our system of local rating, much more than our national taxation, which is open to severe criticism. Rates, except in so far as they are expended on services directly beneficial to the ratepayer, operate as a heavy (id valorem tax on houses, on factory buildings, on fixed capital equipment generally. For poor-relief, public health, education, and other objects of local expendi-ture we exact contributions from our industries, not in proportion to the profits they make, but in proportion to the amount of fixed capital which they employ.. This is an extraordinarily vicious principle; so vicious that we should hardly tolerate it if immemorial usage did not blind our eyes to its significance. It penalises enterprise and capital development. It puts a premium on doing things in ways which require only a small plant to the detriment of ways which require a large one.A business must pay its rates whether it earns any profits or not; it must therefore include an allowance for rates in the prices which it charges. Thus rates, unlike income-tax, enter directly into the costs of production, raising the cost of living, and diminishing the competitive power of our industries. Our industrial leaders are constantly asserting, and with truth, that local rates are now, by reason of their effect on selling price, a serious handicap to our exports.Rates are now so heavy the average rate in the   of assessable value 1 has approximately doubled since 1913 (6s. 8frf. in 1913-14 and 12,s. 5hd. in 1926-7).&apos; that the objections to them on the ground of the vicious principle they embody are of great practical importance. Not only are rates heavy; their burden is spread most unequally between different industries and districts. The depression of the exporting industries during the last few years has led to abnormally heavy expenditure on poor-relief, and correspondingly heavy rates in those districts where the exporting industries are centred. Thus the very industries which are the worst hit and have the greatest difficulties to overcome are by reason of the vicious incidence of rating subjected to the heaviest deterrents.   In just those districts where&apos; The value of lands and buildings has not risen since the War in proportion to the increase in the cost of living, with the result that on the average assessable value did not increase between 1013-14 and 192&amp;-7 by more than about 20 per cent.- Rates collected in 1913-14 amounted to  1 18s. lid. per head of population and in 192G-7 to JK-1 2..[17271] b 2
there is the most unemployment, and where it is therefore most desirable that new industries should be established, a special discouragement is extended to any manufacturer who is looking out for a site for a new works.The Report of the Balfour Committee on Industry and Trade has published some striking examples. For instance (figures given by the President of the Crucible Steel Makers&apos; Association):Cost of rates per ton of crucible steel on actual output :June 30, 1914  . . .      3*-. per tonJune 30, 1924  . . .    21*. per tonCost per ton if working full capacity :June 30, 1924   . . .      6s. Sd. per tonThis example well illustrates the radical defect of local rates as a tax on industry, that the greater the difficulties of a trade, the heavier is the burden per unit of output.In his Presidential Address before the Incorporated Accountants&quot; Conference (September 29. 1927), Mr. Thomas Keens quoted the following figures, supplied to him by incorporated accountants, relating to shipbuilding and coal-mining:1. In a particular shipbuilding yard the rates per vessel built in 1913 were  268, in 1926  3,182, and the corresponding figures per ton dead-weight were 8id. and 7s. 5d.2. In a second case the total rates per vessel built in 1912-13 were  89 55. with a total rate deadweight per ton of 3d., and in 1922-3 the figures were  2,161 and 5.*. 6-Jrf.3. In another yard the rates per vessel in 1914 were  246, or 6fr/. per ton: in 1924-5 the figures were  1.850 per vessel, or 4.*. Q^d. per ton.4. In coal-mining in the year 1925-6 the cost of rates per ton varied in different parts of the country from Id. to Gd. per ton.In the case of cotton spinning, the Chairman of Joshua Hoyle &amp; Sons has stated (November 1927) that in their case rates have increased from 7.&apos;. pre-war to 14.*., 15.*., and 17.*. in the  , whilst at the same time their mills have been assessed at 100 per cent, on their pre-war value; nor is any abatement allowed when these mills are working short time. It is easy to see what a heavy burden this means per lb. of yarn spun in present conditions.In the case of iron, coal, and steel, the burden of local rates at present and as compared with pre-war, may be seen in Table 37 on p. 436.Doubtless these instances are mostly extreme cases due to part-time working of plant situated in a necessitous area. There are many types of industry on which the burden of rates is relatively trifling.   But it is the
TABLE 37LOCAL RATES EFFECT ON COST OF PRODUCTION(Figures supplied by a prominent N.E. Coast Iron, Coal, andSteel Co?nj)any)	Hates per ton.	Selliiuf Price /*-/- ton.	1 Per cent.Coal. dune 1014..... June 1027: On plant 15-20 years old On modern plant ....	s.    d. 2 9-8 9-8	s.   d. 12   0 f.o.b. 13   0 &apos;,, :  13   0   ,,	1 :i9 6-28 6-28Coke. dune 1014..... dime 1927: On plant 15-20 years old On modern plant ....	3-6 1   6-5 1   5-6	14   6 at ovens 14   6 14   6	207 10-6* -10 11iron. dune 1914..... dune 1927: On plant 15-20 years old On modern plant ....	65 -1   4-.S 2   1-7	60   0 70   0 70   0	no 3-37 306Sled Plates. dune 1014.....182 dune 1927: On plant 15-20 years old    .      . j     6   3 On modern plant ....       406		120   0 d/d N.E. Coast 162   6 162   6	1-40 3-80 2-49Steel Angles. June 1014      ..... June 1027: On plant 15-20 years old    .      . j On modern plant	1   79 5 105 4   2-5	1 115   0 152   6 152   6	1-44 3-85 2-76N.B. The rates as shown for each article are cuniulativo, i.e. they include tho rates paid on tho previous articles made by the same company, which aro its raw materials. Tho 1927 assessments have been fixed since the slump set in, but are considered too high and may be the subject of appeal.inequality in the incidence of the burden and the tendency of rates at the present time to fall most heavily, as between industries, on those which are least able to bear them, which constitute the most formidable indictment of the system.
Nor is such inequality limited to tho field of industry. Rates are also divided most unequally between shopkeepers, financial institutions, and professional men, to the great detriment of the first-named. Rates on lands and premises grew up historically at a time when the ownership or occupa-tion of lands and premises was the best rough-and-ready test of capacity to pay. But at the present time our rating system, regarded as an attempt at measuring either capacity to pay or benefit received, may be&apos;said, within the field of industry, agriculture, and business, to have broken down entirely.To relieve enterprise, therefore, from these burdens and inequalities, or at least to mitigate them, is the most pressing task of financial statesmanship.(b) The Burden on the Working ClassesNor is it only on industry that the burden of rates falls injuriously. The incidence of rates on individuals and families is even more unjust. In the case of the working man with a large family the rates may consume nearly 10 per cent, of his income, if his children are to.be housed with the barest minimum of decency. In the case of the rich man they will usually amount to less than 1 per cent, of income. So far from being graded in accordance with ability to pay, rates press most heavily on those least able to bear them.It is evident that a policy of reducing the income-tax, whilst at the same time increasing the burdens of the ratepayer, is a most potent method for transferring burdens from the rich to the poor. Yet this has been in fact the policy of Mr. Churchill. In 1925 he took Qd. off the income-tax. In 1926. in order to avoid raising the income-tax to its previous figure, various expenses were thrust off the National Exchequer on to the rates. In particular the tightening-up of the regulations with regard to granting , Unemployment Insurance benefit and to providing grants in aid of schemes of work for the unemployed involved an increase in expenditure from rates, which, in Manchester alone, came to  1.500 a week, or the equivalent of a 3c?. rate. &quot;Economies&quot; which took the form of shifting burdens with respect to the tuberculous war-pensioners from the taxpayer to the rate-payer and similar measures by the President of the Board of Education brought the total increase of Manchester rates in the single year, 1926, clue to &quot; economy &quot; by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, to 5-22f/. in the  .-This year the same misguided policy has been continued by raiding the Road Fund for the benefit of the Exchequer, instead of using its abundance to diminish road-expenditure from the rates, and by the pxwisions of the Unemployment Insurance Bill which is before Parliament as we write.We think that a reversal of this reactionary policy and a far-reaching reform of our rating system, with a view to the mitigation of the anomalies and injustices which we have here set forth, should be a leading feature of the programme of the Liberal Party.
(2) While it is a fact that shopkeepers pay rates in proportion to their income on a higher scale than financial institutions and professional men, one might point out what an exceptional advantage shopkeepers derive from the existence of an organized community in a compact form. A manufac-turer can successfully start a factory in the open country with his labour drawn from miles around, but not so the shopkeeper.But, in any case, the burden of rates does not stop where it first rests. The shopkeepers of a town are all liable to the same rates and undoubtedly pass cn the charge to their consumers. The manufacturer, on the other hand, is in competition with those working in other areas and abroad. If his rates are high he has only his ground landlord with whom he can share the extra charge, and if, as is usually the case, he is his own ground land-lord and bought the land before the rates rose so high, there is no relief in this direction. No one ever heard of a shopkeeper being forced to move outside a town because of the heavy burden of rates.(3) CP. 8 (28) aims ultimately at complete relief and in the meantime removes all inequalities in the rating of industry due to variation in the poundage of rates between one area and another. Other inequalities are reduced by nearly two-thirds. The Liberal scheme for a much greater net cost to the taxpayer affords a much smaller reduction of these inequalities very roughly a flat reduction of a little over one-third.(4) One of the worst features of democratic government is the tendency for political power to become more and more divorced from financial responsibility, with the result that candidates for election are tempted to offer benefits to the many at the expense of the few. The danger of unduly iiberal expenditure arising from this tendency is far more serious in local than in national administration, owing to the closer and more personal relation between the local council and its electorate, to their lack of appreciation of the true effects of public expenditure on the economic position of the working classes, and to the smaller influence exercised by their less highly trained permanent staff. It would be unsafe, therefore, to carry the system of graduation of taxation to anything like the same point
&apos; Not printed.that it has reached in national taxation even if it would be equitable to do so.In considering the equity of such a graduation it must liot be over-looked that, unlike national expenditure, local expenditure is in the main directly beneficial to the working classes. The English method of rating on net rental instead cf gross has, in fact, resulted in a certain amount of graduation owing to the larger allowance for repairs in the case cf the cheaper houses. This has now been systematised by the Rating and Valuation Act into a definite scale of abatements ranging from 40 per cent, for houses rented at  10 or less to one-sixth per cent, for houses with rents above  100. There are distinct signs that fov the smaller type of authority even this small degree of graduation, covpled with the effects of the coni-pounding system, is beginning to lead to extravagant administration, most of all in regard to the services of poor relief and education, where the opportunities of expenditure are most extensive. This is one of the main reasons for placing these services in the hands of county councils, who are less liable to electoral pressure than smaller authorities.(5) The charge that the present Government has transferred burdens from the taxpayer to the ratepayer has been dealt with in a separate note.* Put briefly, the answer is that if allowance is made for all forms of national expenditure which operate to relieve the rates, the charge on national funds has increased in the last three years much more than the rates.
TABLE 38LOCAL AUTHORITIES, ENGLAND AND WALES NET EXPENDITURE 1924-5(In millions of  s)	Exchequer Giants.	i Sates.	Total.(I) Education..... (2) Public Libraries ....	3868	31-64 1-39	70-32 1-39Totals of (1) and (2) .	38-68	3303	71-71(3) Maternity and Child Welfare (4) Tuberculosis     and     Venereal Diseases.      .... (5) Lunacy and Mental Deficiency   .	-65 1-85 1-43	-70 1-27 5-83	1-35 312 7-20Totals of (3) to (5)	3-93	7-80	11-73(6) Housing and Town Planning	749	1-29	8-78(7) Relief of the Poor	1.20	28-56	9.9-76Totals of (I) to (7)	51-30	70-68	121-98(S) Highways and Bridges	1298	3051	4349(9) Sewage and Refuse Services (10) Hospital and Medical Services   . (11) Public Parks. Baths, etc. (12) Water-supply    .... (13) Cemeteries.....	-30 -44 -19 -06 -01	13-77 5*56 3-90 -57 -40	1407 6-00 4-09 -63 -41Totals of (9) to (13)	1-00	24-20	25-20(14) Police and Police Stations . (15) Administration of Justice  . (16) Fire Brigades     ...	909 02 01	903 -62  . 1-77	1812 -64 1-78Totals of (14) to (16)    .	912	11-42	20-54(17) Other specific services. (IS) General administrative expenses and unallocated	1-66J	5-70 12-93	7-36 1293Grand totals .	76-06*1:	153-08f5	2291515* Excluding Exchequer grants referred to in the next footnote.t Including Exchequer grants totalling  5*36 millions, and foes, tolls, rents, ete., totalling  5-34 millions, which were not allocated to any one service.% Including about  124,000 for Exchequer grants to trading services showing a surplus, g Net figure after deducting about  2,350,000 surplus on certain trading services.Compiled from Eighth Annual Beport of the Ministry of Health, 1926-7 Wind, 293S of 1927], p. 227. L[17271]C
2.   How Rates are spent in the year ending March 31, 1925 (the last year for which detailed figures are available), the net expenditure of Local Authorities in England and Wales 1 on income account (i.e. after deducting receipts in respect of income-earning services) was roughly  229,000,000, of which rather more than one-third (36 per cent.) was paid for from Exchequer Grants and the balance out of local rates. The main headings are given in Table 38 on p. 438.The percentages of the rates received in 1924-5 spent on the principal groups of local expenditure were as follows :TABLE 39LOCAL AUTHORITIES-PROPORTIONATE EXPENDITURE OUT OF RATES ON VARIOUS SERVICES, 1924-5Per cent.Education (including Libraries)        .........21*other Health Services; Lunacy and Mental Deficiency.....5*0Housing and Town Planning..........08Eelief of the Poor    ............1S-4-454Highways and Bridges (excluding Lighting)....... 196Sewage and Refuse Services and Preventive Health Services    ....   156Administration of Justice, Police, Fire Brigades......7&apos;miscellaneous.............3-general Administrative Expenses, etc.      ........8-3-350Total......1000Extracted from the Eighth Annual Report of the Ministry of Health, 1926-7, p. 109.Broadly speaking, we might describe Education, &quot;other&quot; Health Services, Flousing, and Poor Relief as Social Services. These amounted in 1924-5 to 45-4 per cent, of the whole. Highways and Bridges (19-6 per cent.) are mainly a central, as distinguished from a local, service. The rest (35 per cent.) may be called Local Administrative Services.The total rates collected rose from  142,000,000 in 1924-5 to  147,500,000 in 1925-6 and  159,500,000 in 1926-7. The increase of  12,000,000 in 1926-7 over the previous year was mainly due to the extra expenditure imposed on Boards of Guardians as a result of the general All tho llgures given above relate to England and Wales only, since we have not been able to obtain comparable llgures for Scotland. Detailed figures for Scotland have not been published for any year later than 1910-20. Probably about 10 per cent, should bo added to tho above figures to obtain the total for Great Britain as a whole.
(6) It will be observed from pages 22 and 25 that the distinction between Social Services and Local Administrative is intended to be the basis of a division of the rates, the former levied over the county area and the latter over the smaller districts. From this point of view, it seems difficult not to put hospitals along with maternity and child welfare into the class of Social Services, and it would certainly be necessary to allocate &quot; General Administrative Expenses &quot; between the two groups and highways. On this basis the proportion falling in the class of Local Administrative Services might be reduced to little more than 25 per cent.[17271] c 2
(7) The question of national or local administration of any service is one of great difficulty. From the point of view of efficiency, the respective Government Departments concerned could, no doubt, make out an excellent case for taking over the direct administration of education, police and the main roads, while there has been recent experience of the improvement effected in certain cases by the substitution of Government officials for elected Boards of Guardians. Yet such a centralisation of functions would be wholly opposed to British traditions, it would add greatly to the com-plicated machine of central government and it could hardly fail to increase expenditure. People are prepared to put up with imperfections when they are themselves responsible for the business of administration and for meeting the cost. Moreover, a vast amount of valuable voluntary service giving satisfaction as well as useful training to those carrying it out would be lest.And however efficient were the national system of administration, there would be lacking that closeness of touch with local interests and aspira-tions, that adaptability to the wide range of circumstances of different localities and to the varying mental and moral standards and tribal peculiarities of their inhabitants which is the glory of our system of lecal government. National administration is inevitably based on rules and regulations, and in all vast organisations each unit of the machine naturally tends to seek safety in rigid adherence to those rules.For no service are these considerations so important as for that of poor relief. It is not a precise and easily defined service, such as the upkeep of a road, the maintenance of law and order or the teaching of a child. Destitution arises from a multitude of causes, and if the public charity is to be dispensed without waste or hardship and with good, and not bad, reactions on the character of the recipient, each case requires individual treatment by someone in touch with local conditions who understands the local mentality. It is true that a considerable measure of success has been achieved by the nominated Board of Guardians at West Ham and else-where, but it should be remembered first that they succeeded a regime of appalling mismanagement, and, secondly, that they stepped into a local organisation enjoying far more liberty of action than they could have had
strike and the coal trade dispute. The actual outgoings, however, payable out of the rates were another  9,000,000 higher than this, the excess being discharged by temporary borrowings.That every effort should be made to secure that the ratepayers receive full value for their expenditure is obvious. This can only be achieved by a close control, by the Local Authorities who are responsible, over the estimates and disbursements. We come now to proposals for relieving the burden of the rates and the inequities of its distribution along lines which aim at preserving the existing incentives to local responsibility.3.   Proposals for Immediate reform the evils of the present rating system mainly arise from extending a method which probably achieves rough justice and reasonable elliciency as a means of providing for Local Administrative Services to an increasing volume of Social Services and to the greatly increased expenditure on noads necessitated by new methods of transport which are more and more a central, rather than a local, service. Reform must come, therefore, from disentangling the three types of service. When this has been done, we can then redistribute the burden between local and central taxation and between different categories of ratepayers, to the great advantage both of justice and of efficiency.Our proposals fall under two main heads. &quot;We shall first deal with the readjustment of burdens as between rates and taxes, which can be carried out comparatively easily. We shall then turn to consider certain highly desirable reforms in the assessment and collection of local rates, some of which will involve difficult and complex changes.4.   The Readjustment of Rates and Taxes(1) The Burden of Unemployment a National Responsibility. There can be no doubt that the aggravation of the evils of the rating system which has characterised the last few years has been primarily due to so substantial a part of the burden of supporting the families of the able-bodied poor, in other words, of the unemployed having been thrown on to the Poor Law. The Poor Law, whilst it has more than once drifted into such responsibilities, was never designed to deal with problems of protracted unemployment due to national causes, and the attempt to make it fulfil such functions is largely responsible for its present difficulties and failures.Moreover, it is important that such relief as can be afforded by the Exchequer should go in the first instance to the necessitous areas, and that these areas should be aided out of proportion to the relief to those areas which are not suffering from similar burdens.
A beginning has been made in the policy of treating unemployment as a national responsibility by the system of State Insurance. But we are convinced, for the reasons given above and for other reasons to follow, thai the time has now come to go further, and for the State to take over from Local Authorities and administer itself the whole system of out-relief to the able-bodied poor. This could then be co-ordinated with the&quot; existing machinery for administering Unemployment insurance, which is already centrally administered. There would also be the advantage of relieving the political pressure which has been brought to bear on certain notorious Boards of Guardians to give very high rates of out-relief. At the same time a substantial burden which is mainly due to national causes would be removed from the rates.We believe that considerable incidental advantages would be gained from this reform. At present legislation in respect of unemployment is largely concerned, in effect, with deciding what part of the burden shall fall on the Insurance Fund and what part shall be borne locally. Thus any stiffening up of the conditions of the Insurance Fund, which may lie very desirabfe in itself and indeed necessary if the proper principles of insurance are to be observed, has at present the effect of breaking down the Poor Law system at the same time that the Insurance system is strengthened. The real question should be how far the charges arising out of unemployment and the burden of relieving the families of the unemployed represent an insurable risk which it is proper to charge on the Insurance Fund, and how far they represent exceptional and abnormal outgoings due to national causes not contemplated by the Insurance scheme which should be shouldered as a national responsibility and paid for by the Exchequer. We hope, therefore, that the reform we recommend will not only relieve the burden of rates where relief is most needed, but will also allow a great improvement in our methods of handling unemployment as a whole.(2) Roads and Road Fund. We think that the division of the expenditure on roads, both classified and unclassified, between the Local Authorities and the Exchequer should be reconsidered, with a view to throwing a much larger proportion than at present on an augmented Road Fund. All the principal roads of the country now serve a far wider public than the inhabitants of the particular locality through which a road passes. The coming of motor traffic has made it impossible to regard any roads in the country as existing simply to serve local needs. We believe that greater efficiencjr, as well as a relief of the rates, could be secured by increasing central responsibility for the development and maintenance of the roads. That part of the expenditure on roads, especially in towns, which ought to remain a local service, might reasonably be incorporated with what we have called Local Administrative Services/On the basis of distribution by which the Road Fund contributes 50 per cent, to the maintenance and improvement of Class I roads,
1561as part of a national machine. Moreover, they took over the complete service of poor relief, which brought them into touch with every phase of destitution, whereas the present proposal is to place on the State the responsibility for the relief of the able-bodied only.For all practical purposes the State has been attempting to discharge this responsibility for the last five or six years by means of uncovenanted benefit of unlimited duration. That benefit was intentionally fixed on the low side, with the result that Boards of Guardians found it necessary to supplement it in many cases, and yet it has led to serious abuse. Had the benefit been fixed at a level which would have taken the problem of the able-bodied entirely out of the poor law, the abuse must have been vastly greater. With great difficulty the Government has succeeded in putting an end to that system by the Unemployment Act of last session. It has provided in its place an insurance scheme under which everyone capable of work and desirous of obtaining it can receive benefit up to 74 weeks in every two years if he is employed for the remaining 30 weeks. To go back on this decision and to graft again on to the insurance scheme a new and more generous dole would be a disaster.This dees not mean that the present system of Boards of Guardians is satisfactory. Far from it. If national administration is open to objection on account of its rigidity and uniformity, the present system is at fault from its extreme variety of standard and charge. The golden mean would appear to lie in adopting the county as the unit of administration, and it is pro-posed to reduce such variations of charge as would remain between county and county by a suitable adjustment of the new grant.The most difficult problem of all, the moral reform of the unemployable, has still to be tackled. The pre-war poor law system made some slight attempt at it, the post-war dole system ignored it. Possibly the larger poor law authority of the future may be able to improve on the repressive methods of the workhouse system by the establishment of labour training colonies.(8) With the development of motor traffic and the growth of the cost of the roads, it is inevitable that a gradually increasing proportion should be found from motor taxation.   But it is hard to believe that proper
economy would be secured under a system by which a locality received from the Road Fund  3 for every  1 it spent itself. Where County Councils repay to urban authorities the cost of maintaining certain roads, they have the advantage of knowing their own cost of maintaining the same road up to the boundary of the urban authority, and, moreover, the urban authority always has it in mind that the County Council may take over the work if the charge be excessive. Neither check would be available to the Road Department.The transfer of certain &quot;routes nationales &quot; to the State would operate most unfairly between one area and another. It may be reasonable to relieve Huntingdon of the whole cost of the Great North Road within its boundary, for most of the traffic thereon is through traffic, but the same road, when it enters London or any large town, carries a very high propor-tion of purely local traffic.The best solution would appear to lie in transferring to the county the charge for all roads (outside county boroughs) other than residential streets, in maintaining the classification grants in the administrative counties at their present percentages and in merging all other maintenance grants into the new formula grant, adding from time to time such surplus revenue of the Road Fund as was not required for these classification grants or earmarked for improvement schemes.
25 per cent, to that of Class II roads (33 per cent, as from 1927-8), and nothing to unclassified roads, the position in 1926-7 may be estimated as is shown in Table 40. It should be noted, however, that as exact figures are not available, this table represents only an estimate though the best tliiit can be made on existing data.TABLE 40PRESENT EXPENDITURE ON ROADS IN GREAT BRITAIN.1926-7(In millions of  s)		Local		Road Fund.	Authorities.	Total.Class I Roads.....	.    1H*	&apos;    OA	21	4&quot;	12&quot;	16	.      ,     .      ...    21f	15i	18	IS	37	55* This is slightly more than 50 per cent, of the total, because expenditure on certain main trunk roads, in respect of which a higher percentage is payablo out of the Road Fund, is also included. I Estimated special grants in respect of rural roads.Compiled from the Annual Reports on the Road Fund and of the Ministry of Health.We recommend that in future an augmented Road Fund should bear 75 per cent, of the cost of Class I roads, 50 per cent, of Class II roads, and 35 per cent, of the unclassified roads. On the basis of our estimate of the 11(26-7 figures, expenditure would then be distributed as follows:TABLE 41PROPOSED REDISTRIBUTION OF EXPENDITUREON ROADS	(In millions of  s)	local		Road Fund.	Authorities.	Total.	......151		21	......S	8	16	......6i	113	IS	30	25	55Except in the case of the great trunk roads of the country, which probably ought in any case to be taken over by the Central Road Authority, such a proposal need not involve any new administrative machinery. At present it is not uncommon for County Councils to arrange with District [17271] D
Councils for the latter to undertake the maintenance of main roads passim&apos; through their districts, at the cost of the County Councils. Similarly, the Ministry of Transport, or its successor, could often arrange for the actual work of maintenance, in respect of the traffic routes for which central funds had assumed the main financial responsibility, to be carried out locally as heretofore.(3) Grants in A id Local. Generally speaking, the present rating system is a very inexpedient method of paying for Social Services. Since many Social Services are best administered locally, a sufficient part of the charge must remain on the rates to secure local efficiency and responsibility. The present distribution of the burden of local expenditure between local rates and grants in aid from the Central Government is, however, often arbitrary.- -The principle of transferring a. portion of the cost of locally administered Services to national taxation has been already recognised, anil has been adopted in recent years on an increasing scale. At the present time, grants of 50 per cent, of the cost are given in the case of infant welfare work and tuberculosis work, and grants averaging over 50 per cent, for education. The grants have had the advantage of relieving the rates, while there has remained on the Local Authority sufficient responsibility to (9) ensure economical administration. Further, the control gained by the Government owing to its power to withhold the grant has been of great benefit in screwing up laggard Local Authorities to a higher standard of efficiency, and of securing economy all round.We regard, therefore, the general principle of grants in aid of local Services as a proved success, and believe that they could be extended in such a way as to transfer a further substantial burden from rates to taxes without undermining local responsibility.It will not be difficult to find further items suitable for transfer, once(10) an extension of the principle is admitted; for a very large part of local expenditure on Social Services is already virtually outside the discretion of local bodies and is prescribed by Acts of Parliament or by administrative direction from Whitehall. We do not enter here into the difficult and technical questions of the choice in particular cases between block grants and percentage grants.(11) anticipate that under these three proposals not less than a third ofthe present burden of the rates&apos; say  50,000,000 per annum, or  55.000,000 including Scotland would be found suitable, under one head or another, for transfer to the Central Exchequer. It would, of course, be difficult or impossible, both on financial and on administrative grounds, for so considerable a reform to be carried out in a single year. A Chancellor of the Exchequer should aim, we think, at removing from the rates the responsibility for supporting the families of the unemployed with the least Wo are assuming that tho 1926 rate of expenditure was abnormal, and that tho existing expenditure from the rates in England and Wales is . 150,000,00(1 in round llgures.
(9) Reference has been made under (4) to the difficulty of securing due economy in local administration. It has been admitted in many quarters (cf. Mr. W. Graham&apos;s efforts to find another basis) that a system of paying   for   is conducive to unnecessary expenditure. Government Departments may attempt to prevent extravagance, but it is impossible to do this properly without duplicating the work of the authority.(10) It is difficult to reconcile this statement with the actual variations shown in the expenditure of local authorities per unit of service.(11) The transfer of charges to the State, of course, reduces rates generally, but it is an expensive method of giving relief to industry, which only pays about one-quarter of the rates.[17271]
(12) The fear of doing anything for a landlord is, of course, the &quot;bete noire&quot; of the authors of this volume. As far as rates on buildings are concerned, it is generally agreed that the incidence of rates like that of any other tax on a manufactured article is upon the consumer, i.e., the occupier. For land, the ultimate incidence is on the landlord, but the process may be long delayed by leases and custom. As most industrial property is not rented, there can be no question in such cases of benefiting landlords.The rating of site values is too big a question to discuss in this connection. Urban land undoubtedly contributes indirectly under the present system on its monopoly value and there may be a fair case for some further discrimination against it, but any such scheme is hardly likely to find favour with Parliament as at present constituted.
possible delay. The other transferences proposed should be coupled with, and made the opportunity for securing, certain other fundamental reforms in our rating system outlined below.We should add that steps might be necessary to secure that the various reliefs recommended above should accrue to the occupier, and not to the landlord. In the long run the introduction of the principle of rating site-values should prove an important safeguard. But to meet the immediate problem it would be necessary to make certain express provisions&quot;.5.   The Reform of the Rating System.(1) The Rating of Site Values. A very substantial alleviation of the burden imposed by the present system of rating both upon industry and upon working-class housing can be obtained by transferring to the site value of land a fair share of the rates now imposed upon the composite value of the land and the buildings which it carries, and usually paid by the occupier, whether owner or tenant. The existing assessment is based upon the letting value of the whole hereditament, and does not discriminate-between that part of the value which is due to the buildings and that part which is due to the site. The value of the site results mainly from the presence and activity of the community, and is therefore a peculiarly suitable subject for taxation for the needs of the community. Yet the owner of the site, where potential wealth is increased by every improvement, is not called upon to make any direct contribution: and he may actually find it financially advantageous to leave his land undeveloped, or to place obstacles in the way of the healthy development of industry or of housing, because the burden of rates is charged upon the actual yield of the site, and not upon its real value, and is, in any case, usually paid not by the landlord but by the tenant. We believe this arrangement to be fundamentally unjust: and we are satisfied that a redistribution of burdens such as would place a fair share upon site values would form a very solid contribution to the relief of industry, besides helping towards a more healthy and economical solution of the housing problem, which is itself an obstacle in the way of industrial revival.This reform has long been an accepted element in Liberal policy. The arguments in its favour are set out in Towns and the Land, and we need not elaborate them here.We recommend that the principles embodied in Sir John Simon&apos;s Rating of Land Values Bill of 1924 should at once be put into operation, and that Rating Authorities in towns and urban districts should be empowered to assess separately the value of every site and of the buildings and other capital equipment standing upon it. The value of the site should be taken as being the price which it would fetch if sold as an unencumbered site in the open market, whether occupied or unoccupied at the date of assessment, and the basis of assessment should be computed at
5 per cent, of this capital value. A gradually increasing portion of the burden of rates should thus be transferred from buildings and improvements to the unimproved value of sites.(13) (2) Compounded Rates. We think it important that in all cases where rates are &quot; compounded,&apos;* i.e. are paid by the landlord and included in the rent of a tenement, it should be obligatory upon the landlord to present in his demand-note a clear statement of the amount charged respectively for rent and for rates. This seems to us to be desirable for two reasons: first, in order to bring out the real incidence of rates; and secondly, in order to bring home to the tenant how much he is actually paying for the upkeep of social and administrative services, and thus to give him a clearer sense of his civic responsibilities. This would be especially necessary under any system of site-value rating, as a means of showing how far these rates were passed on to the occupant.(3) Rating Areas. At present our Local Government is a mass of anomalies and intricacies due to long-past historical origins. Over-lapping, inefficiency, complications, and inequity exist everywhere, due to the variety of local government areas and to their failure to correspond to the facts and necessities of to-day. Yet local jealousies and local interests are so strong that it is exceedingly difficult to secure the needed reforms and rearrangements particularly because in any redistribution certain areas are bound to lose, as probably in equity they ought, in order that others may gain. It is obvious that any attempt to average out burdens must in some cases leave them heavier than they were.(14) We are strongly of the opinion, therefore, that a change which will have the effect of greatly reducing the aggregate of local burdens should be made the opportunity for carrying through a thorough-going reform of Local Government areas. In the case of the * Administrative Services in particular, efficiency and convenience of operation may require the definition of new areas, which should probably be County or Regional Areas for some purposes, and should preserve something like the existing district, municipal, and parish autonomy for others.The evils arising from the unequal distribution of the burden of rates could be sensibly diminished by increasing the rating area in the case of most of the social services to an area not less than that of a County or County Borough. The Education Rate already approximates to a County Rate. It is probable that the Poor Rate should also be averaged in future over County Areas, as indeed was proposed under the earlier version of the present proposals of the Ministry of Health but abandoned subsequently in face of local opposition.We must not enter further in this report into an exceedingly complicated problem. But we think that this is pre-eminently a case where one reform can be made the opportunity for another.* This should apparently be &apos;&apos; Social Services.&quot;
(13) It is somewhat amusing to find a Committee containing such high legal authority as Sir John Simon recommending a change in the law which was, in fact, made by the Statement of Rates Act, 1919! It is under-stood that the Act is not, in fact, being obeyed in very many cases, mainly because it is nobody&apos;s business to enforce it. The object in view is undoubtedly most desirable.(14) This policy of extension of areas is being followed in CP. 8 (28). The approval of the proposal to adopt the county area for poor law and education is important.
(15) The suggestion for a division of rates into a Social Rate and an Administrative Rate is put forward to permit of a greater adjustment of the former to ability to pay. The dangers of further graduation of rates, especially rates for social services, have already been referred to at (4).(16) The distinction between the two groups would in practice be a distinction between the county rate and the rate for local purposes.
(4) Differentiation and Graduation of Rates. We have argued above that the evils of the rating system are at their worst in the case of industrial, agricultural, and business lands and premises, and of working-class dwellings. It would, therefore, be desirable, if it were practicable, to concentrate as much of the relief as can be afforded by the Central Exchequer on these classes of ratepayers. We should like, that is to say, to introduce into our rating system, as we have done in the case of our income-tax system, measures of differentiation and graduation.In this connection we think it worth while to outline briefly some interesting suggestions, as to the practicability of which we have found it difficult to form a final opinion without more detailed knowledge than is at our disposal.  The suggestions are as follows :The eventual effect of the above proposals would be to reduce the total expenditure from rates in England and Wales to about  100,000,000 per annum. The balance of expenditure thus remaining on the rates is capable of classification into the two broad categories of Social Services and Administrative Services. If the division were to be made on some such lines as indicated above, it would probably be found that Social Services would be responsible for about one-third of the total, and Administrative Services for about two-thirds. There might then be instituted, corresponding to the two sets of services, the levy of two distinct rates which might be termed the Administrative Kate and the Social Rate respectively. The Admini-strative Rate would be levied as at present over the rateable value of all lands and premises, though the existing basis of assessment, which is in some respects illogical and unwise, might be revised in detail. The burden of the Social Rate, on the other hand. misrht be distributed between different categories of ratepayers according to some principle of capacity to pay and other relevant considerations.It has also been suggested that an element of graduation according to rateable value might be introduced, either by partial relief to certain classes of dwelling-houses or by a higher rate where the capacity to pay is greater. The existing principles of our rating system go back to a period before the principle of progressive taxation had been seriously introduced into our fiscal system. The introduction of a distinction between the Social Rate and the Administrative Rate would, however, greatly facilitate the intro-duction of principles of differentiation and graduation. The extent and degree of the relief which would thus be given is. however, a question of facts and figures of a more detailed character than we have before us.If such a system of differentiation and graduation were to work smoothly as between different local areas, it would be necessary to levy the Social Rate over an area sufficiently large to enable a reasonably represen-tative average to be struck over different classes of ratepayers. For this reason it would have to be considered whether the two rates should not also lie distinct in respect of the districts over which they are levied. That is to say the Administrative Rates might be levied over strictly local areas fl7271] E
as at present, whilst the Social Rate would be partly or wholly a county rate. Thus the feasibility of introducing a separate Social Rate would partly depend on the success of the reform of Local Government areas recommended above.6. conclusion the rating system of this country is at present a jungle of anomalies, complications, and historical survivals into the details of which it is-rash for anyone to enter but a Ministry of Health expert. For this reason any such scheme as the above must be susceptible of considerable amendment and improvement in details. Rut we have no doubt as to the character of the evils to be remedied or as to the main lines along which a remedy can alone be found.It will be seen that our financial programme would consist in treating the burden of national and local expenditure as a whole, and in regarding the latter as having a more urgent claim for relief than the former, out of whatever free resources the Chancellor of the Exchequer may obtain, as the result of a steady policy of disarmament, a reform of inheritance duties, or the natural elasticity of the revenue as the country recovers once more a normal rate of progress. Tt makes no difference to taxpayers as a whole whether they pay a given sum in local taxes or in national taxes. But since (17) our system of national taxation is much more efficiently devised than our system of local taxation, it is better that the relief which can be afforded to taxpayers should affect local taxes first.
(17) This policy is the basis of CP. 8 (28).SUMMARY.The opinions expressed in this Chapter are in many respects in striking agreement with CP. 8 (28), but the specific proposals put forward contain little, if anything, new that can usefully be incorporated into the general plan of that document.

</content>
</cab>
