<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/193/0 images: 215-217</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
: e s ret.-.----- eery no0.yPo67(28).0 a 3 i ii e t.SITUATION THAT \7QULD Bg CRSAT33) 3Y THff FATTIESoi? diplomatic rijlatioiis bstjbeh a poad?jt.oj.i aiida fcrpjx:.&apos;? O0Ui;?Y (p.,g,, CAEA.?A AJIS japan-fl).Koto by the Secretary of State for foreign Affcirs covering Joreign Office Memorandum.2 $bitehall Gardens, S.&quot;/. 1. 17th March, 1928.
INTER-IMPERIAL RELATIONS. March 12. 1928.CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1.j.T 3065/2429/384] No. 1.Memorandum for the Cabinet.(Secret.)I CIRCULATE to my colleagues a memorandum on the technical aspect of the situation which would arise in the hypothetical case of Canada recalling her Minister (not as yet appointed) from Tokyo&apos; and requiring the withdrawal of the Japanese Minister from Ottawa.A. C.Foreign Office, March 12. 1928.Memorandum.THE study of the important question of the situation that would be created by the rupture of diplomatic relations between a Dominion and a foreign country, e.g., between Canada and Japan, has been suggested by a recent incident which led to a request by the Canadian Government for the recall of Senor Barron. the Mexican consul-general in Toronto.The facts are briefly as follows : In October last the Canadian Government acquiesced in a visit being paid to Mexico by Sir Henry Thornton, of the Canadian National Railways, who had been invited by the Mexican Government to submit recommendations for the reorganisa-tion of the national railways of Mexico. About the same time a public campaign was begun in Canada against the Mexican religious law, and Mr. Mackenzie King was attacked for assisting the Mexican Government by sanctioning the Thornton mission. In December last Senor Barron, Mexican consul-general in Toronto, considered it necessary to issue to the press a statement in defence of his Government. This statement, which was indiscreetly worded and went beyond an exposition of the purposes of the Mexican religious law to cast reflections upon the Roman Catholic Church itself, was held to be improper by the Canadian Government. Moreover, Senor Barron&quot;s action, by adding further fuel to the controversy, became a source of political embarrassment to the Canadian Government. Mr. Mackenzie King accordingly sent for the consul-general and. after informing him that his action had impaired his usefulness as Mexican consul-general, advised him to suggest his recall to the Mexican Government. This suggestion, when it reached the Mexican Government, gave great offence, and a deadlock has ensued. The Mexican Govern-ment refuse to withdraw Senor Barron and threaten, if the Canadian Government cancel his exequatur, to retaliate, inter alia, by demanding the recall of the Canadian trade commissioner at Mexico City.This would not in itself involve a breach of diplomatic relations, since His Majesty&apos;s Minister would eontiime to protect Canadian interests in Mexico, unless objection were to be raised to such a course by the Mexican Government. The difficulty which has arisen does, however, suggest the necessity of considering the consequences of the more important hypothetical case of the withdrawal of a Canadian Minister at Tokyo and the ejection of the Japanese Minister from Ottawa.The essential difference between the two cases is that the withdrawal of the Canadian Minister from Tokyo and the Japanese Minister from Ottawa would mean a rupture of diplomatic relations between Japan and Canada, while the withdrawal of the Mexican consuls from Canada and the Canadian trade commissioner from Mexico would not involve such a breach between Mexico and Canada. Diplomatic relations between Canada and Mexico are at present conducted exclusively through His Majesty&apos;s Minister in Mexico or the Mexican Minister here, and the situation would be the same after the withdrawal of the officers in question. It is, of course, true that the situation might very easily develop into something much more serious, but for the moment the only change would be that certain officers stationed by one country in the territory of the other for the purpose of performing certain non-diplomatic functions would no longer be there.[420 m-1]
In the other case, however, the action of the Canadian Government would be due to a desire to suspend diplomatic relations between Canada and Japan, and the result of their action could scarcely be regarded as anything else. And the possibility of such action involves considerations which, though they may appear technical, seem to go to the root of the position of the British Empire in relation to foreign affairs.The British Ambassador and the (at present hypothetical) Canadian Minister at Tokyo are both representatives of the King; they are both channels through whom His Majesty conducts his diplomatic relations with the Emperor of Japan; the only difference between them lies in the nature of the subjects with which they deal. His Majesty conducts his Canadian affairs with the Emperor of Japan through the Canadian Minister and all his other affairs through the Ambassador. The King is either in diplomatic relations with the Emperor of Japan or he is not, and so long as he has a diplomatic representative at Tokyo he remains in such relations.But if the above is the correct position, how can it he reconciled with a rupture of diplomatic relations between Canada and Japan which left the relations between the rest of the Empire and Japan unaffected ? Such a state of affairs could, it would seem, only exist on the hypothesis that His Majesty is, for international purposes, something other and different in relation to Canada from what he is in relation to this country and the rest of the Empire. In other words (since the international status of the other Dominions must be identical with that of Canada), His Majesty is, for international purposes, not one King but seven, and King of seven States, whose relations with a particular foreign country may Ik; quite different. Some of them may be in diplomatic relations with that country while others are not, and it would seem to follow logically (though it is not necessary for the argument) that some of them might be at war with that country while others are not. It is obvious that if this is so the British Empire has ceased to exist as an international entity: at most it is a personal union we have destroyed, by dividing it into seven pieces, the only link which held the Empire together as an international unit.There is, perhaps, one way in which this conclusion might be avoided. It is to suggest that the withdrawal of the Canadian Minister and the eviction of the Japanese Minister would not really amount to a rupture of diplomatic relations, but would merely indicate His Majesty&apos;s displeasure with Japan over certain matters exclusively affecting Canada, His Majesty being prepared to remain in diplomatic relations with the Emperor of Japan and to deal with him in all non-Canadian matters through his Ambassador. The objection to this is that it is not what the Canadian Government would have desired and intended by their action, and not what the Japanese Government would consider their action to amount to; it would really be an attempt to maintain that action which in fact amounted to a rupture of diplomatic relations was something different and of less gravity. The situation might be different if the Canadian Government had confined their action to with-drawing their Minister and had taken no steps as regards the Japanese Minister at Ottawa; in that case it might be possible to maintain that no rupture of relations had taken place, especially if the Japanese were informed that the functions of the Canadian Minister would be exercised by the British Ambassador. This, however, is quite a different situation to that which we are examining.If the above considerations are sound it follows that the situation suggested cannot be allowed to arise, unless we are prepared&quot;to acquiesce in the breaking up of the Empire. Tf the Dominions, and Canada in particular, agree with this view and dislike that result, it should follow that they should agree that action such as that suggested should not be taken except in circumstances where the whole of the Empire is prepared to take similar action, so that diplomatic relations between His Majesty and the Emperor of Japan would be completely severed and the British Ambassador would go, too. The conclusions of the last Imperial Conference in relation to foreign policy are, it is suggested, only consistent, with the acceptance of this position by the Dominions; whether they would be prepared to accept it in express terms may be another matter.

</content>
</cab>
