<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 87-106</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT),CHIT. 112 (24)CABINET,IMPERIAL PREFERENCE.Note by the Secretary of State for the Colonies,I circulate for the consideration of my colleagues the accompanying Memorandum on Imperial Preference, which has been prepared by the Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies, Lord Arnold.(Intld).   J.H.T-.COLONIAL OFFICE.February 15th, 1924,,
Memorandum on Imperial Preference. -It is important to call the attention of the Cabinet to tho necessity of taking an immediate decision on the Resolutions regarding Imperial preference passed at the Economic Conference last October.The Secretary of State has been receiving representations from several quarters, especially from the West Indies, asking for a detailed statement of the Governments views regarding these Resolutions, and the need for a decision has become most urgent because a Debate on Imperial Preference In the House of Commons has now been fixed for Tuesday, February 26th..It is also desirable to omphnsizo that the Dominions must be informed of the Government&quot;s intentions well in advance of any statement in the Press or in Parliament, so there is no time to lose..The whole of the Resolutions which were passed at the Imperial Economic Conference dealing with Preference are appended hereto, in the Appendix marked &quot;A&apos;,     The present memorandum is written by me on the assumption that the Govern-merit, though leaving the Resolutions to the vote of the House, will have to state Its own viows on them in detail before long.The most Important of the Resolutions are those relating to Sugar and Dried Fruits.     To take sugar first.     The duty Is at present 2fda lb. and the preference is l/sth, or nearly -Idper lb,     If the sugar duty were halved and became 1.3/8d, it is urged that the preference should still be the present amount of nearly ^d and should not be l/Gth of the reduced duty, which would mean a preference of nearly  d.   . This plan of maintaining tho preference at the present amount of nearly Id is now always called &quot;stabilisation&quot;.The most important point for the Cabinet to consider, in relation to stabilisation, is that it clashes with the Labour
Party policy of abolishing, as soon as it can be done,- the sugar duty altogether,     A further difficulty arises owing to the undertaking given by the Coalition Government in February 1922 that the proportional rate of preference would last for ten years.     It is true that this undertaking only applied to the rate of preference i^e,, l/Sth, and not to the existing ajivount of preference; of nearly Id.     The undertaking meant that,  if the sugar duty were reduced by one-half, the rate of preference would still be one-sixth, and In such an event the actual amount of preference would have been reduced from nearly Id to nearly Id,The words of this ten-year undertaking are set forth In a reply given by&apos; Mr t. Churchill in the House of Commons to a Question on the 23rd February, 1922, and this reply was further amplified by a letter to Sir E.Davson of 11th July, 1922, which was published in the Press at the time.     For purposes of reference, Mr,Churchill&apos;s reply and the copy of the letter to Sir E.Davson are annexed hereto and are marked &apos;B&apos; and &apos;C&apos; respectively.     It should be noted that the undertaking applied not only to the duty on sugar, but to all preferences as prescribed by the Second Schedule of the Finance Act, 1919, that is to say, to all articles on which preference is given.     This ten-year undertaking has been counted upon, particularly by the West Indies.     There is, however, clearly &apos;?;ome misgiving on the part of the sugar growers as to whether the undertaking is definitely binding on the new Government, as is evidenced by the fact that requests from the lest Indies and elsewhere for a declaration of the policy of the Labour Government on this matter   are being received.     Naturally, the sugar growers and others wish to know whether the ten-year undertaking holds good now that *there is a change of Government.     Also, they wish for more
than that.     It is here necessary to make it claar that this ten-year undertaking was carried a distinct step further at the Economic Conference last autumn because, as already stated, the stabilisation now proposed is that the present amount of preference shall not be reduced and that, to take sugar, the preference, if the duty is reduced, shall for a period of ten-years,not fall with it but be maintained at Its present rate of nearly -gd per Ibo so long at least as the duty on foreign sugar does not fall below that levelsTo return, however, to the Churchill -undertaking, I will summarise very briefly what seems to be the position of that matter:-(l) Constitutionally, it would appear that no such undertaking could have been given and therefore it ought not to have been given..(2) No undertaking of this kind could have any definite moral obligation unless it had been agreed to by the other parties in the State, as well as the Coalition Government, So far from any such agreement haying been obtained, the undertaking was, in May 1922, criticised in the House of Commons by the Free Liberals in a series of questionsu(o) In these circumstances, It cannot really be contended that the undertaking is binding upon the present Government.     Consider a counter case.     The Labour Government of Queensland is faced with the necessity of renewing Loans- to a very large amount (about  25,000,000) during this year and next, and other loans fall to be renewed
in the course of the coming ton years. These renewals constitute a very groat problem for the Queensland Labour Government, Let it be assumed that tho British Cabinet, in order to help the Queensland Labour Government, now gave an undertaking that all the money needed by Queensland to renew her loans for the next ten years shall be found for her at Any loss would, of course, have to bo made good by the British taxpayer.     Such an undertaking would be criticised in Parliament by the Unionists and tho Liberals, Therefore, it could not bo argued that later on, when there 5.2 a change of Government, the new Administration ware bound by any such undertaking.     But it is submitted that, in principle, there is no real difference between an undertaking of this hind and that given by Mr,Churchill,     For one thing, both would mean or might mean, in practice, a charge on the British taxpayer-     Mr0Churchill^ words about breaking faith in &apos;DJ annexed her-sto should never have bean U39*d*It is quite impossible for the Labour Government to renew the ten-year- undertaking in a specific form, particularly as amplified in the Economic Conference Resolution, becauset-(l) To do so would assume that the sugar duty would probably remain in existence for ten years, even though at a reduced rate.     Any such assumption ^oes counter to Labour Party policy, and would mean embarrassment in propaganda and for Labour candidates at Election tines.(2) It seems probable that the Liberals would hot be a party to any such undertaking and would vote against the Government on the point in the Eouse of Commons,
1&apos;he result would be that this undertaking would have-; to be carried by labour and Tsry votes against the liberals, nothing could be more disastrous for the Government than that, labour would at ones be- represented in the country as thoroughly unsound cn fiscal matters, end it would be difficult to deny the chargea      Also, the relations between labour and Liberals in the House of Commons would be greatly strained, which mightj on another issue, mean that the liberals would decide to vottf with the lories and bring the Government downo it would be in the last degree unfortunate if the Government got into serious difficulties, leading perhaps to its eventual defsatj not because it had boldly adhered to a point of principle, but because it had givi-n way on a matter on which it should have stood firm.In all the oiroumstanoes, the utmost that the Cabinet should consider is agreeing to stabilisation as long as there, is a sugar duty,,     Hist is to say, that they will maintain-the existing preference of nearly -^d per lb. on sugar so long at least as the duty on foreign sugar does not fall below that level.     But it should also be clearly stated in parliament that thf: labour Party adheres to its policy of abolishing the duty altogether as soon as the - finances of the country will allow. If a comprehensive; statement to this effect were me&amp;fc it would not be necessary, until there is a question on the point, to.say anything about a ten-year undertaking.     As a matter of fact, if ths Cabinet deoides to make the foregoing announcement about stabilisation-it would probably go a very long way to satisfy the, &quot;feat Indies.     Certainly stabilisation should be represented^ in Parliament as a very great concession, and only made because of the extremely difficult position in which tht&apos; action of the late Government and the Economic Conference have placed the present Governmentu
Dried. Fruits. * *c The Government will be pressed to remit altogetherto the Dominions the present duty on dried fruits.     The duty on foreign dried fruits is npw 10/6d. per cwt. and these of Empire origin enjoy a preference of l/6th, l,e. l/9d. per cwt,, making the duty on Empire products 8/9d. It is now proposed that this 8/9d. shall be remitted altogether, the foreign duty remaining at l0/6d, as at present.     Financially, this would involve a loss of revenue of about  90,000 a year.    Such remission would operate mainly for the benefit of Australia and South Africa, and there is a considerable demand from those Dominions to give the remission.As regards Australia, It Is argued that the remission would make- possible increased emigration from the Mother Country for fruit growing.     It is doubtful if there is really much substance in this point.     In any case, emigration could probably be stimulated by other means at less cost to the Mother Country.A chief objection to the remission of the dried fruits duty is the fundamental one that it would operate inequitably as between the various parts of the Empire.     It would help Australia and South Africa, but would do nothing for Canada, New Zealand and Newfoundland,     Another grave objection is that remission would in effect give Increased protection because if, by reason of it, more oapital is employed in the fruit growing industry in Australia and. South Africa, it Would be extraordinarily difficult, in fact almost Impossible, subse-quently to abolish the lO/ed, duty cn foreign dried fruits, In short, whereas it may plausibly be argued, that the remission Is a step Iq the direction of Free Trade because it means the remove 1 of a duty, it is unfortunately equally true that it/almost
almost certainOy-^aiis^the-perT^uatioii  of the foreign duty, and that Is anything but a step in the direction of Free Trade,   -It is also contended that if the Mother Country refuses to give this, remission she may hereafter be disadvantages in certain obvious-ways.in respect of Australian preferential duties,on imports of British manufactured goods0This; Iatter: point, raises a most fundamental principle, and similar considerations, arise In regard to the request to the Mother,. Country to give the ten-year undertaking with a view to &quot;bolstering, up&quot; the sugar Industry in the West IndiesThe,simple feet is that in ail these preferences and reciprocal arrangements the Mother Country is on a slippery sloped - The. appetite ..of the Dominions and Colonies grows upon what It feeds on,. . Unless the Empire is eventually to -break up,.it will be necessary, sooner or later, to take a firm stand and -to say &quot;no&quot;, to these. Dominion and Colonial Importunities and threats, &apos;   Schemes of Dominion and Colonial development such as those which the Government has in view will&apos;do more to help the Empire than all the Tariffs in the world, .The whole policy of preference is economically unsound,- and is really:- based upon the principle of protecting Dominion and Colonial interests at the expense of the people of the Mother Country, and that means mainly of the workers, beoauae preference Involves, certainly if it is to he main-tained, dearer sugar and tea and so forth.Preference and these reciprocal trade arrangements with the Dominions and Colonies are bound to break down in course, of time.,.    As. a matter of orinclple, therefore, it would, undoubtedly be best to toke e firm lino now rather than be dragged further along the evil path,     Whene-irer such a stand is taken It will be said that Dominion end Colonial
interests are being flouted, and that the Empire Is being ruined, and so forth,,     But these things should be faced,, more particularly us they would not be really true, and such criticisms are much less harmful than going further upon wholly wrong lines,     Quite apart from anything else, it Is necessary to emphasise that all these requests from the Dominions and Colonies are a clear violation of the doctrine of economic equality, and this policy, If it is pursued further, will undoubtedly in course of years lead to great International friction and not improbably to war.     It is the height of unwisdom to try and enclose within tariff fences such large parts of the world&apos;s surface, more especially as the various countries ore scattered all ever the globe,Nevertheless, in view of the extraordinarily difficult  -position in which the Cabinet is placed, it may be decided to remit the Dried fruits duty;.     But It i-s submitted that this remission, together with sugar stabilisation as previously outlined, should be the utmost limit of concessions, except that if the dried fruits duty Is remitted, the duty on dried currants should perhaps also be remitted, which would mean that foreign dried currants would continue to pay 2/- per cwt, and. empire dried currants would come in free.     The remission of Empire duty would involve a loss of revenue of about-  10,000, The latter part of the Economic Conference Resolution on currants, about considering an increase in the duty on foreign currants should not of course be entertained.The remaining Resolutions for increased preference ere in respect of tobacco and wine, but the pressure regarding them has been less than In the oases of sugar and dried fruits.
All the other Resolutions dealing with Imperial preference which were passed at the Imperial Economic Conference would require the Imposition of new duties, and I have assumed that the Cabinet would not assent to any such proposalsoTo sum up, it Is undeniable that these preference Resolutions create a critical position for the Government0 If It is decided to agree to sugar stabilisation and the remission of the duties on dried fruits and currants, the dangers of this course must again be stressed,,     Such concessions are wrong in principle, they would be inequitable In operation, and they can be, and In all probability will be, riddled by the criticism of the Liberal Party in Parliaments 1It would obviously be of great assistance to the Cabinet if It were possible to ascertain in advance with some exactitude what view the Liberals are likely to take about these various matters0     It may be the case, in view of the situation created by the Resolutions of the Economic Conference, that the Liberals will be more inclined to compromise than would otherwise be the ease,,(Initialled)    Ae15c2024c
APPENDIX   ABXT5AC5? VfiOH SUJMA3S 03? CONCLUSIONS OP THE IMEEKIAI ECONOMIC GOKPEliEECE, 1923.  (Cmd.1990)3. IMPERIAL PPJiiFEItENCE.. (1) Tffl.&apos;5fLff Preference.It was decidad to adopt the following Resolutions--This Imperial Economic Conference, holding that, especial! in present circumstances, all possible means should be taken to develop the resources of the Empire and trade between the Empire countries, desires to reaffirm the Resolution an the subject of Imperial Preference passed by the Imperial War Conference of 1917,further, as regards Imperial Preference under the United kingdom Customs Tariff to Empire goods, His Majesty1^ Government intimated that they intended to submit to Parliament the following proposalss-Dried Fruit.At present dried figs, raisins and plums (includes apricots) are dutiable at the rate of 10s*6do per cwt, if from foreign countries and enjoy if of Empire origin a preference of one-sixth, i.e., of ls09d. por cwt.,It is proposed to admit those goods free of duty from the Empire so that Empire raisins, figs, and plums will enjoy a preference of 10s*&apos;6d. per cut. Currants.At present dried currants are dutiable at the rate of Ss. per cwt. and enjoy a preference of one-sixth, which on the existing duty only amounts to 4d.His Majesty&apos;s Government are prepared to offer free admission to Empire currants and to consider what increase in the duty on foreign currants may be necessary to make the
preference effective, such increase to come into force at- a future date tc be agreed &quot;upon. .   vOther. Dried Fruit.At present there is no duty on any&apos; other dried fruit, but Whilst continuing to admit such Empire dried fruit free, Sis Majesty&apos;s Government would propose to impose a duty of 10s.6&amp;. per cwt on such foreign dried fruit (e.g.j apples, pears and peaches) as the Dominion representatives may consider of interest to their trade, Other Preserved Fruits,Preserved fruits other than those mentioned above are not dutiable save in respect of sugar contents, if any.   It is proposed in addition to any such duty cn the sugar contents to impose an all-round, duty of 5s, per cwt. on the principal forms of preserved fruit not at present dutiable, except fruit pulp for jam manufacture, which will remain free of duty.   All such fruit will be admitted free from the Empire. Sugar,At present sugar is dutiable according to a scale dependent on the polarisation of the sugar with a basis rate of 25s&apos;.8d. per cwt, on fully refined sugar.Empire sugar enjoys a preference of one sixth or 4s.3id. per cwto being nearly a halfpenny a pound on ref toed, sugar.It is not   possible at present to offer en increase in this preference, but His Majesty*.s Government are ready to guarantee that if the duty is reduced the preference shall for a period of ten years not fall with it, but be maintained at its present rate of nearly -g-d. per pound so long at least as the duty on foreign sugar does not fall- below that level, Tobacco.At present the duty on tobacco varies according to kind, being of course higher on cigars than on ^manufactured tobaccos.   On the latter it is about 8s,2d per lb,,, on which the Empire enjoys a preference of one-sixth or, say, on raw tobacco of 18.41.
His Majesty1s Government would be prepared to adopt the course proposed in regard to sugar, i.e., to stabilise the existing preference for a term of years or alternatively they are prepared to increase the preference to one-quarter, i,e., to about 2s. on unmanufactured tobacco at present rates, the amount of the preference of course varying as the basis varies.As a result of consultation with the oversea representa-tives concerned, it has been decided to adopt the second alternative, i.e.a to raise the Preference from one-sixth to one-quarter. Wine.The proposals are:-I.     To double the existing preference of 2s. per gallon on the duty of 6s. per gallon on wines of a strength exceeding 300 and not exceeding 420. The rate of duty on such wines coming from the Empire, would thus become 2s. por gallon.2.     To inorease from 30 per cent, to 50 per cent, the preference on the surtax of 12s.6d. per gallon on Sparkling Wine. 3aw Apples.It is proposed to levy a duty of 5s. per cwt. on Haw Apples of foreign origin and to admit Haw Apples from the Empire free of duty as at present.Canned Salmon end Canned Lobster, Cray Pish and Grabs,It is proposed that a duty of 10s. per cut. shall be imposed on foreign Canned Salmon and Canned Lobster, Cray Pish and Crabs, and that those goods shall be admitted free of duty from the Empire,, Honey.It is proposed that a duty of 10s. per cwt shall be imposed on foreign honey, and that Honey of Empire origin
shall continue to be admitted free of duty. M-S&amp;i .-^9mon, and ether Fruit Juices.Tho proposal of His Majesty5s Government is that a duty at the rate of 6dc per gallon shall be imposed on foreign lime and lemon Juices and Eis Majesty&apos;s Government would consider a list of other Fruit Juices which the Dominions regarded as of interest to their trade.   The same duty would fall on Fruit Syrups and would be exclusive of the duty on the sugar contents of such syrups.   Fruit Juiees from the Empire will continue to be admitted free of duty.
ABP2HLIX  B.HOUSE Off 00MM0H8&apos; pi&apos;1:. ICIAL REPORT.23rft retmary, 1922a, l WE3T DLUIES (IMPERIAL PREJppPJifSIR So HO ARE aekec the Secretary of State for the Colonies whether his attention has been drawn to the state-ment that the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies announced at a meeting- of the Associated v/est Indian Chambers of Commerce in Trinidad on the 29th January that the British Government had decided to make a trade arrangement -with the   eat Indies guaranteeing the continuance for ths next 10 years of the existing rate of preference; and whether he has any announcement to make on this subject?MR.CHURCHILL:    I have seen the report of the announcement by the Parliamentary Under-secretary of State for the Colonies, which represents in substance the policy which His Majesty&apos;s Government propose for the acceptance of Parliament, namely, an undertaking to the &apos; est Indian Colonies that the preference on goods at present entitled to preferential rates on importation into the United Kingdom shall be continued for 10 years.    The undertaking would be that the Justoms duties on such goods, otter than spirits, shall bear to the ruties on similar goods imported from foreign countries the pro ortions prescribed by the second schedule of the Finance Act, 1919, and that the Customs :,uties on spirits shall   be lower, by not less than 2s06d, per proof gallon, &quot;than the duties on foreign spirits of a like kind.His Majesty1 s Government do not consider that,  it/will
will be necessary to make any formal agreement with the .,est Indie3C   They assume that the ,est Indian Colonies.,, will continue to accord preference to goods of the Mother Country throughout the periods   The proposal for an under-taking to the  .est Indian Colonies is due to the rep re sent a*-tions made to His Majesty!s Government that the introduction of further capital is necessary to maintain and develop the ma hi industries in the   est Indies and that the raising of this capital will he greatly facilitated If the producers can he guaranteed that the preference which they enjoy in the United iCingdom market will be assured to them over a definite term of years0although the honuMember&apos;s question relates solely to the   est Indies and has been answered accordingly, I ought to make it clear that there is no intention of giving less favourable treatment to goods imported into the United Kingdom from any other part of the hlmpire during the 10 years in questions
.APPEMDJZ   &quot;0&quot;,$ Copy of Letter from the Qolonial Offioe toSir Edward DavsQUoBOM IMG STREET, 11th July,1922.Sir,I am directed by Mr.Secretary Churchill to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 26th of May with regard to recent references in Parliament to the continuance of the preference granted by the United Zingdom to certain articles of Jfest Indian produceeSo You refer in your letter to tie wording of the despatah addressed by the Secretary of State to the Governors of the i?est Indian Colonies on the 9th of March as an indl-cation that there has   been some charge in the policy of His majesty&apos;s Government since the announcement which I was authorised to make in Trinidad as to their intentions in this matter,    ind., for the reasons which you state, you anticipate that uncertainty will arise in the West Indies as to the policy of future Governments,   and that bitter disappointment will be felt by those interested in the Colonies.3,   It would be a source cf keen regret to His %,jesty!s Government if there should be any misapprehension in regard to their policy on this matter,   ab MruChurchill explained in the House of Commons on the 23rd of February, the object which His kajesty&apos;s Government had in view in authorising the public announcement of their intentions with regard to preference was to create confidence in the future of the Rest Indian sugar industry by giving to those already interested in it anci to others who might contemplate/the sir EDWARD DAYS OH
the investment of fresh capital in it, a definite assurance that British grown sugar would not be deprived of the benefit of the existing preference foi&apos; a fixed period of years. This object would be defeated if any doubt were to arise as to the leaning or effect of the pledge which I was fern-powers 1 to givoo    The secretary of State therefore Welcomes the opportunity which you ha?e given him of explaining that there has been no change of policy in this matter, and that to tie full extent of their power the Government have, subject always of course to the over-riding authority of Parlisnient, definitely committew the Mother Country to a continuance of preference on the existing lines to articles at present enjoying St for a minimum period of ten years.40     There is in the opinion of His Majest;7&apos;s Govern^ ment no difference between an &quot;agreement&quot; and an &quot;undertaking1 in such a matter.   Both alixe constitute a pledge, the value of which depends on. the prospect of its being kept as a matter of public faith, and not upon the form in which it is cast0    If the undertaking were embodied in a formal written agreement, it would not be the document but the honourable obligation to observe its terms that, would constitute the guarantee to the   est Indies of thy con-tinuance of preference,,    .;-.s therefore there are some con-stitutional and practical, objections to reducing the under-taking to the form of a written agreement, His J-Majesty&apos;s&apos;s Government have on further consideration preferred to use the term &quot;undertaking&quot; which more accurately expresses the substance of their engagement, but in tfeir opinion, in no way detracts from the binding character of their promise.    I trust that with this explanation you will see that   no change of policy whatever was,  or indeed ooul   have beem c ontem&quot; plated when the word &quot;undertaking&quot; was substituted for &quot;agreement&quot;.
5,-    You also refer to the fact,  that in my answer to a question in the Home of Commons on the 22nd of lay I stated that it was the intention of His Majesty5s Government to &quot;maintain their undertaking as long as they continue to enjoy Eis fcajesVs confidence&quot;; and in this connection you express some anxiety lest a change Of Government should lead to a reversal of policy,    I adopted this form of words because, as you are aware, there is in theory no power in any Government or any parliament to &quot;fend their successors even by statute, and it would have been valueless, as well as technically incorrect, for me to profess to do so in reply to a question as to the intentions of the present Government, But this difficulty is incidental both to our constitutional theory and to our system of -parliamentary Government.   His lxc.jestyls Government cannot,however,doubt Tbut that their successors, whether they agreed or disagreed with the policy-involved, would consider &quot;themselves fully bound by the pledge which has been given.   &apos;i&apos;here is in their opinion no ground whatever for anticipating any such departure fr .m established precedent and from the honourable traditions of public life in this country, as world be involved in a failure to observe an undertaing which has been thus formally given to the West Indies Colonies,,     If, as I gather from ,y our letter, mis-apprehension exists in certain quarters on this point, the oeoretary oi State will be grateful to you for any help you can give him in correcting it by publishing this letter here and in the West Indies.I am &amp;c., (signed)     B. -?ood.
HOUSE OF COMMONS&apos; OIPISIA^ 55ffORg*, . (23rd May,1988)KRoHUED asked the Secretary of State for the Colonies whether he is aware that the Government of Jamaica has published in the West Indian and Canadian Press for general information his despatch of 9th March on the proposal to continue for 10 years the preference on goods at present entitled to preferential rates on importation into Great Britain; and whether the despatch will be laid before this Parliament forthwith, together with any replies that may have been received from Colonial Governors?MR.CHURCHILL;     The answer to the first part of thequestion is in the affirmative.   The despatch in question was sent to the Colonial Governments with a view to publication, and it will be laid before the House as early as possible.,   A notification has been received from the Governments of Jamaicaand jiarbafios that pub-li cation has taken place, but no otherreplies have yet been received,LIEUT&quot;-COMMANDER &apos;E8HWORTHY:       Is It proposed to consult the House of Commons before committing future Governments - achange is expected - to a fiscal policy for ten years?ME.CHURCHILL:     I certainly hold that tha Government&apos;has not gone beyond what is usual in matters of this kind.    Itis desirable that the Colonies should have some assurance of a continuance of conditions,,LIEUT.-COMMANDER  EHWORTHY:    Joes the right hon.Gentleman think it is quite falS:, because for the moment thereIs a tremendous Protectionist majority in the House that theyshould bind future Governments for ten years?MU.CHURCHILL:     The hon0and gallant Gentleman, who is toform a part of the Government of tha future, will be perfectlyfree, of course, in this, as in other [matters, to break faithwith the Colonies. &apos;    (

</content>
</cab>
