<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 133-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 i A13 DOOUiiSNT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAPPIC MA JESTY&apos;S GOVERHMEMT)COT,115 (24),OA B I K E T.MOTHERS&apos; PENSIONS,Mote by the Chancellor of the Exchequer; covering a Memorandum by the Government Actuary.I circulate for the information of my colleagues a Memorandum prepared by the Government Actuary on the subject of Mothers&apos; Pensions.     I propose to raise this matter at the next meeting of the Cabinet with particular reference to the debate which will take place in the House on the 20th instant -.(Intd.)gasury, SJald, 16th February, 1924,
MOTHERS&apos;&apos; PENSIONS.Mftmorarduiti by the Gpverpwert Jlotug^.lc     It is very difficult to ascertain the scope of the proposals under this head as put forward fromtime to time by different people..   Thus, in the present session in a scheme put forward in outline   by the late Ministry of Reconstruction the classes to be benefited.were the following mothers of children under tho full time school-leaving age;-(a) Widows - other than war widows;.;(b) Women whose husbands were preventedf from illness or total disablement, from following any regular occupation](c) Women who have divorced their husbands](d) Separated wives;(e) Deserted wives;(f) Unmarried mothers.This latter scheme, the financial implications of which I investigated for the Minister of Reconstruction in 1918, has been within the knowledge of the Ministers who have replied for the Government in the Parliamentary discussions on the subject during the last two years.     It is by no means certain that all the members of the House of Commons who have joined in the discussions have meant the same thing.     Some have definitely limited their advocacy to the case of widows, with children, but others have been much less definite.Mr. Dukes refers toMothers   PensionsMr. Gray refers toMothers&apos; and Widows&apos;&quot; PensionsMr, Hovo-Belisha refers (in. a Question) tonecessitous Widows and Mothers,/2c
lie2j     On the question of qualification, the proposals put forward are equally nebulous. ,   Administration, by. local committees seems to be contemplated as a rule, and. this leads to the presumption that the beneficiaries are -to be &quot;necessitous&quot; as defined by some criterion.     For instance, in the outline scheme put forward by the Ministry of Recojistructlon^ I was instructed to assume that the bene-beneficiaries would be mothers of children of school age who did not &quot;possess an income exceeding  X per annum&quot;o     Kot only was X not translated into a definite figure, but the term &quot;income&quot; was not defined.     It might include earnings, property or benevolence - in fact all the items that have &apos;raised the present controversy as to Old Age Pensions;   and it is worthy of note that in a recent letter to the &quot;Times&quot; Miss Eleanor Rathbone seems to contemplate a. universal allowance regardless of meanstSo     The advocates of mothers&apos; pensions are equallyvague as to the rates of allowance which they would desire,In the outline scheme of the Ministry of Reconstruction itwas said that the amount of the Endowment had yet to bedetermined but should not exceed that paid to the widowof a soldier or sailor with one cr more children,     Accordingtc the scale of War Pensions, then in force,13/Qdo was therate for a widow herself,,     iiiss Rathbone in her recentletter proposes 16/^ a week for the widow, 6/6d. a week for &apos; a weekeach child, and ll/6d./for a motherless orphan, which she describes as the amounts provided on the lowest service widows&apos; pension scale./A:. There
4.     There is one element in the problem which seems to me of great importance.     The proposals put forward are always confined to the case of mothers with children of school age, disregarding what is to happen to the mother when her children reach the age limit.     Their allowances can obviously be terminated,     With the mother&apos;s own pension the case is surely different.     She has received it, with the childrens allowances, to enable her to keep the home together without going out to work.   She has had it for anything up to 14 years, and perhaps l6.     She will now as a rule, be over 4^ years of age.    If she had a trade Bhe has presumably lost her skill, and has become unemployable.     If she had no industrial skill it is now too late for her to acquire it.   Some of her children, one at least of whom must only be 14 to l6 years of age when the crucial point arises, can only be expected to keep themselves:   as they grow older they will all acquire their own responsibilities.     Every argument points to the need to continue the mother&apos;s personal pension till, aS in the case of the blind, it merges in the old age pension,   If this consideration be sound, the cost of any scheme would in a few years be very materially affected by it.It is evident from the foregoing considerations that estimates of cost can only be of a very general character. Such estimates as I was able to prepare for the. Ministry of Reconstruction are out of date, partly because Ireland must now bo excluded, and partly because of the great changes in the death rates and the birth rates which have been experienced in recent years.   The figures of the Census of 1921 are now available, and for the first time these include figures as to the number of dependent children both of men and of widows.     Unfortunately, the figures in relation to widows are of doubtful accuracy. A rather larn:e proportion of the total number of   widows- &apos; - 3 J    -;;
is scheduled under the heading &quot;No Statement&quot; and it is not safe to. assume that this always means &quot;110 children&quot;.    With the aid of other census data respecting children I have attempted to make an estimate of the correction that the &quot;dependency&quot; figures probably require.    The Census figures have also had to toe adjusted to exclude widows with children, who are in receipt of war pensions.     In the result I arrive at the conclusion that the population as enumerated in the Census of 1921 may have included about 300,000  -civilian widows with children under 1.6 years of age, that the total number of the children cf such widows may have been about 580,000, and that there were about ^,000 children who had lost both parents.6.      As regards beneficiaries other than v/ldows, the largest class, and the one presenting the greatest difficulty in the framing of estimates, is that of unmarried mothers.     The number of illegitimate births in Great Britain in the last sixteen years was 748,000. but while it is possible to estimate how many of these children are still surviving, it is impossible to compute the related number of mothers and still less to calculate what number of the mothers have married since the birth of their children or are living in irregular unions and therefore fall, for the present purpose,  in the category of the married.     Giving such weight as is possible to these factors, the probable number of beneficiaries of this class, may, for the present purpose, be reasonably taken at 100,000.
7.     Taking the scale of benefits named in paragraph 3 above(Miss Rath-bone&apos;s proposal) the following estimates of annual cost based, so far as concerns widows, on the figures given in paragraph 5) are obtained for the several classesincluded in the scheme of the late Ministry cfRe c o n s t fiu ction:-Widows and their Children  22,3^0,000Children who have lost both parents        1,650,000Wives and children of invalid and disabled men. 5,800,000Women who have divorced their husbands, separated and desertedwives 1,500,000Unmarried mothers 6,000,000All classes        37,300,000If all the cases of &quot;Uo statement&quot; referred to in para. 5 were cases of &quot;No children&quot; the first of the above items would be reduced to approximately  18,000,000.     The difference between this sum and  22,350,000 represents the adjustment made for the doubt as to the Census figures, 8.     The foregoing figures take no aocount of the possible income of the beneficiaries and would therefore be reduced if a means limit were imposed.     The. amount of the reduction would depend entirely on the details of the means disqualif i cat ion.On the other hand, the figures include nothing:for widows whose children have all passed the age of l6.    If for,,the reasons which I adduce in paragraph 4, it were necessary to continue the personal pensions of such widows, the cost would be increased in a comparatively short tim*e by several millions a year.
9o    It is at present the oase that necessitous widows with dependent children are. entitled to assistance undevr the Poor lawo    Apparently the proportion of widows with ohildrwn, who are actually assisted hy the Guardians is snail, not indeed, being more than about 25 per cent,     //ids proposals for mothers&apos; pensions thus involve the proposition that a large number of widows - possibly as many as two hundred thousand - who are supporting themselves, or otherwise being supported without resort to rate aid, should be sought out by some administrative machinery and pensions bestowed upon them regardless of circumstances except so far, possibly, as a means Limit of some kind may be. applied.     This seems, at least a difficult proposition.10o It is also contended in some quarters that the cost of th^ proposed allowances to which regard has to be had&apos; is only the net cost, after deducting the relief allowed at present under the Poor law.     This argument disregards the consider.id.bra-tion that the cost of the proposed ntnv benefit would be mtt by the Kxohequer while the present expenditure on relief falls upon local rates,11.    The estimates presented in this hemprandum Include nothing for the cost of administration.     presumably this would be a substantial item since the control of expenditure would involve a good deal more than the automatic payment of benefits on such arrangements as are employed in the oase of Old Age Pensions,,(Intdj A. f. W.vernroent Actuary1s Department,February 15th, IS 4*

</content>
</cab>
