<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 155-160</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1924.SECRET.CP. 121 (24).-/iOABINET.PALESTINE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I CIRCULATE for the information of my colleagues a memorandum prepared in the Colonial Office on the subject of Palestine.I think it important that we should come to a decision on the question of policy at the earliest possible date. The situation in Palestine is now calm, but uncertainty is always dangerous, and if the announcement of our policy is delayed there may be a revival of agitation. My own view is that we have no alternative but to adhere to the policy of carrying out the terms of the Balfour Declaration as interpreted by our predecessors. I do not underrate the difficulties, but I- am satisfied that the difficulties of any alternative course would be even greater.Assuming the question of policy to be settled, the most urgent question before us is that of the proposed Palestine loan. This matter is dealt with in paragraph 13 of the office memorandum. Sir H. Samuel attaches great importance to the early issue of a loan, and I am satisfied that it is a pressing necessity. I would ask my colleagues to agree in principle that the loan must be issued, and that it must be issued under some form of British guarantee. The details could then be worked out between the Chancellor of the Exchequer and myself.There is a third point. Negotiations have been in progress for about a year for the conclusion of a treaty with King Hussein of the Hejaz, who is the person to whom the McMahon promises of 1915 (see paragraph 5 of the office memorandum) were given. A draft of the treaty was actually initialled in London in April 1923, but difficulties have since arisen, particularly in regard to Article 2 of the draft, which deals with our position in the Mandated States of Iraq, Palestine and Trans-Jordan. The point is simply this. The late Government hoped to obtain King Hussein&apos;s assent to a formula which would imply his acceptance of the policy pursued by the British Government in the Mandated territories. This would have been an effective answer to those of our critics who assert that the &quot;Zionist &quot; policy in Palestine is a contravention of the promise given to King Hussein in 1915. It is now fairly clear that this object is not likely to be achieved. King Hussein is at present at Amman in Trans-Jordan, where he has had long discussions with Sir Herbert Samuel. The latter proposes that he should be authorised to clinch matters by concluding a treaty with the King&quot;, omitting Article 2 altogether. This may prove in the end the best issue from the impasse. But there are strong objections to reaching such a solution at Amman, through the High Commissioner for Palestine. If Article 2 goes, the treaty has little concern for the Mandated territories, and our reasons for acting through the agency of Sir Herbert Samuel would be difficult to explain. The result would be hailed as an open surrender of our position in regard to the Balfour Declaration. It would be represented that the great King of the Arabs had come in person to the gates of Palestine and had imposed his will on the British High Commissioner. The inevitable result would be a revival of Arab agitation which has lately shown some signs of dying down. I have been in communication with the Foreign Office on this subject, and propose, if my colleagues agree, to instruct Sir Herbert Samuel in the terms of the draft telegram appended hereto.   The draft has the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.To sum up, I invite my colleagues to agree : 1. That the policy of giving effect to the Balfour Declaration, as interpreted by the late Government, be adhered to. [11264] B
22. That the issue of a Palestine loan, under some form of British guarantee,be approved in principle. 3. That the draft telegram to Sir Herbert Samuel on the subject of negotiationswith King Hussein be despatched at once.I think it important that an immediate decision should be taken on all these points.J. H. T.Colonial Office,February 19, 1924.PALESTINE.Memorandum by Middle East Department, Colonial Office.THE whole question of policy in Palestine was discussed in all its bearings in a memorandum of the 16th February, 1923 (CP. 109 (23)), of which a copy has already been submitted to the Secretary of State.2. The key-note of our policy since a civil administration was established in Palestine in July 1920, is to be found in the Balfour Declaration of November 1917, the terms of which are as follows :-.&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government view with favour the establishment in Palestine of a National Home for the Jewish people, and will use their best endeavours to facilitate the achievement of this object, it being clearly understood that nothing shall be done which may prejudice the civil and religious rights of existing non-Jewish communities in Palestine or the rights and political status enjoyed by Jews in any other country.&quot;3. The Declaration was the result of prolonged discussion with the Zionist leaders. Its terms were framed with great care after lengthy deliberations by the War Cabinet, in which all parties of the State were represented, as also the Overseas Dominions in the person of General Smuts. It had a definite war object. It was designed to enlist on behalf of the Allies the sympathy of influential Jews and Jewish organisations all over the world. The Declaration was published at a time when the military situation was exceedingly critical. Russia had dropped out of the Alliance; Italy appeared to be at her last gasp; and the Germans, freed from anxiety in the East, were massing hugh forces on the Western front in preparation for the great offensive of 1918. The promise to the Jews was in fact made at a time of acute national danger. The objections to reoeding from it when the danger is over are obvious.4. The commitment is an international one. The policy of the Declaration was accepted by the Principal Allied Powers at San Remo in April 1920; it was embodied in the Treaty of Sevres; it was adopted in a resolution passed jointly by the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States of America in May 1922; it was quoted textually in the Mandate for Palestine, which was approved by the Council of the League of Nations in July 1922, and definitely brought into operation as from the 30th September, 1923.5. It has frequently been alleged that the Balfour Declaration was inconsistent with previous pledges given to the Arabs during the war. What happened was this: In the course of the correspondence which preceded the Arab revolt of 1916, Sir H. MeMahon, then High Commissioner for Egypt, gave an undertaking (25th October, 1915) to the Sherif of Mecca, now the King of the Hejaz, that His Majesty&apos;s Government would &quot; recognise and support the independence of the Arabs&quot; within certain territorial limits. From these limits &quot;the districts of Mersina and Alexandretta, and the portions of Syria lying to the west of the districts of Damascus, Hama, Homs and Aleppo &quot; were specifically excluded. Was Palestine covered by the definition of the excluded areas, or was it not ? That is the whole question. Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s Government, on two occasions in the summer of 1922, made clear pronouncements nn the subject. They held, that the whole of Palestine, west of the Jordan, was excluded from the McMahon pledge. Mr. Baldwhfs Government took the same ground (despatch to Sir H. Samuel, the 4th October, 1923). Sir H. McMahon, who was consulted personally in March 1922, stated definitely that his intention had been to exclude Palestine.  There seems little
doubt that this was the intention, both of His Majesty&apos;s Government and of their ao-ent at the time when the pledge was given. Whether the actual language of the pledge, if interpreted as a court of law would interpret it, can be held to have given effect to this intention, is more doubtful. The natural meaning of the phrase, &quot; west of the district of Damascus,&quot; has to be strained in order to cover an area lying considerably to the south as well as to the west of Damascus city.6. It should be noted that the McMahon pledge was given, not to the Arabsof Palestine, but to the Sherif of Mecca. It was given for a consideration, viz., participation in the war on the side of the Allies. As few, if any, Palestinian Arabs mined the Hejaz forces or took part in the war, it could perhaps be argued that the condition was not fulfilled in their case. Viewing the situation as a whole, the Arabs have come very well out of the war. Turkish authority has disappeared from the whole Arabian Peninsula. Hussein rules over an independent Hejaz; Feisal reigns at Baghdad, Abdullah in Trans-Jordan. Further south, the Imam of the Yemen and the Idrisi of Asir have become&apos;rulers of independent States. The Arabs as a whole (thanks to Great Britain) have acquired a freedom undreamed of before the war. .7. It is unnecessary to enlarge upon the special position occupied by Palestine in the eyes of the world. It is scarcely conceivable that, having reconquered the Holv Land from the Turks, we could have handed it over to the Arabs. It would have been impossible to justify such a step to the League of Nations or to the civilised world as a whole.8. Our critics would probably retort that this would have been no worse than handing it over to the Jews. The answer, which it is desired to make as emphatic as possible, is that we have not handed it over to the Jews. The Balfour Declara-tion involved a twofold obligation, viz.: (1) to promote the establishment of a Jewish National Home in Palestine (not to convert Palestine into a Jewish State); and (2) to safeguard the interests of the other communities. There is no doubt that, in the early days of,the occupation, exaggerated notions were entertained by the Jewish leaders as to their future position in the country. There is a celebrated statement attributed to Dr. Weizmann (head of the Zionist Organisation) that the intention was to make Palestine &quot; as Jewish as England is English.&quot; It is to this kind of attitude that much of the subsequent opposition to our policy may be ascribed. But it has since been made abundantly plain that His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment do not contemplate anything of the sort. The White Paper published by the Lloyd George Ministry, in June 1922, contained a clear definition of our policy. The main points of this statement are set out in Appendix 3 to the memorandum of February 1923. To summarise briefly, it made clear (1) that we do not aim at the conversion of Palestine into a Jewish State; (2) that there is no question of the disappearance or subordination of the Arab population, language or culture; (3) that the position assigned to the local Jewish agency (which is the body designated by the Mandate to advise and co-operate with the local administration in matters affecting the establishment of the National Home) does not entitle it to any share in the government of the country; and (4) that Jewish immigration is to be limited to the economic capacity of the country to absorb new inhabitants. The above definition of policy was definitely accepted by the Zionist Organisation at the time.  Their letter of acceptance was published in the White Paper.9. The charge that the present administration is a &quot; Jewish Government &quot; will not beai^examination. It is true that the High Commissioner (Sir H. Samuel) is a Jew, but that did not prevent him from being a British Cabinet Minister for many y?ars- The higher ranks of the administration contain only one other Jew, viz. Mr. Bentwich, the Attorney-General. He is a British subject, with previous legal experience in Egypt. He was appointed, not by Sir H. Samuel, but by the mi itary administration which preceded the civil regime. The total number of public servants in Palestine (including railway employees) is, according to the latest hgures available, 2,560. Of these 1,244 are Christians, 632 Mohammedans, and xt- i. enS&apos; - - admimstration is a British administration, controlled by a British . High Commissioner, under the directions of a British Secretary of State. Ifl accordance with the terms of the Mandate, the Jews are accorded&apos; special facilities ror settlement, enterprise, &amp;c, but they do not enjoy (as is sometimes asserted) a position of privilege or monopoly.10- 11 ma7 be mentioned here that, according to the census held in 1921, the Sf   ? 0f Palestine is, in round figures, 756,000.  Of these about 589,600 are Mohammedans, 83,800 are Jews, and 73,000 are Christians; say 79 per cent. [11264] /2
Mohammedans, 11 per cent. Jews, and 10 per cent. Christians. The total number of Jews admitted since the occupation is about 30,000, of whom some 4,000 have not remained. During the war large numbers of the Jewish population were killed or dispersed, and it may be doubted whether the present number of Jewish inhabitants exceeds the pre-war figure. It may be true that during the early days of the occupation immigrants were admitted too freely, and without sufficient checks. But all that is a thing of the past. Immigration is now rigorously controlled, and is confined to persons for whom there is some guarantee of employment. During 1923 the total number of Jewish immigrants amounted to 7,254, while 3,466 Jews left the country. In other words, the net addition to the population by Jewish immigration totalled on the balance only 3,788. These figures afford a striking commentary on the loose talk about &quot; flooding Palestine with hordes of alien immigrants.&quot;11. One of the duties imposed upon the Mandatory Power by the terms of the Mandate (Article 2) is &quot; the development of self-governing institutions.&quot;  Prior to August 1922 the High Commissioner conducted the administration with the help of an Advisory Council, consisting partly of officials and partly of nominated non-officials.  The Palestine Order in Council of the 10th August, 1922, set up a new Constitution for Palestine.  It provided for the establishment of a Legislative Council, partly nominated and partly elective.   The nominated members were to comprise the ten highest British officials in the country; the elected members were to be twelve in number, distributed among the various communities in proportion to their population.   There were to be eight Mohammedans, two Jews and two Christians.   It will be noted that under this scheme the elected members, if unanimous, would have had a majority over the nominated officials. But they would have had to be absolutely unanimous.  If one of them had gone over, to the officials, the latter, with the High Commissioners casting vote, could have voted them down. For example, any attempt by the Mohammedan and Christian representatives to carry a motion prohibiting Jewish immigration could have been defeated by the officials plus the two Jewish representatives.  In the event, the Legislative Council never came into being.   The Arabs boycotted the elections, which broke down i in consequence.   The High Commissioner then made an attempt to reconstitute his Advisory Council on lines which would secure more effective representation of the people.  A number of representative Arabs agreed to serve, but subsequently with-drew their assent under pressure from the extremists.  A further attempt to secure Arab co-operation was made in October 1923, when, as a sequel to the examination of the whole question by a Cabinet Committee in London, Sir H. Samuel proposed to the Arabs that an Arab Agency should be set up in Palestine with a position and functions exactly analogous to those accorded to the Jewish Agency under the Mandate. The proposal was rejected by the Arab representatives. Accordingly, on the 9th November, 1923, the High Commissioner was informed by the late Secretary of State that, in view of these persistent refusals, His Majesty&apos;s Government did not propose to make further attempts to secure Arab co-operation.   They authorised Sir H. Samuel to carry on the administration with a purely official Advisory Council. That is the position at the present moment.12- The latest decision of His Majesty&apos;s Government has created singularly little stir in Palestine. Scarcely a protest has been heard. It is always rash to prophesy, and it may be that there is still trouble to come. On the other hand, it is possible, as the High Commissioner himself seems inclined to think, that the Arabs as a whole will now accept the position and make the best of it. There is no doubt that their hopes were raised high by the change of Government in England in October 1922. They regarded the Conservative Party, and particularly the so-called &quot; Die-hard &quot; section of it, as their special patrons. Their claims have been urged with great vehemence by the &quot; Morning Post.&quot; The late Cabinet contained one member (Sir W. Joynson-Hicks) who had been prominent in the previous House of Commons as a bitter opponent of the Zionist policy. Having failed with the late Government, the Arabs may now consider that they have exhausted the possibilities of British party politics. Our work in Palestine has been severely hampered by the continued uncertainty of the last few years. The plant has been continually dug up to see how it is growing. Iheould not be expected to thrive under such conditions. What we want now, if only we could get it, is a period of settled policy and settled administration. Given that, there seems no reason why our task should not be successfully carried out. i      i(13. The&apos;cost of Palestine to the British taxpayer has been much exploited in the press. As a matter of fact, it is very much less.expensive than Iraq. The cost&apos;to the British Exchequer was rather under 2 millions in 1922-23 and     millions in
1923-24. The estimate for 1924-25 is a million. This expenditure represents the cost of the garrison, including the British gendarmerie established by-Mr. Churchill in 1922. The cost of the civil administration is borne by local revenues. The present garrison consists of two companies of infantry (to be replaced when circumstances permit by a cavalry regiment from Egypt), plus R.A.F. personnel. In addition to the troops there is a force, of some 700 British gendarmerie, paid for at. present by the British Exchequer, and another force of Palestinian gendarmerie paid for locally. It cannot be pretended that the financial situation of Palestine is satisfactory. The country has been hard hit by the general economic depression of the last few years. To keep things going, the High Commissioner has incurred, in anticipation of a public loan, a floating debt of about  1,620,000 to the Crown Agents for the Colonies. It is most desirable that the loan should be issued and the debt to the Crown Agents wiped out with as little delay as possible. The issue of the loan has been delay^ed by a prolonged correspondence with the Treasury (not yet brought to a satisfactory issue) on the question whether, and, if so, to what extent and under what conditions, the loan should be guaranteed by the British Exchequer. Parliamentary legislation would be required before such a guarantee could be given. Whether the loan could be floated without some form of British guarantee is very doubtful. This question is likely to come up in the near future.14. Palestine has been the scene of much political agitation, but little active disorder, during the past three years. There was a serious outbreak in 1920 (before the civil regime was established); another in May 1921, very shortly after the Colonial Office assumed charge of Middle Eastern affairs. In both cases antagonism between Arab and Jew was the cause of the disturbance. There was an abortive outbreak at Jerusalem in November 1921, on the anniversary of the Balfour Declaration. But it was promptly handled and quickly subsided. Since then the public peace has not been disturbed. Palestine is a small country (about the size of Wales) with a population of under a million. The task of maintaining order is not a severe one. The British gendarmerie mentioned in paragraph 13 is a very efficient body, which can be relied upon in case of emergency. But while serious public disturbance has been conspicuous by its absence, there have been a certain number of outrages by parties of bandits, &amp;c. The Arabs of the towns and settled districts are law abiding and amenable to control. But there is a tribal and Beduin element in the outlying areas which presents a more difficult problem. The High Commissioner has recently found it necessary to ask for increased powers to deal with the state of insecurity in these regions Papers on this subject were recently submitted to the Secretary of State. Sir H. SamuePs proposals would enable District Governors to enforce the principle of collective responsibility upon tribal sections and villages in tribal areas, and, where necessary, to impose collective punishment (whether by fine or otherwise) for the misdemeanours of individuals. It is important that the High Commissioner should be authorised as soon as possible to proceed in the manner proposed.15. The question of Trans-Jordan requires a separate paragraph. The limits of the territory covered by the Palestine Mandate have never been defined, but they have always been understood to include territory to the east as well as to the west of the River Jordan. There is this distinction between the two divisions. Under the McMahon pledge, as interpreted in the White Paper of 1922, territory west of the Jordan is held to be excluded from, and territory east of the Jordan to be included in, the area in which we have undertaken to 1&apos; recognise and support the independence of the Arabs.&quot; Article 25 of the Mandate authorises us to make such special provision for the administration of Trans-Jordan as the local conditions require, and to withhold application of any other articles of the Mandate iliat we may deem inappropriate. Under this provision we have actually (with the approval of the Council of League of Nations) withheld application of all the articles in the Mandate that deal specifically with the establishment of a National Home for the Jews in Palestine. In other words, the policy of the Balfour Declaration is not being applied to Trans-Jordan. What we have done there is to foster the establishment of an independent Arab State under the rule of the Emir Abdullah, son of the King of the Hejaz and brother of the King of Iraq. Our relations with the local government are conducted through an officer known as the Chief British Representative, who acts in subordination to the High Commissioner for Palestine. The policy has been only partially successful. Trans-Jordan does not pay its way, and a grant-in-aid of varying amounts has been made to it from British revenues during the^past few years. Ihe actual sums paid were  180,000 in 1921-22;  100,000 in 1922-23; and  150,000 m 1923-24. In 1924-25 it is proposed to reduce the figure to  20,000. It ought to be possible in 1925-26 to get rid of this charge altogether, provided that in the meantime
the finances of Trans-Jordan can be placed upon a sounder basis. It is with this object that a draft despatch to Sir H. Samuel was recently submitted to the Secretary of State, dealing with the whole financial position and&quot; laying down the general lines on which it is considered that the financial supervision of the Trans-Jordan Goyern-ment should in future be conducted. It is hoped that authority for the issue of this despatch may be given at once.16. A despatch from Sir H. Samuel, dealing with the general situation in Palestine at the present moment, has recently been received and is being submitted separately. A despatch on the subject of Trans-Jordan has been promised and will be submitted on receipt.Middle East Department, Colonial Office, February 12, 1924.Draft of Telegram to High Commissioner for Palestine.YOUR telegram No. 40 of 6th February : Hejaz Treaty.After full consideration His Majesty&apos;s Government do not think it desirable that negotiations should be continued at Amman. They are quite willing to consider any further proposals King may have to make in regard to Article 2, if communicated to them through regular diplomatic channel. If Hussein prefers it, they are prepared to transfer negotiations to Jeddah, in which case Bullard would be furnished with full instructions and would be authorised to open discussions as soon as Hussein returns. They see clear objection, however, to conclusion through High Commissioner, Palestine, and under conditions which Hussein himself has engineered, of a Treaty in which, if Article 2 is to go, Mandated countries will have little direct concern. Its conclusion in such circumstances could not but be construed as signal defeat of policy of Balfour Declaration and direct encouragement to Palestine Arabs to renew their agitation now happily quiescent.With reference to paragraph 4 of your telegram, His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot, of course, recognise right of Hussein to depose ruler of Trans-Jordan or to appoint his successor.(Addressed to Palestine, No. . Repeated, No. , to Baghdad, to whom High Commissioner, Jerusalem, is requested to repeat his telegram No. 40 of 6th February.)

</content>
</cab>
