<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 281-283</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0 i Qij1[HI3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTEGRET,,,P, 132 (24),----------- 0 A B I N E T oINDIAN     AFFAIRS, MEMORANDUM BY THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF LANCASTER,1,     The Rangaeharlar Resolution in favour of e Round table conference on constitutional advance has been carried inthe Delhi Assemblys     Practically all the Moderates votedwith the Nationalists In favour of such a Conference,,     In1921 a similar Round Table Conference was offered by theViceroy and rejected on that occasion by the Nationalists,2,     The rejection by the Viceroy of the present Resolutionfor a Conference is in accordance with the cabled instructions e CiP0 &apos; a24) and    Sent by the Secretary of State on the 2nd and 7th February, 91 (24),Indeed, the second of these cables restrains the Viceroy from offering any reforms, even within the Act of 1919, such as the Viceroy was prepared to offer, and for which he thought he had Cabinet sanction,.CP, (24).se CP, 184).3,     This restraint upon the Viceroy continues.     Again inXhis cable   of 15th February, the Viceroy asks for permission to grant an enquiry into the desirability of an advance within the Act (i,e. without having to come to Parliament for an Amending Bill),     And again the Secretary of State has replied that even an enquiry into an advance within&apos; the Act is undesirable.   For, as he points out, any enquiry would show that within the Act little can be dones and*that an Amending Bill must be required toeffeet serious change. 4,     It seems that the Viceroy would welcome permission, at his discretion, to meet the views of the Indian Assembly, eithei in Conference or in enquiry even as to Amendment of the Act,/and
and that the Secretary of State is holding him back,, 5.     The Secretary of State takes up the position that the Parliamentary situation prohibits an amendment of the 1919 Auto     There are the Liberalsj   but the Liberals would probably support whatever Lord Reading advocated. Mr. Hope Simpson favours an advance, and in any case enquiries could be made privately to test the positions It is indeed possible that Liberals might force our hand,, The question really is, does the Labour Government want&quot; to amend the Act (after- enquiry) before 1929, when the next step must be taken,,6o     The Cabinet has not yet discussed this question of constitutional advance in india     The position of the Labour Party on the question has been made clearo     The resolution at the Party Conference in 1922 runs as follows:- &quot;That this Conference approves of the support given by the Parliamentary Labour Party to the Government of India Act, and urges them to support any further legislation in the direction of securing for the people of India the same measure of self-government which is in operation in Canada, Australia and South Africa0&quot;&apos;7o     The Secretary of State rightly picks out. as the most serious element in the situation the Indian loss of faith in Englishmen and in the honesty of our support of the Indian Reforms,8.     It is therefore of the utmost importance/that we should observe our engagements and carefully consider whether any, and if so what, constitutional advance is practicable, before we compel the Vicoroy to reject a Conference and turn do n an offer which may well be made in good faith. 9.     I do not minimise the risks which advance must involve. They are serious, and the most serious is that every advance will just provide a fresh jumping-off ground for fresh demands.     There is&quot;no finality until Dominion status is reached, . /lO,
&apos;-j w J10,     But if Labour too, after all that has been said, just corks the bottle up tighter 3nd allows the fermentation to go on, far graver risks will arise.     The boycott of British goods is bad and may get worse.     Race hatred will certainly increase to the ultimate danger both of British capital and British lives,     ste risk developing a new Ireland in which more than  1.000,000.000 of British capital is to be placed at the mercy of a coloured Sinn Fein.     We increase the risk of separation.11,.     Cannot advance   be combined with real discretion?   The directions in which advance might most safely be made are (a) towards further Provincial autonomy, and (b) a widening of the franchise.     Both these changes require the ultimate amendment of the Government of India Act,     Both would have to be preceded by an enquiry into the working of the Act which could be corrolated with the Round Table Conference. 12. Provincial Autonomy,     Anglo -Indian opinion is prepared . for further provincial autonomy, especially In certain advanced Provinces,     Ultimately, nine Dominions would be more perman-ently within the British Commonwealth than one overwhelmingly large Dominion,     An advance in the direction of Provincial Home Rule would therefore be farseeing statesmanship. 13, Extending; the Franchise,     It is evident that as long as the present narrow franchise endures political questions will continue to be racial and national.     A wider franchise, giving votes to the working class and peasants (as in Burma) would tend to substitute economic for racial divisions, - a horizontal instead of a vertical cleavage, - and prevent the whole of Indian politics from being perpetually directed on nationalist lines.     It is indeed difficult to see how otherwise wages and the status of labour can be raised in India, where industries are developing -r: serious competition not only with Lancashire, but with Sheffield and Birmingham.

</content>
</cab>
