<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 286-289</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this (document is the property of his britaenic majesty1 s governmentFor the Cabinet.     February, 1924,SECRET. CP.134(24)I circulate the following note regarding tho disturbances at jaito in Nabha State which hare just.been reported to me,olivier.22nd February, 1924-.Towards the end af 1920 a movement &quot;started among the Sikhs fcr the reform of their Gurdwaras,     It was genuine,.and \  and was supported by well-disposedendowed religious establishments,    &apos; j- usually buildings &amp; land -, j  Sikhs-   but did not attract somememorials&apos; of some Guru (Sikh )Saint).   The complaint was that j  sectsi     Early in 1921 Its:many of those shrines had passed        jto the guardianship of unorthodox      )  character rapidly changed:    a or immoral custodians, ).----;&apos;.,.., ,------------------------.  committee, the Shiromani Gurdwaraparbandhak Committee, formed to secure and carry on the management of the shrines, fell into the oontrol ef lawless Sikhs (remnants of the Ghadr or mutiny party of 1913-15) whose method was to seize by force rather than use legal means:   / and there is no doubt that the /ultimate object of some of them was to use the funds of the shrines for revolutionary purposes.x x xV&apos; jathas     For this they organized bands of Akalis and formed them intooriginally the Akali Dal (army).     Funds were obtained from malcontent^   * a sikhsedt Sikhs in America and in one case at least from Bolshevik sources,The managers in possession thus attacked were compelled to ask for police protection;    and when this wasgiven
given, the Sikh Guruwara par.bhn.dhak Committee and Akalis- accusedthe Government of opposing reform, hindering&apos; aooess to sacred -places.interference with religious ceremonies and want of respect to theGranth Sahib (the Sikh scriptures) ...    in fact the Government welcomedreform but was bound to enforce order...    It transferred to the SikhG-urdwara -parhandhak Committee in 1922 the keys of the treasury ofthe Golden Temple at Aiar.itsar,. which had always- been kept by amanager appointed by the Government.Scores cf shrines&apos; were seized: &apos; but in the ocurse of theseizures - graise conflicts arose.     At pankana on 2Oth February 1921the 1&apos;iiiahant&apos;  in possession exterminated an armed bank of Akalis that had seized the shrine, killing and burning up over 100 cf them,     Hewas tried-and sentexiced to transportation,.     In August and September1922 the Committee made organised daily attempts to enforce a claim.to trees at a shrine called Guru ka Bagh near Amritsar, sending 570)0cf their followers to jail,,.    Organized lawlessness was displayedin many other forms, and the natural result was a general increasex: of crime;    one band in particular,, which called itself the BabharAkalis committed ten murders of village officials and others who supported the Government.The Government after prolonged attempts to secure agree--aent passed an act -- the Sikh Gurdwaras &amp; Shrines Act - at the endof 1922 setting up machinery for facilitating reform,,     It has neveroperated.     But in fact the position improved after. Its passage untilxthe iiaharaja of ITarha abdicated&apos; in July 1923,.is abdication relieved the ) This abdication, though a purelyDVernment of India of the 1ecesaity of depesiurjg him for )  political matter,, was misrepresentedcas misgovernment and )session of his subjects. ) by the Committee as an attack on is Highness is an orthodox Sikh,)tough his personal morals are        3&apos;ikhism;    an agitation was started,-ploralle.and in pursuance of it meetings were started at Jaito, a place in an outlying part of Nabha state,.    In name they were religious;    their real object was to create a^litioal grievance.     There is a small Gurdwara there, and it has never been closed to worshippers.   But the Akalis organized&apos; daily bands to demonstrate there, and these were denied entry unless they promised to leave again as soo,.i as worship was over,     On their refusal they were arrested, carried by train to a distance and released,,The
; The acts of the Committee in this connectiondecided the Government to proceed against it.   It was in October declared an illegal association and its principal members are being tried on charges of criminal conspiracy-sedition and conspiracy against the King.   Since their trial began, another case of forcible seizure of a shrine has occurred in the Lahore district; and a second committee who replaced the first at Amritoar were arrested after the conclusion of a meeting which they had been holding in the Alcal Takht, a particularly Bacred place.The daily attempt by a small band at Jaito was clearly ineffective: the organizers therefore despatched on 9.2.24 a large band of 500 from Amritsar, - some days march distant - to secure by force access to the Gurdwara. Their intentions were not secret and the authorities on hearing of them decided to admit no more than 50 and then only if they agreed to depart at .once after performing their ceremony.   In its journey the band attracted to it numbers of armed men and the crown on arriving at Jaito attacked the guards.   The following telegram from the Government of India dated 22.2.24 gives particulars..&quot;Jatha of 500 persons reached Jaito in Nahha yesterday accompanied by crowd of Akalis estimated at over 6,000.   Latter wore armed with axes and some firearms. They attempted to force pa,ssago to the Gurdwara and attacked the&apos;State officials, and troops, firing repeatedly at. the latter.   Troops were-obliged to reply with fire which was carefully controlled.   Akalis finally dispersed with loss of 14 killed.   ITo member of the actual Jatha was injured.&quot;The State officials and troops referred to are . those of the ITabha State.    The conduct of the administration of the State, including the maintenance of order, is at ^present-
present Tasted, subject to the general control of the Government of India, in an Administrator (an officer of the Indian Civil Service) appointed by the Government on the Laharaja&apos;s retirement from the Stateo

</content>
</cab>
