<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 526-530</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos; &apos;      ;    :;Vf . &quot;;IS DOCUMENT IS THS PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.,:CRST. C Ai BINE T.P.163(24), LONDON&apos;-TRAFFIC BILL. 13 .Memorandum by the Minister of ^ranagprUAs a result of the negotiations with the Executive of the Labour Party, it has beon suggested that the passage of the London Traffic Bill would be facilitated if all provision for a statutory advisory committee were dropped, and the Minister left to exorcise the powers oonferred on him without any statutory obligation to take advice.The advantage of this proposal is solely that it might secure tho passage of tho Bill without sorious Opposition from the Labour Party.I realise, of course, that the object of the Labour Party Executive in desiring the removal of tho statutory advisory committee from the Bill, is to avoid giving statutory recognition to the London Underground Combine.     In my opinion, however, though their proposal may effect this object, it misses the real point.     The chief value of ths Bill to the Combine is- not so much their representation on the statutory committee as the limitation of the number of omnibuses which may compete with them and therefore of the number of their own omnibuses which have to be kept on the streets.,     This will enable thorn - in my opinion rightly, from the point of view of London traffic as a whole - to divert trafflo from the omnibuses to the tubes and trams, where the latter are not being used up to their economic limit.If, however, firm agreement can be reached with the Labour Party by this concession, the advantages would obviously be so great that it would be desirable to sacrifice other advantages.At the same time I feel it necessary that the Cabinet should realise that this proposal has serious difficulties
not only from the administrative point of view but also from the point of view of gotting a consensus of agree-ment.     The tentative agreements reached with the looal authorities were dependent on the existence of the statutory advisory committee, and from inquiries I have made, I do not think that without a statutory committee we could rely on assistance from these authorltios in the House or in the administration of tho Aot, if the Bill is passed.I desire, therefore, to suggost en alternative proposal which will, I believe, meet the objections of the Labour Party Executive even more effectively than their own proposal and will in addition secure the co-operation of the local authorities,I propose that an advisory committee should be set up consisting of representatives of the looal author-ities with the Government and Pclioo Cfficials only, This would be the statutory committee.     To this committee the Minister would have power to add additional members for the purposes of all matters dealing with the actual regulation of traffic in the streets.     These additional members would bo unofficial persons connectod with traffic Interoats, including labour, -  This scheme avoids the mention of the London. Underground Combine and is an important recognition by the Government of the status of the local authorities.I would remind the Cabinet that the Bill will bo particularly difficult to administer because many of the regulations and restrictions which the Minister will have to make, while very necessary in the general interest, will bo detrimental to particular interests.For example, (l) tho Minister will have to decide the numbor of omnibuses which are to bo allowed to compote
on the tram routes not only of tho London County Council but also of the other municipalities and of the Combine. Obviously this power may affect the profits both of the trams and omnibuses, and its oxorcise leaves the Minister open to attack on the one hand from the public whenever overcrowding occurs, and on the other hand from the tram and omnibus operating authorities for allowing too much competition whenever their profits are not sufficient to allow, for instance, of an adequate rato of wages to the men,     It would be difficult for tho iviinistar to with-stand a cross-fire of this nature unsupported by any committee at which the matter can be discussed by the parties affected.     In so far as the *ramway interests consider that this Bill will be of Importance in connoc-tion with the present wages disputo, this is the essential clause.(2)   Rules as to traffic to be effective must exclude at certain hour from certain streets all slow-moving vehicles, and prescribe the times when vehicles may collect and deliver goods or stand in the streets.   These regulations would affoct vary important interests, and would very probably result in a serious change in the hours and conditions of work of the labour employed in these trades.Unless these and other similar questions are discussed by some body which has given special attention to problems of this nature, each regulation will be pre-codod by and result in deputations from tho interests * adversely affected, and instead of being backed by tho opinion of an authoritative committee they will have -behind them only an inquiry at which the dissentients made a strong case against them or a conference at which all possible objections were strongly put.
Fur-ther, it was confidently anticipated, as a result of inquiries among tiie authorities in the area, that if they were all represented on a committoe they would bo prepared to consider very favourably contributions from the whole area towards schemes for the betterment of communications in London as a whole, as, for instance, tho Victoria Dock Road, which is obviously too heavy a burden for an impoverished district like West Ham.   Agreement as to such contributions could only be reached if the local authorities were working closely with the Ministry and with each other towards a common end with a consciousness of a common responsi-bility for the improvement of London traffic conditions as a vihole.The so difficulties might to some extent be mitigated if the Minister took power in the Bill to appoint an advisory committee, but such an advisory committee would not be representative in the same way as a statutory committee, since it would be impossible, except on a statutory basis, to find one member who could claim to speak for all of either the seven county councils, or the twenty-eijjht metropolitan borough councils, or for other blocks of interests to which only a single representative could be allotted if the committee were to be kept within practical limits.I am bound to say that after giving the matter the very fullest thought I consider the course suggested above, that is, the appointment of a statutory committee consisting of representatives of local authorities and of officials with power to the Minister to add other   -members for particular purposes, has the Greatest advantages, should meet the views of all those who desire a loci governing authority, and would ensure
that elosa oo-operation between the interests which is essential if tho London Traffic Authority (when set up) is to do really offoctive work.A further protection against this Bill being represented aa another obstacle to a greatMLondon authority would bo to insert a preliminary clause stating that the powers are conferred, on tho tdnicter until such time as more extensive powers are conforred on a single authority having jurisdiction over the Greater London area.I therefore ask authority to introduce the Bill drafted on these lines.(Initialled) H..Q

</content>
</cab>
