<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 591-601</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OE HIS BEITAfflIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) SB C R E.T. /&quot; &quot;&quot;    &quot; 9. k JL J-JLJ.lC;Po 176  (24).UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE COMMITTEE.INTERIM REPORT.lc     At the request of the Prime Minister the following Committee have examined tho proposals relative to Unemployment Insurance contained in Memoranda CP. 169(24:) and CP. 169A (24) circulated to the Cabinet by the Minister of Labour.The Minister of Labour&apos;       (In the Chair)The Chancellor of the Exchequer, or, in his absence The Secretary to the Treasury,The President of the Board of TradetThe Minister of Health,The Secretary for Scotland,The President of the Board of Education,The Lord Advocate.After careful consideration of the various proposals contained in the Memoranda above referredto, the Committee submit the following suggestions and recommendations to the Cabinet.SCOPE OP 2,     As the Cabinet are aware, the passage into lawPROPOSEDLEGISLATION.     of an Unemployment Insurance Bill on a very early Sate is necessary if large numbers of unemployed persons are not to be deprived of benefit from the middle of April 1924 onwards.    It is strongly urged that it would be most undesirable even if it were politically possible to confine the proposals of the Government to a stop gap measure, abolishing the &quot;gap&quot;
(extending in extreme oases to as much as 26 weeks), whichwill in the,absence of legislation commence in the middleof April next, and that it would be most difficult,, ifnot impossible, to pass two Unemployment Insurance bills in&apos;the remainder of the present Session, one Bill Sealingwith the coming &quot;gap&quot; and the other dealing with theremaining proposals of the Minister of Labour.3.     On &apos; the other hand it has been pointed out to theCommittee that having regard to the small amount ofParliamentary time available, the fact that the Government,Actuary will require possibly a month to examine and \report on the actuarial aspects of the proposals, thatreasonable time must he provided for the drafting of themeasure and that the proposals themselves are in the mainof a highly controversial character, it will prove quite impracticable to secure the passage into law of a singlecomprehensive Bill covering the various contentious proposalsof the Minister of Labour, by the middle of next month.   -   &apos;4.     It has accordingly been suggested that two bills should be prepared and submitted simultanecJUaly1 * to Parliament- one dealing with the coming &quot;gap&quot; and the other with theremaining proposals, and that having regard to other claims of the Government on parliamentary time after the BasterRecess it would be wise to make provision in the Bill dealingwith the &quot;gap&quot; for a period of not less than six months.5.     The Committee reoommend to the Cabinet -(i)   That the Minister of Labour should be authorised to proceed as speedily as possible with the preparation of a comprehensive Unemployment Insurance Bill, covering the whole of his proposals as approved by the Cabinet;
biods foe 1ICH UNEM-jOYHEOT 2JJEFIT would BE iYaBLE.rss of3EFIT.(ii) that every effort should he made to expedite the introduction in and the passage of the Bill through Parliament and that should it subsequently transpire that there is no possibility of securing the passage into law of the comprehensive Bill before the middle.of April, 1924. the Cabinet should consider the advisability of introducing a separatein paragraph .4 of the Minister of labourrs Mtoafirandom CP. 139(24) as to the desirability of.devising a scheme for paying benefit without the existing arfci-trary limit (on the number of weeks of benefit to be drawn as a maximum during a period of 12 months] to unemployed workers belonging to the insured trades for so long as they are capable of work, geruisely seeking work and unable to obtain it.   The Cabinet have already approved the principle of the abolition of .&quot;Uncovenanted Benefit&quot; and the Committee now recommend:-That the Minister cf labour should be authorised to include in his Bill provisions for securing&apos;payment of Benefit continuously without arbitrary limits to genuine workers so long as they remain unemployed in the manner indicated in detail in the Appendix to his Memorandum CP. .169(24).7. As the Cabinet are aware the existing weekly rates of benefit are as follows:-Basic rate.For wife (cr invalid husband)For each Young childWomenMen15/- . 12/-7/6d.5/-l/-. Girl. v(16-18)6/-    )
PUBLIC RECORD OFFICE reference the FOLLOWING FOLIOS ARE BLANK AND HAVE NOT BEEN COPIED
8.     While the Committee concur generally with theproposals of tho Minister of Labour for increasingRates of Benefit as set out in paragraph 10 of his memorandum CP. .169(24), they must warn the Cabinet ofthe probable re-actions which the. contemplated increasein the Rates will have on National Health Insurance,the Committee recommend to the CabinetThat the Minister of Labour should be authorised to provide in his proposed Bill that the weekly rates of benefit for men and women should be increased to 18/- and 15/- respectively and the rate for each, child to 2/-; the 5/- for a wife remaining unaffected.5Q.DBR 9.     In paragraph 17 of his Memorandum CP. 169(24)RIBDTIOrJ.the Minister of Labour- recommends that power should be taken in the Bill to modify the existing arrangements (under which the Exchequer at present bears one fourth of the total cost of the Unemployment Insurance Scheme, which proportion will, when the. Unemployment Fund is again solvent, be reduced to one-fifth of the- whole) so as to increase (while the Fund- is insolvent) the Exchequer contribution from 6f-d. to 9^d. and - to provide, when solvency is reached, for payment by the employer, the worker and the Exchequer of equal contributions of 6d. which, in other words, will result in an.increase,  (when solvency is attained), of the Exchequer contribution from 3d. to 6d.10.,   The Committee are Informed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer that on the information before him the Unemploy-ment Insurance Fund, ought to bear and is capable of bearing, the new charges which it is proposed to lay upon the Fund without an Increased Exchequer contribution. Owing to the fall in the number of unemployed the existing debt on the Fund in being rapidly reduced.     For example,
475.a decrease of 100,000 in the Unemployment figures means a reduction of  5,000,000 por annum on the liability on the Fund, and, given a continuous decline in the Unemployment figures at the present rate It seems not improbable that the present liability of the Fund to the Exchequer ( 11,000, a)0) may be discharged within the next 18 months,     In these circumstances any proposal to increase the Exchequer, contribution at the moment would, be difficult to justify and would certainly be highly contentious in Parliament.11,   The view was expressed that having regard to possible future claims for measures of social betterment such as Mothers&apos; Pensions, it might be unwise to make any provision in the Bill for a reduction of the existing rates of contribution when the solvency of the Unemploy-ment Insurance Fund is reached, on the other hand, the Cabinet should remember that the present ratet were accepted by Parliament on the distinct understanding that they would only&apos;be enforced while the Fund was insolvent,12.   The Committee have requested the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister of Labour to consider the question of the Exchequer contribution In the light of the Committee&apos;s discussions with a view to the submission to the Cabinet of some agreed solution of the difficulty.
13,    Ths Cabinet have already agreed that provision should be Made in the Unemployment Insurance Bill for the extension of Unemployment Insurance to Juveniles as and when they begin to work for wages.    The proposals of the Minister of Labour are set out in detail in paragraphs 23 to 32 inclusive of his Memorandum CP.169(24).     In effect it is suggested that the rates of contribution in respect of boys and girls between 14 and 16&apos; should be the same as those for boys and girls between 16- and 18.     These rates at present are:-Bmpioyer. Employed. Exchequer.Boys   5d. 4-g-d. 32 d.Girls 4-^d. 4d. 36d,,It is also proposed that the weekly benefit for boys and girls between 14 and 16 should be, boys 5/-, girls 4/-;.   corresponding rates for boys and girls between 16 and 18 are,, boys 7/6d, girls 6/-.   Having regard to the current rate of wages these latter rates of benefit are thought to be too high for boys and girls between 14 and 16 and the suggested reduction in the rate of benefit for thorn, although they pay the same contributions as boys and girls between 16 and 18, could, further be justified on the ground that those between 14 and 16 have only just come into insurance and have therefore necessarily paid very few contribution-tions.14.   It is contemplated that part of the revenue from contributions of juveniles between 14 and 13 should be applied to assist in the maintenance of Juvenile Unemployment Centres.     This contribution might take the form of a per capita attendance grant out of the Unemployment fund to tho Local Education Authority, (or other Body running the centre ), in respect of each
BIOS -17.   The Committee agree generally with the views 3-OP expressed by the Minister of labour in Paras.33 to 38 inclusive IBU-Iiil    of his memorandum resueotinar the desirability of abolishing IK/Li1    the existing provision for refunds of contributions incmcertain cases at the age of 60.18.     The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -(i)     That the Minister of labour should beauthorised to make provision in his Bill for the abolition of the refunds in question without compensation;(ii)     That the Minister of Labour should beauthorised, if pressed in Committee, to offer&apos;a-Scheme of compensation for cases where rights may be said to have already accrued on the linos suggested by him, via. the payment to persons who are over 50 years of age and have paid 50 contributions at leastboy or girl required to attend the Centre as a condition for receiving benefit,15.    Tho Cabinet will no doubt boar in mind the important considerations indicated in pa.ra.50 of the Minister of labour&apos;s Memorandum, respecting tho possible reaction on the Health Insurance Scheme of the proposed reduction in the age for unemployment insurance.     In this connection reference is made to the Memorandum by the Minister of Health (0.P.174(24)) circulated to the Cabinet after the Committee had considered the general question.,16c    The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -That the Minister of labour should be authorised to males provision in his Bill for the&apos;extension of unenrplcyment insurance to juveniles, as and when they begin to work for wages, the provisions to include inter alia arrangements for the rates of contribution being paid in respect of juveniles between 14 and 16 being the same as those for juveniles between 16 and 18: for the weekly benefit which juveniles between 14 and 16 should receive, being, boys 5/-, girls 4/-, and for charging the Unemployment Insurance Fund with payments to be applied towards the maintenance of Unemployment Insurance Centres. The proposed Bill also to contain provisions to secure that as a condition of receiving benefit juveniles shall be required to attend Unemployment Centres if available.
liADE DISPUTE ItSQUALIFICA-[OK ofaOIAL IflEHESIsURAHCE INDUSTRY,of the oresent value of the excess value of their contributions over benefit which they have received, plus compound interest at 2\%,19c     The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -That the Minister of Labour should be authorised to mehe provision in his Bill for the removal of the present disquall-float!on for benefit in cases where work people ere thrown out of work owing to stoppage due to trade disputes at the establishment at which they ere employed, although they pre taking no part in the dispute.20,     The Cabinet will observe that the Minister ofLabour is in favour of the insertion in his Bill ofa Clause withdrawing the right conferred by Section1C of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, on an industry, subject to the approval of the Ministry ofLabour, to set,up a special scheme for itself and soto contract cut of general scheme,21,     In this connection the attention of theCommittee has been drawn to the fact that the adoptionof this proposal would render impracticable infuture the setting up of a special scheme under theAct for, say, agricultural labourers,220     The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -(I)     That, the I. mister of Labour should be authorised to make orovision in his Bill for the abolition of the existing statutory power to form soecial schemes for insurance by industry for the future, on the understanding that such provision will he without prejudice to the position of agricultural workers, domestic servants and other similar categories of employees.(ii)     That the Minister of Labour, in consultation with the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and the secretory for Scotland should be requested to ascertain the views of the Agricultural interests as to the inclusion of agricultural workers in the Unemployment Insurance Scheme and, if so, as to the precise form which such inclusion should take:,
RADE DISPUTE ISQUALIPICA-IOM.PEGIAL CHEHES:PHSURAHCE i INDUSTRY.of the present value of the excess value of their contributions over benefit which they have received, plus compound interest et 2\%,19c     The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -That the Minister of Labour should be authorised to make provision in his Bill for the removal of the present disquall-fication for benefit in cases where work people are thrown out of work owing to stoppage due to trade disputes at the establishment at which they are employed; although, they are taking no part ir the dispute.20,     The Cabinet will observe that the Minister ofLabour is in favour of the insertion in his Bill ofa Clause withdrawing the right conferred by Sectionib of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, on an industry, subject to the approval of the Ministry ofLabour, to set up a special scheme for itself and soto contract cut of general scheme,21,     In this connection the attention of theCommittee has been drawn to the fact that the adoption-of this proposal would render impracticable infuture the setting up of a special scheme under theAct for, say, agricultural labourers,,22,     The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -(i)     That.the Linister of Labour should be authorised to make provision in his Bill for the abolition of the existing statutory power to form special schemes for insurance by industry for the future, on the understanding that such provision will be without prejudice to the position of agricultural workers, domestic servants and other similar categories of employees,(ii)     That the Minister of Labour, in consultation with the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and the tiecretary for Scotland should    -0 be requested to ascertain the views of the Agricultural interests as to the inclusion of agricultural workers in the Unemployment Insurance Scheme and, if so, as to the precise form which such inclusion should take-,
OF CERTAIN LASSES OF .;CHK-?b6P&apos;LE inPSIlivANENT EMPLOYMENT.23.     While the Committee concur generally with the view of the Minister of Labour that itis highly desirable that the classes of workpeoplewho are now &quot;excepted&quot; from the scheme on theprinciple that their employment was permanentshould be brought into insurance, they realise that the adoption of&apos;this proposal would be highlycontentious and might seriously affect the passageof the Bill into law.     The Railway &quot;Conciliation&quot;Grades form, one of the most imoortant &quot;excepted.&quot;categories and the Committee think that it is highly desirable that the views- of the Rail way companies and the workpeople concerned should be ascertained;,24.     The Committee recommend to the Cabinet:-That the Minister of Transport and the Minister cf Labour should be authorised to ascertain.as soon as possible the views of the Railway- Companies&apos;and the Railway &quot;Conciliation&quot; Grades cn the proposal to bring these grades in future into the Unemployment Insur ance B. c he me cRAFT BILL.   25.     The Committee--recommend to the Cabinet:..That the Minister of Labour should be authorised to prepare o draft Bill in &apos; accordance with the decisions reached by the Cabinet and to submit the Bill in question to the Committee for con-sideraticn as soon as practicable.iened) T. JONES. &quot;       R.B. HOWORTH.oint Secretaries to the Committee.T.S.Initialled on behalf of the committee chairman.2j Whitehall Gardens, S.ii.1, 12th March, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
