<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/165/0 images: 711-728</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,       H -Ji.illUS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERKMEHT. I5CRST.&apos; ) ^j C A B I N E T.TRADE   PROSPECTS. Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate for the information of my oolleagu.es a note of the view taken by business men of future trade prospects as given to me in confidence by the members of the Board of Trade Advisory Council at the last meeting of the Council on March 5th.The composition and functions of the Council were j explained in CiP.- 101 (24) .(Itld.)     SolrV.15th March, 1924.
limit   Trade Outlook.INDEX.Subject. &apos;;Banking and General Trade General Trade Indian Trade New Zealand Trade Iron and Steel, Engineering and Shipbuilding Electrical Engineering, Non-Ferrous Metals, Textiles (Wool) Textiles (Cotton) Shipping Coale,..Rubber and Tyres Co-operative Societies,LeathereMiscellaneousThe Indian Boycott Chinese Trade-marks, Merchandise Marks legislationCONFIDENTIAL.-Page.1 12 2 34 -6789 11 12 13 15 1634,9 14
t.THE TRADE OUTLOOK.The President opened the proceedings by welcoming the new Members. He then asked the Members present to express their views on the trade outlook now and In the near future.BANKING- AND GENERAL TRADE, .Mr. Beaumont Pease said that the general tone of trade was fairly cheerful, with the exception of certain indus-tries such as Iron and Steel, Lace and Shipbuilding,   On the Stock Exchange steadiness showed itself in good securities. Tax collection was having its usual effect at this time of the year In a shrinkage of Bank deposits:   this tendency was pronouncing itself to a greater extent/ perhaps, this year than in previous years*   The money and disc cunt markets were firm.   In the. foreign exchange market, fluc-tuations in the French and Belgian currencies continued,-not unccnnected, he thought, with the political situation. Both in France and Belgium, however, a gradual realization seemed to be coming about of the necessity of putting their finances in order without regard to Reparations,BANKING.Mr. Goodenough wrote:-.&quot;So far as trade Is concerned, I think that the general indications point to a continuation of the Improvement which has been noticeable for some time past.   At the same time, there seems to be a general complaint that the business which has been coming to this country has to be taken upon terms which for the most part yield little,^if any, profit,&quot;The Money Market is invariably affected at this time of the year by the collection of taxation and in this year the collection appears to have been unusually rapid.   Apart-1-       t
from the influence which this has had upon Money Market conditions, there is, however, little doubt that the pre-vailing firmness has been also influenced by a larger volume of trade and by increasing demands for ordinary commercial bills,&quot;The Sterling Exchange has improved owing to a revival of confidence,,   A satisfactory feature has been a continued j expansion In the number ef credits opened from abroad, and there has been undoubtedly of late a larger volume of business being financed in London on American and Continental account,   This increase is to some extent seasonal, and many of the credits are for rubber or for Eastern products which do not actually pass through this country.   There is evidence, however, that the number of import credits is Increasing, and that there, is some revival of general trading activity,&quot;INDIAN TRAPS.Mr. Lindsay said that the Indian trade position was strong.   Indian exports for 1923 amounted to  230,000,000, and imports to  150,000,000, as against pre-war figures of  150,000,000 exports and  100,000,000 imports,   These increased figures corresponded roughly with the increase in the general level of prices, and indicated approximately the same volume of trade as before the war.   An adverse-balance of  31,000,000 in 1921 had been converted to the favourable balance shown by last year&apos;s figures.   As regards trade from the United Kingdom, values were being fairly well maintained, and in view of the fall of prices this probably represented a larger volume cf business. *The reason for the decline in the Indian demand for Cotton piece goods appeared from the faot that, while the Indian cultivator, our chief customer for textiles, was
receiving only 5 per cent, more for his crops than he did before the War, the ratio of increase In Cotton, prices was no less than 178 per cent.The President observed that the percentage of increase in food prices since the War appeared to have been generally less than for manufactured goods, and the effects of this were being widely felt.Mr. Hirst drew attention to an announcement by the Bombay Corporation,  advising that no articles manufactured in the British Empire outside India should be used, unless they were not available from any other source.Mr. Lindsay thought that no marked effect had been produced by the attempted boycott as yet,Mr. Gallacher said that he was in Calcutta some nine months previously and had spoken to business men in the Jute trade on the subject: they were of opinion that at that time the movement had had practically no effect.   He thought that the Corporations of Calcutta and Bombay were more extreme in their views on non-co-operation than the working population of India in general.NEW ZEALAND TRADE.Sir James Allen said that New Zealand continued pros-prosperous, and that the results were reflected in increased export trade from this country to New Zealand.   The New Zealand Government was taking action in connection with the proposal adopted by the Imperial Economic Conference in regard to the payment of interest on loans for new works:* he thought that this would result in an increased demand for machinery and electrical plant from this country, but it might not come to much if manufacturers here put up their prices in consequence,
ENGINEERING-.Sir^ Arthur half our said that as a result of tho recent strikes, the homo Engineering Trade was not so good, and there was a oortain risk of cancellation of oontraots on account of tho dolay in dolivery which had resulted:   this had produood nervousness among foroign buyers.   Colonial trado, however, with Canada, Australia and New Zealand was bettor, and improvement was also being shown in the South American marketsThe declino in the French and Belgian exchanges continued to militate against Sheffield interests.As regards the subject&apos; of Chinese Trade Marks,, whioh he had referred to at the previous meetings the situation wa3 now worsej tho latest official advice whioh traders had reoeived \vas to try to hold on as long as possible.. In these circumstances, they had not registered thoir marks, but he doubted if they could refrain from doing so muoh longero     A new announcement by the Patent Office on  -the subject would bo welcome.Trado on the whole was not quite as good as when ho last reported.. The President observed that a Conference had taken plaoo on the subject of the Chinese Trado Marks, and a limited time had been agreed to within which further representations could be made.   Sir Arthur Balfour replied that unless some decisive step were taken.within tho next two weeks, he anticipated that British traders would start registering their marks under the now Chinese Law. ENGINEERING- AND SHIPBUILDING.Sir.Glynn West said that he wa3 disposed to think that, in tho general Snginooring ireland,de, there was a little improvement.   There was also a somewhat better demand in Shipbuilding for special ships, and enquiries were coming
CONFIDENTIAL. ^ p ^D u t3forward, e.g, for tankers, on account.of the advance in oil freights.   He was apprehensive, however, that this tendency would be arrested if demands for increased wages were persisted in.   All orders at present were being taken with-out profit, and if wages were increased, actual losses would be sustained.The Coal situation was threatening, and Coal prices had already risen: this would affect the price of Steel and quotations for Shipbuilding,   The situation in Heavy Steel was worse than ever: Continental competitors were still quoting 12 per ton less than the production costs of up-to-date steel mills in this country, and the outlook was gloomy.Last year!s output amounted to  7,500,000, as compared with a capacity of  12,000,000:    it was true that the figure of output compared well with pre-war figures, but it must be borne in mind that the capacity of the industry had been much swollen as a result of the far.ENGINEERING..Colonel Armstrong confirmed the impression that there was a slight improvement. In general engineering.   Mere enquiries were coming-in, and they were of a more serious kind: a few actual orders from abroad were also being placed.   If this tendency continued, prospects would be brighter than for some time past.Reference was made to the Sydney Bridge contract: the oost of this was estimated at some  4,000,000 sterling.   It was&apos; pointed out, however, that this included a large pro-portion of masonry work, and there was also a condition in the contract that a large proportion   of the Steel*cas to be produced in Australia,Sir Glynn West mentioned that his firm had secured an Australian locomotive contract.,,   India was also about to place orders for locomotives, and he hoped that these would come to this country.
CONFIDENTIAL. IRON AND STEEL.Mr. Bakor agreed that the Iron and Steel Trade raa somewhat bettorB   Production had reached 113 per cent, of the 1913 figure, but it must be borne in mind that the present capacity of the Industry was 150 per cent, of the pre-war capacity.   The figures of unomploymont were lower than for some timo past.   The average wage being oarnod in the Industry as shown by figures published &apos;.by the employers, stood at  2.17.61. per week.   This, he considered, went to show that the relative high level of Steel prices was not due to wages.   The figure quoted represented an average covering over 100,000 work-people engaged in the Industry; they wore, no doubt, actual earnings and not rates of wages, and did not imply a full working weekp   Belgian competition was making itself felt to a marked extent on account of tho depreciation of that country&apos;s currency; this had assisted to check the improvement which had made itself felt during November and December last.&apos; MEi. said t,liat ^fr0 ProSr03S which the ElectricalIndustry had made during the last six months of last year came to a standstill at the time of the general Election, and had not recommenced sinoo.   Generally, new business was not coming forward well.   Employment was not so far adversely affected, on account of works -undertaken, for example, by Railway Companies&apos;and Municipal Authorities with a view to helping employment.Export business was poor except to Australia and* Now Zealand.   The industry had suffered from tho Indian boycott, which had resulted in the placing of orders with Germany and Switzerland even where there was no advantage in price.
At the moment there was little unemployment in the industry, and hands were being taken on rather than dis-oharged, but this he regarded as a temporary phase and to be attributed (l) to   the Government, Municipal, and Railway contracts already mentioned, and (2) to the considerable volume of electrical work which was being done for the British Empire Exhibition,NON-FERROUS METALS.Mr. Tait wrote:-&quot;The following is a short report with regard to Non-Ferrous Metals: &quot;Copper.Consumption remains at much the same level, with a moderate trade in manufactured Copper goods, and a gooddemand for wire.   The rise in the market is more due to ex-pectations that the North American Copper producers will be obliged by the present prices to curtail their productionthan to an increased European demand, although there are some evidences of Germany re-entering the market in ex-pectation of a settlemtnt with Prance and a revival of herCopper manufacturing industry,&quot;Tin.The statistical position remains very strong and deliveries to the United States are estimated to be from 7,500 to  &apos;8,000 tons for this month.   The Tinplate industry in this country continues to be very active.&quot;Lead.The demand is abnormal.     The consumption of Lead in this country during the month of January was estimated*to be 21,000 tons, of which&apos; 9,000 tons went Into the sheet and pipe trade, which latter figure is a &quot;record&quot; for the past two or three years: and concurrently with this the --7-
cable makers have very large orders on their books and are buying Lead freely both for near and future delivery, &quot;Spelter,The consuming trades are absorbing fair quantities, but the position is not nearly as strong as In Lead,   The sheet trade on the Continent is active at the moment, but it is anticipated that reconstruction credits will be on a much smaller scale this year, and this will tend to release larger quantities of metal for this country    Any consider^-able widening in demand does not appear to be Immediately in prospect,&quot;Aluminium,The market in ingot metal continues f irmc.   There is also a good demand in the sheet trade to supply the requirements of the Motor Industry, and the demand for sheets and circles, especially in India, is strong0&quot;&apos;   TEXTILFS (WOOL).Mr, Andrews said that 5? col prices had been advancing; there was an improvement in the trade in Bradford; but perhaps this was only temporary0   The prospect was that the supply of raw wool would be insufficient to.meet the demands Before the war the situation as between supply and demand had balanced, but since, production had declined by 10$, while demand had increased by 10$,   The situation since 1918 had been relieved by the existence of large Government^ owned stocks of wool, which had prevented serious shortage, but he expected that a stringency in this direction would make itself felt during the next six months.,The remedy appeared to be that the Dominions should    * produce more wool: he had discussed this-matter with Sir James Allen, and also with Mr, Bruce and Mr.- Massey0 New Zealand was maintaining her pre-war production, and South Africa was also increasing her&apos;s a little9   The Australian-8- W.t&apos;
CONFIDENTIAL. 570production, on the other hand, had fallen off about 15 per cent. . on account of the drought, y/hich had resulted in the loss of a good many of this year5s lambs.   The effect of this would make itself felt next year also0On the whole, the Woollen Trade was rather better, TEXTILES (COTTON), &apos; Mr. Sutcliffe Smith desired to emphasize the seriousness of the position in regard to Chinese Trade Marks,   A case had corns to his notice recently In which a Russian had registered a British mark under the new Law,   When proceedings were instituted, the Court of first instance had maintained British rights, but this decision had been reversed on appeala   It was held that the original lodgment of a mark at Shanghai did not constitute registration.   The Bradford Dyers&apos; Association had some 500 marks which were thus endangered, and he thought that United States firms had also a large number.In the meantime there was nothing to prevent Germans and Russians from registering these under the New Chinese Law,,It was: his opinion that we must, of necessity, trust the Chinese a good deal in this matter, and he suggested that an attempt should be made to induce them to accept a British expert adviser, and to give some extension cf time.As regards Cotton Textiles, the situation in spinning was better than a month ago, and some 90% of Spindles were running; firms were, he thought, balancing their plant better, and were adhering to the 48-hour week.   There was new some life in enquiries from China, but the fluctuations&apos; of cotton prices were an adverse influence.   As a result of the wider   adoption in that country of European dress, there was now an increased demand for woollens, but here, again, French competition *was serious.In the manufacturing branch of the industry thesituation was by no means so satisfactory; out of 20,000 looms, about 8,.0O0 were idle, and those working were-9- ii
OONFIDSMTIAL.turning out goods at out prices.   He mentioned that the French now quote in sterling and yards, instead of in francs and metres as hitherto.textile interests were anxious for the early ratification of the Anglo-Polish Treaty, since the present situation gave an advantage to tho French.In Esthonia, our traders had, some  150,000 worth of goods which the Esthonians would not take up, nominally on account of the new tariff, but in reality probably through not wanting to take them up under present trade conditions.Mr. Fcrmtain explained that the Anglo-Polish Treaty was now ratified so far as we were concernedj but Poland was unwilling to bring it into force before ratification,, as other countries had done, such as Spain,; Finland and Gzecho-Slovakia,   ^ha Treaty had now to be laid before the Polish Diet,,   He doubted if the Poles were showing any preference W the French on account of the recent loan.Mr. Holroyd said that in the Cotton Trade short time had now again been organized&apos;! some 96 or 97 per cent, of firms were now working 27 hours a weeko   Demand Was not ^uch increased, but a better price was being obtained for their outputs,   Raw material prices declined by 3d. per lb. last month, but a further reduction was needed.There was a possibility of some difficulty in negotiations with the operatives, but he hoped that an agreed arrangement might be reached this week.Mr. Judgon observed that Mr, Holroyd&apos;s remarks applied only to the American section of the trade, and not to the Egyptian, which constituted 50 per cent, of the wholej the latter was working&apos;full time, while, aa regards the rest
of the trade, merchants, bleachers and dyers were also doing well.   The trouble was confined to the American section and was due to the high price of its   raw material.   Operatives in the American section had been working 3 days a week   He hoped that some improvement might result from the organisation of short time working. The price of American Cotton for October was quoted at 3d. less than for nowj this indicated that a big output next year was anticipated.   H9 would emphasize, however, that our chief   hope lay in the development of Cotton growing within the Empire.Many enquiries were being received, and it was clear that the world was virtually bare of stocks of. cotton goods, but was waiting for lower prices.SHIPPING AND SHIPBUILDING-.Sir Alan, Anderson said that In the Shipping Industry, though&apos;, the freight market had shown a certain improvement, the general condition was, and seemed bound to remain, badg there were too many ships and not enough trade. The amount of British tonnage which was unemployed had been reduced^ it now stood at about 1,000,000 tons, and there were still some 25?000 men out of work, in the industry, according to the Ministry of Labour!s figures.   There was some chance, however, that improvement, once it came, might be rapid.   Muoh of the laid-up tonnage was now out of date?   Shipowners felt, however, that tho late Government&apos;s policy of stimulating ship-building by loans was a dangerous one.   What the industry particularly required for recovery was poace and amity, both in    * international relations and internally in this country. They hoped to see some less expensive method discovered for settling strikes and a stabilisation of Continental currencieso
Sir Alan explained that his remarks had reference principally to the ordinary &quot;tramp&quot; in the freight market. Owners were now, it was true, beginning to undertake the building of special ships and the Lines were also rebuilding to some extent.   Many owners felt;1 however, that any artificial stimulus might well have the effect of discouraging normal building.COAL,Mr. Evan Williams wrote:-&quot;The position in the Coal Trade at the present moment is abnormal.   The demand exceeds the supply in many districts, due to the apprehension on the part of consumers, of a strike after Easter on the expiration of the notices to terminate the present Agreement. Prices are consequently rising.The outlook for the future, however, is not encouraging, particularly in the export trade.   The competition of American Coal is becoming keen in the Mediterranean and in South America.   In France there Is an organised campaign against the. importation of British coal and other commodities, and apart from this the increased output of the French pits and of the Ruhr makes France less dependent on British coal.    A similar effect Is being produced in Germany,   Conditions in the export trade are likely to be decidedly more difficult when the present wages crisis is over&quot;,GENERAL TRADE. Sir Eric Geddes said that the Branch reports received by the Federation of British Industries went
to bear out the remarks already made by Mr, Pease and the banking representatives.   A mildly optimistic tone was in evidence throughout the country.   A certain set-back had been produced by the Strikes, and a general uneasiness in regard to labour troubles still prevailed. Wage increases might make the position difficult in face of foreign competition.RUBBER AND TYRES.With regard to rubber, his own firm had a good line in the motor tyre industry.   Motor manufacturers had been, he thought, somewhat too optimistic, but their position was improving and people were now buying cars.   This, together with the demand for cycles and tyres, was a good barometer of trade - though, of course, it did not reflect prosperity among all classes.The principal difficulty which was being experienced in the tyre industry lay in the very large importation, which amounted to more than half the total consumption of tyres in this country,   British tyre manufacturers were cut out almost entirely from markets abroad,   His own firm had two factories on the continent: whereas they used formerly to supply the continental demand (except for France and Germany) entirely from Birmingham, they could now only do so from their French and German factories, and this was of course prejudicial to employment here.   Trade was Increasing at their Rochdale factory, but only for home business. They were attempting to promote a movement for buying British goods.   The Federation of British Industries felt that much could be done in this direction if the
CONFIDENTIAL. RUBBER - MERCHANDISE HARKS.Government could assist.In this connection he referred to the.Merchandise Harks Bill which had been under consideration by the late Government, which was intended to require the marking of goods with their country of origin: this would enable people to know if they were buying British goods.   A large measure of agreement had been reached in regard to this Bill at various conferences, and he hoped that it might be possible to proceed with it.The President replied that trouble in regard to proposals of this character would probably be encountered not so much in connection with manufactured goods as with agricultural produce.   There was a strong element of opposition in Parliament to the proposal for marking agricultural produce, and it appeared inevitable that much time would be lost in putting such legislation through.   The Merchandise Marks Bill, it is true, contained a good deal of non-controversial matter that could be taken up by this Government, as by the last, but it was not possible to prevent private Members from moving amendments which would rouse controversy. There was also possibly a risk that the marking of foreign goods with their country of origin might in some cases serve as an advertisement for the foreign makers. The proposed requirement that goods should be marked simply &quot;Empire made&quot; or &quot;Foreign made&quot; oould hardly be used to prevent a foreign manufacturer marking the actual country of origin on his goods if he wished to.        *The President promised, howover, that the matter should receive consideration.   In the meantime, there was nothing to prevent the Dominions from marking their goods &quot;Empire produce&quot; voluntarily.   The difficulty
GOHFIDHHTIAL.&apos; MERCHANDISE   MARKS.was to prevent foreign goods masquerading as British.Sir A Balfour said that the main point on whioh agreement had been reached in the discussions on the Bill was that foreigners should not be permitted to adopt British style, get-up and wording.   He was not in favour of tho general application of compulsory marking but held that some specified articles should bo required to be marked.GO -OPHRAT tj&quot;b   SOCIETIES. Mr. Gallagher   said that the Scottish Co-operative Wholesale Society produced some 50)&apos; of the goods which they distribute.   The Grocery trade had been good for a considerable time.   They were also large Millers, but this branch of their business was very quiet in Scotland at present.   In the Drapery branch, where also they wore large producers, fair progress was boing made, and there had been an impetus during the last few months to the demand for all kinds of ready-mades, - except the better class of Scottish tweeds, for which there wa3 very little request, largely because people could not afford the price.   There was a better demand for blankets, but the high level of.wool prices was an adverse factor.   The Furnishing and Cabinet Making trades were very quiet.   The Boot and Shoe trade on tho other hand had made progress.&apos; Taking the situation as a whole, there had been signs of a general improvement a little while back, but this had not bee&apos;n altogether maintained.   Competition was now much more intense than before.   The Society&apos;s business in Scotland was largely a reflex on working conditions on
CONFIDENTIAL. the Clyde, and Glasgow had been specially hard hit by the slump.   In fact, the Clyde had probably never been more idle than at the present time.   The anticipated orders for cruisers might ease the situation.   The coal trade in Scotland was good, but the iron and.steel trade was depressed.LEATHER. Sir Percy Denshan wrote:-&quot;I am glad to be able to report that the heavy-leather industry is, and has been for the last 3 months in better form than since early 1020.   Stocks of leather are low and the demand to-day is quite in excess of the output.    I consider that the output is in excess of 1913. Prospects are improving, unfortunate ly however the big advances which are taking place in all raw materials connected with our trade, make business somewhat difficult, as up to the present we have not been able to establish an advance in leather equivalent to the extra costs of hides and tanning materials.   The action of France in prohibiting the export of hides is very detrimental to us, as we are now prohibited from getting our supplies as pre-war from France, Germany, Austria, Hungary and Czecho-Slovakia.    In pre-war days our supplies from these countries were considerable&quot;

</content>
</cab>
