<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/6 images: 64-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1940.SECRET.Copy No.W.M. (40)114th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 114 (40).CONCL conclusions of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S. W. 1, on Tuesday May 7, 1940, at 11 - B0 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Sir&apos;Samuel Hoare,Secretary of State for War. Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Shipping (Item 7).Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chiefof Naval Staff.General Sir John Dill, Vice-Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl. R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. E. P. Donaldson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[21262]
WAR CABINET 114 (40).Contents.minute no.Subject.page 1      The Netherlands        ..................      51Allied Naval, Military and Air action in the event of a german attack on the Netherland Islands.2      The Air Situation      ..................      513      The Naval Situation..................      51Shipping losses.Degaussing of ships.British submarines.Magnetic mines.Defence of destroyers against air attack.H.M.S. afridi.Occupation of Iceland.4      Operations in Norway ...       ...       ...      ...       ...      ...      52Narvik area.Flying-boats Cabot and Caribou.Mo area.6      Norway ...      ...       ...       ...       ...      ...       ...      ...      531Allied assurances to President Hambro.Fighter Command.Bomber Command.Coastal Command.5Germany53Possible intentions.7The MediterraneanProtection of British shipping.53
TheNetherlands.Allied Naval,Military and air action in theevent of aGerman attackon theNetherlandIslands.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 109thConclusions,Minute 9.)The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 113thConclusions,Minute 1.)fighter command.bomber command.coastal command.1. The War Cabinet had under consideration a Report by theChiefs of Staff Committee (W.P. (40) 143).A record of the discussion and of the conclusions reached is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.2. The Secretary of State for Air said that there had been no enemy activity off our coasts during the previous twenty-four hours.A special daylight reconnaissance along the Friesian Islandshad reported 7 or 8 large ships at anchor near Norderney.A mine-laying reconnaissance had been undertaken during theprevious night, but owing to bad weather over the target area,the task had been only partially completed. One of the machinesengaged had been attacked by an enemy fighter 10 miles north ofWangeroog. The British air gunner had engaged the enemy whohad broken away.A photographic reconnaissance had disclosed the presence ofa cruiser of the Nurnberg class at anchor in a narrow channelbetween Norderney and Juist. A striking force of six Beaufortsand six Swordfish aircraft had been despatched to attack this cruiserat 2 a.m. that morning. The Swordfish machines had been unableto locate their target, but four of the Beauforts had succeeded in doing so and had dropped 2,000-pound bombs, which unfortunatelyhad missed.  One Beaufort had not returned.Special reconnaissance flights had been made along theNorwegian coast between Hardanger Fjord and Songe Fjord, and between Lister and Stavanger. Other flights had been made toEsbjerg and the Dutch coast.Two vessels resembling trawlers had been sighted about 40 miles north-west of Sylt and had opened fire on one of our reconnaissancemachines. Two bombs had been dropped but no results had beenobtained.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The Naval 3.   The First Lord of the Admiralty said that on the previousSituation. day the British ship Brighton (5,359 tons), bound from Immingham(Previous to Dunkirk, had been mined off Gravelines.   This ship had not reference:        been de-gaussed and had been in the danger area at the time.W.M. (40) 113thConclusions,Minute 2.)Shipping losses.Degaussing of The de-gaussing of ships was now proceeding very quickly and ships. about 1,700 ships had been fitted.   No de-gaussed ship had yetbeen mined.[21262]
Britishsubmarines.Magnetic mines.Defence ofdestroyersagainst air attack.H.M.S. Afridi.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 112thConclusions,Minute 2.)Occupation of iceland.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 113thConclusions,Minute 10.)A report from Sweden stated that the crew of a pilot steamerwhich had arrived at Goteborg had witnessed the capture of aBritish submarine by a German destroyer close to the 3-mile limit on the morning of the 5th May. The crew of the submarine was said to have been taken aboard the destroyer and the two ships to have sailed in a southerly direction. This report probablyreferred to H.M. submarine Seal, but the Admiralty doubted whetherit was true.One magnetic mine had been exploded off North Foreland anda total of eight had been found in the Would. Four of these hadbeen destroyed.All harbours had now been opened to traffic, except Blyth.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the Admiralty hadbeen considering the further protection of destroyers against air attack. It was proposed to increase their A.A. armament, whichwas inadequate for modern needs, by four additional Oerlikohguns.One petty officer and 55 ratings had been reported missing from.M.S. Afridi.H.M.S. Suffolk, with destroyers, and the large convoy of ships carrying troops returning from Norway, had arrived at Greenockshortly after midnight.A force consisting of 42 officers and 775 other ranks had been due to embark at Greenock at 7 o&apos;clock that morning for Icelandin H.M.S. Glasgow and IT.M.S. Berwick, escorted by the destroyersH.M. ships Fearless and Fortune. The force should arrive in iceland about 5 a.m. on Thursday.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Operations in norway.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 113thConclusions,Minute 3.)Narvik area.Flying-boatsCabot andCaribou.4.   The War Cabinet were given the following information : (i) H.M.S. Ark Royal should have been in position ready for operations in the Narvik area at daylight that morning.H.M.S. Calcutta had sailed and was expected at SkjelFjord on the following day and would provide anti-aircraft protection to H.M.S. Penelope which might, by then, be ready to leave. A shortage of oil had beenreported in the Narvik area. The oiler Broomdale hadgrounded the previous night, as had also a ship carryinganti-aircraft guns. These accidents would cause some delay.(ii) The flying-boats Cabot and Caribou had been destroyedby enemy aircraft.(iii) Anti-aircraft units had arrived at Narvik, and the PolishBrigade and Foreign Legion at Tromso and Narvikrespectively.(iv) There had been several air attacks on the Harstad-Skaanland area on the 5th May and frequent low flyingattacks on French and Norwegian troops in theGratangen area. The Air Staff thought that the largenumber of enemy aircraft which had been reported asflying in the direction of Narvik were probably carryingfood supplies for the garrison.(v) The situation on the Ankenes peninsula remained virtuallyunchanged. In the Gratangen area Shaufjeldet was reported clear of the enemy, who appeared to be retiringsouthwards. French troops were suffering severely fromfrostbite.
Germany. 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionPossible to telegram No. 55, dated the 6th May, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;intentions. Minister, the Vatican, reporting that the Vatican expected a(Previous German invasion in the west to begin that week; according to their reference: information this offensive might include not only the Maginot LineW.M. (40) 110th and the Netherlands and Belgium, but even Switzerland.Conclusions, The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Minute 6.)Norway.Alliedassurances toPresidentHambro.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 112thConclusions,Minute 5.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto telegram No. 482, dated the 6th May, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;representative, Stockholm, reporting that he had conveyed to theNorwegian Government the assurance requested by PresidentHambro that the Allies did not intend to abandon Narvik andNorthern Norway. President Hambro had welcomed this assurance,but was sceptical whether we could hold Narvik when we had captured it. He had added that German aircraft were able toproceed to Narvik with impunity, and that 100 troop carriers hadflown there the previous day.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Tne 7.   The Minister of Shipping said that since Thursday, theMediterranean. 2nd May, the Italian attitude in the Mediterranean, according to protection of reports received from the Foreign Secretary, had appeared to be british somewhat less threatening.   He was anxious, therefore, to obtainshipping. authority to allow a few selected ships to proceed through the(Previous Mediterranean, care being taken to choose those ships in the caseReference: of which the longer passage would be particularly disadvantageous.W.M. (40) 113th He had in mind particularly oil tankers proceeding from AbadanConclusions, (Persian Gulf) and ships from the west coast of India. In the minute 8.)        course of the next few days about 7 liners, 2 tramps and 2 tankerswould be reaching Aden.   The mail boats were at present being allowed to proceed through the Mediterranean.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, in the judgment of the Foreign Office, while it would be rash to make anyconfident prophecy, the action recently taken by the United StatesGovernment had had some effect, and he doubted whether Mussoliniwould attempt any desperate action in the immediate future. Whiletherefore he did not think that we should at once relax all ourprecautions in regard to shipping, he hoped that the Cabinet would approve the proposal of the Minister of Shipping and would permit a start to be made in passing a number of vessels through theMediterranean in both directions.Mo area. (vi) A report had been received from the Norwegian Legationin Stockholm to the effect that enemy mechanised troops were already in Mo and that already over one hundredtroop carriers had proceeded towards Narvik. Thereport should, however, be treated with reserve.It had also been reported that neither the railway from Namsos to Mosjoen nor the road had been destroyed.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.The First Lord of the Admiralty reported that a further telegram had been received from Lord Cork as to operations at narvik. A record of the discussion and of the conclusions reachedis contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.
The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he would raise noobjection to this procedure, provided that a careful watch was kepton the position from day to day.(Previous The Minister of Shipping said that diversion via the CapeReference: had been ordered the previous week. 190 British merchant shipsW.M. (40) 105th had been in the Mediterranean. At the present time, there were conclusions,      only 160 (including 19 Norwegian) ships.Minute 5.) The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Shipping to relax the precautionary measures at present in force, to the extentof allowing a number of British ships (which would otherwise have been diverted via the Cape) to pass throughthe Mediterranean in both directions. A careful watchshould continue to be kept on the position from day to day.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,May 7, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
