<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/48/0 images: 233-234</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(IIlJ)(XmiJ!I!:iS OT&quot; H)EilBTY OF HIS BRITAMIC MAJESTY?S GOVEl-iSLCT)TOR q^BIHIiSgOrganisation of. Irish Resistance to Conscript ion* Memorandum by the Chief Secretary?Reports have now reached mo from all tho Irish provinces of tho meetings hold during last wook-cn&amp; for organising resistanceto conscription.     The meetings were general in all parts of the country.     The. Romen Catholic priests wore in all cases foremost among tho advocates of resistances     Passive resistance is&quot;the course more generally proscribed.     In some cases, however, bieod-shod i3 looked for.     Priests in Antrim. Tyrone, Cavan and Donegal; Heath., Weetmoath fin numerous cases) and Wexford;.   Kerry fat various centres). Tippsircry, Gaiway end Sligo, doclarod their determination to join their parishioners and resist to the death.    Some of the meetings comprised several thousands of mm.     All wore attended by multitudes and most of thee shoved a formidable spirit.     In the Sorth tho constabulary reports speak in many oases of tho presence of Unionists as well as Nationalists in tho throngs^ who pledged themselves to rcsistenoo.     The Insp cetor-Goncral sees no evidence at present of any failure of loyalty on tho part of the constabulary, but is anxious   as to tho possible effect of the pressure which is being put upon them generally in public and by personal qppoul, tc induce them not to assist in any action for enforcement of Military Service,asAppended is a precis ot information gathered by tho constabulary to threatened action of Extremists in various parts of tho countryThe condition.make it clear to mo that the Minister of National Service should not move in any way with regard to Irclsjpd, except after close and careful consultation with the authorities of both the Constabulary and the Metropolitan Police.(Sgd.) H.B.Duko 8th April,1918
A P P 3 B D I X,Precis of Information.Kerry. (Caherciveen)   That on the passing of the ConscriptionBill Sinn Feiners will commandeer motor ears and cycles..Limerick. That conscription will he fiercelyresisted &quot;by all creeds and classes, and that Unionists are joining the Sinn Feiners.     That there will be a general strike of workers, bloodshed, and destruction of property.Cork 3. R. -      (Chnrleville)   That should conscription be enforced,the people Till evacuate seaports and concentrate and entrench themselves inland.Tipperary S.R.(Clonmel) The Railway Locomotive Staff have beennotified from the Headquarters of their Union , that they will be ordered to strike if conscription becomes law,.Kings Co. (Rhode &amp; Tullamore)    Conscription has caused a r-^nicin King&apos;e County, and respectable farmer?- ars now as hostile towards the police as Sinn Feiners;    also that Sinn Feiners &quot;contemplate rebellion and expect German help.     That on a signal from Lublin bridges will be blown up; workers will strike, etc.Louth. (Lrogheda &amp;   Lundalk)   That Sinn Feiners will dierather than be conscripted, and that Sinn Fein, railway and transport workers have been warned from 6, Harcourt St., to expect orders te cease work.Tyrone. (Omagh)      That if conscription is to be enforced,police barracks will be simultaneously attacked, and all police guides ^ith military pnrties for pointing out conscripts1 houses will be shot.

</content>
</cab>
