<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/48/0 images: 280-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government,]205 31Printed for the War Cabinet.   April 1918.SECRET.c-1V-hNAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION-No. 47. Pfeeyfc ewcfoZ 13th April, 1918.NAVAL OPERATIONS.Minelaying in the Heligoland Bight has been continued.On the night of 11th-12th April our monitors bombarded Ostend at long range.R.A.F. machines from Dunkirk, employed on Naval duty, have carried out a number&apos; of patrols and reconnaissances, the following being the principal incidents reported, other than those in connection with anti-submarine patrols : On 7th April four of our machines attacked 11 enemy aeroplanes over Ostend without decisive result, but one of our machines which left the formation 10 miles N.W. of Zeebrugge has not returned. -Three enemy destroyers also were attacked three miles N.E. of Ostend and one bomb, dropped from an altitude of 1,000 feet, exploded within about 40 feet of the vessels.On 11th April seven machines bombed Zeebrugge Mole ; bombs fell near two large ships lying close to a big railway seaplane shed, and one direct hit on the fortified harbour offices was observed. A bomb was also dropped near the hangar of the Bassin-de-Chasse at Ostend.On 12th April two of our machines were attacked by 10 enemy machines over Ostend. One of the enemy was driven down, but both of our machines, although hit, returned safely. Two bombs were observed to fall on the Mole, near the seaplane shed.On the same day four 230 lb. bombs were dropped between Zembartzyde and Westend, and a raid on Ostend was also carried out, four 230 lb. bombs being dropped on the railway junction north of the Bassin-de-Chasse, two 2301b. bombs east of the Hindenburg Battery, and fourteen 230 lb. bombs on the Mole, a direct hit being observed on a building east of the Mole.North Sea.Flanders area.On 7th April the armed escort ship &quot; Knight Templar &quot; was torpedoed about 114 miles Casualties, west of Vierge Island Lighthouse.   One officer and five men were killed, but destroyers and tugs rendered assistance and the^ship was brought safely into Plymouth.On 10th April the destroyer &quot; Magic &quot; was mined or torpedoed at the entrance of Lough Swilly and had her bows blown off, 23 &apos;of the crew being lost. She was, however, able to proceed under her own steam, and arrived at Rathmullen, where she was repaired temporarily.-   On 11th April the cruiser &quot; King Alfred &quot; when 30 miles horn Malin Head, was torpedoed and damaged, but was able to proceed to Belfast Lough for repairs.On 11th April P. 16 collided with a merchant steamer off Havre and was holed. On 13th April airship S.S.Z. 15 fell into the sea and was lost, about two miles S.S.E. from Exmouth, two officers and three men being drowned.(o1094)   55 4/18   has
ATTACK UPON ENEMY SUBMARINES.Submarines During the week under review from 13 to 15 large enemy submarines were located operating. and although the numbers are rather smaller than usual, they have shown greater activity and achieved a larger measure of success. Five of the large submarines were of the converted &quot; Deutschland &quot; type, one operating about 500 miles south-west of Finisterre one off Sierra Leone, another off Dakar, and the remaining two being homeward bound. In Home. Waters the scenes of greatest activity were the North Channel and off the Isle of Wight. The North Sea has been quiet so far as attacks are concerned, though several reports of boats on passage have been received from Fair Island.Actions The following Table shows the number of actions with enemy submarines in Homewith enemy Waters during recent weeks, and the nature of the craft which have been engaged, and su marines. ajg() ^ ^^gj. 0f submarines destroyed : 	Week ended	Week	ended	Week ended		Week ended		March 23rd.	March 30th.		April 6th.		1    April 13th.	Nature of Craft.	I							Actions. Results -   :	Actions.	Results. - -	j Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.T.B.D. and T.B..........	5        -	&apos;.    4		!     3		2	A.P. Vessels      .........	9   -!	8	1*	5		6	1Aircraft   ...		8	 	1	 	4	2Sloops and Patrol Boats	&apos;-.-. 4&apos;&apos; --	3	 	1	-	8	 -Merchant Vessels......	.4    ;   - .	2	-	 		1	 Special Service Ship	- i    !   __		- 			-.-	 Total	22        -	25    1	1*	10 i	_-   1	16	3&quot; Results &quot; indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.* This result lias been definitely established during the week under review.On the 11th instant one of the enemy submarine cruisers arrived off Monrovia, Liberia, and after communicating with the shore bombarded the French W/T Station and the town.Number and ton-nage of all vessels sunk.MERCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all Merchant Vessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action :-	British Vessels.				Allied and Neutral Vessels.				Total.	Week Ended	1.600	ions tn\ ss	Under	1,600 tons	] .600	tons gross	Undei	1,600 tons	All sizes.		and over.		0	ross.	and over.			gross.			No.	* Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Ton nage.	No.  &apos; Tonnage. 1		No.	Tonnage.1918,		-								March 2nd	12	50,319	6	5,529	5	16,985	10	7,171	33	80,004March 9th	15	44,103	3	1,824	6*	20,218*	10	4,955	34*	71,100*March 16th	10	42,767	6	4,624	14	36,170	8 &quot;	5,932	38	89,493March 23rd	15	56,664	9	6,262	10	34,834	12	5,402	46	103,162&quot;March 30th	5	16,109	fi*	2,616*	3	18,443	13*	2,925*	27*	40,093*April 6th-........ April 13th	...4	13,892*	.2	..     708	4*	10,575*	1	201	11*	25,376*	11	48,787	3	-    2,377 -	5 .-	15,066	u	2,406	24	68,636* Adjusted.
The table in Appendix I shows the uumbers and tonnage of sailings and of losses by Losses of enemy action, and the percentage of losses to sailings of British merchant steamships of Briti8^ . over 500 tons gross register ; and the table in Appendix II is a summary of those ?t*fm?hiP8 percentages for the last four weeks. m ra es&apos;The total tonnage engaged in Overseas trades continues at the high level of recent weeks, but the losses this week show an appreciable increase and include several vessels of somewhat larger tonnage than usual. The percentage of losses to sailings in Overseas trades is 2.22 as against .83 last week, and the percentages as regards Cross-Channel and Coasting traffic are .09 and .35 respectively as against no Tosses in the previous week, while as xegards all United Kingdom trades the percentage of losses to sailings is .93 as against .28 last week.vessels lost.The table in Appendix III is a comparative statement of all merchant vessels, Foreign Areas in as well as British, sunk, damaged, and unsuccessfully attacked in the last two weeks by which enemy craft and by mine, classified according to areas.The number of attacks made during the week shows an increase in almost every area excepting the Irish Sea and Bristol Channel and, in particular, the submarines operating in the Atlantic (Southern) area and South of Mogador have shown greatly increased activitv. It will also be seen that the attacks made by the enemy have been more successful than usual, since, while the total number of attacks have materially increased, the number of vessels at present reported as having escaped horn attack is the same as in the previous week..The total number of vessels of all nationalities which sailed to and from the United Attacks Kingdom in Overseas trades in the month of March was 2,086 and, of these, 1,837 (or 88 per on ygssds cent.) sailed in convoy and 249 independently of convoy.   Thirty attacks were made on enCTa(red in the 249 non-convoyed vessels, whilst of the 1,837 convoyed vessels only 17 were attacked Unitedwhilst in convoy, and 25 before joining or after dispersal. Kingdom. Overseas trades.The total number of enemy attacks made upon shipping of all nationalities during the Enemy month.of March was 213 as against 156 in February, and the following table shows the attacks in method and result of such attacks and classifies the vessels as to whether in convoy or ^arcj^ed not at the time of attack : Method and result of Attack.	Convoyed.	Escorted by A.P. Vessel.	Before joining, after dispersal, or ssparated from Convoy.	Unaccompanied.	Total.Sunk by :  Torpedo       ...... Gunfire Mine   ...	11 1	19 1	8 1	58 10 4	96] 12 M13 5JDamaged by :  Torpedo Gunfire Mine   ......... Aircraft or T.B.D	3 .1	8	5 2	10 2 2	26] 2 [ u-3f 2JEscaped from:  Torpedo       ...... Gunfire         ...... S/M encountered	2 3 .1	7	3 2 5	30 8 J 6	42] 13 y 67 12 JTotal      ......	22	35	26	130 i	213Although the percentage of attacks is very much less on convoyed than on non-convoyed vessels, the enemy, as might be expected, achieves a considerably higher percentage of success when he does attack convoyed or escorted vessels.(C 1094)
Result of The foUowing table shows the number of British steamships of over 500 tons grossattacks W^ were attacked m each of the last four Quarters and the percentage of such steamships &apos;    &quot;   &quot;   which were sunk, damaged, or escaped as a result of the attacks :-classified in QuartersPeriod.	Total	Percentage.			attacked.					Sunk.	Damaged.	Escaped.1917 2nd Quarter......... 3rd              ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 4th              ...      ...      ...      ......	657 418 370	Per cent. 50 53 55	Per cent. 7 9 14	Per cent. 43 38 311918				1st Quarter    ...   - ...	341	50	17	33The proportion of vessels sunk increased in the third and fourth quarters of 1917, but has now fallen to the level of the second quarter of 1917. On the other hand the proportion of vessels damaged shows a progressive increase. Probably some of these vessels would have been lost but for the increased efficiency of our salvage tugs.ENEMY MINES.Minelaying. There has been an increase in enemy minelaying activity this week. In Home Waters mines have been laid in the Peterhead, Harwich and Dover areas, and in Foreign Waters within British, zones of responsibility, in the neighbourhood of Havre and Alexandria.The approaches to Havre were heavily mined, no doubt in view of troop move-&apos; . *       ments, but the Port was closed, for only a few hours, and the clearing operations were completed-without accident to any vessel.   The mining at Alexandria, which is doubtless also aimed at troop movements, is now systematic.Casualties, The following table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed and British vesselssunk by mine in Home Waters in recent weeks : Week Ended.	-Number of Enemy Mines Destroyed.	Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.March 16th    ...   . &quot;...	,   34    -	2	Nil-       23rd	67	2	Nil30th    ...	33	Nil	NilApril 6th	24	Nil	Nil. 13th - &apos; .    - *&apos;   &apos;    -	54	Nil	NilA merchant ship has been sunk by mine in the Alexandria Channel, and the Destroyer &quot; Magic &quot; was damaged-in the entrance to Lough Swilly, probably by a mine, the release of which was delayed intentionally or otherwise. The risk of these mines must be accepted unless a port, which has been mined, is to be closed for an indefinite period.
DEFENCE AGAINST SUBMARINE AND MINE.The number of Vessels under organised Convoy and the losses sustained whilst Convoy, in Convoy during the last two weeks are as follows : 	Week ended		Week ended	Convoys.	6th April.		13th April.						No. of		No. of		Ships	No. Lost.	Ships	No. Lost.	Convoyed.		Convoyed.	Atlantic Trades: 			-	Homeward ...	150	_	132	2Outward    ..................	93		96	1Scandinavia Methil   ...............	66		90	French Coal Trade      .........	389		256	2Mediterranean Local -	186	1	246	3Total......	884	1	820	8Of the three Vessels lost in the Mediterranean, one was in the Alexandria Bizerta Convoy, one in the Milo Alexandria Convoy, and one in the Malta Milo Convoy.The position as regards the fitting of Merchant Ships for Defensive Armament is as Defensive follows :  armament.Number fitted during the week Total number at present fitted-Primary Armament.28 3.899Supplementary Armament.23 755The number of Howitzers and Bomb Throwers delivered to date is 929.1,681 Merchant Ships have been fitted with Otter Equipment to date, and the number Mine pro-of Warships fitted with Paravanes is now 377. &quot;tectiongear.MOVEMENTS OF ENEMY SHIPS.The number of enemy Merchant Ships trading between Germany and Norwegian Merchant-ports outside the Cattegat is still considerable, 11 such ships having arrived at, and. 18 meQ-having sailed from, those ports.   No enemy ships have entered or left Rotterdam.FOREIGN NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. Russia.The outcry caused by the Aliied landing at Vladivostok appears to be dying down, and it is reported that all sections of the population at Vladivostok feel more secure under the protection of the armed landing parties, and that the town is quieter than it has been for many weeks. The Allied stores at Vladivostok ai?e not being interfered with, but orders have been received from Moscow to send forward all Russian stores, including rolling stock, to Europe.The Archangel stores were still being removed up to the 3rd April, and no reply has yet been received to the Allied demand that these stores shall be retained at Archangel pending the arrival at that port of the food ships which are now at Murmansk, whence the expedition was to sail for Archangel on tho 17th inst.. The German forces in Finland are gradually converging on Helsingfors, and the German Fleet is reported to have entered the harbour without opposition on 13th April.(C 1094) A 3
All the big ships of the Russian Baltic Fleet have now been evacuated from Helsingfors &quot;to Kronstadt, and destroyers, submarines and auxiliaries are reported to have left Helsing-fors on April 9th and 10th for the same destination.Trotsky has been appointed Commissary of Naval Affairs, and is fully alive to the importance of restoring the fighting value of the Black Sea Fleet, Admiral Sablin, the Commander-in-Chief, having been given extraordinary powers to enable him to reintroduce discipline.   This fleet is to be reconstituted at Novorossisk in the Northern Caucasus.tItaly.On the 6th April an enemy Motor Boat raid on the railway north of Ancona occurred and one Motor Boat full of demolition material, and 6 officers and 55 men were captured after a hand-to-hand fight. An enemy Light Cruiser and 4 T.B.Ds. were sighted on the following day off the Coast.It is reported from Italy that, on the renewal of the enemy offensive on the Italian Front, a strong attack by sea is anticipated, and on this account 3 Battleships have been withdrawn &apos;from Brindisi to Taranto. During their passage to Taranto two of the escorting Italian T.B.Ds. came into collision, one being sunk and the other severely damaged. These boats were only commissioned early this year.France.On the 10th April the French destroyer &quot; Faulx &quot; was sunk by collision in the Straits of Otranto, but fortunately the casualties were very few.The &quot; Faulx,&quot; which was completed in 1912, was of 850 tons displacement and 32 knots speed.Spain.It is satisfactory to note that the crew of the submarine which last month put into Ferrol have been interned in the interior of Spain.* H.M. Consul at Vigo states that a German submarine is reported to have surreptitiously entered that port on the night of April 8th and communicated with the German S.S. &quot; Neidenfels.&quot; An enemy submarine is also known to have landed a German subject in the vicinity of Alicante about the same date, who, however, was promptly arrested by the Spanish authorities.German.It is reported that four naval craft are undergoing repairs at Ghent as a result of damage inflicted by bombs from Allied aircraft. This confirms reports already received of the success of recent bombing raids on Zeebrugge and Bruges Docks.Naval Staff,ISth April, 1918.[Appendices;
APPENDIX I.Statement of Numbers and Tonnage of SAILINGS and LOSSES of British Merchant Steamships, of over 500 tons gross for theWeek ended 13th-April, 1918.United Kingdom Trade.	Sailings.						Losses.						Percentage of Losses to Sailings.						In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.		No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	1 No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.Overseas         ........:      ...... Cross-Channel  ......       ......... Coasting.................. Total of all United Kingdom Trades	115 164*	528,217 749,927*	148 87* 342 371*	673,388 363,449*	1   263 251*	1,201,605 1,113,376*	3 1*	11,478 2,059*	3 2*	15,148 7,216*	6 3* 1 2	26,626 9,275*	2.61 .61*	2.17 .27*	2.03 2.30*	2.25 1.99*	2.28 1.20*	2.22 .83*	313 392*	559,922 645,589*		576,096 593,123*	655 763*	1,136,018 1,238,712*		-	1	986		986			.29	.17	.15	.09				_	577 554*	1,021,777 928,442*	-	-	-	-		3,627					.35	.36	 	 	 	 	1,495 1,568*	3,359,400 3,280,530*	 	 	 	 	9 3* 4 1*	31,239 9,275* 19,815 4,610*				 	.60 .19*	.93 .28*-	Losses on other Trades												t					Total Losses for Week..........											13 4*	51,054 13,886*						Previous week&apos;i figures.
sAPPENDIX II.Statement showing as regards British Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross sailing to and from United Kingdom Ports the percentage of tonnage sunk by-enemy action to tonnage sailing during recent weeks.United Kingdom Trade.Week ended 23fd Mar.Week ended 30th Mar.Week ended 6th AprilWeek ended 13th April		&quot;In  ...		1.05	.27	2.17Overseas       ... -  .........	... i	Out...	2.90	.92	1.99	2.25		^ Total	1.51	.99	.83	2.22		&quot;In   ...	2.16	 	 	 Cross-Channel............		Out ...	.32	 	 	.17		^ Total	1.25	 	 	.09Coasting        ...............	....	Total	AO	.52	-	.35Total of all United Kingdom Trades   ......			1.09	.53	.28	.93
APPENDIX III.Statement of the number of British and Foreign Merchant Vessels sunk, damaged, or molested during weeks ended6th and 13th April, 1918, according to Areas.Area.Arctic and White Sea Atlantic (Northern) .. Atlantic (Southern) .. Bay of Biscay Gibraltar Azores South of Mogador   ..North Sea    .....English Channel/British.. &apos;&quot;\Foreign/ British.. &quot;&quot; \ Foreign/&quot;-British... &apos;&quot;\Foreign/&quot;British.. &apos;&quot;&apos;\ForeignSunk.1,600 tons and over.Under 1,600 tons.Totals.Week ended   Week endedWeek ended6th April13th April6th April13th April6th April13th April/British.. &apos;&quot;\Foreign/British.. *&quot; \ Foreign/ British.. &quot;&apos;\ Foreignf British.. *&quot;\ForeignIrish Sea and Bristol Channel(British.. ForeignMediterraneanTotal 8    ./British.. &quot;&apos;\ Foreign/British.. **      &quot;&apos;\ Foreign44.1 3124 21152 1121 2134 22 24 314 10Damaged, but not Sunk.1,600 tons and over.Under 1,600 tons.Totals.Week ended   Week ended    Week ended6th April13th April6th April13th April6th April13th April3 1Unsuccessfully attacked.1,60Q tons and over.Under 1,600 tons.Totals.Week ended   Week endedWeek ended6th April13th April6th April13th April6th April13th April5 33 19 34 13 13 14 110 410 4Attacks.Totals.Week ended6th April2 16 110 119 10

</content>
</cab>
