<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/48/0 images: 325-330</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
is--CONFIDENTIAL.April 19th,  1918Political Intelligence Dcpar bm en t Foreign Office. UoS,A,/001.M E II 0 R A S D U I/&apos; onAlgHLOAJ   LA3CJH,Two items which have appeared in the dress during the last two days furnish a convenient   opportunity for brief comment on the labour situation in the United States as it affects Anglo-American relations at this moment,The first of these items is the remark reported to have been made by Mr,  James Wilson, of the American Patternmakers League, at the House of Commons luncheon on April 14th that &quot;there is only one labour movement dm America and that movement is represented by the American Federation of Labour&apos;-,The second   is the statement Issued by Mr. Appleton end his colleagues at New York, referring to the &quot;Extremists in the British Labour Party&quot; and implying that these &quot;Extremists&apos;&apos; had endeavoured to &quot;undermine the usefulness of the Mission and to delay the trans-port of men, of munitions and of food&quot;-.Mr. Apnletoivs mission has done excellent work in two ways.      It has gone far to counteract an impression which still lingered in the mind of many American employers and even of one or two officials at Washington - notably the Chairman of the Shipping Board - that the , industrial policy of British labour, as allied to munitions, ship-building and other war work,  is calculated to restrict and delay output.     The advice it has given has tended towards closer co-operation between the administrative authorities at Washington and the labour unions, on a more cordial basis than in the past. Secondly, the mission has done a good deal,  in centres like Chicago, to remove from the mind of the more radical section of American labour
- 2 -the idea that there is some fundamental divergence in war policybetween the British Government and&apos; a minority of British labourcn the one hand and the bulk of the British Labour party on the other,Similarly the labour delegation to this country of which Mr, Wilson is the head could certainly do great good in convincing British opinion of the fundamental soundness of American labour in its outlook on the war and in clearing up, as between the American Federation of labour and the leaders of the British labour party, the suspicions and misunderstandings which at present constitute an obstacle to any real mutual understanding of the political situation in the two countries.For these reasons it is the more regrettable that such statements as those of Mr. Appleton and Mr. Wilson should be made.   They give a wrong impression of the political situation in the two countries. They tend to confirm two views quite widely held in the United States. One is the belief of American Conservatives, including Mr. r-ompers, that a section of the British labour party, as represented by Mr* Henderson and Mr. Thomas, are putting Socialism before loyalty and class interests before the attainment of victory.     The other is the suspicion growing up among intellectual radicals as well as among the independent labour and socialist -groups., that the policy of the British Government if  only supported by a small section of con-servative labour leaders, while the great bulk of British labour has lost confidence in the Government and regards its policy, especially its foreign policy, as reactionary and undemocratic,The American Federation of Labour is, it is true, the one labour body in the United states strong enough to speak with some assurance for American labour as a whole.     Its loyalty has been of immense value to the administration and deserves the warmest recognition from the Allies.     Moreover i. , as is probable., it has within        -itself the seeds of progress, it will in the future maintain and
strengthen its position of leadership.     Other organisations suffer from many weaknesses.    Both sections of the now divided Socialist party - the pro-war and the anti-war sections - are led mainly by intellectuals.     The more radical groups of organised labour out-iside the Federation probably at present contain too large an elementof foreign-immigrants to lay claim to thorough &quot;Americanism&quot;.    Theviolent radical labour elements in the Far West; whioh are commonly,though erroneously,  lumped together under the name of the ICW.W.frepresent a definitely low grade of civilisation, and are incapableat present of high organisation or coherent action.But the Federations claim to speak-for American labour as awhole is of slight value when it, is   remembered that American la-bour is not a whole at all.     In industrial policy, in the crganisaption of war work, In the institution of wage adjustment boards andcouncils of arbitration, the Federation is indeed the only bodyable to assist the Government and the principles which it acceptsare the best that, as a general rule, can be applied not only toindustrial disputes in whioh its own unions are concerned but also tothose,  like the copper strike in Arizona,  occurring outside itsmembership and control.     Sven in this sphere, however., industrialpeace depends not a little on the mediation of intellectual- liberalsoutside the labour movement altogether who are often able to treatthe grievances and aspirations of independent labour with moreImagination and under standing than the Federation^ officials andwho are exempt from the suspicion, almost amounting to hatred, withwhich those Officials are often, and sometimes not undeservedly,regarded by the independents.x   But outside the sohere of industrial2&quot;--------------------------------------------------------------------------&quot;It must be admitted however that the presence of labour officials connected with the American Federation of labour on government boards does not always assist the government in dealing with certain classes of disputes.    ?or instance in connection with the Board of Control of Standards in Army Clothing, it was necessary to exclude such representatives from membership because of the presence in the production field of a s&amp;rong rival organisation&quot;.... \&apos;ehie Labour Problems in the United States during the War,
policy , American labour is not only not a whole;    it is also not distinct in its views or in the influences to which its mind res-ponds, from other sections of the pomi&amp;ation.     Mr. tempers, as head of the Federation of Labour, has pronounced in favour of the whole-hearted prosectrtion of the-war and in this he has responded tc, and represents, the great bulk df American feeling outside  as well as inside the ranks of labour.     But Mr. Gompers, as an English Jew by origin, surrounded by union officials of British or Irish Catholic stock, is on much weaker ground when he aspires, in his views on foreign policy and in his relations with the Labour and Socialist parties of Allied countries, to represent or dictate to the multi-farious elements of American labour -,the Russian Jews of the Clothing-workers&apos; unions, the unorganised Polish labour of the Pittsburg and Gary steel-works, the semi-submerged labour of the Chicago stock-yards, the New York East-side Socialists who have sent Meyer London to Congress, or even the ordinary American workmen of the Middle West.There has never been a political labour party in the United States. Labour has followed one or other of the two great parties or has, more recently, revolted from them into progressivism or socialism. The Federation has never even attempted to secure unity of political thought within itself since Mr. Gompers captured its &quot;machine&apos;7, its official policy has been strongly anti-Social ist but it still con-tains a group of moderate Socialists and many of its leading members, like Mr. Prey, now in this country, are more liberal a&apos;nd progressive than Mr. Gompers and probably agree with him on very few subjects. Politicians say that the members of the various unions very often vote at party elections solidly against their leaders .     The characteristic conservatisms and liberalisms of the American people have been shared by the American working man.    The Irish and Jewish race influences which have so largely affected American politics,
vnd the other European race influences, such as Polish and Bohemian, more recently introduced into the political field, affect him as they affect Americans in general.     The &quot;plain man&quot; in America, whether bourgeois or workman, has never thought about foreign politics and to a certain extent the Administration at Washington is preventing him from thinking freely at the&quot; present moment, but his attitude towards foreign Questions follows naturally from his general political tradi-tions.      It is not the object of this memorandum to discuss the tendencies of American opinion about war aims;   -that is reserved for more detailed treatment.     But it should be clearly recognised that the inevitable trend of American labour feeling on this subject is towards the policy of the advanced labour and Socialist parties in England and Prance,  if only because all formative currents of opinion in the United States are in the same direction.For instance,  it is not only the Hussian and Polish Jews of the Clothing-workers Unions who are in keen sympathy with the general ideals which they conceive to be those of the Bolshevists,     This is probably the tendency also of the whole body of Slav labour through-out the country;    it is the tendency of the younger intellectual radicals of the Eastern States, of whose meddlesomeness.Mr. Apoleton very justly complains;    and fundamentally,  in the long run, it is also the tendency of the mass of American &quot;democratic&quot; f-eling.     The average representative American of the Middle West may vt this mo-ment be chiefly swayed by resentment and contempt at the&quot;gullibility&quot; or the treachery of the Soviets;    the cartoons in the American press showing the Kaiser an in arm with Trotsky may adequately represent his feelings;    hatred of Germany and desire to win the war ere doubtless uppermost in his mind.     But he nevertheless instinctively expects has3 own Government and those of the Allies to supoort and save a revolutionary republic in Russia and he will not easily be able to understand any argument against this. .   He will respond
readily to any peace movement which he conceives to he &quot;democratic&quot;.Ho understands neither/problems of power in politics noi the economicimplications of revolutionary programmes, but his sympathies, oninstinctive human grounds, ate traditionally with the &quot;man againstthe dollar&quot;.     The Dre3idcnt was expressing these ingrained ideaswhen he startled sober opinion in tho Hast &quot;by his recent allusion,in a public letter on internal policy, to the &quot;economic serfdom&quot;of the working classes.All these tendencise ate those of American labour because theyare endemic in the American people.     At the present moment theyall make for a unified and unanimous war feeling, not least amongthe Russian Jewish working men and women already mentioned,     TheGerman invasion of Russia called forth from Mr. Hillman, of theClothing-worker^&apos; Union, one of the ablest labour leaders outsidethe Federation, his first whole-hearted pronouncement in favour ofthe war.     The final Russian debacle has even shaken anti-warSocialists like Morris Hillquit.     But this enthusiasm for war isnot one that Mr. C-ompers can lead.     It arises from sentiments whichhis conservatism cannot appreciate;    it tends to aims with which hecan have no real sympathy.    It will be led by the President, but, inorder to lead it, his programme of foreign policy will become in-creasingly radical and will go far over the heads of &quot;orthodox&quot;labour leaders.     He will either abandon his present attitude ofopposition to inter-Allied labour meetings on matters cf policy cr,more probably, he will carry further the attempts he has certainly aalready made to steal the thunder cf the Allied labour parties andto render inter-Allied labour meetings unnecessary by himself as-suming^the leadership of labour sentiment.     The development of thesituation is doubtless delayed by the military crisis in Prance butthe influence of that crisis on public opinion will be less absorbingin America than in Europe and it is to be anticipated that, in theabsence of public pronouncements by Allied statesmen, the prestige ofthe Allied labour parties, based on the programme of the inter-AlliedLabour Conference, will grow steadily with American labour during the next few months.

</content>
</cab>
