<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/48/0 images: 335-337</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;pa r TK,KJ m o i /./5S    flayafiMINISTRY OF PENSIONS Su^vsmary of Report for period from April 13th toApril 19th 1918.PENSIONSNumber of Pensions . 18.,807- pensions and allowances - a record number, have been granted during the week to Officers and Men and to Widows, children,and dependants. , The number since the beginning of the war is 1,269,979,2.        Pensions to. Soldiers. During the week,out of 6.,684 cases (including 265 rejected under previous Warrants) dealt with by the Awards to Soldiers Branch. 4961 were awarded pensions, permanent or temporary, 1680 w-;re granted gratuities, and 43 were rejected.3.        Pensions to Widows and Dependants^   During the week: 2269 widows (&quot;including unmarried A&quot; ivosT&quot; -2095 parents and 82 other dependants were awarded pensions and 3825 children were granted allowances.4.        New Scheme of Pensions to Parents. Under a recent concession the pre-war dependence of 108 parents who were in pecuniary need has, during the week, be^n raised from an average of 5/9 a week to an average of ll/8, whilst 151 Ainpensioned parents in pecuniary -rieed have been granted an average pension of 5/9 a week. 146 cases have been refused pension *5*        Alternative Pens ions,. Disabled men.   Up to date 23 permanent and 588 conditional alternative pensions have been awarded; this represents an increased charge of  27,705 upon the minimum pensions.   175 men under treatment and training are receiving alternative pension allowances.Widows.   Out, of 3252 claims for alternative pensions, there have been 1768 awards and 645 rejections.   This represents an increased annual charge of  30,654 upon the minimum pensions of these widows.6.        New Royal &quot;Warrants . The new Royal Warrant for Soldiers disabled, etc., in the present war and the Royal Warrant, for soldiers disabled, etc., in former wars were signed by His Majesty on the 17th instant and will take effect as from the 1st May.7.        New Order in Council. A new Order in Council for the pensions of sailors and marines and an Order in Council for sailors and marines disabled in former wars are being prepared on the same lines as the Warrant, and will also take effect as from the 1st Hay.8.        Pensions Appeal Tribunal. Since the 10th April, 21 cases of appeal for pensions have been decided in favour of and 2 cases against the appellant.9.        Retired, Pay to Officers. Nurses, &amp;c.*   Up to date, 1255 Army and Naval Officers (including Warrant Officers), 76 Nurses, 583 widows 532 parents   and 911 children of Widows of Officers (including VIarrant Officers) have benefited mainly by increases la rates of pension, from a review of their cases under the Officers&apos; V/arrant and Orders in Council of last year.
10,        Hospital Accommodation * At a conference between the Ministry and the British Red Cross Society, the Ministry was prepared i6 accept any available beds or to pay out of public funds, for annexes to existing hospitals *   The Red Cross are to ascertain, their available accommodation; when a further conference will be held.IX        ^Convalescent Treatment. The Treasury have been asked to sanction, the payment of 23/- a week for lodgings for men who are certified to need reBt btfore going out to work.12,        Treatment of the Deaf* A ciroular has been issued to all VJar Pensions Committees on the duties of the Special Aural Boards and the procedure to be adopted in the case of men discharged for deafness.13.        Treatment of Orthopaedic cases. A scheme has been proposed to establish an orthopaedic centre at Birmingham in connection with the Highbury Military Orthopaedic Hospital.14*       Neurasthenia oases In Homes of Recovery.   The Kareh return from these Homes shows 95 admissions and the discharge of 25 men as cured.   78 men refused or neglected to enter the Homes *   At the end of the month the patients numbered 176 and ther*e was a waiting list of 94*15*        Arrangements with Hospitals &amp;c* Arrangements continue to be made with Hospitals and other Institutions with respect to beds available, fees and other matters,16*        Numbers under Treatment * During the week 1687 cases were admitted for treatment in or at Institutions, and 14299 cases were under treatment, on that dote.   The total number of men reported as having been or still being under treatment is 26,905.TRAINING AND Si^LOYl^NT.17*        Trade Advisory Committees, On a ballot of the members of the Carpenters and Joiners Society a substantial i-Iajori^y were in favour of disabled soldiers and sailors being admitted into their trade.   The various Committees are taking an interest in their work.18*       Training of Canadian Soldiers discharged in England, Arrangements have been made to,train Canadian Soldiers discharged in England; reciprocal arrangements have been made in Canada.19.-        Training Schemes. 11 out of 19 Schemes submitted by V/ar Pensions Committees have been sanctioned.   60 individual cases   of training outside approved Schemes were sanctioned during the week,- and 244. men were admitted to and 103 discharged from training.   The total number of men under training at the end of the week was 3554.   Up to date 5683 men have been or are under training, exclusive of 672 nen training for munition work.20.        Employment of discharged disabled men.   Various Car Pension Committees have sent in resolutions containing suggestions on the subject.ORGANIZATION.
21. H. &amp; K.: V:&apos;.?.6cc (Committees) Act, 1917.      Supplementalschemes are being submitted by Local Committees.STAFF.22* Numbers of Staff.,The staff on the books of thoMinistry comprises &quot;543 men, 5485 v:omen or 5828 in all.20th ;-.pril, 1918.LiATTHEW NATHAN.

</content>
</cab>
