<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/79/6 images: 90-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALoplS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT Usi ns $^N COPY NOCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street on&lt;^^&gt; THURSDAY 2 AUGUST 1984&lt;JX? at 10.30 am[lor/j Hon viIn, . * of CouncilPRESENTThe//R&apos;t\Hon Margaret Thatcher MP v^/^jP^ime MinisterThe Rt Hon Lord Hailsham Lord Chancellor.jg. &quot; iion c *Ctar* of LGeoffrey Howe QC MPnwealth il3te for F reign and AffairsB&gt; He Rt Hon Leon Brittan QC MPetary of State for the Home DepartmentIL*1 Hon f thon MPe ExchequerCreta^ofa^.Pri r MPte for Northern Ireland\ . &quot;* State for Defence S^*1 H^^ofS^1 Heseltine MPa^ of S0las Edward MP State for Wal(on Sir Keith Joseph MPof State for Education and ScienceThe Rt SecretaryThe Rt .Hon Secretaryeter Walker MP State for Energye Younger MP tate for Scotland.es.    ^ of ^ Tehbit MP?e Rf , Ste f r Trade and IndustryP  ft*The Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MP Secretary of State for the EnvironmentThe Rt Hon Norman Secretary of State foang mpState for Employment y  TreasuryThe Rt Hon Lord Cockfie Chancellor of the DuchyThe Rt Hon Michael Jopling ME//2 Minister of Agriculture, Fish-^ial Servicesasteres) and FoodThe Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP Secretary of State for Transport&lt;4S7/CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALSir Michael Havers QC MP eral (Item 5)THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTitem1,3.The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP Parliamentary Secretary, TreasuryMr John Gummer MPMinister of State, Department of Employment SECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMr P L Gregson     (Items 3-5)Mr B G Cartledge (Items 1 and 2)Mr M S Buckley     (Items 3-5)Mr G Stapleton     (Items 1 and 2)CONTENTS SubjectForeign affairsHong Kong COMMUNITY AFFAIRSCommunity Budget and Unifs^d INDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSCoal Industry Dispute ECONOMIC AFFAIRS .Privatisation of British Telecom l/yyUnemployment CIVIL AVIATION AUTHORITY REVIEWPagegdom RefundsiiCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL1.     THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Cabinet would wish to welcome the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary on his return from conducting a very successful negotiation in Peking on the future of Hong Kong.rHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY, reporting on the progress and :come of the negotiation, said that the most difficult issue had that of the location and other arrangements for the proposed Anglo-Chinese Liaison Group.   After hard negotiations on and until midday on 29 July, the Chinese had finally moved to^rdi\the United Kingdom position.   The outcome had been agreement thai^H^Joint Group would operate on terms of reference very close to thp^^pxoposed by the British Government; that the Joint Group would fSwe located in Hong Kong until July 1988; that the functions of the G^Aip^would be divided into two equal periods; and that the Joint Gro&quot;STwould continue to operate until the year 2000. The Executive Council (EXCO)  in Hong Kong attached particular importance to this last provision, since it was perceived in Hong Kong as Providing some askance of continuing British involvement there after 1997.The high priority questions relating to achieve agreement major outstanding issu which made the main Agrthe Chinese had attached to resolving the Joint Group had enabled the British team eptable terms on virtually all the other ese included the adoption of language iftep &gt;and its Annexes equally binding; the provision that the ma^^Ag^eement and its Annexes would be stipulated in the Chinese B^J^ALaw; specific acknowledgment in the Agreement that the United Kr^fafi^ould remain responsible for H rig Kong until 1997; and the\ e o&lt;fBl of some prejudicial language concerning sovereignty from the&lt;&amp;ip*se draft.    The text of six of the Annexes to the main Agreement$*ad xow been virtually agreed, although hard work remained to be d^e^Jf the others, in particular those concerning land, nationality a the prospects were reasonably good,meet our requirements concerning f reedoVo^movement in and out of H ng Kong. &lt;&lt;^Tti sum, it could be said that a breakthrough in the negotiations had  een achieved: a number of rocks still lay ahead.yil aviation.   On nationality, e Chinese seemed likely tout they were fewer and smaller than had earlier seemed likely.   EXCOT^to whom he had reported on his way back from Peking, had reac^fevourably; Sir S Y Chung had been generous and statesmanlike(f^s attitude and had been supported in this by Miss Lydia Dunn.Summarising his impressions of the negotiations in Pelt and Commonwealth Secretary said that the role of the O Minister, Mr Zhao Ziyang, seemed to have been crucial. ^ who had conceded the final six months of the delay in loc^ Joint Group in Hong Kong, and who had confirmed the specif. Provisions concerning its functions.   He had also met the Chi  f the Central Advisory Committee of the Chinese Communist Pa^  eng Xiaoping, who had interrupted his holiday for theirCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL231 July.    The first half hour of the meeting had been given over to the discussion of East-West relations.   When the conversation eventually turned to the subject of Hong Kong, Deng Xiaoping had spoken at length about his concept of two systems in one country; Le had also voiced all his familiar fears concerning the period fore 1997, including the possiblity of a flight of capital from Kong.    The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary had done his best move these apprehensions, and to implant in Chinese minds the at movement of capital depended not on assertions by statesmen &quot;the decisions of individual investors: hence the importance of mair^HrMng the attraction of Hong Kong to investment during the period^ffore 1997.   Deng Xiaoping had said with solemnity that in_ the co&amp;Siyof the negotiations concerning Hong Kong, the Chinese side had take^A^ecision to put its trust in the British Government.The Foreigr)and Commonwealth Secretary said that one advantage of the proposed Joint Group would be that it would provide opportunities to educate the Chinese in the operations of capitalism. Current developments in ffiTn itself might assist this process.   He had heardvabout the success of the new agricultural sing prosperity and economic weight of the Example, created surplus demand in the significant shift was taking place ina great deal in Policy and of the Peasants which had,x construction industr,. inese economic perceIn discussion, the follownts were made -a. The British Governme^Ak deep concern that it might not be able to discharge adequa^ly its duty to the people of Hong Kong had now been gre^Waased.   Although predictions that the Chinese would be ton^nyp to and beyond the eleventh hour had been vindicated, their^tfsast had nevertheless beenwon.b. The change in Chinese economic/attitudes provided important opportunities, in particular to the United Kingdom which would be working closely with^he Chinese during the transitional period in Hong Kong before 1997.    The United Kingdom would have a chance to exert influence on Chinese thinking on wider issues as well, at a tim^TJh^en China&apos;s fear of the Soviet Union remained obsessivvi^u^when, equally, the Chinese Government did not wisn/ro~h\2 associated too closely with the United States.    The negc4* U*^n, although   it   still had to be brought to a succ6^s^i&gt; conclusion, was the most substantial and importajy the Chinese had engaged with any foreign, let alot Government.    The period following an agreement, in Chinese themselves clearly visualised wider contacts&apos; the United Kingdom, could offer significant commercial well as diplomatic opportunities.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALc.     Although there could be no effective insurance against an adverse shift in Chinese attitudes after 1997, the fact remained that Hong Kong had survived until now only by virtue of Chinese tolerance and of Chinese respect for the existing Treaty despite their reservations concerning it.    In place of the Treaty, there would now be a solemn Agreement.    It was significant that Deng Xiaoping had referred frequently, during the latest discussions, Ta iwan.THE &lt;3&amp;LMk&gt; MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that although some i^au 5, such as the problem of nationality, still had to be resolv 3*^rt now seemed that the Chinese were prepared to accept an agreemen^/^p/a considerable extent on British terms; this was a matter fd^considerable satisfaction.    The United Kingdom had won Chinese trirst and this offered important opportunities for the future, It would be essential, in any public comment or statement before the Agreement was concluded, for British Ministers to avoid going beyond the terms of thevfo teign and Commonwealth Secretary&apos;s statement to his press confer^rjc^^o Hong Kong on 1 August, which represented the limit of what coulo(oe)Jsaid in public at this stage.   The text of that statement, whr 3^v|u5 being placed in the Library of the House  f Commons,  should be^Vyr Ulated to all members of the Cabinet.The Cabinet -Took note with approval^/)&apos;the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary&apos;s negotiatioivs-^rWleking and of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up oi.scussion,s&lt;unche 32-     THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SEC^TARY reported that there had been no further developments on the G^t^sion&apos;s proposals for a _ _ supplementary Community budget for 198ti%*pe the regrettable decision of the new European Parliament to hold u^the transfer of the funds for the United Kingdom&apos;s 1983 refund fromC&gt;the reserve chapter of the 1984 budget until the supplementary budget was put to it.The Cabinet -Took note.CONFIDENTIAL
Hutethe latest position in the coal industry dispute, discussion is recorded separately.CONFIDENTIALTHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR ENERGY reported to the Cabinet onThe Cabinet&apos;s.1 ritishSi 6rebC CTHE SECRETARY steps in the privat The previous day Industry (Mr Ba^ef) which would be a _ in BT when privati change from that o the Companies Acts Telecommunications, On 20 August a subs preparation for theOF STATE FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY isation of British Telecom (BT) Minister of State, Department had made an announcement about to telephone subscribers t At the weekend, the status lie corporation to that ofa1thfe/fre^Vegulatory body, would tantralVa^ertising campaign wou f lotasaid that important were in progress, of Trade andthe incentives o take up shares of BT woulda company under Office oftake up his duties. Id begin inThe Cabinet -!      Took note.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENTS^ statistics published that day would, sho, &quot;headline&quot; figure and 16,000 in the seapublic comment he would acknowledge that   *&quot;&quot;= *   &quot;J-0 hut explain that they were difficult to interpret because the seasonal adjustment might not properly reflect cuxrent patterns school leaving and the effect of the Youth Tra draw attention to the encouraging figure for v risen on a seasonally adjusted basis for five sue the fact that the level of unemployment was partly increase in the numbers becoming available for work and othethat the July unemployment ise of 71,000 in the ally adjusted figure. In e figures were disappointing,-r reasons, to the good prospects for the econ extent to which strikes put jobs at risk.The Cabinet -2.     Took note.mScheme.    He would which had e months, to esult of an ographic d the
CONFIDENTIALCabinet OfficeAugust 19845CONFIDENTIAL88
CONFIDENTIALkIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO 1 4CABINETHum&apos;TRIALRSV 28thLIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEX CC(8A) 29th Conclusions, Minute 3 ^Thursday 2 August 1984 at 10.30 amromTHE SECRETARY OF numbered 20 with with some produc three pits with / interpret the tr _ evidence that grou work shortly.    A s Glen pit in Scotland return to work after existent both there andSit depot where there had pre It was thought that the to around 3,500 compared with Problems over the running of Nottinghamshire coalfield, the Power station coal stocks had beSTATE FOR ENERGY said that pits fully working a further 26 on holiday.   There were also six pits &gt;et^ with a further three on holiday; and there were workers in attendance.    It was difficult to attendances because of holidays but there was miners in various localities might return to tendance had been maintained at the Bilston was hoped that a further 12 miners would end.   Picketing was now light or non-er sites such as the Orgreave coke been heavy and violent picketing, jber of active pickets was currently arlier in the dispute. Despite ains and the holiday in the been substantial coal deliveries, ^ru^\down by 220,000 tonnes in they%Previous week. ^THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT&apos;S* brought against the South Wales area of Mineworkers (NUM) by two road haulage c had failed to pay a fine of  50,000 for c_.time set and sequestrators had been appointed to seize their assets. The sequestrators would probably be able to carr without entering the South Wales area offices had been mounted.    The fact that there had rec_. Picketing at Port Talbot suggested that the Sout trying to avoid further breaches of the injunction them.   The NUM President, Mr Scargill, had met othe union leaders the previous day and there might bed__.^ support of the NUM and against the employment legislat had referred publicly to the decision of the Wembley Con Trades Union Congress (TUC) to give fraternal support to affected by the employment legislation.    The authorisati-.. support was a matter for the TUC General Council and had to conditional on observance of the TUC disputes procedure cover batters as the number of pickets.   It was not clear whether Mr _ would wish to bring the dispute within the official ambit of thethat, following the action  National Union of ies, the South Wales area tempt of court within the&gt;ut their duties a demonstration en little or no area might be d against wing trade ions inScargill of theCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE HOME SECRETARY said that the figures for arrests in connection with intimidation had increased markedly, possibly indicating a greater readiness to report such offences.    It vas thought that the police now had intimidation well under control in Nottinghamshire ut there had been a less effective effort in Derbyshire, possibly &quot;ause of local problems with the Police Authority, and he was ng whether anything could be done to improve the situation.RETARY OF STATE FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY said that the British oration (BSC) was faced with delicate situations both at and at Hunterston.   At Immingham the training of dockers ront loaders for the handling of iron ore would be 8 August.    The dockers had indicated that they would t no iron ore trains would be available because of action by the rail unions.    If the dockers refused toprocedures under the National Dock Labour Scheme would take their course during the remainder of the week.    The Scunthorpe Plant had enough &gt;xon ore to last until some time in September, theg on the extent of deliveries through small At Hunterston a coal ship would be docking at e coal could be delivered to Ravenscraig cease operations within about three weeks, only in moving the coal within the hold cent of the coal could be unloaded BSC Chairman, Mr Haslam, would s to be taken locally and also the courts, and would be in touch taken.   He would in turn keep in cerned.    The undesirability of docks was well understood.precise date dep( wharves on the the weekend. Unl that plant would h Lock workers were in of the vessel and some . without their assistanc consider very carefully t_ advisability of civil acti with him before any decisi close touch with other Minist Precipitating industrial actiTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the dp^ssion, being, it would be appropriate for Mm* Public comment.   The main message to no industrial reason for the strike. * Coal Board, Mr MacGregor, had put out aexplaining how well the closure Procedure^..-- - * pNo Government had done or could be expected to have don support the coal industry and to ensure that miners we. and had the benefit of generous redundancy term on strike had been deprived of a ballot.    It snw clear that the motivation for the strike could on Throughout August the Secretary of State for Ener _ for daily meetings, chaired by a Department of Ener^ which would be attended by representatives of the Dep concerned.   A written report would be &quot;r^f*^ to members of the Ministerial Group on Coal (MISC 101). use in the media would be agreed daily and guidance could ^ Ministers from the Department of Energy and the Press 10 Downing Street.said that, for the time s to adopt a low profile in across was that there was irman of the National tement the previous day had worked in the past.e miners still erefore be made political. arrange ster,s mainly eeting for tainedCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALThe Home Secretary, the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretaries of State for Trade and Industry, Employment and Transport would ensure that a Minister from each of their Departments was available in Britain at all times throughout August to receive &quot;eports and take part in whatever discussions, by telephone or at tings, were required.    If, during her absence, it was essential the Ministerial Group on Coal to meet to consider an issue of the Lord President of the Council or, if he was unavailable, e Secretary, would chair the meeting.ftie^Cabinet -TSo^ote,Cabinet Office 3 August 1984CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL,THlS D0CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO20CABINET8&amp;*LIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEX CC(84) 29th Conclusions, Minute 5 ,c:\^&gt;Thursday 2 August 1984 at 10.30 amn V -The Cabinetrconsidered a memorandum by the Secretary of State for Transport (C(84) 21) on civil aviation.THE SECRETARY OF| Aviation Authori--, privatisation of B development of the had proposed that BA Manchester and Birmin, Europe; between Glasgow an between Heathrow and Haran Portugal, Gibraltar, Italy Birmingham routes, which wou concerned would be likely to (BCal).   When the Ministerial Sub-Committee on Economic Arrairst^ majority had favoured rejecting transfers.   When the conclusions OlCabinet on 19 July the Cabinet ag Exchequer hadcompromise which would provide for an   g&lt;^hanceUot of the Excheq BCal.   After discussions wh-b he and    ^ he ,ad cone uded that^ held with the Chairmen of the two        DiscuSsions with ^ compromise transfer could be agree* the^rder of impBCal, Sir Adam Thomson, ^d established ^ BCal of the routes in question waE FOR TRANSPORT said that on 16 July the Civilhad published a report on the implications of the Airways (BA)-for competition and the soundairline industry.   Among other things the report relinquish scheduled service routes out of wide variety of destinations in Western ris; between Heathrow and Saudi Arabia and between Gatwick and points in Spain, ndinavia.    Apart from the Manchester and to smaller airlines, the routes ded by the CAA to British Caledonian Committee on Economic Strategy, had considered the report, a endations regarding route ub-Committee were reported to the the best solution would be a transfer of routes from BA to1.Saudi Arabia (estimated profit for 198Harare (estimated profit of  7i million) 30 million)y Routes from Gatwick to Madrid, Lisbon, Barce (estimated profit of  3 million).HeXf       ^ed that Sir Adam Thomson was not interested in the o mo     a^ was offered these routes, it would probably be able mo      needed for the investment they would require.    They wouia. baseP .y~type profits to BCal, and by strengthening the airline ^  lve it continuing financial strength to compete with BA ancCONFIDENTIAL92
CONFIDENTIALairlines.    BA claimed that the transfer of routes would delay Privatisation.    His financial advisers (the merchant bank Hill Samuel) believed that this was true of the routes to Saudi Arabia and Harare, _ but not of the Gatwick-Iberia routes if BA showed goodwill.    In his view t might also be possible to transfer the Harare route with such goodwill. Chairman of BA, Lord King, and his Board were absolutely opposed to sfer: he saw no prospect of the Board voluntarily changing their }ion.rnaent thus faced a choice    On. option would be to reject the pf t. suggested by th .CAA an d  gu. that th ey vou ^ ig_ compet it ion in the airline inauscry.    d^i r  ek a^^r with BA.    If this were denied, the Ylow ^t be iSfv* expand.    If it then, for other reasons, ran into cash flow Problems^might have to go out of business.    This would J&quot;ve only one ^Jor BritSh scheduled international carrier   reduce the pressure on BA ^ be efficient, and make it harder to liberalise aii&quot;ansport in Europe. The alternative waste insist on the transfer of su&quot;1^e^er r^esC ut of strengthen BCal&apos; *^P%tion.    A possible package would be the routes out Gatwick to Madri^LJKpn, Barcelona and Bilbao, plus the Harare route from Heathrow.   T?^ld require the Board of BA to show P, c Practical co-operaXs^d the Board of BCal to accept that the P^kage was adequate     It wou^fenecessary to see whether the two parties couiaauequace.    it WOUWI/S%, iBa kofarp a final decision was made,be persuaded to accept $  N:ompromise before a tinai  ^ that it would bypass ParliaS^s It was conceivable   but in his Pinion unlikely, that the Boa^/56 night resign.    There might dama-&apos;gmg adverse reactions from t\iff.In his view, the Government would ^^^^-^rrnaeprndent&apos;airlinfs &quot; a  in response to the CAA s &quot;COmmerfg^S.    in   succ; fuily against a s*w little prospect of their being ^/^^^^ airline was already Privatised BA of its present size and s**? gt &apos; ^ Governmentbeginning to behave aggressively in impotent   kets. ^ uld well find itself obliged, when BA was P&quot; &quot;&quot;*^&quot;^ order to -rline to retain a substantial part of the -^^ovlde some form of lengthen its balance sheet; it might also  vep*^P ^ actionsindemnity or other financial support in tne rac^&gt; n.r Airwavs. Such ln the United States arising out of the collapse.     of BA&apos;S ^tion would be criticised as an unfair further en   |   Qr allAlready dominant position.    If, as was quite ^^fff^^^s, the Jritish airlines in competition with BA were driven rance ofGovernment would be regarded as having connived at tn*&lt;^ $   hilosophy. ^petition.   That would be entirely contrary todiScussi0n, some members of the Cabinet considered that transfers proposed by the CAA would do nothing &quot;foster gen &apos;^petition: they would simply transfer monopoly rights from c  another.    Their main effect would be to &quot;&quot;^^^^^ t  ^rseas competitors.    No doubt BA would be likely to dominCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALlngdom airline market and to behave more aggressively once it had been Privatised; but that was inherent in the existing situation and in the vernment&apos;s decision, which was not in dispute, to privatise BA. Other ^embers of the Cabinet argued that the ability to earn monopoly-type |r fits on overseas routes was a precondition for effective competition on [se routes which could be flown by more than one British airline. It &gt;essential in the interests of competition to ensure that the United &quot;lorn had at least one international carrier other than BA.wing main points were also made -e legal actions in the United States arising out of the e of Laker Airways were a serious complicating factor. Theential liabilities involved were of the order of $2 billion, no doubt, as was common in the American courts, the claims n greatly exaggerated.    The existence of these potential liabilities might greatly delay the privatisation of BA by deterringprospective this: the G, would both difficult to the potential possible to rea a satisfactory so in the first half turned down the CAA&apos; privatisation of BA event precluded by the this it was argued that take a long time to resol to defer a decision on the had been cleared up.estors.   There were possible measures that might avoid ent might give an indemnity to BA (though this erious difficulties of principle and make it more the actions quickly and at a reasonable cost); ity was an insurable risk; and it might belements out of court.    It was not clear whether could be found in time for a flotation of BA The Government would be criticised if it sals in the interests of early find subsequently that this was in any ctions in the United States. Against inties over the legal action could was neither necessary nor desirable. CA^s&apos;Cproposals until those uncertaintiesh.     The Government had given c&lt;$d i m nts, both in Parliament and to the management and workforce of B^Wtopthe effect that BA would be Privatised in its present form, anoV^hat there would be no arbitrary reallocation or hiving-off of routes^  Moreover, the staff of BA had heen induced to accept heavy redundancies by, among other things, assurances based on the Government&apos;s commitments.    It would be difficult if not impossible to reconcile tk^froposals of the Secretary of State for Transport with thos(a_ asisurances and commitments.xercise of the was issued refuse to their s. Thec.     It was possible, though uncertain, that^ Government&apos;s powers as sole shareholder, an inst^ to the Board of BA to relinquish routes, the Boar accept it on the grounds that it would entail a brea fiduciary duty to future shareholders and present e: matter could be put beyond doubt by inserting an appr provision in the Articles of Association; but that woulbebtedlyvery contentiousCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALd.     Although route licences were not property (they could not, for example, be bought and sold) they were nevertheless valuable assets in that they provided opportunities to make substantial profits. Some members of the Cabinet argued that it would be difficult to justify the arbitrary transfer of such assets from the public sector to a private company without valuable consideration.   The Government was, in effect, a trustee for the taxpayer and should not simply )give public assets away.    It had sharply criticised, and promoted ^gislative action against, such behaviour by the Greater LondonAt the very least, it would be essential to secure clear^ explicit Parliamentary approval for the transfers.    Against this, fis pointed out that it had long been public policy that route r%33n es were awarded and transferred without payment.    BA had not pai^W&gt;the licences which it held; and BCal had been brought into existence by the award of licences.Even if the view was taken that the transfer of routes wasjustified, was arguabl Position to1 antagonise th&quot; serious public^ substance.^BCal was awarded the relevant licences by the CAA, it it the airline would still not have a strong enough ;e effectively against BA.    The transfer would thus rd and workforce of BA and expose the Government to :ism without achieving any useful.result ofe members of the Cabinet chought that it wasn proposed by the Secretary of State for nsferring additional routes, such as those , however, thought that BA would be kthis that it was not a practicalf.     For that reas necessary to go furtl Transport and to aim to Saudi Arabia. Othei bound to object so strong course of action.There was much to be sarO^subjecting the airline industry, to scrutiny by the Office of Fair^fr^ing and the Monopolies and Mergers Commission, rather than the CAA^ajSfccularly as regarded competition on domestic routes. The CAA&apos;s afp^cA was to allocate rights according to its own view of the d&amp;frable structure for the industry rather than the requirements of the^harket.PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the Cabinet&apos;wereunable to reach a decision.   They would return In Preparation for that the Secretary of State Prepare a further paper.    This should assess th Proposals for route transfers would have on the vA th-e other United Kingdom airline companies and how w uld in practice significantly improve competition United Kingdom consumer, and strengthen the United Ki..^-, industry as a whole against foreign competition.    The pap set out in detail the steps which would need to be taken, use of the Government&apos;s powers as sole shareholder in BA legislation, to effect any route transfers, and assess the ch*Uenge to such action.    It should consider the P liamenta ^Plications, including the possible attitude of the Public Ac Conanittee to the transfer of assets from the public sector to Sector company without recompense; and all other relevant considee issues in September, ransport shouldwhich the various y of BA, BCal and such transfers benefit of the irlineould also er by theCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALThe paper should in addition set out the situation on the legal actions in the United States with an assessment of the likely timetable and outcome, and of the steps open to the Government to deal with the situation. She .would arrange for a small group of Ministers under her chairmanship to \ive preliminary consideration to the issues before the Cabinet resumed \rr discussion.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;s g up of their discussion.reed to resume their discussion in September.J   preparation for that discussion, invited theSecretary of State for Transport, in consultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry and the Attorney General, to circulate a/^ape)r on the lines described by the Prime Minister in\Wr&gt;^S3Knming up.Cabmet OfficeAugust 1984CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
