<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/89/0 images: 34-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1957SECRET Copy No.C (57) 20813th September, 1957CABINETREDISTRIBUTION OF seats memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department and theSecretary of State for scotland. Together with the Chief Whip we have now held the further discussion withthe Leaders of the Opposition Parties authorised by the Cabinet last autumn (CM.(56) 70th Conclusions, Minute 5) on our proposals for amendments of the Houseof Commons (Redistribution of Seats) Act, 1949. A note of the discussion is annexed.2.   Our conclusions on the points raised in the discussion are as follows:  Intervals Between the Reviews of Constituencies3. We are satisfied that section 2(3) of the 1949 Act is wide enough as it standsto enable a Commission to recommend major alterations of individualconstituencies in exceptional cases between general reviews; and we recommendthat the Opposition Leaders should be informed that in the Governments view nofurther clarification is needed.Basic Number of Constituencies4.   No further action is needed.County and Borough Constituencies5. We recommend that the Opposition should be informed that theGovernment adhere to the view that the question of weighting must be left to thegood sense of the Commissions, and that it is not practicable to set out a formula inthe Rules.Membership6. We do not think that Mr. Gaitskell&apos;s proposal that one member of eachCommission should be nominated by the Prime Minister and one member by the leader of the Opposition is acceptable, if only because, as Mr. Grimond pointedout, this would inevitably lead to claims for similar representation by other Parties.We see no objection, however, to Mr. GaitskelFs compromise proposal thatappointments should be made in agreement between the Parties: in fact, his proposal should assist in securing acceptance of the Commission^ recommendations by the House. The Minister of Housing and Local Government, who appoints one member each to the English and Welsh Commissions, agrees, provided it isunderstood that he would continue to appoint people with a knowledge of localgovernment because of the link between local government and parliamentaryboundaries.7. We therefore recommend that the Opposition Leaders should be informedthat the Government accept this proposal subject to the proviso above.52243
Composition of the Commissions8. We adhere to the view endorsed by the Cabinet last autumn that the speaker should continue to be the Chairman of the Commissions. He hasreaffirmed his willingness to do so.9. The Speaker also expressed the view, before the recent discussions withthe Opposition Leaders took place, that there was no particular need for the deputy chairmen to be Judges. The system has, however, worked well in Scotland and,with a view to reaching the greatest possible measure of agreement with theOpposition Parties, we think it would be desirable to provide that all deputy chairmen should be Judges. The Lord Chancellor would much prefer that theoffice should be held by a Member of the Bar of not less than 15 years standing,but he does not feel able to oppose the suggestion if the Parties in the Commons are agreed.10. We therefore recommend that, subject to the Speaker&apos;s acquiescence,the Opposition should be informed that the Government accept this proposal.11. We recommend that the Opposition should be informed that theGovernment confirm the provisional agreement reached at the meeting that theRegistrars-General and the Director-General of Ordnance Survey should serve asassessors and not, as at present, as members.12. As regards Mr. Griffiths&apos; suggestion, we agree that the knowledge and experience of the national agents of the Parties would be useful to the Commissions.We do not think, however, that it would be desirable for the national agents to begiven the close and continuous association with the Commissions which wouldresult from their serving as assessors. We think the point could be met on thelines suggested in paragraph 111 of the 1942 Report of the Vivian Committee on electoral Machinery namely that, in addition to local hearings, each separateCommission should sit under its Deputy Chairman &quot; to hear any representations from the Chief or National officers of the principal Party organisations with respectto the provisional proposals.&quot; We recommend that the Opposition should beinformed that the Government are prepared to see that this suggestion isimplemented.13. The necessary amending legislation ought to be introduced as soon aspossible so that it can be passed as far in advance as may be of the next GeneralElection and before the present law operates to require the Commissions to startanother general review.14. We therefore propose that, subject to further consultation with the Speakeron the question of Deputy Chairmen (see paragraphs 9 and 10 above) we should write to the Opposition Leaders on the lines indicated in paragraphs 3, 5, 7, 10, 11and 12 above, and say that, subject to any further comments they may have, theGovernment propose to introduce the necessary legislation as soon as parliamentary time permits.15.   We seek our Colleagues&apos; authority to proceed accordingly.R. A. BJ. S. M.13 th September, 1957.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCONFIDENTIALANNEX TO C. (57) 208NOTE OF MEETING HELD ON 16th MAY AT THE HOUSE OF COMMONSPROPOSED AMENDMENT OF HOUSE OF COMMONS (redistribution of SEATS) ACT, 1949Present:The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.The Right Hon. J. Maclay, M.P.The Right Hon. E. R. G. Heath, M.P.The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell, M.P.The Right Hon. J. Griffiths, M.P.Mr. Herbert W. Bowden, M.P.Mr. J. Grimond, M.P.Mr. Butler said that the purpose of the meeting was to consider certain proposals for the amendment of the House of Commons (Redistribution of Seats)Act, 1949, which his predecessor had communicated to the Opposition Partieslast year. There had been agreement on a considerable part of the proposals putforward, and he suggested that the discussion should be directed to those points onwhich there was some difference of opinion.Intervals between Reviews of ConstituenciesMr. Butler said that the Government scheme was that reports of the boundary Commission should be submitted at intervals of not less than 10 andnot more than 15 years, instead of the present period of not less than 3 and notmore than 7 years. Both the Opposition Parties in commenting had felt that while this was generally acceptable there should be some provision for dealing withspecial cases at rather shorter intervals than 10-15 years. The Labour Party had suggested that if the electorate of a constituency rose above 80,000 or fell below40,000 an &quot; interested authority,&quot; or not less than 100 electors in the constituency,should be entitled to require the Boundary Commission to consider adjustments.Mr. Butler did not feel that the Government could accept this proposal. Therewere constituencies in Wales and Scotland where the electorate must necessarilyremain below 40,000 for geographical reasons. The Government were not infavour of having a detailed statutory specification of the circumstances in whichconstituencies must be reconsidered. The Redistribution Rules in the original act of 1944 had provided that the electorate of a constituency should not vary from the electoral quota by more than approximately one-quarter of trie quota. When the boundary Commission started their first general review in 1946 they found thatthis requirement gave rise to so much dismemberment of constituencies and localprotests that the then Government abolished it in 1947 in the House of Commons(Redistribution of Seats) Act, 1947.Mr. Gaitskell said that he and his colleagues were not tied to the figures of80,000 and 40,000, but they did think that there ought to be a workable provisionfor review in exceptional cases in which circumstances had changed between thegeneral reviews.Mr. Grimond, said that Mr. Clement Davies had expressed the same view andhe agreed with it.52256
Mr. Butler pointed out that section 2(3) of the House of Commons(Redistribution of Seats) Act, 1949, empowered Commissions to make recommendations affecting particular constituencies between general reviews, buthitherto this power had only been used to adjust constituency boundaries to localauthority boundaries.It was agreed that the Government would give consideration to the questionwhether there was any need to clarify the point that the Commissions couldrecommend major alterations in exceptional cases under this power.Basic Number of ConstituenciesMr. Butler said that the Labour Opposition had suggested that the number of constituencies should be increased from 613 to 625 and that in their view thisfollowed from the Governments proposals on electoral quotas. He explainedthat the Government did not consider this to be consequential upon their plans,since the proposal was to take the average electorate of each of the three countries and not of Great Britain. This would give 618 seats as now.Mr. Bowden said that provided the Government were satisfied that the totalnumber of constituencies would remain at 618 this meant that there would be noconflict with Rule 1 of the Redistribution Rules. They did not wish to press thispoint.County and Borough ConstituenciesMr. Butler said that the Labour Opposition had suggested that the rules should be amended to avoid the present general disparity between county andborough constituencies. The Governments view was that this was a matter whichhad to be left to the good sense of the Commissions. The problem of geographymade it impossible to have electorates of the same size in the counties as inboroughs, and he did not think that a satisfactory mathematical formula could befound for the necessary &quot; weighting.&quot;Mr. Gaitskell said there was not likely to be agreement between theParties on this point. The Labour Opposition could only hold themselves free to criticise or seek to amend any proposal which the Government might put forwardwhen they had it in precise terms.Composition of the CommissionsMr. Butler said that the last point was the composition of the Commissions.The Labour Opposition had proposed that the Chairmen of the Commissionsshould be High Court Judges in England and Wales and persons of similar judicialstanding in Scotland and Northern Ireland. Mr. Gaitskell said that this was not intended in any way as a criticism of the present Speaker but the Speaker of any party had been a politician. The Chairmanship was a judicial function and shouldbe exercised by someone with the qualifications and experience of a judge.Mr. Butler said that the Government were anxious to retain the Speaker as chairman and the Speaker was, he understood, willing to continue to be Chairman.There was no other way of securing the same degree of guidance and experiencefor the Commissions as could be obtained by having the Speaker as Chairman.Mr. Gaitskell said that the question of the Chairmanship was part of thegeneral question of the composition of the Commissions. He and his friends didnot think the present arrangements satisfactory. It was desirable to recognise the realities of the situation, and a proposal that one member should be nominated by the Prime Minister and one by the Leader of the Opposition seemed to meet this. They should not be members of Parliament but persons of standing andrepute like Heads of Colleges.Mr. Grimond said that if there were any question of representation he wouldhave to press for representation of the Liberal Party and there would no doubt be others.Mr. Butler said that it had seemed desirable to the Government to remove the Commissions from the direct impact of political differences as much as possible.The Vivian Committee of 1942, on whose recommendations the present constitutionof the Commissions was based, had considered the question of political
representation and had pointed out that, apart from the difficulty of maintaining a fair balance of political opinion, political members would find it impossible todivest themselves of their party allegiance, with the result that there would befrequent deadlocks or majority decisions which would go far to deprive the commissions&apos; recommendations of any inherent validity or authority.Mr. Gaitskell said that he knew the history but still thought that present arrangements were not satisfactory. He pointed out that the members were appointed by Ministers. Could this not be done in agreement between the parties?This might form the ground for a compromise. Mr. Butler promised to consider this.On the question of the Chairmanship, it might prove possible to make a compromise on the basis of the Scottish system by which a judge was appointedDeputy Chairman and Mr. Maclay said that this had worked well in Scotland.The meeting then considered the question of assessors. It was agreed thatthe Registrar-General and the Director-General of Ordnance Survey could wellbe assessors to the Commissions. Mr. Griffiths said that the Labour Party wouldlike to propose the appointment of assessors with political experience for example,the National Agents whose experience and knowledge would be very useful.It was agreed that the Government would consider their proposals further in the light of the discussion and would consult again with the Opposition parties.

</content>
</cab>
