<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/89/0 images: 80-83</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1957Copy No.C. (57) 2163rd October, 1957CABINETTHE QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OF parliament note by the Lord chancellor circulate for the consideration of the Cabinet, a draft of The Queen&apos;s speech on the Prorogation of Parliament which has been prepared by the Committee onThe Queen&apos;s Speeches.K.House of Lords, S.W. 1,3rd October, 1957.52329
draft speech ON THE PROROGATION OF parliament my Lords and Members of the House of CommonsA few days ago I returned to London with My Dear Husband on theconclusion of a short stay in Canada and a visit to the United States. It was a greatjoy to Me to have this opportunity to see again My People in Canada, to open theCanadian Parliament and to renew My personal experience of that great and developing Commonwealth country. I was also very happy, at president eisenhower&apos;s invitation, to pay a second visit to the United States, and, during Mystay, to meet members of the United States Government, Congress and theSupreme Court. Everywhere I received a most warm and friendly welcome. my visit has further convinced Me that the ties which bind our peoples are strong andenduring.2. I shall always retain the happiest recollections of the visits which I paidwith My Dear Husband to France, Portugal and Denmark, and the movingreception extended to us by the peoples of those countries.3. My Dear Husband and I were deeply grieved at the death of King Haakonthe Seventh of Norway, who held a special place in the hearts of My People. our sympathy goes out to the members of His family and to the whole Norwegianpeople.4. I recall with pleasure the reception accorded to Me and My Husband bythe Secretary-General and by the General Assembly of the United Nations in thecourse of My visit to New York this month. My Government have continued toco-Operate in the work of the Disarmament Commission of the United nations and have joined in putting forward practical proposals for an international agreement on conventional and nuclear disarmament.5. My Ministers have welcomed the continuing progress being made withinthe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation and Western European Union in strengthening the defence of the Atlantic Community and in broadening the scopeof European co-operation.6. After the cessation of hostilities between Israel and Egypt and theestablishment of an effective United Nations force, United Kingdom Forces were withdrawn from the Suez Canal area. My Government have thereafter continued their efforts to bring about a just settlement of the dangerous situation in theMiddle East.7. My Government welcome the Joint Resolution of the Congress of theUnited States, designed to promote peace and stability in the Middle East, andthe decision of the United States Government to participate in the military committee of the Bagdad Pact.8. In view of the long-standing ties of friendship between Muscat and Omanand the United Kingdom, My Government took prompt action in response to a request from the Sultan for armed assistance in quelling a rebellion in hisdominions. No losses were sustained by the small number of United kingdom troops engaged.9. It gave Me great pleasure to meet the Prime Ministers and other representatives of Commonwealth countries who were in London at the end ofJune. In their discussions they reviewed all the.major international questions ofthe day which were of common concern to their countries and affirmed that inthe interests of world peace and security they would continue to work for increasedco-operation between nations.10. During the year Acts were passed as a result of which Ghana and theFederation of Malaya have become independent Members of the.Commonwealth.I wish the peoples of these new Member countries all happiness and prosperity;52329
and I welcome their admission to the United Nations. I was much gratified atthe cordial reception extended to My Dear Uncle, His Royal Highness The duke of Gloucester, and My Dear Aunt, Her Royal Highness The Duchess of Kent,who represented Me at the celebrations in the Federation of Malaya and in Ghanarespectively. United Kingdom Forces, together with Forces from other commonwealth countries, are continuing to support the Army of the Federationof Malaya in the campaign against the terrorists.11. The Nigeria Constitutional Conference which was held in London inMay and June has led to the establishment, under the chairmanship of theGovernor-General, of an All-Nigerian Council of Ministers with a Federal PrimeMinister, and to the grant of Regional self-government in the Eastern and WesternRegions. An Order in Council has been made providing for the establishmentof the Federation of the British West Indies.12. My Ministers have made progress in discussing the proposals for the closer association of Malta with the United Kingdom, while in Cyprus they have continued their unremitting efforts to reach a peaceful solution of the problems involved.13. My Ministers have announced plans for reorganising My Armed Forcesat home and overseas. Compensation terms and resettlement plans for those officers and men whose service will be prematurely terminated have been published.A new Naval Discipline Act has been passed.14.   A successful series of nuclear trials was carried out in the Pacific Ocean.15. My Government have approved a redeployment and expansion of theinformation services overseas, with greater emphasis on films for television andthe teaching of English abroad.Members of the House of Commons16.   I thank you for the provision which you have made for the public services.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons17. My Government have entered into negotiations in the Organisation for european Economic Co-operation for the establishment of a Free Trade Area inEurope.18. Provision has been made for more effective long-term assurances to agriculture and for assistance in the modernisation of farms in the United Kingdom.New provision has also been made for the development of the pig industry inGreat Britain.19. Legislation has been passed providing further assistance for the whitefish and herring industries and for the modernisation of the fishing fleet.20. [My Ministers have appointed a Committee of Inquiry into the fishing industry.]21. An Act has been passed to amend the law of homicide and to limit thescope of capital punishment.22. I have given My Assent to legislation to enable effect to be given to thefour international conventions which provide for protection for the victims of war.23. Legislation has been enacted amending the Rent Restrictions Acts and providing for a minimum period of notice for the termination of residential lettings.A measure has been enacted to revise Scottish housing subsidies and to facilitate the movement of population from overcrowded areas in Scotland.24. The law relating to rating and valuation in England and Wales has been amended.25. An Act has been passed providing for the payment by all insured persons of a special weekly National Health Service contribution.26. Provision had been made for reorganising the electricity supply industryin England and Wales.
27. A measure has been enacted permitting the imposition of countervailingand anti-dumping duties on goods imported into the United Kingdom.28. An Act has been passed to impose a levy on exhibitors of cinematograph films, and to continue certain other provisions, to assist British film production.29. I have assented to an Act to extend the right of redress for damage causedby subsidence resulting from coal mining.30. Improvements have been made in the provisions for elderly and seriouslydisabled war pensioners.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons31.   I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.

</content>
</cab>
