<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/89/0 images: 146-147</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THE ECONOMIC situation note by the Chancellor of the exchequer circulate this note on our external position for the informationof my colleagues.2.     We have been near to the edge of economic disaster.    We arestill near the edge.    Over the past two months we have lost  185 millions from our gold and dollar reserves.    The reserves at the end ofSeptember were down to  660 millions, only two-thirds of what they were at the end of 1954, despite the  200 millions which we drew from theInternational Monetary Fund (I.M.F.) last year and the  37 millions which we gained by not paying last year&apos;s interest on the American loan.3.     A continued run on the reserves at the rate which we haverecently experienced would exhaust them in six months.    In practice,of course, the crack would come much sooner.    Within weeks it wouldbecome clear that the rate could not be held.    Increased leads and lagsand the run which would be started by the central core of holders of sterling in the sterling area and elsewhere could and would start the reserves pouring out many times faster.    In the collapse which would follow the cost of our imports of essential food and raw materials would rise sharply, adding very much to the dangers of an inflationary spiralat home.4.     Two factors are holding the situation:-(a) the money we have borrowed to fortify the reserves;(b) the policies we have declared at home for dealingwith inflation.We have got to repay the former and carry through the latter.5.     But now we have got not only to hold the position but re-establishit.    Reasonably sound as our current trading position may be in itself,this is going to be very difficult indeed.(i)   If we draw in full the  180 millions from the Export/importtBank between now and next January, we shall bear debt obligations in dollars alone repayable over the following seven years of  870 millions,i. e.  200 millions to the I. M, F.,  180 to the Export /import Bank and 70 millions a year for the Canadian and United States loans.    By-1-TOP SECRETWt. 38549/D.1291   50m   8/57   P.I.   Gp. 1144THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of....................................................-TOP SECRET        coPrNoACLC.(57) 23014th October, 1957CABINET
TOP SECRET145claiming a &quot;bisque&quot; under the United States and Canadian agreements wecan only save  70 millions a year from our existing commitments andwe should do this only twice or three times in the period.(ii)    We have got to face the run down of sterling balances by the restof the sterling area.    India may impose a great strain in the coming year.    Last year her I. M. F. drawing helped us out.    We shall almost certainly not have the relief Australia gave us in the last twelve months and the Colonies may start being a strain too.(iii) We have to meet these increased burdens from a weaker initialposition and in a world in which the earning of gold and dollars may beeven harder than it has been in recent years.6.      We will remain in danger of another crisis until our policieshave finally and demonstrably shown themselves successful.    their first announcement has been greeted with respect.    Inside and outsidethis country we are being watched to see that we carry them through.P.T.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.14th October, 1957.-2-

</content>
</cab>
