<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/89/0 images: 190-192</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the. Cabinet.   October 1957The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of...........................................................TOP SECRET Copy No.   58C. (57) 242 Copy No.18th October, 1957CABINETLEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME : 1957-58 session memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department andLord Privy SealSince I circulated my memorandum, C. (57) 132, on future legislation, theprogramme for next session has been altered in various respects.2. In Appendix A I set out the Bills which are at present mentioned in thedraft of The Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament. In Appendix B I setout the Bills which, though not mentioned in The Queen&apos;s Speech, are known tobe essential or, although contingent at the moment, are likely to have to be accomodated in the programme. In Appendix C I set out some other Bills whichthe Ministers concerned are anxious to introduce. -3. The time likely to be available for legislation remains, as indicated inC. (57) 132, at about fifty-five days. The Bills listed in Appendix A alone would absorb practically the whole of this allocation, while those listed in Appendices Band C would probably require, in total, more than half as much time again.4. I suggest, therefore, that, in order to provide ourselves with rather moreroom for manoeuvre than we have at present:  (a) If the Cabinet decide in principle to introduce legislation on agricultural holdings, &amp;c. (which will be a substantial Bill, requiring specificmention in The Queen&apos;s Speech), the Slaughterhouses Bill should be omitted from the Speech and placed on the reserve list of Billsmentioned in (d) below.(b) The Public Records Bill should also be omitted from the Speech, althoughit should remain in the legislative programme and might be introduced in the House of Lords.(c) We should consider carefully whether we should be well advised to proceedwith legislation on Administrative Tribunals or whether we should deferthis until the 1958-59 session.(d) We should decide that all the Bills in List C, together with theSlaughterhouses Bill, should constitute a reserve list, from which individual Bills may be selected for introduction provided that timepermits and the Bills themselves are ready.(e) We should review the programme again early in the New Year, in the lightof the progress achieved before Christmas.R. A. B.Halstead, Essex,17th October, 1957.52416
Appendix BBills known to be essentialCommonwealth Institute.British Nationality (Amendment).Post Office (Money).Expiring Laws Continuance.Exchequer Loans to Nationalised Boards.New Towns (Money).Representation of the People (Redistribution).Representation of the People (Cars to take voters to the poll).Christmas Island.Bills which may become essentialCrown Aircraft (actions for nuisance).Ceylon (Consequential Provisions).Jamaica Dependencies.West Indies Regiment.Public Works Loans.Egyptian Sterling Balances.Insurance (Nuclear Reactors).Pensions (No. 2 Bill) subject to Cabinet decision on policy.Appendix COverseas Civil Service.Isle of Man Constitutional Reform.Royal Naval Hospital, Great Yarmouth.Inventions and Designs.Charitable Trusts (Baddeley Judgment).Trustee Savings Banks.Appendix ABills mentioned in The Queen&apos;s SpeechSingapore.Malta.Overseas Resources Development.Agricultural Holdings.Land Drainage (Scotland).Slaughterhouses.Child Welfare and Adoption.:Penal Reform.Local Government Reorganisation.Local Government Finance (Scotland).Public Records.Disabled Persons (Employment).Tariffs.Milford Haven.Hyde Park Corner.Lords Reform.Emergency. Powers Repeal (Land).Administrative Tribunals.Pensions (No. 1 Bill).
Appendix ABills mentioned in The Queen&apos;s SpeechSingapore.Malta.Overseas Resources Development.Agricultural Holdings.Land Drainage (Scotland).Slaughterhouses.Child Welfare and Adoption.,oH vq iPenal Reform.Local Government Reorganisation.Local Government Finance (Scotland).Public Records.Disabled Persons (Employment).Tariffs.Milford Haven.Hyde Park Corner.Lords Reform.Emergency. Powers Repeal (Land).Administrative Tribunals.Pensions (No. 1 Bill).Appendix BBills known to be essentialCommonwealth Institute.British Nationality (Amendment).Post Office (Money).Expiring Laws Continuance.Exchequer Loans to Nationalised Boards.New Towns (Money).Representation of the People (Redistribution).Representation of the People (Cars to take voters to the poll).Christmas Island.Bills which may become essentialCrown Aircraft (actions for nuisance).Ceylon (Consequential Provisions).Jamaica Dependencies.West Indies Regiment.Public Works Loans.Egyptian Sterling Balances.Insurance (Nuclear Reactors).Pensions (No. 2 Bill) subject to Cabinet decision on policy.Appendix COverseas Civil Service.Isle of Man Constitutional Reform.Royal Naval Hospital, Great Yarmouth.Inventions and Designs.Charitable Trusts (Baddeley Judgment).Trustee Savings Banks.

</content>
</cab>
