<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/89/0 images: 193-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.(57) 24318th October, 1957CABINETWAGES policy:   FOST OFFICE ENGINEERSMemorandum by the Postmaster-general  accept completely the general wages policy in paragraph 2 ofC. (57) 237.2. I disagree entirely with the proposed treatment of the outstandinwage claim of Fost Office engineers.3.      My attitude to this claim is:-(a) The Post Office (like the whole Civil Service) is committed to honour &quot;Priestley&quot;.    This RoyalCommission was appointed in 1952 and reportedin 1955.    The Government accepted its recommenda-tions that pay and conditions in the Civil service should be comparable to outside industry.(b) 80 per cent of the Post Office staff have already received their Priestley increase.(c) I have committed myself in the House of commons to give the Priestley increase to 100 per cent of post Office staff.     Here is my pledge:-&quot;Mr. Hobson:   For what, surplus is the right on. Gentleman budgeting ?    Do these increasesaccount for any outstanding wage demands thatare in process of negotiation?Mr. Marples:   I budgeted for an increasedcumulative surplus of  5 millions by 3lst March,1959.     We have estimated that some of the wage .awards that will be made in the future will begiven on a basis pro rata to those already madein the past. &quot;(d) The public is already paying the cash for Priestleyincreases for 100 per cent of our staff. That is why the recent Post Office tariff increases were so huge.-1-TOP SECRETWt. 38549/D.1291   SOm   8/57   P.I.   Gp. 1144THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of......................................................
(e) My proposed offer to our engineers is the smallestmy conscience will allow. Even so they may goto arbitration. But at any rate I could make out some sort of a case.The Treasury proposals summarised are:-(a)Agree Priestley in principle.    But dishonour it inpractice.    The Postmaster-General can do thedishonouring by making:-(i)  no offer at all to some engineering grades;(ii)   a deliberately unacceptable offer to others.(b)Then arbitration will follow and all will be well.5.     My objections to these proposals are:-(a) We shall be faced at once with the political accusationof dishonesty.    And we shall have no answer.(The Union*s present Secretary was Colchester&apos;sMember of Parliament for five years.    A pastSecretary of the Union is John Edwards, the presentMember of Parliament for Brighouse who was a former Economic Secretary.)(b) In addition to the political price we cannot avoidpaying the cash price.    Arbitration is likely to cost as much (or probably more) as my proposals.In other words we shall get the worst of both worlds.6. All this would be the worst possible send off to the Governmentsnew wages policy.E.M.General Post Office, E. C. 1.18th October, 1957.-2

</content>
</cab>
