<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/249/0 images: 306-320</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1934.SECRET. Copy No.CP, 145 (34).213CABINET.INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE COLONIAL EMPIRE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues, with the concurrence of the President of the Board of Trade, the report of an inter-departmental Committee on the industrial development of the Colonial Empire. I propose to send copies of this report to all Colonial Governments with instructions to the effect that they should guide themselves by the principles laid down therein.P. C.-L.Colonial Office, May 31, 1934.110084]
Miscellaneous No. 445ConfidentialznREPORTOF THEINTER-DEPARTMENTAL COMMITTEEON THEINDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE COLONIAL EMPIREMARCH,  1934
Report of the Inter-Departmental Committee on the Industrial Developmentof the Colonial Empire, March, 1934.MEMBERSHIP  OF  COMMITTEE. Mr. R. V. Vernon, C.B. (Chairman).Mr J. A. Edgcumbe, C.M.G., C.B.E. (Department of Overseas Trade).Mr. G. L. M. Clauson, C.M.G., O.B.E. (Colonial Office).Mr. E. Hale (Board of Trade).Miss A. H. M. Kilroy (Board of Trade).Mr. G. E. Boyd Shannon (Dominions Office).Mr. L. S. Smith (Colonial Office), Secretary. O -f rTERMS OF REFERENCE.To consider and report how far it is desirable to frame and pursue a policy either to encourage or to discourage the establishment of industrial enterprises in the Colonial Empire and, in this connection,(i) whether Colonial Governments should be permitted to establish protective tariffs against the United Kingdom in order to assist such enterprises;(ii) whether the United Kingdom should continue to allow free entry to all imports from the Colonial Empire, both primary products and manufactured goods, whidh are at present admitted free of duty under the Import Duties Act, 1932;(iii) whether His Majesty&apos;s Government should use the powers bestowed upon them by the Ottawa Agreements to obtain in the Dominions and India the continuance or extension to goods manufactured in the Colonial Empire of the tariff preferences accorded to goods manufactured in the United Kingdom.1. We have held five meetings and have considered memoranda which have been submitted to us by the Colonial Office and Board of Trade supplying in summary form data relating to the particular examples of industrial develop-ment in the Colonial Empire which appear to be the most important in themselves or in their reactions on Imperial trade relations. We have not thought it necessary to hear any witnesses.2.   Our terms of reference require us&quot; to consider and report how far it is desirable to frame and pursue a policy either to encourage or to discourage the establishment of industrial enterprises in the Colonial Empire &quot;. We are invited to consider certain specific expedients in connection with this question, but before, we proceed to do so we think it appropriate to indicate how far in our opinion the establishment of industrial enterprises in the Colonies is to be regarded as in itself desirable or undesirable.3. We imagine that if a considered plan had been devised and consistently followed with regard to the trade relations of the United Kingdom and its oversea dependencies it would probably have taken the form of a United Kingdom predominantly industrial and oversea dependencies primarily engaged in the production of raw materials for use in United Kingdom industries and food supplies for consumption in the United Kingdom. To some extent this ideal differentiation of functions corresponds with the actual facts of the situation. The United Kingdom is predominantly industrial; the oversea dependencies are for the most part producers of food supplies and raw materials.4. We feel, however, that it is not possible to lay down&apos;a definite and consistent policy of maintaining this differentiation. History has neglected to follow a line of planned evolution. There has already been some development of industrial enterprise in oversea dependencies.   In the case of India (with
which we are not directly concerned) this development has of course reached a very high stage. India to-day competes with the United Kingdom (particularly in the textile industries) in overseas as well as in Indian markets, and there can be no question of imposing any kind of restraint upon this industrial activity. The principle of fiscal autonomy has been definitely recognized in the case of India and she is under no obligation to consider United Kingdom industrial interests. We are not disposed to suggest the full application of the same prin-ciple to the Colonies. But it appears to us that a freedom which is allowed without limitation to India cannot be refused in toto to Eastern dependencies, such as the Straits Settlements, Ceylon and Hong Kong; or indeed to African, West Indian and other dependencies. We recognize moreover that substitution of industrial for agricultural conditions may be expected to lead to the gradual evolution of different, and, in many cases, improved general economic and social standards. Ultimately the purchasing power of native communities will be increased if they are actively engaged in industrial as well as in agricultural enterprises (provided such industrial enterprises are economically justifiable) and, taking a long distance view of the future, we feel that development of this kind will probably increase the general trade activity of the world and, it is to be hoped, the prosperity of the British Empire.5. There are some obvious advantages in manufacturing the finished pro-duct near the source of the raw materials, and in the case of such commodities as minerals or mineral oil the winning of the raw materials may be in itself an industrial undertaking. There is no law of nature which prescribes that cotton piece-goods to be sold in Brazil shall be manufactured in Lancashire from cotton grown in the Southern States, and the production of tin ingots at Singapore is no legitimate grievance to tin-smelters in the United Kingdom. We therefore regard some industrial development in Colonial dependencies as a contingency which is inevitable and which cannot be prohibited or indefinitely retarded. In any case no law of self-denial imposed upon British dependencies will govern the oversea dependencies of France, Belgium, Portugal and Holland, to say nothing of India and Japan; and an elimination of such competition may reflect less advantage to the United Kingdom manufacturer in the world markets than to his foreign competitor, to whom production by &quot; native &quot; labour with &quot;native &quot; standards of living remains open. We should like to see Trinidad oil refined at Swansea; but we would rather see it refined in Trinidad than in Curacao.6. At the same time we are not inclined to consider that the development which we foresee is one which there is any need to accelerate. We do not think that it is possible for the United Kingdom to attempt to keep its Colonial dependencies in the position of &quot; plantations &quot; whose sole economic function is the production of food supplies and raw materials. But a policy of Colonial development must clearly have regard not to Colonial interests alone, but also to those of the United Kingdom and its industries. In any case, we think that industrial development is most likely to be healthy and successful if it is the outcome of natural growth, and that there is no reason at all why a conscious policy of artificial encouragement of industry should be undertaken and pursued. Indeed we feel that the adoption of such a policy is bound to have reactions in the United Kingdom unfavourable to the continuance in this country of the policy of the &quot; open door &quot; for Colonial products and manufactures. The simplicity of the &quot; open door &quot; policy in tariff relations with the Colonies is a factor which, as is pointed out later in this report, has much to commend it.7. There are many forms which encouragement of industry can take, for example, investment of Government funds in industrial enterprises, guarantee of interest on private capital invested, special remission of taxation, the accord of special terms or facilities in connection with transport on Government railways or waterways, monopoly privileges, etc.; but a more common form of encouragement is the institution of a tariff sufficiently high to protect the products of industry in the domestic market against products of a similar kind imported whether from the United Kingdom, from other parts of the Empire or from foreign countries. It is obvious that such protection, if sufficiently effective, may also lead to production expanding beyond the requirements of the domestic market and developing into a capacity for export, and even for &quot; dumping &quot; into other markets in which the United Kingdom manufacturer is
a competitor. This brings us to the first specific question which is put to us, namely,&quot; whether Colonial Governments should be permitted to establish pro-tective tariffs against the United Kingdom in order to assist such enterprises &quot;.8. Until quite recently the Customs tariffs of Colonial Dependencies were with very occasional exceptions imposed without any protective motive. The produce of the Colonies was admitted free of duty into the United Kingdom; in foreign markets it generally competed on &quot; most-favoured-nation &quot; terms, thanks to the Colonies being covered by the commercial treaties which the United Kingdom had concluded; in the Colonies themselves there was no competition in their home markets which their own primary products had to face. Customs duties were imposed almost entirely as a means of collecting revenue. They were imposed in the first instance on practically all imports without any dis-crimination as to their source. Gradually the principle of tariff preference was introduced into the Colonies, a noteworthy example being the result of the Trade Agreements concluded between most of the West Indian Colonies and the Dominion of Canada in 1920 and 1925. The advantage of preferential tariffs, where introduced, was as a rule extended to all parts of the British Empire, but the preference was given solely as an advantage in competition with foreign importers. It was not conceived as rendering possible, or rendering easier, competition by United Kingdom or Dominion importers with local producers in the Colonies because in scarcely any cases did such local producers exist.9. It was probably considered a natural consequence of the admission of Colonial products free into the United Kingdom market that United Kingdom products should be admitted into Colonial markets on terms which did not subject them to any kind of handicap in competition, that is to say, terms which subjected them to customs duties only in cases where there was no local competition to face. So long as this position was maintained, there would, we consider, be no ground of complaint on the part of United Kingdom industries. No doubt, the existence of customs duties is a disadvantage to the importer. Customs duties are a form of taxation and all forms of taxation reduce the purchasing power of the tax-payer. Customs duties on particular articles increase the price, and probably reduce the consumption of these articles. But if the importer bears no tax burden, from which competitors are free, he is not seriously concerned by this limitation of demand. The existence of a tariff, however, and especially of a high tariff, exerts a powerful influence to suggest or promote the establishment of a local industry which will enjoy protection by the tariff, though the motive for its institution was not protective. Under a strict free-trade regime a customs duty on imported goods should be accom-panied by an equivalent excise duty on like goods locally manufactured, but it was hardly to be expected that Colonies would invariably follow &quot; the letter of the law &quot;.10. We have considered a number of examples of industries established in particular Colonies under the shelter of a tariff which was in fact protective and examples of proposals for the establishment of industries under such tariff shelter which have not actually been carried into effect. The most important cases of Colonial industries in actual operation with tariff protection relate to breweries, match factories, cement factories and factories for the production of soap and edible oils. In all these cases, except perhaps that of matches, there is competition with imports from the United Kingdom, and in practically every case objection has been taken by the United Kingdom industries affected to the protection afforded to their local competitors. We think that it can be laid down as a general principle that the creation of such protected local industries can only be justified by special considerations in individual cases. We have, therefore, set ourselves to examine what considerations should be allowed to carry weight in this connection.11. So far as the more important existing cases of protection are concerned, the following considerations have been adduced. In the cases of breweries established in West African Colonies and in Cyprus it was represented to the Secretary of State that the beer imported, with which beer locally produced would compete, was for the most part of foreign origin.   Much the same has23766 a 2
been said in defence of the Colonial match enterprises, and where this fact can be established we regard the objections to the protection of local industries as very greatly reduced.12. In the case of the soap and edible oil factories most of which are situated in West Indian Colonies, it was represented that the principal raw material, copra, was of local origin; that prices for it in the world market had fallen so low as to leave no margin over the cost of production; that a fair price to the local producer could be, and generally was, made a condition of the continuance of protection; and that as costs of transport, distribution, etc. were eliminated, the local industry should be able to sell on the local market at prices Which would be but little in excess of the world prices of the finished product.It was generally also represented that the local raw material had become the object of unfair discrimination in price on the part of the oversea purchasers. We do not think that there was any good ground for this representation. The fall in the prices of raw materials has led producers all over the world to feel that they must be the victims of some special conspiracy, and not merely of economic forces.13. We are inclined to think that, at any rate in the case of soaps and edible oils, the economies resulting from large scale production and a world wide organisation of distribution are so great that a local industry, even with the advantage of raw materials on the spot and a local market for the finished product, cannot hope to compete on equal terms with the United Kingdom manu-facturer. We accordingly consider that in these cases the protective duty has undoubtedly the effect of raising the price of the finished product in the Colonial market and therefore of subjecting the United Kingdom manufacturer, who has to bear the import duty, to what may not unreasonably be regarded as &quot; unfair &quot; competition from the Colonial manufacturer, subjected as he is to no excise duty (or only to a disproportionately low one). It is conceivable that the advantages to a particular Colony of securing a market at a &quot; fair &quot; price to local raw material may outbalance, the disadvantage to the local consumer of paying a higher price for the finished product; but this is one of the cases in which we consider that the interests of the United Kingdom manufacturer and those of the Colonial producer of raw material must both be regarded as factors which require to be carefully weighed in determining the policy to be followed. It must not be assumed that either of them alone should be a determining factor.14. In this connection we have made reference to the guiding principles followed by the Government of India in the matter of Discriminating Protection.These, as laid down originally by the Indian Fiscal Commission may be stated as follows : &quot; (1) No industry should be protected unless : (a) India has natural advantages for its practice.(b) Without  protection  the  industry will  not  develop  as rapidly as the national interests require.(c) The industry is likely in the end to be able to stand alone without protection.&quot; (2) Protective duties must be adequate for their purpose, but not more than adequate, and must not be placed so high as to shelter inefficiency.&quot; (3) Protective duties are applied only to those products of an industry which are actually made in India or may compete with those made in India &quot;.We are informed that before protection is granted, a searching enquiry into the industry is made by the Tariff Board in which all the circumstances affecting-it are fully examined; and that the policy aims at an orderly and balanced industrial development and is very different from an out-and-out protective policy which encourages all industries alike, whatever their advantages and prospects, regardless of times and circumstances and taking no account of efficiency.15. We do not think it can be claimed that these guiding principles have been applied in Colonies before the application of protection to local industries, and we suggest that they might with advantage be applied in future, at any
rate in cases in which protection is sought by a Colonial industry against United Kingdom competition. These conditions were quite expressly laid down in the interests of India and not from any regard to those of the United Kingdom exporter. They were designed to prevent the creation of uneconomic industries which would be a burden on the community at large and, in so far as they increased costs of production, would impair the competitive position of Indian exporters. In suggesting their application to Colonies we are not therefore suggesting any sacrifice of Colonial to United Kingdom interests. But it must not be forgotten that the fiscal autonomy which has been conceded to India as a right is not recognised as an irresistible claim in the case of the Colonies. From this it follows that the interests of the Colonial communities are not the only consideration which must determine Colonial tariff policy. The industrial and commercial interests of the United Kingdom are considerations which cannot be, and ought not to be neglected. The Dominions and India, as partners in the British Commonwealth of Nations, also have a right to expect that their interests will be considered.16. But we regard the principle of trusteeship, which has been laid down in another connection and on which increasing emphasis is tending to be laid, as applicable in this connection also. To enforce in the Colonies in the interests of United Kingdom manufacturers, tariff provisions which impeded promising lines of economic development would be to revert to the mentality of &quot; plantation &quot; days and to provoke keen and not unreasonable resentment. Generally speaking, therefore, we suggest that, while the commercial interests of the United Kingdom and the general economic well-being of the particular Colony are both of them factors to be weighed in determining the tariff of a Colony, if the two appear to be in conflict the latter should prevail. But we should not accept the advantage of a small sectional interest, which is not the same thing as &quot; general economic well-being&quot;, as sufficient justification for the imposition of protective duties; and there must be a reasonable discretion to depart from the principle suggested when the United Kingdom interest is very large and the Colonial interest very small.17. Moreover, &quot; general economic well-being &quot; must not be interpreted too narrowly. Nearly all Colonies are dependent for their well-being on their export trade to the United Kingdom and a complete disregard of the interests of the United Kingdom exporter might in the end prejudice the interests of the Colony by not only decreasing the margin of preference which the United Kingdom is prepared to give but also alienating the sympathies of the United Kingdom purchaser who in the last resort is free to buy Colonial products or not as he pleases. The same considerations apply, perhaps to a less degree, to Colonial trade with the Dominions and India. It must also be remembered that the United Kingdom purchasers are not only the &quot; men in the street &quot;; they include the large manufacturers, who may be directly interested in the export trade to the Colonial Empire. The principal purchasers of copra and groundnuts are the manufacturers of soap and edible oils.18.   We now proceed to consider paragraph (ii) of our Terms of Reference &quot; whether the United Kingdom should continue to allow free entry to all imports from the Colonial Empire,  both primary products and manufactured goods &quot;.Section 5 of the Import Duties Act, 1932, gave an entire exemption from the general ad valorem duty imposed by that Act and from any &quot; additional duty &quot; imposed thereunder, to all imports from all Colonies and Protectorates or from Mandated Territories to which the Section might be applied by Order in Council. Imports from the Dominions and India were to be exempt until the 15th of November, 1932, or until a later date to be fixed by Treasury order. The effect of the Ottawa Agreements Act, 1932, taking into account the terms of the Agreements scheduled under it, is to continue this exemption for imports from those Dominions with which agreements were made and from India. With the trade between the United Kingdom and the Dominions and India we are not at present concerned; but we should see grave difficulties in a tariff which discriminated against Colonial products in favour of other parts of the Empire. In the case of trade with the Colonies, the position contemplated at the time of the passing of the Import Duties Act was perfectly clear. The Colonial Empire was to be entirely exempt from the new duties.     It was no doubt2376C A. 3
regarded as the source of primary products and food supplies only, and as therefore not being an actual, and probably not even a potential, competitor with producing or manufacturing interests in the United Kingdom. Whether this be so or not, the exemption granted was quite general in its terms. We think that any departure from this simple and easily intelligible position would be an unfortunate development. Once it is abandoned, it will be difficult to find any equally simple principle by reference to which tariff policy vis-a-vis the Colonial Empire can be regulated, and accordingly more difficult to find an alternative basis of principle for settling the tariff policy of the Colonial Empire.19. In considering earlier in this report the question of the imposition of protective duties by the Colonies, we assumed throughout that the exports to the United Kingdom from the Colonies concerned were admitted free of duty (other than revenue duties), and that consequently the Colonies were in the position of receiving from the United Kingdom the most favourable possible treatment in this respect. If any of their products are subject to protective duties here the arguments in favour of restraining the imposition of protective duties in the Colonies are obviously greatly weakened. Ultimately a position might be reached in which there was a minute calculation on both sides of reciprocal advantages and &quot; the balance of trade &quot; before tariffs were fixed, and we should not regard such a state of affairs as likely to contribute either to good feeling between the constituent parts of the Empire or to general expansion of inter-Imperial trade.20. In particular, it would somewhat weaken the position of the Secretary of State for the Colonies in future discussions of tariff matters with repre-sentatives of the Dominions and India. At present he is able to appear as the guardian and advocate of Colonial interests, and as the representative of a Government which pays such regard to those interests that it admits Colonial produce and manufactures into its own market on a basis of absolute equality with its own producers.21. The difficulties which have arisen in this connection and which we proceed to discuss are connected with the words &quot; produce and manufactures &quot; in the previous sentence. So long as the Colonies were producers of raw materials and food supplies only, British manufacturers had nothing to fear from them and were perfectly ready to welcome imports from them; but certain exporting industries have already established themselves in some Eastern Colonies and sooner or later industry is bound to become an interest of other parts of the Colonial Empire, though it is likely for an indefinite time to be a very minor interest compared with primary production. With the advent on the United Kingdom market of industrial products and manufactures from the Colonies a different situation arises from that which was contemplated when the Import Duties Act was passed.22. The only class of manufactured goods which has come to our notice in which any Colonial manufacturer is at present an effective competitor in the United Kingdom market is that of rubber goods (almost exclusively rubber boots and shoes) from Singapore, and to an increasing extent from Hong Kong. The British Empire was recently faced with an increasing import of rubber shoes manufactured in Japan and offered for sale at prices with which no European or Dominion manufacturer can possibly compete. As a result of these imports, high duties were imposed both in the United Kingdom and in Canada on foreign imports of these goods. In the Agreement concluded at Ottawa between the United Kingdom and Canada His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom expressly undertook to invite a number of Colonies, including the West Indies, Fiji, Malaya, Mauritius and Northern Rhodesia, to accord to Canada (which meant to the Empire generally) a preference of not less than one shilling per pair on rubber boots and shoes and canvas boots and shoes rubber-soled. This meant a very high degree of protection against the menacing competition of Japan. But representations have been made that this preference inures prin-cipally to the benefit of Singapore and Hong Kong, which are also producing rubber shoes at prices which render competition by United Kingdom or Dominion manufacturers difficult, if not impossible. This competition is not limited to Colonial markets but extends to the United Kingdom and to Dominion markets. It has been urged that duties, not perhaps as high as those already in force against foreign rubber shoes but still sufficiently high to be not far short of
prohibition, should be imposed on rubber shoes from Singapore and Hong Kong, and it has been suggested that the Government of Canada should exercise its power to propose a variation in the terms of the Ottawa Agreement with a view to affording further protection to the Canadian manufacturer in his home market against these Colonial products which are invading it.23. We recognize that this invasion of United Kingdom and Dominion markets by a manufactured product, which is the result of Oriental labour working under Oriental conditions, is a serious factor in the whole problem of inter-Imperial trade relations and calls for very careful consideration. We should be very sorry if it became the occasion for breaking the comparative simplicity and symmetry of the present position under the Import Duties Act. If protective duties are imposed by the United Kingdom against one Colonial product the demand for them will spring up as fast as other Colonial products make their entry into the market, and we see no reason to suppose that the rubber shoe is the last word in the potentialities of Colonial industry. (We pass over as falling outside our terms of reference the question of free trade for India which manufactures many things for export.)24. We regard the invasion of the United Kingdom market by cheap rubber shoes produced under Oriental conditions as an evil, and we wish to make suggestions for meeting that evil, but we should be sorry to see it met by an expedient which in its ultimate consequences might prove more serious than the evil itself. We think that one step that should be taken, both in the case of rubber shoe production at Singapore or Hong Kong and in the case of in-dustrial enterprises generally in the Colonies, is to exercise some control over &quot; factory and workshop &quot; conditions in those places where such enterprises are conducted. Mass production by highly mechanized industrial technique is a Western device whidh the East has found it not difficult to copy; and it is probably only a question of time before Africa follows the example set by Asia. Mass production, in whatever continent, means a reduced cost of manufacture, but the demands of the human links in the mechanism are a limiting factor in the race for cheapness which is more operative in advanced than in primitive communities. The ultimate cause of cheap production in the latter is probably in most cases the persistence of a general standard of living far below that of Western Europe or of the Dominions, and in so far as this is the cause nothing can remove it except a long process of social development which will raise the standard of life and the demand for comfort, recreation and even luxury on the part of Oriental populations.25. But the United Kingdom manufacturer constantly represents and we see no ground to question either his sincerity or his accuracy that his cost of production is materially increased not only by high taxation, but also by the restriction of hours and the imposition of minimum wage rates, which are the result either of legislation or of&apos; trade union action, by the Factory Acts which prescribe conditions of health and safety and by &quot; social insurance &quot; legislation regarding unemployment, health insurance, compensation for accident, etc., etc. Generally speaking, we think that the burden on the employer and the resultant increase in his cost of manufacture from all these causes is very much less in the Colonies than it is in the United Kingdom. We think that a deliberate policy should be pursued of securing the adoption in the Colonies of conditions of employment as regards wages, hours of work, &quot; factory and workshop &quot; regula-tions and compensation for accidents which will be to some extent comparable, though no doubt not identical, with those in force in the United Kingdom. This will probably do a good deal to eliminate the unfairness of competition which actually derives its ability to quote low prices, from its dependence on undesirable conditions of employment. It will also do something to remove the justly felt grievance of the United Kingdom manufacturer when he is exposed to the competition of employers from remote parts of the Empire who enjoy the advantage not only of the general &quot; low standard of comfort atmosphere &quot; on which we have commented but also of an almost complete freedom from industrial restrictions.26. A convenient method of raising the general standard of conditions of employment in the Colonies is probably the application to them of the terms of the numerous International Labour Conventions concluded at Geneva. Many of these Conventions, which are of general application, recognize the difference
/between Western and Eastern conditions by, for example, conceding longer hours or some similar relaxation of conditions to India and to Japan. No doubt some such relaxations should be admitted in the Colonies (and their admission is contemplated by the article of the Treaty of Versailles which governs the Colonial application of these Conventions); but there is no reason why they should be of indefinite duration, and they would no doubt not be, if the conscious policy of tightening up the conditions of employment in the Colonies, which we have suggested, were applied.27. We do not anticipate that the assimilation of Colonial conditions of employment to those of this country can proceed otherwise than very slowly, or that it can for a long time have any appreciable consequences in preventing the offering of some products of Colonial manufacture on the market at &quot; cut-throat &quot; prices. The process of raising the general standard of life and consequently increasing the wage level in Colonial populations must, if it occurs at all, be even more gradual. We cannot rely on either of these processes to meet an immediate emergency presented by the appearance of unreasonably cheap products of Colonial industry on the United Kingdom market, and we have, therefore, considered whether any more immediate action short of the imposition of protective duties on Colonial products could not be taken to meet such emergencies as and when they arise.28. The only expedient that we can suggest is that steps should be taken to encourage negotiation between producing interests in this country and the producers of the particular articles in question in the Colonies (or their agents in the United Kingdom), with a view to arranging some kind of division of the market and assignment of respective &quot; quotas &quot; between them. Where manu-facture in the Colonies is the work of a considerable enterprise (which is likely to be the case where serious competition in the United Kingdom market is threatened), or where there is any kind of organisation representative of the Colonial producers, we see no reason why consultation and mutual arrangement on these lines should not be possible. It would represent an application to the case of Colonial competition of the expedients which have been attempted in the case of competition between Japan, India and Lancashire in the textile market. We suggest that it is only if it proves impossible to reach some accommodation by these means that the introduction of protective tariffs in the United Kingdom against Colonial manufactured products, or the imposition upon such products of compulsory quotas should be contemplated, since in our opinion such action is to be strongly deprecated and recourse should be had to it only in more extreme circumstances than those which appear so far to have arisen.29. In paragraph (iii) of our terms of reference we are asked to consider and report&quot; whether His Majesty&apos;s Government should use the powers bestowed upon them by the Ottawa Agreements to obtain in the Dominions and India the continuance or extension to goods manufactured in the Colonial Empire of the tariff preferences accorded to goods manufactured in the United Kingdom &quot;.The potential privileges for the Colonies expressed in these words of our terms of reference were obtained for them at Ottawa in return for privileges granted by them. The Secretary of State for the Colonies acted, as the direct representative of their interests at Ottawa, and has since taken opportunities of pointing out to Colonial Governments the advantages which they secured from this arrangement.30. At the same time the circumstances in which this concession was obtained must be remembered. The negotiations at Ottawa were conducted under con-siderable pressure. Certain specified tariff preferences were obtained for the Colonial Empire in the Dominions* and India and for the Dominions and India in the Colonial Empire, but none of the negotiators felt sure that the requests made were absolutely comprehensive and that nothing had been overlooked. Obviously it was not possible to insert a clause in the Agreements permitting entirely new requests for preferences to be made at any time, but it was felt that some of these casus omissi might be covered if it was provided that the* No Agreement was mado tit Ottawa with tho Irish Freo Stato.
Colonial Empire should be granted on demand any preferences granted to the United Kingdom and that the Dominions and India should receive in the Colonial Empire all preferences granted to any Empire country. But it was never antici-pated that this arrangement would raise problems of the kind created by the emergence of the rubber-shoe industry in Singapore and Hong Kong. If it had been, it is probable that Dominion Governments would have seen strong objection to admitting goods manufactured under Oriental conditions to their markets under a tariff designed prima facie to place the United Kingdom in the position of a &quot; domestic competitor &quot; with the Dominion industries.31. On the other hand we think that having obtained the right to claim privileges on behalf of the Colonies His Majesty&apos;s Government are, morally speaking, bound to exercise that right and seek tlhe privileges desired, if requested by a Colony, unless some very strong reason affecting the interests either of the United Kingdom or of the Colonial Empire can be shown for a different course of action.32. Looking at the matter from the point of view of the Colonial Empire we should not consider that His Majesty&apos;s Government are under any obligation to accept too short-sighted a view of their responsibility in this connection, and to assume that a privilege which can be obtained on demand must necessarily be immediately demanded. If a Colony seeks to obtain admission for its products to a &quot; Dominion &quot; market (including India in this term, as a matter of convenience), on the terms applicable to the products of the United Kingdom, and His Majesty&apos;s Government are entitled by the Ottawa Agreements to demand such admission, then very strong reason must be shown before refusal to make such a demand; but we are not certain that in some instances, taking a long view of the real economic interests of the Colonies, it may not be a mistake to put forward demands, the presentation of which may induce Dominions to exercise forthwith their right to propose variations in the provisions of the Ottawa Agreements relating to the Colonial Empire and in due course to re-consider the whole arrangement of giving the Colonial Empire the right to the same tariff treatment for its products as that accorded to the United Kingdom. It is probably not in the ultimate interests of any Colony that its products should be forced upon a Dominion market at prices with which Dominion manufacurers of similar products cannot compete, with the almost certain con-sequence that there will be an irresistible demand for the termination of that part of the agreements which render such a condition of affairs possible. We, therefore, think that the Secretary of State would be justified in examining very closely all the circumstances as to cost of production and transport, price at which articles can be placed on the market, and subsisting trade interests with which they will enter into&apos; competition in the case of any such demand from a Colony as we have envisaged, and that he would be,justified in turning down an immediate advantage to the manufacturers of a particular article in a Colony if he reached a considered opinion that the Colony&apos;s &quot; goodwill &quot; in the particular Dominion market would be seriously imperilled, and a brief enjoyment of a privilege which was resented as unjust would be followed by a final abrogation of the privilege in its application to trade generally, and possibly by the adoption of a generally hostile trade policy on the part of the Dominion concerned.33. We are not prepared to say that a position at all like this has yet been reached in any particular instance, but the case of the cheap rubber shoes manufactured at Singapore, to which we have alluded in the previous part of this report, indicates what may easily happen. In that case the shoes are admitted to the Canadian market under the British preferential tariff, and there-fore no question arises of demanding for them in that market any privilege of preferential duty enjoyed by the United Kingdom, but the suggestion has already been made that the circumstances of this case would justify a proposal by the Canadian Government to vary the terms of the Ottawa Agreement under the provisions of Article 23 and we think it is obvious that frequent instances of competition of this character would probably lead the Dominions to frame their general tariff policy with a view to the definite penalisation of manufactured products which are the work of &quot; coloured labour &quot;, whether under the British flag or not.
34. Again if a particular Colony has declined to grant the privileges to the Dominions provided for in the Ottawa Agreements (that is to say, has refused to make its payment for the privileges contained in the clause we are discussing), we think the Secretary of State would be under no obligation to ask the Dominions to accord that Colony further benefits.35. The cases in which it might be necessary to refuse to put forward a request made by a Colony on account of its effect on United Kingdom interests are, in view of the considerations above referred to, naturally much fewer. We think however that it may be useful to state the kind of case we have in mind. We refer to two but there may of course be others : (a) The concessions made to the United Kingdom by the Dominions (apart from Canada) are in general in the form of rates of preference and not rates of duty so that they admit of the &quot; British preferential tariff &quot; rates being raised provided the &quot; general tariff &quot; rates are raised pro-porfcionately. It is possible that where the Colonial industry is an important one the extension of a particular preference to the Colonies might, owing to relative costs of production, unduly reduce the protection afforded to the local industry and thus result in a demand for an increase in the preferential rate of duty. This is particularly likely to happen where, as in Australia, the British preferential rates are supposed to be based on relative costs of production, and we think that in such a case His Majesty&apos;s Government would be justified in refusing to put forward the Colony&apos;s request.(b) Where a Colony has refused to give the appropriate preferences to the United Kingdom we think His Majesty&apos;s Government should be much less ready to ask for the extension of increased favours to that Colony.36. While, therefore, we think it should be the general practice for His Majesty&apos;s Government to claim on behalf of the Colonies the advantages in Dominion and Indian markets which the Ottawa Agreements give them the right to claim, we think that the considerations to which we have referred may properly be taken into account before action in this direction is taken in any individual instance.37. We proceed to summarize the conclusions at which we have arrived and the recommendations which we put forward : (i) We regard some industrial development in Colonial dependencies as an inevitable contingency which cannot be prohibited or indefinitely retarded.   (Paragraphs 1-4.)(ii) It is preferable that if production by native labour with native standards of living is to develop it should take place in British Dependencies rather than in foreign possessions.   (Paragraph 5.)(iii) We do not think that there is any need to accelerate such develop-ment and policy in this connection must be determined by consideration of the interests of the United Kingdom as well as those of the Colonies. (Paragraph 6.)(iv) Until recently the Colonies imposed import duties almost solely for revenue purposes, there being no local industries to protect: for the same reason such duties were not accompanied by corresponding excise duties. Subsequently preferential duties were introduced, these now extending to, and being designed to encourage the import of goods from, all parts of the British Empire.   (Paragraphs 8 and 9.)(v) In some instances, however, Colonial tariffs are protective: whilst we regard protection against foreign industries as less open to objection we regard the creation of local industries by protection against United Kingdom industries as requiring to be justified by special considerations.   (Paragraphs 10-12.)(vi) The advantages to the local producer of raw materials of a guaranteed local market are not sufficient in themselves to justify pro-tection against the United Kingdom manufacturer, whose interests should also be taken into consideration in determining tariff policy.   (Paragraph
n(vii) Subject to the qualification just mentioned, we recommend the Principles of Discriminating Protection laid down by the Government of India as affording useful guidance in the matter of Colonial Tariff Policy. As these principles were adopted by the Government of India solely for the benefit of India it could not be contended that their adoption by the Colonies would be prejudicial to Colonial interests. (Paragraphs 14 and 15.)(viii) While the commercial interests of the United Kingdom and the general economic well-being of the particular Colony are both factors to be weighed in determining the tariff of a Colony, if the two appear to be in conflict the latter should prevail. We suggest a general line of interpretation for the words &quot; general economic well-being&quot;. (Paragraphs 16-17.)(ix) We should regret to see any departure from the general prin-ciple of free entry for Colonial products embodied in the Import Duties Act, 1932.   (Paragraph 18.)(x) A departure from this principle would weaken the arguments for restricting the imposition of protective duties in the Colonies. (Paragraphs 19-20.)(xi) We have considered particular instances of competition in the United Kingdom and Dominion markets of manufactured articles pro-duced in certain Colonies under Oriental conditions. We regard this as a serious factor in inter-Imperial trade relations, but we should be sorry to see it made the occasion of a breach in the symmetrical system of &quot; free trade for Colonial imports &quot;.   (Paragraphs 21-24.)(xii) We recommend that a deliberate policy should be pursued of assimilating within reasonable limits conditions of employment in the Colonies to those in the United Kingdom, although we recognize that such assimilation must proceed slowly and cannot solve the problem of Colonial competition which is likely ultimately to arise. (Paragraphs 25-27.)(xiii) We suggest the encouragement of negotiations between pro-ducing interests in this country and in the Colonies where the problem of Colonial competition becomes acute, with a view to arrangements being reached to mitigate such competition.   (Paragraph 28.)(xiv) Only in the last resort should we regard the introduction of protective tariffs in the United Kingdom against Colonial manufactured products or the imposition upon such products of compulsory quotas as an expedient to be contemplated.   (Paragraph 28.)(xv) With reference to the provisions in the Ottawa Agreements empowering the United Kingdom Government to ask for the extension to the Colonies of tariff preferences granted to the United Kingdom by the Dominions and India, we give some account of the circumstances under which this power was conferred.   (Paragraphs 29 and 30.)(xvi) We consider that the United Kingdom Government are morally bound to exercise the power which they have obtained if requested by a Colony unless some very strong reason to the contrary can be shown. (Paragraph 31.)(xvii) Such reason might be one affecting the interests either of the United Kingdom or of the Colonial Empire. The United Kingdom Government ought to take a long-sighted view of the real economic interests of the Colonies, and we suggest a number of considerations to be borne in mind.  (Paragraphs 32-36.)38.   Our specific recommendations are : (i) That the grant of tariff protection to industries established in the Colonial Empire which compete with United Kingdom industries, should only be sanctioned in special cases in accordance with general considerations which we have laid down.(ii) That every endeavour should be made to avoid the imposition on any Colonial products by the United Kingdom of any import duties other than &quot; revenue duties &quot;; and that the best immediate method of
meeting the problem of competition by Colonial products with the products of United Kingdom industry is to promote agreement between the producing interests on a basis of sharing markets.(iii) That having obtained the right to claim privileges on behalf of the Colonies, His Majesty&apos;s Government should hold themselves morally bound to exercise that right and seek the privileges desired, if requested by a Colony, unless some very strong reason affecting the interests of the Colonial Empire (or in special cases of the United Kingdom) can be shown for a different course of action.We have been much indebted to our Secretary, Mr. L. S. Smith, for his assiduity and accuracy in presenting and dealing with the material which we have had to consider, and we wish to express our thanks to him for the ready assistance which he has rendered to us throughout.R. V. VERNON.G. L. M. CLAUSON.A. EDGCUMBE.E. HALE.A. KILROY.G. E. BO YD SHANNON.L. S. SMITH, Secretary.Colonial Office, 3rd March, 1934.(23700-2)  Wt. 10388-3201 375 8/34  V. St.  G. 3


</content>
</cab>
