<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/249/0 images: 404-408</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1934.Copy No....*CABINET.Situation in the Wa States, on the Burmo-Chinese Frontier.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.A situation giviug cause for some anxiety vis-d-vis China has arisen on a small section of the Burmo-Chinese frontier which is still undemarcated, and though it will not, I hope, be fraught with serious consequences, and such action as appears possible is already being taken by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and myself, I have thought it desirable at this stage to circulate a brief note for the information of my colleagues.2. The greater part of the frontier between Burma and China, including the section now in question, is laid down in Anglo-Chinese Conventions of 1894 and 1897, hut, while the rest of the prescribed frontier was demarcated in the years 1897-99,. the joint Boundary Commission failed in the following year to reach agreement on a section in the unadministered area of the primitive Wa tribes, stretching roughly from a point on the Namting River (about lat. 23d 29&apos; N.) to Nalawt (about lat. 22c 10&apos; N.). The Chinese commissioners adopted an unreasonable attitude, ignored the general alignment of the frontier laid down in the Convention and claimed a line some miles to the west of it. Finally the British Commissioner, Sir George Scott, determined an alignment conforming as nearly as practicable to the description in the Treaty and notified this (Scott&apos;s line) to his Chinese colleagues. His Majesty&apos;s Government decided that this line should he regarded as the provisional froutier. The Chinese Government were informed accordingly in Notes of 12th May 1904 and 7th March 1905, the latter of which stated that Chinese officials and troops could not be allowed to transgress across the Scott line. The Chinese Government in a Note of 30th March 1905, declined to accept this provisional boundary, and suggested that, pending demarcation, each side &quot; should maintain its old limits of jurisdiction without trespass on either side, so that the welfare of the frontier between the two countries may he duly preserved.&quot; The westernmost line claimed by the Chinese is known as the Liu-Chen line, or yellow line. The experience of the Commission in 1900 made it clear that no progress could he expected from further attempts at demarcation on the spot, and His Majesty&apos;s Government have continued to regard the Scott line as the provisional frontier. No attempt, however, was made on our side to administer the Wa country, and there is little doubt that there has been some infiltration of Chinese influence into it for some time past. In 1929, the question was considered whether an attempt should be made to settle the frontier question by means of a conference with the Chinese Government, which would lay down principles with a view to facilitating a subsequent agreed demarcation. This plan came to nothing, however, as His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Peking at that time doubted whether the Chinese were prepared for serious negotiotions.3. During recent years reports were received from non-official travellers, indicating; a possibility that valuable deposits of lead, silver, zinc and copper might be found, in a locality in the northern corner of the Wa States. In 1933 the Burma Corporation, came to the conclusion that these reports were sufficiently circumstantial to justify them in examining an area round a place called Lufang, which is on our side of the Liu-Chen line, and some 10 or 15 miles distant (as the crow flies) from, our administered areas. The Corporation were anxious to send a surveying party to this area, and, since an escort would be required to protect the surveyoi&apos;s from possible attacks by the local tribesmen, asked for the co-operation of Government. Since, if such minerals were found, their exploitation by the Corporation would be of great benefit to Burma economically, and to the Government of Burma financially, I decided, after informal consultation with Sir Robert Home, Chairman of the Burma Corporation, and Sir Hugh Stephenson, the Governor of Burma, to authorise the despatch to Lufang2866      65   6.34SECRET.CP. 158 (34).
of a surveying party accompanied by a small force of the Burma military police, with a civil officer in control of the expedition. As Lufang is in indisputably British territory, no international question arose from the despatch of an expedition to that place. In view, however, of the Chinese claim to the Liu-Chen line, instructions were given that nO survey or other operations were to be carried out to the east of that line. Arrangements were also made to inform His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Pekino-of all developments, in order that he might be able to deal with any enquiries made by the Chinese authorities regarding the expedition, since it was anticipated that its despatch might lead to unwarranted agitation in Chinese nationalistic circles. The expedition started early this year, and reached Lufang about 21st January. The result has been disappointing to the Burma Corporation, as no mineral deposits have been found in commercially exploitable quantities, and the Corporation^ experts have now been withdrawn. During the surveys, however, friendly relations were established with several of the small statelets (on our side of the Liu-Chen line) into which the Wa tribes are divided, though other chieftains, under Chinese instigation, adopted a hostile attitude. The Burma Government is thus committed, as it of course anticipated might be the case, to maintaining some form of control of the hitherto unadministered areas which the expedition has entered. The instructions that the Liu-Chen line was not to be crossed have been scrupulously observed.4. Nevertheless, exaggerated and incorrect reports of the proceedings and intentions of the expedition led to considerable agitation in Yunnan. The Nanking-Governments representative at Yunnanfu enquired of His Majesty&apos;s Consul-General to what point the expedition would proceed. It was necessary to avoid language which might prejudice the British claim to the Scott line, and the Consul-General was instructed on 17th February to reply that His Majesty&apos;s Government regarded the Scott line as the frontier, but that, as a matter of fact, it was not at present anticipated that our party would have occasion to go beyond its present position at Lufang. Various representations were also received from the Chinese Govei-nment at Nanking, and, on the other hand, we protested against an incursion by Chinese officials and troops across the Scott line in March. On 14th May, however, the Nanking Government stated that they were sending a party, which would be instructed to cross the Scott line, as a &quot; bond fide mission of enquiry to study conditions on the spot.&quot;5. The question of the delimitation of the frontier has also been mentioned in the course of conversations at Nanking, and the Chinese Government are being informed that His Majesty&apos;s Government are prepared to agree to this, but consider that the first step should he to settle the principles, on which a delimitation can be based, by means of a conference at Nanking, pending which the status quo should be observed. Sir A. Cadogan is accordingly to take strong exception to the Chinese proposal to send a mission across the Scott line, and is to point out that His Majesty&apos;s Government on their side have scrupulously refrained from crossing the Lm-Chen line out of consideration for the status quo of 30 years&apos; standing.6. Meanwhile, since 1st June numerous telegrams have been received from the Government of Burma reporting concentrations of Chinese troops with the intention of attacking our positions and communications. It is not clear whether these troop movements are connected with the intention of the Chinese Government to send a mission of enquiry, whether the Chinese forces are acting under the orders of the Nanking Government or of the Provincial Government of Yunnan, or to what extent they are composed of regulars. Certain bodies of Chinese troops have, however, already actually penetrated to our side of the Liu-Chen line. The Burma Govern-ment&apos;s telegram of 1st June reported that uniformed, and therefore presumably regular, Chinese had been found entrenched on the Panglao ridge (a mile or two on our side of the Liu-Chen line), from which they were dislodged with the loss of over a dozen Chinese killed, but with no casualties on our side; the uniform and property on the Chinese killed showed that they all were, or had been, Chinese regulars. Later telegrams report definite information that approximately 2,000 Chinese troops are concentrated at a place, Manchiu, about one mile east of the Liu-Chen line, with the intention of attacking Lufang, and reliable information that another body of 3,000 Chinese troops have arrived at Mengcheng (some distance on the Chinese side of the frontier), who are credited with the intention of an attack on Hopang, on our line of communications some distance within our acknowledged frontier. The presence has also been reported of a body of Chinese, stated to be 300 strong, in one
India Office, 11th June 1934,S. H.of the Wa statelets well to the west of the Liu-Chen line, with which we had established relations. The chief of another State has received letters from the commander of a Yunnan volunteer organisation inciting him to rise against us. These events have naturally caused great anxiety among our friendlies.7. A telegram from the Government of Burma of 6th June reports that our military police forces are at present confined to the defensive by large threatening Chinese forces, and points out that the situation involves some risk either of our forces being invested by superior Chinese forces, if the latter cross the Liu-Chen line, or of a general turmoil among the Wa States, which might also affect the peace of the neighbouring Shan States in administered British territory. Steps are- being taken to reinforce (from Lashio in the Northern Shan States) our military police in the occupied area (Hopang-Lufang). Their existing strength on 8th June was about 750. Reinforcements amounting to 200, including one section of a mountain battery, have already arrived or are on their way up. A battalion of the Burma Rifles is being sent to Lashio to take the place of the military police sent forward as reinforcements.8. The policy which we should pursue is, I think, sufficiently clear. In the first place, r,he immediate necessity is to send up sufficient reinforcements to avert any risk of a successful Chinese attack against our existing forces or their comirmnications. In the second place, while refraining, as before, from crossing the Liu-Chen line pending a settlement of the frontier question by negotiation, we must so far as possible maintain control over the States with which we have established relations, and should resist by force any Chinese aggression to our side of the Liu-Chen line. With the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, I have sent a telegram (of which copy is annexed) to the Government of India, indicating, in reply to their request for instructions, that this policy should be pursued, and also suggesting that the officer in command of our forces should communicate a message to the Chinese commanders calculated to reduce the risk of further incidents. Copy is also annexed of a telegram sent by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to His M.ajesty&apos;s Minister, Peking, instructing him to lodge a strong protest against the unprovoked Chinese aggression and dealing with the question of negotiations for a settlement of the disputed frontier.
APPENDIX I.Telegram from Secretary of State to Government of India, Foreign and PoliticalDepartment, dated 7th Jane 1934. (Repeated to Governor of Burma, No. 1492)No. 1491. Your telegrams 6th June, Nos. 1319 and 1324, and connected corre-spondence ending with Burma telegram 6th June, No. 80. Wa States. Telegram instructing His Majesty&apos;s Minister, Peking, to lodge strong protest with Chinese Government is being repeated to you.2. Our policy must be (i) to continue for the present to refrain from any extension of our commitments and from crossing Liu-Chen line, or taking any action against Chinese forces on the east of that line ; (ii) to take all possible steps to protect positions and communications of our military police forces, and so far as possible to preserve control of areas which we have entered and of Wa States on the west of the Liu-Chen line with which we have established friendly relations ; (iii) so far as military situation permits, to resist hy force any attempts by Chinese troops to cross the Liu-Chen line.3. It is consequently very desirable that all possible steps which are considered necessary for the above purposes should be taken to reinforce our military police forces in the Hopang-Lufang areas, with a view at any rate to reducing to a minimum, risk of disaster to our forces through investment by superior Chinese forces or through a general rising in the Wa States stirred up by Chinese intrigue. I note that one section of guns is to be sent to operations area, and that Burma Rifles are to move to Lashio to relieve maximum number of military police there for t-einforcing our columns. Please telegraph existing strength of military police in the operations area and number of reinforcements on their way. If it is considered necessary and desirable to move regulars into the operations area, this will not increase difficulties of a settlement of the dispute by diplomatic methods, since if Chinese cross the Liu-Chen line in force and attack our columns, they will in any case put themselves in the wrong and it will make no difference diplomatically whether they are opposed by civil armed forces or by regulars. You should therefore make all the preparations which you consider necessary to meet such an eventuality. -4. I suggest that officer in command of the expedition should send messages to the commanders of Chinese troops at Manchiu and Mengchang and any other place where threatening concentrations may be reported to the effect that (a) discussions regarding disputed frontier and the present situation are inprogress between His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Chinese Government and that the provincial Government of Yunnan is being informed of these discussions;(b) while these negotiations are in progress our forces will not cross a specifiedline (corresponding to the Liu-Chen line) which is the extreme limit of the Chinese Governments claim ;(c) we consider that similarly, pending negotiations, Chinese forces should notcross Scott line, which we claim ; and(d) in any case, if Chinese forces cross the Liu-Chen line this will be an act of aggression which will be forcibly resisted.5. Similar messages might perhaps be sent to any Chinese officers who have penetrated into our Wa States.APPENDIX II.Telegram from Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Sir A. Gadogan (Peking),dated 8th June 1934. (Repeated to India, No. 28.)No. 202. Burma telegrams Nos. 70, 71, 72, 75, 76 and 80 (of 1st and 5th June : Chinese activities in Wa States).2. You will observe that uniformed Chinese troops have been found entrenched on the Panglao ridge and have apparently been located elsewhere to the west of the Liu-Chen line.
3. You should immediately protest in the strongest possible terms to the Chinese Government regarding this unprovoked aggression by Chinese uniformed and presumably regular forces. You should state that these forces have penetrated deep into British territory west of the Scott line, laying special emphasis on the fact that bodies of troops have been located even to the west of the Liu-Chen line, which our expedition has scrupulously refrained from crossing, and have come into conflict with the Burma military police in the area to the west of that line. You should suggest that it is essential in order to avoid furthur incidents that immediate orders should be given for withdrawal of all bodies of troops that have crossed the Scott line, failing which the Chinese Government must take the responsibility for the consequences and His Majesty&apos;s Government would naturally consider themselves free to take such action as they considered necessary or desirable. Protests should also be made against the occupation by the Chinese of the zone between the Scott and Liu-Chen lines and the intrigues carried on among our tribesmen to the west of the Liu-Chen line. It should be stated that the Chinese occupation of the disputed zone can in no way prejudice the British claim to the territory tip to the Scott line.4. In regard to the despatch by the Chinese Government of an exploring party-reported in your telegrams Nos. 38 and 39 Tour, you should make representations to the Chinese Government in the following sense : 5. While the Chinese Government do not admit, and His Majesty&apos;s Government claim, the Scott line, His Majesty&apos;s Government do not admit the Chinese claim to the Liu-Chen line, and, as His Majest3&apos;&apos;s Government have scrupulously refrained from crossing the latter out of consideration for the status quo of 30 years&apos; standing in this region, it is reasonable to expect the Chinese, out of a similar consideration, to refrain from crossing the Scott line. The despatch of the party proposed by the Chinese Government could only give rise to serious difficulties and postpone, perhaps indefinitely, a friendly settlement of the disputed frontier. If the Chinese Govern-ment proceed with their proposal it will, of course, be necessary for His Majesty&apos;s Government to retain complete liberty of action, and the Chinese Government will appreciate the difficulties likely to arise if exploratory missions were to be despatched by both sides.0. On the question of the potential mineral value of this area of which apparently the Chinese have exaggerated notions you may assure the Nanking Government, in such manner and at such time as you think fit, that the recent mining investigations carried out by the Burma Corporation^ experts in areas west of the Liu-Chen line have yielded only negative results, from which they7 are satisfied that the neighbouring areas also do not offer any more favourable prospects than those investigated.7. You should go on to point out that the dispute regarding the frontier is of long standing, and can only be satisfactorily settled by an agreed delimitation, such as the Chinese Government have already suggested. His Majesty&apos;s Government are quite prepared to agree to this, and would, of course, adopt a reasonable attitude on all points in dispute, but they consider that as a first step it is necessary to settle the principles which should underlie a delimitation, and therefore suggest that these should first be discussed at Nanking with representatives of His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Government of Burma. It would, of course, be essential that representatives of the Government of Yunnan should be associated with the discussions from the outset. When once principles had been settled, a joint commission could, if necessary, be sent to demarcate the frontier on the spot. But to send an advance party before an agreement on principles has been reached would, apart from the other objections already referred to, be a mere waste of effort and unlikely to lead to any satisfactory result. The essential points are to settle the governing principles for a delimitation of the frontier, and, until this has been done, to avoid any inter-ference with the status quo. His Majesty&apos;s Government feel confident that, on further reflection, the Chinese Government will agree with this view, and will let His Majesty&apos;s Government have early proposals for consideration.8. You should not yourself mention the question of a reference of the boundary question to the League of Nations, but if the Chinese raise and press this question, you should emphasise that direct negotiations on this highly complex issue, though not formally opened, have been definitely envisaged, and that while this is the position it would be premature and entirely unreasonable to suggest a reference to a third party.9. If you consider it desirable that Consul-General at Yunuanfu should take similar and simultaneous action, please instruct him accordingly.2806 is

</content>
</cab>
