<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/249/0 images: 481-482</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITMNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOFEKMKSNT.HET- C A B I N E T COPY MO.     *g    j  ..166(54) . 7     -TOMIPLOTMENI ASSISTANCE BOARD.Date of the First Appointed.Day.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.Since my memorandum CP.134 (34) I have discussed the matter with the Chancellor.     He has satisfied me that in spite of the difficulties which I stated in that memorandum, we must aim at fixing the First Appointed Day early in November.In order to achieve this the Minister of Labour will need the active co-operation of his colleagues in the Cabinet and I therefore set out the time-table which will have to be adhered to.If the Appointed Day is to be in November it will be necessary for the draft Regulations to be completed by the Board and formally submitted to the Minister of Labour by the middle of September.     The Board is to be appointed in the first week in July and therefore will only have about ten weeks at most (including August) for the consideration of the details of the Regulations and for the discussions that must obviously take place with the interested Departments and others.The Regulations will in effect state the standard of assistance which the Government thinks appropriate for persons who are long unemployed.      The Minister of Labour will have the right to alter the draft submitted by the Board. And the draft approved by him must be positively approved by both Houses of Parliament before it comes into force.It will be necessary for the Cabinet to approve the draft Regulations before they are submitted to Parliament and for this purpose the draft must first be examined by a Cabinet Committee, which will have to be ready to sit in the first week of October and possibly to devote a considerable amount of time to the task.     The Regulations will have to be submitted to Parliament about the middle of October for affirmative approval.I ought to add that the time required for the consideration of the Regulations by the Board and subsequently by the Minister of Labour and the Cabinet Committee may prove to be longer than this time-table contemplates.
(intd.). H.B.25th June, 1934.Further, despite the efforts that are being made by the officials of the various Departments,  the mechanical difficulties of setting up such a big&apos; organisation may make the start of the&apos; scheme at the beginning of November impossible.While, therefore, I hope that this time-table may prove to be possible, it is important that no announcement should be made at present or promise given that the first Appointed Day will be as early as November.      I should propose that the Chairman of the Board communicates with the Minister of Labour so soon as he is in a position to do so, probably early in September, stating what in his view is the earliest practicable date.      It would obviously gravely prejudice the success of the scheme should the date be fixed before the Board is ready to take over the work from Local Authorities.     The Board should of course be informed of the desirability of completing the arrangements as early as possible.

</content>
</cab>
