<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/249/0 images: 638-639</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Bl3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MA.J3STY&apos;S GOVHEUaifflMT.0.P.17O- (34)HARBOURS.  PIERSJIDJJSSRRIES (SCOTLAND) BILL. M^ S^^^LJbZ-^g.-^g.QTetary of State for Scotland.From two different aspects legislation In regard to piers and harbours in Scotland is overdue.In the first plaoe there is the question of ensuring the maintenance of adequate means of communication &quot;by sea, especially in the Highlands and Islands.    Many piers were built by proprietors of estates, who are not now able to maintain them in proper repair.    Other piers were provided by County Councils with the aid of Government grants, but the rating pov/ers of these Councils under the present law are now inadequate for maintenance purposes.Secondly,  legislation is needed to provide a simple procedure whereby pier and harbour authorities can obtain powers for the construction of new vrorlcs and other purposes.    This mainly affects the small fishery harbours, particularly the herring fishery ports.A Bill has been drafted to deal with these points.    Part I provides a simple procedure by which Counts&apos;&apos; or Town Councils may be authorised to accept the transfer of privately-owned piers, harbours or ferries.    Part II deals with the construction of new worics under simplified procedure.     Part III is a &quot;maintenance&quot; code, the main object of which is to provide for the fixing of dues and to empower any local authorities in whom piers, harbours or ferries may be vested to meet any deficiency out of rates.The Bill does not cover the grant of assistance from public funds.   No additional powers are required, as such assistance, when necessary, oan be given through the Development Fund orSecret.cabinet.from/
from Departmental Votes (e.g., the Department of Agriculture or the Fishery Board).The Bill has been framed in consultation -with, and with the approval of, the Treasury, the Ministry of Transport, the Board of Trade and other Departments interested, but local authorities may&quot; have various points to raise on its character and provisions.I ask for authority for its early introduction for purposes of publication, and ulth a view to its reintroduction next Session after discussion with local authorities.(Intld.)    G.P.C.29th June, 1934,

</content>
</cab>
