<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/215/0 images: 144-146</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
130iTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROP1RTY OF HIS BRITANNIO MAJESTYlS GOVERKMENT].   MaiORANDW by the PRESIDENT of the BOARD OF EDUCATION.     When, in July,-1929, I first brou^it before the Cabinet thequestion of implementing our intention of raising the school leaving age I pointed out (CP.204 ( 29) ) that it would &quot;have to&quot;be decided whether allowances are to be given as a right or&quot;whether the Local Education Authority is to award them in&quot;accordance with a need standard&quot;.     I had previously received representations from the Associa-tions of Local Education Authorities that they were opposed to any system of universal allowances and were in favour of a plan underwhich these allowances would be awai-ded in necessitous cases only and in accordance with the needs of the family.     On the second reading of the Education Bill on 29th May ofthis year I stated that I proposed to use a report presented tome by the representatives of the Local Education Authoritiesrecommending scales of need and a simple procedure for determing eligibility and to frame the regulations generally on the lines suggested by them.     On 2nd July; however,  a meeting of the Parliamentary LabourParty passed the following resolutions:-          &quot;That this meeting of the Parliamentary Labour Party     &quot;express the hope that the Government can include in the     &quot;Education (1930)  Bill provision hereby  a maintenanceSECRET.CP.  305(30).CABINET. -RAISING THE SCHOOL LEAVING AGE.feintenance, A3Jowances.
131      &quot;allowance per child of fivt shillings a week be paid to      &quot;persons in respect of all schCol children in the age group      &quot;14-15, the amount of such allowance io be1 deducted in the      &quot;case of income tax-payers from the sums granted as ohild-      &quot;allowance under the income tax regulations in order to      &quot;prevent duplication of payment&quot;.     This proposal would seem to involve the payment of 5/- a week to all parents of school children having less than  270,  thepayment of a variety of rates to parents having incomes between 270 and  350, and the payment of the difference between 5/-a week and 2/3i (the amount of rebate) to all parents havingincomes between  350 and  500 a year.   Moreover,  the administra-tive difficulties would be almost insuperable,  since detailedparticulars of every rebate case would have to be obtained by theLocal Education Authorities from the Inland Revenue.     The simple criterion of liability to pay Income Tax hasalso been suggested, but I am advised that this criterion would bring in parents with wages of nearly  7 a week if they had one child, and that about 95 per cent,  of the children of 14-15 in the schools would receive allowances.    This proposal  must be ruled out as going far beyond any criterion of need in the recipient.     I have discussed the matter with the Chancellor of theExchequer, and we agree that,  while  we must find a basis  whichwould be less costly to the Exchequer than either of the  schemesabove mentioned, at the same time in view of the strong feelingmanifested by the Party we shall be  bound to put forward  someplan which is much more generous than that suggested by theLocal Authorities&apos; Committee.     I accordingly propose,  with the concurrence of the Ghancellppof the Exchequer, that maintenance allowances should be limited tooases in which the parents&apos;  income does not exceed  3 a week ifthey have one or two children,  3:5:0 - if they have three children,                                2.
132 3:15:0 - if thoy have four children,  4:5:0 - if they have fivechildren,  4:15:0 - if they have six children,  5:5:0 - if theyhave 7 or more children.&apos;   It is estimated that approximately75 per cent, of the children of 14-15 in the schools would receive allowances on this basis.     I further suggest that the parent should be required tomake a formal application for an allowance accompanied by astatement of income on a prescribed form with penalties for falsedeclarations.   Notwithstanding the views expressed at the Partymeeting, I do not think that the Local Authorities can be prohibited from verifying the applications if they think fit,in view of the fact that they are to be called upon to administer the scheme and to pay part of the cost.     I shall endeavour to secure the agreement of the LocalEducation Authorities to this scheme,   I am, however, bound topoint out that they originally pressed for 100 per cent,  grant,and I  must make it quite clear to the Cabinet that if the LocalAuthorities are asked to bear a larger expenditure than under their own scheme and are at the same time deprived of thediscretionary powers which they would have had under the reportof their own -Committee, it will be by no means easy to persuade them to work new proposals on the basis of a 60 per cent,  grant.This,  however, is the limit beyond rhich the Chancellor of theExchequer is not prepared to go, and if the Authorities continueto press for a hi^ier rate I am prepared to proceed with the Billwithout any further concession to them.                                               C.T.11.9.30.

</content>
</cab>
