<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/215/0 images: 234-240</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY QF HIS  BRITANN!C MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. 13pret                                                                y.F&quot;.&quot;507(5Q) .                                                Copy Ho. ^CU                                  CABINET                    &apos;           &quot;                           IMPORT  BOARD  POLICY.         Memorandum by  the Minister  of  Agriculture  and Fisheries.                         J     teeneral  ConsideraTions.          1.     It  is important,  as  stated  in  I.E.C.  (30) 61, para.  14,        that any decision  to set  up  Import  Boards -should be  taken with        a clear  idea of the purpose  for which  they  are to be used.   This        memorandum  suggests the appointment of a Board for the purchase        of imported &quot;Wheat and Flour,  and of home-grown Wheat of millable        quality, as  an  ingredient of  our home  agricultural policy.          2.     Although Lulk Purchase  may  become valuable as a        part of  our  Imperial machinery,  the Import  Board policy of        the Labour  Party was designed to secure a reasonable measure        of stability and a fair price for the  home  producer, to arrest        the decline  in  cultivation and  employment in arable  farmin:,,        and to safeguard the consumer against  unfair prices within        our existing system of tax-free  food imports.          3.     The  reasons which prompted  the formulation of this        policy three years ago are much more urgent today.  Our        returns  for  the present year  indicate  a deoline of 114,000 acres        under the plough and of 23,000  men  employed in agriculture in        England  and Wales.          4.     The position, however,  is now much worse than when        these returns were compiled on  4th  June.  It is already certain        that this winter there will be  a much  larger decline in arable        cultivation, and probably a much greater volume of agricultural        unemployment than last year.          5.     A decision on the Quota  scheme has  boen deferred        pending  the  Imperial Conference, and if the Import
Board system were accepted, it might not he necessaryto use it, although perhaps the Board on the side  ofits home operations, would find the quota machinery helpful in the marketing of home-grcwn wheat of mlllcble .  quality.  6.      This memorandum is written in the light,  and takes account of the considerations presented in the othermemoranda already submitted.  7.      It is suggested that by means of the Import board a stabilised price for home-grown wheat of millable qualityshould be secured to the home grower, and that the  extraprice s&amp; afforded, sc far as it was above World price,  wouldbe provided by the Board distributing the amount over itssales of imported wheat or flour.  8,      It should not be forgotten, also, that whether welike it or not, the consolidation of the wheat sellingagencies is proceeding apace, and that the method  of freepurchase is fast disappearing.  9o      I agree with tho statement in memorandum IaEoCo(30) 61, i)ara0 36 that we cannot with confidence atthis stage say that an Import Board would be able tosecure such economies as would compensate for the  extraprices given to the home grower - at all events when world prices are so far below what would probably be yffered,say 50s.  It is on ;this aocount the more necessary  tbjaV,the scheme should be accompanied by powers to be exercisedif necessary to control Bread Prices upon the basis of  flourorices.  10.     I concur with the statement in the memorandum that there is not evidence to show that there is undueprofit on the wholesale side.  The statement in para. 2, page 15together with Table 31, page 18,  indicate the profits that are certainly being made in those branches of the bal-cery
183trade which are charging the higher bread prices.    Inaddition the subjoined table shows the relation between wheat and bread prices,  as well as the variation in bread prices,and indicates an ample margin for Control.                          TABLE.Town.           Price of 4 lb. loaft   Corresponding price cf                                       wheat per quarter                                       T480 lbs) on millers                                              scale.Newcastle,                  lOd.        60s. to 65s. per qr.Colwyn Bay,Barrow- in-Fumes s .Leicester.                   9^d.       55s. to 60s.  n    &quot;Leeds.Glasgow, Cardiff.            9d.        50s.  &quot; 55s.  &quot;    &quot;Bristol, Edinburgh       )Norwich, Ipswich,        )London, Birmingham,      )(London Co-cps selling   )              45s.  &quot; 5Cs.  &quot;    &quot;at -g-d. less delivered    )and Id. less over counter)Liverpool.                   8d.        40s.  11 45s.  &quot;    &quot;Gloucester.                  7-gd.       35s.  &quot; 40s.  &quot;    &quot;Manchester.                7d. - 7^d.   3Cs.  &quot; 4Cs.  &quot;    &quot;Blackburn.                   7d.        30a.  &quot; 35s.  &quot;    &quot;          Bread was therefare selling at the same time atranges equivalent to variations ef from 30s. to 65s. per quarter of wheat.                   Part II. Difficulties.    11.   The chief difficulties anticipated in the workingof the Impart Beard system affect (a) Relations with theDominions, (b) International Trade,  and (c) Internaldifficulties.                    (a) The Dominions.    12.   It would be felly to ignore the difficultiesforecasted, and we may confidently expect that  theDominions will put forward big claims.   At the same timenone of the difficulties appear to ms tc be such as
                                                     A 134 -could not be dealt with by a sensible&apos;and well managed  Board, provided that we made clear beforehand its governing  purpose, and the principle upon which it would be  directed to operate with regard to purchasese   Its  governing purpose would be to stabilise and help  home agriculture, and it would be instructed to make  its purchases so far as possible at world prices, and to  have regard to the necessary interests of our trade  in other countries, for example, the Argentine.(b)    Effect on International Trade.    13. There is one consideration which is scarcely  stressed sufficiently, I think, in the Cabinet  memorandum, viz, the risk of interference of a  considerable international exchange trade which is  centred in London.   This is referred to in the  Report of the Royal Commission on Pood Prices,  paragraph 329, and it would require to be met by leaving  shippers free to buy in the world markets and to offer  their supplies either to the National Board or to -  importers in other countries, provided that when the wheat  is not purchased by the Boat&quot;d for home use it is transhipped( c)    Internal difficulties.    14, The disturbance of internal arrangements and the  dislocation of the business of existing importers would  require to be dealt with by enlisting their services to  operate as agents for the Board.       Part III - Details of the Scheme for Wheat and Flour.    15. It will, I feel sure, be necessary in the course  of time to have Import Boards operating on various  commodities, but in view of its urgency as the key to  the arable situationfl I suggest that our first proposal  should relate to a Wheat and Flour Board only, and the  following scheme is designed so far as possible .on lines  to meet the various objections that have been put forward.
&quot;    185                                                          5.            16.  A British Grain and Flour Corporati&apos;n would be     constituted by Act of Parliament which should be the  sole     importer of wheat and wheat flour from Overseas, and  the     sole purchaser of all home-produced wheat of millable     quality.MOTS:    The Corporation would have power to license in exceptional cases importation by other bodies and to exclude from its operations such portions of the home crop as werenot of millable quality.             17.  It would be governed by a Board composed      of State representatives and representatives of existing     ^trade interests and the co-operative, movement.             18.  It \70uld be empowered to raise its own      capital subject to Treasury sanction, and its capital      would be guaranteed Dy the Government, both a3 regards      principal and interest.   The Corporation would have the      right of borrowing money for short terms and would be      expected to finance the major part of its operations in      this way.HOTS:     To a p?eat extent it would finance its shipments  bymeans of Bills of Exchange now customary in the trade, therebyobviating the necessity for an unduly large amount of working capital.             19.  Subject to the control of the Minister of       Agriculture (? or President-of the Board of Trade)  in       matters of general policy, the Corporation would act  as a       business on the lines, for example, of the British       Broadcasting Corporation or the Central Electricity Board.            20.  It would probably be necessary in the Bill  to       authorise the Corporation to include other cereals  in      the scope of its operation, subject to Parliamentary sanction.
    -     186   21.     Tho Corporation would purohase the entire homeorop of wheat of millable quality, and would, I suggest,fix a reasonable price in advance.   22.     I suggest that for the first year the price of the home orop should he fixed at SO/- per quarter allowing for deviations from this price in relation to variation in quality according to the methods now in use in the trade. The prioes for subsequent years would be fixed by the Corporation subject to confirmation by Parliament.   23.     All authorised millers would be allowed to purchase wheat direotly as agents of the Corporation, if this were found desirable to avoid unnecessary handling, storage and transport, provided that the price charged by the Corporation for imported grain, where the home prioe was higher than the world price, would be suffioient to compensate for the difference.   24,     The Corporation would be left as unfettered as possible in its: methods of purchasing grain, and it would be left free to buy from day to day or to enter into built for -ard contracts as might be deemed desirable.  Itwould certainly be a mistake to tie down the Oorporation at the outset to any particular method of purchase.  .25.     Nevertheless it would be one of the objects of the Corporation,  as exijerience developed,  to enter into bulk contracts  with Overseas producers for a forward delivery of grain either at a fixed price or  at a variable price determined in advance according to a fixed formula. In this connection it might be  open to the Corporation to give Empire countries the first chance of  supplying its requirements at  world prices by arranging bulk forward contracts which would probably be as  far a3  it
187Ministry of Agriculture  and Fisheries-     10, Whitehall Place,  S.W.1.         15th September, 1930,would be safe to use it in the first instance as  apiece of Imperial machinery,26o       It is suggested that the milling industry should remain under its present control with themilling firms acting largely as agents for the homecrop, but it would be necessary to take powers tocontrol the Price of Flour upon the basis of allowing the miller a fair conversion charge over the price atwhich he &quot;feuys his grain,,   Power would also be needed to fix the Price of Bread with reasonable margins,probably on a district basis.87e       The Corporation would aim at conducting its operations on a self-supporting basis, selling thewheat at prices based on the average cost at which ithas been bought, but it would aim at eliminating  short period fluctuations as far as possible and, as experiencedeveloped, securing stability in prides over longer andlonger periods.    The Corporation^ administrative costs would be met on the ordinary business basis, and  it isnot suggested that it should receive any contributionor subsidy from the Exchequer apart from theguaranteeing of the capital.

</content>
</cab>
