<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/215/0 images: 358-365</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS SOCDLLiSgJ IS THE gHOgjgxigY Oi)&apos; HZ8 BRITANIJIC iuAJESTY&apos;3 GOTOMMEHg) 3 S C B 3 a. CP. 319(50).                                          COPY HO. _                              C A ii IHSS.                            COTTOR SITUATION.       Memorandum, by the Secretary of State for Home Affairs.1,        ny colleagues T)ill wish to receive a r^ort on the general position in the Cotton Industry and the action taken following thepublication of the Report of the Committee of which I was Chairman.     I.  MLOYllENT ABP SRASE SITUATION.2.        Employment has continued to decline.   On the 25th August,the latest date for T^HICII figures are available, the number ofcotton operatives out of work (both wholly unemployed and temporarily stopped) haci increased since tho 25th June from 234,000 to 258,000.The cotton operatives unemployed- at the 25th August represented12.5c/o of the total unemployed at that uate.   In tne American spinninsection employment is only 50^.   In tiie Egyptian spinning sectionit is rather better though still depressed.   In manufacturing(i.3&apos;. weaving) employment is also very bad.3.        2hQ trade outlook gives little ground for optimism.   Theprices of raw cotton are 40$ below the prices at the correspondingperiod last year.   Although there was a slight recovery lafat week in-the price of Egyptian cotton, American cotton continues to declineinlprtce.   Some small encouragement HAB been derived from signs ofslackening in the Indian boycott and from an improvement in the shanghai exchange reflecting an upward movement in the price of silver,  but there has been nothing to indicate any real change inthe  situation,  , As in other industries, the position continues tobe dominated by the slump in the prices both of rav material and finished products and aa long as prices remain low and tnere is no corresponding fall in THE cost of production, there oan be no realimprovement.
     II.  ACTION SINCE PUBLICATION OP THE REPORT.4.        It will be remembered that, after it had been decided to publish the Committee1s Report, it was arranged&apos; that I should visitManchester on the day of publication in order to communicate theCommittee&apos;s findings to representatives of the industry,  and secure their co-operation in applying the recommendations of the Report.Nearly every interest of importance, whether employers or operatives,is represented on the Joint Committee of Cotton Trade organisations and a meeting of this body, with a few additions; was entirelysuitable for this purpose.   This meeting was of a purely introductorycharacter; it could not have been expected that on the day of publication I should receive considered views on questions of suchgravity as those raised by the Report.   All I asked for was an indication in general terms that the various sections of the industry were prepared to take immediate steps to examine the recommendationsof the Report,and this I received,5.        A further meeting of the Joint Committee was held on the29th July, to consider those aspects of the Report which particularly 1affect the Joint Committee.   At this meeting the followingresolution \?as passed.     &quot;The Joint Committee of Cotton Trade Organisations,  having     considered those sections of the report of the Cotton Inquiry     Committee which relate to its own activities, is gratified to     find that the report so largely endorses its policy.    It     proposes to take up without delay the questions which lie     within its province, namely the extension and improvement of     statistical and other information,  closer co-operation between     the various sections of the industry,  and the development of     organised propaganda.   The Executive is authorised  to take the  i     necessary steps to hasten progress in all these directions.     All sections of the Industry are invited to assist and support     its efforts.&quot;6.        The executive of the Joint Committee is now at  work on aconcrete programme embracing the various activities which the JointCommittee could profitably undertake during the next few  years.This programme will include     (1) The development of information services.
? &amp; 0hi O O&apos;(2)  Machinery for closer relations between technical and  , economic research,  with a view to concentrating effort    upon the immediate  needs of the industry.(3)  Proposals for the application of the results of    investigation to the ao^J    of Lancashire&apos;s goods..;^investigation to the actual production and distribution     (4) Organisation and development OF propaganda for the         industry as a whole.7,        As instances of the projects on which the Joint Committeeare working may be mentioned a proposal for the co-operativeproduction and marketing OF standard lines, a beginning being madewith a &quot;grey cloth&quot;; it is hoped that by the co-operation of allconcerned it may be possible to get down to a price sufficientlylow to recover some of our markets in lines where our loss of trade has been particularly grave.   ANOTHER interesting step which hasBEEN arranged is the holding OF a British Cotton Textile Exhibitionin connection with the British Industries JPair next Pebruary.   AnEconomic Mission under Government auspices to the Far East,  whichhas just left London,  includes a cottoa sub-mission,8.        A further meeting of the Joint Committee will be held onthe 30th September.   At this meeting the following resolution willbe proposed:-     She Joint Committee of Cotton Trade Organisations isanzious that no reproach shall attaoh to the cotton industryregarding its efforts to apply the recommendations of theCotton Inquiry Committee.   It observes that definite action is already being taken In various sections, particularlytowards the introduction of more modern technique and millorganisation.   The Joint Committee recognises that in many directions progress can only be achieved by the sections actingindependently or in direct negotiation with one another.   Butthe final result of seotional progress affects the well being of the industry as a whole;  the potential benefits of improve-ments in one seotion may be destroyed or impaired by failure on the part of another sectIon to make corresponding progress.It therefore appears to the Joint Committee that in addition tothose aspects of the report wniou affect them directly as aJoint Committee, they also ht,ve the duty of informing themselvesfully on sectional action and even, should it be necessary, of representing to any particular section the considerations which seem to other sections to be o*f special importance to theindustry as a whole.   It cordially invites sections not onlyto make reports at this and subsequent meetings of the endeavoursthey are making but also to agree as a matter of principle thatfrank discussion by the Joint Committee of these efforts shallbe encouraged.
          Whatever action is taken by tho cotton industry,  however-,     many of the causes of the present depression axe beyond its     control, and the Joint Committee emphasises cnae move  that the     responsibility for dealing with these lies in the hands of the     Government and of ether interests outrride the cotton industry.     Such problems as are raised by the difference in working     conditions and hours between this country and its competitors,     the burden of national and local taxation, s.nd the anomalous     effects of monetary policy, call for immediate action.It is evident that tho Joint Committee are doing all in their powerto secure the most earnest consideration for the recommendations ofthe Report.9.        Thus Considerable progress is being made to give  effect tothose recommendations of the Report which relate to the development -of co-operative effort in the industry.   As regards the other recommendations of the report progress must necessarily be  slower.Shese other recommendations fall into two groups:-     (l) possible technical changes, suoh as the increased  use                                                 -         of Bhort-stapled cotton, the substitution of ring  spindles         for mules, and the increased use of automatic looms.   3ome         of these suggestions Involve consideration of changes in         working conditions; and     (2) amalgamation.10.       Tho recommendations in the former group are underconsideration by the sections concerned.   Tho questions involved arecomplex and some raise issues which may prove controversial,   Thequestion of putting a time limit on the consideration of these recommendations by the various sections may have to be considered,but there are obvious dangers in inviting the formulation of opposingviews on points of controversy as long as there is any prospect thatwith further time the differences might be resolved.   The  Chairmanof the Joint Committee (Mr.Herbert Lee) contemplates using  themeeting on the 30th September to press on the different sections ofthe industry the fulfilment of their undertaking to give the Reportearly and urgent consideration.   He aopes to use the machinery oftho Committee to resolve any differences taal may emerge between theviows of the various sections     -4-
11.       Referance may be made In this connection to thenegotiations which arc going on in connection with the introductionof the eight loom system.   On that and any other question whichis a matter of controversy between the parties concerned, we cannotof course take sides.   The Ministry of Labour are watching thesituation vory closely, and I understand that, difficult as theposition is, both the employers and the operatives axe handlingit with care.12.       As regards amalgamations, the reasons for delay are rather different.   The traditions of Lancashire are strongly individualist,and although the spirit of co-operation is making headway, individualspinners, manufacturers and merchants are often reluctant to combinewith their business rivals.   Even when this obstacle has been overcome, and negotiations start, formidable difficulties remain.Many of the firms which amalgamations will have to embrace have long ceased to be profitable, and an amalgamation of such.unitscannot succeed unless the assets of the proprietors and creditorsare written down to their true value.   It is however natural thatproprietors and creditors should be slow to realise the full extentto which their assets have depreciated; and even if an agreed value for the whole of the assets can be reached, it will still benecessary to secure the agreement of debenture holders  and othercreditors (including bankers) and shareholders to the proportionsin wnich losses are to fall on each class of interest.13.       Some of those difficulties are illustrated by a scheme the failure of which has been ventilated in the press by itspromoter, doubtless in tho hope of creating embarrassment.Mr. S.S. Hammersley,M. 1&quot;. is Interested in a group of spinningmills, whion have got into such serious difficulties that they canonly continue if absorbed into some other combination.   TheLancashire Cotton Corporation have been willing and oven anxiousto tale them over, but their valuation of the assets of the group
is very far below that of the proprietors.   For this and other reasons Mr. Hammersley and his friends are extremely reluctant to &apos;join the Corporation.   Ur.Hammersley accordingly endeavoured toarrange another combination and hoped to raise a large sum ofnew money from the Bankers Industrial Development Company.   I donot propose here to go into the details of the scheme.   Sufficeit to say that none of the new money which it was proposed toraise was allocated to measures designed to reduce the cost ofproduction; the greater part of it was to be used to pay offcreditors, the bulk of &quot;hose claims were unsecured,  and evenshareholders.14.       She announcement made in January, as lord Privy Seal,  bythe Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, and the subsequent-recommendation of the Cotton Committee make It quite clear thatthe essential featuxe-.of rationalisation is the reduction of the costs of production and that it is for schemes embodying measures designed to reduce costs, o.g. by the modernisation of plant, that new money will be available.   It should have been clear thatthere was never any intention of providing new money simply toenable old money to be taken out.   Finance cannot reasonably beexpected for the purpose of paying out those who put money induring the boom period.   I am satisfied that the rejection ofMr. Hammersley&apos;s scheme is in no vay inconsistent with the under-takings that have been given, and does not imply any change in theattitude of the City.15.       While this scheme has failed,  as I thinl. it was boundto do, progress is being made in other directions.   The lancashire cotton Corporation, which was floated under the auspices of theBank of England with a view to tho control of 10,000,000 spindles,continues to consolidate its position.   Proposals arc underconsideration for the amalgamation of another group of spinning
mills on a basis of low capitalisation with a view to economicalworking, and- there is also a proposal to group certain combinedspinning and weaving firms making Cheshire Printer cloths.   I hopesoon to see progress towards the amalgamation of weaving -firms &quot;hichis so badly needed, and I understand that discussions are beginningamong certain groups of merchants.   While there are as yet fewconcrete proposals, a good deal of discussion is taking place fromwhich I hope that concrete proposals will emerge.16.       Thus it may be seen that, while good progress is beingmade on the recommendations relating to co-operation in the industry,progress is slow on other matters, namely, amalgamations and questions of technical improvements (involving consideration of changes in working condition).   It remains to consider whether anyfurther action can be taken to accelerate matters.   During July received a letter from Mr.James Bell, the Secretary of the UnitedTextile Factory Workers&apos; Association, suggesting that a conference should be held under a neutral chairman of the various interestsaffocteu...   To this I replied that until the various sections had completed their consideration of the Report, such a conference seemedto be premature, but that I would of course be glad to considerholding such a conference later if the various seotions thought thatwould be a good way of making progress.   That is still my position.I do not think that a general conference would help matters unless there were some definite subject to put before it, and that is notthe case at the moment.   It would be unwise to try to hasten ameeting or,to hold a conference before the parties we should calltogether were ready for suoh a gathering.   Mr. Herbert Lee, theChairman of the Joint Committee, has informed me that hecontemplates using the machinery of the Committee to resolve anydisagreements that-may emerge between the various Sections, and-this appears to me a more hopeful method of procedure than a general
conference.    In the meantime I remain in close  contact withthe situation, and I shall not fail to take any opportunity thatmay present  itself of assisting the industry  to  surmount  any difficulties that may arise.(Initialled)   J.R.C.25th September,  1930.

</content>
</cab>
