<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/215/0 images: 638-703</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 DOOUMENr IS,.THE&apos; PROPERTY OF HIS BRITATOIQ MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERHItENT.iET.                                                 OS 3L.IOJ,10.....347(30)                                OABIITET.                            STATE OF TRADE.     ?Lpc!L  S!iH L.^iLJ^Pi?^.?..Sadp^the meeting- of the Board of Trade,                 AdjyiBory Council on 8th October,  1930.       Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.     The reports received from the Members of the AdvisoryOounoil show that the general depression in trade in this countrycontinued during September.  At the same time the reports arenot entirely devoid of encouraging points.     In the coal trade output for the September quarter showed ascompared with last year an average decrease of 250,000 tons a  &apos;week, of which nearly half IB attributable to decreased exports.These are due in turn largely to increased Polish competition in scandinavia and the Baltic, a recent instance of which is a contract with the Finnish State Railways at 10/- a ton f.0.b.Danzig/Gdynia which&apos;leaves the Polish Collieries only 5/- a tonat the pithead.     In the home trade business is waiting until the schemes under the Goal Mines Act of this year become operative, when thetrade generally will benefit through the salesmen being enabled to know what quantities there are for disposal and at whatminimum prices.     As indicated in my last Memorandum of this series, steel production in August fell to the lowest level of any month inrecent years except those attributable to coal stoppages iri 1921and 19.-V? and, though no September figures are yet available, itwould appear that they will not show any improvement.  The povertyof demand is general and has led to the dissolution of the
continental International Price Associations;-  Continentalprices are very low,  &quot;basic pig iron delivered at  works inSouth V/ales being offered at 57s.  3d.  per ton as  against  Britishprioes of 85s, to 67s, 6de, v/hile  stoel pricos are  pounds perton below the british, o,g., rods   4.  17. 6d. against   9. 10. Od.Belgium and Prance maintained their output of both  pig iron and  &apos;steel fairly well in August.  Scotland reports that thecontinental prices are almost-as low as in 1914,  but the  biggestimports of pig iron into Scotland  are  from India, 9,585 tons  inAugust;  the steel output in August last was only 57.5 * of thatin August 1929, and the September  output is expected to be stilllower.  The position can be summed up  as very unsatisfactory  andwithout sign of improvement;  the  only exception being that although the recent reduction in price caused little increase in demand the tinplate trade is fairly well maintained.     In engineering the position has deteriorated seriouslyduring the last two months.  Attention was called particularly to the difficulty experienced abroad in the length of creditoffered by our German competitors, as  much as five  to seven years being offered in some cases  with agricultural machinery.     The electrical industry has new  begun to feol the pinch,orders for new general business having fallen off - morenoticeably in the South of England.   The effects of foreignimportation are beginning to be folt;   the general  tradeconditions from which all countries are suffering have led manyto concentrate on the English market,  wireless apparatus  is coming from the United States of America, lamps from Holland andwires and general supplies from Germany,  Such importation isbeing met by price reductions, e.g., in lamps which are now37:&apos; below 1914 prices and in valves.  The Grid 3oheme is  stillkeeping-some firms busy, but the fooling was expressed that theforeign importer is gaining the advantage from the  greatlyincreased use of electric current which the scheme  was devised to promote.
     There are still no orders for new cargo ships and only afew for tankers and smaller craft and the shipping situationmakes the outlook poor for shipbuilding,     Tho Shipping Freights Indox receded during September to13,5;* below the 1913 average.  The only marked feature has beenthe wholesale chartering of tonnage for the shipment of Russiancoroals.  This has brought into uso a number of British ships that were laid up and on balance it is expected that the laidup tonnage figure for October 1st will be about 100,000 tons lessthan three months earlier.  However, owing to the low pricestaken for this Russian wheat  (dropping to about 9,5/- per quarters-)shipments from other exporting centres such as Australia and the st, Laurence has been stopped.     The Australian tariff and general economic depression areblamed for poor outward freights to that Dominion.  This is borne out by figures communicated to the Council which show that theimports into Australia during July and August last were only 14,000,000, a decrease of 511,000,000 as compared with a yearago.     The decline in total railway traffic receipts Bince themiddle of the year has been much accentuated;  the figures forthe first six months of the year, for July, August and Septemberbeing 3%.S, 8; ,     and 9^.&apos; respectively.  The heaviest decline isin raw material traffic (eg. iron ore and pig iron) and thisaugurs badly for the future activity of the railways.     Necessarily the Oompanios are economising in current expenditure and the shops are working to only 50.? of their capacity.At the Bame time the arrangement with the Government relative tothe remission of Passenger Duty and the Development Act, 1929, have^-Figures given by Mr, E. Glover.  The Oo-operative Member  (Mr. Varley) has given prices between 31B.8d. and 29B.  for  September 8th,  - 13th.
enabled oxtensive capital works to bo put  in hand.;   these  shouldgradually Involve a total expenditure of between  50,000,000  and 40,000,000.     The motor manufacturing industry shows some slight  improvement.The commercial car side is, however, beginning to feel the accumulated results of the general trade position;   there  was a drop of 839 in the number of these newly registered in August last(from tho figure for August 1929) while the total drop in suohregistrationo for all vehicles was 3,197.   In the export  trade thereis a growing demand for light cars in Empire markets and forBritish agencies abroad, apparently at the expense of the UnitedStates of America, which should bo fruitful when commodity pricesbecome more  stable.     There is little increase of activity in the cotton trade;the weakening in the Indian boycott has not yet had substantialresults, and buyers are awaiting a rise in the price of cotton,which fell during September to below 6d (middling American) the lowest for fifteen years.     One very interesting  and  Important move has however been made,the Lancashire Ootton Corporations offering yarns spun from IndianCotton at effectively low  prices.  The primary object of the experiment  is to take advantage of the improving raw Cotton from india, which has hitherto  been neglected in Lancashire, and to makefrom it  yarn suitable for  cloth which can compete with Japan andthe Continent.   Considerable  succoss has attended the Corporation^initial  efforts  and though the matter is still in the experimentalstage  it appears to have been established that Lancashire can produce  from Indian Ootton Cloth  at  a lower cost than either the indians  or  the Japanese  can produce  it,     The report  of the Cotton Enouiry is being very  seriously considered  by  the various  sections  of the trade  and  by the JointCommittee  of Ootton Trade  Organisations;  the employers and
operatives should meet to discuss it in the couroe of thenext few weeks, and it is hoped that these discussions wouldembrace important matters affecting the industry,  such as thepolicy of the Trade Unions and the price rates for variousoperations.   The Joint Committee is moreover occupied with matters which can only be settled by the Government,  such as the monetary system which it was stated was considered by Lanoaehireas very largely responsible for low prioes - also internationalconditions of labour.     The view was expresood that the problem of getting rid ofpart-time working by closing a certain number of Mills would haveto be faced.  Emphasis was also laid on the necessity andfeasibility of cultivating alternative Markets to India such asthe Near East and Africa.     The wool trade remains in a very depressed condition mainlyowing to a further fall in wool prices.  Stocks of manufacturedand semi-manufactured goods are, however, abnormally low.  Pricesof wool tops are now lower than at any time since 1908,and someexpectation of a revival of manufacture under these favourable conditions was expressed.  Complaints are made of the newCanadian tariff which it was stated would increase the price inCanada  (hitherto the best customer abroad for our woollens) ontho lowest class of goods by over 70;? and affect the better classmaterials severely.  Some concession had been granted to meet  thecase of goods already contracted for, but the period of graceprescribed was regarded as Inadequate.     Hosiery shows some seasonal improvement, but not as much asnormally.  Continental imports at low prices are complained of aswell as the Canadian tariff.     As is only to be expected, the general situation in the chemical trade shows little change, but there is some sign ofimprovement in the fine chemicals trade.
     The dominant factor in the wheat market at the moment isthe Russian export, which has already been referred to,   Thisis not now of such good quality as the early shipments, hut theprice is attractive.  The Co-operative Wholesale Society state in their report that they have &quot;not been a free user of Russianwheat compared with private millers, as the quality hac not been so good, but owing to the low price of flour now ruling, theirmillers arc obliged to draw their attention to this wheat&quot;.     In Canada whore the yield of the new crop is better than was anticipated, the initial payment by the Pool has beenreduced from 65 cents, to $0 cents.  The U,S. crops have yieldedwell, but the short maize crop may have the effect of keepingwheat supplies in the country.  In tho Argentine and australia the outlook is for large crops.     Preliminary figures from departmental stores show that notwithstanding the fall in retail prices tho turnover for september is down by only a slight percentage accounted for,namely by falls in the furnishing and hardware departments.Stocks have been considerably reduced^ but numbers employed showa slight increase.     Co-operative  sales in England for the four weeks ended september 15, show a drop of 7.7^ in values as compared with-corresponding period in 1929, and in Scotland there is a similardecline whioh is not entirely accounted for by lower prices.Retail prices have not fallen as much as wholesale, e.g. whilethe falls since September 1929, in the wholesale price of flour,sugar and butter have boen  25.&apos;, 18.&apos;, and 9.9A respectively, thecorresponding retail falls have been only 7,1, 8&apos;/&apos; and 16?$,     Unemployment  increased during September by 101,895 to2,161,689  (September 29), the change being praotically wholly inthe numbers wholly unemployed.  The greatest increases were inthe London and South Eastern Division  (30,000) and tho NorthEastern Division  (23,000).  In the cotton  industry thore was a
  W      welcome fall of 11,400 in the numbers unemployed and a slight      improvement also in the coal mining Industry;  iron and steel,      engineering and shipbuilding showed increases.           There has been little change in the monetary situation      during September, easy conditions continuing.  Prance has taken      most of the gold available in the open market here and some from      Germany owing to political developments in the latter country;      the franc is now  (October 7) above the export point.           As regards the trade of our most important Colonies      attention was called to the inoreased proportion of British      goods in the total imports of several of theso countries, a point      mentioned in my last Memorandum, and also to the substantial      favourable balances of visible trade they enjoy which support the      &amp; sterling.           The now Governments in Argentina and in Peru appear-to bo      strongly established.  The Argentine peso remains at a      comparatively low level owing to the great reduction in the value      of the country^  exports, e,g, - from over 600,000,000 gold pesos      in the first seven months of  1929 to under 400,000,000, in the      corresponding period of this year.  Similar declines of exports      have occurred in  other South American countries, in Chile it has      been even more  severe and, though the peso there is above par,      the official discount rate has had to be raised from 6;j to 7fy,      The United States and Canada are restricting  loans and at the      same time raising their import tariffs, thus making things more      difficult for the South American countries whose sentiment      against their Northern neighbours is now stronger than ever.  The      outlook generally in that quarter is particularly obscure.                                               YJ.G.Board of Trade,   20th October,  1930.                                -7-
INDEX.Australian TradeBanking  ..Building .ChemicalsCoalColonial TradeCoroperative TradeCo-operative Trade in ScotlandCottonDistributing TradesElectrical IndustryEmployment .EngineeringGeneral TradeHosieryIron and SteelMeetings of the Council, alteration of dayMotor IndustryNon-ferrous MetalsR.101Railway TrafficShipping and ShipbuildingSouth American TradeVoolStatistical Data  Pago.   17 2,40,79   16   2327,23,30 5,49   1918,42 9-nl5,38   17 2,-3518,44    3   30 9,39 8,29,31,32,34    1   36   35    136,46 6,16,30,45   50 5,25 Annex.
CONFIDENTIAL .Meeting of the Board of Trade Advisory Council            on 8th October. 19 50,    CHAIRMAN: Gentlemen, the Minister has asked me toapologise to you for his non-attendance at thiB meeting todayas he has to attend a gathering of the Imperial Conference.                     R. 101.     Before we commence our business may I say this.  I donot think any gathering of this standing, could take place inEngland at the present time without an expression being made from the Chair of the great sympathy we feel for the widows and relatives of the men who lost their lives in the recentair disaster.  I expect some of those men were personallyknown to you.  It is not alone a tragio event from the pointof view of the misery and suffering that has been inflictedupon their relatives by losing those who were near and dearto them, but it is also tragic because we have to mourn the tremendous loss of gifted men to the air industry of thiscountry.  The only one of them that I had any acquaintancewith personally was Lord Thomson, and any of you who knew himwill agree with me that we have lost one who was anenthusiastic worker in the cause of air development, a mostdelightful personality, and a charming man to those who wereprivileged to have him as a colleague.  I am sure I am onlyexpressing the view of all of you when I say how much weregret him and the gallant men whose lives have been lostwith him.              Change of day for Council Meetings.     There Is one other matter that I have becn asked by thePresident to bring before you.  Of late the attendance of thePresident at these meetings has largely been limited tocoming in for about half an hour at the beginning on accountof the fact that the Cabinet meets on Wednesday.  He has there fore asked me to put it to the members of this AdvisoryCouncil whether instead of meeting on the second Wednesday inthe month it would be possible to agree to having the datechanged to the second Thursday in the month.  I think youwill agree with me it is unfortunate that the president should not be able to attend the meetings as regularly as hewould like.  Perhaps the simplest way would be if I were toask those who would find it impossible or very difficult to change from the Wednesday to the Thursday to hold up theirhande.  Would those who find it impossible or veryinconvenient mind holding up their hands,     I see you hold up your hand, Lord Bradbury.  Does thatmean that it is quite impossible for you?     LORD BRADBURY: Yes, that is so.  But my term of office is coming to an end now so that you need not consider me.I have only half a year to run.     OEAIRLAN: Is it impossible for you, Mr. Lee?-1-
     MR^ H.W. LEE; I always have a Board Meeting of myCompany in Manchester on Thursday, and I am afraid I could notregularly be s,way from that.     CHAIRMAN: Does the same apply to you, Dr, Clayton?     DR. G.C. CLAYTON: I have a Board Meeting in London onThursday, at 12 o!clock, and I would have to go away for that,but I might be here for an hour.     CHAIRMAN: I will report the position to the President, andwe will let you know definitely if he thinks of making anychange,     MR. DOUGLAS HAMILTON:  I suppose the hour could not bereadjusted, retaining Wednesday but altering the hour so as tomake It later in the morning?     CHAIRMAN; I gather that the Cabinet sits until about 12 or1 o*clock, and I do not think you would find the President wasin any better position in that way.  If the hour of meetingon the Wednesday was altered it would be a question of meeting in the afternoon,     MR. DOUGLAS HAMILTON:  Some of us coming from the Northfind an advantage in leaving the North in the morning andgetting back in the evening.  I just throw it out as asuggestion.     A MEMBER: Would it be any use suggesting Tuesday insteadof Wednesday?     CHAIRMAN: No.  The difficulty is that Tuesday is the chiefday in the House of Commons when the President -answers questions and that makes it almost impossible.  When he has 25 questionscoming on about 3 o&apos;clook he cannot be too much tied up.  we will report to the President what the position 1B and will letyou know the result.     Lord Bradbury, we will begin with your report.                          BANKING.     LORD BRADBURY: I have handed in my report^, but Sir GuyGranet will read his.     SIR GUY GRANET: I have a report^ but I will hand it inbecause there is nothing special in it to call attention to. Itis really a technical description of the condition of things.                       ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.     SIR HUGO HIRST: I have hitherto been in the fortunateposition of always having, good reports to make on the electrical industry when there have been complaints from otherindustries, but I regret to say that the last few months the electrical industry has begun to feel the pinch.  That is toeay, the class of people connected with the Grid and supplyingcables and switchgear and overhead transmission are still busy,but general business has shown a distinct falling off in theway of incoming orders.  It is peculiar that for once the**See appendix, p. 41/      Ditto   p. 42
falling off is more noticeable in the South of England thanin the Frovinoes.  I do not know whether it is due to theStock Exchange and other matters that the depression is greater in the South, or whether it Is due to the fact thatthere has been a slight improvement shown in the Provinces.That is problematical.  For the first time we notice this change;  otherwise works are still busy on acoount of the goodorders which we have had,  I am only speaking of the incomingorders.  The contractors throughout the country complainthat they have not much work in spite of the building tradebeing still fairly busy.  .1 repeat again that in generalsupplies we are beginning to feel more and more foreignimportation.     In one or two of our leading commodities such as, forinstance, lamps, which have been highly protected throughpatents, we have again made reductions, and the price Is nowsomething, like 40 per cent, cheaper than before the War, showing-how mass production has enabled us to give the public thebenefit of reduced prices.      That Is in a few words the general condition of the electrical industry.  I am speaking for the Industry as awhole and not for any companies with which I am connected. i must admit that the six months which have just passed havebeen for the electrical Industry generally the worst sixmonths of the year, because they have been the summer months.We have had very fine weather for a long time - we certainly have had very fine weather in September - and that keeps thedemand in the electrical industry back,  Waen we have our normal weather in winter time it.is possible that-theimprovement one expects in the Autumn will come on, buthitherto It has not shown itself.     OHAIRMAN: Are the goods that you refer to coming fromother countries - from Germany or the United States?      SIR HUGO HIRST: They are ooming from nearly allcountries, according to the various articles.  Wirelessapparatus is coming from the United States, lamps from holland, wires and supplies generally from Germany.  france has become an exporter to this country, and even Italy.  It isnot  an attaok on any one country.  Might I put it in thisway.  The general conditions throughout the world which every country suffers from at present have drawn attention to this market where the people of other countries imagine there Ismore money than in their own countries, and consequently theyhave concentrated on this market and we  are experiencing allkinds of newcomers coming in,      CHAIRMAN: I suppose development of the industry Inregard to the big scheme for linking up the differentelectricity stations and developing electricity in the countryside is still going on  just the same.     SIR HUGO HIRST:   That is going on.   All work inconnection with the Grid scheme is proceeding, and thosefirms who concentrate on that are naturally busy, but,If I may refer to it, my great hope of the Gridscheme  -  and it has been stated in the House of Commonswas  that it would cheapen current and would create new industries throughout the country, and all kinds of
appliances would be accessible even to the poor man along with cheaper current, but what I feel is that the foreignimporter is already gaining an advantage from government expenditure expended for the benefit of the people here.  Thatis the point I wanted to mention^*ENGINEERING,     MR. G.E. RO^IAND:  My province covers a verv big fieldextending over at least 60 different branches of engineering.If I were to generalise I would say that during the last twomonths the position has very sadly deteriorated in those branchesof engineering that previously were able 3ust about to hold their own, and I am sorry to say that short time- has resulted.There has been a very serious falling off both at home andabroad.  The difficulty abroad is not only that of price, butit is also that of credit.  There is no doubt we are facedwith competitors who are in a position to give two to fouryears&apos; credit.  I think that is a fact we shall have seriouslyto consider in industry as a whole.  In agricultural engineer-ing I know of credits that have been offered extending fronfive to seven years.  I am not referring to Russia but to othercountries.  I am at a loss to understand how Germany in her present position is able to make these offers.  There are serious offers being made from Germany,  Whether if the offerswere accepted they would be in a position to give those creditsis another question, hut such offers have undoubtedly been made.Y/e are finding in the Couth American market that owing to thedepression, many farmers&apos; notes have had to be renewed, and thesame tiling, as you know, is happening in Spain,  The questionof finance is a very serious factor in engineering as a whole.At a later meeting I should like to place my proposal.s before you in that connection.     CHAIRMAN:  I am sure we shall be very glad to hear your proposals, Mr. Rowland, if you would let the Minister have them.In Germany it is the Banks, I suppose, that make these advances,     MR, G.E. ROY/LAND:  And they use the credit v/hich they have in other countries,  I think in certain of the countries theyare utilising the credits which they have.     CHAIRMAN:  In some other countries it is not bankinginstitutions, hut there are special institutions which make these offers, are there?     MR, G.E, ROWLAND:  That is so.  At another meeting Ishould like to submit a report to you for your consideration onthese points.     uIR HUGO HIRST:  May I say in this connection that I suppose the President is aware that some countries likeSwitzerland give an export bonus for business done in thiscountry when the local industry is suffering.  They absolutelygive the manufacturer a bonus in the shape of particularcontracts to he carried out in Switzerland if they can show somuch export to this country,  V^e are suffering under thatgenerally.*See also written Report from Mr,  Hugo Hirst,  Appendix p.35*
f                                 VOOL.          MR. DOUGLAS HAMILTON:  September is usually a month when     seasonal demands begin to make themselves felt, and     machinery activity increases noticeably.  In normal circum-     stances there would by now have been a very definite     improvement in the wool textile trade, as raw material has     touched an unexpectedly low level and stocks of manufactured     and semi-manufactured goods in the hands of merchants and     manufacturers are abnormally low.  Despite these factors,     trade ie in a very depressed condition, and at the September     Wool Sales, a further drop in prices of about 10 per cent.     took place.  It is evident  that the industry is suffering     from an attack of nerves, and the fall in the prices of wheat,     rubber, etc,9 has had its psychological effect, retarding the     seasonal inflow of orders.          On the other handy, it seems unlikely that the normal     improvement can be postponed much longer., and it will be     surprising if there is not a distinct increase in machinery     activity during the next month or six weeks.          The nev/ Canadian tariff has struck the textile trade of     the West Riding the severest blow it has experienced for     years,  Canada took the first position a s an importer of     British wool textiles, roughly  5,0O09000 being the amount of     last year*s sales of tops, yarns and woollen and worsted     goods.  On the lowest class of goods the new tariff will     increase the price by ever 70 per cent,, and even the better     class materiels will Buffer severely.          It is hoped in the West Riding that the President of     the Board of Trade will press for concessions in the tariff     whilst the Dominion Premiers are in London,          Canada has met us I must sar in many respects more     generoxusly than has been the case in other tariff imposition.     They have allowed a longer period of time in which to execute     contracts that have been placed,, but the period of time they     have given is quite inadequate, and we hope that at any rate     in that direction some efforts will be made to obtain an     extension of time so that goods that were ordered before the     tariff was imposed may be imported into Canada under the old     rate.          CrLAIRMAN:  We Will draw the attention of the President     to the point you have mentioned and will ask him to bear     it in mind.                              COLONIAL TRADE.          MR. CLAUSEN?  I will hand in the usual monthly statement. *     Perhaps I might call attention to one or two tendencies in it.     It relates mostly, of course5 to tr de in the British     Possessions in Africa other than the Dominions.  The general     tendency is downwards moetly.  We export raw materials, and     the price of raw materials is down.  That means our imports     are down too.  There is  one very satisfactory feature however,     and that is that almost universally the proportion of British*See Appendix p.49.
imports is going up.   For instance,  in Kenya and Ugandathe percentage of imports from the United Kingdom is  37  percent, in this period  of 1930 as compared with 36 per  cent.in the corresponding  period in 19R9;    in Tanganyika  It  is58 per cent, as compared with 34 per cent,;   and in the  gold coast it has hit a high level of 49J per cent, as against46 per cent.  In the  case of the Gold Coast, I think  aloneof these territories  the import trade has actually gone  upin the first six months of i930 as compared  with the  firstsi:: months of 19H9, so that that increase Is npt only in proportion, but it is also actually  in the amount of  goodstaken.  In Tanganyika the total imports are  only down 2  percent,, but the imports from the United Kingdom are up from34 to 38 per cent.   That is rather striking, becauseTanganyika is a mandated territory and we as a Government can do nothing overt to favour British.trade as  opposed to anyother trade.     Thore is one other point I should like  to call attenr-tion to0  In most of  these tropical  African  territories  thereis a very substantial favourable balance of  trade. In theGold Ooast, for instance, the value  of the export trade  inthe first six months  was  6.755,000  odd, while the imports were only  4.550.;000  odd0  That is a very favourable  balance.The point is this*  All these Colonial currencies are tiedirrevocably to sterling.  The note issue is  based entirely on sterling securities, so that that favourable balance  is afavourable balance expressed in sterling.  That enables  these territories, so . to speak, to take up the slack from foreigncountries that have sterling balances, and it means by thesefavourable exports that we are protecting the   sterling,                  SHIPPING AND SHIPBUILDING,     SIR ERNEST Wo GLOVERs--  There is no improvement to reportin the shipping position generally which presents diffi-culties almost without precedent in determining the employmentof ships.  The index number of freights which a month agoshowed an advance has receded from 88 to 86,5 and is  thus13.5 per cent, below the 1913 average.     With regard to Russia, the dominant faotor in allmarkets has been the action of Russia in chartering an enormous amount of tonnage for September /October shipment  ofcereals,  From all accounts the grain comes  forwardirrospootivo of market considerations, and is either sold  orstored as occasion requires.  The result of this has  been  a heavy fall in the price of cereals which has prevented otherexporting countries sending their grain forward.     With regard to Argentine, the improvement noted in thehomeward market a month or two ago was of short duration,and freights fell rapidly to suoh an extent  that severalsteamers intended fur grain were diverted from the RiverPlate to the West Ooast to load nitrate, with the immediate result that nitrate rates fell considerably.  A mere  hopefulview  is taken in the Argentine of future business, both in exports and imports seeing the general improvement in theLabour situation resulting from tho change of Government,arid the somewhat better exchange,  This optimism has,however, not materialised sufficiently to have any effeoton shipping yet.
     In Australia the affect of the, Russian action has been severely felt, and would-be shippers are holding back ana are unwilling to pay rates for forward loading previously ruling.Business for the moment is practically at a standstill.Outwards trade is very poor owing largely to the increase inthe protective tariff and the general economic position.     India shows no serious interest In chartering, lineraccommodation being more than adequate.   So far as linersare concerned, the depression in the commodity markets hasreacted on their rates which are on an unremunerative level,the volume of tonnage being in excess of requirements. Forwardbusiness Is neglected.  Large stocks are available, but thelow prices on this side prevent their shipment outwards.There has been a slight improvement, as is expected after themonsoon period, but nothing approaching normal.  The boycottagainst British goods though not so severe is still a factor,but the cheaper products of Japan and of Indian manufacturers are competing seriously against British goods.     Canada and North America have been very disappointing.Chartering for grain from the St, Lawrence which at this seasonof the year should be very active, has come to a stop.  Steam -ers have been compelled to leave and seek employment elsewhere,either in the Eastern States or on the West Coast of America,thus incurring the expense of long ballast voyages.     Outward coal freights remain on a vary low level in alldirections.   The River Plate is the only market which hasshown any variations, rates outwards rising somewhat as thehomeward rates fell, and receding again at the first sign ofa slight improvement homewards.     As regards shipbuilding there are still no orders to record of contracts for new cargo ships.   The only ordersreported are two large motor tankers for Norwegian account,and several small steamers, either for special passenger trade or for cargo and passengers.     As to shipments of coals, at 3,90O,OUU tons for Augustthere Is a drop of three-quarter million compared with July,and over a million compared with August 1929.   Bunker coalsalso show some reduction.     With regard to laid up tonnage there Is no vary greatchange.   The Russian demand enabled some steamers to move,but whilst tonnage laid up at Cardiff was reduced to about half, there was a slight increase of vessels laid up in the tyne,   Probably the 1st October total figure is about 100,OoOnet tons less than 1st July,     I put In the usual statistics. *     CHAIRMAN:  Did any cf the Russian shipments of grain come in British ships?     SIR ERNEST GLOVER:  Oh yes, a considerable number ofBritish ships that were laid up went out to load grain.  Ofcourse they have taken the tonnage of all flags, and a veryconsiderable number of British ships.* See Appendix page 45.
     MR CLAUSEN:  I suppose the point of that is-that thedemand for tonnage for short freights has damaged and nothelped shipping aa a whole because it has squashed the demandfor long freights ?     SIR ERNEST GLOVER:  I think that is the position.  TheAustralian shippers and Canadian shippers are practically allknocked out of the market for the time being because Russiangrain is selling at any price it can fetch, the price ofRussian wheat having gone down to somewhere about 26s.Od., andI believe some has been sold at even less.  If they cannotsell it, I think they simply store it.  I think the main fearis that no one knows how far Russia may knock down the pricefurther, and no one knows, as far as I can gather, whatquantity of wheat Russia has to export.                   EMPLOYMENT .     MR T.W.PHILLIPS:  There has been some fluctuation in the registered unemployment during September, but the net effect was an increase of 101,245 in the total.  This was entirelyamong those described as wholly unemployed, whioh increased by101,895, the number of temporarily stopped being 650 less in total, the increase on the register being made up of 84,000men, 18,000 women and l,50o juveniles *  Geographically therewere Increases in every division:  30,000 in the London andSouth Eastern division, 9,000 In the South Western division,28,000 In the North Eastern division, 20,000 In lancashire and Cheshire, 16,000 In Scotland, and 18,000 in Wales.  TheMidlands camB off best with an increase of l,25o.  Takingthe Industrial analysis for the date 22nd September comparedwith the 25th August, there was a slight improvement in thecoal mining industry.   The numbers temporarily stopped, I am informed,, were about 8,000, but the numbers wholly unemployedincreased by nearly 2,000*  The numbers unemployed increasedhowever in the iron and steel industry, in general engineering and in shipbuilding and ship repairing.   In the cottonindustry the numbers temporarily stopped&quot;fell by 18,000,andthe wholly unemployed Increased by 6,600;  so that therewas a net decrease of ll,40o.   The total number of Insuredpersons in employment as estimated at the 25th September wasabout 51,000 less than on the 25th August, and about 661,000less than a year ago.   But at this time of the year thesefigures are quite provisional as we make a new estimate for July of the total number, and that is not quite readyyet.*                    IRON &amp; STEEL.     MR ARTHUR PUGH:  I will put in a statement giving a resume of the conditions in our various districtsf   I hardly expect that we shall have anything more encouraging this month thanin the past month having regard to the general world depressionwhich I may say is affecting us more keenly then ever.  Therehave been a number of causes of stoppage of works, either in whole or in part&apos;, and that of course will account for the*See also Appendix, page 44.   ,-SQe Appendix,page 34.
contribution wo have unfortunately given to the figures which have been placed before you by Mr. Phillips.    this state of affairs is of g-moral application, with theexception that perhaps the tinplate trade is  holding itsown rather better than any other British branch of  theindustry.  At any rate, the position Is very much less satisfactory than it was In the early months of theyear.                        HOSIERY.     MR ERNEST T. WALKER;  As regards hosiery, there Is generallya seasonal improvement at this time of the year, but thehosiery trade is in a very considerably worse positionthis year than It has been for a long time past, and I am afraid I cannot see any improvement while the presentconditions remain.  We always suffer from imports,  butthis year the increase in imp rts is quite remarkable,especially of the cheap er goods, owing to the fact that money is short0  We have been hit in the  home trade owingto the general depression!, and in regard to the exporttrade we have again been hit.   Canada and Australia weretogether our two best markets, but the Australian tariff haspractically made it almost impossible to ship to Australia,while we shall be very badly hit by the new duties  that arebeing imposed by Canada.     We have a suggestion to make from the hosiery tradewith regard to these duties.   It has been stated that these duties are being put on purely owing to the unemployment inCanada.   If that is really genuinely the oase, it would help the trade very much indeed if the President of the  Board ofTrade would press that these duties should be taken offdirectly trade gets better in Canada.   If we could obtain thatassurance it would give very great satisfaction to the hosiery tradeand also, of course, to Yorkshire.  I will put in the usualreports of the various districts .*     CHAIRMAN;  We will take note of your question and have itsent on, along with the other points raised today,  to thePresident and ask him to look into it,                        COTTON,   .  Sir KENNETH STEWART; Activity in the export trade in cotton goods was not very much more evident during  Septemberthan during the earlier months.  A good many hopes  have been raised by the evident weakening of the boycott position in India,but this has not brought any very great accession of business toManchester as yet, at any rate. Other markets appear topresent more hopeful signs of further trade coming  along,but I am afraid it is a good deal more hope at present thanactual business put through.  I think the real difficulty that exists in most peopled mines is whether the price ofcotton has really reached the bottom.  While these  falls are*See Appendix, page 3 9
taking place in cotton, anyone with business to place prefersto wait until the rise begins.     There have been one or two interesting movements in thecotton trade during the month,  At the very beginning ofSeptember the Lancashire Cotton Corporation announced to thetrade that they were ready to accept rather low prices forcertain yarns.  These prices were based on Indian cotton ofrather a different type of yarn, I think, to the usualManchester yarns.  They were considered by the trade very lowindeed and they met with an Instant response In the way oforders.  So much so that it was found necessary to open andrun at full time all the mills that cculd make these particularyarns.   At the beginning of September there were two millspartially engaged in these yarns, but since then it has been necessary for this particular purpose to open five more mills,and there Is no doubt that If there were more mills availablemore mills would be opened.   The primary object of these yarnswas to provice yarn suitable for cloth tc compete with japan and the Continent,   The results have been very gratifying tothe Lancashire Cotton Corporation, and instances are coming totheir notice daily where orders which were going to foreigncountries are now coming tc this country.     The Trade Mission to the Far Fast left during September,and^ their reports are locked forward tc with considerable interest.  They are, of course, still on the high seas.     I have recently had two letters from America which arerather interesting.  The first gives the position of Americanindustry during this year.  For the first eight months ofthis year, production in America appears to have decreased by 22-g- per cent compared to last year.  This is a very con-siderable decrease.  It is equivalent to a production of1,345,000,000 yards less in those sight months than in thesame period last year.  The other letter refers to a meeting which took place in New York at which were present the leadingcotton mill executives from Maine to Texas, where, without adissenting vote, the 45 members of the Institutes Boards in attendance recommended &quot;That the employment of women and minorsunder 18 years of age be discontinued between the hours of 9 p.m. - \and 6 a.m. as soon as possible, and net later than March 1st,1931&quot;.  There was a very strong sentiment manifested in favourof  making the period of discontinuance even longer than from p.m. to 6 a.m.  This is rather interesting because once or twice \the allegation has been made that in America women and childrenwork all night in the cotton mills, and this letter certainlyseems tc confirm that statement, because this was really a veryrepresentative meeting.  I am afraid what is  meant by this is that!the discontinuance of this night work for women and. minors will only take place while the present depression lasts.  That Isthe impression one gathers from the letter.     CHAIRMAN:  The labour question you have been speaking of,with reference to women and children working through the night,is chiefly concentrated In a few of the Southern States, isit not?     Sir KENNETH STEWART:  I do not know.  Perhaps you know,Mr, Lee,  Is it found in the Eastern States as well?
*  A note on the subject of hours of  labour in the Pine Cotton Spinning Industry of the United States will be found  at  page  29 of the Minutes of the 91st meeting of the Council (may 8th, 1929).       MR. H.?/. LEE:  No.  The Eastern States went on the 48$ hours, hut  the only State that*has  struck to the -,;:8 hours is  Massachusetts.  The other States, like  fhode Island and all  round there, have gone hack to 52, 53 or 54 hours, hut they  do not, as  far as T know, work night tiiae.  The great.place  where they  work night time is in all the Southern States.  I  quite understand this vote that has h een carried because of  course the  Southern States are ruining  the Eastern States just  in the sane way as we are being ruined  in our markets by the  Continental wor-kers and Eastern workers. There is no question  that the Eastern States would all go for the abolition of  women and children working at night, but I do not think  .ithout considerable pressure the Southern States wall agree  to it.       CHAIRMAN:  Do you understand that  this Conference that has  been referred to covered the Southern States?       IfR. H.W. LEE:  Conferences in America are very funny things.  I should doubt whether there were a very great many people  from the Southern States at that Conference.  There is no doubt  that there  is a certain amount of public opinion in America  which thinks the working at night of women and children ought  to be done  away with, and the Federal Government set up an  inquiry, but for the first few days the evidence given was so  bad that the Federal Government thought it had better close  it, and they closed down that inquiry.  They cannot control  the individual States in these matters.  These matters are all  settled by  the individual States for themselves.  There is a  big report  on the subject which gives full particulars of the  times of working in all parts of America.*       CHAIRMAN:  I had a most interesting account of this  position from one of our representatives in the United States  who was over in this country.  If I remember rightly, he told  me that the labour conditions in the Southern States were almost  on a par with what they were in England about 50 or 50 years  ago in connection with women and children working in mills.  That was really the point I was asking  about.       LP. H.&quot;vY. LEE:  I think the conditions in America are even  worse  than  that, Sir.       CHAIRMAN:  possibly the representative I speak of did not  wish  to go  too far in his expression, so as to be on the safe  side.       MR. H.W. LEE:  They are working in the Southern States  at Rates that are actually lower per lb of yarn them any of our  rates  in Lancashire.       CHAIRMAN:  We can only hope that this recommendation will  be carried  out, even if  it is only  for  a  time, because if once  this  night  working of women and children  is done  away with,  even for a  tine, probably public opinion may tend to influence  matters before it is renewed.  I think  it is very satisfactory  to have had the report on the  other matters that  we have had  from  you, Sir Lenneth.   I think it  is a long time since we  have had anyone at this meeting who has reported about mills  being re-opened.  It always seems to be the other way round,  and  it  is a delightful change  to find,  even if in only one  case,  that  we may have something to cheer us up.
     MR. PUGH:  I was wondering whether the agitation which theAmerican Federation of Labour conducted in the Southern states has had anything to do with this recommendation.  I should imagineit ia a case of conscience and preasure from some quarter-, and Irather think the American Federation of Labour has had something to do with it.  I know there was a considerable amount of organised effort in the Southern States last year, and I think the early part of this year  so that I hope it is rather more permanent than the report seems to suggest.     SIR KENNETH STEWART;  I am afraid the first letter I readreally explains the whole reason, namely, that the demand has fallen off so tremendously that mill owners themselves are trying to organise something that will enable a reduction to be carriedout in the cheapest way possible,  I am afraid it is not amatter of conscience, and I am afraid there is not much pressure.     MR. H. W, LEE:  I do not think in the United States, from what experience I have had of it, that anything but the &quot;almightydollar&quot;&quot;has any influence whatever.     CHAIRMAN:  Mr. Lee, have you anything to add?     MR. H. W. LEE:  Sir Kenneth Stewart has given such a lengthyreport, and I agree with so much of it, that I will not duplicateit.  I was delighted to hear that he has four or five more millsgoing, but of course it remains to be soen whether the gettinggoing of those mills will stop other spindles.  *7e shall find thatout later on.     The only thing that I think you might perhaps like me justto so.y a word on Is the Cotton Commission Report.  I daresay you would like to know that that is being taken very ss-riously intoconsideration by the various sections of the trade, and thatprobably some considerable discussion will take place between theemployers1 side and the  workpeople&apos;s side in the course of thenext few weeks.  The difficulty Is that some of the most importantsubjects that affect the industry are those which are hardlymentioned in  the Report at all, i,e., the policy of the TradeUnions, and the price rates for the various operations,  I think weshall be getting&quot; before long to the contentious part of thebusiness, because the employers will be putting forward the alterations which they oonsider are necessary for the considerationof the Trade  Unions.  V:e shall then see whether there is asufficient give and take on both  sides to come to some arrangement which will be for the benefit of  the trade.  In these discussions the Joint Committee of the cotton trade organisations has notyet taken part, but it has had a  meeting and it haB decidedunanimously   and when I say unanimously, that decisionincludes the  Unions who are represented on the Committee  that it is going to consider these points and that If the sections of the trade are unable  to come to an agreement theJoint Committee will take up the  question and will go Into It and give their judgment upon it.  It  cannot, of course, in any waycompel any section to take its view, but I think it will be useful in giving its opinion for both sections of the trade, and for thepeople, and for the Government, and it may help a little in that way.   In the meantime the Joint  Committee is occupying itself  inseeing ho&quot;&apos; it can be, shall I say. of use to the Government.  It islooking Into  various questions which cannot be  settled by thetrade and which can only be settled by the Government, and it will
&quot;be discussing those very shortly,  and I  think will have  somerecommendations to make.  I refer,  for instance,  to suchmatters as the monetary system which we  in Lancashire consideris responsible very largely for these cheap prices which aregenerally ruining our customers,  and consequently affectingour trade.  I think it will be bringing up something about thelabour position abroad very much on the  lines that Sir KennethStewart has mentioned, and which you have been discussing,  in&apos;the hope that representation to the Government might do  some-thing to get the conditions of labour abroad modified so asto bring them somewhat nearer to the conditions we are working under.  Particulars of those subjects we shall, I think,  besending on to you before very long.  One of our great difficulties is this.  I mention this really as a personal view,and not as a view that has been expressed by the trade.   I donot think that if we are to maintain the standard of livingthat we have adopted in England we ever can regain anything approaching the trade that we have lost.  That means that acertain number of mills will have to go out of existence,because if we attempt to work the mills of Lancashire half-time,we are simply gradually diminishing the trade, because we shallnot then be able to compete with the people outside, or  we aredriving the whole lot into bankruptcy.  To my mind, It will benecessary to get the number of spindles and the number of millsworking down to the number  which can work in the trade  on fulltime.  This part-time working means absolute ruination to thewhole trade of Lancashire.  It is a very difficult problem and it is very hard to see how it can be done, but I am  quite certain myself that it is a problem we shall have to tackle,and tackle very seriously and quickly if we are to save  thetrade of Lancashire.     CHAIRMAN;  We are very much obliged, and I am sure  thePresident will be very interested to hear what your Gommitteehas to say on these particular points you have mentioned.     MR. DOUGLAS HAMILTONs  I should like to ask whether theincreased use of Indian cotton which has been r preferred to is theresult of the Cotton Commission&apos;s recommendations, or whetherit is merely a coincidence.     MR. H.W.LEE;  Indian cotton has always been used to acertain extent in Lancashire, but nobody uses it if they can keep  their machinery running full time on better class goods.I think the credit for the increased use of Indian cottonshould really be given to Sir Kenneth Stewart.  He started onthis  a considerable time before the Cotton Commission ever sat.      SIR KENNETH STEWARTj  The question of Indian cotton is anextraordinarily interesting one.   It is a matter v/hichI consider, and always have considered, is almost the cruxof the situation.  It must.be remembered that Mr. Leedeals in his own business with the Egyptian side, whichhas always been run in this country in an extremely efficient and  satisfactory manner, and in which we still maintain a tremendous supremacy.  Whether that supremacy is as completeas it was in pre-war days or not I do not know, but I shouldnot &quot;think it is very far short.  When you come to the questionof American and Indian ootton you get on to a very big and, tomy mind, very important question.  The American crop has been steadily degenerating in quality, and it has also been
steadily taken up to a larger extent in America itself,  and wehave steadily been losing our position as user of thatcotton.  In the meantime the Indian crop has been steadilyimproving in quality while at the same time it has been increasing in quantity.  We however have entirely left it on one side.  So much so that in a year like 1927 or 1928 theimport of Indian cotton to England was 138,000 bales of 400lbs., while our import of American cotton waB somewhere inthe region of 2,000,000 bales of 500 lbs.  The Japanese andthe people on the Continent were taking this Indian cotton and substituting it for American cotton with very satisfactory results, to the extent that as against our 158,000 bales -the Japanese took 1,500,000 bales.  Their purchases ofIndian cotton and their use of Indian cotton have been thebasis of the very greatest inroads into our export trade,  my own belief, and it is a very sincere belief which I amtrying to carry out in actual practice, is that we can useIndian cotton, and not only can we use it, but we can make ayarn of Indian cotton cheaper and better than the Japanese,the Chinese, or the Indians can actually do it.  Thatremains to be proved, but it was after many months of themost careful experiments that we issued this notice atthe&apos; beginning of September offering to sell yarn made of thisIndian cotton at these particular prices, and excellent results have been turned out in every possible way, fromthe point of view of dyeing, bleaching, and everything else.We have already reoeived information that it is quite impossible for us to do it because they cannot do it in india at these prices.  Prom information that we have received -though as I say it remains to be proved - the actual costs ofthe cloth which we are now producing and the prices which wecan sell at in places like Egypt and the Near Fast are atany rate as cheap if not cheaper than the prices at whichthe Japanese are willing to sell similar clothe.  We havesold a fair amount, and our present difficulty is to cope with the demand.  We are not absolutely ready for a fulldress campaign., because It does mean a good deal ofarrangement with regard to mills, and that sort of thing,because it is not very easy to manipulate, and it takestime,  I put this forward to you.  We have not proved allthese statements yet, but at the same time we have a veryfirm belief, backed up with a certain amount of experiencenow, that if we continue to practise the use of this Indiancotton we add on to our present very large trade in clothbased on Egyptian cotton and based  on American cotton a verylarge business in trade based on Indian cotton.  That is what the Lancashire Cotton Corporation is out to do, and theyare having extremely encouraging orders, and a good deal ofencouragement in the way of success.  It is distinctly earlyyet to say that we have mastered the problem, but at thesame time we feel sincerely that we are very far on towards.that particular point.  We are still in the region of hope, and still in the region of conjecture, and still in the region to some extent of experiment, but I think we are getting quite a long way.     CHAIRMAN: Thank you very much.   Your account is very interesting,     SIR GUY GRANET:  Is there no danger as regards theextension of spinning in India?  Your success depends verylargely on the use of Indian cotton;  is not the tendency inIndia to encourage manufactures there as much as posaible?
     SIR KENNETH STEWART:  Yes.  I think there is this  to beconsidered too.  The ootton trade is a very many-sided  thing,and you bring up another side of it.  In the medium counts andin the general American and Indian type this country1s wholeexport trade is pi-voted round the Indian demand.  When  theIndian demand falls off I think there is a tendency to  throwup our hands in despair and to say we shall have to wait tillit oomes back before we oan move.  I think that is a verygreat mistake.  I think there has been too much of a tendency to wait on the Indian demand, whioh takes one-third of  thewhole of our export, before we feel we oan do anything.  Thereare, however, a great many other markets in. the world today.As an example, to my mind some of the most interesting  ordersthat we have received lately have been from Turkey and  fromthe Near East, and from all the swarming population who useeotton goods in that direotion.  Africa is another very interesting market indeed.  Although It Is perfectly true thatit is not going to be at all an easy thing and that it  is goingto take time to work up alternative markets to India, I do notbelieve it is out of the question, and I believe it is  goingto come i  and certainly from the symptoms and from what wehave found in our own business I think the revival of theeotton trade is going to come from all those markets ratherthan necessarily from India.   There is no doubt that india will improve very largely from the present position, but itwill never mean the market for our goods that it has been inthe past.  I do not think, however, that is by any means a reason for despairing of the ootton trade in the future.     SIR GUY GRANFTi I was not thinking of India aa yourmarket.  I was thinking of India is your source of supply ofraw material  * Is that assured to you?     SIR KENNETH STEWART;  I think it is pretty well assured,because there has always been a very large surplus export ofraw ootton there, and it is a growing surplus the whole time,because the actual growth of raw Cotton is proceeding verymuch faster than the manufacturing trade of that country is growing.     MR. LENNOX B. LEE:  I have nothing to add to the Report^I put in, except that the finishing trades are working about50 per oent.  The Russians are now starting the dumping whichwas so much talked of in the Press a short time ago.  Thegoods they send are very good, and their price is about 40per oent. below the equivalent price of British goods.  Incases where they have been slightly late with their firstdeliveries 10  per oent. has been demanded and agreed to, and where their packing has not been quite right a further 10 peroent. has been demanded  and in easeB agreed to, consequentlythey have brought down the prioe to 60 or 70 per oent. of the equivalent prioe of British goods,      MR, H,W. LEEs I do not think that will continue, becausethe Board of  Trade has made an agreement with the Russiansthat In future they shall not  export to British Dominions.      MR. LENNOX B. LEE: I am not talking about the BritishDominionsj  I  am talking about the Par East.  The shippers are getting their  goods, and the contract is for steadydeliveries.tfSee Appendix p. 38.
BUILDING.    MR. THOMAS BARRONs I have no encouraging report to makeIn connection with the building trade.  Unemployment is still very high.  It has not been under the figure of 100,000 thewhole of this year, and the latest figures I have show about 115,000 unemployed compared with a total employed ofabout 800,000.  The biggest decrease is in connection withthe ereotion of working-clase dwellings whioh I think to some extent will be temporary because of legislation that wasenacted some time ago and the effect of that legislation not having yet been felt as far as the actual construction of dwellings and slum olearanoe goes.  While one would thinkfrom the appearance of some of our cities that there is agreat masB of building going on, and that is true to someextent, It cannot be taken that It is general over alldescriptions of building.  There Is a great deal of what we might call luxury building going on, cinemas, theatres, and soon, but there Is not the amount of commercial or industrial building that we would like, and there is certainly not theamount of building in connection with working-class dwellingsthat we would like.     Mention has often been made of the building industrybeing one of the sheltered industries, and I notice that arespected member  of this Council was having a go at it onlylast night,  Speaking of Russia, Russia seems to be able todump building materials or building parts into this country.We have had for some years an agreement in the buildingindustry relating to the importation of foreign-made joinery,which I am sure the Board has knowledge of.  It has been workedrather successfully,  not in any compulsory sense, but byagreement, and the method is simply that from the country of origin we get a certain authorised statement that the joineryis made under fair conditions, conditions that have beenagreed to between the employers and the operatives in thecountry of production.  The largest part of It hitherto hasoome from America, and a considerable amount from scandinavian countries,   Russia made application in the usual way,fulfilled conditions, and succeeded in getting her goods puton the &quot;Fair List&quot;, as we may call It, but as a result of thatwe have a general complaint from the English JoineryManufacturers1 Association that Russia is now selling doors -doors being the main production - at  5s.6d. as against10s.Sd. which I think is the lowest quoted price at which doorscan either be imported or made here.   So that even in theprivileged building industry Russia is finding a way to  dump ,some or her products,  I do not think it is seriouB, and I donot think it will have any very great effect, but it is interesting in view of what has been said that even in thissheltered Industry Russia has found a way to get in.SHIPBUILDING,     With regard to shipbuilding, Sir Ernest Glover&apos;sreport is, I think, quite a fair pioture of what  is happening,and I am sorry to say I have to agree with his ratherpessimistic view of that trade *
                       AUSTRALIAN TRADE.     MR JOHN SANDERSON (Australia)i  The wool season is now in full swing.   The average prices for September sales are about 7  per cent lower than last year, and there has been good competition for not less than average qualities from the Continent and Japan, with limited support from Yorkshire.     Regarding wheat, exports this season are 40,600,000 bushels compared with 79,200,000 bushels last season.   Votes have been taken amongst the New South Wales and Victorian wheat growers in regard to the formation of Marketing Boards, and although there has been an affirmative majority in each case, it is below the prescribed majority, so that the Marketing Boards cannot be formed.   The prospects for the coming crop are bright, especially since the useful rains which have fallen in a good many wheat districts during the past few days.   It is of course too soon yet to say what the results will be.     As regards flour, the exports this season are 372,500 tons compared with 464,700 last season.     The Customs revenue, for the first quarter of the financial year is  7,470,000,  a decrease of  4,000,000 compared with last year, and is  2,500,000 below estimate. The postal revenue is  3,280,000, an increase of  15,000 compared with last year, being  421,000 below estimate.     The exports for August were  5,000,000;  and the imports  6,800,000, a decrease of  2,200,000 and  5,600,000 respectively as compared with August,  1929.   Por the two months since the end of the financial year, viz., July and august, the exports are  12,250,000, the imports  14,000,000, being a decrease (as compared with 1929) of  1,300,000 in exports and  11,250,000 in imports.     The bank clearances from the 1st  January to the 29th September have been in Sydney  645,000,000, and in Melbourne  537,800,000, a decrease of  134,700^000, and 62,500,000 respectively.    I  think these figures are quite eloquent evidence of the position that has resulted from the recent financial difficulty.     The Federal Government is meeting on the 30th October for the financial session,  and probably the Council have noticed in the cable appearing in the  Press, various efforts that have been made and decisions that have been taken in regard to costs and arbitration awards, and the individual States are all engaged in balancing their budgets.     There has been a merger completed of the AustraliaGeneral Electric Company, Ferguson Pailin,  Ltd.,  and metropolitan-Vickers.                     DISTRIBUTING TRADES.     SIR WOODMAN BURBIDG3:   I  am very pleased to be able toreport to the Board that through the  help of Professor Qay ofthe Bank of England we are  in  future  able to give much
bigger returns of different houses than we have done hitherto.Up to now we have only had returns from retail distributors,but now through the help of Professor Clay an arrangement isbeing made to have all the official returns of stock andemployment sent to him every month.   That is a very usefulthing, and it should be very interesting to the members ofthe trade generally.     I have not had much time to obtain returns aboutSeptember trade from a representative number of storesthroughout the country, but from the figures from some thirtystores so far received, it may be concluded that the Septemberreturns will make a much better showing than the ratherdepressing report which had to be issued in connection with august trade.   The trade has had the benefit of an extra day in September as compared with 1929, but after making allowance for this, it is satisfactory to report, when regard is had tothe very severe fall in retail prices which has occurred since last year, that the total turnover for Great Britain is downby not more than 1.2 per cent, which I think is very satisfactory.   In the West End of London, turnover shows nochange from last year, whereaB reductions in turnover in theNorth and South of England, and the suburbs of London haveshown decreases.     I have not had the time yet to get out the full details,but under the individual headings the best showing is made bywomen1s wear, and in particular the fashion departments overthe country show an increase of 5 per cent over last year,A similar increase is also shown by the boot and shoedepartments.   The falling off in the sales of furniture andsoft furnishings unfortunately continues, average fallsamounting to 14.7 per cent and 10.5 per cent over the country.Substantial falls are also shown in the hardware departments.     On the other hand, the total value of stocks at costhas fallen by 6.6 per cent over the country, and in the WestEnd, stocks are down by as much as 9.7 per cent.   It is significant that in spite of the prevailing depression,numbers employed show a small increase.                CO-OPERATIVE TRADE IN SCOTLAND.     MR JOHN CAIRNS:  My report is not optimistic.    For thefirst time in recent years our&apos;;&apos;sales measured in money showa decrease, which cannot be wholly explained by a fall inprices.   The 20 weeks which have expired of the currenthalf-year show the drop to be qxiite 5 per cent without any prospect of the deficiency being made up before the end ofthe accounting period.   The sales of some of the primaryarticles of food show the bulk sold to be less,  and of others to be more, but on balance the total of the quantities is less.     The consumption of butter reveals a special feature,  asdespite the apparent decrease in the spending power of themembers, the quantity of butter sold has relatively increasedto that of margarine, the apparent reason for this preferencebeing that the price of butter has fallen about 6d. per lb. inthe course of the year while there has been no equivalentdecrease in the price of margarine.
     Our attention has &quot;been called to a reputed flaw inthe working of the Merchandise Marks Act with regard to eggs. .It is allowable to sell imported &quot;chilled&quot;  eggs or &quot;coldstored&quot; eggsj including those from the Irish Free State withoutmarking them as such, whereas Home and Northern Ireland mustbe thus distinctly marked.   In the Free State eggs are stampedin black from February to June inclusive, and in red from july to Januars&apos;, the idea being to prevent the sale of stored eggsas fresh on the assumption that any storing will be done priorto July.   What is said to have happened was that, with storingfinished, a substantial increase took place in the quantityof fresh eggs available during July, the market weakened andcertain buyers secured quantities in excess of their needsat the time, put them into cold store and sold them lateras fresh eggs in competition with the genuine article.     In a former report the effect of the Scottish Milk Poolwas mentioned as having, by providing the farmer with the certainty of a market, encouraged production.   I regrethaving to report that now when the time has arrived for thetriennial contracts to be renewed, a very large majority ofthe farmers supplying us have refused to continue their membership of the Pool end have insisted on reverting to theold method of making individual contracts with us directly.&quot;We are probably the largest distributors of milk in thecountry, and if anything like the same proportion of farmerssupplying other distributors adopt the same policy that curshave done towards the Pool and us, it will entail the end ofwhat was regarded as the beginning of a valuable system oforderly marketing for British farmers.     The slack trade in the preserve factories which wasforeseen as a result of the increased quantity of domesticallymade preserves, following cheap supplies of fruit and sugarhas been even more pronounced than was expected and the factories are being shut down for a week at a time.   Russianstrawberries treated with preservative after the Dutch methodhave appeared in the market this season.   They made excellentjam and commanded a sale of  2 per ton less than the Dutch,the lower price not being due to inferior quality, but to thefact that being a new article buyers had to be offered aspecial inducement to take them.     Our fish department reports that for the month whitefish has been plentiful and prices moderate.   The Scotchherring fishing has beenvessy unsuccessful with a shortage in cured herrings of 300,000 barrels.   Last week we received an order of 1,000 barrels and 500 half-barrels from PolishGo-operative Societies.     The rest of the report is routine, Mr. Chairman, and i will put it \rif*                       CO-OPERATIVE TRADE.     Mr. ARTHUR VARLEfi:  Mr.  Chairman,  so far as my report  isconcerned compared with three months ago, our cash receipts areup, even though many of the prices are  down.   Our cash; receipts* See appendix p.42-
are up from three months ago by 3 per cent,  but they aredown from 13 months a.?o by 7.7 per cent.   There is oneinteresting feature about this, and that is that the prices of .both wholesale and retail are considerably down.   Comparedwith September, 1929, sugar is down 18 per cent,  butter 22per cent, flour 23 per cent, bacon 14 per cent, lard 0.79per cent, and cheese 18 per &apos;cent.  These are in the wholesale prices.  Then in the retail prices, sugar is down as compared-with September, 1929, by 7.69 per cent, butter by 16.33 percent, flour by 6.9 per cent, bacon by 13.51 per cent and lard10 per cent.  So that none of these things is down in retail price quite so much ? s in 7&apos;wholesale price.     So far as butter is concerned, in the early days ofthe month the price of butter fron Sweden, Finland and denmark went up about 10s. per cwt.  v/ith the increase in price the counter demand went dorm, and the prices had to comedown again, and today Danish butter is 52s.  less then it wasa year ago, Swedish butter is 35s.6d less, Finnish butter is55s. less, New Zealand butter is 57s.6d less and Australia51s. less.     On the question of sugar, every Konday morning during september the price of sugar went down 9d,6d, 3d, 3d and 3drespectively, making 2s. down on the month.   It was said that before the first reduction sugar was selling below cost ofproduction, so that now the losses to producers must beenormous.  Over-production or under-consumption with lack of funds to finance stocks seems to be the cause of the decline.Today American cables are firmer on reported negotiations between Cuban and other producers to stop the rot.  No changehas been made on this side yet, although there is now anundercurrent of firmness in the market.     Dried fruit.  New crop Creek currants and Smyrnasultanas and figs are now on the market and a fair demand is already being experienced.  !?ith the exception of low-grade Smyrna sultanas, which are not value against Australian,all new fruit is good Quality and our prices are below 1929opening figures, thus Greek currants by about 8s.6d per cwt;Smyrna sultanas by about 2s. to 10s. per cwt; Smyrna figs byabout 10s. per cwt.  Californian produce is quiet without special feature worthy of report.     The tea market has not shown any marked change duringthe  past month and has continued generally steady for alldescriptions.  There has been some improvement in quality,and better prices have been realised, fine teas becomingparticularly strong.  Common teas fetched s toady prices and amore confident tone prevailed on the Indian market, the lowerand. medium grades coning into good demand.  A pleasing feature*at the latter end of the month was the improvement in quality of teas from the finer Ceylon gardens which was fully appreciated by the trade and some of the better teas advanced in price against recent rates.     Bacon end Haras;   As compared with a month ago, prices in the main are down to the extent of 15s. per cwt, and are practically on 1913 level, and there is a reasonable prospectof their continuing so.  The reduction is entirely due tothe enormous and unprecedented supplies coming forward from denmark and other Continental sources,  and this can be easilyaccounted for by the fact that an 1913 Danish killings for,
say, two weeks corresponding with those ended September  27th-,1930, amounted to * out 90,000 pigs,  while for the latterperiod they reached the enormous total of 243,000   roughly -one quarter of a million   and are likely to continue on abig scale for some time to come.     wheat:   Since our last report markets generally havehad a very severe fall, Liverpool being about 5s. per quarterlower, and Winnipeg and Chicago about 3s.5d per quarter  lower.     In Canada harvesting has now been completed, and generally the yield is better than anticipated.   deliveries to market have been very heavy despite the low prices.   the initial payment by the Pool to farmer members has been reduced from 65 cents to 60 cents, and if conditions remain as atpresent it is quite possible a further reduction may have tobe made.  The competition from Russia is very severe, and allefforts to check the decline seem unavailing.     In the United States of America harvesting has beencompleted, and both Winter and Spring crops have yieldedwell, and are good quality.  Owing to the possibility oflarge quantities of low-grade wheat being used as a substitute for maize, this country has not been a free sellerof wheat, and is more on a domestic basis, although -world prices have had their effect.  Stock markets there have experienced a heavy fall owing to several financial failures,and this may further affect the price of wheat.     Russia continues to offer freely and ship good quantities.While the wheat now being shipped, is not as good quality asthe early shipments,  the price being attractive the wheat iseagerly taken by millers and good quantities are being used.The Co-operative Wholesale Society has not been a f ree userof Russian wheat, compared with private millers, as thequality has not been so good, but owing to the low price of flour now ruling our millers- are obliged to turn their attention to this wheat.  We are endeavouring to secureonly the best qualities.     In Australia conditions for the new crop continuefavourable, and efforts are being made to test the market for the value, without finding much interest.   A plentifulsupply of all wheats discourages millers from buying forward.With an increased acreage this country is expected to harvesta very big crop.     India continues to ship small quantities, but owing tothe disturbed state of the country offers are not made freelyand the wheat is not as satisfactory as our millers expectedowing to the greater moisture content than is usual.     Prom the Argentine conditions for the new crop havebeen very favourable indeed, and the present outlook is  fora l^rge crop again from this country.  The critical period is now approaching, and next month a more correct estimateof the possible yield may be obtained.     Maize, in conjunction with other feeding stuffs,  has declined on the month, but not to thssame extent.   We under-stand that there is every possibility that owing to thefailure of the maize crop in America this country may importsmall quantities.
     With, regard to &quot;barley, the heavy supplies from Russiacontinue to depress this commodity, which is now at a very low price, having declined about 4s. on the month.     In our drapery departments, the oaution of buyers inrelation to-cotton, referred to in the last report, was apparently justified, the price of the raw material beingnow below 6d.  As applies to wool, the price for a 64s,average top is about 26-^d against Sl-gd a year ago, but un-certainty and forced liquidation of stocks has rather shakenthe market, and the feeling is not so satisfactory as wasthe case at the date of the last report.  The position inthe general textile and drapery trade remains about thesame.     In woollens and readymades, the trade conditions gen-erally throughout Lancashire and Yorkshire are unaltered^The heavy decreases reported by a large proportion of retailSooieties arc naturally being reflected in our trade*     So far as the ootton trade is concerned, some of ourvillages in Lancashire are in a very poor way.  I have notthe name of the town given, but I have a report that of the26 mills in the town only three are working.     In the boot and shoe trade there is nothing of note to report during the past month.   Business has been verysteady and the markets quite normal.     In the general furnishing trade they are now feelingthe effects of the general depression.   Since our last report,the Axminster and Wilton carpet manufacturers have r educedtheir prices, and the reduction average is about 10 per cent.These reductions are mainly attributable to the fall in priceof wool and also owing to keen foreign competition.  Thegeneral trend is now for customers to purchase goods at lower prices than hitherto, and until there is a considerable reduction in the number of unemployed, it will be verydifficult to maintain our figures.     In the furniture trade, as reported last month, thereis a slight improvement in the demand for furniture, thoughit is still for the lower grade.  The demand for this classis maintained throughout the whole of the country.  Ofcourse, in normal times we do look forward to better trade at the latter part of the year.     So far as domestic ooal is concerned, the price,excepting in Lancashire, was advanced in September, and that hadthe effect that in Lancashire coal was being sold cheapercomparatively than in other districts, and other districtswere sending their coal into Lancashire without the increase which they charged in their general marketing counties.So that Lancashire during the month of September had has afavour in that respect.   But the Lancashire coal price wentup on the 1st October, ls.8d. a ton.     Exports from the export department have oontinued tothe Co-operative Sooieties mainly on the Continent, but someinto Sou.th Africa and some into the American continent.One rather remarkable feature is that we have been sendingsugar into ;3sthonia and Latvia,  To Russia our exports ofspices, jute, metals and cocoa have amounted to about  36,000.
It might interest the Board to know that we have just received a contract for margarine to send it into Russia.we only began delivery last week.  If everything goes onsatisfactorily, it will be a rather interesting experiment,and a fairly big order will come through.  It all dependshow the first samples go on.   We sent 60 tons last week andare sending 30 tons this week.  If they are acceptable andthe conditions are good when they get into Russia, the orderswill be for larger quantities than that for each week forsome time to come.                         CHEMICALS.     MR. G.C. CLAYTON:  The general situation seems to belittle if  any brighter than previously.  While the officialreturns for September trade are not yet available, reports on the week by week overseas trade would seem to indicatethat while some products have shown slight improvement on export business, these are of insufficient importance tojustify any expectation of all round improvement.     As regards heavy chemicals there are, as yet, no indications of a general revival in the activities of thechief consuming trades,- and deliveries to the home marketremain below normal.     The slight improvement in the artificial silk trade reported last month is still apparent, but textiles generallycontinue depressed.     Slackness in the metal trades is still general, andis reflected in r educed requirements of both hydrochloric andsulphuric  acid, particularly the former.     The falling off in the demand for sulphuric acid byreason of  conditions prevailing in the textile and metaltrades is  accentuated by the reduced requirements, at thisseason of  the year, for the manufacture of fertilisers.     Further evidence of Russian competition is reported from India, and quantities of Russian caustic soda have been landed in  China; despite which, sales of British products are maintained.     Considering that this is the quiet season forconsumption of fertilisers, trade may be regarded asperfectly  normal.   At this time of the year there is verylittle of  importance to report.     So far as market conditions are concerned, thedepression in the textile and other dye consuming industriescontinues  and is of course reflected in reduced sales ofdyestuffs.     As the Advisory Council would be well aware, the future prospects  of the dyestuffs and intermediates manufacturing industry is very.much in the balance and as the end of theyear draws  nearer, the interest in current developmentsincreases.   It is thought possible therefore that the council may be interested in the appendix to this report which dealswith the above subject.
    The tar distillation industry continues to suffer withthe rest of the chemical industry as the result of depression in c onsumers&apos; activities.  Apart from this general statement, there seems to he no direct developmentof interest.     It is in the markets for fine chemicals we can findprobably the only sign of improvement.  7/hile conditions -generally remain decidedly depressed, the month ofSeptember shows a slight Improvement over august in thewhole market.  It is important to notice that pricesgenerally remain fairly steady though they are undoubtedlyat a limited low level.     On the export side, business continues slow, being more particularly depressed on account of the Indianboycott on British goods and British drugs in particular.Hopes of the raising of the boycott are  growing weakeras the movement continues equally as active as hitherto.     The negotiations between the dyemakers and the colourusers, regarding the future of the Dyestuffs (importRegulation) Act, 1920, which expires in&apos;  January, have broken down;  the -Association of British ChemicalManufacturers has therefore decided to publish a Memorandumrepresenting the views of the chemical industry regardingthe operation of the .^ct, and containing suggestions forthe future.  The Act was passed to protect a key industry of vital importance to the national prosperity and safety.Though there have been many industrial and other difficulties during the period of the Act which havemilitated against the development of the industry, ncver-theless the Act has largely succeeded in achieving its main object, and, as a consequence, we have a well organised,technically efficient and virile dyestuffs industry in thiscountry,,   No other form of protection would probably have achieved the same result.   The progress made is demonstratedby the following facts      (l) The 1929 production was over six times that of          1913 by weight.      (2) The home production provides 90 per cent, of the          home consumption by weight and 74 per cent, by value.      (3) The British industry affords a more extensive          range of colours than any country except Germany          and Switzerland,      (4) The industry has been an important competitive          instrument in reducing the price of dyes.      (5) Prices have now been reduced to a level at which          the burden on the consuming industries is          negligible.      (6) British dyes are now admitted  to be fully equal          in quality to any foreign competitive products,      (7) The British Industry has played a prominent part          in the discovery and development of new products,          being responsible for three of the five main post-          war developments.      (s) An expanding export trade is being secured.
        (9) The industry employs a larger proportion of            teohnically-trained men than probably any other            manufacturing industry in this oountry, and its            existence is essential for the adequate            maintenance Of instruction and research in            organio chemistry which are vital to national            prosperity and security,    \7hile a sound foundation has been laid, and a strongstructure is steadily being erected on efficient lines, therej.s still considerable headway to make before the industry canmeet the full requirements of the colour users, secure its proper share of the export trade, and withstand unaided the intensive foreign competition and price outting which wouldresult if the Aot were allowed to lapse.  The removal of thepresent protection would jeopardise the consummation of thework which it was the object of the Act to achieve withoutany countervailing gain to the consuming industries which  &apos;would make the risk worthwhile;  in other words, there wouldbe nothing to gain and everything to lose.     The dyemakers, therefore, press for a further periodof protection on the lines of the present Act, and subjectto safeguards, to protect the British manufacturer againstunfair competition, are agreeable to a modification of theprocedure so that the prohibition of imports will onlyapply where a British maker is prepared to supply an equiva-lent product at an.equal price.  This would secure thecontinuance of the development of the industry in thiscountry under conditions which would plaoe no economic burden on the consuming industries^     MR. H.\7. L3S:  \7e do not agree with No, (5).     CHAIRLAN:  Do you expect the report which you say is being prepared will be ready fairly soon ?     MR. G.C. CLAYTON:  It has already gone in, I understand.     CHAIRMAN; I&quot; thought you meant it was being prepared.     MR. G.C. CLAYTON:  No, it has gone in.  It was delayed until it was found out whether the negotiations between the makersand the consumers would give any results, and as those negotiations fell through we have sent in the report from the chemical makers,     CHAIRMAN:  I suppose the colour users have already senttheirs in ?     MR. G.C. CLAYTON:  I-think they had already sent it in before.                              WOOL..     ALDIIRMAN M.P. TITT:2RINGT0N:  The rather more hopefulfeeling which I mentioned a month ago has not shown any further development owing mainly to a further set baok in wool prices,which the representative of Australia has confirmed.  Thishas caused a temporary lack of confidence on the part ofusers of wool, tops, and yarns-  The demand for fullymanufacturered goods is patchy, and machinery is still under-employed, but with slightly better prospects.  The home tradeis relatively better than the export trade, which is poor.
t     I notice from the recent report of our last meeting referred     to by Sir woodman Burbidge that the sales of piece  goods in     departmental stores in August were only 9.3 percent,  less &apos;     than a year ago.   This is an interesting point that one ought     to explore.  Exports of woollen and worsted tissues, on the     other hand, were  38 per cent, down in August, reckoned by     value, and 36 per cent, down reckoned by quantity,  compared     with a year ago.          Unfortunately our best customer abroad - Canada - has just     imposed higher tariffs on wool-textile imports.   Ve have     already had our trade with Australia cut down to less than one-     third by higher tariffs.   I wonder what reaction our 7/est     Riding exporters  and manufacturers register when they see the -     elegant posters exhorting them to buy Canadian and  Australian     produce.  I happen to be Chairman of the Committee  of the     Bradford Technical College, which receives with open arms     students from the Dominions who cone over to learn  the trade     in order that they can carry it back to their own countries.     One hesitates to  suggest what the solution may be,  but I concur     with the observations made by Mr. Hamilton in terms that the     President of the  Board of Trade might usefully consider our     complaint in this direction.   It is a cause for great disquiet     to say the least.   It is rather curious to note that the     European market for piece goods has held up better  than any -     other during the  present slump, and that if our trade with     Canada is seriously reduced it will be a race between the     Argentine Republic and Germany for the honour of being our     best customer.          Although the decline in wool prioes has checked business     for the time being, it is by no means an unmixed evil.   The     new wool season has commenced, and it is much better for     topmakers and importers to start from a reasonable  basis. .     Prices of wool tops are now lower than at any time  since the     slump &quot;of 1908,  and are 15 to 20 per cent,  lower than in 1913.     This despite the  fact., that the cost of combing is substan-     tially higher than before the war.    Pine wools, I  am told,     are regarded as being cheap enough to warrant speculation,     because there are no excessive stocks to depress the market.          At the dyeing and finishing end of the trade there is     a slight activity in slubbing and yarn dyeing, and  fancy     worsteds in one area, but it is difficult to say exactly     whether it is an  addition to the volume of trade or whether     it is merely a transference of production which is  the     outcome of the  reorganisation scheme of an employers&apos;     association under which the general level of the whole  of the     textile trade,  including silk, artificial silk,  cotton and wool,     is refleoted unfortunately in a growing unemployment list and     shorter working time.                     RAILWAY TRAFFIC     SIR RALPH WEDGWOOD:  The position in the Railway industry has got markedly worse in the last quarter.   That, 1 think, was probably expected.-   7/&quot;e have heard during the first half-year from manufacturers and others of the lack of orders coming forward, and that reflects itself in the railway reoeiptswhich show what traffic is actually moving.    In fact, in the quarter ending 30th September the railway revenue went down
                            COAL.     MR. RIDLEY WARHAM:   The output of coal in the UnitedKingdom for the three weeics ended  September 20th was  as under:-       Week ended September 6th -  4,574,000 tons.         &quot;    &quot;       &quot;     13th -  4,258,000   &quot;                      &quot;     80th -  4,666,000   &quot;by more than that of the whole of the previous half-year.Taking the published figures, the actual figure of decreasein receipts for the first half-year is 3^ per cent, over all.Por the last three months, roughly July, August and September,thendecrease has been at the rate of 8 per cent, for July,8f per cent, for August, and 9^ per cent, for September.   Itgot very rapidly worse about the turn of the half-year,  and  itis still getting slightly worse as the year goes on.  I  amsorry to say there is no sign of any improvement in front of us so far as we can judge from our figures, .and,I.-:aB afraidso far as we hear from trade reports.   It may be of interestto give certain figures as regards the tonnage handled bythe railways and the rate of decrease in that respect.   Thetonnage has gone down very much in the same ratio as thereceipts.   It has gone down least in coal.   I am sureMr. Warham will be glad to hear that coal is a favourablefeature showing a decrease of only 11 per cent, in the quarter.Merchandise has gone down 12 per cent., and the heaviestdrop of all is in what is called minerals, which is reallyraw materials for the most part.   The latter shows a decreasefor the quarter of 20 per cent.   That, I think, is on thewhole more discouraging than a similar decrease would havebeen in the other items, because the raw materials are theearlier stages of manufacture, and if raw materials go down20 per cent, one must, I am afraid, expect to see thatdecrease extended in time to merchandise.   So that I am bound to confess that at the present time the railway outlooKis extremely bad.     Everything is being done at the present moment to cutdown cost.   That, of course, means unemployment, because it means that orders are not being given which at this time  ofthe year normally would be given.   At the present time  inthe railway shops short time is being worked by anything  from60 to 80 per cent, of the employees.   In addition, therehave been large numbers of dismissals.   So far as revenue isconcerned, costs are being cut down in every direction.   Onthe other hand, it may be some satisfaction to industry generally to know that on the capital side there is quiteunusual activity.   As the result of the arrangement madewith the late Government in reference to the remission of passenger duty, there is a considerable volume of works  inprogress, and that has been further added to by the worksundertaken, or about to be undertaken, under the applicationof the Development Act.   Without any official figures,  Iestimate roughly the number of works now in hand, or about to be put in hand in connection with the normal passengerprogramme and under the application of the Development *vct,total a sum of between  30,000,000 and  40,000,000.    Thatis gradually coming into effect, but of course it takes  timeto get these works going.   I think it indicates that therewill be considerable activity in the way of materials requiredin connection with those works in the comparatively nearfuture.
The average output for the thirteen weeks June 28-aeptemher -20was 4,310,000 tons, as compared v/ith 4,806-^000 tons for thecorresponding period last year, an average decrease of500,000 tons a week.     I vrill hand in the employment figures.   The quantityof coal exported from the United Kingdom (excluding IrishFree State) in August was 3,747,321,tons as compared with,460,454 tons in July (a decrease of 713,133 tons) and4,778,009 tons in August last, year (a decrease of over1,000,000 tons).   The average price  per ton f.o.&quot;b. in Augustwas 16s.2d., as compared v/ith 16s.8d. in July.   Exports to scandinavia in august were 412,000 tons, as compared with a monthly average in 1913 of 825,.000 tons - this decrease, ofcourse, is owing to Polish compeGition - and to Germany where an import licensing system is still in operation there were also 412,000 tons as compared with a  monthly average of746,000 tons in 1913.     Exports by sea from Poland in August show a decrease of37,000 tons as compared with July, the figures being, July762,000 tons;  August 725,000 tons.   The Finnish State Rail- &apos;ways have placed an order with Poland for 4S,000 tons of bestPolish coal at a price which works out at about I0s.0d. a ton.o.b. Danzig/Gdynia.   The contract  was taken at 3s.5d. perton less than the prices that we quoted, which we thought were very good competitive prices.   This  leaves, as I say, only10s.Od. a ton f:-o.b.   The railwajr rate from the colliery,together with the shipping charges, amounts to about 5s.Od a ton,which leaves a pithead price of 5s.Od. a ton, out of which the collieries have to pay two agents&apos; commissions.   It isimpossible, of course, for us to even attempt to compete withsuch an extraordinary price, but it goes to show the determination of Poland to get orders at any price.   the contract was made by the Scarboferme Company, in which thePolish Government is largely interested.   It is about half and half the Polish Government and French investors.     There is very little movement in the British coal trade,in spite of the near approach of winter.   Business is in astate of suspense until the various schemes under the CoalMines Act actually become operative.    Generally speaking,this is the time for contracts to be  made over next year, butthere is practically nothing doing yet in that direction.Trade remains bad, and there have been one or two morecollieries temporarily laid in, including Lord Londonderry&apos;s.     As you will be aware, a trade delegation recentlyvisited Norway, Sweden and Denmark to investigate the position there, and the Mines Department will  shortly be issuing areport on the subject, so that it will not be necessary to mention it further yet.
MR. MITCHELL sent the following report:-               COAL TRADE IN SCOTLAND.     The trade shows no signs of recovery.  The output inAugust 1930 was 2,463,151 tons as compared with 2,899,321tons in August, 1929.     For the months of July and August, the last months forwhich ascertainments are available, shew losses overhead ofls.2.79d and 5c33d. per tor respectively.     The consumption of coal in the Iron and Steel Trades ismuch reduced owing to the idle time in the Works.     Shipments are unsatisfactory and the competition with Poland is more difficult owing to the low offers of polish coal being made for next season.  Several importantcontracts, such as that &quot;of the Finish State Railways, havebeen lost.     The Coal Owners are looking forward with anxiety tothe conditions being created by the new Coal Mines Act.  Therewill- be an increase in the cost of working and the prospectof obtaining additional prices is not satisfactory.  Thewrovisions of the Act under the marketing scheme arrangements will be difficult to w.o-rk and may be rather a hindrance thana help  in the attempt to get better prices.IRON AND STEEL.     Pig Iron in Scotland:   There have been only 12 furnacesin blast, and it is stated that other 3 furnaces are to  beblown out shortly.  In August the output of Pig Iron w as20,600 tons as com ared with 33,200 tons for July and 55,900tons for August 1929.  Competition with imported iron isimpossible.  Continental iron is being offered at pricesalmost as low as 1914.     The imports of Pig Iron into Scotland in August were5,642 from the continent and 9,585 from India = 15,227 tons.     Scran:   The position is still easy and imports are coming into Scotland from the Continent; the total imports  inAugust being 5,033 tons.     Over the whole country it should be noted, in August,that there was an excess of 1,671 tons of exports over imports.     Steel;,   The position is bad without any promise ofimprovement.  One Work is working 2 shifts per day insteadof 3, and others have only been working part of a week.   one large Steel &quot;Vork that has been working fairly steadily forsone months, though with some short tine, has been entirelyidle this week.     The Steel output for August was 91,800 tons ascompared with 159,700 tons for August 19-39.  The outputover the whole country shows a siuilar decrease.APPENDIX.
SIR WALTER RAINE sent the following report: -COAL.     The position for Steam Coals is in about thesame serious condition as it has been for some months.   Howeverwhere unpayable Seams have been closed down,  and the outputreduced, it has been possible in some instances to work with very little broken time.   The same remarks apply even more soto Durham, where as it is well known gas and  Coking Coals  arein more or less continuous demand.   Quite apart from the approach of the longer nights the termination of Summer timealways causes an immediate increased consumption of gas inparticular and also electricity both for lighting and heating.It may be reasonable to assume that with the  concentration above referred to, the Durham Collieries will be able to work withoutinterruption for some months,  (Storms etc. which cause delay to tonnage excepted.);.  There still prevails a great measure ofuncertainly and hesitation, it will be to the benefit of thetrade generally to have the Coal Mines Act in operation, in sofar as it enables the Salesmen (l)  to know what quantities thereare for disposal (2) to know what Minimum prices must berealised.     Largely owing to&quot; the serious state of the Iron andSteel Trades at Home and the consequent lessened demand for&quot;Patent Coke, this article is a drug on the Market, and  theposition is accentuated by the severity of the competition from Westphalia and Belgium.SHIPBUILDING.     Unfortunately there is nothing new to report inthis direction.   Ship repairing which has been unusually  slackon the Vest Coast, has been fairly busy on the East  Coast.GENERAL TRADE.     There is nothing of an encouraging nature to record.Of course, in Seasonal Trades there has on the one hand been increased activity, according to the particular commodityproduced, but at the same time it has brought a decreaseddemand in other articles for which the changing Season haslessened the requirements for this year.                       IROK AND STEEL.     MR.. Y/ALMSLEY sent the following report: -     The Meeting of the advisory Council  this mouth  is too early for the figures either of production or of imports and exports to be available.  It will be remembered that  .-;teel     Generally as far as can be a scertainert the outputsfor September will be lower than the outputs for August.     Tube Trade;,   In the Tube Trade there has been fair  workfor some classes of tubes but for other classes there  has been much idle time;   the export trade generally is at a low level.&apos;.There has been a very slight improvement in the last few  days in the demand from Australia.
production in August fell to  the lowest level of any month inrecent years except those affected by the coal stoppages  of1921 and 1926, while exports  were lower than in any month sincethe coal stoppage of 1926, VJhile the Board of Trade figuresfor exports are not yet available, figures issued by the  TeesConservancy show that Iron and Steel shipments from the Tees  InSeptember are lower than in any month this year and some  5,500tons less than the August figure,     Y?hile the exceptionally  low figures for August were  partly due to the holiday period, there has been no suoh recovery inSeptember as usually marks this period of the year.     It may have been noted that imports of Iron and Steel InJuly and August were also lower than in recent months  thisis due to lack of demand and  must not be interpreted as reflectinga decline in Continental competitionj  in fact the very oppositeis the case.  The low Continental prices have attracted a&quot;considerable amount of buying In this country and semis from  thoContinent are finding their way to the home market with regularityand in increasing tonnages, a fact which will be reflected in theimport figures of the next few months.     As has previously been pointed out, the decline in demand is general and the desire to keep the big works of France, belgium and Germany operating as near to capacity as possible led to  theprioes fixed by the International Price Associations (in  which great Britain does not participate) being undersold to such an extent that these Associations were dissolved, leading to stillfurther declines in prices.  The level to which Continentalprices has fallen has already been reported to the President(see copy of Sir William Larke*s letter of 26th September below),but in certain cases there have been further declinesj forexample, Continental Basic Pig Iron, which was being deliveredat works in South V/ales at 59s,Sd. per ton a fortnight ago, isnow being offered at 57s,3d.  compared with the British prices of65s, to 67s. 3d,     The last Meeting of the Cartel, however, decreed areduotion in production of some 25 per cent, compared with October1929, and moreover, a step which is likely to prove more  effective,has re-imposed the fines for overproduction so that even  ifInternational arrangements for fixing prices are not revived forsome time there is a hope that Continental prices may eventuallybecome firmer, although in the meantime it is understood that thereare accumulations of stocks which must be disposed of.     Although there has been such a serious fall in Continentalprioes, the output in some countries has been maintained on a muchmore satisfactory level than in Great Britain.  The following figures for Belgium and France will illustrate this posit ion:-BELGIUM&apos;1 BJuly 1930.&quot;&quot;&quot; Tons&quot;,&apos;August 1930.   Tons 0  &quot;&quot;&quot;Pig Iron........................Steel Ingots....................Steel Castings..................Finished Products in Basic Steel,259,750255,840246,740237,1508, 1407,720Wrought Iron209,060 10,070206,020 10,720Total&apos;figures of output for the first 8 monthsare :-
                                  1929.        19 30.Pig Iron.......................2,708,400    2,585,100Steel Ingots ...................2,380,600    2,31*, 200Steel Castings.................   80,200       74,000Finished Products in Basio                      Steel ....2,383,100    2,939,100    tf       n     n  wrought                      Iron .....  110,900       83,200533                            June 1930.  July JL? 30.   August 193%              France.          &quot;Tons.    &quot; tons &quot;&quot;       Toha&apos;.        Pig Iron........... 841,000   860,000        845,900        Steel Ingots ....... 753,000   789,000        775,000     The Shipbuilding industry is still very depressed and thisparticularly affects the North East Coast and Scotland.   Onthe North East Coast the position is mitigated to some extent bya fair amount of activity for structural Steel, but in Scotlandthere is no such relieving feature and the output of finished steel Is estimated at less than 50 per cent, of actual capacity;nor is there any prospect of an immediate improvement.   Ship-builders are to a great extent working on ships that have been onthe stocks for a period and are nearing completion, and are facedwith the difficult problem of finding further work or closing down altogether.      Copy of letter referred to in^Mr^Walmsley^s report.                                           25th September, 1930,The Right Hon&apos;ble William Graham, M.P.,     President of the Board of Trade,          Great George Street, S.V/.1.Dear Mr. Graham,     I promised to keep you personally advised from time to timeof information bearing on the present position which came to mynotice, and I have therefore had prepared for you a comparison of continental and British prices delivered British works, based on recent quotations within the past two or threo weeks,  whioh Ienclose &quot;herewith,  A reliable report received this week states thatOugree-Marlhaye Company, a large Belgian concern, has sold 50,000tons of semi-finished Steel in one week mainly in the british market.     Our difficulty is that we are not yet in a position to measure the full extent of possible Continental competition;  forexample, the price was quoted for Steel Sheet Bars yesterday of 5,lS.6d. per ton F.O.B. Antwerp, which is about the cost ofHematite Pig Iron in this country;  and although no doubt the presendepression will,affect the financial returns of the ContinentalCompanies, we have experienced in the past seven years similarphenomenal collapses in prices over periods of months at a time,  and yet the Continental Companies concerned have practically neverfailed to pay a 5 or 6 per cent, dividend on their capital and make substantial contributions to tho depreciation and reserve accounts,so that their reserves are not only substantial to-day but they havecontinually improved and oxtended their plant.Yours sincerely,(Sgd.)  V/,  J.  LARICE.
GOLJPlTITiyS PRIG5S OP TYPICAL PRODUCTS.1.  NORTH BAST COAST.          British.                  Continental.                        F.O.3.    pD/VVkS,/nS^         P.O.B.   .,                      V^lorU   CTs\Ztlk0/T&apos;      Antwerp (a).   Pig Iron:    Hematite........        -       ?2/6d.  D/d       No definite)                                                    information)    Basic...........        -       75/-    &quot;            55/-   Billets..........        -      f.6.10,0 D/cL        3e11.0 -  3.13.   Sheet Bars.......        -       5o15c.0  &quot;         3.15, 0 -  3.16*   Steel Bars.......        -       7=15.0  &quot;         4. 5.0   Joists...........    7. 7.5      8.10.0  &quot; (b)     4. 2, 0 (B.S. .                                                          Section) .   Plates...........    7.15.0      8,15.0  &quot; (c)     5. 0.0        (a)  We -understand the present freight Antwerp/Liiddlesbrough             to be 5/- to 5/5d.  per ton.        (b^  Subject to Rebate of 12/6d. per ton.        (c)  Subject to Rebate of 10/- per ton,2.  SCOTLAND,                              Prices,  Delivered ITorks, Mothervrell,.         &apos;:&quot;                    British.                Contrr. entail   Pig Iron:    Hematite - Scotch,...    .   78/-                   No offers.    Basic    -Scotch..,.       75/-                       64/-             - English...       67/-   Billets............. 6. 0,0                      80/-   Sheet Bars............      6, 5.0                      82/-   Steel Bars............      7. 5.0                    4.17,6   Joists................      8010.0 Basis *            4,12.6   Plates................      8.15.0 Basis fV          5.12.6               * Subject to rebate of 12/6d. per ton.               / Subject to rebate of 10/- per ton.3,  SOUTH WALES.               Prices?  Delivered Works. Wales.,                              British.           Continental-,   Pig Iron:    Hematite -Welsh,....        74/-            Dutch     72/-             - E.Coast.,,        75/-             - W.Coast.. .        75/6d,    Basic    - Welsh &amp;                           Luxemburg               Midlands.,        67/6d.          &amp; Prance,  59/6d.             - Lines.....        65/-   Sheet Bars - Y/elsh               Siemens...       5. 15. 0         Thomas Basic   )                                                  4.2.6 -  4,5.0)4,  LANCASHIRE.                Delivered P.O.R.  Makers&apos; Wks , Lanes.      &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;                BrXliXili            Continental                              Per&quot; iTon              Per ton   Ordinary Soft Steel Bars.   8. 0.0              4.15.0   2S/32-ton Steel for    Perro-conorete purposes.   8. 0.0              4.14.0   28/ 32-ton Steel (other    than Perro-concrete)....   8. 2.6              4.19,0   Rods, assorted...........   9.10.0              4.17,6   Hoops, basis.............   8.15,0              5.10.0
IRON AND STEEL.     Employment in the iron and steel industry was very unsatisfactory in September, and trade in general showed no signs of improvement.  Reports from Scotland in particularare very depressing, it being estimated that there are nowapproximately 5,000 unemployed iron and steel workers in the glasgow Area with a very much larger number suffering fromacute under-employment.      The pig-iron trade remains about the same, the onlyfavourable report received being, that Messrs. W. Dixon,Limited, have put into blast a reconstructed furnace attheir Govan Works, Glasgow.  On the North East Coast anotherfurnace was closed down thus leaving a total in commissionin that district of 25 as compared with 46 in operation ayear ago.     Trade in the Heavy steel section was certainly not sogood as a month ago.  In Scotland every Works has only partof its plant in operation and the work available is, as faras possible, being shared.  On the North East Coast them&amp;lting shop of one works and the mills of another  havo  closed down completely, thereby adding 500 to 600 men to t ieunemployed.  In Lingulnshlre two of the plants are fairlybusy, at another the melting department-has closed two outof four furnaces whioh were operating a month ago havingceased work, but the mills at the same works .are now workinga full week as against five shifts per week during August.The Parkgate works at Rotherham have only five furnacesengaged out of eight, this being the lowest number for manyyearB, and the plate  mill which has always been fairlywell occupied is now working  ot more than half-time.  Thefour principal steel.works in the Birmingham Area have only about two-thirds of their plant engaged part time.     The wrought iron trade remains very poor also.  InScotland the volume of work has been much smaller and the mills, when and where operating, are working principallysteel.  The Low Moor Works in South Yorkshire, after beingclosed down for seven weeks was restarted during the month,the forge and mills working four shifts a week.  In the birmingham district, half-time is being worked, and owingto small orders, rolls have to be continuously changed, thus reducing the output.     There is not much alteration in the condition of the steel sheet trade.  The only Area showing improvement beingGlasgow, where the two principal works have put further millsInto operation.  Of the four plants on the Tees-side onlyone ie working to full oapacity, the others operating halftheir mills for five shifts per week.  In South Wales and monmouthshire six establishments are completely shut down,five of them being in the South West Wales district where,out of a full complement of 45 mills, only 14 are working.     Employment in the light steel trades of Sheffield is aBbad as it has been for a considerable period.  At one of themost important works, for example, there are 25$ lessworkmen engaged than were occupied a month ago.     The fitting and socket departments of the tube trade areobtaining very few orders and the small shops In theMidlands are only working half time.  The Newport, Mori,, TubeWorks operated for two weeks in September but the men engaged in the finishing department were fully occupied. Theother principal works, at Landore, had a bad month, themen only working short time.
     Apart from unemployment due to the stop-week arrange-ment, the tinplate trade is fairly well maintaining its position.  Seven works are completely shut up and in the places where all the mills are not in action the work isbeing shared.                       NON-FERROUS METALS,     CAPTAIN LYTTELTON sent the following report    Copper:  The recent considerable price reductions havenot greatly increased consumers&apos; interest, and demand hasbeen very quiet,  Consumers are not disposed to buyexcept against actual orders, and there is a general shortageof these at the present time, especially amongst Wiredrawers.     Tin:  Consumption continues at a not unsatisfactoryrate, although the response to the recent reduction in theprice of Tinplates was small.     Lead:  The Birmingham Pipe and Sheet trade remainsbelow normal.  The cheapness of Spelter is apparentlycausing demand to swing over to Zinc Sheets at the expenseof Lead Sheets.  Liverpool reports little change.     Spelter:  In Birmingham High Grade has been in betterdemand&quot;.  GaTvanisers in Swansea and Liverpool, however,report no improvement, and continue working on a much reduced scale.ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.     SIR HUGO HIRST handed in the following report:-     The general condition of the Electrical Industry ofthis country since my last report, can only be described as one of stagnation.  This is particularly the case as regardsthe heavy engineering section of the Industry, where thevolume of orders obtained and the number of Inquiriesgoing, especially the latter, shew a most marked declineduring the past few months.     The prevailing conditions in the Coal Industry, in shipbuilding and Engineering trades,have  resulted in such a restriction of new capital development, that  enquiriesfor engineering plant from these Industries have practicallyceased.     The general conditions of Unemployment and depreciatedinvestment values, which today exist all over the World, aremaking competition on such enquiries as are forthcoming,ever more strenuous and severe.     The necessity of converting stocks into monetaryvalues in the endeavour to keep producing organisations in being, has caused a general lowering of prices to an uneconomic level.  This naturally has had a depressinginfluence on the prices obtainable for home manufacture.     It is an undoubted fact that the number of enquiriesduring the last few months has been the lowest for at least
two yearse  Electrical Contractors throughout the countryall complain of a general shortage of work, despite theamount of new building that is going, on.  There is also ageneral tendency for work to be placed on the basis of priceonly, irrespective of the quality of material offered.  OnAocount of shortage of money, Electrical Dealers arekeeping, their stock purchases to a minimum, and manufacturers are finding that transactions are invariably at a loweraverage value than in 1929.     During the past three months, there has been quite adefinite trend for business in the Provinces to be betterrelatively than business in London and the Home Counties.The reasons for this trend are to an extent problematical,but are partly due to a reduction in export business throughShipping Houses which are, of course, mainly centred inLondon, and to the fewer number of new developments in theLondon area, due to the depressed condition of trade andthe Stock Exchange.     An important reduction in the prices of Electric Lampswas made by the principal lamp manufacturers in thiscountry at the beginning of September, and it is intresting to note that the average price of British made lamps istoday considerably lower than pre-war.  If the average priceof lamps In 1914 is taken as 100, the average price rulingtoday is 62, a decrease of Z7%,     Despite the general depression, the Wireless sectionof the Electrical Industry continues to make progress *  Thenumber of Licencees is now over three million, and the attendance at the recent Radio Exhibition at Olympia reached a record figure, despite the Exhibition being open for a shorter time than in previous years.     A reduction in the prices of British made Valves alsotook place at the beginning of September, which it is hopedwill bring about a larger use of valve sets, and a biggerdemand for British made valves.  Competition from importedvalves has been very acute, and the importation of suchvalves ie of very large proportions.     The Summer months are, of course, the slack monthsof the year in the Electrical Industry for most commodities,and the busy trading period does not commence until the endof September.  There is no doubt that the Electrical industry will have the greatest difficulty in holding its own duringthe coming months, and there are unfortuaately, no signs whichpoint to any immediate improvement in the near future.MOTOR INDUSTRY.     SIR WILLIAM MORRIS wrote: -     It is not possible to indicate any change in generaldomestic conditions during the past two months.  Seasonally,car factories have been rather more fully engaged indeliveries to agents, but, except in relation to  the smallertype of oar, these do not seem to be up to the average ofthe last two years.
     Employment In all factories shews some slightimprovement, but It is doubtful If this is of a permanentnature, and unemployment or short time employment Isconsiderable In all branches.     The Commercial Vehicle Industry is beginning to fe.el the cumulative results of the general trade position,  ordersfor new motor coaches and omnibuses have slackened considerably,due partly to an uncertainty of the licensing regulations.     In the case of commercial goods vehicles, similarly,demands for vehicles of over 3 tons capacity are scarce,while the demand for smaller types, for which there iskeener competition, shows distinct signs of slackening.     Export,, although In the aggregate below last year stillmaintains certain signs of promise, particularly in NewZealand.  There appears, in various Empire markets, a growing demand for light cars, probably due to the economy factor.This-  even applies to Australia,     Demand for Imported cars In Great Britain is negligible,and there apparently still remain long standing stocks,which may be difficult to liquidate at any but bankruptprices.     In other parts of the Empire, heavy stocks of Americancars and trucks imported in 1929 remain in distributors&apos;hands.  New imports from the United States  of America are ingeneral, 60% below corresponding figures of 192 9.     Thera is certainly still evidence of growing demand forBritish Agencies abroad, which should lead to improvementin general export trade, when commodity prices generallyassume a greater stability,     SIR CYRIL BURCOMB wrote:-     The number of motor vehicles (excluding meter cycles)newly registered in August 1930 was 3,197 less than in thecorresponding period of 1929,  This decrease is made up asfollows:-Increase (*)   or decrease (-) Goods VehiclesMctor Hac kne ys.Other vehicles.Cars taxed on horse power- 2,186    839    181+     9- 3,197     Motor cycles newly registered in August,  1950,  sheweda dec re ase o f 806 compared with August 1929,
iCOTTON0     MR. LENNOX LEE handed in the following report:    Trading conditions in the cotton trade during iieptemberhave3 on the whole, remained difficult.     The  spot price of Middling American cotton at Liverpoolon oeptember 1st was 6.&apos;43d and on the publication of the bureau Report the price fell to 6.18d. and later to below Sd.which is the lowest level for 15 years.  The lack of confidenceengendered ^y the continued fall in the price of the rawmaterial is reflected in the restricted purchases not only of raw cotton but also of yarn and cloth.  Egyptian cotton hasfluctuated irregularly during the months  On September 1stfully good fair Salcellaridis at Liverpool was 10,40d and onthe American Bureau Report it fell to 9.95d. but later roseagain to 10o70d.     With cotton prices falling and clearances in foreing markets leaving a good deal to be desired business has notbeen brisk.  There has, however, been a slight improvementin the sales of piece goods to India el.though little efforthas been made to take goods in bulk2 the prices offered being,inmost cases, much too low to make business possible.Dealers in Bombay are reported to be clearing goods which havebeen held up for some time in consoquence of the Boycott andin order to avoid the Congress Pickets packages are beingtransported direct from the Port to the Dealers connectionsup-count ry.     Reports from the South and Central American Marketsindicate that a fair amount of business has been done withthe Argentine notwithstanding the Revolution.  In Brazil thesituation continues to be very depressed whilst in Columbiabusiness has generally been worse than during the previousmonths of the year.     As regards the Near and Middle East the demand from Egypthas been somewhat better although the improvement has been small.  The reports from Constantinople of favourable crops are having a good effect upon the market.  Demand from greece and Uyria remains poor but a fair amount of business has beendone with Roumania.     The Par Last has given more promise, the clearances at shangai through the auctions and otherwise being ratherlarger and the improvement in the exchange value of the Taelshould make for more favourable trading conditions.     In the Finishing section of the trade the Dyers reportthat although there is no immediate improvement in the piecedyeing department much interest has been taken in the placing of some 5/63OOO cases for Hong Kong for December/Januaryshipment, mainly in. shadow stripes, coloured stripes and plainpoptinettes.  This business has been made possible by a declinein cloth and finishing costs combined with the favourable turnin the exchange.  Further recession of cloth treated at bleachworks during&apos; September is reported and this is mainly attri-buted to the conditions^ in the principal overseas markets.  Inthe printing branch of the industry the home trade has shown some little Improvement but on the shipping side, whilstenquiries are reported to have been better for certain styles,orders on the whole have been disappointing and many firmstook the opportunity of closing their works by extending theustial September &quot;rolidoy,-O O-
                              HOSIERY.       MR.. WALKER handed in the following report:-       Leicester,   There is a slight seasonal improvement in  the Home trade, particularly in Fancy Outerwear Departments,  where repeat orders are being received, chiefly on novelties.  This has put many of the departments concerned on full  production.       In the Cotton Underwear and Khicker trade, repeats  are not so good as usual for the time of the year, hut medium  trade is being done.       The general turnover is still below last year&apos;s level.&apos;       The recent increases in the Canadian Tariff have caused  a serious set back to export business.       Nottingham.   During the last week or two there has been  an improvement in the seasonal classes of goods., such as -/inter  Underwear and Cashmere Hose and Half Hose, and so far as can/ be ascertained, stocks both in the Wholesale and Retail do not  appear to be heavy, indicating that given the right kind of  weather there is every reason to expect that the improvement  now shewing will be maintained.   The volume of business  passing, however, is below normal for the time of the year,  and the trend of trade is towards cheaper lines.       Manufacturers of lull Fashioned real si lie hose and  fine gauge artificial silk hose are fairly well occupied.       As regards Artificial Silk Underwear, business is fair,  and in the Outerwear Section there is a distinct improvement,  with indications that the improvement will continue to the  end of the year.       Business in the export trade is moderate.   The Canadian  tariff is already being felt, no new orders now being placed.  South Africa and New Zealand, -- trade appears to be better but  with the European markets business is only moderate.       Mansfield.   Trade in this district is no better at all;  every branch seems as bad as ever,-except perhaps the fancy  departments.   Fashioned pure Silks are slightly better but at  considerably lower prices.   &quot;inhere-ever one goes, one is faced  with continental imports at ridiculous values, which makes the  present state of trade easily accounted, for.       Loughborough.   Trade here is still bad and worse than  a month ago, short time being worked in all branches;  lack  of confidence which is generally evident is  attributable to  foreign competition at very cut prices.       Hawicx.   There is little or no improvement to report.  Trade continues to languish, and as the  fashion  for knitted  outerwear seems to have gone off for the present the only hope  of any improvement before Christmas is in a cold, and earl;/  Winter.       Hinchley.   The report I have received here reads as  follows:       &quot;I have very little to add to my previous reports as to
the state of trade here-   Although some sections  are better,others are worse and taking the trade as a whole,  conditionsI must say, are generally bad.     The number of unemployed registered varies, but -shewsno great improvement.     The depression in values all round is one  of  the mostserious factors, because it is  holding up deliveries.     I dare not anticipate what is likely to  happen between now and Christmas.&quot;                            BANKING.     ME. GOODENOUGH sent the following report     Easy conditions prevailed in the short loan marketduring most of September and day-to-day money was obtainableat very low rates.   On September 30th, however, end of the quarter requirements, coinciding with heavy payments forTreasury Bills compelled the market to borrow a substantial amount from the Bank of England, but since the turn of themonth, credit supplies have again been ample.     Gold movements have not been of outstanding importance.Towards the end of September, considerable sums were withdrawn from the Bank of England, mainly, it is believed,on Drench account, but according to the published dail3rstatements, the Bank of England, on balance, increased itsholding of  Old between August 30th and October 6th by 1,424,442.   The largest Individual receipts by the Bankwere two items of  1,070,000 and  1,000,000 respectivelyin sovereigns from Australia during the early days ofOctober.   The weekly returns have also shown that amountshave been received from sources other than those published in the daily statements.   On October 1st, the gold held inthe Issue Department amounted to  155.6 millions, comparedwith 3154.5 millions on September 3rd and with  129.1 millions on October 2nd, 1929.    Most of the gold available in the open market ha3 been purchased on French account.     During the greater part of September, discount ratesexhibited a declining tendency and, at one time, three months&apos;fine Bank bills were quoted at about 2-2 1/16 per cent.Towards the end of the month, quotations tended to harden andfollowing the announcement of the new issue of 4 per cent.Treasury Bonds 19.34-36 a further upward movement took place,although the advance was not  maintained and on October 6th,the rate for three months&apos; fine Ban^ bills had reacted toabout 2 3/32- 2%.   The margin between Bank Rate and jnarketrates is still wide and in the absence of definite signs ofan improvement in trade, it seems doubtful whether anysustained advance is likely to occur.     A rather larger volume of business has been reported inthe foreign exchange market.   The German mark has depreciatedas a result of the nervousness regarding possible politicaldevelopments in Germany and substantial quantities of gold havebeen sent from Germany to Paris.   The London-New York exchangehas moved in favour of the dollar, partly owing to seasonalinfluences, but the French franc, which,  at one time duringthe month, was as low as 123-65, has now risen above theexport point for standard gold to about 123.84.
     On the Stock Exchange, business is still of very smalldimensions.   A feature is the strength of the gilt-edgedmarket, which has received an added stimulus from theannouncement of the new issue of 4 per cent. Treasury Bonds-,Home Rails have been weak, following a further series of poortraffic returns, whilst the Industrial Market continues to lack support, largely owing to the unfavourable tradingoutlook.     LORD BRADBURY handed in the following statement:-     During a dull month in the Money Market almost the onlynotable feature has been the extreme ease of short money whichhas kept the Bill Rates round about 2fs while day to day money was often lent as low as 1$.   Some gold went to Prance duringthe month and the New York exchange weakened from about 4.87to 4.86 but this was no more than a normal seasonal movementat this time of year and the lost gold was more than  made upby receipts from other quarters.   The Bank&apos;s holding of goldat the end of the month was about  156,000,000, which represents an increase of  10,000,000 since the 1st January.     The Market was momentarily disturbed to an unexpectedextent on the last day of the month by a sudden demand for money to take up a disproportionate amount of Treasury Billson that day, the maturity of the Bills three months forward on the 30th December being a popular one.   The Market were forced to borrow extensively from the Bank of England and theBill Rates in consequence have since been quoted a good dealhigher at something approaching        It remains to  be seenafter the repayment of the Bank this week whether or  not theinfluence of easy money will reassert itself and bring theBill Rates:down again to a level unprofitable for the market and out of touch with the present Bank Rate.     The Stock Markets remained quiet during the month apartfrom a sharp fall in German securities after the election.Gilt edged stocks began to advance before the end of  the month and the advance has of course been carried a good deal furtherduring the past week by the announcement of a forthcoming issueof 4$ Treasury Bonds and by notice of repayment of the 4^5 TaxFree War Loan next January, which is expected to free a gooddeal of money for reinvestment in the gilt edged Market.     Some of the demand for gilt edged investments is saidto come from the Banks, which in times of bad trade mustusually seek an outlet for their money in this way.     SIR GUY GRANET handed in the following statement     The easy monetary conditions ruling at the time  of mylast reoort a month ago continued until the 29th of September.On that day, however, owing to the quarterly turnover of funds and the fact that there were no maturities of Treasury Bills,and also because the bulk of the Treasury Bills tendered for onthe previous Friday had to be paid for on the two last days.
of the month in order to obtain the end December maturity,  fundswere in short supply and it became necessary for the DiscountMarket to borrow rather a large amount from the Bank of England.This stringency is believed to be temporary, although  it isexpected that money may be a little more usable for the next fewweeks.   The large amount of short term money seeding  employment has kept Discount rates very low.   Bills maturing on  or before december 31st have been quoted about 2?^.   The rate for Januarymaturities has, however, been higher and is about 2 3/16$,  andI think the firmer discount rate will probably be maintained,  asthe market has to repay the Bank of England, and also  the applications for the new 4$ Treasury Bonds and increased offeringof Treasury Bills will have some effect on the supply  of funds.     Although tfci; Mil Rate has been and still is abnormally low,it is not expected, that any change will be made in the Bank ofEngland&apos;s official rate as the state of certain of the foreignexchanges, notably Prance, U.S.A., and Switzerland, does not warrant a downward movement at the present time.   The Bank ofEngland has succeeded in maintaining its&apos;  stock of gold which  at3156,000,000 is  2,000,000 more than it was a month ago. Prancehas taken most of the London open market gold, and has alsoshipped about  9,000,000 from Cologne to Paris.  In addition tothis gold shipment the Reichsbank has sold foreign currencyamounting to about  81,000,000 since the middle of September tothat at least  30,000,000 must have been withdrawn or  sent  outof Germany since the recent election results were announced.It istherefore to be hoped that political events in Germany  in thenear future will justify a return of confidence in the national finances.     There is little change to report in connection with theStock Markets.   Gilt edged and trustee stocks have continuedto receive the support of funds not required in trade, butindustrial and commercial stocks have with a few exceptionsbeen neglected and depressed.     There have been a few new issues of capital and those  ofan investment character have been well received.                  CO-OPERATIVE TRADE  IN  SCOTLAND.     MR. CAIRNS handed in the following  report:-     A notable experience in our trade this season has been  thehigh quality of butter from the Irish Pree State Creameries,  acircumstance which increased the demand  for it  relatively  to thedemand for this class of butter produced in Northern Ireland.     The sales of sugar are slightly less though the price ofgranulated is 4/l  per cwt lower than at the same  date a yearago, and a more than usual quantity has  been purchased for domestic jam-making.     Tea sales are also less, and it has been found that an effect of the abolition of the duty has  been to increase thedemand for low price teas.   Evidently the point is beingappreciated by the consumer that a given sum spent on a lowpriced tea no longer contains a disproportionate addition  tothe price as it did under our flat rate  of duty when comparedwith an equal sum spent on a high priced tea.
     Lately the market has been weak for eggs and it maybe proper to mention that the trade blamed for the weakness a reputed flaw in the Merchandise Marks Act.     Since the beginning of August, Irish Hams have beenexceedingly scarce-- almost unprocurable, in spite of the relatively high prices that were going for them. Withregard to the high price of these hams not bringing out an increased supply, it is explained that the price of the&quot;hams is not fully reflected in the price of the pork,The public taste is for large haras and small bacon and asthe bacon is necessarily large in keeping with the hamfc acomparatively low price has to be accepted for it and the&apos;combination of the tv/o prices determines the value of thenig.     In  Scotland the oat crop has been seriously damaged by continuous rains since the grain was ripe.   Consequentlynew oats are much discoloured, and in bad condition,  Newlythreshed oats of last year&apos;s crop have been in good demand,as millers find that they are very superior in quality tothe new crop, and such oats have risen in  price about-2/- a quarter during the last fortnight.  The demand foroatmeal is very poor and there is no alteration in price.Feeding stuffs continue to meet with a small demand andthere seems to be no bottom to the prices of some foreigngrains.  Plate oats are offered at ;25ol0s.Od a ton,Russian Barley at  4.5s.0d and Plate Maize at  5.2s.6dfor various dates of shipment.  These prices are below thepre-war level.  Until within the last few days during whichmarkets have steadied and prices become firmer, sales ofwheat have been depressed to such an extent that quotationshave been decidedly under the pre-war values.   The price ofK0.8 Northern Mani bob a has been as low as 27s.lOsd per quarter while in the corresponding month of 1913 the pricewas 32s.9d.  An aggravating factor in the depression hasbeen the Russian contribution of wheat.  As yet we have notbeen able to make a comparative test of the two wheatsRussian and Canadian, but the Russian we have received ismuch cleaner than the lots that came from that country informer tines.
EMPLOYiiSNT.Mr. Phillips handed  in the  following statement     HONTHI.Y STATISTICS OP  INSURED PERSONS.          AGED 16 TO 64 IN  3MPLOYi:5NT.IDATIEstimatednumbersinsured.Numbersunemploy-ed.DifferencebetweenCols.2 &amp; 3(to nearesthundred).m131 Estimated number inI employment after(deducting from Col.4 3-^  of the numbers in Col. 2  to  allow for sickness^ and other unrecorded non-employment exclusive of temporary holidays.141Includingpersonsdirectlyinvolved in trade dis-putes.._ill-Excludingpersonsdirectlyinvolved in trade dis-put^s^  Augustfl September  October  November  December  January  February  March  Apr il  May  June  July  August  September11,870,000/11,888,000/11,906,000/11,924,000/11,938,000/11,960,000/11,978,000/12,046,000/12,090,000/12,116,000/12,134,000/12,150,000^12,170,000^12,187,000^1,161,5001,165,9001,216,3001,236,5001,304,900.1,476,1001,538,1001,641,4001,703,9001,796,7001,850,8002,002,0002,049,7002,116,80010,708,500  10,293,10010 ,722,10010,639,70010,637,70010,633,10010,483,90010,439,90010,404,60010,386,10010 ,319,30010,233,20010 ,148,00010,120,30010,070,20010,306,00010,273,00010,220,40010,215,30010,065,00010,020,700 9,983,000 9,963,000 9,895,200 9,858,500 9,722,800 9,694,400 9,643,60010,292,10010,304,00010,266,00010,219,40010,213,30010,064,00010,016,700 9,981,000 9,910,000 9,845,200 9,845,500 9,719,0 00 9,693,400 9,642,600/ Revised figures.$ Provisional figures.* The sickness rate has been  taken at  an  estimated annual mean;   it  has not been  possible to allow for Seasonal Variations,
6/ L.              SHIPPING AND SHIP3UE -DING.  &apos;Sir Ernest Glover handed in the following statement:-Index number of Shipping freights,                        1920=100September 1930August 1930September 192920.2420. SI24,961913=100 86. 50 38.08106,67Laid up tonnage.  Tonnage laid up at the principal port                  of Great Britain and  Ireland,1st July 19301st April 19301st July 1929British &amp; Foreign   Net Tons.     913.853     892 ,154     381,158Tonnage under construction. Quarter ended30th June 1930      In U.K.                    Abroad31st March 193030th June 1929Tonnage launched. Quarter ended50th June 1930.31st March 193030th June 1929In U.K.abroad in U.K.AbroadGt,3ritain&amp; Ireland.468 ,023344,699392,888 Gross Tons1,592,0631,665,6723 ,057 ,7351,614,9931 ,650,9363 ,26o*,9291,453,9061 ,584.5192 ,858 ,225Gross TonsAbroad413,853508,184321 ,877Total886,376652,883714,755  Tonnage commenced.30th June 1930      230,466       350,425    580,89131st March 1930     426,570       430,231    856,80130th June 1929      428,400       270,597    698,997  Weight of Coal exports from the U.K.August 1930             August 1929           July 1930     tons                    tons               tons  3,933,677               4,976,756          4,655,579
   Bunker coal Shipped for the use of Vessels engaged inthe Foreign Trade.   August 1950             August 1929           July 1930        tons                   tons                  tons     1,335,159              1,441,497             1,358,200  Bunker Coal Prioes. Special Durham Bunkers f. o,b. Newcastle                                  s. - d.           Average 1913          14. 0.               &quot;   1927          16. 5.               11   1928          15. 31               &quot;   1929          17. 2,                         1930           January               17. 0.           February              16.10-i-           Liarch                 16.10-1           April                 16. 6.           Hay                   16. 6.           June                  16. 6.           July&quot;                  15. 0.           August                15. 0*                         RAILWAY TRAFFIC   ,     Sir Oyril Huroomh sent the following report:-     The serious falling-off in railway traffics continue during the four weeks ended 28th September 1930, and during thatperiod the receipts of the four amalgamated companies were 1,365,000 less than in the corresponding period of 1929.  Thisdecrease is made up as follows:-                                                 Decrease                                                                    Passenger train traffio           472,000              Freight train traffio:               Merchandise, minerals and live-               stock.                            635,000               Goal, Coke  and Patent Fuel.       258,000                                               1,365,000     The figures of each of the four amalgamated companies are set out in the attached statement.     Complete statistics are available only to the 51st July,1930.In that month the number of passengers (excluding season ticketholders) conveyed over all standard gauge railways in GreatBritain (excluding the London Tubes and Metropolitan DistriotRailway) was 4,468,148 less than on July 1929, a decrease of5 percent;  of this number 1,245,789 were in respeot  of passengers conveyed at workmen&apos;s fares.    The tonnage of freight traffic in July 1930&apos;was 3,364,777, or 12 per cent, less than in thecorresponding period of 1929.   Decreases in the tonnages of
individual commodities include the following: -                                       Tons       Per cent.Goal, colce and patent fuelIron Ore.?ig IronIron and SteelLimestone.2,022,233      12.0  341,569      29.6  101,946      30.9  307,261      21.3  111,251      24.0
PASSENGER TRAIN RECEIPTS.COAL, POKE AND PA]M..gDgL*.     Great Western     London and North Eastern.     London, Midland and Scottish     Southern,...................                                       TO (&quot;&apos;&amp;10 eoocooocoTOIAI, TRAPE-IC RE0EIFJ3 - PASGBiNGER AND .HmCG^Jj.     Great 7/estern     London and North Eastern     London, Midland and Scottish.     ; Southern,Total.   4 weeks ended20th September. 1950,1929.(Thous.) 1,131 1^659 2,442 6 s 731   914 1,726 2,381...  329 5,3501930.I Thous.)   1,062   1,54.4   2,249  .-ls4p4   6,259  485 1,085 1,064... 131 2,765 2,530 4,470 5,007 1,95914,846  8721,4702S059 . 3M4,715  449  976  971  -1112,507 2,383 3,990 5,279. Ij82913,401Decrease 1930compared with     1929.(Thous.)   &apos; 69   115   193    954.72 42256322...13.635  36109  93.20251147480608130.. PerCent. 6.10 6.93. 7,90 60 34-7.01  59 weeks ended20th  September. 1930.1929.(T hous.)- 9,95314,75922,25415,19060,156 4.6014.8313,52 I11. 87 0,39516,16322,040 3,0414-49 , 947 704210,05 8a7614,09^.33 5.0110,7410,33 6. 64 9.19&quot;- 4,34810,45110,494 1,27427,06723,49641, 37354,79617,505137,1701930.(Decrease  1930 compared  with      1929.(Thous.)  9,610. 14,190. 21,010! 12,907j 57,717j(Thous.)   343   569 1,244   2832,439 8,216j14,948)         479       1,215       1,5482,991;     5020,50046,655:4,506i9,859j9,727j1,14613,29226259276712825,318!  1,74922,41238,99751,23717,044129,6901,0042,3765,559  4617,400PerCent.3,453.865. 592cl54.055.517. 527.021.636.59- 5.40 5,66 7.3110.086.464.615.746.492.635.45Great Western,London and North Eastern....,London, Midland and Scottish,SouthernMERCHANDISE,. MINERALS AND LIVESTOCK.,     Great Western,     London and North Eastern.     London, Midland and  Scottish.     Southern,TotalTotal
COLONIAL TRADE.MR. CLAySON handed in the following report;-     Kenya and Uganda.   The value of the export trade of kenya and Uganda during the first five months of 1930 was 2,888,078 as compared with  3,557,700 in the correspondingperiod in 1929.     The value of the import trade of Kenya and Uganda duringthe first four months of 1930 was  2,542,933 as compered with 2,916,960 in the corresponding period in 1929.  The percentage-of imports from the United Kingdom in this period  in 1930 was37/J as compared with 36$* in the corresponding period in 1929.     Tanganyika. Territory;   The value of the export trade of tanganyika during the first six months of 1930 was  1,151,021as compared with  1,490,784 in the corresponding period in1929.     The value of the import trade of Tanganyika during the-first six months of 1930 was  1,964,994 as compared with 2,010,800 in the corresponding period in 1929.  The percentageof imports from the United Kingdom during this period in 1930was 38^ as compared with 34fs in the corresponding period in1929.     Northern Rhodesia;   The value of the minerals produced inNorthern Rhodesia in July 1930, was  62,994 as compared with 99,863 in the corresponding month in 1929.     The total value of minerals produced during the firstseven months of 1930 was  558,961 as compared with  620,296for the corresponding period in 1929.     The value of the Northern Rhodesia export trade duringthe first two months of 1930 was  524,398 as compared with 428,032 in the corresponding period in 1929.     The value of the Northern Rhodesia import trade in thefirst two months of 1930 was  176,639 as compared with 128,927 in the corresponding period in 1929.     Cold Coast;   The value of the Gold Coast export trade inthe first six months -of 1930 was  6,756,801 as compared with,37,178,314 in the corresponding period in 1929.     The value of the Gold Coast import trade in the first sixmonths of 1930 was  4,356,230 as compared with  4,159,258 inthe corresponding period in 1929.  The percentage of importsfrom the United Kingdom in this period in 1930. was 49.74;J as.compared with 46.16Ju in the corresponding period in 19 29.     Nigeria:   The value of the Nigerian export trade in thefirst six months of 1930 was  8,247,409 as compared with 9,.&quot;34,810 in the corresponding period in 1929.     The value of the Nigeria import trade in the first sixmonths of 1930 was  6,023,537 as compared with  5,526,481 inthe corresponding period in 1929.
    Ceylon:  The value of the export trade of Ceylon duringthe first s even months of 1930 was -315,518,365 as comparedwith 519,193,021 in the corresponding period in 1929.     The value of the import trade of Ceylon during the firstseven months of 1930 was  14,498,242  as compared with 18,211,375 in the corresponding period in 1929.     British halaya:   The ocean shipments of tin in August1930 were 7,868 &quot;tons.  Imports of tin ore during that monthamounted to 2,830 tons.     The ocean shipments of Rubber in August 19 30 amounted to47,802 tons.   Imports of Rubber during that month were 10,304tons.  Stocks of Rubber in hand at 31.8.1930 totalled47,190 tons.     The total exports of Rubber in the first seven months of1930 were 319,575 tons of which Domestic Exports amounted to245,738 tons.     Ocean shipments of Rubber in September 1930 amounted to49,229 tons.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.MR. HOSE sent the following report:-.     Since the occurrence of the political coup d&apos;etat in argentina, to which I referred in my last Report to the Councilnormal conditions have been maintained in the Republic, although a temporary measure of martial law continues to be in operation.The new Government has apparently fully established its authority and is in a strong position to carry on the administration,pending the inauguration of Constitutional elections.     In regard to the Argentine exchange situation, the sterling value of the gold peso, at 39-gd., is still at a low level, and this is to be attributed to the great reduction whichhas taken place this year in the total value of exports of thecountry&apos;s produce, bearing in mind the fact that withdrawals ofgold for shipment from the Caja de Conversion have not been permitted since 16th December last.  It is officially statedthat exports of bullion - apparently from the stock of gold heldoutside the Caja - during the first seven months of 1930totalled only 927,555 pesos, as compared with as much as95,030,491 pesos in the corresponding period of 1929.  At thesame time, the provisional value of total shipments of merchandise from the country is returned at 393,046,040 pesos(gold), against 608,778,845 pesos in January-July,  1929.   Thevolume of shipments this year was also much less than in 1929,having been only 6,800,973 tons, against 10,618,570 tons.  Thereduction in both volume and value is almost entirely accountedfor by the diminished movement of grain, this having amountedto 4,802,311 tons, as compared with 9,137,382 tons, the valuebeing 197,070,826 pesos (gold),  against 381,132,066 pesos.   Woolshipments also contributed in a relatively marked degree to thedecline in the value of exports this year, for,  although thevolume was only slightly reduced, at 95,670 tons, against96,422 tons,  the total value,  owing to the much lower level of
prices, was only 31,703,667 pesos (gold), as compared with53,586,775 pesos.     Latest re-ports received by cable from the Argentinaagricultural areas indicate that the crop prospects are very satisfactory.  Import market conditions are dull, beingnaturally affected by the low level of exchange,  and must beexpected to remain so, pending clarification of the generalsituation and, more particularly, some measure of recovery in the consuming markets for Argentina&apos;s staple products.     The rapid,political changes which have taken place withinrecent weeks not only in Argentina, but also in Peru and3olivia, have naturally not been without repercussions inother South American States.  The latest attempt to solveeconomic difficulties by means of political changes is apparently taking place in 3razil, where widespread disturbanceshave been reported during the last few days.  The Gove nmentis Stated to have control of the situation in the importantcities of Rio de Janeiro and Sao Paulo, but a national holidayhas been declared for a period of fifteen days, the banksbeing therefore closed.  The reason assigned is the necessityof preventing undue speculation in coffee or in the exchange.In the circumstances, the outlook is obscure, but it is nevertheless satisfactory that the Brazilian Congress isreported to have voted a credit for the purpose of maintainingorder.  It is sincerely to be hoped that there will be an early settlement of these political difficulties, especially in viewof the measure of success which has already been attained inthe direction of solving the problem of over-production of coffee in the Republic,     The trade situation in Chile continues to be difficult,and necessitated the raising of the discount rate of the BancoCentral de Chile on 4th August from 6 to 7 per cent, to the member banks and from 7 to 8 per cent, to the public, thuscausing the commercial banks to increase their rates to an approximate average of 9 per cent.  The level of the Chileanexchange rate has risen slightly, but the benefits accruingfrom the functioning of the Central Bank are demonstrated bythe fact that the sterling value of the currency is stillmaintained at slightly above the parity of 40 pesos to thethe advance during September having been only from 39.65 to39.95.     In common with other South American countries, Chile has suffered a considerable diminution in the total value of her exports, shipments during the first six months of 1930 havingamounted to only 718,400,000 pesos, as compared with 1,297, lOCyGOOpesos in the corresponding period of 1929.  Imports during thesame months of the current year were 733,600,000 pesos,  against743,800,000 pesos.  The decline in the total value of exportsis 1: rgely attributable to reduced shipments of nitrate of soda,and also to the lower prices of other leading products,  such as-copper  and wool.  Until such time as the situation in thisrespect is improved by some measure of recovery in the world economic position, no appreciably increased movement can beanticipated in the Chilean import markets.     Peruvian conditions continue to be characterised byserious depression in the commercial situation.  The new government appears to be firmly established, in office, but theabsence of any recovery in prices of the country&apos;s staple products
of cotton and sugar militate against an early resuscitationof the demand for imported goods.  The exchange, however, isbeing fairly well maintained, the current  rate being14.93^ gold soles to the   sterling, as compared with15 soles at end-August last and the legal parity of 12.166soles.     Mail advices received from Bogota, the capital of theRepublic of Colombia, state that the commercial situation there is quiet, although in some cases merchants reportincreased buying from the countx^y towns.  Transportconditions are stated to be good.  The political situation isquiet, and the Executive which took office with the inauguration of the new President in the early days ofAugust, have full authorisation to effect economies in public expenditure.  In regard to the general outlook inColombia, this must depend largely upon the course of coffeeprices, and it is to be noted that a slight improvement inquotations in the local market for the commodity haslatterly been reported.     Cables received from Ecuador indicate that, in order to conciliate^ opposing political influences, the President ofthe Republic, tended his resignation, but, at the specialrequest of Congress and all Parties of the State,  laterconsented to remain in office.  So far as concerns the general commercial situation in Ecuador, some improvement seems tohave taken place as a result of increased e. ports of coffeeand rice.  The increased movement in these commodities has provided a fair amount of commercial bills, and the tendency in the exchange is firm.  A restrictive influence,  however,continues to be exerted upon Ecuadorian commercial conditionsby reason of the depression in the overseas markets.     In Salvador, prospects for the coming coffee crop are satisfactory;  the general opinion appears to be that the yield will be heavy and probably as much as that of thecurrent year&apos;s crop.  During the period 1st October, 1929, to31st July, 1930, shipments of coffee from Salvador totalled725,111 bags, as compared with 638,607 bags for the corresponding&quot;period of the preceding season, and it is estimated that total exports for the year ended 30th September,  1930, exceeded750,000 bags.  Moreover, the maize and bean crops of theRepublic are reported to be good, despite the drought which prevailed during the latter half of July and the first halfof August, and which threatened to cause serious damage.Prospects for the next coffee crop in the Caracas district ofVenezuela continue to be excellent,  but reports from theWestern areas of the Republic state that the crop there may be adversely affected by local rain.     Prosperity in the Central American Republics is closely associated with conditions in the consuming markets for coffee,so that, pending an appreciable recovery in prices of thatcommodity, and so long as the Brazilian coffee situationcontinues to be obscure, it appears probable that development programmes will continue to be curtailed and the volume ofbusiness in imported merchandise restricted.     To sum up, the revolutionary movements in the principalSouth  merican centres - which in themselves are mainlyattributable to economic depression - render the outlookparticularly obscure at the present moment.  The I^orth Americans&quot;are restricting loans and at the sa:-..e time  raising their importtariffs, and much will depend upon the outcome of these twoconflicting policies.  undoubtedly sentiment against the North-Americans is stronger than ever at the moment.
    &apos;                  Reprinted from, THE BOARD OF TRADE JOURNAL dated September 25, 1930.TABLES  ILLUSTRATING  THE  ECONOMIC POSITION  IN THE  UNITED  KINGDOM.                                                  TABLE I. GENERAL.Items.   Unit ofMeasurement.i. NEW CAPITAL ISSUES.   (Midland Bank Statements)   (a) Unitod Kingdom purposes .  (6) Overseas purposes       Total All purposes       PER CENT, OF 1924  ...&apos;,. BANK CLEARINGS. (Country Cheque nnd Provincial-   England and Wales)    Average amount daily ...       PER CENT, OF 1924 ..., POSTAL     RECEIPTS    (GREAT  BRITAIN)--A verage amount daily      PER CENT, OF 1924  ......-t. WHOLESALE  PRICES-BOARD  OP    TRADE INDEJC  NUMBERRAILWAYS   FREIGHT  TRAFFIC (Great Britain). (o) Coal, Coke and Patent Fuel     PER CENT, OF 1924  ...... (&amp;) Other Minerals and General       Merchandise    ......     PER CENT, OF 1924  ......SHIPPING    ENTRANCES   AND CLEARANCES  with cargoes  in the Foreign Trade  (a)  Entrances   .........     PER CENT, OF 1924  ...... (B)  Clearances   .........     PER CENT, OF 1924  ......7. SHIPPING FREIGHTS     Chamber of Shipping Index (2)        PER CENT, OF 1924  ......EXTERNAL TRADE- (u) SET IMPORTS Value as  de-    clared............     Value at 1024 prices     PER CENT, OF 1924  ...... (6) BRITISH  EXPORTS   Value  as    declared      ...    ......     Value at 1924 prices     PER CENT, OF 1924  ...... (c) NET IMPORTS OF RAW  MATE-    RIAIS Value as  declared     Valuo at 1024 pricos     PER CENT, OF 1924  ......9. INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTION-BOARD    OP TRADE INDEX NUMBER   ...10. EMPLOYMENT (Great Britain)     (a) Estimated number of lnsurod      workers (aged 10-64) in  em-      employment (5) ...     ......        PER CENT, OF 1924  ......    (B) Numbers of insured workors      (aged 10-64) unemployed  ...        PER CENT, OF 1924  ......Million  &apos;s.Million  &apos;s.Thousand  &apos;s.Million net ton    miles.Million net tons million  &apos;s.Monthly Averages.Tear1924.Tear1928.MillionsThousands  7-4 11-2 18-6100 15-6100115100825100763100  4-61100  5-44100 94-8 94-8100 66-7 60-7100 27-0 27-0100  9-51100 1,137100 18-3 11-9 30-216215-498-9131114722 87-5750 99-0  5-03109-0  5-37 98-787-0 89-6102-2107-8 60-8 69-9104-7 22-4 27-3101-3 10-00105-11,247109-7Year1929. 13-3  7-8 21-111415-298-2132110April-June,1929.784 95-0788103-3  5-23113-2  6-72105-2 92-7108-2114-1 60-8 72-3108-3 23-8 80-5112-9111-8 10-19107-11,224107-6 18-4 -8-7 27-114515-298-012911282-2706 8B-5810106-1  5-30114-9  5-76105-985-1 89-6104-1109-8 59-2 71-1106-5 22-6 28-2104-1 10-27107-91,138100-1July-Sept.,1929.Oct.-Dec,1929.Jam-Mar.,1980.April-June,1930. 6-9 3-6 9-55114-794-I128112768 93-1804105-3  5-91128 1  6-20114-1 89-7103-7109-4 61-6 72-8109-1 20-8 25-6 94-2110-7 10-28&apos;108-01,156101-75-94-015-499-414913080-7810 98-2813106-6  5-30114-9  5-75105-6 99-9117-5124 0 620 74-1111-0 25-9 34-5129-2114 0 10-19*107-11,269111-6 12-1 11-1 23-212415-096-712911376-9810 98-2782102-4  4-64100-6  5-36 98-663-6 80-3107-0112-8 54-7 60-7 99-9 22-8 31-6116-9110-9  9-94&apos;104-51,552136-5 12-5 11-0 24-113014-392-4131114670 81-2754 98-8  5-53119-8  6-52101-5Aug.,1029.July,1930. 77-9101-4106-9 40-9 68-3 87-4 17-2 26-1  9-75&apos;102-61,784156-9 2-2 1-4 3-61914-190-9123107777 94-2794104  5-88127-5  6-48119-2 82-9 92-0  (3) 630  (3) 20-7J- (3) (4) 10 27108 01,101102-113 3-316-414-392-113211609784-475298-5  6-051311  5-71104 978-0 (3)50-7 (3116-6 (3) (4)   9-5S&apos; 100-72,002 176-1(1) Information not yet available          (2) Published by courtesy of the CHAMBER OF SHIPPING OF THE UNITED KINGDOM and of tho STATIST Company, Limited.                          (3)  Tho calculation of the valuo of the Imports and exports at 1024 prices is only made quarterly.(4) The calculation of tho Index Number of Industrial Production Is only made quarterly.     (5) Allowance Is made for sloknoss, otc, and for trade disputes.* Provisional.   X  (302)2040(2810)  Wt 14874-8170  250  10/80  E&amp;S
TABLES  ILLUSTRATING  THE  ECONOMIC   POSITION  IN THE  UNITED  KINGDOM.                    .....                   Table II. Particular  Trades.Items,   Unit ofMeasurement.1. CO All MININO     (a) Quantity  of saleable  coal      raised .........        Per cent, of 1924 ......    (6) Quantity  of coal  export-      ed (1)............        Per cent, of 1924 ......    (c) Percentage   of   Insured      Workers  wholly unemployed       Percentage   of   Insured      Workers Temporarily stoppedIron and Steel  (a) Crude Steel Output     Per cent, of 1924...... (6) Pig  Iron Output......     Per cent, of 1924 ...... (c)&quot;Percentage   of   Insured    Workers Unemployed3.  General Engineering     Percentage of Insured Workers      Unemployed...3*. Electrical -Engineering      (a)  BEAMA Index of Activity.       (2) Per cent, of 1924     (6)  Percentage    of   Insured       Workers Unemployed6. Electricity  Generated   by    authorised undortakers-in Great    Britain............        Per cent, of 1924 ......8. Shipbuilding (3)     (a) Merchant vessels under con-      struction at end of Quarter...        Per cent, of 1924 ...    (6) Merchant vessels commenced      during Quarter        Per cent, of 1924 ......    (c) Percentage   of   Insured      Workers   in  Shipbuilding,      Ship repairing, and  Marine      Engineering Unemployed  ...7.  Base Metals-    (a) Copper available for manu-      facture (5) (6).........        Per cent, of 1924  ......    (4) Percentage   of   Insured      Workers UnemployedCotton  (a); Raw Cotton  delivered  oo    Mills............     Per cent, of 1924 ...... (6) Percentage    of    Insured    Workers UnemployedWool Textile Industky  (o) Index of Wages Paid.  Per    cent, of 1924 ......... (6) Percentage    of    Insured    Workers Unemployed10. Artificial Silk      Production of Yarn and Waste         Per cent, of 1924  ......11.  Natural Silk-     Deliveries for Home Consump-       tion (7)     .........         Per cent, of 1924  ......12-. Crude  Rubber  available     manufacture (6)         Per cent, of 1924  ...for13. Building-     (a) Plans  approved   by  140       Local Authorities  in Great       Britain, estimated cost ;         (1) Dwelling Houses.  Per           cent, of 1924   ......         (ti) Other  Buildings  and           additions and alterations           to  existing   buildings.           Per cent, of 192 J     0) Percontago   of    Insured       Workers Unemployed :         (i) Building     ......         (ii) Public   Works  Con-           tracting, eto.......Mill, tonsMill, tonsThou, tonsThou, tonsMill, unitsMill, gross tonsThou, gross tonsThou, tonsMill. lbs.Mill. lbs.Thou. lbs.Thou, tons monthly Averages.Year1024.Year1928. 22-3100  5 14100w08310000910020-6100605081001-44(4) 1002031009-410012-311810013-81007-02-11100   (8)1801001-90100 10010-317-019-889-0  4-1781-214-6 7-7  710104-0 55190-521-09-889-8 4-9768149 1-2486-5  324123-511-7 12510-012510692-711-24-52214201145403212106-512-320-3Year1929.21-496-1 6-0297-812-1 4-3  805117-7  032103-718-9107-0  4-4858169  1-45101-1  412157-111-3 12012510513-290-313-24-742252661486-96313117-513-122-3April-June,1929.20-592-0 4-9997-111-5 5-9  828121-1  641105-3105-4  4-7751148  1-45101-0  428163-120-012-0 12813011093-311-44-39208200145503264135-9 9019 0July-Sept.,1929.Oct.-Dec.,1929.20-893-6  5-34104-011-6 6-3  802117-4  673110-518-6107-6  4-0731144  1-45100-7  360137-120-710-8 1158-814-05-232482681496-66350119-4  0-3 19-822-299-8  5-38104-710-8 3-9  789115-4  054107-520-5101111-1  4-21,001  197  1-50108-4  499190-0210110 1178-313511413-890-614-25002402691490-76354124-815-223-9Jam-Mar.,1930. 22-6101-7 60097-410-2 3-8  791115-8  041105-322-912-7116-4  5-71,006  198  1-61112-2  427152-52208-2 87110 120-10223-883-92004-27 2032551425-88309120 0146-7 17-5 20-9April-June,1930.19-886-8 4-6187-812-3 8-6 66397-0 59998-415-1109 0  .7-2788155 1;3996-7 23037-825-611-6 12414 09278S7-3 73-8.  - . 21-83-781802872595-27277139-912-925-9Aug.,1929.July,1930.20-592-34-9896-911-7 4-5  753110-2  682112-00-7107-3  40706139(3)20-7111 119766414 S87-314, 24-67 2222521407 03 36963-984-0 9 019-818-984-7 4 6590-614-214 0 62190-9 48079 -S32 5105-2  8-47861S5CD13 7 14666565 022382081490-00318188270    (1) In addition tho quantity of coal shipped as bunkors in the Foreign Trado averaged 1,474,000 tons per month in 1924 and 1,368,000 tons per month in 1929.      (2) Published by courtesy of the British  Electrical and Allied Manufacturers&apos; Association.      (3) The figures relating to shipbuilding nro pub-liBhed at quarterly intervals.       (4) Including  an averago of 62,000 gross tons on which work was suspended.     (5)  Tho figures given do not include intho avallahlo supply the motal produced from imported  ores,  matte,  etc.    (6) i.e.,  Not Imports,  less  additions to warehouse stocks or  plus reductions inwarehouse stocks.    (7) The silk oontont of tho cocoons and waste has boon estimated at one-third of their full weight,    (8) Estimated.     * Provisional.
         LATEST STATISTICAL DAOj(Information received rip to 181Latest.A monthearlier,-Capital Issues in Greatitain (Midland Bank statement):  &apos;ited Kingdom purposes.......Sept.overseas Purposes.................&quot;Total,2,409,000!  3,454,0002,650,000 j  5,106,0005,039,0001  6,560,000Ink Clearings:lountry Cheque and Provincial -[leek ended..............o..........; Oot .11eroentages of Advances toDeposits (London Clearing Banks)..! Sept.hey Market:                        ,ank Rate.....................Oot,17arket Rate 3 months&apos; Bank Bills...)    nisoount (3 months&apos; treasury bills)............................!    &quot;ices:  Wholesale &quot;Board  of        jIradeH Index No.-(1924 s  100):       Pood.......................: Sept .       Materials....................:   &quot;81,078,000   52 .468,539,000    52.8/ie  2A/l6-20/^b $   2X/16$              I 2.16.9.lid.  ; 2.0s.l0.O5d.74.467 .069.5    1,888,0001,382,900       Total......................i  &quot; ilway reoeipts  -  week ended -     j cods Traffic (Gross)....,,........I Oot.11 passenger  Traffic  (gross)J.........I  &quot; ternal Trade:           &quot;          ; et Imports.............Sept.british Exports....................\  w let Imports,  of Raw Materials.......j  &quot; lipping -  Entrances and Clearances j dth cargoes in  the Foreign        i rade:     Entrances................... .j Sept .     Clearanoes................\  &quot;fjupbuilding:             :          j easels under construction: World................J........; Sept .30 United Kingdom................ ,;    &quot; easels  commenced -                ; World..........................; Sept .30 United Kingdom.. /. ................!    &quot; seels laid up In United Kingdom   j orts: British.........-..................j Oot.l Foreign.......-....................j    11 ployment:                         ! fJnemployment:                      j Oct.6 Unemployed on Live Register       j Wholly un-  (incl.  persons on short time     ,   employed 1,474,67073,258,34842,r40.63714,844,839Net tons.  5,882,552  5,787,023 Gross tons   75.9   68.2   7o.8       1,783,100 1,622,9,00!73.i566-,l9442,776,96915,063,091Net tons.5,638,8095,888,715300!             Gross tons.2,569,036 ; June 30 3,057,735:l,116,746i   w    1,392,063480,244 i June 33160,714!   &quot;Net tons, 876,167   9,251receiving benefit)Others.July  ft  580,89.1,  230,466;Net tons.: 917,368 I   1,485 :  701,5212,176,191!reduction:                          jpoal Output during week  ended......j Oct.4Pig Iron output in month...........] Sept.Average per calendar day...........j   &quot;Crude steel output in month........j  Tons .4,672,600  425,000   14,170  580,6001,368,030  771,5412,139,571  Tons.4,574,100  416*700   13,440  451*300^Including tonnage on which work wStatistics Department,     Board of T^ade,        18th October, 1930.
PAL DATA.to LSfch October, 1950)At corresponding date in1929 .1928.1924.1,459,0001,205,0002,664,000  7,575,000 10,751,000. 18,306,0005,334,0002,569,0007,903,000!  88,866,000      55.1i  -I   6ifj 6&quot;^ - 6^/16% 6.3s.6.39d.! 89,010,000I!      53.5j! 4.7s.8.35d.92,347,000    49.1     4? 3.14s,11.17d.   85.8   79.5   81.7        2,057,100 1,622,90091,680,22455,104,25721,883,524    88.7    79.8    S2.8!         2,005,800  1,455,400&apos; 80,822,803* 56,619,972I 17,930,911    102.7     99.3    100.5         2,084,100 1,655,40091,289,17163,282,87623,088,141Net tons.5,894,4075j962,735Net tons.5,157,7015,473,966Net tons.5,009,2535,708,576Gross tons.Gross tons.1,735  Sep. 30 ,063    &quot;,891, Sep.30,466;  ..*2,817,339 .Sep.30 2,521,3421,448,355&apos;  w    1,089,760660,693360,087ons.i       Net tons,368 j Oct,l  260,4704855,527868,912338,31,207,236 Tons.5,170,100  664,600   22,150  847,900Sep.30  it497,580244,591     Net tons.0ot.l  412,363  &quot;      3,036  917,628  402,0781,319,706 Tons.4,797,300  503,900   16,800  718,600   Gross tons.Sep.30  2,551,012   M    1,468,408Sep.30   n530,833252,745      Net tons.Oct.l  307,999        25,8211,215,575  Tons .5,155.300  569\200   18,970  645,000rk was suspended.

SIPIEMBER 1931

</content>
</cab>
