<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/1/20 images: 290-303</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
copy no war    CABINET,RELEASE FROM THE ARMED FORCES OF KEY MENIN INDUSTRY.Note by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.At their Meeting on 4th October, 1939, at 5.30 p.m.(W.M.(39) 37th Conclusions, Minute 7)Pthe ?\far Cabinet invited meto take up the question of the immediate release from the armed Forces of key men in industryBI accordingly asked the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Food, as Chairman of the Man power committee, to summon a _m.meeting of the Committee to consider this question and i attach, for the information of the WarCabinet? a copy of a Report which I have receivedoThe Conclusions of the Report (page 5) were, Iunderstand, accepted by the representatives of the departments at the meeting of the Man Power Committee.      It will be seen,however, from paragraph 10 and Conclusion (ill) of the Reportthat the period of suspension of Reservists is left fordetermination by the War Cabinet,(initialled)      C.Richmond Terrace, S,7,l.,18th October, 1939c

&apos;jpJgU 39)20 7ENCLOSURE.RELEASE PROM THE FORCES OF KEY LI.IT III INDUSTRY.REPORT.The Man Power Committee had already considered this question on 28th September- as a result of requestsreceived by the Ministry of Supply for the return to firms of tradesmen already serving with the Armed forces and for the retention in industry of Reservists andTerritorials whose temporary suspension from being called up had been agreed by the rar Officer2. It should be stated at the outset that the questionis a most difficult one owing to the fact that there isa shortage of tradesmen in many trades, that, inparticular, the Army since it has become mechanizedrequires more tradesmen than ever1 beforehand that, withits rapid expansion, its tradesmen requirements mustincrease enormously.      Thus of the modern army 20%only are Infantry-men.      The requirements of the RoyalAir Force are,  of course, similarly heavy and necessary.3. The problem obviously cannot be settled to the satisfaction of all interested.      The best that can bedone is to arrange,  as far as is possible, for the rightdistribution of the available supply between the three defence Services, the Ministry of Supply, and Industry,who, recognizing the shortage of skilled tradesmen,must train substitutes, improvise and get on with lessthan the,y really needn    The training of semi-skilled personnel

and &quot;rearrangement&quot; (dilution) will go some way tohelp meet demands and it is receiving carefulconsideration.      This matter is now &quot;being discussed by representatives of employers and Trade Unionsunder the auspices of the Ministry of Labour and wewere warned that, as the matter is of great delicacy,care should be taken in saying anything about it.h. It should be recorded in fairness to the   :arOffice that the machinery prepared in peace, whereby theSchedule of Reserved Occupations would operate in thecase of all post mobilisation recruits and theSchedule of Reserved Occupations would be used in a modified form as a basis for a comb-out from theTerritorial Field Army of certain skilled personnel,was immediately applied on the outbreak of war.      Inaddition to the foregoing arrangements the Tar Office,recognising .that there were key men in industry not covered by the Schedule in the modified form used forthe comb-out, agreed to the temporary individual releaseof over 3,000 soldiers from all branches of the Armyincluding the Militia.It should be made clear that the comb-outarrangements made before the outbreak of war did notapply to Regular Reservists or to men of anti-aircraft units.5, We are assured that the Army are making everyeffort to produce tradesmen and have already turned to other sources such as Technical Schools,  thePolytechnic and the Universities.

6.      &apos;  The war Oflice point out that firms shouldhave &quot;been aware of the losses they would incur on mobilisation.     Further, the &apos; rar Office stress the factthat they cannot spare Regular Reservists permanently.These men are essential to meet early casualties andto train Territorials.      Great difficulties havealready been created for the war Office by their efforts on behalf of Production, particularly as aresult of the delayed calling up of no less thanli+,600 Reservists and 600 Reserve Officers,      They havealso released individually to industry 1,700 Territorials,while the comb-out of the Territorial Field Army hasalready yielded 6,000 and, when complete, should haveyielded about lip000.In all, the war Office are already committed tothe loss,  temporary or permanent,  of nearly 28,000 men,either Reservists or Territorials, the equivalent ofapproximately 2 Divisions.7, We are impressed with the war Office contention that the Army cannot be built up efficiently to perform the tasks required of it whilst continuous withdrawalsof individuals are being made from units and we are agreed that final figures of releases should be decidedwithout delay and that firms should be warned that theymay expect no more.     Firms would then be forced tomake serious efforts to find or train substitutes fortheir employees permanently lost to the   fightingServices.

80 With a view to expediting the operation of thecomb-out   of the Territorial Army we have causedinstructions to he given for local military UnitCommanders to he assisted by the Ministry of Labour&apos;slocal organisation, where found necessary, in the compilation of the Form (EoD0 45) used for securing therelease -of Territorials from military service.9. It seems clear to us that the comb-out of theTerritorial Army should be allowed to proceed on thepresent lines but that the safeguards, already arranged for, should be operated to prevent the combing-out ofTerritorials into unemployment.10.        Further, as regards Reservists, the War office have conceded the necessity for postponing for a period the recall to the Colours of a limited number of certainReservists, the length of the period being still at issue.The War Office feel strongly that 3 months should beregarded as - an absolute maximumo      They stress that theReservist is a trained soldier and that if they releasesuch men for a period in excess of 3 months, they willnot have available the necessary and vitally importanttrained personnel for training the future contingentsfor the Field Force,.      On the other hand the interestsof Production would obviously be better served if thatperiod were made 6 months, and the Air Ministry haveagreed to that period of grace to Air Force Reservistsreleased to their own contractors..11.       A considerable number of applications for releasewhich might refer to Reservists, to Territorials or evenoccasionally to Militiamen, have been rejected and by wayof appeasemant the War Office are ready to assent, as afinal gesture, -   ^(a) to make permanent the 1,700 temporaryreleases from the Territorial Armyalready granted,   (see paragraph 6)0

(b) to grant a further 1,200 releases fromthe Territorial Army to industry, thesereleases also to he permanento(c) to commence the comb-out of the A.D.G.B.as soon as they are able to replace bytrained personnel the men to be combed-out.A considerable number of releases of menin reserved occupations will result fromthe comb-out of the A.DoGoB0 unitsoCONCLUSIONS,fe-..r&amp;commend: -(i) that the comb-out of the TerritorialArmy should continue and that the safeguards already arranged for toprevent comb-out to unemployment should be applied,(ii) that it is desirable, apart from thecomb-cut, that a final surrender oftradesmen (Territorials) should beagreed and made known as soon as.possible, so that firms may be broughtto face the situation by trainingsubstitutes and arranging necessaryimprovisations.(iii) that the maximum period of suspension of Army Reservists must be determinedby the Y/ar Cabinet,(iv) that the Admiralty, Air Ministry and theMinistry of Supply should (a) urgeIndustry to avail itself of the opportunity-nity to tap the unemployed market foremployees in place of those lost to theServices and (b) impress upon firms thenecessity for training substitutes andfor improvisationo(v) that the following final offer of theWar Office should be accepted:-(a) the I:,700 temporary releases already made from the Territorial army to be permanent,(b) the permanent release of a further,200 tradesmen from the TerritorialArmyo(c) the comb-out of the A.D.G.B.  to be commended as soon as it is possibleto replace the men to be combed-out.(Signed)    V/0  S, MORRISON-Chairman, Man Power Committee,Rlchmond Terrace, S.V/,1. ,!Stb.-Octobap.* 1939. -




</content>
</cab>
