<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/22/0 images: 156-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i^j^- .   &apos;7   134SAB G&amp;BlMf: THE STOCKHOLM OONgEMOB.Memorandum by the^Attorney General wltiL a-covering note&quot; by 3ir Edward&quot; Oars on.In view of the proposal to hold an International Confer-fence at Stockholm, I have communicated with the Attorney General WitJt a view to ascertaining whether the holding of suoh a,-Gciifie^n6^y any of His Majesty1b subjects was legal and I append the reply W&amp;USk he has sent me(Intd.) 3UC.2 7^bi t ehall Gardens, - - -3. W ; ; &quot;&apos;gth jg&amp;usji 1917. ............R B t0? 1624.It is a general principle of our common law.that in time of war, intercourse between subjects of this country and enemy subjects ii forbidden.a wide construction, is to be&apos; given to the term &quot;intercourse&quot; which ia by no means limited to a bommercial transaction, see the Cosmopolite 4.C.Roq.8, .10,.and Lord Stowell&apos;a judgment in the Hoop 1. CRob. 196 and Yonge Pieter 4 C. Rob.- 65. 79.The law has recently been reconsidered and restated by Evans in a oareful and learned judgment - The Pariariellos (1915) 34 L.J. Preb. 140.Aftor an examination of many authorities he comes to the conclusion that all intercourse with enemy subjects is forbidden, except by writing.   The case was affirmed on appeal by the Privy Council, 1916, 85 L.J. Prob. 112.In the particular case both courts took the view *m the facts that the case was one *f innocent commercial intercourse, but Evans P. con-sidered the case of non-commeroial intercourse in view of the possible appeal.   The Privy Council did not.In Robson, a Premier Oil &amp; Pipe Co., 1915 2 Chanc 124, Sargant J. adopted the judgment of Evans P. as a oorreot statement of the Common Law, observing at p.131   ;-&quot; It is not merely commercial intercourse, but all intercourse with an alien enemy, that is forbidden by the Common Law&quot;.To take part in a Peace Conference with enemy subjects wouia in my opinion clearly constitute &quot;intercourse&quot;.(3d) Frederick Smith.

</content>
</cab>
