<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/22/0 images: 161-162</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PW-&apos; WAR CABIHBT *(J.T.1626.STATE OF AFFAIRS IN ARABIA.Oopy of despatch Ho. 950/1173, of 17,7.17 from Cewmaadeo^ia-Shief Eaet Indies, with covering note &quot;by Mr. J.W ,8. Anders on, Admiralty, 5.8.17.... 5th Aug.1917.sir,I am ceuaawLea by My Lerds Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit herewith, for the information of the Far Cabinet, a copy of a despatch frem the Oommandcr-in-Ohief, East Indies. Ho. 950 of 17th July, relative to the state of affairs in Arabia.2.    A eepy has also been sent to the FenaLgn Office and War Office.I am,   etc.(Sgd)   J.W.S.AHDERSOH.for Secretary.Col. Sir Maurice Hankey, K.O.B. 2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W. (1)Ho. 950/1171. Naval Commander-in-Chief,East Indies A Egypt,17th July 1917.Sir,In continuation of my letter Ho. 773/1171 of the 13th June, 1917, be pleased to lay before the lords Commissioners of the Admiralty some further remarks on the state of affairs in Arabia,2.    Owing to the highly successful accomplishment ef a Mission entrusted to Captain Lawrence, a British official attached to the Hedjaz Operations Division, there has opened out a proepeot of development in the affairs of Arabia which may well be pregnant with important results to the whole situation in Palestine,3.    This Officer left the Wej area in the middle ef May accompanied by the Sheroef Hasir, the Eowetat Sheik Auda Abu Tayyem, and 36 Arabs with the object of raising the Tribes of the Haan region to the Standard of the King of the Hedjoz;   and since he arrived at Akaba on the 9th July with a following of some 8,000 Tribesmen, he has some tangible Bigns of the success of this part of hia undertaking.    Leaving hie companions in the region ef Maan, Captain Lawrence himself, with only two persons accompanying him, proceeded as far North as Tadmur, some 80 miles to the East-south-eastwards of Horns, getting in touch with the local Arab 8heiks, and with the Druzes as he passed through their territories.4.    His report on the attitude of these Tribes is highly aatis-faotory, and he describee them as not only willing but anxious to join the Arab Rising against the Turks provided they are supplied with the means to do so.5.    If Captain Lawrence&apos;e estimate ie in any ways correct, this attitude of these Tribes may well havo a groat effect on our oper-Jtions in Southern Palestine, for thny would be in a position to threaten the enemy lines of communication from Aleppo to the South.
6.      One of Sir Archibald Murray&apos;3 objections to landing a force at Afcaba was tho uncertainty of the attitude of tho neighbouring Tribes;   but if their attitude oan be proved to bo friendly it appears that this objection, at any rate, ceases to exist, and that consequently tho possi-hilities of using Akaba as a base both for operations on the Akaba - Ilaan - Damascus lino, end for supplying the Arabs may possibly be once more contemplated.7.      That those Tribes are - to u-30 an expressive if slang expression - &quot;out for business&quot; sesms to be proved by one or two instances of which Captain Lawrence was a witness. On one occasion when in the vicinity of iiaan, ohoik-Auda Abu Tayyeh wished to uttaok a force of Tunes estimated at 600, v/hilst he himsolf had only 400 men;   but Captain Lawrence, strong in tbo belief that in this kind of warfare the Arab is no match for the Turk, tried to disouado the SLoi&apos; from such a course,   Tho Sheik, however, asserted that he knew their capacity, and eventually at nightfall confidently charged a Turk Battalion with 5C horsemen followed up by his camel men. scattering the Turkish troops and capturing their Commander and 160 prisoners,   He also claims that ho buried 60C Turks * Later on, on Captain Lawrence rejoining hie companions at Ma an it was decided not to try rmc\ te ke the place, but instead to round up all the Turkish posts between Maan and A!:aha0   This was moat successfully carriod out, and they over/jually reached Akaba with 20 officers end 600 Turks, one German liCO, as prisoners, and with one captured ^un.   Tho Turkish lossos in theoo operations were estimated et 700 killed.   The total Arab forces which reached Akaba numbered 2,000.8.      This, of course, is Intelligence of a Lailitary rather than of a $aval interest, but whero the Hedjaa is concerned nothing can well be 3 one without tho co-operation of H.J4. ships, and I lay this information before Their Lordships with a view oi their having &amp; knowledge of tho main facts of the case should the question of using Akaba as a base be once more raised.9.      as I have before pointed out, auch a step would present no difficulties from the $aval point of view, end I should be in the position of being able to afford the Military Authoritioe any assistance that they might require.10.    The question of water tiould inevitably crop up, but since the use of Akaba ss &amp; base would probably moan the removal of tho Sgyptian troops end the K.F.C, Flight from 7*0 j to Akaba, I should, of course, be able to give them the same amount of wat^r and the same amount of orotection with Naval gun-fire as I do now at the forraer place.I am, $to.,(Signed)    1U 2. \&apos;*WtS$*VICB ABUXKAL COliuAUDSR-XH-OHISF.Sa.m.a

</content>
</cab>
