<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/22/0 images: 303-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
s SCRET.-&apos;- WAR CABIIIBT.G.T. 1661.COO I MO B   01?   I R E L 1 B 3). Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland.The past week in Dublin has been without any new political excitement.     The Chief Commissioner of the Metro-politan Police reports that &quot;the condition of affairs in the &quot;DM, Police District has been satisfactory&quot;.     The new Regulations under the Defence of the Realm Acts with regard to marching with weapons and wearing rebel uniforms appear to have caused some disquiet among the extremists and there was and is expectation of organised attempts to defeat this object of tho proclamation made by the General Officer Commanding in Chief - as yet, however, the police heve enforced the Regulations without difficulty.The comings and goings of the body of agitators, de Valera, Griffith and their associates, who are carrying on the Sinn Join movement in the Irish provinces, have not as yet brought either of them into open conflict with the law.    A question ia, however, ponding before the General Officer Command-ing as to whether de Valera shall be included in a prosecution for breach of the Regulations against drilling, which is before him for sanction.     My present impression is that there was a flagrant and insolent offence which might properly be dealt with in this way, either before Resident Magistrates under the Crimes Prevention Act 1887, or in the more usual way of cases of illegal drilling by Court Martial.A troublesome situation is being created by Colonel Maurice Moore, C..B. who acted as &quot;Inspector General&quot; of the Netional &quot;volunteers&quot; when Mr.Redmond, M.P. secured the control of that body.     The&quot;Irish volunteers&quot; who afterwards organised the Rebellion Of April 1916 seceded as soon as Mr.Redmond took charge of the general organisation, and from that time to the present the National Volunteers have been a Redmondite organisation
while since the Rebellion the Irish Volunteers have been regarded and dealt with as an illegal society. In the Southern and Midland counties of Ireland the national volunteers had and still have premises in which are stored several thousand- stands of Italian rifles of comparatively recent type.   These weapons lying in scattered places under no trustworthy or sufficient guardianship have been often the subject of consultation between the G.O*C. the heads of the police and myself.   They form an element of danger, not very great perhaps while no supply of ammunition is available for the rifles, but appreciable and capable of beooming serious. Heretofore, there has been a sort of safeguard in the differences which divide the Kati&amp;nalist Volunteers from the men of the Rebellion.   It is here that the mischievous action of Colonel iviOOre, C.3, comes into consideration-   He has been burying himself for.some timein efforts to resuscitate the Volunteer organisation   though v:ithout much success, but on Sunday last he brought together an assemblage of delegates from -Nationalist Volunteer Companies in various districts and secured the adoption of a scheme for re-union with the Irish Volunteers. Colonel Moore has been warned more than once by the G*ChCa as to the tendency of his conduct, and Sir Bryan Mahon is now considering his caec, and also the necessity of steps to prevent any transfer of the arms in question to the control of disaffected personseThe set speeches made by Griffith to seme of his associates at the meetings the Sinn Pein leaders continue to hold in the Midlands and \.est still show the mere restrained and moderate tone on which I have before observed- Z -
It is commonly reported that the various &quot;leaders&quot; in the revolutionary-movement are a good deal divided as to policy and that the recent disclaimers of violence of some of them are due to a determination on their part to shape a course vihich will win them the support of the R.C.Clergy and the farmers.At a recent Sinn Fein meeting in the Midlands Mr.Arthur Griffith said &quot;the object of Sinn Fein was the complete independence &quot;of Ireland, and to that end their principle was, as in the case &quot;of the Land League, that no wan standing by Sinn Fein could be &quot;Struck at without striking at all Ireland.     They were asking the &quot;people of Ireland at the present time to help the oause of their &quot;country by electing in every constituency a man who believed in &quot;complete independence and who- would support the claim they intended &quot;to put forward at the Peace Conference.     If the Sinn Fein Party &quot;were in full working order and a National Council sitting in Dublin &quot;new markets would be opened to the country which would foroe England to pay, not what she was paying now, her own price, for Irish goods &quot;but a competitive price&quot;.Another agitation of the Griffith stamp -Mr.Herbert Pim of Belfast, speaking at another Sinn Fs n &quot;meeting in Donegal said   &quot;the machinery of national reconstruction &quot;was being set up everywhere in the form of Sinn Fein clubs.   If &quot;Ireland failed to obtain an entrance to the Peace Conference, what &quot;then? he asked.     The answer was simple, for by the time the Peaoe &quot;Conference sits Sinn Fein trott-ift ^e in possession of the whole politi-&quot;cal machinery of Ireland if they excepted the Unionist districts &quot;in Uorth-East Ulster,   then they possessed the constituencies and &quot;Boards throughout the country, the National Council in Dublin would &quot;be complete, and they -;?ould immediately make Ireland in practice &quot;an independent state.      A tariff v?ould be immediately placed on &quot;English goods, direct trade v/ould be set up with friendly countries; hy passive resistance they could make England&apos;a tax collectors
&quot;imyotent, and just as &quot;Ulster&quot; w&amp;i? glad to avail itself of the * &quot;land won by Fenianism and the Land League; so &quot;Ulster&quot; would be &quot;only too glad to reap the fruits of a taxation reduced by two-thirds. &quot;English insurance Companies would be starved, and great Irish &quot;institutions would spring up.    Metal would be procured from America &quot;and spur lines laid to Irish collieries, and the ten millions &quot;paid annually to English coal-owners would be saved to Ireland. &quot;They would set up a postal service, and the Sinn Fein clubs would &quot;see to it that they were no more hampered in the transmission of &quot;messages by telegraph and telephone than the Government,     A ^wireless station would be set up and a great national bank estab-, &quot;lished, which would absorb the deposits of the Anglo-Irish banks. &quot;They must prepare for a generation of strenuous work.     If they &apos;had independence tomorrow, they would require years to repair the damage of centuries.&quot;Again a Catholic curate addressing a Sinn Fein Club in the West a few days since said -&quot;Some people had formed a wrong impression of Sinn Fein, inasmuch &apos;as they thought it was a wild and revolutionary movement.     There &quot;was nothing revolutionary about it;   the movement was eonstitu-&quot;tipnal, and most of the young men and women of Ireland had joined &quot;its ranks.     In all their actions he counselled peaceful and brderly methods, and said they should always respect the opinions &quot;of&quot;their opponents, whether Parliamentarians, nationalists or &quot;Unionists.&quot;Assertions of a resolve to avoid violence such as Ichave quoted, do not prevent de Valera and others of the released rebel prisoners from systematic efforts in various parts of Ireland t.9 bring into existence organised forces of men who are to be $rilled in anticipation that some day arms may be forthcoming for them.     Several cases of drilling which have been reported by the police have been dealt with by bringing the ringleaders before court martial for breach of Defence of the Eealm Regulations.
Arroste have been made of some prominent Sinn Feiners inelud-ing three released rebels who made speeches inciting their hearers to acts of rebellion.     The question of dealing with the performances of de Valera as an advocate of force and of the formation of an armed revolutionary organisation arises in this connection.Sinn IPein Clubs are stil? being formed and there are now upwards of 350 with a reputed membership of above 22,000.The Inspector General, Royal Irish Constabulary reports that there is no reason to believe that anas are being imported or that another rising ie imminent.9th August, 1917.(Initialled)   E.E.D.

</content>
</cab>
