<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/22/0 images: 380-380</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AFTKR careful consideration I have come to the conclusion that, in the absence of a general agreement with the trade unions being reached in favour of the Dilution Clause of the Munitions of War Amendment Bill now before Parliament, it will be better to continue negotiating and not force the Bill through before the adjournment.Extended facilities for dilution in private firms are of great importance to the execution of the Munitions Programme, 10.18, including particularly the expansion in aircraft which is called for, and to drop this Clause Avould be to rob the Bill of the sole feature which it contains favourable to an increased output. On the other hand, the proposal to abolish leaving certificates in the present circumstances causes me much anxiety, and might easily lead to widespread dislocation, detrimental to output. Before leaving certificates can be abolished or suspended wholly or partially it is necessary that the wage rates of important skilled classes should be effectively raised above the levels frequently attained by newcomers on repetition or other less skilled work. Otherwise there might he a. general migration from skilled to less highly skilled, but more highly paid work, with consequent serious injury to output.Any pledges which were given on this subject were contingent upon the passage and acceptance of the Dilution Clause.I propose, therefore, to continue my negotiations with a view to passing the Bill in its entirety when Parliament reassembles. Meanwhile I have ascertained that it will be possible, by administrative action and without legislative power, to suspend the leaving certificates should a serious recrudescence of unrest occur during the recess. The general labour position seems easier now, and I do not know of any special reason for expecting trouble. Unless the War Cabinet desire to discuss this matter with me, I shall proceed on these lines.W. s. C.August 9, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
