<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/22/0 images: 389-395</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
4Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information.BY/A/d2-Vfeekly Report on Austria-Hungary. Xll* (11th August, 1917.)The situation in Austria remains extremely obscure.     It has been openly announced that Dr. von Seidler is about to reconstruct his Cabinet on a parliamentary basis: but though he has negotiated v/ith all the various party leaders, nothing further has happened. There are repeated attempts to start the engine, but each time without success.     The real negotiations are conducted behind the scenes and not allowed into the press.     An interesting proof of this is that even the ^eue ffreie Presse&apos;s   references to Baron Beck as negotiator were cut down by the censor.Attempts to Reconstruct Cabinet.     Baron Beck, who was Austrian^ Premier when Universal Suffrage v/as introduced in 1906-7 and has intimate knowledge of the psychology and composition of the parliament which he re-created, is widely regarded as the coming man.     But from trustworthy information obtained through certain Socialist delegates to Stockholm, it Y/ould appear that a prominent part is being taken by Baron Sieghardt, the big Austrian financier and one of the most influential figures in Austrian public life.     He is urging the necessity for an agreement in the vital question of 3ohemia and for constitutional reconstruction in Austria before the Peace Conference , in order to avert the danger of the various national problems of the Dual Monarchy being brought up for dis-cussion there, and the consequent weakening of the Monarchy&apos;s moral position in Europe.     The Emperor himself takes an active part in negotiations, and has caused some sensation by twice receiving in audience one of the leading German socialists in Austria, Herr
- 2 -pernerstorfer, who is believed to have been offered a seat in theCabinet.Hitter von Seidler, having secured the two main German groups, concentrated his efforts on beguiling the Southern Slavs and Ula-ainians away from the Slav Bloc by the offer of portfolios - so far without success.     The attitude of the Poles remained enigmatic. The more conservative   factions among them would undoubtedly be filling to renew their traditional pact with the Vienna government in return for the restoration of civil administration in Galicia and a pledge of indemnities.     But the more radical groups - notably the peasants and the socialists - are averse to compromise and un-doubtedly represent the feelings of the population, which has been growing steadily more Slavophil since the Russian Revolution and has been roused to a high state of excitement by the arrest of the national hero, General Pilsudski, by the Germans.Attitude of the C2echs*     Most uncompromising of all are the Czechs.     Dr. Kramarz on his release from prison had a triumphal reception in Bohemia, being received with bands and speeches at the various stations on his route.     While he has withdrawn to recruit his health, the most radical exponents of Czech policy are his former supporter, Dr. Stransky, whose outspoken appeal to a Peace Congress was referred to in a former report, and the agrarian leader Baron Prazek, an ex-minister of standing.     The latter, who in the Reichsrat stated in its extreme form the demand for a Czecho-Slovak State, has since added to the sensation by an article in his organ Venkov,   urging a policy of no compromise and &quot;now or never&quot; , and insisting that not merely the authorities in Vienna, but also foreign powers, must be in no doubt as to the seriousness of Czech aims.Dissensions in the Slav Bloc      The Czech Parliamentary Club by 43 to 33 decided to hold in Prague a joint meeting of the Club and of the Czech National Council, in order to decide the question ^hatiier their representatives should take part in the deliberations
f the Constitutional Committee of the Reichsrat.     The Southern glavs and Ukrainians   were invited to take part in the discussion, and the former sent as delegates the two Slovene leaders, Father Korosec and Father Krek.     Unfortunately they were violently attacked on the very evening of their arrival in Prague   by the Czech Agrarian organ, and after heated personal discussions insisted on leaving again next morning without attending the proposed conference.     As a result the Ukrainians delegates abandoned their visit to Prague and the German press of Austria has been exulting ever since over the &quot;break-up of the Slav Bloc&quot;.     Obviously there are many v/heels uithin wheels: but to ascribe the breach to the Slovene Clericals&apos; resentment at an anti-Clerical article of the deputy Stransky is obviously excessive, in vie?/ of the fact that Krek and Korosec v/ent out of their way on leaving Prague to send a communique to the organ of the Czech Social Democrats, who are of course equally anti-Clerical.     All this proves an acute difference of opinion in the Slav camp as to the proper tactics to be adopted.     The Slovene Clericals, most of the Czech Clericals and one wing of the Czech Socialists favour an opportunist policy; they are prepared to discuss constitutional reform v/ith the Germans without abating their own claims, and hold that.the next 3tep after their statement of policy in Parliament must of necessity be discussion, as only thereby can the delicate problem of the Slovaks be raised in a practical form against the Magyars.     A majority of the Czechs, however, is quite intransigent and inclined to denounce as a traitor any one who works at the reconstruction of the Austrian constitution alone, instead of throwing -Austria and Hungary together into the con-stitutional melting pot-    The latter tactics are of course in-tended as a definite Ententophil demonstration, and are denounced as such in the German press.     (it appears that the Czoch leaders, whenever possible, make use of phrases employed in various pro-nouncement3 of the Allies.)
 am crmVc $^ntt.There is less and less attempt to conceal the had economic conditions prevalent in Austria and Hungary.     The papers are full of details as to the lack of fruit and vegetables, the milk short-agein Vienna, the state of famine in Istria and the special pro-visions for letting its destitute inhabitants cross over into Camiola.     Statistics are published showing that the deaths from tuberculosis in Vienna have nearly doubled since the war.The coal question promises to becomo extremely serious in the event of a fourth winter of war, and to complicate still further the relations between Austria and Hungary, already strained owing to food questions; It appears that in 1917 a further fall of 1,600,000 tons in the production of coal in Austria is regarded as certain, while the import of coal from Germany has fallen by more than half.     It is openly admitted that the miners&apos; capacity for work is sinking daily &quot;owing to underfeeding&quot;, and that the miners brought back from the front find food and wages in so unsatisfactory a condition ao to clamour to be sent back.    This admission and its connection with recent disturbances at Mahrisch-Ostrau (in in-duotrial Moravia) come from the Socialist Arbeiter Zeitung.     The problem is rendered still worse by the deterioration of the railway service and rolling stock.     Meanwhile owing to the destruction of the TranBylvanian mines Hungary has to import more coal than before -6,400 tons per day from Austria in 1917 ase^ginst 4,400 in 1913 -and the Austrian Minister of Public Works has given a plain warning that this 3Upply cannot be continued, unless Hungary consents to disgorge more grain for Austria1s use.Some idea of the strain upon Austrian resources may be gathered from the official statistics of the Minister of the Interior with regard to destitute refugees.     On lot June, 1917, there were admitted to be 491,745 of these from Galicia and Bukovina (177,000 Jews, 84,000 Ukrainians and 37,000 Poles) and 110,000 from the South (82,000 Italians and 18,000 Slovenes).
Tiie tremendous speculation on the Vienna and Budapest Bourses in the last few weeks - especially in shipping shares - would seem to suggest a &quot;belief in the attainment of an early peace.The visit of the new German Chancellor to Vienna on the 31st July was made the occasion of press assurances, in every tone and cadence, of undying loyalty to the German alliance.     But there is an undercurrent of over-profession, and it is quite evident that Count Czernin is more anxious for peace than Dr. Michaelis and anxious to pin him down to such a policy as would make dis-cussion of peace possible.     Kence the very remarkable difference in tone between Czernin&apos;s and Michaelis&apos; pronouncements to press representatives.---Archbishop Szeptycki, the Metropolitan of the Unraine UniateChurch in Eastern Galicia, vrho remained in his diocese during the Russian invasion and was deported and persecuted by the Tsarist regime, wa3 released by the Russian Provisional Government and allowed to return home last month.     In the interval, events in the Russian Ukraine and the formation of a national Ukraine Government at Kiev, have completely altered the Archbishop&apos;s perspective.     Rull religious toleration is assured to his Church in Great and Little Russia, and the national cause to which he has devoted all his energies and resources for many years seems on the eve of triumph. It i3 thus only natural that Austria, which was his sole hope in the years preceding the war, should now be almost at a discount politically v/ith him and his followers: and it is significant that instead of going to Vienna, where his arrival was announced with a great flourish of trumpets in the Clerical press, he should have gone direct fsom Hamburg to Switzerland - under the excuse of recruiting his health and awaiting Italian permission to present himself at the Holy See.     He wired for the Ukraine leaders in the Reiehorat, MM. Lewicki and Petruszewicz, and conferred with them in
* 6 r*the train while passing through Germany,     On their return to Vienna they published a pronouncement declaring the Ukraine Question to be of the very front rank in matters of international politics, but saving appearances in respect of their very &quot;Austrian&quot; past by a vague expression of regret that obstacles should be placed in the way of constitutional reform in Austria.     Archbishop Szeptycki is obviously awaiting events, and will when the time cones play an extremely important part in the international settle-ment.     During his passage through Stockholm he expressed himself to Sir E. Howard in a manner which shows him (if he spoke his real mind) to be more favourable to-day to Russia than to the Central Powsrs, for the obvious reason that Ukraine unity seems more easily attainable under a federal democratic Russia than under Austtria.Count Agenor Goluchowski, the veteran Polish statesman who was for 11 years (1896-1907) Austro-Hungarian Foreign Minister and who enjoys a certain Russophil reputation (justified $inly in so far as Vienna and Petrograd only drifted seriously apart after his fall), is now fcr the second time in Switzerland, in the hope of playing upon Entente susceptibilities.     He is reported also to be conferring with Count Szeptycki regarding the fate of Eastern Galicia.     Certainly the recovery of that province brings considerable embarrassments for Austria in its train.     It accentuates very greatly the friction between Poles and Ukrainians and f6rces Vienna to commit itself soon one way or the other: for since the Revolution Eastern Galicia had been administered on a national Ukraine basis, and the Ukraine leaders naturally insist that under restored Austrian rule there can be no return to the old favouritism of the Poles, and that Austria cannot give less than Russia had given.Tire CorTtr Agreement, concluded between the Serbian government and the Jugo-Slav Committee aB equal contracting parties, is an event of capital importance in the history of the Southern Slavs
and requires special treatment.     Its effect upon public opinion in the Southern Slav provinces of Austria-Hungary will be profound, and may be gauged &quot;by two facts:    i1)   ?he Jugo-Slav Committee, which contains among its members - apart from two men of world-wide fame, Kestrovic,the sculptor and Pupin,the inventor of long-distance telephony - members of the Croatian, Istrian Dalmatianand Bosnian Diets and of the Hungarian and Austrian Parliaments, a number ofhas issued/public manifestos in the name of all   Jugo-Slavo (notably in May, 1915 to the British Parliament, and in December, 1916 on the occasion of the Hungarian Coronation), but has never been openly repudiated by any party or individual among the Croats and Slovenes, despite extreme pressure brought to bear from Budapest and Vienna.     On the contrary, messages - naturally of a highly confidential nature - have on more t&amp;an one occasion reached mejobere of the Committee from their political friends at homo, even from apparent &quot;Austrophils of very high standings secretly approving the Committee&apos;s policy.     (2)   Last week Mr. Stephen Raditch, leader of the Peasant Party in Croatia, made a public protest in the Croatian Diet against Mr. Hoel Buxton&apos;s unfounded assertions in the House of Commons on July 30.    Raditidh boldly declared for Croatia&apos;s complete independence, including even the Banat, and asserted that union with Serbia v/as ultimately inevitable.     The Berne wireless report adds that his speech was received &quot;with wild applause&quot; by all parties in the Diet save the Minority (this doubtless refers to the little Austrophil group of seven led by Dr. Ivo Jrank).     Knowing Raditch/well personally, I am not surprised at his daring, but would prefer to reserve further comment until it is possible to estimate the effect upon Southern Slav opinion of the Corfu Agreement and tho speeches at the&apos; Serbian Society lunch.Ro7/.S*W. .11/8/17.

</content>
</cab>
