<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/22/0 images: 476-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the use of the Cabinet.   August 1917.Pl7T&quot;GN^^ CONFIDENTIALA NOTE ON INDIAN REFORM.&quot;WHEN the question of Indian reforms came up before tbe Cabinet shortly before Mr. Chamberlam&apos;s resignation, I expressed orally the difficulty I felt in accepting the formula which embodied the policy of the Viceroy and the India Office.This formula is again urged upon us, without substantial modification, by Mr. Montagu; and, though I admit the great strength of the case which he makes in its favour, I feel constrained to put on record the reasons why I view it with the gravest misgiving.The whole difficulty centres on the word &quot; Self-Government.&quot; This, according to the highest authorities, both in India and at home, is the &quot; word of power.&quot; If we promise Self-Government at however remote a period, Indian public opinion will, it seems, be satisfied. If we promise anything else, however desirable, and however easy of attainment, we shall$ promise in vain. Moderate reformers and extremists will combine against us, and the Govern-ment of India will become difficult or impossible.The advantages of pledging ourselves to work towards &quot; Self-Government&quot; as our ideal of Indian reform are obviously very strong.   What are the arguments against it ?To my thinking, they may be stated somewhat as follows : The word &quot; Self-Government,&quot; as applied to any fraction of the British Empire, has a perfectly definite and familiar meaning. It means Parliamentary Government on a democratic basis. This is not only its recognised meaning ; among men of British race it is the meaning which will be universally attributed to it in India. So that, if we promise to work towards Self-Government, we promise in fact to establish in India, some day or other, a Government on the same lines as that which has been set up in Canada, Australasia, and the Cape&quot;.Now everybody admits that for India, as it is, this form of Government is totally unsuitable. Where I differ, with some misgiving, from high Indian authorities, is in holding the vie*v that in all probability neither the lapse of time nor the development of education will ever make it suitable. East is East and West is West., Even in the West, Parliamentary institutions have rarely been a great success, except amongst the English-speaking peoples. In the East, not only have they never been seriously tried, but they have never been seriously desired, except by intellectuals who have come under Western influences. In negro States like Liberia and San Domingo, where they have been tried, they have proved disastrous and almost ludicrous failures.But it may be replied that these two black republics are inhabited by inferior races. Have we any right to predicate inferiority of our Indian fellow-citizens ? Certainly I should commit myself to no such general statement. I doubt, indeed, whether any general statement can be made about the many races which inhabit India, except that they all belong to the genus&quot;llomo. There are some from the pre-historic Arian immigrants down to the last civil service clerk who belong to the most distinguished human breeds; and, whether they be specially qualified or not for that difficult form of social activity which we call Parliamentary Government, they at least possess great qualities of intellect and imagination.This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government,]
But does India as a whole possess the characteristics which would give Parliamentary Government a chance ? To me it seems that it does not. People often talk as if democracy produced equality. The truth is that democracy is only successful where equality  fundamental racial equality approximately exists already. Where racial differences are clear-cut and profound, where a race obviously superior is mixed with a race obviously inferior, the superior race may be constituted as a democracy, but into that democracy the inferior race will never be admitted^ It may be kept out by law, as in South Africa, or it may be kept out by practice, as in the Southern States of America; but kept out it will be.The problem of India, I admit, is not so simple. The lines of demarcation between races, even when they are emphasised by the system of caste, are not nearly so sharply marked as those which in America and Africa divide white from black. But per-onally I believe the differences are quite sufficient to make real Parliamentary institutions unworkable in the future, as they are admittedly unworkable in the present.The demand for them comes from Eastern intellectuals inspired by Western models. This does not make the demand less for-midable, but it does make the fulfilment of it much less likely to succeed. Parliamentary institutions in English-speaking countries are of natural and spontaneous growth. In India they would be utterly alien and artificial. Graft them upon the ancient and unchanging social system of the East, and you will produce a hybrid which will certainly be worthless and probably dangerous. Nor would education provide any sufficient remedy : for education cannot fundamentally alter the material on which it works, and it is the essential character and variety of that material which in India is the bar to political advance along the rather narrow and specialised lines which have been found to yield good results in England and America.To me, then, it appears that if we promise Self-Government we shall be promising something which, in the sense already defined, we neither can nor ought to give. A system under which India shall more and more be governed by Indians, we may well hope to develop. If it be thought that such a form of Government may properly be described as Self-Government (as perhaps it may) we might defend in this way the inclusion of the magic word in our statement of policy. But I greatly fear that this is not the sense in which it-would be understood by those to whom the formula is addressed, and, if so, they will have much cause to complain when its entire meaning becomes fully apparent.A. J. B.Foreign Office,August 7, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
