<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/11/19 images: 142-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  A ugust 1940.SECRET. , Copy No.W.P. (40) 339.August 29, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.THE MUNITIONS SITUATION.Note by the Minister of Supply.NOW that the special and considerable deficiencies in arms and ammunition,created by the losses on the Continent, have been made good to an appreciable extent, the time has come to put before my colleagues a reasoned statement on the munitions situation generally.HERBERT MORRISON.Ministry of Supply, W.C. 2,August 29, 1940.[21684a]

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNWIENT-PTinted for the War Cabinet.  August VdAQ.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (40) 339.August 29, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.THE MUNITIONS SITUATION.Memorandum by the Minister of Supply.I. *After two months.II. &quot;The Force against Us.III. Germany&apos;s War Potential.IV. Forces against Germany.V. -Our Programme of Guns and TanksVI. The Ammunition Programme.VIL-^Munitions from North America.VIII.-Raw Material.IX. Finding Labour.Summary.SINCE the beginning of June the supply of arms for the Army, which wasdesperately low two months ago, has greatly improved.But our present stock of weapons is trifling compared to the 15,000 to20,000 field guns and the equivalent other arms of Germany. Italy&apos;s equipment and the captures from France, Belgium and Britain make the disproportion still greater.Fortunately, these resources cannot be effectively used against Englandwithout the command of the sea; but the Middle East position must be a cause for anxiety.Germany&apos;s war potential, as measured by steel output though lessdisproportionate than her actual stock of land armaments is also much greaterthan ours unless we put into the scale the huge steel output of the United States.Germany&apos;s stock of arms is so enormous that she has no need to devote aserious proportion of her industrial capacity to the production of guns andammunition, and is free to devote her capacity to developing new forms of armament or to internal purposes.But though we cannot compete with Germany in sheer weight of metal in anear future, command of the sea and air may enable us to gain a considerablelocal superiority over Germany in particular parts of Europe or elsewhere. Wemust, therefore, assume that substantial land forces can be used and will be needed[21684] b
to bring victory. This means armoured vehicles and mobile guns reckoned in many thousands from the factories of England and America.We are planning to produce for the Army between now and the end of nextyear 5,000 field guns, 700 medium guns, 6,000 anti-tank guns, 5,000 anti-aircraft guns, over 50,000 Brens and 7,000 tanks.At the end of next year our output will be nearly equal to the peak outputof the last war in field artillery. It will be appreciably less in small arms, and very much less in medium and heavy artillery; but, on the other hand, it will bemuch greater in anti-aircraft guns, heavy and light the former corresponding in manufacturing capacity to medium artillery, and the latter to field guns. Theproduction of anti-tank and tank guns and of tanks will also be on a farhigher scale.The problem of ammunition is a very different one.The calculation of ammunition requirements on the basis of the &quot; siege &quot;conditions of 1914-18 may or may not be justified by events; but, even ifammunition is required on such a scale, it would be a misuse of resources and present a stupendous storage problem if we were to produce from now until theend of next year the full amount of ammunition that would in theory be fired bythe guns if they were in continuous action.We have therefore proposed a smaller production programme of completedammunition, which will afford an ample supply of ammunition for the guns asthey come forward. But, side by side with this, we shall have to provideammunition-producing capacity, which will enable us quickly to build up the ammunition supply to a full war basis if and when the occasion arises.The need for surplus capacity means that we must expect to have a largeproportion of our ammunition factories working at half capacity next year, thatwe must make provision in advance for expanding the labour supply in the factories when the time comes, and that we must build up a planned stock of emptyshell and components, explosives, shell steel and other raw materials.We have placed orders in North America (or shall have done when thequestion of types of field artillery and of tanks to be made in the United states is settled) both to complete the gaps in our own programme and to provide an insurance margin. When these orders materialise, we shall be spending oncompleted munitions much more in the United States and a little more in Canadathan in the last war.If these orders are to provide a genuine insurance, either the americans should let us order British types, or we should at some stage formally embodyAmerican-type weapons in the British Army&apos;? equipment. As our programme is so far ahead of that of America the former is preferable.The breaking down of our programme into raw material is not yet complete;but the figures quoted suggest that we need to accumulate a stock of at least a quarter of a million tons of shell steel, with other materials in proportion.The programme which is now being established will furnish some of theessential statistics for the proper functioning of whatever system of allocation orpriority may be adopted.As to labour, the large expansion needed will require the employment of agreat deal of female labour. But the requirements of the programme can alsobe modified by ordering a still larger proportion of such articles as mechanical transport vehicles in the United States and thus releasing men for tank orother work.The scientific control of both materials and labour requires much fullerstatistical information than we at present possess. The initial steps in thisdirection have been taken. The programme which has been formulated for thearmy provides a part of the essential information.Ministry of Supply, W.C. 2,August 29, 1940.
THE MUNITIONS SITUATIONSI. After Two Months.Ten weeks ago a miracle happened when the evacuation from Dunkirk savednearly a quarter of a million of England&apos;s sons and her best trained troops.The B.E.F., however, was compelled to leave behind practically the whole of itsfighting equipment, save some of its rifles.The losses of equipment in France included 880 fields guns, 310 guns ofheavier calibre, 276 heavy and 230 light A.A. guns, 852 Anti-Tank Guns, 6,400Anti-Tank rifles, 11,000 machine-guns, 408 light and 280 heavier tanks, nearly20,000 motor-cycles, 5,000 cars and 40,000 transport vehicles.In the England to which the Flanders army returned, the Units in formationwere in possession of some 100 18-pdrs., 240 25-pdrs. (of which all but 30 wereconverted 18-pdrs.), 200 4-5-inch Hows, and 136 heavier guns. In addition, therewere in ordnance depots some 120 guns of various calibres. For the older type of guns there was only a small supply of ammunition available, for they had notbeen expected to see active service again. The Army (excluding A.D.G.B. units)also had 8,000 Bren guns, 120 anti-tank guns and 4,000 anti-tank rifles. It isdifficult to believe that Hitler would have stayed his hand in June had he knownthe nakedness of the land.To-day, the Army is much better supplied though its steel clothing is a somewhat patchwork affair. During June and July our factories have completed and handed to the Army 275 new 25-pdrs., plus 250 converted 18/25&apos;s. Somehundreds of 18-pdrs., 4-5-inch Hows, and 6-inch Hows, have been renderedserviceable and issued to the troops, and these veterans of the last war have beenprovided with ammunition which, though not yet quite up to full standard,amounts to 1,300 rounds per gun for the 18-pdr., 312 for the 4-5-inch and 730for the 6-inch Hows. The 2-pdr, anti-tank equipments in the hands of the Armyhave risen from 120 to 580; while the stock of Bren guns and Anti-tank rifleswill soon have doubled.Finally, thanks to the prompt action of the American authorities in releasingarmy stocks, and to the fortunate fact that we have inherited the French shareof these &quot; releases,&quot; 820 75-mm. field guns with ammunition, 20,000 ground and2,600 tank machine guns, and 535,000 rifles have been sent from the United States.Nearly all of these weapons have arrived, and a large number of them have beenissued to troops. As, however, the small arms are of a different calibre to ourown and have only a limited amount of ammunition, they can only be issued tothe Home Guard or to fixed defensive points.Taking as an arbitrary standard the initial equipment of the 27 divisionsformed or in formation in this country at the end of June, the following table shows the improvement in the provision of certain arms during the last twomonths. &quot;Initial equipment&quot; is not, of course, all that is necessary for thefighting units, for they need also to hold reserves before going into action. Noris it suggested that the number of Army formations has been constant during these two months. But the table is presented in this form in order to showprogress in relation to the minimum standard equipment required by the numberof Units which happened to be in being on the 30th June : Initial Unit Equipment required by 27 divisions, 2 Armoured divisions, 7 Tankbrigades, Corps and, Army troops, A.A. Units, &amp;c.With troops at homoStandard. or in Ordnance Stores.End May. End July.Field Artillery (18-pdr., 25-pdr. and Per cent- Per cent.4-5-inch How.)       ......... 3,100 20* 52Bren guns        ............ 34,000 about 27 532-pdr. A.T. equipments ...... 2,600 U 22A.T. rifles        ............ 19,000 about 27 51* Note. The figures given in this paper are intended only to give a sense of scale to the picture here painted. Some of them are rough estimates and are incapable of verification.Others would take so long to check that to do so would delay the paper until it would have lostany practical value that it may possess.
It will, I think, be agreed that this represents a considerable achievementfor the brief period of two months.In certain cases the actual output would show bigger increases than thisif it had all remained at home; but some of it has had to be sent to our forces overseas.If all the 75-mm. guns sent from America should prove to be in good condition and were issued to the troops, they would provide a further 29 per cent,of the above standard of field artillery, making over 80 per cent, in all.,The rifle situation also has been improved by the American shipments. Butin this case the scope for further early progress is very limited. Broadly, it maybe said that the present army possesses its full equipment of rifles, although thenumber of men under arms is much greater than was expected at this date. Butthere are no appreciable reserves, and the raising of the Home Guard presented a problem which would have been insoluble without American help. The rifleswith the Home Guard amount roughly to about half their strength. As rapidly growing demands for rifles were not foreseen, there is a quite inadequate outputof new rifles in this country, and it cannot be increased substantially until new factories come into operation in the New Year.For similar reasons the capacity to produce SAA. has not increasedsufficiently to meet requirements, nor was it planned on a sufficient scale. Thefact that there has been no fighting for two months has, however, enabled a stock of SAA. to be accumulated which would make possible a quite heavy expendi-ture for the rest of the campaigning season.The Army also has plenty of 2-inch and some 3-inch mortars, but unfortunately the supply of ammunition is still very inadequate.The output of light tanks in the past two months has been small in relationto the losses in France, as production of these types has been slowed down. Butthe output of Cruiser and Infantry tanks has a little more than replaced the losses of these types. The stock now at home represents about two-thirds of the required establishment of the light variety; but the 400 tanks of heavier type area very modest fraction of the War Office programme.Nevertheless, taken as a whole, the arming of our troops at home hasimmensely improved. For this we have to thank the energy which managers and workers alike put into their war stroke when the crisis came in factoriesthroughout the country; the fortunate fact that the orders placed before and atthe outbreak of war were beginning to materialise in April and May and could bespeeded up; the promptness of the ordnance authorities in finding and furbishingup all kinds of old equipments; and last, but by no means least, the promptnessof the Americans in turning out and shipping a quite substantial armament whichhad survived from the last war.II. The Force Against Us.But the progress is not nearly enough. The munitions baby has doubled ortrebled its weight in a couple of months. Yet it is still a very small infantcompared with the giant that threatens to attack it.I suppose that Germany possesses from 15,000 to 20,000 field guns and alarge number of heavies, which I have no means of estimating. Every single oneof these pieces is a modern weapon, for her artillery of the last war was melteddown under the watchful eye of the Allied Disarmament Commission set up bythe Treaty of Versailles.She has now added to her own colossal armament the 5,000 or 6,000 75-mm.field guns and a proportionate amount of heavy artillery with their stocks of $ammunition which she has captured from the French, plus a sizeable make-weightcaptured from the British and Belgian Armies. She has also at her disposalFrance&apos;s anti-tank guns and other weapons. These were no match in number for germany&apos;s own armament, but they were on a far larger scale than our own.Germany has also added to her potential producing capacity, which alreadyincluded the Skoda works, the output of Creusot and a host of other armamentconcerns. If we add to this catalogue the artillery, tanks and other equipment of Italy, the total must amount to over one-half, and in the case of the more modern
weapons perhaps three-quarters, of the land armaments existing in the world to-day. By comparison, our 2,500 field guns and 500 tanks are very light weightindeed.Fortunately, Germany&apos;s great munition supplies cannot be directly mobilisedagainst this country unless Hitler can secure the command of the sea; and in anycase there is a limit to the armament that can be deployed on any single front.The morals of these figures are :  (1) That we cannot relax for one moment our effort to bring forward everygun, rifle or round of ammunition that we can lay our hands on duringthe next few months.(2) That if invasion comes we must, by hook or by crook, prevent Hitler fromgaining a sufficient foothold to enable him to turn on the tap of hisvast resources.I would add that the state of the equipment of our armies in the Middle East,which have only 200 or 300 field guns and 240 tanks, must give rise to anxiety.Fortunately, these armies, too, are defended by sea, sand and space.III.-Germany&apos;s War Potential.Before passing to our own long-range programme, a word more should besaid about the war potential of the enemy. I have no figures available that have any claim to accuracy about other countries&apos; armaments, but I imagine that theland armament of the great Powers three months ago, measured in terms of artillery, rifles and machine guns, would be in something like the followingratios : Germany ...      ... 20 Japan       ... ... 5Russia ...      ... 15 United Kingdom ... 3France ...      ... 10 United States ... italy ...... 6But these figures give no clue to potential armament production. In theabsence of much more elaborate statistics, which would have to include such factors as forging capacity, essential alloys and many other elements, a roughguide to industrial strength is furnished by steel output.Before the annexation of Czechoslovakia, the steel-making capacity of the reich was about 22 million long tons, per annum. The figures for the countriesnow under German control are as follows (the figure given is the highest recentyear, in most cases 1937) :  Million long tonsof ingot steel.Germany - - - ......France ...       ............ q RBelgium       ............... *\*Luxemburg............... * &quot;Czechoslovakia       ... - -Italy.................. i&apos;\Poland ......Total............ 42-5Moreover, three months ago, Germany was faced with a possible shortage ofore, which would have prevented full use of her steel-making capacity. This hasnow been remedied. Germany has a monopoly of Swedish ore (though with possible difficulties in winter transportation) and has gained access to the iron ore of Lorraine and, subject to transport difficulties, of Spain.Three months ago, the United Kingdom and France had a steel-making capacity of some 21 million tons, against Germany&apos;s 26 million tons. The Frenchcapacity is now lost to the Allies and the British steel industry is faced with difficulties in its supply of raw materials. The supply of steel which it is hoped to make available in the United Kingdom in the next twelve months is estimatedat a minimum of 15 million tons of ingot steel, or between 11 and 12 million tonsof finished steel, including substantial imports from the United States.
This gives a ratio of nearly three to one in favour of Germany.But to complete the picture, it should be added that in 1937 (a /)od year,but one in which capacity was even then not fully employed) the United Statesproduced more than 50,000,000 tons of steel. India, Australia and Canadaproduced between them a further 3-3 million tons.Finally, Russia in the last recorded year produced 12^ million tons.From these figures the following among other conclusions emerge : 1. Germany need no longer strain her every nerve to produce guns andammunition. It was no idle boast when Hitler said in his recentspeech that Germany had quickly replaced the relatively moderateamount of munitions that was expended in the battle of France.She is therefore in the position of being able to divert some ofher industrial capacity to any new forms of armament she may beable to devise; to improving internal conditions; or to developing the countries under her domination.2. The conquest of Europe will do a little to relieve the pressure of her supplies of alloy steel, either by the appropriation of stocks of alloysor by salvage from captured armaments; this junk will give her aconsiderable supply of copper and brass, and the occupation of western Europe may even do something to relieve her shortage ofsuch things as lubricating oil.3. It is very important to know on which side the war potential of Russia isto be thrown.IV. Forces against Germany.Our own army programme must be considered in the light of these facts.They mean that we cannot hope to compete for many years to come in sheerweight of land armament, and if this were the sole determining factor ourprospect of victory would be remote.But the figures mentioned are only some of the factors that affect the issueof the war.Germany&apos;s hold over- the countries under her sway depends on nothing butfear.   She will remain morally isolated in Europe.Hunger and the steady influence of sea power on the economic life of Europemay be expected slowly to undermine morale.We may hope to gain ascendancy in the air by the quality and quantity ofour pilots and machines.Finally, it should be possible to choose fields and conditions of battle in whichthe legend of the German army&apos;s invincibility can be broken. Once this isaccomplished there are strong hidden forces in Europe waiting to help throw offthe Hitler yoke.Yet we dare not assume that economic pressure or political discontent will suffice. It is extremely difficult.at this moment to attempt to foresee when wemay be called upon to do land fighting on a large scale; but it is hard to conceivea victorious end of the war without the employment of expeditionary forces insome form or another. The call may take the form of prolonged and growing warin Africa or the Middle East; we may find a starting point in the revolt of some european country; the opportunity may occur, when local air mastery has been achieved, of recapturing a bridge-head across the Channel or in the low countries, and thus placing ourselves in a better position for carrying the airwar into the enemy&apos;s country.If the last of these suggestions comes within the bounds of possibility, it means that we must be able to concentrate artillery and tanks in numberscomparable to those which the Germans can concentrate in a similar limited area.This means armoured vehicles and mobile guns reckoned in many thousands, andto achieve this the combined output of England and America is essential.We do not yet know whether the man-power, which.must ultimately inflicta military defeat on Hitler&apos;s armies, will be British, American, French, &quot;Scandinavian-scandinavian, Czechoslovakian, or even rebel German. But the material, and the shotand shell to feed it, must be available when the time comes. Even though in pureweight of metal Germany may remain supreme, it is necessary that there should
be somewhere in the world a munition-producing capacity which is not purelyderisory compared with that of Germany.Our plans, also, should not overlook the possibility that smuggled arms,i.e., small arms of a suitable type, may play an important role.: V. Our Programme of Guns and Tanks.The decision of the Defence Committee of the Cabinet is that we should provide equipment in sufficient quantities to enable the Army to be raised to a strength of 55 divisions by the end of next year, to provide for the maintenance in action of some part of that force in the intervening period, and to have capacity in being or sources of production available by that date sufficient to maintain55 divisions in action.In the light of so many uncertainties, however, it is not very profitable tothink too rigidly in terms of divisions. What is essential is that we should develop capacity for producing more and more weapons, and that this should goto the limit compatible with other needs of equal, or in some cases of greater,urgency.I speak of weapons because the problems of weapons and of ammunition are,under present conditions, very different ones. The ammunition problem will bereferred to separately below.Forecasts have recently been forwarded to the War Office forecastingdeliveries month by month or quarter by quarter until the end of 1941. Theyindicate that, in the case of most of the important weapons with the exceptionof anti-tank guns and A.T. rifles -we shall have ready the initial equipment for55 divisions in advance of December 1941. provided : (a) Our munition factories are not bombed too disastrously.(b) There is no heavy wastage as the result of fighting in the meantime.If there is fighting and there are important losses, the date at whichwe could complete the initial equipment of 55 divisions would be correspondingly delayed.(c) Labour and materials are available.If these conditions are fulfilled we shall in 1942 have a capacity well in excessof that required to maintain the weapons of 55 divisions, and could thereforecontemplate a further increase in the Army thereafter provided wastage and theexpenditure of ammunition were not on too high a scale.These forecasts envisage the following production between now and the1st December, 1941 : Field Artillery ...Medium ArtilleryA.T. EquipmentsTanks : Light,,      Light CruisersHeavy  ...A. A. Guns : HeavyLightBren GunsA.T. RiflesFour months to Dee. 1,1940.750507506019343930051010,0006,000Twelve months to Deo.1941.4,1006505,2001,2001.1033,9001,1123,00043,50022,000Total.4.8507005,9501,2601,2964,3301.412&apos;3.51053,50028,000These figures only include a small number of deliveries from our American orders and will be exceeded if production in North America can be speeded up and ourown production is not seriously interfered with by enemy action.We must not, however, count on the above figures too confidently; for wastagein subsidiary theatres of war and loss of production at home through enemy actionare both probable even certain events. It is for this reason that large orders have been placed as an insurance in the United States and Canada. The Americanprogramme is discussed in Section VII of this paper.Is the scale of our preparations adequate? To this there is no simple answer.But some light on the degree to which our resources will be fully extendedmay be thrown by a comparison with the peak production of weapons in the
last war. This scale of output ultimately equipped and maintained the 96divisions which comprised the British forces at the end of 1918, as well asfurnishing the heavy artillery which was used by the American Army in France.Actual MonthlyHome Output, Expected Monthly Home Output,Spring 1918. November 1941.Field guns    (18-pdr., 4-5-in. Howitzer, &amp;e.) (25-pdr.)Guns         ............                534* 450 (barrels)Carriages............                 840 370Medium           ...     (60-pdr. 6-in. Howitzer) (4-5-in. gun and 5-5-in. gunHowitzer)Equipments        .....        ...                 160f 66Heavy    ...    (6-in. gun, 8-in. Howitzer, &amp;c.)        64 (7-in., 8-in. or 9-2-in.) a fewA.A. guns Light        ............             None (Bofors)      270Heavy       ......      (13-pdr. to 4-in.)        45 (3-7)      102$A.T. and T. guns        ...        (chiefly 6-pdr.)      285 (2-pdr.)   1,130Machine guns............             11,000 4,750gRifles    ...............            98,000 60,000Tanks    ...      ............                170 620* In addition 180 repaired gun bodies and 48 repaired carriages.-f In addition 45 new gun bodies, 155 repaired gun bodies and 35 repaired carriages.$ The production of 3 - 7-in A. A. guns, carriages and instruments is not comparable withthe production of A.A. guns in 1918, since the nature of their equipment involves far greatermanufacturing difficulties. Moreover, in addition to the figures in the table, we shall be makinga large number of spare barrels.g Bren guns only-excluding machine guns for the R.A.F. and for tanks and A.T. rifles.This table is not in any sense a comparison of the nation&apos;s war effort thenand now. That effort has to supply all three services. In order to make such a comparison we should have to include our output of much more elaborate fightingaircraft with its much greater call on labour, plant and materials (andincidentally add in the machine guns manufactured by M.A.P.) and balance thisagainst the smaller output of ammunition. But we should also note that ourpopulation aged 18 to 65 includes 3 million more males and 3 million more- females than 25 years ago, and that our industrial capacity (steel, for example)has increased very considerably. The table simply compares the scale on whichweapons are being supplied to the Army.The significant differences in equipment brought out by the table are the much greater number of tanks and armoured vehicles we shall provide this time,the need for a swarm of Anti-tank guns and a much smaller output of medium and heavy artillery and Small Arms.*The figures show that, whereas the factories turned out much more heavy artillery in the last war than we are contemplating in this and that we producedas many field guns 25 years ago as we now propose to do, this is offset by agreater production of anti-aircraft and anti-tank guns. In particular, thematerial required for the Air defence of Great Britain is out of all proportion to the needs of 1914-18. But even allowing for these differences, the figures ofthe present programme do not look excessive compared with what we did before,and they could probably be further increased were it not for certain limitingfactors. The limits on the side of labour are not labour in the bulk, but skilled labour-though the experience of the last war showed that it is possible to diluteand upgrade even on gun and carriage making. An equally serious limitationI is the difficulty in expanding capacity,.for jmaking gun and other forgings. It&apos;l is unsatisfactory to have to say that on account&quot;of a lack of forging capacity we may have either offensive weapons or anti-aircraft guns all over the country but[IS not both.Lastly, the fulfilment of the tank programme is only assured so long as theAdmiralty building programme is held up. Now is the time to consider whether we may not need armour for both vehicles and ships in 1942. At that dateAmerica may not be able to help us if in the meantime Congress has decided thatit must have both an Atlantic and a Pacific fleet.* So far are we from being a nation in arms that with a male population of over 10,000,000aged 20 to.49, we only possess about 2 million rifles and shall make only another half million or so before the end of next year; we shall have less than 100,000 land machine guns by December1941 and have only ordered 60,000 Tommy guns in the U.S.A.
sVI. The Ammunition Programme.If the problem of equipping the Army is to produce as many weapons as wepossibly can, the ammunition problem is to supply an ample, but at the same timereasonable, amount of ammunition for the guns in existence at a time when mostof them are in fact not firing.The War Office programme is built up in part on an initial equipment forthe guns which are delivered to them, and in part on the assumption thatultimately they will, in fact, be firing at a rate based on the experience in thelast war.It is open to question whether the number of rounds per gun per day firedin 1918 is the right test for the present war. Those rates of fire were reachedunder conditions of &quot; siege &quot; warfare--with railway as well as road communi-cations behind the line for bringing up-great quantities of ammunition to moreor less fixed positions. If the war for which we have to prepare proves to be ofa more mobile character, it is by no means certain that the big supplies ofammunition which we propose to provide could ever get to the guns. On theother hand, if we have to contemplate &quot;siege&quot; warfare as a possibility, it is arguable that we may need a higher percentage of heavy and long-range artillery.But whatever may be the assumptions underlying the programme, theMinistry of Supply is, in fact, arranging to provide ammunition on a high basisof expenditure for the guns which will be available to put into the field.Yet in view of the probability that the artillery produced will not, in fact,fire their official ration during the current year and may not even do so in 1941,it would be unreasonable, and would, in fact, present a stupendous storageproblem, if we were to produce from now until the end of next year the full amount of ammunition that would, in fact, be fired if the guns were in action,and, in addition, have in being a capacity to repeat this output in 1942. Thecolossal stock that would be accumulated, plus the enormous supply envisaged in the War Office demands for 1942, could not be handled in any foreseeableconditions.On the other hand, it would not be sensible to work rapidly up to theexpenditure required by a 55-division army, then to stop production and expect to start up again if war conditions required it.We therefore have to plan the double task on the one hand of producingan ample supply of ammunition for the guns as they come forward, and on theother of having ready a capacity to produce, at comparatively short notice, the ammunition which the guns can fire.. The War Office have not asked that in the building up period the guns should .be provided with full wartime expenditure, and a project has been sent to the IWar Office which is calculated to provide the &apos;&apos; ample supply &apos;&apos; mentioned in thelast paragraph.  To go far beyond this is not only impossible from a storage pointof view, but will use up steel and other materials which, at the moment, can be far more usefully employed in other ways.To show the scale of the problem, the programme of actual manufacturewill produce 38 million complete rounds of ammunition of all natures in 1941,which, with the production of the present year, will give a grand total at the endof next year of 48 million rounds (some of the A.A.. will of course have beenfired). If there is no fighting in Europe before that date, the deduction orexpenditure in other theatres of war would be a comparatively modest proportionof this total. Storage accommodation must therefore be provided for something like this last figure of completed rounds of ammunition.At the end of next year we shall be producing 3 - 7 million rounds per month,but must have a manufacturing capacity (including imports of complete rounds)sufficient to provide 8 - 3 millions a month.The statistics of the last war show that in 1917, when shell productionreached its peak, the total output of complete rounds was 88 million. In thesame year 68 million rounds were fired on the Western Front and many millions in other theatres of war. By Christmas 1917 some 12.millions were in stock athome or abroad; this figure being substantially higher than at.Christmas 1916,and it was in fact considered safe to slack off shell production in the early partof 1918. Indeed, the output in the last year of war never reached the top figuresof the summer of 1917.
The fact that our ammunition output is likely for a time to be so much lessthan that of the last war has an important bearing on the nature of our war effort next year.It was the munitions programme of 1915, and in particular the manufactureof empty shell, cartridge cases, primers and fuses, which brought into the greatmunitions drive so many small firms all over the country. It is much more difficultto-day to employ Tom, Dick and Harry on the much more complex task of makingguns and the other complex articles of precision. It will therefore be less possibleto distribute the work among a number of factories of modest size, and it willbe more necessary to move skilled or semi-skilled labour, and to some extentmachinery, to the ordnance factories or the larger factories of main contractors.We must consequently be prepared to face the dissatisfaction that will arise whenit is discovered that there are not orders for all and sundry and the social problems involved in moving men away from their homes.These very real difficulties can perhaps to some extent be relieved bycontinuous pressure to simplify the design of weapons from the production pointof view and by efforts to split up and make plans for producing in small factoriesthe more simple components of complex mechanism.At the best, however, there will be inevitable disappointments unless thereis some quite unexpected development of simple fighting equipments.Another difficult problem is set by the need of preparing capacity muchgreater than that which is actually being used. This can only be done by adopting the single shift system to which Germany resorted in the years before the warin building up her aircraft strength or by running day and night shifts at halfcapacity in order to have the organisation for full output in running order.This plan, however, requires that arrangements should be made, by enrolmentor alternative team work in the factories, to have a sufficient labour force availablefor full output.If this general expectation is realised, the Minister of Labour should considerwhether effective use in some other directions could be made in the meantime ofthe labour which will, under this scheme, be enrolled for but not continuouslyengaged in producing or filling gun ammunition.This scheme requires that reserves should be built up of say two monthsstock of empty shell and other components, as well as a stock of shell steel, brass,&amp;c. For without these reserves it would not be possible to beat up at short notice the full production that may be needed.VII. Munitions from North America.Before discussing the programme outlined in terms of labour and material,I would consider what role may be played by supplies from North America.I am not now^concerned with the dollar problem. On the 30th June last, theBritish Ambassador in Washington was instructed to approach the United states administration on the general principles applicable to the assistance which wewere seeking in America.  The instructions sent to Lord Lothian stated that: &quot; So long as the gold and other foreign assets at our disposal permit,we shall, of course, continue to pay cash for essential armaments, rawmaterials, and food-stuffs, but we desire to impress upon the administration in the clearest possible manner the utter impossibility of our continuing todo this for any indefinite period in view of the scale on which we shall need to obtain such resources from the United States. Our immediate anxietyarises from the necessity of entering into long-term contracts.&quot;It is outside the province of this paper to consider how this financial question will be solved; but in the meantime the Ministry has been acting on the instructionof the Defence Committee of the Cabinet, which on the 19th June authorised the placing of supplementary orders in North America in addition to those orders which would be required in any case to complete the programme. 1 hese supple-mentary orders are designed to meet &quot; the danger of interruption of output inthis country clS cl result of enemy action.&quot;
No definite rule was laid down as to the scale of these insurance orders. Thedecision merely stated that &quot; if the Ministry anticipated a reduction of UnitedKingdom output through air-raids in the next eighteen months by say 20 per cent.,the North American production aimed at by Z 4- 27 should be increased by acorresponding amount.&quot; In other words, the ratio is left to the discretion, of theMinistry. In putting forward their proposals, therefore, Departments have beenasked to take into account the nature of the product, the extent to which itsproduction at home is concentrated in one or dispersed in many factories andlocalities, the period of time likely to be taken up in repairing damage, and theimportance of the commodity in the munition programme as a whole.The insurance principle will not apply to any important extent to clothing,engineering stores, &amp;e, where there are a great variety of possible producers athome, but in the case of important armaments the percentage may run as high as 25 per cent, to 35 per cent.This instruction, together with the need of filling certain gaps in our own production, is responsible for the placing or the negotiation of orders estimatedat  54 millions in Canada and  110 millions in the United States. The latter figure includes  10 millions for surplus Army stocks and  17 millions for machine tools. To this we must add  46 millions for the orders for field guns and certain other items which have still to be negotiated in order to complete requirements,some  30 millions or more for Tanks, and, say  50 millions for field gun ammunition.It is impossible to forecast what proportion of these orders will be deliveredfrom North America before the end of next year; but if they were all to be delivered before December 1941 it would mean a rate of delivery of finished munitions from the United States greatly in excess of the corresponding figure for the last war, but not so far ahead for Canada.The deliveries under these contracts have only been taken into account to alimited extent in estimating the supplies available by the end of 1941; for american production is comparatively new, and we cannot yet tell what willhappen to our orders when Americans own defence programme is fully launched.We hope that the American authorities will put a common drive behind bothprogrammes, and indeed they have already set their face against competitiveproduction to the extent of prohibiting new orders except such as are approvedby the Defence Board.If, therefore, we are to get a substantial output from the United States,we must either (a) adopt a common type of weapon and share in a jointprogramme, or (6) get the goodwill of the Americans in helping forward such orders of British type as they agree should run parallel with their own orders.These considerations particularly affect field guns and tanks. In the caseof tanks, there is a possibility that we may be able to persuade the american authorities to agree to modify their own new design in the direction desired by our military authorities in regard to such matters as armour and armament, andthat we may share in a joint output. There is less prospect of agreement inregard to the field gun.It would appear that, in this matter of field artillery, the Americans are determined to produce 105-mm. Hows, as the standard infantry weapon. We, onthe other hand, have gone so far or by the end of 1941 shall have gone so far in equipping the Army with the 25-pclr., that it would be folly to contemplate a deliberate change over to an American type at a late stage in our equipment. the argument for being allowed to order 25-pdrs. as an insurance in the United states is a very strong one. If our own production were imperilled, it is not a genuineinsurance to have to make good the deficiencies by importing a new type of-&quot;weapon. It would be extremely difficult to change over if our troops mere actually in the field, and a new weapon means not merely substituting the firing pieceitself, but supplying ammunition, sights and all the ancillaries. Our own production for supplying all the composite items which make up the completearmament would be rendered useless by introducing a new calibre of weapon. in short, insurance means, not an entirely different type (of equipment, but thepossibility of obtaining from another source a reserve supply of all the itemsthat go to make up our own.Next year in the winter of 1941, when our own production should be in fullflight, and we shall -already possess from 5,000 to 6,009 25-pdr. equipments,American production will just be starting.
The only satisfactory way in which another type could become a realinsurance for our own artillery would be to incorporate it on a percentage basis in the standard equipment of the British Army and to start a small productionof the gun, ammunition and ancillaries in this country in parallel to our ownoutput, for repair, spares, &amp;c, in case supplies from overseas were temporarilyinterrupted. This would, however, complicate and certainly reduce for a time atleast our total output, and in view of the preceding figures, the early stage of american plans and the moderate scale on which they are launching their newweapon, it would be unwise to commit ourselves to this policy now.In view of the uncertain date of delivery of American supplies, it may beasked what prospect there is that these orders will provide a genuine insurancewithin a reasonable time. It has been recalled that in the last war the american army, through delay in deciding to adopt types of artillery already in the field,did not in fact substantially contribute through their great munition programme to the fighting power of the American troops in the field.If, however, we only look at this side of the story we get a false impression.The Americans entered the war in 1917, with the great advantage of havingmanufactured on a large scale almost all forms of munitions for the French andBritish Armies. They failed to get a flying start owing to hesitation and awrong initial decision about types. But the record of America&apos;s munition effortshows that though, for the reasons mentioned, their output was too late to influence the events of 1918, the momentum of their production was tremendousand produced big results in the latter part of 1918. In 1917, America&apos;s productionof her own Army&apos;s requirements was negligible. In 1918 it amounted to thefollowing figures :  -Rifles: 2,390,000.Machine Guns : 220,000.SAA. (April 1917 to November 1918) : 3,500 million rounds.Artillery Equipments : 2,078 (1,000 in last 3 months).Artillery Ammunition :  19 million rounds (8 million in last 3 months).These figures, together with those in Section V comparing our present planned output with that of the last war, bring out the small scale on which weare proposing to produce small arms.America does not start this time with munition factories in being; nor isshe as yet under the pressure of actually being at war; but if the drive behindproduction is comparable to that of 1917, American munitions can be a factor ofenormous importance if the war continues into 1942.By that time it may well be that America will be ready to play a more active part in the war. If so, and if our own home orders have come forward accordingto plan, the American production will not be wasted, for our joint supply ofmunitions will be available to equip very large forces indeed.I would add that whether we have to bring over America&apos;s supplies for ourown use, or whether American man-power is used on a considerable scale inEurope, the building up of an American munitions output which may be usedoutside the American continent involves the use of shipping on a great scale. Inthe last war, when no less than 306,000 soldiers with their equipment were broughtto Europe in a single month, half of the big tonnage required was British, but most of the rest came in American ships. In order to tackle this transportproblem the Americans embarked on a vast ship-building programme. Oneproject alone the Hog Island scheme was planned to produce 3 million tonsof new ships a year. It actually produced nearly 1^ million tons in 12 months a figure which exceeds our present output of merchant shipping from all british yards.The present tonnage of ships available for this country is fairly abundant,but we must beware of assuming that this condition may continue indefinitely.It is perhaps politically difficult at the moment for the Americans to plan to carry the goods and possibly the men also as well as to produce munitions.But sea transport is of crucial importance if our strategic conception is that ofGreat Britain and the United States providing the means to fight the world&apos;sbattle for freedom from countries and at points of conflict scattered all over theglobe.   The ship-building programmes must not be overlooked.
i&apos;6VIII.-Raw Material.I return to our Munitions programme.The figures of our prospective output during the next 16 months require for their fulfilment adequate raw material and labour. Estimates of what theprogramme will involve in these two respects are being prepared. I will onlyadd here certain very general comments.The task of preparing for war on a great scale but with the possibility that for considerable periods there may be no substantial expenditure ofammunition, presents the problem, referred to on a previous page, of providingnot only storage, but productive capacity well&apos; in excess of actual production.Moreover, the fact that we are not asked to provide heavy artillery on the sames cale as before means that the tonnage of ammunition manufactured will, in anycase, not be as great as in the last war.In 1916 1^ million tons of shell steel were used for the shell programme.In 1917 this rose to nearly 2^ million tons, and in 1918 it fell back to rather less than If million tons.The programme of actual ammunition output in 1941 will absorb 840,000 tonsof shell steel. But to provide for a war rate of expenditure--on the 36 divisionbasis, which should be available by mid-1941, will absorb steel at the rate ofapproximately 1\ million tons a year and on a 55 division basis at 2 million tons.But in this latter figure there are margins of excessive demand, particularly inthe assumed rate of anti-aircraft fire; and if one may venture a guess it is unlikely that in the present war we shall see ammunition expenditure at a rate which will absorb more than 1^ million tons a year unless unexpected developmentsbring about siege warfare on a very extended scale.These figures suggest certain definite conclusions.In the first place it is evident that if the Army Council agrees to theprogramme of ammunition production that has been put forward there must beprovided behind the army stock not only a reserve capacity of production and astock of empty shell and components, but also a substantial stock of shell steel and all the other materials needed in ammunition production. In the case ofshell steel the amount of this stock at the end of next year should certainly notbe less than \ million tons, and should be built up to a higher figure if circum-stances, in the meantime, seem to make it desirable. Other material stocks shouldbe in proportion.Secondly, the basis of the ammunition demand is of very great importance from the point of view of the best use of our resources. If, for example, theWar Office should decide that under modern conditions 30, instead of 36, roundsa gun a day for field guns, with a corresponding reduction for other types, is asufficient ration under war conditions, the saving in the steel which we should need to earmark in 1942 would be sufficient to provide all the steel needed by theMinistry of Aircraft Production for six months at their current rate of output.Material, however, is not only a question of bulk supply, but also of f orgings,stampings, alloy steel, plates, or whatever it may be.At the moment many of the programmes are limited by the supply ofparticular forms of material, and it would seem that preparation for supplyingthese products has not been made on nearly a broad enough basis. comparison of the total need of forgings with the supply would certainly show that it is an urgent matter to increase forging capacity though something might be achieved by ensuring that our capacity is fully Used.Whatever precautions may be taken, there will always be bottle-necks, anduntil they can be cleared priority or other machinery must be brought intooperation to ensure the harmonious flow of production. Simple priority underwhich requirement &quot;X&quot; is fully met before requirement &quot; Y &quot; gets anythingis clearly unsound. The more intelligent way is to allocate an appropriate&apos;&apos;proportion of material to all requirements. There is, however, one way on whicAalone the principle of allocation can be successfully applied, and that is that the Arbitrator, whoever he may be, has an adequate statistical basis for his decision.Such a basis must include (a) Requirements the basis of which the arbitrator must be entitled tofscrutinise.(b) Current consumption of materials analysed in detail.(c) Stocks.
Without adequate statistics on these points priority rulings must inevitably be largely of the hit-and-miss order. It cannot be too strongly emphasised thatin a planned economy statistics must fill the role that competition plays in a freeeconomy-. And whether we like it or not, a planned economy is the only possibleone in wartime.IX. Finding Labour.Finally, labour.It has not yet been possible to estimate what the Army programme may mean in additional labour on munitions. The increase will certainly be large. But,apart from figures, there are certain general propositions that may be set out.The first is that emphasis on weapons rather than on ammunition means thatour bulk demand will be less than it was in the last war. On the other hand, weshall want a larger proportion of skilled labour.The demand for skilled men, however, may be modified by suitable measures.The munition production of the present war has been nurtured in the atmosphere of the pre-war peace, in which Treasury control and the need for economy made it necessary for Supply departments to attach importance to methods ofproduction which saved labour by modern specialised machinery.The Stewart and Lloyd&apos;s shell shop near Birmingham, for example, has awonderful display of machine tools-some of them taking several cuts at once which turn out shell with surprising rapidity and at a cheap rate. But on theoccasion of a visit to the factory some three months ago, there was scarcely afemale worker to be seen. If you could make the same number of shells in a shopfitted with general purpose lathes and employing women to five times the number,it would be a wartime economy though the shell might cost a little more-to do this and use the skilled men for making tanks or guns.Moreover, even on the more complex jobs, the experience of firms who have seriously set about it is that you can train semi-skilled labour or women for such work. The way has been shown by pioneers. The task of equipping the british army will only be carried through if their example is followed universally.Again, in this matter of making the best use of our labour, we may go fartherthan we have already gone in developing American supplies of commodities whichthe United States can produce quickly. For example, at the moment we are planning to produce in Great Britain something like 150,000 specialisedmechanical vehicles for the Army in a year.. There is no reason why a large partof these requirements should not be bought from the United States if they cannotbe requisitioned here. If that were done large numbers of skilled men would beavailable for the tank or other programmes, ;and the scarcity of drop forgings,which is worrying every Supply department at the moment, would largelydisappear.Finally, I would add that, without statistics of the movements of labour andan analysis of their employment, the planning of the full and most effective useof our labour force must be as much a groping in the dark as a priority systemwithout adequate statistics. We have not, as yet, the apparatus for keeping a close statistical check on the employment of our labour supply ;and on itsmovements. One of the purposes of this memorandum is to give a sense of proportion and so help in preparing the way for a more precise planning of theuse of our labour and material resources.



</content>
</cab>
