<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/188/0 images: 129-166</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
, 10330THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT. SECRET. CABINET.CP.220/27.       THE CO-ORDINATION OF LONDON TRAFFIC aGSSCIES.MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF TRANSPORT. INTRODUCTORY. &apos;I circulate herewith a copy of the Report of the London Traffic Advisory Committee on the Co-ordination of Passenger Transport Facilities in the London Traffic Area, which is dated 27th July, 1927.   It is signed by sixteen out of nineteen of the members.   Mr* K.E.Chalmers (representing the County Councils of Kent and Surrey) has been ill and is, therefore, not in a position to sign the report but has added a note indicating his general concurrence.   Sir Herbert Walker (representing the Railway Corapanie Association) has affixed a note stating that he is unable to sign the report &quot;because the kain Line Companies and the Metropolitan Railway Company, whose interests may be seriously involved if the report is given effect to, have not been consulted&quot; and because, as their representative, he feels &quot;that they should be left with an entirely free hand to take what steps they may consider necessary to protect their interests when they become aware of the varying recommendations contained in the report&quot;.   Sir Charles Cleveland (one of the representatives of the interests of persons providing means of transport) also dissents on the ground that, while he recognises that important changes in existing traffic arrangements are necessary, the scheme is, in his opinion, unsuitable, . impracticable and unfair to the independent omnibus proprietors whom he specially represents and that they will wish to reserve to themselves a right of protest.1.     The problem of some greater co-ordination of transport services in London is urgent and it is in my opinion necessary that the Government should consider certain aspects of this matter at once.
2.     The London Traffic Act of 1924, gave power to the Minister of Transport to restrict the number of omnibuses plying for hire on selected streets where he considered that among other reasons the existence of alternative facilities for the conveyance of passengers along the street or in proximity thereto, or an excess of omnibus accommodation alone the street, made it desirable to take this course.   Alternative facilities include tramways, tube railways and the suburban services of the main lines.The position was first stabilised and then regulations providing for an actual reduction in the number of omnibuses plying for hire on certain routes were made early last year. Their validity was challenged, and while important points of principle were awaiting the decision of the High Court I did not feel justified in pursuing the policy of reducing omnibus services, but these difficulties have now been removed and, with the Prime Minister*s approval, I have asked the Committee to submit any further proposals which they may think desirable -with regard to the removal of redundant omnibuses engaged in merely wasteful competition.   At the same time, there is a concensus of opinion that exercise of the powers conferred upon me by the Act of 1924 will not provide a solution of the London Traffio problem, and that further co-ordination of the passenger transport agencies in London will be required if the facilities which the growth and spread of the population demand aro to be afforded.3.     In their Kepo^t of the 17th March, 1926, upon travelling facilities to and from North and North-East London, the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee reported as follows:-
&quot;Finally, the Committee desire to add that they have been impressed by the contention of the representatives of the railway companies and the managements of the tramway undertakings that the main difficulty in the way of the provision of additional &quot;through&quot; facilities is the acute and wasteful competition between the various passenger transport agencies operating in the area.The proposals submitted by Mr. Frank Pick, on behalf of the Underground Group of Hallways and the London General Omnibus Company, for the establishment of a common management and a common fund, appear to the Committee to present a possible solution of the whole problex of London passenger transport, and they recommend that these proposals should he carefully examined with the least possible delay.The Committee would be prepared to undertake this examination and report thereon tci the Minister, but as these proposals may be thought bo be outside the terms of reference, the Committee feel that before they proceed to give f tort her consideration to the matter the iiinister * s concurrence to their doing so should be sought and obtained&quot;.In view of this recommendation, I asked theCommittee by minute of the 19th April, 1926, to arrangefor the Sub-Committee which held the Inquiry upon whichthe Iteport was based or for some other Sub-Commit tee to&quot;discuss with the Companies and Municipalities engaged inthe operation of transport undertakings in the London areawhether any further co-operation or combined action ispossible or desirable&quot;.4.     It is in pursuance of the Committee1 s investigationalong these lines that the present report is submitted.   TheCommittee point out (paragraph 12) that, while they have hadno formal negotiations with any of the undertakers, informal-discussions have proceeded far enough to justify an expectation that the main interests concerned would agree upon a scheme for common management and a pooling of resources if the Governmentwere prepared to let it be known that they would approve inprinciple a scheme of this kind and be willing to &quot;promote orsupport&quot; the legislation necessary to enforce it.
5.      Behind the opinion of this representative Committee, there is a widespread feeling that some advance along these lines is essential if London^ traffic difficulties are to be solved.   I need only oall attention to the pamphlet recently issued by the Labour Party advocating the establishment of a new joint municipal traffic authority consisting of the County and County Borough Councils in the London Traffic Area to which all existing powers of control and the present privately-owned concerns (except the suburban services of the main line railways) should be transferred.   This no doubt would secure complete co-ordination of London passenger services but by means of complete public ownership   and operation.6.     The scheme now proposed is of quite a different character. It rejects the idea of any new authority and of any change in existing ownerships (apart from the possible absorption of the smaller omnibus proprietors), and aims at establishing unified operation and a common financial interest through the institution of a Common Fund which should not be interfered with, except by agreement, for a period of 42 years.Scope of Spheme recommenced by Advisory Committee.V.     Before the nature of the scheme is further explained, it may be well to enumerate the undertakings which would naturally fall within its scope.   The Passenger Transport Agencies in the London area other than the trunk railways are as follows:-(a) The London County Council as tramway undertakers *(b) Other tramway undertakings owned by local authorities,of which there are several.(c) Certain tramways owned or controlled by the UndergroundGroup, which are statutory undertakings.(d) The four Electric Railways in the underground Group,whioh are already managed as one concern and are statutory undertakings.(e) The London General Omnibus Company and allied companies,whioh are not statutory undertakings.(f) About 400 omnibuses owned &quot;independently&quot; also notstatutory undertakings.(g) The Metropolitan Railway.
The four Electric Railways, the London General Omnibus Company and allied Companies and the tramways in Group (c) form what is known as the &quot;Combine&quot; and are all controlled by the Underground Electric Railway Company of London, which owns the greater part of the Common Stock, andJLs &amp; finance or holding Company * not subject to statutory control.It is hoped that the scheme would in principle be readily accepted by most, if not all, of the municipal tramways, but it may be necessary to apply compulsory powers in order to bring In some of the municipal tramways and certain of the independent omnibus proprietors.     The position of the Metropolitan Railway may require special consideration.   Power would be taken to enable the undertakings coming within the scheme to enter into voluntary agreements with the Main Line Companies for the provision of through services, for the allocation of traffic and pooling of receipts and for the leasing and* or working of any of the suburban lines of the main line companies by an undertaking or group of undertakings in the scheme. Common Management.8.     Unified operation is essential to maxlmun efficiency. The Committee leave open for the present the exact constitution of the common management, but contemplate that executive control will be vested either in a single general manager or in a small board, consisting of the general managers or corresponding officers of the larger undertakings.     It will, however, be observed that the Committee consider that common management on these lines would only be practicable If it is agreed and they appear to contemplate that in the last resort certain \indertakers while brought compulsorily into the Common Fvmd might be left free as to their management, subject to adequate safeguards for other parties to the Fund.
jSxtent of regulation and control by Transport Department*9*    As It is desired to avoid the creation of any new public authority it is suggested by the Committee that the necessary regulation and control of the Transport agencies to be brought Into the Common Fund should be exercised through the Minister responsible for Transport after reference to the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee *   The object of regulation and control would be to secure, so far as possible, (a) reasonable fares, (b) adequate services, and (c) new develop-raents.The main functions to be exercised would be(a)   the determination of questions of general transport policy and development and in particular what new facilities a.?e required, by what agency they should be provided, and how the additional capital required can most advantageously be obtained;(b) the approval of the level of fares to be charged from time to time, in accordance with some general basis (which would presumablybe laid down In the Act and would be aimed at enabling the undertakings to meet their necessary expenses of working and management, and fixed charges, together with a reasonable return on share capital) and to ensure the provision of adequate servioesj(c) the determination of questions affecting the Common Management and the Common Fund upon which the parties might fail to agree* This could probably in many cases be done by appointing an arbitrator.It is proposed to give to Local Authorities in thearea   a right to make application to the Minister in respectof (a) and (b), and the Minister would save to be given power to make the necessary orders and to be armed with adequate powers for requiring and obtaining from the undertakings all necessary Information *
It ia, of course, of the essence of the scheme to prevent the establishment of new agencies which would conflict with the general plan and to this end the Committee propose that no omnibus licences should be Issued except with the consent of the Minister and on such terms and conditions as he may direct, after reference to the Advisory Committee.Common Fund.10.     The balance of the gross revenue of each undertaking, after meeting proper charges to revenue, including provisions   I for maintenance and fixed charges (to be defined), would be paid into a Common Fund.   Generally speaking, If the revenue, of any party did. not suffice to meet these charges, the deficiency would be made good out of the Fund, and the balance remaining in the Common Fund would then be divided among the several parties in some proportion which would be laid down by the Act.   It is contemplated that this proportion might be based upon the proportion in which each undertaking would have contributed to the Common Fund in a standard year. Provision would also have to be made for the division of Isurplus earnings.The financial basis of the scheme will require carefulconsideration.     The treatment of the municipal capital is one problem.     The basis and the rate of the remuneration of the share capital of the other undertakings is another.
It Is essential that it should be possible to raise capital for further tube extensions on reasonable terms and on this ground it is suggested by the Committee that the level of fares should be such as to meet the full interest on all preference stocks, which are treated as prior chargestocks, and to give a reasonable rate of return on ordinary capital.   It Is further suggested that this rate should be that which would be necessary to attract new ordinary capital at par.   At this point I need only aay that I do not think that determination of the ranking capital or the returns upon capital to be earned by undertakings of this magnitude and complex organisation could properly be left to departmental decision, even with the advice of the Traffic Advisory Committee, and that the distribution of surplus earnings Is a matter which will need special examination.     The suggestion of the Committee Is that a reasonable return on all capital should besecured &quot;before any portion of the surplus over standard is applied to other purposes.   The early provision of new facilities by tube must be secured, and control over surplus earnings, together with the power which it is proposed to give to Local Authorities to raise loans for the-development of new means of transport, are means of securing the necessary financial support.
11.     I do not suggest that at this stage the Government should give Its approval to details.   Many difficult and intricate problems arise which cannot be resolved at the moment or in advance of examination of figures which has not yet taken place.   The capital which is to be allowed to rank for remunera-tion and the priority in which such capital is to rank, the income to be brought into account, the revenue liabilities to be charged before any balances are paid into the Common Fund, the treatment of arrears of maintenance, the basis of the distribution of the balance of the Common Fund, the safeguards to be provided for ensuring the proper maintenance of the under-takings, the protection of the public against an undue burden In the shape of the fares to be imposed,  the relations which are to prevail between the Common Management, the owners of the various undertakings, the Advisory Committee and the Transport Department, and other matters (including the measure of control to be taken over the undertakings and particularly over the non-statutory companies) will require closer consideration before any complete scheme can be formulated and submitted for final approval.   The Committee themselves point out that certain questions can only be settled after ascertainment and complete examination of the capital position and revenue accounts of each undertaking in past years.   But I agree with the view of the Advisory Committee that they would be greatly assisted in elaborating a workable plan if they knew that they would not be confronted at the end of their labours with a rejection of their proposals on the ground of some fundamental objection in policy to one or other of the major features of a Common Management and a Common Fund.   Before further progress can be made, it will be necessary for me to have authority to inform the Traffic Advisory Committee that they may prooeed upon the assumption that the Government will be prepared to promote     or   to     support     legislation    which     has
for its object a co-ordination of the Passenger Transport Agencies in the London Area upon the basis of a unified management and a pooling of resources through the machinery of a Common Fund without material disturbance of existing ownerships and subject to all the necessary detailed provisions required to ensure a successful operation of these undertakings and adequately to safeguard the interests of the travelling public.   The Committee could then, as they propose, approach the predominant parties, including the Metropolitan Railway, and in due course the remaining agencies whose co-operation it is desired to secure.13*   In view of the public interest which the whole matter has excited, and of the number of persons and public bodies who will toe acquainted with the tenour of the Report, It will, I think, be necessary to publish the report of the Committee and at the same time to announce any provisional decision which the Government may reach.   It is, however, for consideration whether, before the Cabinet takes any decision, copies of the Report should not first be sent to the interests mainly affected, so that they may have an opportunity of making any observations they wish upon the main principles of the Report.     The main line and Metropolitan Railway Companies have already asked that they may be allowed to see a copy of the- Report and, if necessary to make representations thereon before any action is taken. It is possible that the independent omnibus proprietors may adopt a similar attitude, and, as a matter of form, all the Interests are entitled to say that they are not officially cognisant of the proposals which their representatives have submitted to me*   I am as much impressed as the Committee with the urgency of the problem, but, in spite of the
fact that they have worked under great pressure, they have only been able to present their heport after the Parliamentary Session has closed.   The Intermediate step which I indicate will, therefore, probably not be found to involve loss of time and it will remove ground for a grievance which, if permitted to arise, might hamper negotiations in the next stage.1*.     There is another point to which I should refer.   The difficulties of the Parliamentary timetable are obvious.   No Bill whioh would in effect confer upon the associated undertakings for a long term of years (see para. 11) a monopoly of the road passenger traffi6 in the London area, can be regarded as uncontentious.   It is generally known that the omnibus services are lucrative, and the extent to which the London General Omnibus Company contributes to the Tube Kailways under the present Common Fund Agreement though not dis-closed is undoubtedly substantial.   The Combiners omnibuses are supporting other public facilities, but the existing independent proprietors retain the whole of their high profits which they may be reluctant to surrender.   Their opposition would not be reasonable, for they owe their monopolistic advantage to the Traffic Act, but I am bound to draw attention to the fact that at present they have not accepted the sohsme.The Committee do not state how far the parties to the negotiations consider that they require a Government Bill in order to secure the results which they desire,    what they seek to know is whether the Government will be prepared to &quot;promote or support&quot;&apos; the necessary legislation.   The new powers to be given to the Department and the new duties to be given to the Advisory Committee appear to be so extensive as to require a special Government Bill, which will also be necessary in order to apply compulsion to reluctant parties, but it is possible that the undertakers could, secure many of the new powers which they seek by private bill or bills into which appropriate provisions for public control oould be inserted and that a short Bill amending the London Traffic Act may be all that is necessary on the Government&apos;3 part.   This Act is being continued for one month up to the 51st Deoember, 1928, by this year!s inspiring Laws Continuance Bill, and will expire at the end of next year.   In these circumstances, the Committee should now, I think, be asked to advise what amendments their experience leads them to suggest, especially with a vieiv to giving the Minister more effective power to restrict wasteful competition between
different Transport Agencies and to seoure the most economicaluse of the highways.15.     To sum up, I submit as follows(1)   That I should be authorised to send copies of the Report at once to each of the transport agenoies concerned, including the Association of Independent Omnibus proprietors, with a request that, if they desire to make any representations as to the major principles of the scheme outlined by the Committee, they should submit them to me by a named date. I should prop08e to add that detailed comments may, if desired be reserved but it iS necessary that I should receive without delay any views they mey desire to express as to the principle of a Common Management and a Compulsory Oomm0n Fund,(ii) In view of the large number of bodies and persons who will then be in possession of the Report and in view of the inevitability of its main features becoming known through meetings of publio bodies^, etc., I submit that it will be impracticable to withhold full publication and I 6hould be glad to have Authority if I find it necessary to do so to place the Report on sale in the usual way at any time during the recess,(iii) That any representations received in consequence of the action proposed in (i) should be awaited before the Cabinet oonsiders whether it will be prepared to support legislation which has for its object a co-ordination of Passenger Transport Agenoies of London upon the basis of a^unified management and a pooling of resources (through the machinery of a Common Fund without material disturbance of existing ownerships) subject always to inclusion of all detailed safeguards necessary to protect the public interest, in the conditions whioh will thus be created.     If any such intimation is given it would be made olaar that the Government iw not to be taken as having considered any of the (detailed proposals in the present Report,
6, Whitehall Gardens,S.W.I., 3th August, 1927.(iv)   If the Cabinet decide to accept the main principle of the Report, the Committee should also be asked to consider and include in their next Report the amendments in the London Traffio Aot, 1924, which they suggest should be made in order to give effect to their proposals and also to submit any other recommendations whioh their experience leads them to suggest for amendment of that Aot, more especially with a view to giving the minister more effective power to restrict wasteful competition between different Transport Agencies and to secure the most economical possible use of the highways.(Intld.)   W. A,
ICTIiY C0M7IDBNTIAL. L.T.458.REPORT 0? THE . LONDON AND, HOME, COUIITISC TRAFFIC ADVISORY COMMITTEE.lnclud in%PARTICULARS OF^A. SCH3ME i&apos;CR THB ,00-QRDIHA.T llOff OF PASSENGER TRANSPORT FACIJLI.TJSS&quot; if THE LONDON TRAFFIC AREA.1. INTRODUCTORY.    During the course of the Inquiries by theCommittee as to the travelling facilities to and from areas inthe North, North-East, East and South-East of London, it becameabundantly dear that additional Railway facilities, (includingparticularly the extension of the Underground Railway system in certain districts) were urgently required so as to enablethe public to be conveyed to and from their homes with reasonablespeed and comfort.     The evidence submitted however made it equallyclear that, so long as the present competitive methods arepursued, the Railway Companies as a whole are not prepared, or are not in a position, to raiso the capital necessary for substantialschemes of extension or Improvement.In their Reports to the Minister, the Committee expressed the opinion that some scheme for bringing all forms of public passenger transport under unified management, subject to public - control, appeared to offer the only e&amp;tisfactory and lasting solution of the whole problem of passenger transport in London as experience has shewn that the powers conferred upon the Minister by the London Traffic Act, 1924-, are quite inadequate as a means of eliminating the existing wasteful, uneconomic and unnecessary competition between the several transport agencies.On the 19th of April, 1926, the Minister addressed the following minute to the Chairman of the Committee:-
&quot;I hare further considered the Report of the Sub-committee of the London Traffic Committee on Travelling &quot;Facilities in North-East London.&quot;I desire to express,, in the first instance, ny &quot;appreciation of the services which you and the other &quot;members of the committee have given in holding this laborious &quot;Inquiry and in the preparation of the able Report.   I &quot;have noted the suggestion made by the witness for the General &quot;Omnibus and Tube Railway Companies that the solution for &quot;the traffic difficulties in London Is to be found in the &quot;extension of the principle of common management  rrui a common &quot;fund.     This proposal raises many important and cotrplsx &quot;issues, the proper examination and elucidation of which &quot;was obviously outside the scope of the Committee^ inquiry. &quot;I am, therefore, not in a position to form any opinion &quot;on the proposal and should not attempt to do so.   I agree, &quot;however, with the Sub-Committee that a proposal put forward &quot;with such authority ought to be fully and impartially &quot;examined.     I should be glad, therefore, if the London &quot;Traffic Committee would arrange for this or some other &quot;Sub-Committee to discuss with the Companies and Municipalities &quot;engaged in the operation of transport undertakings in the &quot;London Area whether any further co-operation or combined &quot;action is possible or desirable&quot;.The comivtcs have., with %ne aaeistance of the Members representing the London County Council and the Underground Groups of Companies on the Committee, carefully examined this subject and have formulated the following scheme which they submit to the Minister for his consideration.
2. OUTLINE OF SCHSME.The scheme provides for the consolidation of the passenger transport services of London with such public control aB is required to protect the interests of the community in the matter of:-(a) the level of fares,(b) the adequacy of services,(c) development to the limit of available resources.In order to remove all the sectional financial interests and to ensure that the consolidated services work efficiently and economically, it further provides for the setting up of a Common Fund and a Common Management, to which the passenger transport undertakings operating wholly or partly within the London Traffic Area, comprising underground and other local railways, tramway and omnibus undertakings, should be parties.The ownership of the existing undertakings would remain with the present proprietors, whether they be municipalities or private companies, but an exception to this principle or some variation of it may be necessary in the case of the small omnibus proprietors having regard to their numbers and the small interests which they severally represent.So far as the present amalgamated railvrays are concerned, it is not suggested that they should be parties to the scheme in respect of their London Suburban Traffic.     Complications, both of accounting and operation, would be involved in such a step, as wall as a possible conflict of interest.     It is, however, desirable that powers cshould be conferred upon all such Companies to enable them to enter into agreements with parties to the scheme for the routeing, exchange and clearance of traffic; the provision
of through services;   the leasing and/or working of any of the suburban lines;   the pooling of receipts, and other matters of common interest.   These power swculd he permissive in nature and not compulsory.The Committee feel satisfied that, if the proposals set out in this memorandum are accepted, the transport undertakings concerned can be made self-supporting without any increase in the general level of fares now prevailing. 3.    CONSTITUTION OF THE COMMON FUND.The foundation and assurance of the scheme is the CommonFund.The general basis of the Common Fund is that the balances of the gross revenues of the several undertakings, after meeting their respective revenue liabilities - namely, working expenses, provision for depreciation and renewal, rents, interest on loans, debentures, guaranteed and preference stocks and other prior charges - would be pooled and thereafter distributed or applied in accordance with the proposals set out belo?j.By providing for the charges on the fixed interest bearing capital before determining the amounts to be paid into the Common Fund by the several parties, no disturbance need be occasioned in the terms and conditions under which such capital has been issued.   The security and position of such capital would be strengthened, as it is proposed that the Common Fund shall be applied, in the first instance, to meeting the deficiency of any party thereto in the  sum required to meet in full its revenue liabilities.   Each party, therefore would have the benefit not only of its own revenues in support of its prior charges, but of the balances of the revenues of the other parties to the scheme.
The manner in which municipal loans are to ho truatad for the purposes of the Common Fund will, however, require further consideration.   From a financial standpoint, a municipal loan is on an equality with the debenture or guaranteed stocks of a company It enjoys the same market standing and affords the same or better security.   Further, not only must interest be paid upon these loans ,j but in addition sums must be set aside annually out of revenue, if sufficient for the purpose, but otherwise out of the rates, for the redemption or repayment of the capital within a aefinite period of time.    It is manifestly impracticable to treat all the loan charges on this capital as a revenue liability, as this would mean that the municipal authorities would have no financial Interest in the Common Fund beyond its capacity to make good any deficiencies in the sums required to meet their revenue liabilities, including loan charges.    Such a preferred burden upon the Common Fund, might wholly destroy its value, especially in the initial years.It has been suggested that either the interest on out-standing loans or the sums required to provide for their redemption might be treated as a revenue liability for the purposes of the Common Fund.   It may, however, be convenient that the loan capital of the municipalities should be dealt with on an equal footing with the ordinary capital of the companies.   As the principal companies likely to enter into the scheme nave met their prior charge securities in full for many years with ample and considerable mar gi ns, the adoption of the latter course would not involve any appreciable financial risk, while it would serve to increase the share of the municipalitios in tha divisible balances of the Common Fund.   Where a company has hitherto failed to meet its prior charges in full, the extent to which such prior charges should rank as a revenue liability would, in any event be a subjeot for negotiation   between the parties to any scheme.
These questions and alBo that of an exact definition of the &quot;revenue liabilities&quot; in the case of each undertaking, whether privately or municipally-owned, can only be settled after ascertainment and complete examination of the capital position and revenue accounts in past years in relation to the results of those years.Some further points need to be mentioned via;-(a) Some margin of current revenue mutt be secured to estab-lieh a credit for the raising of additional capital for the purpose of the extension and development of travelling facilities.    It may, therefore, be necessary to seek authority to extend the periods for the repayment of loans raised by the Municipalities and so afford Bome relief from the heavy charges now falling upon tramways in particular.    In the case of the London County Council, this would necessitate application to H.Ii. Treasury; as regards the other local Authorities, the matter might be met by Parliament empowering the Minister to extend the periods.(b) For the protection of the parties to the scheme it would be necessary to provide:-(l) That no party shall increase in amount its revenue liabilities as they exist &amp;t the date of adoption, or commencement of the scheme except to such extent as may be agreed by the other parties, or, failing agreement, as shall be determined by arbitration. (2) That the ar.ount which each party may include in its revenue liabilities in respect of reserve for depreciation and renewal shall be such as shall be agreed between the parties, or failing agreement, a&amp; shall be determined by arbitration.
(3) That no pexty shall enter into any agreement or arrangement with any transport agency not comprised in the Scheme which would prejudice the contribution of such party to the Common Fund except with the consent of the other parties to the scheme, or, in the case of dispute, with the consent of the Minister of Transport.(c) To provide for the temporary financing and to facilitate the execution of new works and improvement,  it is suggested:-(i) that powers should be conferred upon the constituent undertakings to borrow from the banks, on the security of the Common Fund,  sums not exceeding  1,000,000 in the aggregate at any one time, for the purposes of capital and extraordinary expenditure incurred by the Common Management, (ii) that the Minister should be empowered to sanction the execution of new works by any of the constituent undertakings and the acquisition of land required therefor, within the limit of the sum mentioned in (i) in accordance with the precedent contained in Sections 16 and 1? of the Railways Act,  1921.(d) It would also be convenient if some uniform basis were adopted for the calculating of the reserves for depreciation and renewal,  e.g. car mileage.    If this principle were agreed, the only outstanding question would be the rate per car mile year by year for each form of transport.DISTRIBUTION OF THE COSIVQH gPSD.With regard to the distribution of the Common Fund, it is recognised that the various partiee to the soheme will be of different degrees of finanoial strength and security.    It
might, therefore, be unfair ana give rise to complications with the stock and shareholders if the balances available for distribution from the Common Fund were in the first instance to be divided pro rata to the capital of the constitutent undertakings so as to equalise the return on such capital.   It would seem more fair to select a past year as a standard year and distribute the Common Fund pro rata to the contributions which would have been made to it in such standard year, until the results for such standard years are exceeded.   (borne modification of this basis of distribution may be necessary in order to remunerate any capital raised and expended since the stanoard year).    Suoh an arrangement obviously would not guarantee any party against loss if the results for the standard year are not reached, but it would not introduce any fresh or varied basis of distribution as a further disturbing factor at such a stage.   If, when the results for the standard year are exceeded, no party is allowed to benefit while there are other parties receiving a lower return on their capital the proportions in which the Common Fund is distributed would shift progressively until at length, with the growth of the Common Fund, all get an equal return;   and thereafter it would be convenient simply to distribute the Common Fund on a basis which recognises this equal return as a desirable oriterion, that is, pro rata to the depenaent capital.Accordingly the Common Fund should in respect of each year be administered and applied as folio/s:-(l) If the revenue of any party for any year is not sufficient to meet its &quot;revenue liabilities&quot; at the close of suoh year, any suoh deficiency shall be made good out of the Common Fund.(2) After payment out of the Common Fund of such sum, if any, as Is provided for in (l) above, it shall be divided between the parties in the following proportions:-(a) Until the amount available for distribution from
9.124the Common Fund exceeds the amount represented by the Standard Year, in the proportion in whioh the several parties would have paid into the Fund in the Standard Year if this scheme had been in opera-tion in that year providing that under this distri-bution no party receives^more than a reasonable return upon its oapital.(Kbte: As already stated provision may require to be made for the remuneration of any capital raised and expended since the Standard Year).(b) To the extent to which the Common Fund exceeds the amount represented by the Standard Year, insuch proportions as will tend to raise the percentage return upon the capital ultimately dependent upon the Common Fund (i.e. the ordinary share capital in the oase of Companies and all or such portion of the oapital municipally-owned upon which the charges do not rank as a revenue liability) until such percentage Is alike for all parties.(c) As soon as the percentage return upon the Capital dependent upon the Common Fund has reachedthe same level for all parties, then in the proportions which the capital of such parties bears to the total capital related to the Common Fund, until such distribution shall amount to a reasonable return upon such capital.It is not possible, to define precisely what is a reasonable return upon oapital, as this will vary from time to time with the price of money in
the market.     The return must, however, be such as would enable additional ordinary capital to be raised, at or about par. (3)   Any balance remaining in the Common Fund after payment of a reasonable return upon the capital employed, should be used for any of the following purposes:-(a) To provide a credit to attract new capital.(b) To carry out improvements to the existing undertakings.(c) To reduce fares and other charges,(d) To provide a general reserve against possible futurebad years.(e) To finance temporarily new capital expenditure,(f) Such other purposes as may be approved by theMinister of Transport.SCOFF? OF THJB COMMON FTT1TD.If the Common Fund is to be   equitable and effective, it ia essential that it should embrace all local passenger transport undertakings operating within the London Traffic Area as defined in the London Traffic Act, 1924.   If there is to be a redistribution of gains and losses as between the various undertakings, all must eventually take their fair share,whilst it is hoped that this will be effected by cgree-ment, such powers must be conferred on the appropriate authority by Parliament as would ensure that all the undertakings concerned become parties to the Common Fund,So far, no attempt has been ma&amp;e to examine the capital, reserve and revenue accounts of the several under-takings and it is realised that fresh practical considerations will arise when negotiations oan be opened with the parties.
At this stage it is sufficient to record that an equitable basis must be adopted upon which all parties may start within the Common Fund fairly as regards each other.With a Common Fund, the widest facilities for the exchange of traffic become possible without the need for a close check.     This would, render the ticket and fares systems to be adopted extremely flexible and permit of a choice of routes and serrices by the public which is not otherwise possible.Further, one of the conveniences and economies which would result from the establishment of a Common Fund is the cessation of all inter-party accounting for &quot;through&quot; traffic and the parties to the scheme should, therefore, be empowered to exchequer into agreements (but without prejudice to the rights of creditors and any persons having a charge on the respective undertakings) to retain all monies which they receive without apportionment, except in so far as they receive monies in respect of through fares, rates and charges attributable to a transport undertaking not a party to the scheme. 6,       TH3 COMMON MAHA EIMB3T..A Common Fund postulates a Common Management. Ifiy a Common Management is meant one or more persons (working together If more than one as a single unit) forming an executive actually engaged in the task of maintaining, working, renewing and developing the combined undertakings, and responsible to the proprietors of the several undertakings for the results of his or their management.As the various sectional financial interests would be merged, separate managements would not serve any useful
purpoee but on the contrary would be a hindrance rather than a help towards prosperity.   Considerable economies would result from a oommon management.    It would become possible to reduce the number of the high administrative posts, to consolidate the work of overhaul and repair and so eliminate marginal waste; to obviate inter-party correspondence and returns; to purchase supplies upon a large and economical scale; and to standardise plant and equipment.    Furthermore substantial economies would result from co-ordination of tram and omnibus services.    For these reasons it is most desirable that all the undertakings, parties to the Common Fund should be unaer a Common Management.Coramon Management is not however considered practicable except by agreement, but it is expected that agreement would in the main be reached.    Should this not be so then it would be necessary to provide adequate safeguards for the protection of the Common Fund against the results of any improvident or extravagant operation by any undertaking embraced within it but not covered by the Common Management.The existing staffs whilst continuing to be the employees of the several transport undertakings, would, as opportunity occurred, be consolidated into one organisation as part of this common mangement, and in so far as any employees were displaced in consequence, provision should be made to afford them reasonable compensation.Each undertaking should be empowered to enter into agreements for the management, working, equipment, staffing, maintenance and renewal of its properties in conjunction with those of other undertaking parties to the scheme.
-13128PRINCIPLES OF MANAGEMENT.For the protection both of the public and of the undertakings, certain principles should be laid down to govern the conduct of the Common Management, v&amp;z:-(a) That the combined undertakings shall at all times be maintained in good and efficient  forking order and condition, and operated as a single system of transport so that adequate travelling facilities are providedfor the public.The reserves for depreciation and renewal in respect of each undertaking should be at the disposal of the common management for this purpose.   Any dispute as to the manner in which such reserves are being expended or applied should be referred to arbitration.(b) That the oombr.ned undertakings shall at all times be managed and worked so that the earnings shall be sufficient to meet ail proper charges a&amp;ainst them and provide a reasonable return upon the capital invested.(c) That any general scheme of fares determined shall be applied as far as practicable on a uniform basis throughout the combined undertakings,   except where special circumstances affecting the traffic or its distribution, or the cost of operation warrant a differentiation, and the Common Management shall be required to satisfy the Minister as to the reasonable-ness of any auch differentiation.   Fares and charges shall be fixed within the governing legal maxim.These principles should govern not only the conduct of the Common Management, so that if they fail properly to observe them the several undertakings may intervene for their
own protection, but are also Intended to be binding upon any arbitrator or other person or body required to decide any matter arising under the scheme.The accounts of the Common Fund and the asveral undertaking   parties to it should be subject to audit by chartered accountants to be appointed for this purpose by agreement or failing agreement by the Minister.   The certificates of such chartered accountants should t.8 regards the facts, be final and binding on all parties, and such certificates should state, subject to any comment that may be deemed fitting, whether expenses and charges incurred In respect of each undertaking are reasonable and proper and cause no unfairness as between the  several parties. The Common Management should submit to the Minister of Transport an annual report of the operation of the Common Fund and of the several transport undertakings covered by it, in such form as the Minister may require. PUBLIC OOMTKOL.With the establishment of a Common Fund and a Common Management, an effective public control body must be set up to ensure a programme of expansion and development; proper scales of fares, adequate services capable of meeting the needs of the public and sound financial arrangements for raising additional capital.The agreements and arrangements made in connection with the Common Fund will inevitably affect the Public, and there may be disputes and differences between the Parties, or with respect to the action of the Common Management, maohinery for the settlement of which must be devised.
Under the London Traffic Act, 1924, the Sinister of Transport, acting with the advice of the London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee, is already oharged with powers and duties pertinent to the control of London Traffic j and it -would therefore seem fitting that such further powers as are required for the purposes of control under this scheme should he added thereto.     The Committee, in arriving at this conclusion, have had regard to the widespread objection to the setting up of another ad hop body in London, and to the fact that no existing local authority has jurisdiction over the whole area.     If at a future date Parliament see fit to establish a local authority for Greater London the adoption of the scheme outlined in this Report would not create any obstacle to the transfer of such powers and duties to such authority as Parliament deemed expedient.It is therefore proposed that the Unister should, after consultation with the Committee, settle questions arising with the Common Management, between those engaged in the provision of public transport and the local authorities, and between the proprietors themselves.    Many questions thus arising might be of such a character as could be more conveniently dealt with by technical experts and accordingly the Minister should be empowered in such oases to appoint one or more such persons to act as arbitrator or referee.    Any ref erence   to arbitration in this Report means arbitration by the Minister with the advice of the Committee or by an arbitrator or referee nominated by the Minister.
Without derogation of the powers now exercised &quot;by the Minister under the London Traffio Act, 1924, or any other Act, additional powers would be required to enable the Minister to deal with questions as to fares and services arising for settlement under the scheme.The London and Home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee now consists of ordinary members representing the central and local governments and of additional members representing specific interests in transport.   The additional members representing specific interests should not take part in any vote of the Committee where matters directly affecting the interests which they represent are involved, TUB LOCAL AUTHORITIES AITD CONTROL.In order that the travelling facilities to be provided by the several undertakings may, so far as practicabl accord with public needs, provision should be made to enable any local authority within the London Traffic Area to apply to the MiniBter with respect to any of the following matters:-(a) The formulation and revision, from time to time,of a general plan for the development and extension of travelling facilities, the means   for carrying such plan into effect; and the review of proposals , put forward for extension and development with the object of ensuring that these conform with the general plan,(b) The consideration of financial questions arisingout of any development, extension or improvement, with the object of ensuring that all additional capital required for such purposes is secured under as advantageous conditions as possible
i 9 9(c) The review of the services furnished by the common management so as to ascertain that the provision.of travelling facilities is adequate and convenient, having regard to the financial resources available.(d) The determination of a general basis of fares, rates and charges, including the provision, as required, of special fare facilities; for example, cheap fares for workmen. Erovided always that the fares, rates and charges shall be on such basis as will be sufficient to cover in respect of the combined, undertakings not Isbs than the running expenses and all other expenses of management   maintenance and working, the requisite provision   for depreciation and renewal, the fixed interest and other charges in respect of loan, debenture and preferred capital together with a reasonable return in respect of the ordinary capital.The Minister should   be required to refer all such applicatiore to the Committee for investigation and if, after considering their advice, it appears to him that some redress ox alteration is required, the Minister should be empowered to make such Order or to give such directions as may be necessary for the purpose and the Common Management and any constituent party shall comply with such Order or directions.further. It should be provided that any constituent party may at any time mske representations to the Minister, that the terms and provisions of the scheme are not being adequately and fairly put into effect, and in such event the Minister, after considering the advice of the Committee, shall take such  oepe as will ensure due and proper observance of the provisions of the scheme.
looThe recent enqvaries by the London and home Counties Traffic Advisory Committee into the transport needs of various sectors of London have shown that there is an insistent and justifiable demand for additional railway facilities which cannot be met in full because certain of the railway Companies contend that their financial position, under existing conditions, is not such as would enable them to raise the necessary capital.Given unified management, and efficient operation of the various passenger transport agencies in the London Traffic Area, there is littDe  doubt that the consequent elimination of the present wasteful competition would result in sufficient revenue being obtained from the operation of the several undertakings at the present level of fares as to leave, after meeting all legitimate claims and obligations, a margin available to attract fresh capital sufficient to provide for a programme of steady and continuous development of the traffic facilities of the area.It would be the duty of the Common Management, either of its own initiative or by direction of the Minister, to prepare and submit, with all proper information, plans for improvement and development.   Such plans, whan approved by the Minister after consultation with the Committee, may be carried out by that constituent party best adapted to the purpose or, in default, by any .other party to the scheme securing the necessary powers, it being assumed that, in the first place, existing undertakings would be improved and developed as may be required by the expansion of traffic   The financial terms for the execution of any works must be agreed by the parties cr, failing agreement, be settled by the Minister after consultation with the Committee,
it being clear that the Minister may not require any works to toe carried out unless the Common Fund has a margin of resources sufficient to meet the charges likely to fall on it in respect of the additional capital, after allowing for any net revenue to be derived from the new assets.The Common Management should, however, be empowered to carry out suoh minor works of betterment and improvement as it thinks fit, providad no fresh powers are required from Parliament or the Central Government, and to charge to revenue or reserve the cost of such norks as is properly chargeable thereto.Powers should be conferred upon the local authorities to raise loans for the development of any means of transport comprised in an approved plan.Under the proposed operation of the Common Fund, no constituent party undertaking a particular plan of development would secure any direct or special advantage^     equally such ptarty would not suffer any direot or special burden.   It is intended that once the Common Fund is established the security and terms of future finance would be based upon that Fund and not upon the results of the individual undertakings although the capital issues will continue to be made by the owners of such undertakings.Any party to the scheme should be quite free to oppose any application made to Parliament or to any Government Department or Commission or Tribunal by any of the other parties in respect to any one or more of the undertakings.As it is of the essence of the scheme to provide for the development of traffic facilities within the London Traffic Area, it is equally essential to prevent any traffic facilities
being provided which would conflict with the general plan. Only, therefore, where all existing parties to the scheme refuss to undertake developments or to expand services which, in the opinion of the Minister, after considering the advice of the Committee, are desirable, and for wnich reasonable financial provision can be made under the scheme, should any new transport undertaking, not a party to the sche-re, be allowed to provide additional facilities in the area.   Under the proposed scheme it is unlikely that existing undertakers would fail to provided the necessary developments.So far as railways and tramways are concerned, the necessary powers for development must be secured either from Parliament or from the Central Government.    It may, therefore, be assumed that Parliament,  if it grants the powers essential to the establishment of the scheme, would ensure the observance and maintenance of the scheme.    So far as onibuses are concerned, the only powers now available for the protection of the parties are those contained in Section 7 of the London Traffic Act,  1924. These are cumbrous and experimental, and it would appear essential that the Minister should have power   by the control of the licensing of public service vehicles, to take all steps that may be necessary to protect the scheme against disruption   . L or  impairment.    It should be provided that no additional licences for public service vehicles should be issued by any licensing authority within the London Traffic Area except with the consent of the Minister and on such terms and conditions as he may direct.   The Minister of Transport should refer all applications for additional licences to the Committee for advice and report, and the Committee should be required to
give notice of the applications received, to afford opportunity for interested parties to lodge objections and to hear, either by the Committee as a whole or by a Sub-Committee of its members the case for or against the granting of additional licences.Given these measures of protection, the passenger transport facilities of the area should be developed and expanded in the manner best adapted to meet the needs of the travelling public. PERIOD OF OPERATION OF SCHEME.It will be evident from the outline of the scheme that the period for which It is established must extend over a long term of years even If it should not be permanent.   In the first place, alterations may be made In the operation of various undertakings which might, if the scheme were terminated prematurely, be prejudicial to one or more of the parties. In the second place, additional capital would be raised on the security of the Common Fund, which would require to be repaid during the existence of that Fund,   in the third place, onae a scheme of co-ordination is adopted it would appear a retrograde step to revert to the competitive, unregulated and uneconomic methods now existing.   Transport is a public service and must be governed by public considerations.On these grounds the scheme should only be terminated by the substitution of Borne fresh scheme, which would afford at least equivalent security and protection to both the undertakers and the publio, or by the acquisition and amalgamation of all the undertakings by some authority, company or body created by Parliament for the purpose, or by their transfer to municipal or national ownership.
It is therefore suggested that provision should he made that the scheme if adopted should continue in operation for a minimum period of 42 years and that it should not be subjectto any revision or variation within that period except by generalconsent of the parties.   Any revision or variation agreed bythe parties must provide for the compensation, protection and security of all those who may be prejudiced or injured thereby.12.      GOVBRNMEIgT APRGVAL OF THE GiSlxiLHAL PRIffCIELEB CP TKS PROPOSED SCHEME.The Committee have not had any formal negotiations with any of the transport undertakers, but from information obtained informally there is every reason to believe that the proposals set out herein provide a basis upon which formal negotia-tions might be opened with a reasonable prospect of success. It is thought, however, that no useful purpose   would be served by attempting to negotiate unless the Committee were in a position to indicate the outlines of a scheme, coupled with an assurance that *n its main principles it would meet with the approval of the Government, and tnat if it were generally acceptable to the Local Authorities and Companies concerned, the Government would be prepared either to promote or to support the necessary legislation to enable effect to be given to it.   To open formal negotiations without such assurance from the Government would seriously jeopardise the prospects of any scheme of co-ordination being adopted.The preparation of any detailed sen erne, including the ascertainment of the requisite facts and data, would involve the several parties in a considerable amount of tiine and labour, and it is therefore very doubtful whether they would be prepared to undertake the necessary work if there is any risk of the scheme when prepared, being summarily rejected.
Given Government approval, in principle, the scheme could be submitted to the London County-Council, the Underground uroup of Companies and the Metropolitan Railway Company, and, should it prove acceptable to them as the predominant parties, negotiations could then be opened with the other municipalities and companies owning and/or operating passenger transport services either wholly or partly within the London Traffic Area,   negotiations could also be  entered into with the Main Line Companies with a view to reaching agreement relative to the provisions to be embodied in any Bill to enable any of the constituent parties to the scheme to enter Into agreements with these Companies or any of them for the routeing exchange and clearance of traffic, the provision of through services, the pooling of receipts and also for the leasing and/or working of any of the suburban lines.In conclusion the Committee desire to exaphasise their view that this matter is one of extreme urgency as they feel convinced that no substantial improvement of the travelling facilities in Greater London can be affected until some such scheme as is outlined in this Report can be made effective. The present conditions are rapidly becoming worse and delay can only add to the difficulties of finding a solution
and any formal negotiations with the parties concerned must necessarily take a considerable time.   The Committee therefore consider it imperative that they should be authorised to commence them at the earliest possible moment.(Signed)     Henry P. Maybury(Chairman)E.B. Barnard John Cliff V...G. Davie A.L. Dixon Frank Elliott Henry Jackson Charles fo. Matthews Henry F. New Andrew 0&apos;Leary John H. Pakeman Frank Pick Angus No Scott Ben Smith K.S. Turhbull Joseph H. Turner.J.S. Pool Godaell, (Secretary).
yote by Mr. K.E. Chalmers. J.P. j 4 (jI am the representative of the Councils of the Adminlstra-i tive Counties of Kent and Surrey on the Committee.   I was a Member of the Sub-Committee appointed to consider the question of travailleur-elling Facilities in certain areas and a Member of the Sub-Committee which enquired into and reported upon the Travelling Facilities in Worth and Worth-East London.   Unfortunately, owing to illness, I have, however, been unable to attend the Meetings of the Committee when the subject matter of this Report was under discussion and, accordingly, I do not consider that I can properly sign it.   I have, however, read the whole of the documents circulated to the Members of the Committee on this subject and desire to express myself as being in general agreement with the proposals outlined in this Report.(Sgd, ) KENNETH E. CHALI?ERS. Note by Sir Charles Cleveland. K.C.I.E. f K.B.B. Although I arc fully conscious that the existing traffic arrangements in London are vey unsatisfactory and that important changes are necessary, I regret that I am compelled to record a &quot;Vote of dissent from the scheme embodied in this Report.   I consider that the scheme as planned and described is unsuitable, impracticable and unfair so far as the omnibus undertakings other than those included in the Combine are concerned, and I feel certain that they will wish to reserve to themselves the right of protest against the scheme in the further- stages through which it must go before it ia adopted by the hi-Jier authorities.(Sgd.) C.R. CLEVELAND. Note by Sir Herbert &quot;Walker. I am not able to sign this report because the Main Line Railway Companies, and the Metropolitan Railway Company whose interest may be seriously involved if the report is given effect to, have not been consulted, and as their representative I am of opinion that they should be left with an entirely free hand to take what steps they may consider necessary to protect their interests when they become aware of the varying recommendations contained in the report.(Sgd.) H.A. WAjLKisiR.

</content>
</cab>
