<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/188/0 images: 167-235</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;tS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.OOPY NO30^^7231(87) cabinet trade OUTLOOKNote by the president of the Board of Trade.I circulate to the Cabinet the reoord of the meeting of the Board of Trade Counoil held in July, together with the letters ^vhich I have received from the members of the Council at the beginning of this month.    I think my colleagues -rill find it convenient to have the combined record in one document, as it gives the best appreciation I can obtain of the position as it is to-day.The reoord confirms the rather gloomy forecast whioh I have already given.     I think the position may be summed up as follows.     The prospects in industry are very uncertain.   There is a general slackening off in the placing of orders, and there appears to be an all round unwillingness on the part of buyers to commit themselves.       There Is no improvement in the iron and steel trade.    On the contrary the position appears to be getting worse.   Cotton is perhaps a little better.   The wool textile trade, apart from the primary processes and certain special lines, shows no improvement.     Increased competition is looked for from Germany and from the United States.    Trade within the Empire is the only bright feature.Side by side with this slackness in trade, the actual purchasing po-ver in the home market is well maintained.   This emphasises the fact, to which I drew attention in the trade debate in the House of Commons, that the home market to-day is relatively much more important to us than it was before the War. The Autumn may bring an improvement in trade; but at present I see no evidenoe on which to Justify a certain hope.P. C-L.pard of Trade, 10th August, 1927.
BOARD OP TRADE ADVISORY COUNCILReports received from members in writing relating to TRADE CONDITIONS AND PROSPECTS AT THE END OF JULY, 1937.Contents.Page.Coal........................................... 1Iron and Steel................................. 6Non-Ferrous Metals............................. 8Electrical Industries.......................... 9Shipbuilding................................... 9Motor Car Manufacture.......................... 10Ootton......................................... 12Wool.......... ................................. 14Artificial Silk................................ 16Chemicals....................................... 16Pottery........................................ IVRubber......................................... 17Food Industries................................ 18General Trade.....&apos;......... *........*.......... 18Finance and Banking.......,.................... 22Shipping.....................................** 23Railway Traffic. .&apos;.............................. 24Employment..................................... 25Australian Trade............................... 27Conditions in the United States................ 27South American Trade........................... 27Statistical Data............................... Annex
COAL.FROM SIR ADAM NIMMO.1st August, 1927.I send the latest statistics that I have received, which bring the position down to the week ended July 16th.   These figures will shew the position for the Country as a whole and for each district, in respect of(a) Weekly Output,(b) No. of Wage Earners employed,(c) Output per person per week,(d) Shipments of Coal from British Ports,(e) Coal exported from Gt, Britain,(f) Employment, and(g) No. of days per week on which pits wound coal.The figures also shew the foreign position both as regards output and exports.Taking the figures as a whole, the general result seems to be less satisfactory than it was when I last reported.The differences are not great, but In most directions there is a slight falling off.I am afraid that I cannot speak with any certainty in regard to the immediate future.   Prospects cannot be regarded as satisfactory, although a fair volume of trade is passing. The inland demand Is very slow but there are distinct indica-tions that we are holding our own against German and Polish competition.
CONFIDENTIAL. COAL (CONTD.).I.Weekly Output of Coal March 1925. March 1926 and June 4th-July 16th, 1927, in 1.000 tons.	Scotland.	Northum-herland.	Durham	South &apos; Wales.	York.	Lanes, Ches. and North Wales.	Derby Notts. and Lelcs.	Staffs, Salop V/orcs. and Warwick.	Other Districts	Great Britain.		Week ended.										1,000 Tons.	Index Nos.												Maioch 1925 s 100,	March 1926 * 100.	706	237	666	980	979	468	685	406	112	5,239	100		719	273	711	1,001	992	441	689 . , . ... . -	402	110	5,338		100	- 1 653   . 623 655 663	272 222 266 237 248 259 233	738 578 661 656 621 673 637	1,011	953	410 261 398 419 366 334 384	592 289 634 632 644 632 640	360 181 362 360 360 362 368	114 77 108 112 101 113 115	5,103 3,3.78 5,012 5,0C5 4,849 4,846 4,851	97.4 60.7 95.7 95.5 92.6 92.5 92.6	95.6 59.5 93.9 93.8 90.8 90.8 90.9				451 1,014 1,001	496 914 925 913 914 915								678 .    691 667			917 868 893								Output in week ended July 16th as percentage of output in March,1925.	94.5	98.3	95,6	91.1	93.5	82.1	93.4	90.6	102.7	92.6		Output in week ended July 16th as percentage . of output in March, 1926.	92.8	85.3	89.6	89.2	92.2	87.1	92.9	91.5	104.6	90.9		 -Includes Whitsun holidays. *-1.5*.
CONFIDENTIAL.COAL (CONTD.). II. Number of Wage-earners employed in 1,000 persons,-	Scotland.	Northum-berland.	Durham	South Wales,	York.	Lanes. Ches. and North Wales.	Derby Notts, and Leics.	Staffs. Salop Worcs. and Warwick.	Other Dis-tricts.	Gre 1,000 per-sons.	at Brit, Inde: ,Iarch L925 s 100.	lin. k Nos. March 1926 s 100.(a) Average March 1925. (b) Average March 1926. (c) Week-ended July	132.9 126.8 104.9	54.1 57.3   . 48.7	153.8 156.9 127.3	221.1 214.5 192.6	190.2 189.2 182.5	121.9 115.2 105.2	134.2 132.1 127.0	92.3 91.3 85.4	27.0. 27.0 26.0	1,123/) 1,110.3 999.6	100 88.6	100 90.0	78.9 82.7	90.0 85.0	82.8 81.1	87.1 89.8	96.0 96.5	86.3 91.3	94.6 96.1	92.5 93.5	96.3 96.3	88.6 90.0		III, Output per person per week,(a) Average March,1925. (b) Average March,1926. (c) Y/eek ended July	5.31 5.67 6.36	4.38 4.76 4.77	4.33 4.53 5.00	4.43 4.67 4.64	5.15 5.24 5.01	3.84 3.83 3.65	5.10 5.22 5.04	4.40 4.40 4.31	4.15 4.07 4.44	4.64 4.81 4.85	*..... 100 104.5	100 100.8	119.8 112.2 _^_1	108.9 100.2	115.5 110.4	104.7 99.3	97.3 95.6	95.1 95.3	98.8 96.5	97.9 97.9	107.0 109.1	104.5 100.8		
COAL (CONTD).IV. WEEKLY SHIPMENTS OF COAL FROM THE VARIOUS GROUPS OF PORTS. MARCH 1926 and JUNE 4th - JULY 16th, 1927.Week ended.Shipments of coal fromBritish&apos; N.E. jHumber Channel!    Coast I PortsPorts.j    Ports.Scotch Ports.All Ports in Great Britain.Averar-e March,1926..475,387i495,243I68,4661 238,9161,344,795June 4th, 1927......1451,949(506,149S 354,3311420,601 I 518,152 435,235 499,604.420,802 452,890:400,644 463,5731453,032 445,3081436 , 766&quot;   11th&quot; 18th ii25 th July 2nd &quot;   9 th &quot;   16th35,553j41,02138, 84828, 23831,01142,357S47,432252,5951213,546i225,272!236,195241,6751266,335&apos;277,2771,309,849 1,063,208 1,258,549 1,225,281 1,161,484 1,267,217 1,257,977COAL EXPORTED FROM GREAT BRITAIN.I Average Frice Value f.o.b. per ton f.o.b,   s.   d.Tonnage.March,1925 March,1926 May,1927 .. June, 19274,392,298 4,702,536 4,802,805 4,312,9544,557,002 4,184,079 4,407,722 3,848,70620. 9 17. 10 18. 4 17. 10VI.    EMPLOYMENT.Percentage of Unemployed (entitled to benefit) among insured persons in the Coal Mining Indus try?-March, 1926 .......&apos;    9.3$May, 1927 ......... 17.2,*June, 1927 ........ 19.0$VII. NUMBER OF DAYS PER WEEK ON WHICH PITS WOUND COAL.March, 1925 ....... 5.20March, 1926....... 5.30May, 1927 ........ 4.63June, 1927 ...... 4.68
COAL (CONTD).VIII.    WEEKLY OUTPUT IN RUHR DISTRICT JUNE AND JULY, 1927IN 1,000 METRIC TONS.Week ended.	Output of			Output per v/orking da-			Coal.	Coke	Briquettes	Coal	Coke j Briquettes	Average March,1926.	-   -1,888	401	71	315	57	12June 4th, 1927 ....	2,219	505	65	370	72	11&quot;   11th   11       ,   ,	1,866	477	52	373	68	10&quot;   18th    &quot;    .....	2,074	491	65	369	70	12	2,281	504	76	380	72	13	2,106	512	68	392	73	13&quot;   9th     &quot; .....	2,215	504	66	369	-72	11	2,236	507	66	373 i	72 1 ::-:&quot; -	11VIIIA* STOCKS OF COAL IN THE RUHR DISTRICT IN 1.000 METRIC ----30th November, 1926 31st December,1926 . 31st January, 1927 ,585   28th February, 1927 . .. 590569    31st March,  1927 .....      903553   30th April, 1927 ......&quot;1,11231st May, 1927 ........ 1,022IX. OUTPUT OF COAL (INCLUDING LIGNITE) IN PRINCIPAL FOREIGN -COUNTRIES Eg 1,000 T0NS&quot;(2&apos;.2&quot;46&quot;lbaT7-	United States of America.	Germany	France	Saar	Belgium.April, 1927 ...........	49,042 37,326 38,747	11,241 11,605 12,100	1 4,400 4,233 4,220	1,247 1,025 1,068	2,099 2-244 2,198X. EXPORTS OF COAL FROM CERTAIN FOREIGN COUNTRIES IN&apos;1,000* TONS 12,540 lbs).	U.S.A.	G Free Exports.	ermany. Reparations.	Poland.March,1926 .... April, 1927 ... June, 1927 ..  .	1,021 1,459 1,673 t	1,160 1,563 2,615 2,062	991 357 t	590 815              &apos; 1 834* 870* Revised figure . t Not available.
COAL (OOKTD.)FROM LORD GAINFORD (F.B.I.)30th July, 1927.The demand for home manufactures is very quiet, due largely to the requirements of the steel trade being so poor, resulting in aooumulation of large screened and nuts at the collieries.The export requirements are insufficient to absorb the surplus, so that for each enquiry from abroad there is keen competition and business can only be obtained at prices much below cost.   There is very little enquiry for forward business, and the prices indicated by the buyer are such as oan only be looked at by the most favourably situated pits and do not even then shew a profit, so that business is a hand to mouth affair.There is an impression that prices have got to the bottom, but this is not borne out by aotual experience.The demand for household coal is also depressed, but this may be expeoted in the summer season.   The lower priced coals of a secondary quality are the only ones for which there is any demand.The conditions in Durham for coke and ooal at present, and the immediate outlook, are worse than have ever before been experienced.The export market for coke is In a very depressed condition both as regards quantity and price.    The prioe obtainable is several shillings per ton less than the home price for furnaces and this trade is only of value to the producer to keep his coke making plant at work.The looal foundry coke trade is also very dull and the quantity supplied to the Midlands and other districts is below normal, due to lack of work and competition from other districts.IRON AND STEEL.FROM LORD GAINFORD    (F,B.I.)30th July, 1927.The condition of the pig iron trade in the North East s district has been going from bad to worse during the last fbur months until to-day we seem to be very near the position when furnaces making iron for sale for foundry purposes will be almost entirely closed down.   Foundry iron to-day is being sold at or below cost, but even at this figure the make is not being taken up and stocks are very rapidly increasing.Continental foundry iron free on trucks Grangemouth for the Sootoh market is 8/- per ton cheeper than Cleveland foundry pig iron, and it is a notorious fact that the Continental product oannot be made for the prioe at which it is being sold free on board Antwerp.
IRON AND STEEL (CONTD).The stocks of Cleveland pig iron have increased to a very large extent during the last eighteen weeks and this notwithstanding that some furnaces have been put out of operation.Exports of pig iron from the Tees were as underr-During 1913 exports from the Tees amounted to 1,246,884 tons; for the first 6 months of 1927 they amounted to 80,133 tons.Hematite pig iron is in a similar plight.    Furnaces on the East and West Coasts have been blown out or damped down, and it is understood further furnaces are being damped down on the West Coast next week.British Steel Makers are rapidly working through the orders which were accumulated during the strike, and are finding little fresh work coming on.    Unless there is a material change in the state of trade almost immediately, many works will be on short time In September or October.Steel and iron imported into the country in June amounted to 336,866 tons, of which about 51,000 tons was in the form of pig iron and the remaining 285,000 tons was finished and semi-finished steel.The price of Continental material delivered in London is very considerably below the price at which any English works could deliver without Inourring a prohibitive loss.    Actually the f,o.t. price at Makers&apos; works for Continental steel exported to England is - for Blooms - about  3.15-0, compared with an f.o.t. price for the same material for the Continental market   erf  4.17.0. In the case of joists and sections the f.o.t. price at Continental works for export is about  4.9.0. compared with  5.5.6. for the same material for delivery in the Continental home market.It would appear,  therefore, that Continental material is being dumped into England, although Continental makers have some advantage in erst due to longer working hours, lower standard of living and cheaper rates and taxes.June 1925 June 1925 June 192731,380 24,155 13,113STEELFROM SIR ARTHUR BALE OUR.25th July, 1927.I have now had an opportunity of thoroughly Investigating trade conditions in Sheffield and I have to reporV-
STEEL (CONTD.)While there is a good deal of production going on the orders that are coming in are not keeping pace with shipments and I fear there will have to be a great deal of slowing down of production.    In fact this is already taking place.   Some of the weakness in the Home trade may be partly  . due to Stocktaking on June 30th, but there are signs that the shipbuilding and engineering trade Is not ordering as freely as it was three weeks ago.The Canadian and Australian, and also New Zealand trade keeps up agreeably well.   On the other hand South American trade is only fair.    The trade with the United States as regards Sheffield&apos;s special articles, Is in a very bad state indeed.    The French trade is practically dead.   Belgian trade is just surviving.    Ihere has been a little more life from Italy and Switzerland, but really if it were not for our Dominions at the present time, things would be very desperatev.Japanese trade is on a very restricted basis and the financial situation there is far from cleared up;    in fact until their whole banking system has been over-hauled, we shall be liable at any moment to further difficulties.    Chinese trade is still being done though,.of course, on a restricted basis .    The movement of goods from the coast inwards is very much hampered.There has been a decided weakening in the sale of Alloys, such as Tungsten,Vanadium, Molybdenum etc. which is always a sure sign in advance of a reduction in output of special steels. As regards Engineers&apos; Tools, Hacksaws, Files, Milling Cutters etc, these trades are really better than the Steel trade at the moment.I- think the real truth Is that there is a big volume of trade being done and cf course the statistics show this, but the moment the latent capacity of Sheffield and district is opened up to deal with orders, the market practically becomes swamped.   Another serious feature of the situation is that the profit which is being secured on the bulk of the trade is far too low to make anything likevprosperous times or to allow for proper depreciation and renewals of plant and machinery which ought to take place automatically in any well regulated business.NON-FERROUS METALS.FROM SIR CECIL BUDD.28th July, 1927.In general there has been an increase of business, synchronising with firmer metal markets, which seems to confirm the view that orders were being withheld on account
NON-FERROUS METALS (OONTD*)of falling raw material prices.    Business is by no means what it should be, and competition from the Continent and America, particularly in the lead industries, is being felt; but there is a little more moving in the copper and galvanising trades, and generally speaking a moderately hopeful outlook is held.ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.FROM SIR PHILIP NASH.4th August, 1927.As far as the home market is concerned the electrical industry has been below normal for upwards of twelve months, and there was an increased depression during the coal strike and the months immediately following.   Although this home market has not shown any definite signs of improvement, I think it is safe to say that there are signs to-day which indicate some revival, particularly in small apparatus.   This activity in the small apparatus side comes from various industries whose demands have been sub-normal.    Central power house and municipal power house requirements are still below normal, and will not become active until the Central Electricity Authority has had time to consider and approve the general scheme of power house development in the country, and has named those stations which under the new Act are known as r&apos;selected&quot; stations.    Until this has been done the demand for power house equipment will only be for very urgent requirements.As regards the export market, the demand remains normal, although not up to last year&apos;s demand which was, in my opinion,abnormal.    The electrical industry in Great Britain is receiving its full share of this business, but at bad prices.    Although, as I say, the business is obtained at bad prices, it must not be overlooked that British manu-facturers are, in taking this business, building up a substantial goodwill in the overseas markets.In these remarks I include the cable industry as well as the electrical plant manufacturing industry.SHIPBUILDING.FROM SIR FREDERICK HENDERSON.1st August, 1037.Recent Returns in respect of tonnage under construction and unemployment shew that there is at present a somewhat larger volume of work in hand.
SHIPBUILDING (CONTD.)lloyd figures for the first quarter of the year, and for the June quarter, in respect of tonnage commenoed were considerably swollen by orders held up owing to the coal dispute and by orders not commenced earlier owing to difficulties in obtaining materials.Compared with the closing months of 1926, orders secured this year have shewn a steady fall.    In April last they were down by 20c/o as compared with the volume in October and November 1926: by June they had fallen by 40^.   The latest information available shews that the volume of orders obtained continues to fall.The following table giving tonnage under construction, which shews the position immediately prior to the Var, at the peak period in 1920, and in 1926 and 1927, may be of interest -June 1914 ...... 1,782,134 tons.September 1920 ...... 3,731,098    &quot;Maroh 1926 ...... 843,070    &quot;December 1926 ...... 760,084   &quot;March 1927 ...... 1,216,932    &quot;June 1927 ...... 1,390,388    &quot;The information relates only to Merchant work, and does not include any &quot;Varship tonnage which is of course much less than pre-warThe depressed state of the Industry, notwithstanding the increased amount of work in hand, is indicated by the fact that less than half the available berths are occupied, and that, according to the latest Ministry of Labour figures, 22$ of the insured workmen classified as belonging to the shipbuilding and shiprepairing industry were unemployed.One point of importance in relation to prospects is that an unusually large proportion of the tonnage which has been ordered since the coal strike is for tankers, the temporary increased demand for which arose out of special post-strike conditions.MOTOR CAR MANUFACTURE.FROM SIR JOHN THORNYCROFT.20th June, 1927.The views of oertain Agents who are interested in the export of oars to Empire Markets have, during the last few days, been given in the press.    It has been suggested that it should be quite an easy matter for the British Manufacturers to capture the Empire Markets; but when the report of the delegation who are visiting the Dominions is received, I am afraid^it will be found that there are many obstacles.There is no doubt whatever that in Australia and New Zealand they desire to have British goods, but will only take them if they conform to their requirements.     It is rather significant that the American National Autumoblle Chamber of Commerce, in their Eighth Annual Edition of &quot;Facts &amp; Figures relating to the Industry&quot; refer to Australia as being their best prospective export market.
MOTOR CAR MANUFACTURE, (CONTD.)Among the throe or four firms in this country who have made serious efforts to sell cars abroad there is only one whose factory equipment is run at all on similar lines to that of the American firms.    In regard to this firm&apos;s products I have a letter from Brazil to-day from someone who knows the Brazilian ^ar Market very well, in which he says, &quot;the oars which are listed at from ll:200$00o to 24:200^000 are, in my opinion, a hopeless proposition for this market, as they will be easily undersold by much more important looking American and Continental cars.&quot;   He goes on to say that &quot;with regard to the trucks, they should do better, as you will note the prices are from 8:200^000 to I8:300jt^000 for the li tens. They have already sold a considerable   number of the one ton machines in Sao Paulo and Santos, and now that they have stocks here, they should do a good business in the Rio market&quot;. The American oar has, of course, hitherto monopolised the South American market.   The British Oar, which has been taxed on cylinder dimensions, and has been designed to keep the tax to a minimum, has not conformed to the requirements of South America and Empire markets.     Assuming cars could be offered of suitable design, the price must not be materially greater than the equivalent American cars if they are to sell in Empire and Foreign markets.I have said that there is only one organisation which is working on American lines.    As an example of the difference in the outputs obtained in this country and America, it is interesting to compare the output of the factory whioh claims to make the highest class car in this country with the factory in America in which the General Motors Organisation olaim to make the best American car.    In each case they have their own foundries and smithies and produce everything except their crank forgings, including making their own radiators.   With 4,000 men the English factory turns out about 24 cars a week and two or three aeroplane engines.    The American factory, with 6,000 men, turns out between 400 and 500 cars a week.   The American car is by no means a simple design, having an 8-cylinder engine and is in every way a high-class product.The example I have stated is no cioubt an extreme case but is indicative of the difference in the British and American factory production,    tfo doubt those responsible for British firms should accept some measure of blame, but the report of the deputation which went to study labour conditions in America has made it quite clear that American firms work under much more advantageous conditions and, as a result of their making handsome profits, have been able to continually spend very large Bums on Improved plant.Sir Arthur Balfour mentioned at the last meeting of the Council that, during his visit to Sweden, he found that tho American firms were well established with selling organisations and service stations, while the British firms did not appear to be represented.   The same thing is true in most other countries, but the British firms cannot be blamed if they have not money available to spend in order to establish themselves in the same way.
I *J &apos;confidential.MOTOR CAR INDUSTRY (CONTD .)With regard to service stations and selling organisations there is no doubt that even at home the American firms are much better equipped than the 3rltish firms who would like to be in the same position but have not the money to spend.COTTON . FROM SIR V7. CLARE LEES.29th July, 1927.Without any marked improvement having taken place, there Is a feeling in Manchester that more business Is about.China has done a little, and but for complications of a financial character on the other side, would, doubtless, have done rather more.    There has been some buying for the Dutch East Indies.India is sending plenty of offers, but most of them are too low for acceptance.     Some of the offers, however, keep going through, and no doubt that will continue to be the ease. The stocks in Egypt are getting very low, and it is expected that an increased demand will spring up during the Autumn for that market.     Tunis has been doing badly, but Morocco has been quite a good market now for several months.     ;/est Africa remains a good deal below par, and South America is still a poor market.As an indication of the activities of the various sections of the Trade, I enclose a table which will indicate the degree to which each section of the trade Is contributing towards the present Export figures.It will be observed that the average for the trade, in terms of employment, having made allowance for the reduction of 15% in working hours, is 71f2 , for the first six months of 1927, of the 1913 figures.     Greys and printed goods make the worst showing, at 61/i&apos;.     Dyed goods aro the best at 86$. Bleached goods are 79/;, and coloured cottons 75 .
UNITED KINGDOM EXPORTS OF COTTON PIECE GOODS IN 3IX MONTHS january-june,  1987 COMPARED with thoseIN THE 3AM5 &quot;PERIOD OF 1913:--&quot;The basis of the attached comparison is the total exports of each class of cotton piece goods in the corresnonrHrxr period of 1913 - Col. 1,, H mingThese figures have been reduced by 15% in order to arrive at a basis comparable with the shorter working week now in force. - Col. 2,Cols. 3 and 6 indicate the proportion of each class to the total of all kinds.The figures for 1927 have been converted from square yards to linear yards in the ratio found to exist betweensquare and linear yards in each class in the year 1925 - Col. 5. Col. 7 shows the percentage relation of 1927 to the reduced basis of 1913.	1913.                    J                                   1927.							Total Jan.- June (000 Lin.yards)	Less 15%	i of Total.	Square yards (000)	Equivalent L in t &quot;:!&quot;Yds (000).	i of Total.	% of 1913 reduced by 15$	Col; 1. 1,221,760 1,058,488 622,878 548.-401 141,262	Col.2. 1,029,996 899,715 529,446 466,141 120,073	Col, 3. 33.8 29.5 17,4 15.3 4.0	Col.4. 673,493 695,981 270.807 358,417 76,991	Col.5. 634,026 &quot;711,711 323,506 402,825 90,464	Col.6. 29.3 32.9 15.0 18.6 4.2	Col.7. 61.6 79.1 61.1 86.4 75.3TOTAL...................	3,582,789	3,045,371	100.0	2,075,689	2,169,718	100.0	71.2							* On basis of variation in 1925 in the several classes, and in the total.   The proportions of the different kinds of piece-goods not being closely similar in the two periods, the details do not exactly reproduce the aggregate thus calculated.i-1.CJ7
COTTON (CONTD.)FROM COL. SEDDON BROWN.30th July, 1927.The Egyptian Section of the Spinning Trade still continue-s-to work full time and mills have fairly good order &quot;books at prices which generally Bhew some profit to the Spinner.   There has been a tendency lately for the coarse counts in this section of the Industry to be more difficult to sell than the fine counts.In the American Section trade still continues to be in a terrible condition.   Sales have been a little better than when I last reported and there has been some slight improvement in prices, but prices are so bad that speaking generally, they still shew serious losses to the spinner.   The mills that are members of the Amerioan Yarn Association are working short time, and the short time varies in accordance with the particular counts that they happen to be spinning.   The amount of Bhort time varies from 20 to 50$ reduction of the normal week.The Federation of Master Cotton Spinners&apos; Associations have circularised their members recommending them to make an additional stoppage of one oomplete week between now and the week ending 10th September.    This stoppage to be in addition to the usual Summer Holidays.   This proposition will be balloted on by all the members, and until the ballot is complete it is not known what action &apos;.7ill be taken.   It is estimated that, in addition to the short time being worked in this section of the trade, about 1-g- million spindles are stopped entirely owing to bad trade or financial difficulties connected with the particular concerns.In the Weaving Section of the trade, approximately the same number of looms are running as last month, but the majority of offers which are being made for cloths appear to be about 10/6 below prices which could be taken by manufacturers.To summarise the position, the Egyptian Section of the industry is fairly satisfactory, but the Amerioan Section is desperately bad.WOOL.FROM MR. AYKROYD.29th July,  1927.The Wool Sales have finished and have exhibited wonderful strength, the ohief feature of whioh was the dominating position of Germany and Austria to compete most strongly In the world1s markets for raw material.
C 0NFID3NTIAL.WOOL (CORED ) .Reviewing, from the followine tPble -  -raw wool, and comparing 1925 with i9P?U S?i ?5tributlon of Germany is graduallv vSalZtiJl  vLi926*&quot;fJ will be seen howBelow is a complete Table for comparison and refers to the Australian Clip:	1926/27.		1925/26.		Bales.	%	Bales.	%United States of America	802,900 575,000 252,665 322,573 143,712 276,044 88,455 6,265	32.5 23.3 10.2 13.1 5.8 11.2 3.&apos;6. .3	947,000 738,400 204,857 217,851 209,765 204,259 109,785 12,000	36 28 8 8 8 7.5 4&quot; .5	2,467,615	100 0	2,643,918	100.0The percentage of standing machinery in the West Riding does not vary, and a larger percentage of looms are standing than spindles, but a larger percentage of spindles than ccmb&apos;s , which proves the domination of the raw material.   The West Riding appears to be in a very difficult position for securing Its fair share of Continental trade other, than those lines which are more or less specialities in this district.France and Italy have in the past been the two great competitors owing to their cost of production being much lower than here, as they were countenancing Inflation.    Italy has now stabilised, with the consequence that her cost of production is bound to go up, and from that standpoint she is not likely to be as serious a competitor In the future.    France&apos;s position will follow ultimately, but she is not yet so placed as not to be able to secure a big share of European trade.   When the cost of production in France assumes a level anywhere near this country cur next great difficulty is likely to be Germany. She is working very hard at wages very much under ours, and her costs appear much lower than we have been able to reach up to the present time.The improvement in the West Riding cannot be Other than very slow, and in the meantime it will be wrong to give any other Impression than that the trade as a whole is going through a very trying period.
ARTIFICIAL SILK. FROM MR. ADDISON.29th July, 1927.There is a brisk demand in the home market, with perhaps a slight easing-off in certain districts owing to the holidays.A certain amount of business is going through for India in the cheaper qualities, and enquiries are beginning to oome through again for China, - but not to any large extent.   The Australian demand oontinues good.   Conditions on the Continent shew no material change.CHEMICALS. FROM MR. HILL.2nd August, 1927.The state of Chemical Industry during June 1927 showed no marked difference from that in May: if anything, June was the more depressed month of the two, so that the falling off in trade during the seoond quarter of the year, following a really good first quarter, appears to have culminated in the disappointing trade for June.    Competition has been keener than ever, arising from over-production and depleted buying oapacity.     It is pleasing to note that July shows signs of improvement, prices being firm and business on the up-jard grade.In the Fine Chemical Industry, home trade during June was distinctly disappointing, while export business remained practioally unchanged.     The Industry has suffered from Continental competition, whioh has been if anything stronger than ever.     One hears that the foreign makers, however, are beginning to feel the pinch and are considering advancing their prices generally.Such increased activity as was evident in June has been confined to one or two sections in the Heavy Chemical Industry. In the general chemicals and raw materials section, however, there is little, if any, improvement to report; the fertilisers section shows no particular ohangej while business in coal tar preducts has been depressed.In regard to international relations, I would like to bring to the notice of the Council a point which was dlsoussed during the recent visit of British Industrialists to Berlin, namely the problem of tariff nomenclature and classification. In fact, the general question of nomenclature in connection with international trade has been the subject of considerable investigation for many years.   As  he result of the Berlin conversations the Association of British chemical Manu-facturers has already begun an investigation of the present situation
CHEMICALS (CONTD).in so far aa it affects our members; and while It is probable that the chemical Industry is not 30 adversely influenced aa some others, yet I am confident that the Investigation will be useful, and Its value will be enhanced if the co-operation of the Board of Trade Is available, which co-operation I may have to seek at a later period.POTTERY.FROM MR. ROLLINS. ,--1st Auttust, 1927.The month of July which normally is a busy one on account of the push to complete holiday orders, has been rather disappointing.   Unemployment figures have increased during the month and some firms have closed down during the last week for prolonged holidays.   The prospects are not very assuring and many firms are giving longer holidays in August than usual.Exports have kept up fairly well    in June; but while the values have increased, the quantities have decreased by 151,926 cwt.   This decrease will be reflected in the unemployment figures.The English China trade and the Scottish stoneware trade continue to be very slack.    Sanitary Earthenware, Sanitary Fireclay and Tiles are good.   Jet and Rockingham and General ware are fair.RUBBER,FROM MR. JOHNSTON.28th July, 1927.The general situation of the trade continues to improve slowly but steadily.In the Tyre branch considerable activity exists, and notwithstanding the existence of heavy stocks of foreign-made tyres, British factories are already feeling the improvement due to the imposition of the 33V3$ duty under the Finance Act.    The imposition of this duty has already also decided one of the largest of the American tyre concerns (the Goodyear Tire Company) to establish a factory In Wolverhampton;   the Pirelli Company (an Italian concern) are also considering the establishment of a tyre factory in Southampton.As regards Summer rubber footwear, the unfavourable weather of the last two months has caused a cessation in demand, which, however, has not seriously affected production, as the very warm early summer months created a demand greater than could be supplied.,
RUBBER  (CONTD).Prospeota for the winter footwear trade appear to be favourable, and are likely to be assisted by a  10,000 propaganda advertising scheme which is being undertaken in respect of rubber boots and shoes, in conjunction with the Rubber Growers&apos; Association.The general rubber goods trade ia patchy, and while at times the demand is excellent, it appears to slack off at intervals. On the whole, however, the indications are that the general industries of the country are active, judging by the demand for rubber goods for mechanical purposesExports to the Colonies and Dominions are satisfactory, and in certain Continental markets British goods are regaining some of the ground lost during the period of unstable currency conditions.Employment is rather better than a month ago, and on the whole, conditions appear to be satisfactory,&apos; and slowly improving.FOOD INDUSTRIES.FROM SIR STANLEY MACHIN,n &apos; 28th July, 1927.I regret to report that the outlook has not Improved since I last wrote to you. The long hoped-for improvement in trade generally, which seemed imminent in the early part of the year, has not matured, and complaints of increasing foreign competition are being received from many quarters. Dealing specially with the Food Industry, business in general is listless and quiet. Buyers are acting with gre.it caution and maintaining stocks at a very low ebb.    There can be no doubt that the slackness of trade has been aggravated by the abnormal weather experienced this summer. From reports received from different part.s of the country, it seems that the purchasing public are not spending as freely as they have done in normal seasons.GENERAL TRADE.FROM MR. VYLB.4th August, 1927.EXETER AND DISTRICT.Reports from local industries continue favourable. Paper and Woollen Mills are all on full time; engineering and building trades are busy, although the decorative trades are slacking off, and the situation on this side may be considered satisfactory.   Distributive trades, however, are still complaining of business being quiet.    Seaside towns are fairly full, but the report is that people are not spending much money except on char-a-bano trips.
CONFIDENTIAL. GENERAL OR APE (CONTD. )GREENOCK.Condition of Shipbuilding Industry.   Work on the orders in hand is proceeding normally in the district, having been resumed after the Fair Holidays.Condition of Sugar Refining Industry.   During the month deliveries against old sales have been satisfactory, but new business is very difficult to obtain in view of the depressing outlook for the Autumn, when an increased supply of subsidised sugar will again come on the market.   In the recent discussion which took place in the House of Commons, the gravity of the situation was fully realised by Members of all shades of political opinion, and the demand for an impartial enquiry into the position of the British refiner Is gaining considerably in weight.NOTTINGHAM.Conditions in the local textile industries r-.ve remained featureless during the past month.   Much business is not expected to come through in fashion trades during this time of the year, and the unsettled weather has had the effect of killing any possibility of repeat orders for summer goods.Lace and Curtains.     Though there has been a slight falling off in demand for curtains, this has not been so marked as is expected in July; and generally speaking, therefore, this branch of the industry is continuing to enjoy comparative prosperity.   The fancy lace trade is maintaining its position and there are evidences that some of the business lost to Continental competitors is being recovered.   The autumn season is full of promise, aid those in the best position to read the signs of the times believe   that the tide has turned, and that whilst big business cannot be expected, a distinct improvement may be anticipated with confidence.LIVERPOOL.In Nigeria the month has been a quiet one for trade. The Cotton. Cocoa and Groundnut seasons are over.   The question of developing the Palm Oil Industry on more up-to-date lines is being considered both by the Government and the merchants, and it is heped that a satisfactory scheme will be the result.The Gold Coast has been busy with the mid-Cocoa, crop, which it is estimated will amount to about 10,000 tons.    It commenced rather earlier this year and is now finished.   The demand for goods is still active.In Sierra Leone the Palm Kernel trade has continued normal and this Colony is now about the third largest producer of this article of produce.   The attention of the Government here also has been given to the question of developing the Palm Oil industry on more scientific lines and the Agricultural Department is laying out a plantation.   It is reported that deposits of haematite Ore havj been discovered, which may lead to a new industry in the Colony.
GENERAL TRADE (CONTD.)Timber. The most important feature of the market during the past month has been the steadiness of the demand for all varieties of wood.     This steadiness has been evident during the past three months, but it is now definite and is evidence of the more stable conditions throughout the country.   This steadiness affects the particular varieties of woods imported rather than the volume.     It has brought into strong demand the best cuts of the Canadian Spruce from the Maritime Provinces and along with that an equally strong demand for Long Leaf Yellow Pine (Pitch pine) from the Southern States of America, the available supply of which in slightly less than the demand.     Both of these varieties of wood are for house building and constructional purposes generally, and for the same purpose there is a healthy demand for flooring and matching of the usual sizes.   The improvement in the ship-building and wagon building trades is also evident by the improved demand for the particular varieties of woods for whioh these trades call, and with an active demand both from motor body builders and furniture makers, it would be true to say that market conditions in the Timber Trade are more normal at the moment than they have been since the outbreak of war.FROM SIR STANLEY MACHIN.88th July, 1927.No one can view the present, figures in connection with our imports and exports -without the greatest misgiving. The Industrial conditions existing in several part3 of the Continent     enable the Manufacturer to produce at a comparatively low cost and it would seem that under existing conditions, foreign competition must get worse rather than better.      It would seem that America is making a special effort to capture many of our important markets and with their comparatively low taxation and large command of capital, they are placed in an- extremely favourable position, which I am assured, in many oase3 makes competition, not only difficult but practically impossible.   All can sympathise with the attempt to reduce tariffs and remove barriers, but unfortunately while commercial men are advocating this ideal, foreign Governments continue to increase their tariffs and restrictions, making the position of the Export market more and more difficult.Again, in view of our increasing imports and decreasing exports, one can only ask how long can this state of affairs be allowed to continue?
GENERAL TRADE DISTRIBUTING TRADES. FROM MR. DEBENHAM.S7th July, 1927.The retail trade continues to he fairly good. The wholesale trade is exceptionally difficult, particularly the export branches.I am in communication with Mr. Jackson, the Seoretary of the Retail Distributors1 Association,   I have sent him a form, and hope that, if the Association cannot as a body fill up the particulars, at all events, a certain number of the members will do so.     Curious though it may seem, I find that they do not all take out their figures monthly.CO-OPERATIVE WHOLESALE SOCIETY. FROM MR. HAYHURST.23rd July, 1927.GROCERY AND PROVISIONS .Up to the time of reporting, trade for the month of July has been satisfactory in every branch, increases over the corresponsing period of last year being recorded in practically all sections.DRAPERY. FURNISHING. BOOTS AND SHOES.It is very satisfactory to report that trade in these sections shows a good increase over the corresponding month of last year.Buyers in practically every section ajpeak optimistically as to future trade,TEA, COFFEE AND COCOA,The tea market continues strong and active for all descriptions.     Some new season Indian tea has been on offer during the past fortnight, and met a ready sale at very good rates.     The quality appears to be excellent, and this also applies to Ceylon tea which is now coming forward and which shows a distinct improvement in quality on the early oonsign-ment.     There would appear to be a coming shortage on the North Indian market, notwithstanding that the weather has been better.     Fair supplies of coffee have been coming forward on the home market, but the bulk of the coffee is of poor quality.     There has been a further small drop in the prices of West African cocoa, and the Lagos cocoa which was beginning to come in fair weights is affecting prices a little.     The trade is still discussing the attitude of America when the new season^ west African cocoas arrive in September.     If America is not prepared to tak$ a large part of the crop this year, then there should be a very substantial fall in the prices.
FINANCE AND BANKING.FROM MR. BRAND.29th July, 1927.The general outlook for money rates remains uncertain while the decisions of the Bankers&apos; Conference in New York are unknown; but, as far as can be judged at present, no weakening, can be expected in this country.   The funds of the Banks are fully employed, the money market is working on a very narrow margin - It has recently found it necessary to borrow from the Bank of England - and there is no early prospect of the Bank of England increasing Its gold holding and thereby extending the basis of credit.In the last week of July there has been a weakening of the discount rate in New York, and supplies of call and time money in that centre are abundant; but the high level of brokers1 loans and the danger of the top-heavy development of the Stock Market makes it doubtful whether this will lead to a lowering of the New York re-discount rate.   In spite of an influx of foreign capital, money rates in Germany remain firm, as the exchange resulting from the foreign loans is not being bought by the Reichsbank, but is being sold in the open market.In Paris, conditions still remain very easy, with a superabundance of funds, owing to the repatriation of capital held abroad and the inflow of foreign money.   There has been a slight stiffening of rates in Amsterdam and Switzerland, owing to local business conditions and transfers of funds to other centres.FROM MR. CURRIE.3rd August, 1927.Discount rates have been well maintained during July. Expectation of a possible rise in the Bank rate has made the market cautious and has kept the Treasury Bill rate in the neighbourhood of 4&quot;/q^.,Money was in good demand at the end of the month; and a small amount wa3 borrowed from the Bank of England.On the Stock Exchange the prices of gilt-^dged Securities have remained steady but Home Railway Stocks have been depressed.   Most of the recent new issues, especially the loans of German Municipalities, have had to be taken up largely by the underwriters and have in consequence fallen to a discount.   The supply of new issues has in fact been largely in excess of the demand.The aggregate Deposits of the London Clearing Banks for the month of June show a substantial increase over the figures for May and also over those of June 1926, while the percentages of Loans to Deposits at 54,0 compares with 53.3 a year ago./
SHIPPING.FROM HON. ALEX: SHAW.29th July,.1927.Compared with the 1st April 1927, the tonnage laid up on the 1st July 1927 shows an increase of ever *75% as compared with the 1st April 1927.     In the case of the British tonnage laid up, the whole of the increase on the 1st July 1927 as compared with the 1st April 1927, has occurred among the vessels of over 1,000 tons not. 94 such vessels of 382,705 net tons were laid up on the 1st July, as compared with 53 of 190,625 net tons on the 1st April.INDEX NUMBER OF SHIPPING FREIGHTS.1920 S 1001913- 100June 1927...................   26.91M*y 1927....................    29.21June 1526...................   23.71, 115.00.124.83 ,101.32TONNAGE LAID UP AT THE PRINCIPAL PORTS OF GREAT BRITAIN AND IRELAND.British and Foreign, net tons.July 1st, 1S27 ...............     420,164April 1st, 1927 ..............     239,681July 1st, 1926 ...............     859,739TONNAGE LAUNCHED.   Gt\Britain ft Ireland1lowest figures since returns first collected in January 1921.AbroadTotalQuarter ended: June 30th, 1927.. March 31st, 1927. June 30 th, 1926..TONNAGE COMMENCED.Quarter ended: June 30th, 1927. . March 31st, 1927. June 30th, 1926..gross tons268,545 127,747 171,725437,112 579,839 168,483gross tons gross tons309,223 161,048 204,064336,503 367,026 163,233577,768 288-795 375,789773,615 946,865 331,716
RAILWAY TRAFFIC . PROM MR. HURCOMB28th July, 1927.The published traffic returns of the four groups of railways for the first 28 weeks of the year compared with those for the corresponding period in 1925 shew a decrease of  2,672,000 In passenger receipts, and increases of  2,536,000 in merchandxre, and  1,081,000 in coal; a net increase for all descriptions of traffic of  945,000. The improvement, however, was not equally distributed between the Companies.The &apos;Jembley traffic in 1925 accounts for some part of the reduction in passenger receipts, and the increase of something over 6 per cent, made in freight rates in February last largely explains the increase in goods receipts. Coal traffic was, however, exceptionally heavy In July, 1925, in view of the expected stoppage in the coal mines.The latest figures of tonnage available are for the month of May, and indicate, compared with May, 1925, an increase of 1,855,000 tons,- mainly under the heads of Coal, Coke and Patent Fuel, which Increased by 799,000 tons or 5 per cent; and &quot;Other Minerals&quot; which increased by 753,000 tons or 13 per cent.     The tonnages of Bricks, and of Stone for roadmaking, conveyed were the highest recorded for any month since the statistics were first made available in January, 1920.     There was also a general increase in all descriptions of Iron and Steel, while 223,700 tons of Plates were carried in 1927 as compared with 148,000 tons in 1925, an increase of nearly 51 per cent.     Ironstone and Iron Ore increased by 24 per cent and Oils and Inflammable Liquids by 29 per cent.RAILWAY PUBLISHED TRAFFIC RETURNS .Passenger   Merchandise       Coal Total.28 weeks to, 17th July, compared with corresponding periodof 1926 .       Southern....... h-   432,000 *   139,400 +   293,600 *   865,000Great Western.. 4-   341,000 +   880,000 41,254,000 42,475,000 London Midlandand Scottish. . 4-1,046,000 4-2,526,000 4-2,664,000 46,236,000 London and north Eastern. 4-   665,000 4-2.138,000 4-2 ,654 ,000 45 .455 ,000Total.. 4-2,,482,000 45 ,683 ,400 -t-6 , 845 ,600 -05,011,000The same period compared with corresponding period of 1925.Southern.......-    259., 000 4-       4,500 4- 65,500 - 189,000Great Western.. -   325,000 4-   616,000 4- 191,000 * 482,000 London Midlandand Scottish. . -ly293,000 4-   735,700 4- 387,300 - 170,000 London and north Eastern. -    795,000 4-1,180,000 4- 457.000 4- 822.000Total.. -2.672,000 4-2,556,200 4-1,080,800 4- 945.000 
EMPLOYMENT .FROM MR. PHILLIFS.29th July, 1927.The unemployment total so far during July has been at a level about 40-000 higher than that during June and on 18th July amounted to 1,048,000.A Table is appended showing the numbers registered at the Exchanges on 18th July, 1927, in each of the seven Divisions into which the country Is divided, with corresponding figures for 19th July, 1926 (a year previously) when the figures were greatly inflated by the coal dispute, and for 26th April, 1926, just before the general strike and coal dispute.   The total for 26th April, 1926, it should be observed3 was lower than any figure previously reached since the beginning of 1921 and only a little more than the lowest figure for the present year.The Table shows that the South of England, which was relatively unaffected by the coal dispute, is at an even better level of employment today than in April, 1926. The Midlands and North of England generally, which were badly hit by the dispute, are appreciably worse than in April, 1926.   Wales was not only badly bit by the dispute while it was in progress, but, alone of the Divisions, is rather worse today than in July, 1926.   Scotland is the one Division which shows a marked improvement, not only over July but also over April 1926; this is no doubt due to the improvement in shipbuilding which is a relatively large factor in the Scotland figures.
EMPLOYMENT (OONTD.).Table shewing the Changes in the L3,ve Register Figures between 26th April, 1926, 19th July, 1926 and 18th July, 1927.Division.London .......South Eastern South Western.Midlands......North Eastern. North Western.Scotland......Wales........,&amp;reat Britain.Total. Numbers on Register.26thApril1926.115,447 32,497 52,486 104,574 231,333 206,331 170,541 68,668981,87719 th July 1926133,230 37,078 57,401 263,053 399,519 378,230 227,588 155,1691,631,26818th July 1927.Total Numbers on Registers   Increase (or Decrease as a Percentage of Total   j (-) in Percentage atNuiiboi&apos;8 Insured.100,951 29,839 46,241 138,518 267,868 209,623 116,195 158,72126th April 19261,047,9565.6 4.0 6.6 6.0 11.5 9.7 12.9 11.18.519th July 19266.3 4.4 7.1 14.8 19.8 17.6 17.2 21.614.018th July4.8 3.6 5.7 7.813.3 9.8 8.822.19 .018th July- 1927.As compared with 26th Aor.i.l 1926.. 0.8. 0.4* 0.9+ 1.84- 1.8+ 0.1- 4.1+ 11.0+ 0.5As compared with 19th July 1926.1.5 .8 1.4 7.0 6.5 7.8 8.4 0.5-   5.0* The figures of numbers insured differ slightly for the various dates.NOTE;     As the Live Register includes uninsured persons, it is not strictly acourateto express it as a percentage of the number insured; but the comparison thus obtained between the three dates ib probably not far from the truth.oo
AUSTRALIAN TRADE.FROM MR. SANDERSON.29th July, 1927.The drought conditions continue in Queensland and New South Wales, and are being aggravated as each successive month goes by without any rain.   The condition of affairs therefore in these two States continues to be critical so far as the pastoral industry is concerned, but in Victoria, South Australia,   and Western Australia, the position is rather better.There are better reports from nearly all the agricultural districts in all the States, and there still remains a large quantity of last year&apos;s harvest to be shipped.CONDITIONS IN THE UNITED STATES.FROM SIR A. BALFCJR.28th July, 1927.I had the opportunity yesterday of meeting some influential people from Cleveland, U.S.A., who are closely in touch with the American Iron and Steel situation.They expect their steel output to fall during the next twelve months from 60 million tons to 50 million tons. Already in all directions ore boats are being laid up on the Great Lakes, and this is causing considerable unemployment, both in the shipping trade ana on the railways.   Generally, they are very concerned about the whole situation, and are fearing a serious slump.    It is anticipated that the enormous amount of purchasing on the instalment system may cause a crisis, as in America, the moment there is no prospect of any work, people are ruthlessly discharged.   Further than this, there is a big slump in the building trade.I fear that these conditions will increase American activity in the export markets of the world and generally add to the difficulties in the way of this country expanding its export trade, to say nothing of the handicap to such trade as we are able to do with America.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.FROM MR. HOSE.28th July, 1927.Despite the approaching close of the shipping season for cereals and linseed in Argentina, the volume of exports, especially of maize, has been well maintained.   The quantity of wheat exported from the Republic In the first six months of the current year was as much as 3,213,990 metric tons, as
SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE (CONTD. ) .compared with 1,730,324 for the corresponding period of 1926; that of oats, 451,137 metric tons, against 417,437; of linseed, 1,125,358 metric tons, against 1,049,794; and of maize, 3,661,138 metric tons, against 1,708,678.   Moreover, the second official estimate of this year&apos;s maize crop gives the yield at 8,150,000 metric tons, representing an increase of about 41$ on the average for the preceding five years.The official returns of Argentine foreign trade show that the visible excess of imports in the first three months of 1926, amounting to $3,142,691 (gold), gave place In the corresponding period of this year to a surplus of exports totalling no less than  89,404,420 (gold).   This extensive recovery In the trade balance and the continuance of heavy grain shipments to a later date than usual were no doubt the chief factors in maintaining the exchange in respect of sterling at around the parity rate of 47.58d. per gold peso since the first week of March last, the current quotation being 472%2d.The general commercial situation in Argentina is com-paratively satisfactory, although the tone of the import markets is still somewhat dull.   In the textile markets, however, which had been depressed for some time past, the demand has recently shown expansion.   Mail advices from Bahia Blanca state that there is wide scope in the district for the activities of British representatives, the position being that all requirements of the surrounding agricultural areas, with the exception of lumber and oil, could be met by British exporters.In Chile, the Banco Central de Chile, which commenced operations in January, 1926, as the central bank of issue, has become firmly established as a national institution, and its first year of working resulted in a net profit of over 10,300,000 pesos.   The chief purposes of the establishment of the Bank have been fully attained, the &quot;vales del tesoro&quot; and other paper money in circulation having been replaced by the Central Bank&apos;s own notes to the extent of $240,299,680, while the &quot;gold exchange&quot; standard of the peso, on the basis of the parity of 40 pesos to the   sterling, which became operative on the opening of the Bank, has been maintained. Indeed, a slight premium on sterling has been recorded throughout, and on 3lst December. 1926, the legal reserve against the note issue and deposits was 62.88/0, while the legal reserve including time deposits in gold abroad was 106.13.&amp;.The Chilean Government are proceeding v/Ith their proposed measures for assisting the nitrate industry, and a loyj reduction has been arranged in railway freights for nitrate, which will diminish the f .o.b. costs by about 1-J-d. per metric quintal.   There has also been effected a lowering of the railway transport charges on oil and coal, calculated to bring about small reductions in operating costs at the oficinas.   Apart from the Guggenheim system of producing nitrate on a low cost basis, which it is claimed has already been successful, trials are being made of a new process, of
SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE (CONTD.).which the basis is treatment of the unrefined &quot;caliche&quot; by artificial rain.   The latter has been fully patented, and, if the preliminary results, which were most encouraging, could be secured on a large scale, the lowest grades of &quot;caliche&quot; could be worked profitably.   Active sales of the fertiliser have been made during the past month under the free selling system, amounting to about 72,500 metric tons, making the total disposed of since the commencement of free selling on 14th April, 1,100,000 metric tons.   Prices have been steady.The commercial situation in the Northern and Central districts of the Republic has improved slightly, although business is still dull in the Southern agricultural districts. In general, the import markets have been more active.   There is a good demand for hardware of all classes, but the textile trade is comparatively quiet.The successful conference of the coffee-producing States of Brazil, to which I referred in my last Report to the Council, has been followed by the States of Minas Geraes, Rio de Janeiro, and Espirito Santo agreeing to act in unison with the State of Sao Paulo in regard to the limitation of entries of oof fee into the ports of Rio de Janeiro and Victoria,   In some quarters, however, it is held that the restriction on the marketing of this yearrs heavy coffee crop may give rise to credit stringency, unless the respective State governments are able to arrange advances to the planters. The outlook is therefore somewhat uncertain, and general trade conditions are dull.The commercial situation in Peru has recently shown an improvement, although a petition to the Government by several importing houses for the reduction or abolition of the new import duties which came into force this year has not been successful.   An advance has occurred in local prices for Peruvian cotton, and this movement will probably induce planters to market their crop as soon as possible.   It is, moreover, predicted in some quarters that a higher level of values may be reached later in the season.   Picking of cotton has become general, although in the Southern valleys the crop was much later than last year.   On the whole, the quality is much above the average.In regard to the commercial situation in the Central American countries, special interest attaches to the rapid development In recent years of the Venezuelan oil industry. At a recent meeting of the V.O.C. Holding Co., the Chairman, Viscount Bearated, stated that Venezuela now ranks as the fourth largest oil-producing country in the world, mentioning that the Company^ production in 1926, at 1,802,943 metric tons, was almost three times that for 1925.   Moreover, the output for the first six months of 1927 was 1,510,982 metric tons, and it was expected that this rate would be maintained for the second half of the year.
ANNEX.Some leading statistical data Indicating the trend of(Information received upiLatest. s--month earlier.Smployment . Unemployed on live Register (including persons on short time receiving benefit).................,Railway Receipts week ended -Ck)ods Traffic (Gross)......Passenger Traffic (Gross) .. ?r eduction tCoal, output during weekended.....................Fig Iron output during month.. Steel output   during month..., iVlces? Wholesale! &quot;Times&quot; Index No. (1913-100).Food........................Materials..................Total.......................nited Kingdom Trade ftNet Imports............*......Exports (Domestic Produce)... easels laid up in United Kingdom Ports:British....................A Foreign. . *..................ijhipplng Freights: f Chamber of Shipping Index I No. (1920 5 100)...........25th July Wholly un-employed. Other ....23rd July, it16th July, JuneJulyJune1st JulyJunefank Clearings:Country Cheque and Provincial,week ended.....................23rd Julyer cent age of Advances to Deposits (London clearing banks).........................I    Junebney Market:Bank Rate...................*. j 29th JulyUarket Rate 3 months&apos; BankBills..................i.....Discount (3 months&apos;Treasury Bills)..............658,200 568,700 1,0&quot;26,9002,026,400 2,162,700Tons. 4,851,100 650,500 747,300144.9 140.7 142.2  88,711,923 55,981,796Net tons ^13,835 6,32926.9184,697,000 54.0 4.63.8.29d,549,9 354,6 1,TJ0T^ 2,089,,1 1,696, &quot;ITonal 5,011,9f 720, 884,149. 138. 142.84,043, 7f 63,2*5,net to 1st April 228,0 11,629. 82,523,55. 4.5s.5.65d* Approximate weekly average for July, 1913. t Monthly average for 1913.tt The figures for the present year, for a year ago and for two yea Northern Ireland with the Irish Free State and exclude the dire 1913 figures are exclusive of the former- and Inclusive of the 1
17*TIAL.rend of the Economic situation in Great Britain, ived up to 30th July,1927).n--month arl ier.1A&quot;-year earlier,Two years earlier.At correa-ponding data In 1913.549,942 354,671 1,004,6132,089,700 1,696,700Tons. 5,011,900 720,100 884,600149.0 138.6 142.4  ,043,757 3,2*5,874Net tons 11 228,049 11,63229.2152,523,00055.14ft*Ss .5.65d.85^,823 747,597 1^-606,4201,146,100 2,053,000__Tons.&quot;&apos;Mines stopped, April       539,100 &quot; 661,000151.1 142.8 145.8 86,780,981 50,107,041Net tons 848,621 11,11823.71j 1,197.631 ) 1,978,100 2,341,600Tons. 4,888,800 510,300 585,400156.7 159.4 158.4 100,384,659 58,893,190Net tons 753,721 23,45877,030,00053.3 &amp;% 4,73.0,29d,23.6681,980,000 52.1 4.53. .44dNoComparable data.1*134,500 1*290,300Tons. 5,134,000* 855,000t 638, SOOtAverage for 1913 - 100 49,769,296 42,837,462Average for 1913 \ 23.4039,927,0004tftwo years ago, include the trade of Great Britain and he direct foreign trade of the Irish Free state the *f the latter.
CONFIDENTIAL. THE TRADE OUTLOOK.Page.Date of Next Meeting............................ 1Coal............................................ gas and By-Products............................. iron and Steel.................................. non-Ferrous Metals.............................. 4Electrical Industry............................. engineering..................................... 5Shipbuilding and Motor Car Manufacture.......... 7Cotton.......................................... 8Wool_____......................................... 11Artificial Silk................................. 16Chemicals....................................... 16Pottery......................................... 16Food Industries................................. 17General Trade................................... 17-    Shipping........................................ 20Railway Traffic................................. 21Employment...................................... 21Geneva Economic Conference...................... 22International Chamber of Commerce............... 25Trade Visit to Virginia......................... 26Australian Trade................................ 27Indian Trade.................................... 28South American Trade............................ 29Statistical Date,............................... Annex.
DATE OF NEXT MEETING.THE PRESIDENT said that sometimes in past years a meeting of the Council had been held on the first Wednesday in August, but the attendance was usually not a fun 1 one.   As regards September, it had always beer, found useless to have a meeting In that month;    there was no com/nercial information of any particular value available at that time of the year. He suggested that the most useful course would be for the members of the Council, if they agreed, to send in, about the beginning of August, written reports as to the situation in the several Industries as at that date.    They would then have the next meeting of the Council at the Board of Trade on the first Wednesday in October, - October 5th.The Council concurred.COAL.SIR ADAM NIMMO had not been able to give a very satisfac-tory report at the last Council meeting regarding coal, and was afraid he could not give a very satisfactory one on this occasion, although there were some indications that the position in certain directions might be said to have slightly improved.    The position varied as between district and district. Output was marking time.    For the week ending ISth June the figure was slightly over 5,000,000 tons and for a month earlier just a little more still, but on the whole it was keeping very steadily at a little above 5,000,000 tons a week.    That output was about 95 .7 per cent, of the output cf March, 1925, and 93.9 per cent, of the output cf Larch, 1926.    In regard to the persons employed, the position was a little better than it had been.    The latest figures available for June showed that the number of wage earners was  9.9 per cent, of iarch, 1925, and 91.3 per cent, of Larch, 1926.    The output per person employed, which might be looked upon as a very searching figure, was substantially better to-day than it had been either in March 1925 or March 1926.In our export trade in May there had been a very substantial increase as compared with April, the increase being fully 68 0,000 tons, and an increase of more than 400,000 tons over March 1925, and one of more than 100,000 tons over March 1926, - which, however, as pointed out at the last Council meeting, v.as not quite a fair month to take-Of course the prices which had to be taken in order to secure this expansion in the export trade v.ere exceedingly low and very difficult to adhere to, but the fact remained that the export trade was better,  and unemployment slightly less at the end of May than it had been in April.In Germany, the reported output for March of this year was 13,621,000 tons, in April it fell to 11,605,000 tons; the
COAL (CONTD.)-French output was 4,649,000 tons in March and 4,233,000 tons in April.    In 3elgium output had somewhat decreased.    Germany appeared to have substantially increased her exports in May as compared with April, which of oourse indicated that she was making a very hard fight against British coal.   In Poland, again, the figure of export was rather larger in May than April.THE PRESIDENT thought that this was a hopeful sign.    If we and these other countries were selling more, it appeared that the world must be buying more.   And one did not look on May as a good export month.    It would be interesting to get an analysis of where these exports were going.   We might have to reconsider our views of the amount of coal which the world was oapable of taking.MR. BOND mentioned that the falling off of American exports might have something to do with it.    These had got to a high level last year but had fallen off very fast.SIR ADAM NIMM0 said that our main difficulty in standing up now to competition arose from the low wages on the Continent and also the fact that the Polish Government had been subsidising the carriage of coal to the Baltic ports. He thought it was dear from inside information that British coal at the most recent level of prices was able to press back Polish competition; that was reflected in the exports from Scotland and from the North of England.In regard to the general position there was need for calmness of judgment.    There wa3, no doubt, a very special effort being made to work up popular feeling about it.    It was suggested that there was a crisis in the industry, but there was no crisis whatever.    7here was a crisis going to come from?   ^ho were the people who were suffering?   Not the consumer;    he was getting coal relatively cheaper than he had had it since the war, and the effect of that ought to be seen in expansion of industry, if expansion was possible at all.    The coal trade was doing all it could, or all it could be compelled to do by economic pressure, to assist itself.    It could not be fairly said that the minor was suffering.   He was now secured in a minimum wage based upon the 1921 minimum, - a relatively high minimum wage.   The only people who were really suffering from the severity of economic pressure were the coalowners, who were undoubtedly all over the country making very substantial losses; but the coalowners were not accustomed to receive a great deal of public sympathy, and we must leave it at that.But Sir Adam Nimmo did not regard the existing situation a8 an unmixed evil.   The industry was undoubtedly being subjected at the moment to severe economic pressure, and he had not the slightest doubt that this pressure would ultimately be found to have done good in many directions. A shake up like this, which was the first real economic shake up chat had taken place in the industry since the war-, was bound to do a great deal of good in the long run, and there were many indications that the cost of production of British coal was being so steadily brought down that we should have a very good chance of working our way through, expanding our export trade, and getting baok the markets which in very many cases we had lost during recent years..
GAS AND BY-PRODUCTS.SIR D. MILNE-WATSON reported a steady increase in sales and a lowering of prices since&quot;the high prices that had to be oharged in the industry owing to the cost of foreign coal. The lowering of prices had largely been brought about by the contracts which had been made for oil and coal at lower rates than previously.   There was every indication of lower prices for sulphate of ammonia, one of the principal residuals, owing to the increased use of synthetic ammonia. The quantities used in this country were increasing, slowly it was true, but they showed a very substantial increase compared with pre-war times.   Pre-war consumption had been only about 40,000 tons a year;    today It was something like 140,000 tons.   That had been accomplished by the merits of sulphate of ammonia being more generally realised and by keeping out nitrates. With regard to coke, very severe competition with German coke was met with In the export market in Scandinavia, but notwith-standing this the Gas Light and Coke Company had been able to sell quite as large quantities of coke this year for export to Scandinavia as they had done In previous years.   With re-gard to tar, which was one of their most important by-products, and largely used for road-making, considerable quantities had been sold but the competition of bitumen was being severely felt.   Care was needed so that tar should be given every chance in competition with an Imported material like bitumen. It was a question whether bitumen was preferable to tar for use on roads adjacent to rivers. It certainly was claimed by the bitumen industry that their product was non-toxic; that might be so, but there was no reason -why roads miles away from fisheries should not be dressed with tar. The proportion of roads adjoining rivers was only about 4 per cent, so that left a large proportion on which British tar might be used.IRON AND STEEL.MR. BOND said that the iron and steel industry was following the course that had been forecasted during the last few months at the meetings of the Council.   The rate of pro-duotion had evidently already reached the peak, and in May there were five fewer furnaces in blast than in April, and further furnaces had been blown out in June, Imports of iron, and steel were lower in May than they had been since August last. They were at a total of 356,000 tons. Exports in May for the first time since May last year exceeded imports, amounting to 422,000 tons.   There was, however, only a balance of 66,000 tons of exports over imports. It was rather remarkable that something like 800,000 tons of steel a month must have been consumed in the country beyond what had 1  been sent out in the form of ships and engineering.Competition from the Continent continued to be very severe, and such articles as sheets, bars and billets were being sold at a price quite as low as before the strike.
IRON AND STEEL (OONTD.).There were signs that home consumption in Germany was slackening off and there was a danger that she might press her goods into the export trade.    She had so far followed French prices.    It might have been noticed that a Director of the United Steelworks in Germany had stated that they had Investigated the operation of the eight-hour day in Western Europe and had come to the conclusion that to Institute the eight-hour day at their works would imvolve an additional cost of 10s. a ton on ingot steel.As regards South Wales,  the unemployment there was increasing rapidlyj and more and more steelworks were going out of operation.    It was understood that in some of the larger towns there was less money and the people were really worse off, than during the strike.     There was a good deal of partial as well as of total unemployment.     The tirplate industry, which was a large customer, was only working67 per cent of its capacity, compared with about 95 per cent, in the first three or four months of the year.      It was remarkable that we, who had always been the greatest exporters of tinplates, had in the first four months of the year exported 158,000 tons, whilst America had exported 115,000 tons. Further,  it was interesting to note that the steelworks in South Wales were getting their raw material at the same prioe as in 1913.    The trouble lay in the cost of converting trr; raw materials into steel.    If we were to find some means of making our steel considerably cheaper than we could today, we might hope to get back some of our trade.Orders were not coming forward as fast as had been hoped, and there was no improvement, generally speaking, in the iron and steel industry.STSSL.SIR ARTHUR BALF0UR stated that  the Sheffield trade had been good, but in the last four weeks there had been a decided falling off, particularly in the branches of the home trade connected with shipbuilding and engineering.    Sections of the trade which had been good for the first four or five months of the year had now gone back considerably.NON-FERROUS METALS.SIR CECIL BUDD reported that business in the metal trades was very patchy, but he thought that, on the whole,  consumption-tion had rather increased.     The bad condition of the industry was due very largely to the fact that raw materials had been falling quite substantially in price.    A considerable amount
NON-FERROUS METALS (OONTD.)of spot business was being done, but no forward business. In face, the price of some metals were now below the coot of production.   A number of orders were being held back which 7/ould come forward when confidence in the stability of raw material prices vas restored.    In particular, reports seemed to indicate that there was business from the engineering and shipbuilding industries to come along later on.ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.Slis. PHILIP NASH reported that on the heavy electrical engineering side the home market was still not very strong. He had cold the Council at the beginning of the year that he felt it would be autumn before there was any real revival of the heavy plant in the home market.    That was due to the length of time that must elapse before the new electricity Act and its machinery got into working order. There was fair employment in the industry, but still a large amount of unoccupied capacity.    The demand from industry was weak, but, on the other hand, the electrical power supply companies appeared all to be reporting a very good increase in demand for power for domestic purposes. On the export side demand kept up very -well.    This country was getting   its full proportion of the work that was offering in the export market, and the only bad point in it was the prices.    It was not the competition of Germany or the competition of America that we were feeling: it was rather the competition of firms in this country that was really depressing the price.    In the cable business demand was very good, and it probably never was better.THE PRESIDENT remarked that if it was internal competition that was depressing export prices, surely that ought to be capable of adjustment.    It would be another matter if prices were excessive at home, but we did not want to see export prices lowered in this way.ENGINEERING.MR. BROWNLIE recalled that when he was present at the Council Meeting in May he directed attention to the unemployment figures of the Amalga-mated Engineering Union.    Those ( unemployment figures at that period were 16,270, or 7.76$.      In June those figures were 14,914, or 7.09$, and the latest figures for July were 14,099, or 6.78$, a decrease of 2,171 since May.    That series of figures might be taken as indicative of the general state of the engineering industry.    It did not show any marked improvement but there had been a gradual improvement continued from the beginning of the year, and it was to be hoped it would still continue.
During the past three years the unions connected with the engineering industry, about 32 in all, had been in negotiation with the Engineering and Allied Employers National Federation for an advance in wages.    The application was for 20s. a week.   Whilst it could not be said that the engineering employers never refused to concede an advance in wages, they had never met the Union&apos;s application.    On 19th May last they had made two alternative offers.    The first was 2/6d. a week to all workpeople engaged in the industry - with conditions, . namely, a modification in over-time rates and a modification in night-shift rates.   At present over-time was paid time and a half until midnight and double time from midnight to the usual starting time the following morning.    Night-shift rates were paid at time and a third.    The employers&apos; proposals were that over-time rates should be time and a quarter for the first two hours and time and a half afterwards, and night-shift rates were to be reduced from time and a third to time and a quarter.    These proposals were not accepted by the Union. Then the employers made a second proposal, viz., 2s. per week to plain-time workers.    The alternative proposal had also been rejected.    On 24th May the National Committee of the Amalgamated Engineering Union went into session and this matter was discussed at considerable length.   Mr. Brownlie had directed attention to what the employers1 offer meant and also to the present state of the industry and other factors; and as the result of a very long discussion, with resolutions and numerous amendments moved, the meeting ultimately arrived at a decision to instruct their Executive to continue negotiations and endeavour to secure an improvement upon the offer of 19th May, any offer arising therefrom to be submitted to a ballot vote of the members.That resolution enabled Mr. prownlie to get in touch with the employers for a new conference, although the conference of 19th May had arrived at no conclusion.    The employers&apos;  chairman readily granted a conference, which was held on 14th June.    The. employers renewed their offer of 19th May.   After considerable reflection It was decided to submit the employers&apos; alternative offer, namely, 2s. a week to plain-time workers, to a ballot vote of the members without any recommendation.    That vote had now taken place but the result would not be known probably until 21st July.   Mr. Brownlie was now speaking in the presence of some who were present at those negotiations, and they would not be at all surprised when he said that the offer of the employers was not viewed with any satisfaction.   However, it was realised that the offer applied to 165,000 workpeople employed in federated firms and also to many thousands of work-people in non-federated firms whose wage rates were governed by the fluctuations determined by the Unions and the Engineering and Allied National Employers Federation.   Further, in the light of past practice, whenever wage rates were determined between the Unions and the Engineering Employer^ Federation, a very powerful lever was provided for bringing non-federated firms into line.    It was very difficult to say to what extent this offer might ultimately apply if the ballot resulted in favour of acceptance.Having all these factors in mind, and having regard to what took place in another industry of this country and the policy., pursued by the unions connected with that industry, whichENGINEERING (CON TP.) .
CONFIDENTIAL. ENGINEERING (contd..) ^ 8 (was the antithesis of the policy pursued by the engineering unions, and in view of the unions1  financial position and resources, Mr. Brownlie gave It as his considered opinion that the unions had much reason for relative satisfaction at the result of the negotiations.    Re hoped the vote would be in favour of aocepting the employers&apos; offer, although the unions had made no definite recommendation for acceptance.    They had pressed for a higher amount than that offered by the employers on 19th May and that request had not been acceded to.   It would have been a very difficult matter, indeed it would have been invidious, for any of the unions to recommend their members to accept the lower offer.    That might largely explain the reason 7/hy no definite recommendation was made.   Mr. Brownlie had made himself responsible In his individual capacity, in tov/ns he had visited and also through the medium of the Press, for recommending the union members to accept the offer.    From the workman&apos;s point of view it marked the beginning of a movement towards a higher rate of wages, but much would depend on the state of trade in the future and he hoped that if the offer was accepted, -   given that tranquility and co-operation which existed in the industry tc .a much greater extent than many people would think who read the news-papers, - there would be a possibility of a further Increase in wages at the termination of the agreement.    The offer of the employers obtained for six months.    In other words there would be no general alteration in wage-rates for at least six months.SHIPBUILDING AND MOTOR CAR MANUFACTURE.SIR JOHN TKORNYCROFT had referred at the last meeting of the Council to the fact that the Argentine Government had placed the majority of its warship orders on the Continent, A fortnight ago they placed an order for three   destroyers in this country, at extraordinarily low trices, however, which would probably not cover cost of labour and material when they were finished.    The armaments would also be made in this country,, and there would probably be a margin of profit on tho^e orders.As regards the destroyers which the Argentines had purchased in Spain, the Spaniards were anxious to encourage friendly relations with th m,  and had offered them a loan of about  ,10,000, IA.G if they would place their orders with them - (See Mr.Hose&apos;s note on South American Trade).    These ships had already been built by a concern which consisted of a group of English shipping companies, so they were, to all Intents and purposes, of British design.    They were not the latest design, however, so the Spanish Government was quite pleased to sell them and to give the concern an opportunity of building more vessels for Spain herself of a later design.    There were also orders for three more destroyers, which had been placed in this country, but to a design which corresponded to our standard at about the end of the war.    The British Admiralty had done all they could to help British firms, and said, &quot;If any firm can secure an order frr.m the Argentine Government, we will give them the design of a certain class of vessel to use&quot;.   Without that support none of the boats would have been built in this country.
SETPBUTLDING &amp; MOTOR CAR MANUFACTURE (CONTD. )Sir John thought that as regards shipbuilding generally there was no marked change in the situation.    With regard to engineering generally, Mr. Brownlie had referred to unemploy-ment, and the employers&apos; view was very much the same as his -namely, that there was a slight improvement, but nothing very great,F/ith regard to the motor industry7 Mr. Pratten, Minister of Trade and Customs in Australia, had been in this country and had had a meeting with representatives of the oar building firms. Apparently, It was still desired in Australia to build their own cars there, but naturally the British trade delegation had been putting the arguments against it.   Mr.Pratten had pointed out that a great body-building industry, which has now a monopoly, had been established in Australia;    and why should not this be extended to the vehicles themselves?     But while they had been persuaded of the difficulty of building chassis, they were still desirous of doing so.    They said &quot;Cannot you come to Australia and build a type of engine which we can use for cars for transport and for agricultural purposes?&quot;   Difficulties in the way of that were pointed out.   They then said &quot;if you are not prepared to do It, probably the Americans will&quot;,    Mr. Pratten was on his way to America to study the question there now.    The position was not looking too favourable for us, and British manu-facturers thought they would have to wait until they got a definite report from their delegation in Australia.   The car position in this country was fairly satisfactory and the trade was fairly well employed, though some firms were not doing too well.    There was still a very considerable importation of foreign cars.SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR remarked that when he was in Sweden recently, he noticed that the British motor trade did not seom to have any organisation there to compete with the Americans in selling cars .     The Americans had an excellent service and seemed to push their motors, but he saw very little of English motors, It was, however, quite a good market and a growing market:COTTON.SIR W. GLARE LEES thought that the position in the cotton trade was not a very easy one to judge exactly.     The export figures at present were better than they had been for some considerable period.        The June export figures were net yet available, but they were not likely to be very different from those for May, and the May figures seemed to Indicate an average employment In Lancashire of Q6?&apos; which, although It was not full time, was much better than it had been ^ The export figures for the first five months of the year indicated an average employment of 73? , so that the May position was 86f. against an average of 73$ for the year from January 1st.     The Order books, however,- were running out. The Orders coming in were not equivalent to the ^exports that were going out, and there were two things which might account
00L. SEDDON BROWN wrote&quot;Frcm the Egyptian section of the spinning trade, there is little of interest to report.     MIIIb engaged on this trade oontinue to run full time and business on the whole has been fairly satisfactory.&quot;During the period under review, trade in the Amerioan section haB been as bad as it oould be and it is still in a deplorable oondition.      During the last two weeks for which figures are available, production has been little more than 50$ of normal 48 hours production.   But even with a reduced production suoh as this, sales have only reached about 39$ of actual production.OOTTON (CONTD.).for that.   One, we had no control over,   that was the considerable increase in the price of raw material.     The second was that the iarn Association whioh had been formed, had told everything they were doing to the Press.   All this had oaused a kind of resentment among buyers against what appeared to be the arbitrary raising of prices, and the ^arn Association was being blamed for rises which were really rises in the world price of raw material.    If their object of putting the trade on to a profit-earning basis could be accomplished without talking so muoh in the Press about it, it would be very much better for the trade as a whole.   For if buyers were told in the Press that they had got to pay three-farthings a lb. more, they would rebel against doing it, and although business went on, there had been hesitations in the buyers&apos; minds on that account, particularly in India.     In fact, however, the prices that were being quoted were very reasonable and not really high enough to give a proper return on the oapital.British India, China, Hong Kong, Japan, the Dutch East Indies, Cuba and Central America were the markets in which we were suffering.    If the trade in those parts was on the same level as the rest of the trade we should be in quite a favourable condition.     In China it had not been just a falling off in trade, but almost a total cessation, although there had been an Indication reoently of fresh orders. V/e might do more in the second half of the year than we had done in the first, in China.   The position in the Balkans, and in Europe generally, was very remarkable.    One felt, particularly if one was out there, that we were suffering heavily from foreign competition, but on the other hand when the figures were examined it was found, so far as May went for instance, that we actually exported more in cotton goods to the Balkans last May than we had done in May 1913. And so far as Europe as a whole was concerned, there again we actually exported more in cotton goods, in volume, than in May 1913.     It was rather encouraging that in the Balkans, in particular, where we undoubtedly suffered competition both from Europe and from Japan, the oonsuming power of the markets seemed to have materially lnoreased, because in Bpite of that competition we had increased our export trade&quot;. But, on the whole, the general feeling was that unless we got some fresh orders very quickly these figures would grow less in the immediate future rather than more.
COTTON (CONTD.) .&quot;Tnc-se firms who are members of the newly formed Cotton Yarn Association are working short time, and the amount of this short time varies in accordance with the particular counts of yarn the Spinners may be spinning.    It is significant, however, that on January 24th the Yarn Association decided that those of Its members who are spinning 32s. to 42s,  (which might be termed as the &apos;&apos;bread and butter&quot; trade   of Lancashire) should only work 24 hours per week.&quot;It would perhaps interest the Council to know that my Company has recently had the Balkan markets, Syria, Palestine and Egypt specially visited by our own representatives, and they report that the competition in cotton goods from Japan is steadily taking away all Lancashire trade.    Particularly in Turkey and Syria, which used to be such good markets for American yarn spun in Lancashire, the peasants are abandoning their hand looms on which they used to weave the Lancashire-made yarn, and buying instead the cheap cloth woven in Japan and China.    I have again had samples of these cloths brought over, and it is an undoubted fact that Lancashire with its short hours of work, high wages and heavy taxation cannot compete with them.    To give one particular example - one town where there used to be 10,000 handlooms consuming yarn, it is estimated that now only about 4 to 5 hundred are in commission.&quot;Many firms In the American section of the trade have had to make Schemes of Arrangement with their creditors, and. many more are to-day in a desperate condition financially.&quot;Last month I reported that the Liverpool Cotton Association had before them a suggested alteration of their rules which, if put into effect, would mean that spinners would have to pay cash before delivery of their cotton.    It was, however, decided on June 3rd by the Liverpool Association, not to adopt this alteration to their rules, but it must be remembered, however, that under the existing rules, any individual member of the Association can, if he so desires, demand cash before delivery when quoting for the sale of his cotton.&quot;As regards weaving, generally speaking, less looms are running in Lancashire    than last month, and looms are unfortunate-ly tending to become idle day by day.    In the fancy trade slightly more looms are running and. there is a fair demand for their production, but in the ordinary trade the prospect at the moment is bad.    The increased prices quoted by spinners under the selling scheme of the Yarn Association have had to be reflected in cloth quotations and have undoubtedly checked business.    At the moment buyers of cloth, both at home and abroad, are waiting to see whether the Yarn Association prices can be adhered to by spinners and are, therefore, curtailing their purchases to absolute minimum requirements.
COTTON (OONTD.).&quot;This is the season of the year when the prospects of the growing cotton crops is having the particular attention of the market.      It ie estimated that the reduction of acreage in America will be approximately 10$, and it is thought by raeny that the American crop has not had a good start.     The fact that many are waiting to make up their minds as to the size of the cotton crops, and the prices that they are likely to be marketed at, makes trade very difficult at the moment, and it is almost impossible today to find any factors upon which one might base any optimistic views for the near future&quot;.WOOL.&quot;MR. AY.KR01D remarked that the Soviets had set up an organisation in Bradford for buying raw material.      It had been thought that this would possibly be closed with the closing of Arcos, but such had not been the case, and - what was rather extraordinary       they were beginning to negotiate business in that district once more.       The Russians undoubtedly would require raw material.     They could get it in Bradford, and possibly this would be the means of bringing about a better understanding.      Sir Arthur Balfour had mentioned (see section on &quot;Geneva Economic Conference&quot;) that it was exceedingly difficult to believe the statements made by the Soviets.    It was only ten days to a fortnight ago that it was published in the papers that two British firms had granted the Soviets  2,500,000 of open credits for a period of two years.    It had been stated on the other hand,  that this was not correct, and the rumour had possibly been started with the idea of helping to build up confidence in the Soviets. If the report was absolutely untrue, however,  this ought to be made perfectly   plain, because many firms were trying to extract pretty stringent terms from the Soviets, and if reports such as this were given currency they tended to inspire people with confidence who had been hesitating whether oredit should be granted or not.     Trade in the Bradford district was so exceedingly difficult that many were anxious to grasp at anything that came along.There was not at the moment enough trade to go round, although, speaking generally, the export trade was improving, particularly the export trade with Germany.     Mr. Aykroyd had mentioned last time that the single yarn trade was better. He could now confirm that.     There had been considerably more business done with Germany, and that branch of the industry looked like being tolerably busy for a few months to come.     The ordinary home trade was in a very difficult position.     Export was improving a little but the home trade was not.     It was just existing, but there was not sufficient to go round.     The consequence was an excess of competition, one against another, for a trade that hardly existed.    Some had been trying to deal with the problem by getting an arrangement whereby they could have a minimum conversion cost, based
C Q NF TD&amp;ti TIA L. WOOL (contd..)4 o Jabsolutely on an economic price as low as ever it could be,not allowing the slightest profit to anyone-    This had been done purely with the Idea of saving them from absolute disaster.Mr. Aykroyd had had a short trip to America since he was at the Council last, ahd had been very much astonished to find that the position of affairs there in the wool textile industry was considerably worse even than in England.    Their great draw-back was that they seemed to have no cohesion between one and another.    What was happening there, taking the wool combing industry.as an illustration, was that they were making almost, individual bargains for each parcel of wool, which was an appalling state of affairs.   He h*d been glad to have an opportunity of addressing the woollen manufacturers of the States because It was almost the first time that an effort had been made to get them a little more in touch with the Industry of this country.    They were very large consumers of wool, and bought as much as they grew.    Three years ago the British manufacturers had had conferences with the wool growers from the Dominions on the occasion of the Wembley exhibition, and they realised that It would have been much wiser if they had had representatives from America also, trying to come to a conclusion on this point.    It was with that idea that they had taken steps just no?/ to Inform the American users of wool exactly what they were doing.   The producers of raw material had gone on for many years without being brought in contact with the users, and consequently they had been producing raw material just as they thought fit, irrespective of its uses in our markets.    It was felt that considerable good had been done In pointing out the various deficiencies that existed, and that this would not only help them but would materially help our own people also.Apropos of the discussion that had been taking place In Parliament as to taxing undistributed profits in limited companies for the purpose of super tax, it might be recalled thatt. the Association of Chambers of Commerce had for marry years brought to the notice of the Government the advisability of taxing Co-operative Societies.    On most occasions the difficulty of conducting such an operation had been pointed out to them, by way of answer.   But if the principle was accepted that limited companies should be taxed for the purpose of super tax on undistributed profits, this opened up the whole question of putting the Co-operative Societies on a level with other sections of industry.THE PRESIDENT read out a letter from Mr. Shaw (which follows), confirming what Mr.Aykroyd sa4d as to the woollen trade and adding some detailed figures.   He was glad to hear that the suggestion as to initiating conversations between employers and employed respecting the prospects of the industry had been followed up.    He had expressed the hope In the House of Commons in the debate on the Adjournment before Whitsuntide that the proposition would be acted upon.
WOOL (CONTD.).MR. ARTHUR. SHAW wrote:-&quot;It is very difficult to summarise the position in the TVool Textile Industry owing to the different classes of work and the changes in employment from district to district.&quot;In Huddersfield, the trade is patchy, and during the month there has been a rapid increase in the number of persons signing the Unemployment Registers,  the figures at the end of the month having reached the highest point since December, 19c&quot;Halifax has shewn a steady improvement, but is still fax from normal.    The trade reports are fair and indicate a still further reduction of the number of unemployed.&quot;Bradford and district is still further depressed.   At the end of the month, the numbers signing were the highest since January 5th, 1927.&quot;Following the previous reports and the suggestion for a joint consultation between the employers and the Trade Union representatives, I have to report (confidentially) that meetings have taken place between the two sides.    Enclosed are figures that I have extracted from the Accounts relating to Trade and Navigation, which clearly indicate the serious position of the Trade (see Tables I to III at the end of this note).    The following figures for the five months ending May 31st, unfortunately, shew the continued increase in our import and the decrease in exports:-WOOLLEN AND 7/ORSTED TISSUES (sq. yds.).1927 (5 months) 1926        &quot; 1925        &quot;Imports.18,280,398 15,274,426 14,174,949Re-Exports1,920,823 1,151,686 1,146,722EXPORTS.Woollens.Worsteds.Total.1927 (5 months) 48,418,300 1926        &quot; 47,472,7001925        &quot; 55,076,40016,631,200 19,049,000 21,825,60065,049,500 66,521,700 76,903,000&quot;The exports on Table III clearly indicate that the decrease can practically be traced to the seven countries named, and applies to Woollens and Worsteds.    If the joint consultations result in tracing any of the causes of this continued I033 of trade, a useful purpose will be served.&quot;The following figures relate to the members signing the Vacant Book for the six month ending June 30th, 1927, and have been slightly adjusted for the early months:-Bradford   Heavy Woollen   Huddersfield     GeneralDeo.29/26. Jan.26/27. Feb.23/27. Mar.30/27. Apl.27/27. May 25/37. June 39/27 .District.      District13.07 23.0610.177.47 10.46 10.889.21 11.2222.95 19.79 14.72 13.48 10.97 9.46 -1?.Distriot.10.43 10.557.983.426 .535.81 11.15Average.fo15.03 13.81 11.02 10.41 10.24 8.63 10.68 M
Linear Yards.Imports-^- Re -Export s*1910 65,580,918 9,572,4351911 65.628,425 8,437,9731912 67,088,169 9,108,4051913 65,182,694 8,245,959Square Yards.1920 10,477,429 1,458,6691921 9,833,579 1,004,1501922 13,136,553 1,358,1291923 23,110,630 2,125,846192 4 2 9,736,259 2,606,8271925 36,436,967 2,445,9991926 38,089,499 3,457,231*The figures for 1910-1913 unavoidably include flannels, plushes and damasks, tapestry, etc.TABLE II.IMPORTS OF WOOLLENS &amp; WORSTEDS FROM VARIOUS COUNTRIES .Square Yards,Year.		Germany.	France.	Other Countries	Total.1922		449,198	10,152,452	2,534,908	13,136,5581923	1	,583,348	16,488,571	5,038,711	23,110,6301924	2	,040,697	21,627,144	6,068,418	29,736,2591925	3	,335,091	25,293,193	7,808,683	36,436,9671926	9	,265,605	20,975,298	7,847,596	38,089,499			TABLE	III.	EXPORTS FROM THE UNITED KINGDOM TO VARIOUS COUNTRIES SHE..1^G THE PRINCIPAL DECRMAbES.WOOLLENS. Square Yards.1924.                     1925. 1926.Netherlands       5,898,100            4,9y^7D&quot;00 3,330,100Belgium              4,311,300             3,411,800 1,690,500Greece                2,731,400            2,460,600 1,030,600Turkey                2,876,600             2,926,500 1,698,700China                22,883,000           13,744,900 15,186,000Japan                29,702,900           15,312,900 9,768,400Australia 14,087,400_10,068,^00_8,881,90082 , 4 9 0,700           52,917,100 41,586,200Total Exports 164,739,900         132,174,200 120,331,500WORSTEDS.                  1924.                     1925. 1926.Netherlands           127,600                 96,600 84,000Belgium                    78,900                  40,500 32,800Greece                 1,352,700             1,036,400 3 93,3 00Turkey                    841,4 0 0                6 03 , 400 2 95,2 00China                  6,177,300             4,072,200 3,869,300Japan                  8,050,600             4,700,000 2,498,000Australia 2 ,324,400_  ,348,000_1,819,20019,452,900           12,897,100 8,991,800Total Exports   56,843,000           47,302,000 43,136,400FIGURES OF IMPORTS AND EXPORTS REFERRED TFCT&quot;IN MR. SHAWS REPORT.TABLE I.IMPORTS OF WOOLLENS AND WORSTEDS TO THIS COUNTRY.
WOOL ( CONTD.)COLONEL WILLEY reported that in the woollen trade there was some increase of employment; the hosiery trade was still disappointing, but the carpet trade remained good.    The employ-ment figures showed perhaps a tendency towards better employ-ment in the industry as a whole, unemployment falling more rapidly than pai^t-time unemployment.    The figures were, however, rather unequally distributed because while employment had improved in combing and spinning in the worsted trade, it remained disappointing in the weaving.    It was the improvement in Germany, with its reactions all over the Continent&quot;, which had reacted most quickly upon industry in this country.    Our exports of yarns and tops had both gone up this year as against last year, but our bad trade last year appeared to have been the result of bad foreign trade and not of domestic trade, and it was interesting to note that in tops our exports in 1926 were less by a quarter than those in 1913; at the same time in exports of worsted fabrics there was a decline from 62,400,000 linear yards (equivalent to, say, 78,000,000 square yards) in 1913 to 43,000,000 square yards in 1926, so there was a downward curve of exports.    It was interesting to note that both in this country and in neutral markets the keenest competition was coming from fabrics produced in countries with high protectionist tariffs, - Italy, France and Poland, and from Germany also, with its substantial tariff.    Information available was confirming that the import of wool garments was showing a steady increase.There had been an industrial conference in Germany a few weeks ago and it had been emphasised that the textile trade there was suffering from low wages in Czecho-Slovakla, which was competing in their markets.    Now the wages in Germany were very much lower than in this country, and that showed the extent of the competition that exports in this country must face from countries like Czecho-Slovakla.   Another factor was that in Czecho-Slovakia they had the advantage of two-shift operations in their spinning and weaving.    In Italy there were three shifts, and we were confined to one.    In those countries also overhead charges were very much below those in this country and that contributed to facilitate exports.    The industry as a whole was suffering from a downward curve of the general price level, and there was little inclination to buy forward.    For the first time for many years prices of raw materials had been practically constant, and as the industry had been built up traditionally on speculative profits, this phenomenon was really causing perplexity.    While, as Mr.Aykroyd had pointed out, an attempt was being made to correct it by a price arrangement, that would only be effective In the case of materials produced in this country which had to meet in competition articles produced in all other markets.    Opinion, for that reason, was growing that the necessary correction would have to como from reconstruction within the industry along lines of rationalisation which must adjust production to markets.
ARTIFICIAL    SILK.MR. ADDISON had nothing to add to the brief report whioh he had made to the Council last month.     The industry was in the happy position of experiencing a brisk demand in all sections.CHEMICALS.MR. HILL reported that the month of May, so far as the chemical industry went, had been one of further improvement as a whole, though without any outstanding features.     Home trade had not moved forward, but the overseas trade had continued in that improvement whioh had been foreshadowed in the April figures.     The fine chemical trade was experiencing very keen competition from the Continent, which made export business very difficult.The fine ohemical Industry had benefited greatly, and was still benefitting greatly, from the Safeguarding of Industry duties, and it was hoped that it would not have to suffer further, inroads into the list of substances chargeable with duty under Part I of the Act.     Opinions in the chemical trade were somewhat divided on the effect of the Merchandise Marts Act, 1926, on home trade, but there was certainly no question as to the cordial reception that was being given to the efforts of the Board of Trade in explaining and ameliorating some of the difficulties which had arisen; and,  in partioular, the relief given to the pharmaceutical trade had caused great satisfaotion.It had been suggested that the Board of Trade could perhaps anticipate some of the difficulties expected to arise in connection with the Therapeutic Substances Act, 1925, and regulations made under it.      In connection with the regulations, manufacturers had appreciated fully the action of the Ministry of Health in taking cognisance of their recommendations, though the attitude of the Department in refusing a discussion with representatives of the manufacturers was not fully understood.     It seemed olear that in this, as in many other similar oases where highly technioal considera-tions were involved, olose co-operation between Government Departments and manufacturers was one of the safest methods by which smooth working of these Acts could be assured. Manufacturers of therapeutic substances welcomed the Act which, If administered in the spirit in which the regulations appeared to have been drafted, would be of benefit to manufacturers as well as to the community as a whole.POTTERY *MR. HOLLINS observed that the export trade was still being well maintained, according to the offloial figures which covered - the first five months of the year till 31st May.   The export of
POTTERY.   (CONTD.)china and translucent ware had increased both in quantities and value.     This is what vms called the fine china section, -more or less a luxury trade.     In English bone china, which was made chiefly in Longton, there was very little export trade and they were largely dependent on the home trade, which at the present time was very slack.     This was obviously due to the glut of continental china which had been rushed into the country prior to April 19th, on which date the Safeguarding duty had been imposed.     We had to get clear of this stock first.       On the other hand, general earthenware had benefited/ to some extent because there were still buyers who had not been able to lay hold of these stocks and were placing orders for earthenware rather than for china.     From the point of view of utility earthenware was quite as good ts the average person as china ware, and probably the decreased purchasing power of the working classes would drive them to the cheaper article, and they would take to it as readily as to the Longton china, which was rather expensive.     A prominent employer in the ohina trade had stated that unless some amelioration occurred very soon there would be very serious financial difficulties among the china makers.     Unemployment in the Potteries was, generally speaking, about the same as last month if the Whitsuntide holidays were allowed for, except that the Longton china trade was In a worse position, even making that allowance.FOOD INDUSTRIES.SIR STANLEY MACHIN wrote:-&quot;In the food industry the conditions are but little changed.     Buyers are adopting a very cautious attitude and while orders are fairly numerous, the bulk trade is at present nothing approaching normal.     At the same time, a hopeful feeling exists that better times are at hand and with the advent of more seasonable weather, I hope in the near future I may be able to send you a more encouraging report&quot;.GENERAL TRADE.MR. VYLE thought that the Chamber of Commerce reports indicated general dulness, amounting almost to a oertain dissatisfaction in various districts.     Quite briefly, trade in the North of Scotland was fairly good;     in Coventry it was normal, but there was a steady Increase in the number of persons unemployed.     From Leicester they reported that orders In the boot and shoe trade were not coming in in a satisfactory way, but other branches of industry were in a better condition; in Sheffield, the general trade is reported as quiet, with an increase of
GENERAL TRADE (CONTD.)1,680 in the number of unemployed during the month.    A bright spot seemed to be the South of Scotland where, in the textile area, the roll of unemployed was the lowest for some time and trade was better than it had been in the past few years;    there was very little unemployment among skilled workers.    In Lancashire generally there was no alteration.    In the Midlands the general position was considered unsatisfactory.   There the motor trade had picked up, and there was a better demand for higher-priced cars; but the hollow-ware trade was dull, the wireless trade poor, electrical machinery rather quiet, and as regards iron and steel the new business coning along was disappointing.SIR STANLEY MACHIN wrote:-&quot;Speaking generally, it would seem that trade is still on the up-grade only to a very limited extent.    I need not here refer to the grave difficulties in tho coal trade, which will be dealt with by exports in that industry, but the seriously depressed conditions existing in the mining areas are naturally having effect on trade in many directions&quot;.121. BRAND wrote:-&quot;I have nooning in particular to report this month. In general, the various money markets are awaiting with great interest the result of the meeting of the Central Banks in   New York on the gold problem&quot;.LIR. DEBENHAIi stated that during the last six months there had been no indication of a falling off in the expenditure of worsen on dress,    Trade had been better than last year when we h?.d the strike, and even slightly better, so far as he could see, than in 1925.    There had been a marked falling off in the demand for silk materials and lighter woollens, and an improvement in demand for the better-class printed cotton goods.    That improvement had not, however, been as great as it would have been if the weather had been more f a/vourable.    There was also a marked demand for mixed cotton and woollen goods, and for the finer counts of artificial silk,    This would tend to make the pure silk trade rather worse in certain directions than it had been.The question of figures as to the course of retail trade being provided by the principal members of the trade had been considered, and certainly not turned down.    It would be fairly simple to supply firures in a form which would indicate the spending power of the community.    Then it was a question whether they should also be divided into the several sections of the trade so as to show the directions in which expenditure w.,s going.-   THE.PRESIDENT said that the most important thing to ascertain was the spending power generally;    it would be most valuable information, and in combination with the particulars from the Co-operative Wholesale Society which Mr. Hayhurst gave - would present a complete picture.
GENERAL TRADE (CONTD . ) .Co-operative Wholesale Society.MR. HAiHURST regretted to say that during June the Society&apos;s sales throughout the country in groceries and provisions had shown a decrease compared with the corresponding period of last year, but as the latter followed upon the close of the general strike when customers were replenishing stocks, the difficulties referred to should not be looked upon as indicating reduced trade generally.   There was a matter which, it would seem, the Ministry of Agriculture might take notice of, and that was the question of butter.    In the past few weeks markets had been irregular and somewhat difficult to rollow.    It was interesting to record that during May 554,000 cwts. of butter were imported from Denmark.    If we had made that quantity ourselves it would have been an advantage. These imports showed an increase of 86,000 cwts. over those in May 1926.      Surely it was worthy of the notice of someone who might be concerned in the matter.   &apos; Almost the same remark applied to cheese.    We had our Empire produce but many times we forgot ou^ own country&apos;s produce.    Take New Zealand and Canadian.   They had had steady sales, were of excellent quality, and the markets were firm.   But the quality of Cheshire was higher, and it was undoubtedly the best value on the market.    There again was a problem for the ministry of Agriculture.    The production and sales of flour had been satisfactory, and wheat prices had advanced slightly during the past week.    As far as bacon was concerned, there had been large supplies from Denmark.    A few years ago the Jiinistry of Agriculture took up the question of increased pig-breeding in this country.      It was surprising that we still did not meet a tithe of our requirements in bacon and ham, and there again appeared to be a problem for the Ministry of Agriculture.It was rather a strange feature that the Society were able to record satisfactory increases in drapery, boots and shoes, and furnishing.     For the most part these were really what might be termed in bad times semi-luxury branches of business.    It was also rather remarkable that in some parts of Lancashire the holiday funds which were being distributed, did not show very much decrease, so that after all conditions were perhaps not quite so bad as would appear on the surface,The tea markets had been fairly active since the Society&apos;s last report.     There had been a hardening in prices, but last week a drop of about ^d. a lb. had occurred.    As had already been reported to the Council, the West African cocoa crop had been bought up by Americans and the price had risen by over 100 per cent.    Now that a large new crop was coming, it would be Interesting to see what thoy would do with the supplies on their hands.On the whole, it might be considered that the Soclety&apos;s report was fairly satisfactory.
CONFIDENTIAL. , ^ .liJ 1SHIPPING.MR. ALEXANDER SHAW sent the following report:-&quot;(1) SHIPPING FREIGHTS.The Index Number for June will probably be somewhat lower than the May Index.River Plate rates for grain fell from 28/6d per ton at the beginning, to 22/6d at the end of the month, and rates for grain from United States (Northern Range) from 3/6d a quarter at the beginning, to 2/6d In the middle, of the month, improving to 3/- at the end of the month.&quot;(2) There are no new figures for shipbuilding or for laidup tonnage.&quot;(3) Coal exports and bunker coal shipped were both higher in May than in April, and bunker coal was cheaper&quot;.&quot;INDEX NUMBER OF SHIPPING FREIGHTS.1920 * 100. 1913 &quot; 100.May 1927 ...........      29,00 12:&apos;.&quot;?3April 1927  .........     28.44 121 5May 1926 ...........      22.78 97.4&quot;LAID UP TONNAGE.Tonnage Laid up at the principalports of Great Britain and Ireland.British and Foreign Net Tons.April 1st, 1927 ..........    239,681 - lowest figures sincereturns first collected In January 1921.January 1st, 1927  ........    364,874April 1st, 1926 ..........    359,848Returns for July 1st, 1927, are now being collected but will not be available for two or three weeks.&quot;TONNAGE UNDER CONSTRUCTION.Gross Tons.March 31st, 1927 ....... In U.K.......      1,216,932Abroad  .......      1,35.2,9322,569 ,864December 31st, 1926 ....  In U*K.Abroad.March 51st,  1926 .......  In U.K.Abroad	76 0,084	172 ,9431,	933,027	843 0701,	16&apos;7 ,13601	010,206
CONFIDENTIAL. SKIPPING (CONTp.)&quot; TONNAGE LAUNCHED.Gt.Britain &amp; Ireland : Gross Tons.Gross Tons.Abroad.Gross Tons.TotalMar. 31st, 1927.... Dec. 31st, 1926.... Mar. 31st,  1926. .. .Quarter ended:127,747 67,853 190,705161,048 342,42 3 269 ,868268,795 410,276 460,573TONNAGE COMMENCED.Quarter ended: Mar. 31st, 1927 Dec. 31st,  1926.... Mar. 31st, 1926----579,839 152,404 193,121367,046 271,237 164 , 343946,865 423,641 387,464RAILWAY TRAFFIC.MR. HURCCMB said that, to arrive at a satisfactory comparison, it would he best to set the figures of railway receipts for the first 25 weeks of the year against those for the corresponding period in 1925.    They showed that, for the four groups of railways together there was a decrease this year of about  2,000,000 in passenger receipts, and an increase of about  2,000,000 in general merchandise figures other than coal,   with an increase of about  1,250,000 in coal.    The net improvement for the four groups together was approximately  l,40o,000.    That improvement, however, was not equally distributed.    The London, Midland and Scottish was in fact about the same as in 1925, and the Southern was slightly worse off, so that the increase was distributed between the Great Western and the London and North Eastern.   As to the decline in passenger receipts, it had to be remembered that the Wembley traffic was a very substantial addition in 1925, and accounted for a large part of the drop in the figures for this year.   Again, in considering receipts from merchandise and coal, there 7*-as an Increase, as the Council was well aware, in the rates of something over 6 per cent, in February last, and that accounted for a large part of the rise in goods receipts.MR. PHILLIPS said that, apart from a \temporary increase it Whitsuntide, the unemployment total had remained fairly steady for some time in the neighbourhood of a million. Indeed, apart from the V/whitsun increase the difference between the highest and lowest figures recorded since the end of April was not more th&amp;n about 50,000.EMPLOYMENT.
EMPLOYMENT (CONTD.) .At w*hi tsuntide there had been the usual Increase in temporary stoppages, amounting this year to something over 100,000, but practically this affected the figures for only one week, or at most two weeks.   Judging by the experience of past years we had now reached the time of year when the net effect of seasonal tendencies began to be adverse; co that, unless these tendencies were counterbalanced, by a general improvement, an increase in the unemployment total was to be expected between now and the autumn.GENEVA ECONOMIC COKFI^RSNCF,.SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR, one of the delegates from this country, said that the Conference had found some difficulty from the French and from the Soviets..    The French had cere with preconceived Ideas of what they wanted; and it tecame essential to put up a resistance to their proposals, bit by bit, and to wind up by resisting them entirely.    Some concession was made to them as to the future organisation of the Economic Section of the League of Nations, and that was all they got.There was a general concensus of opinion at the Conference that tariffs were too high and too complicated, and that they changed too often and with too little notice.    Some very strong resolutions had been passed on these matters.    It was shown what a number of tariff wars there had been in Europe since the Peace Treaty and the breaking up of various countries.   V/hat was said was really based on the Trade Barriers report of the International Chamber of Commerce. Since the passing of those resolutions the Dutch, Belgians and Czecho-Slovakians had made statements on the lines of the resolutions; and in particular the Minister of Economics in Germany had made a clear announcement that the German Government was prepared and determined, to set an example by reducing its tariffs.    Tne French were in a very difficult position because their proposed new and increased tariff was before the world, but finally they gave way and unanimously subscribed to all the resolutions.The Soviet delegates issued nothing but propaganda.    They cut a very poor figure.    They gave the impression that they were living from hand to mouth, and did not know where they stood.   For instance, they made a speech one day, and evidently got instructions from Moscow   the next and tried to get out of what they had said.    Their form of propaganda was extremely dangerous.    They had a letter purporting to be signed by Mr. McKenna to the effect that the Midland Bank were prepared to give them  20,000,000 of credit instead of  10,000,000. They shewed this to, the Germans who were very much Impressed.   Two members of the German delegation told Sir A, Balfour about it, and he wired to this country and got  the facts&apos;.   Mc. McKenna said he never wrote a letter of such a description.    Then the
CO-NiiliJiSMriAL..GENEVA ECONOMIC CONFERENCE (OONTD.) . If Q a soviet delegates made a very vindictive speech against Great Britain and Sir Arthur had occasion to reply to them clearly and shortly.     They went straight to the Germans after he had spoken and said:    &quot;You heard Sir Arthur Balfour&apos;s speech, but you do not realise that his firm are giving us large credits for two years.&quot;    Again the Germans were impressed and came to him for the truth.   He told them he had refused to do any business with Russia for two years; that he had previously sold them a lot of steel which had boon rolled before the war, and which he could not sell anywhere else; that he had taken one-third in cash, one-third at three months and one-third at six months; and that they still owed him  36,000 out of  100,000.   He also had occasion to inform them that he might have to make a speech on China, and he kept that threat hanging over them.    He had been able in that way to head off trouble from them, and he never made the speech.   The Soviets made a strong demand that the Conference should recognise their system of trading, and say they were fit to do business with.     A struggle arose on that and their demand broke down.On the industry side the Conference made an endeavour to get international statistics on some kind of comparable basis, as regards methods of classification, nomenclature and so on.    It passed a fairly strong resolution on that.   Then there was a big question on industrial agreements, national and international. The French had come determined to secure a complete blessing for national and international cartels as a panacea for all the economic ills of the world today.    That Idea was, however, entirely exploded.    It was shown that cartels were appropriate in certain industries where the articles manufactured were comparable and produced in mass, but the French pressed the point that industrial cartels and agreements would lead to a reduction of tariffs, and they pressed it so far that the Germans were forced to point out that it had had quite a contrary effect with them, and that the French themselves had deliberately used tariffs to force them into their cartels on their terms.There was a desire on the part of some members of the Conference to set up at Geneva an International Bureau to control industrial cartels and international agreements, but after a week&apos;s discussion it became clear to them that this was not a feasible proposition; that, after all, each industrial cartel or international agreement wherever it operated in another nation, came under the laws of that nation; that the laws of all the nations were different and that Internationa,! control was not practicable; and that the most one could get would be a collection of statistics and other information.     Further, it was brought home to the Conference that unless there was to be rationalization in agriculture, and unless it was to be adhered to systematically, and the selling of the product done without great waste, there was no hope for industry and commerce in this world. All increased selling power and increased production had to comegfc the outset from agriculture, and agriculture received a blessing and a recognition which it had not had for a very long time.      It was also made very clear that nations who were developing their industry must not run away with the idea that they could industrialize their countries completely, but it would be wise to try and keep some balance between agriculture and corameroe.
CONFIDENTIAL. GENEVA ECONOMIC CONFERENCE (OONTD.).Lastly there was a cortaln   section, including the French who were supported in this by their Government, who showed a determination to set up at Geneva a large bureau of Industry and commerce, parallel with the Labour Bureau,   There was much opposition to that, there were very great dangers in it, and it was to &quot;be hoped that the British Government would not subscribe to the idea.   One of the reasons was that the Dominions would not stand the expense; they had Intimated as much.     Then there was enough in the way of organisation at Geneva already; and in approaching industrial and commercial matters, it was the people who were engaged In the business at the moment that were required. If a permanent bureau were set up, the members would get out of date.    It was much better to have a good economic committee calling in to its aid from time to time, - as was done in the case of the preparatory committee, for Instance, - people who were really active In business and fit at the time to deal with those questions. If there was onoe a bureau established there, it would have quite the contrary effect,THE- PRESIDENT agreed that it was much better to keep the present Economic Committee, perhaps reinforced, with power to consult, whenever they desired, the best people they could get.    If a large organization was set up it would become stereotyped, it would collect masses of information and issue endless questionnaires which would not lead anywhere, and people would try to use It for their own ends.    On the other hand, the value of this reoent conference was that practical men met together   quite unfettered, and laid down certain principles.   The proper oourse the us would be to follow up any negotiations which might be upened by the League of Nations or otherwise, on the lines of those principles, using this conference and its resolutions to re-inforoe the particular objeot which we might be aiming at.SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR added that we should also have to take some trouble to train more young men in this country in this kind of business of international negotiation, because it was falling on too few shoulders; it was becoming a skilled occupation.   The sucoess of this conference depended on a few men who had. international experience, who spoke foreign languages, and who were known to the representatives of other nations.    If we got the wrong people at one of these oonferences we might be landed in all kindB of difficulties. VJe would have to be extremely careful, because the other representatives were very skilled; the Germans, particularly were training people specially for this work.COLONEL WTLLEY emphasized our need of what were really commercial diplomats to deal with questions of international moment in these Conferences.   The question of Russia had also been raised. One quite understood that few bills were being drawn on Russia at present.     It appeared, also, that while
GFJVEVA ECONOMIC CONFERENCE.  (CONTP)their purchases of wool had continued, practically nothing had been done in tea or jute or machinery.     As to what Sir Arthur Balfour had said with fcegard to the fraud of marking Italian goods as goods produced in this country (see section on International Chamber of Commerce), that was frequently practised.     Col. flilley had seen in Italian mlll3 packages with English label3 on, for export to the British Colonies.     But in this country he had seen a mill in Yorkshire putting up Yorkshire-made commodities with German labels on, for export to Chinaj so it worked both ways .INTERNATIONAL CHAMBER OF COMMERCE.SIR ARTHUR BALFOUR   said that at the recent Stockholm meeting there were nearly 1,000 delegates from about 40 nations, the Germans being 145 strong, America 165, and our-selves 80.     It unanimously endorsed the Economic Committeers Geneva Report, and had given its reasons.The Americans were getting to the point at which, in spite of all their talk, they saw that if they were still going to invest money in Europe, as they would in fact still have to, the only way they were going to get their interest was in goods.     Again there was trouble with the French, Their spokesman made a statement that the French tariff was not high enough and that they were going to put It higher. His colleagues were very much disturbed, and all the other delegates went to them and said: &quot;If that is what you are going to do, and if the French franc goes to 200, you must not be surprised if people will not lend you money.&quot;   Finally they completely withdrew the speech, and said they saw it would not do, and that they would have to come into line with other people.     It was not oertain, however, that they would do it, although their delegates were people of great influence. But, apart from the formal resolutions, every delegate under-took to go home and do- some active propaganda towards a more rational system of Industry and commerce for the world, and requests might be expected in this country for deputations to be received from Chambers of Commerce and other people asking for some kind of declaration to be made about the Eoonomic Conference.     It was true that Mr. Samuel had made a statement In the House of Commons on the subject, but if some general declaration could be made soon, it might save some hard work In receiving these deputations.An immense amount of unofficial work had been done at Stockholm.     Our coal exporters oame out there with a speech which they were going to make about the French coal licencing soheme.
INTERNATIONAL CHAMBER OF COMMERCE (CONTD) .First, however, the British delegates got the French delegates together and told them they had better read the speech.     They were very disturbed about it;  they oomnunioated it to the Minister in Paris. and had undertaken to send a deputation to ii. Tardieu, and point out that if we in this country were suddenly to make up our minus that, for instance, we would not have French steel in except under licence, they must not be astonished, because they were asking for trouble.Another point raised was the fraud going on in Italy In selling textiles with a false indication of British origin.    Our delegates were promised by the Italians that this would be brought to the notice of M. Mussolini and that it would be Btopped at once.   There were about a dozen little conferences like that on similar matters, where a lot of useful work for British trade was done, quite outside the official work, and the British representatives had come back from Stockholm very well satisfied with the results accomplished.The British Delegation was excellent, itwap -veil organised and had a Chairman for every subject,with a committee under him which had studied the subjeot and met here before they went out;  indeed, the organisation of the British Delegation was the admiration of the French and the Germans and everyone else.    There was a real force in the International Chamber of Commerce, but we had to get more people in this country to take an interest ; in these things;    if we did not we should not keep up our prestige or hold our own in international negotiations.THE PRESIDENT, in congratulating Sir Arthur Balfour and his colleagues on their work at Geneva and at Stockholm, desired to enforce what he himself had said months before the Economic Conference started, as to the importance of industries getting more men who were prepared to take part in international work.    He felt sure that there was no question of a company&apos;s interests being sacrificed by allowing one of their able men to take part In this kind of work, but that   he would turn out to be still more useful to the company from having undertaken it.TRADE VISIT TO VIRGINIA.MR. VYLE stated that twenty-five members of the Chambers of Commerce accepted an Invitation from the State of Virginia to go over there and see their industries.    They were there twc weeks, and had a well organized tour.   Their reception everywhere wan extremely cordial;   Virginia, though Amerioah in name, appeared to be essentially British in spirit.   B&quot;*rom there they went up to the Middle^West to Chioago,    Detroit and New York, and in all those places, even in Chicago&apos;, they were received with very great cordiality.
TRADE VISIT TO VIRGINIA (CONTD.)Ship-building really did not exist on the Virginia sea-board, although they had very large facilities.   Some 400 boats were already there, thoroxighly seaworthy and ready to be used as soon as they could find some occasion for using them;   and when it was remembered that there was a still larger number on the Pacific coa3t, and some 300 or 4 00 up the Hudson, it was evident that there would not &quot;be much shipbuilding business going on there.   With regard to coal, their coal shipping facilities were vastly in excess of what they were able to use at the present time.   They had had a wonderful run when our coal strike was on, but that was over now.    This gave an opportunity of pointing out that we bought from them about 4-1 times as much as they bought from us of our domestic manufacture, and of making a suggestion to them that instead of boats going back there in ballast, they should fill them up on the return journey with British goods and make a two-way trade in that way.   As to how they could pass the tariff wall, it was rather a domestic matter for them.   They were quite responsive on the seaboard.    Up country also they began thinking about it; and there was no doubt that they could afford to buy a great deal more from us in spite of their tariffs.   Mr. Vyle told them that the best opportunity they could have of seeing how to set up this return trade was to come over to the British Industries Fair and see the sort of goods they could buy.    Their prosperity at the present moment was very great and looked as if it was going to continue.   There were two schools of thought, however; the bankers, who were professional pessimists, and thought that there might be some trouble very shortly;    and the others who thought there was no reason why the whole of this tremendous prosperity should not continue, andvho pointed to a great increase in life insurance and to the savings of the w hole people, as an indication that in spite of their indulgence in so much purchase by deferred payments, there was. solid capital at the back of each person.   However, there was some real misgiving on account of the deferred payment system.     They pointed out that the whole nation Tfas in debt, and that should tnere be a break-down at any point the effect would be felt all along the line.MR. SAMUEL asked whether Mr.Vyle got the impression that it was a system which should be discouraged here.MR. VYLE said he did not gather that;    within reason It was all right...AUSTRALIAlv TRADE.MR. SANDERSON observed that the weather conditions continued to be the main topic of interest in Australia for the moment.   The agricultural districts had had beneficial rains, and it depended a good deal on the next couple of months what the harvest was likely to be; but in the pastoral districts, with very fev; exceptions, the drought was still bad and the shearing which would steit next noihand go onf or the next;d 7
australian  LIA N   TRADE.(CONTD.)two or three months, would reveal what the losses among the sheep and the lambs had been.    The cattle industry was still handicapped by high costs and low prices.Two rather important developments in the business world had taken place during the last two or three months.    One was the visit of Sir Ernest Harvey of the Bank of England; the opportunity was taken of his being there to have conferences between the Commonwealth and the Associated Banks, and a Committee of the Associated Banks was formed to confer with the Commonwealth Bank.    The second development was the agreement recently reached between the Commonwealth Government and the various States with regard to loans.    The agreement was to be placed before the electors by a referendum. Unfortunately no referendum, k^Sanderson thought, had yet been successful, but it was confidently anticipated that this one would be an exception;    and it seemed likely that the Commonwealth Government would be able to bring into line with them the State Governments, and probably also, therefore, the electors in the States.    This would, accordingly, be likely to have a big influence e,n future financial transactions out in the Commonwealth.INDIAN   TRADE.MR. LINDSAY observed that since the last meeting of the Advisory Council the report of the Indian Tariff Board on the Textile Inquiry had been published.   Briefly, the majority of the members of the Board had proposed a bonus on the ma-nu- -v -facture of yarn In India, the funds to be found from an increase in the import duty on cotton piecegoods from 11 to 15 per cent.    The minority report of the chairman had been against the grant of the bonus and had suggested further    -that the Inorease from 11 to 15 per cent, should operate against Japan only.    The Government of India, however, had announced that they were against both the bonus and the increase in import duties.    In regard to the Japanese side of the question, which was the one Mr.Lindsay desired specially to refer to, India&apos;s trade position with Japan explained the decision of the Government.    Last year   Japan had sold to India  12,000,000 sterling worth of goods and had bought from her  30,000,000 worth; so that she was a very important customer and the trade balance was entirely in India&apos;s favour. Again, Japan had sold to India  8,000,000 sterling worth of cotton goods of all classes - yarn-, hosiery, and piece goods - but had bought from her  25,000,000 worth of raw cotton. Incidentally India&apos;s trade with Europe in cotton piece goods and raw cotton followed very much the same line.    To take one example: Italy sold to India cotton piece goods worth about  750,000 and bought from her raw cotton to the value of nearly  4,000,000.The Government of India were considering a scheme for the
INDIAN TRADE,  (C ONTD.)improvement of road traffic in India, which would probably include a sys-tem of taxation of motor vehicles, the funds to be devoted to the improvement of roads.     On the general crop position the monsoon seemed to be developing satis-factorily.     That morning a preliminary forecast of the jute crop, which was the only crop of importance at the moment, had been received.     This showed that an acreage of about 50Q 000 acres less than last year had been sown, but last yearfs acreage had been abnormally high.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.MR. HOSE wrote:-&quot;The policy of economy in publio administration inaugu--rated in Chile some months ago by Colonel Ibanez, who&apos; was recently elected Presidentf is being continued, and an endeavour is being made to avoid further external borrowing so far as possible.     A project, however, is before Congress for consolidating the debt of the State railways, and, for this purpose, an issue is proposed to be made abroad, probably through the newly appointed Government fiscal agents, the National City Bank of New York in the United States and Messrs, Rothschilds in Great Britain,&quot;It 13 part of the declared policy of the present Chilean Government to afford protection to the national industries, and. in this connection, the Finance Minister Has decreed an increase  of the import duties on bottles, glassware, etcr, of approximately 50%r     In addition, as a means of protection for the paper industry, only printing paper will In future be admitted into the country free of duty.     No detail3 are yet to hand regarding the composition of the new Customs Tariff,, which is under consideration, but the new duties will no doubt refleot the Governments desire to protect home manufacturers,&quot;Although the Presidential elections passed off normally, no general improrement in business conditions has followed, excepting a slight increase in the volume of buying by importers and wholesalers for future deliverya      When the new Customs duties come into force, importation in some lines is almost bound to be adversely affected, but prospects for future trade conditions nevertheless appear somewhat brighter.&quot;During the pasA month, sales of Chilean nitrate have continued to be made under the free selling system.   The level of prices, although still substantially below the fixed scale ruling a year ago, has been steady to firm.     The total amount of the fertiliser disposed of since the introduction of free selling on 14th April last is now 882,000 metric tons, refined -nitrate having been sold at up to 17s. 4d, per metric quintal and ordinary at prices ranging from about 16s.4d. to 17s. per metric quintal.     On this basis, a fairly substantial reduoticn Is taking place in stocks of nitrate in Chile, but, owing to the low levels of prices, only those companies having very low
SOUTH AMERIOAN TRADE (CONTD.).production costs arc working profitably.   The situation is unlikely to be remedied until a reduction is made in the heavy export duties - a change regarding wLi*h the Government has deferred a decision until after June 1928.   Arrangements are already being made, however, for mitigating to some extent the &quot;burden of taxation on the Indus try by way of enforcing reduced tariffs on the railways for the carriage of nitrate and for fuel for the ofioinas, lower import duties on jute sacks, eto.   Results attending the new system of nitrate production installed by the Guggenheim Company at the Coya Norte oficlna, as well as those of the process Invented by M. Prudhomme, are awaited with the greatest interest by the producers.&quot;The latest reports to hand regarding the general situation in Argentina indicate that, although light and fairly general rains have occurred over the agricultural zones, more rain Is still required.   Ploughing and sewing operations for the wheat, linseed, and oats crops are proceeding slowly on aocount of frosts.    On the other hand, results in respect to the current maize crop ensure that the yield will be abundant, and probably far above normal.    Ihe dry, cold weather has been favourable to tho picking and shelling operations, and shipments of maize in good condition have been taking place on a large scale.      Although exports, especially of grain, continue heavy, no very substantial improvoment haB yet taken place In the general trade situation, commercial failures, both in Buenos Aires and the Interior, being still somewhat extensive. Quotations in Buenos Aires for maize and linseed are firm since a month ago, but wheat and oat3 have cheapened.   The tendency in exchange has been firm, at slightly above the parity rate of 47.58d. per gold peso.&quot;The Argentine Government has recently negotiated in Spain a loan of Ptas.100,000,000 to provide partly for the construction of two destroyers in Spanish shipyards.   The full amount of the loan has been taken up by some of the principal Spanish banks, and it is understood that no public issue will take place.nA conference recently held between the various.coffee growing States of Brazil proved a success from the point of view of the Coffee Institute.    The States of Minas Geraes, Rio de Janeiro, and Sspirito Santo undertook to come into line with the State of Sao Paulo in regard to the limitations of entries of coffee into their respective port3 during the current season.     The success of the coffee Conference,  as well as recent official pronouncements, has created an excellent impression in the local market,   and anxiety regarding the distribution of the present heavy crop haB largely disappeared. Expectations in regard to the outlook are generally optimistic. In regard to the general trade situation in Brazil, it is of speoial interest to note that, owing to the construction of new roads in progress, a heavy domand for engineering supplies has recently been a feature in the markets for imported goods. Mail advices from Rio de Janeiro state that the commercial situation there has shown some improvement, an advance having taken place in the prioes of sugar and cotton.    A slight betterment in conditions is also reported in the markets of the Interior.
2 i) south AMERICAN TRADE (CONTD. ) .&quot;No improvement has yet occurred in economic conditions in Mexico.    Business is extremely quiet, and oredit facilities are restricted.    The Mexican Government has directed all State Departments to refrain from purchasing supplies in the United states for use in the administration of public services, this action being said to be a reprisal for an embargo place-* by the United States on goods consigned to: the Mexican Governm&amp;ec,&quot;In Colombia, the continued inflow of funds from the United States offset to some extent the reoent decline in coffee prices, but slow progress is being made in general trade conditions.   The state of the River Magdalena is satisfactory, and, given normal weather, should now remain so until the end of the year.    The Colombian Government has been conducting loan negotiations in New York for a maximum amount of U.S.^60,000,000, of which U.S.$30,000,000 has already been plaoed.&quot;The flowering of the coffee trees in Nioaragua has been very heavy this season, and there is every indication of a large crop.    It is expected that gathering will commence In November this year - a month earlier than is usual.   The President of the United States has recently appointed an official representative to supervise the Presidential elections to take place in Nicaragua in 1928&quot;,
CONFIDENTIAL, ANNEX.Some leading statistical data indicating the trend of th(Information received up to 16thEmployment:Unemployed on live register (including persons on short time receiving benefit)............................Railway Reoeipts week ended -Goods Traffio (Gross)................Passenger Traffio (Gross)............Production:Coal, output during week ended ..    ....Pig Iron output during month .....  ....Steel output during month...........  ,Prioes: Wholesale: 3oard of Trade Index No. (1913 &quot; 100):Food................................Materials...........................Total...............................United Kingdom Trade ttNet Imports..........................Exports (Domestic Produce)............Vessels laid up In United Kingdom Ports?British..............................Foreign.............................Shipping Freights: Chamber of Shipping Index NO. (1920 a 100) .......................Bank Clearings:Country Cheque and Provincial, week ended,. Percentages of Advances to Deposits(London Clearing Banks).................Money market:Bank rate..............................Market rate 3 months1 Bank Bills ..........Discount (3 months&apos; Treasury Bills)  ......Latest.4th July Wholly un-employed. Other . ..9th July. ii2nd July.June, tiii it iiii ii1st April, itJune.9th July.661,900 391,700June.2,003,400 1,902,600Tons. , 4,848,900 550,500 747,300156.0 134.2 141.8 88,711,923 55,981,796 Net tons 228,049 11,63226.91 108,860,000 54.04&quot;o7a15th July.&quot;        4. 6s. 1.34d,1st financial 4. 7* Approximate weekly average for Juno, 1913, t Monthly average for 1913.tt The figures for the present year, for a year ago and of Great Britain and Northern Ireland with the Irish foreign trade of the Irish Free State; the 1913 flgu inclusive of the latter.
of the Soonomic situation in Great Britain.. Ito 16th July, 1927).P JO&apos;0P i-0&apos; 21 &apos;iij	A	A	Two	At oorres-month		year	year 8	ponding dateennlior		earlier.	earlier.	in 1913.	637,299	869,609	)	No	452,341	775,461	) 1,300,350	comparable	1,089,640	1,645,070	)	data.	 	 	 	 	1,638,100	1,139,100	2,007,100	1,138,800	1,834,100.	1,702,800	2,069,700	1,158,200	Tons.	Tons,	Tons.	Tons.	5,102,900	Mines stopped	4,676,200	5,626,000*	720yl00.	April,539,100	510,300	855,000t	884,600	661,000	585,400	638,600t	152.7	156,7	166,0	Average for	134.9	141,5	152.5	1913 b	141.1	146.9	157.2	100.	 	 	 	 84,043,757		-86,780,981	100,384,559	49,769,296.    63,275,874		50,107,041	58,893,190	42,837,462Net tons.		Net tons.	Net tons.	1st Jan,  352,416		347,066	377,461	-	12,458	12,782	15,601	-	29.21	23.71	23.65	average^e for				1913 s				23.40.	 	 	 	 f	39,559,000	90,054,000	93,945,000	49,367,000	55,1	53.3	52.1	-	4k%		5/&amp;	4$	45/l6^	45/16^		 4, 7	3. 7.26d,	 4. 7s. 0.18d,	 4.4s.6.4ld.    -  1	i.(to and for two years ago, include the trade lq Irish Free State and exclude the direct H3 figures are exclusive of the former and

FLUCTUATIONS DURING THE PERIOD APRIL 1926 JUNE 1927.

</content>
</cab>
