<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/188/0 images: 268-269</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1927SECRET. Copy No.    30CP. 232 (27).CABINET.SPECIAL  REPORT  ON   UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 148.   August 1927.THIS Report gives a summary of the recently published returns of unemployment in the various industries. In Table (A) is shown the course of uneinplojunent during August, while Table (B) gives an analysis of the number of persons on the registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at the 29th August, 1927.(A.) Number of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges inGreat Britain.	1925.	1926.	1927.						Increase (4-) or Decrease ( ) since July 25, 1927.	Aug. 31.	Aug. 30.	July 25.	Aug. 1.	Aug. 8.	Aug. 15.	Aug. 22.	Aug. 29.	Men .. Boys .. Women Girls ..	1,058,384 44,370 217,105 34,443	1,168,457 47,148 288,553 45,601	816,031 33,062 148,190 29,619	899,908 36,135 153,192 30,593	805,480 34,489 152,995 31,777	802,000 35,563 152,041 32,546	819,306 36,111 155,382 33,556	823,444 35,959 156,081 33,777	4-    7,413 4-    2,897 4-    7,891 4-    4,158Total..	1,354,302	1,549,759	1,026,902	1,119,828	1,024,741	1,022,150	1,044,355	1,049,261	4-  22,359Notk (1) : The above figures represent the number of persons registered at Local Offices as applicants for employment. In the main they relate to persons who had claims to benefit current and were not at work on the dates given.(2)   The figures for the 30th August, 1926, were affected by the dispute in the Coal Mining Industry.(3) The latest figure available, viz., for the week ended the 19th September, 1927, is given in Part (D) of this Report.(B.) Analysis of the Number of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at the 29th August, 1927.-	Men.	Boys.	Women.	Girls.	Total.	Increase ( 4-) or Decrease (-) since July 25, 1927.Wholly unemployed Temporary stoppages Casuals..	554,286 206,928 62,230	28,918 6,940 101	78,471 76,990 620	28,713 5,056 8	690,388 295,914 62,959	4-    32,226 -    13,159 4-      3,292Total	823,444	35,959	156,081	33,777	1,049,261	4-    22,359[10623i
(C.) Unemployment in Insured Industries.The latest date for which unemployment figures by industries are available is the 22nd August, 1927, at which date the percentage unemployed in Great Britain and Northern Ireland was 9&apos;4, as compared with 9&apos;3 at the 25th July, 1927, with 14*0 at the 23rd August, 1926, and with 12*1 at the 24th August, 1925. The figures at the 22nd August, 1927, in respect of industries showing appreciable variations in unemployment during the month, together with the increase or deorease as compared with the previous month and with a year ago are given in the table below : Industry.	M umber of Insured Persons recorded as Unemployed at August 22, 1927.	Increase (-f-) or Decrease (-) compared with 			July 25, 1927.	Aug. 23, 1926*All Insured Industries.. Tailoring Cotton Distributive Trades Construction and Repair of Motor Vehicles, Cycles and Aircraft v^ Cocoa, Chocolate and Sugar Confectionery Building Pig-iron Manufacture (Blast Furnaces) .. Canal, River, Dock and Harbour Service.. Public Works Contracting, &amp;c. Coal Mining	1,129,953	-1-    15,990	  554,554	15,625 57,292 73,282 21,434 7,732 62,214 4,622 41,331 26,004 244,777	+      5,485 -t-      3,750 +     3,256 +     3,095 +      2,794 +      1,997 +      1,547 +      1,513 +      1,149 -    13,489	- 8,537 - 78,335 - 29,729 - 3,183 - 59 - 13,024 - 11,202 - 20,319 - 6,077 -f  136,154** The figures for the 23rd August, 1926, were affected by the dispute in the Coal Mining Industry and in the case of the Coal Industry itself the unemployment figures were exclusive of persons in the industry -who ceased work on account of the dispute.(D.) Latest Figures.The latest figure of unemployment published is that for the 19th September, giving the total number on the registers as 1,048,000. This is a decrease over the position on the 29th August amounting to 1,261, and a decrease over a year ago of 482,884.ARTHUR STEEL-MAITLAND.Ministry of Labour,September 26, 1927.The percentage of unemployment (Great Britain) in the insured industries at the undermentioned dates was August 24, 1925    .... ........ ....   H&quot;923, 1926     .... ........ ....   13-822, 1927    .... .... .... 9&apos;3 (men only 10-9)

</content>
</cab>
