<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/188/0 images: 294-310</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Memorandum by the Home Secretary.I should like to bring to the notice of ray colleagues the constitution and working of the College of Arms which present certain unsatisfactory features to which attention is called in the attached memorandum.The activities of the College have long been a source of considerable anxiety to the Home Office, and, unless the abuses referred to are remedied,  I fear that they will sooner or later bring about a public scandal of a kind which the subversive elements in the community will be quick to exploit for their own purposes.    It is only,  I feel, by determining to eliminate what is useless and out of date,  if not positively vicious, that we shall be able to preserve from attack those traditional forms and observances which are of real value in the constitutional development of the Empire.    In my view, the remedy should be applied as quickly and as unobtrusively as possible.I accordingly propose, and His Majesty     has signified his approval, that a Committee of&quot; Enquiry should he set up to &quot;consider the constitution and present working of the College and to make recommendations for their improvement&quot; .    I think that the Enquiry, which should be of a private character, should be conducted by persons of Ministerial standing, and I would propose a small Committee of, say, three Cabinet Ministers with whom might be associated,  if thought fit, the Deputy Earl Marshal and a senior member of the Royal Household.W.J.H.13th October,  1927.CABINET. \-&amp;SECRET. _ ^   &quot;&quot;O.P. 242(27).CONSTITUTION AND WORKING OF THE COLLEGE OP HERALDS.
The position of the College of Arms is an anomaly and gives rise to constant difficulties.The College of Arms is.a corporation (created by Queen Mary) consisting of three Kings of Arms, six Heralds and four Persui*/ant3.    They are appointed by the Crown on the nomination of the Earl Marshal, who is responsible for directing them in the exercise of their duties.    They are officers of the Royal Household and as such receive small salaries  (ranging from  49.1.4 for Garter to  13, 19. 0 for a Persui&apos;/ant) and are very occasionally required to perform services in connection with state ceremonials0    Under their charter and warrants of appointment they possess the power of granting armorial bearings,  and they also do work for private clients in the investigation of pedigrees and similar matters.The great bulk of their receipts comes from these latter classes of work.    The incomes of the different heralds no doubt vary according to the business connection,  energy, or good luck of the individual, and for obvious reasons no particulars are available,  but it is understood that successful heralds may make very substantial sums.It will be obvious from the foregoing that the English College of Arms is essentially a mediaeval survival.    Its members are not,  like the Eoyal Household, proper, under the -personal control of the Sovereign:-    and they are not,  like civil servants, under the control of a Minister responsible to the Sovereign and Parliament.    The only authority to which they are subject is that of the Earl Marshal, who is a hereditary feudal officer not responsible in any way to Parliament and owing to the hereditary nature of his office not effectively responsible to the Crown.The experience of the Home Office goes to show that the Earl Marshal does not in practice exercj.se much control over the College,  but on the contrary is guided by them and acts as their mouthpiece.
This wtate of affairs has led to actions on the partf&apos; the members of the College which have been severely criticised by successive Secretari.es of State and riven ground for f,rave misgivings as to their possible effect on the prestige of the crown and its Prerogative.    They have, as it ill be seen from this memorandum,  in many cases attempted to interfere with the exercise by the Secretary of State of his constitutional responsibility for advising the Crown on petitions submitted by subjects;    they have adopted practices in connection with matters within their jurisdiction which seem highly improper in themselves,  and calculated to bring the Royal Prerogative into contempt.The Home Office comes into contact with the College ofArms over certain classes of cases in which individuals petitionthe Crown for the Royal permission to enjoy some privilege inthe nature of an honour.    These are Royal licences for( change of name (( change of arms (( the use of foreign titles (( supporters (( special precedence . Such petitions are usually prepared by a member of the College, who aots as agent for the petitioner (of course for payment). The three Kings of Arms collectively or  (in some cases) Garter as the Chief Officer of the  College,  are asked to advj.se  the Secretary of State on the applications,   since they relate to matters which are supposed to be within their special knowledge, and the Royal licence,  if granted,  is addressed to the Earl Marshal and directed to be officially recorded in the College.Obviously the members of the College are placed in a -very anomalous position.    It is true that when one of the Kings of Arms is agent it is usual for the other two only to report upon the petition;    but this arrangement gives them obvious motives for not being too hard on each other&apos;s applications, and in any
case, as heavy fees are payable on the grant of Royal licences, the College collectively is strongly interested in promoting and ensuring the success of as many petitions as possible.The purx*oce of this eiemorandum is to give some concrete illustrations of the unsatisfactory state of affairs and of the difficultie3 which the attitude of the College causes in dealing with petitions to the King.(1) Change of iTame.A Royal licence for a change of name has no more legal validity than the other methods  (deed poll, or advertisement in the Press) .   It is therefore obviously undesirable that His Majesty should be troubled with petitions for these licences, and the Home Office discourages them, except in the case of peers and baronets, where hereditary titles are involved.    But the heralds persistently maintain,  j.n season and out of season, the doctrine that a Royal licence is &quot;the only proper way for a gentleman to change his name&quot; - a view to which it need hardly be said that the Home Office lends no support,  and in more than one case recently this feeling has led the College or members of it into proceedings which are very unseemly on the part of an official body.    Thus a petitioner informed the Home Office that he had been told by a Herald that to change his name by deed poll was to defraud the revenue.   And when Defence of the Realm Regulation Ho.14 H (forbidding changes of name by persons not natural-born British subjects (but containing an exception for changes of name by Royal licence)) was issued,  a member of the College gave an interview to the &quot;Evening iTews&quot;  in which he stated that &quot;to get a fresh name by deed poll is practically to pass under an alias&quot;  adding &quot;the only gentlemanly way to make the alteration is to come to the College&quot;.    In 1915 Windsor (then Mr. Lindsay&apos;) went so far as to address a formal complaint to the Secretary of State about the conduct of the Home Office in regard, to these petitions for change of name, alleging that it &quot;seriously hampered the professional business of the officers
of arms&quot;.   He actually stated in writing (a) that the Ho^ia) 0 Office when submitting applications did not acquaint the Sovereign with the facts of the case:    (b) that the present form of refusal was offensive to the applicants and was a recent innovation.    It is hardly necessary to say that as all petitions go to the King in original, it is the fault of the petitioner or his agent if His Majesty has not the facts before him;    and that the form of refusal is a traditional form of unknown antiquity which the late King Edv/ard expressly directed should be used for all petitions. (2) Change of Arms.It is held that a Royal licence is necessary to enable a man to take the arms of another family than his own.    Most of the petitions are put forward in consequence of a will or settlement requiring the petitioner to take the arms of a relative on succeeding to an estate, and these usually present no difficulty.    But the Home Office has clear evidence that when the College found that licences were not granted for change of name alone they began to advise applicants who were petitioning for a change of name to ask for a change of arms as well, whether they wanted it or not,  because in this way they would stand a better chance of getting the Royal licence.    Two cases are given herewith,  in which this proceeding created a ludicrous situation.    In one of these the applicant wished to assume the name and quarter the arms of his step-grandmotherr it was ascertained from the agent that this lady&apos;s family had never had arms,  and arms would have to be invented for the family (of which no male representative was known to exist) in order that the applicant might quarter them.    In the other a new baronet who had for many years used the double name Gwynne-Evans asked for ,a licence to continue the name and quarter the arms of Gwynne.    The name Gwynne was purely a fancy oner    the applicant claimed no connection with any family named Gwynne?    and the proposal was that a coat of arms should be
indented fox&apos; a non-existent family in order that he mightquarter it.   When such applications as these are put forward bymembers of the College of Arms acting as agents and are returnedby the Kings of Arms with a favourable report, no one canpossibly take the College seriously when it claims to be theguardian of the traditions of heraldry and the lav; of arms.(3) Foreign Titles )Supporters )Precedence )Special Remainders )These cases have a number of features in common.    They are of comparatively rare occurrence, and the grant of an application is a very special mark of Royal favour:    applications usually come from people of rank and position;    and the King has given definite directions that applications are to be discouraged as a general rule and that grants are only to be recommended in very exceptional circumstances.    It is therefore on all grounds particularly desirable that these cases should be handled with discretion and that care should be taken not to encourage doubtful applications or to raise false hopes.    But we have had a series of cases in which it is beyond doubt that the College of Arms have entirely disregarded the King&apos;s instructions and have gone out of their way to suggest the putting forward of improper applications and to create difficulties for the Secretary of State in carrying out his duty of advising His Majesty.Brief particulars of the individual cases are attached.Baron Harochettj,  an Italian who became naturalised during the war in order to serve in the English Army,  applied in 1918 for permission to use his foreign title.    The Home Office received - obviously by inadvertence on someone&apos;s part -an original letter from the herald who was acting as agent advising the petitioner &quot;to set to. work any interest which you may be able to influence in getting the prayer of the petition passed&quot;.    The writer went on to say - &quot;If you are in a position to enlist the support of His Royal Highness the Prince of Wales
and Lord Stamfordham, now is the time to move&quot;.   This is a specially flagrant instance of a practice which has become usual with some members of the College,  viz:  recommending their clients to bring political or social influence to bear in support of their petitions.Sir W. Hoble was given a baronetcy in 1921:    his only son had been killed in the war and he asked for a special remainder to enable the baronetcy to go to hj.s daughter&apos;s sons. This was contrary to a general ruling which was laid down by His Majesty during the war and which had been officially notified to Garter,  and obviously could not be recommended to His Majesty.    But three years later Sir W. Hoble 1 s friends began, to write to urge his request for a special remainder, and one letter contained the following passage:- &quot;Moreover the King&apos;s Garter urges Sir Wm0 to get his friends to bring this matter to the notice of the Home Secretary and that in all probability the first reply will be an indication that it is not possible, yet if he will persist and bring to the notice of the Home Secretary the fact that there are precedents for such procedure,  it is  very likely that his petition will be granted&quot; .    Sir W. IToble  subsequently stated that Garter had not urged him to use his friends influence, but it was admitted that Garter&apos;s secretary had furnished him with &quot;precedents&quot;,  and it was obvious that the College could not have informed him,  as they ought, of the King&apos;s definite ruling on the subject.In the same year (1923) two very gross cases occurred almost simultaneously.Immediately on being created a peer,  Lord Younger applied for a Warrant of precedence for the widow of his second son who had been killed in action 3 years before the grant of the peerage.   The Secretary of State recommended the grant of the warrant, but His Majesty did not approve,  thinking that the interval between the son&apos;s death and the creation of the peerage was too long.
On being informed of the decision Lord Younger wrote to the Secretary of State explaining that the application was suggested to him by Garter, who gave him to understand that such applJ.catj.ons were granted as a matter of course and said that &quot;he knew of no similar refusal&quot;.   He evidently also suggested to Lord Younger that his petition had never been seen by the Secretary of State personally.    This is a most glaring, case of suggesting to a client to make an improper application and supporting the suggestion by misleading information.    Garter must have known perfectly well that it is absolutely contrary to the general rule to grant a warrant of precedence in such a case, and that in fact there is only one case in existence in which precedence was granted to the wife of a man who died before his father was made a peer,  and this occurred during the War in most exceptional circumstances.The other case is that of Sir Li. Fraser.    On being created a baronet he at once applied for a grant of heredi.ta.ry supporters (he already had personal supporters as a G .  .3.), It has long been laid down by the Sovereign that supporters are only to be granted as a mark of special favour and in reco.gnJ.tion of very distinguished public services and that applications should as a rule be discouraged.    On being refused,   Sir II. Fraser remonstrated somewhat angrily with the Secretary of State at a personal interview, making it plain that the application had been suggested to him by the College of Arms  (this confirms a suspicion that we have long entertained that they make a practice of suggesting to new baronets that they should ask for supporters) and that he had been led to think the grant would be allowed as a matter of course.Attention may also be called to a recent extension of the sphere of the heralds&apos; work,  viz: the granting of badges. Until quite recently the use of badges was confined to Royalty and a few very ancient famili.es who had used them continuously from mediaeval times.    But it apparently occurred to the heralds
-Pi254that badges, having hitherto been rare and a mark of high antiquity, would be an even more marketable article than coats of arms, and they have now begun to grant them to applicants in the same way as arms.    Also antiquaries have lately called attention to the mediaeval practice of using pennons bearing the coat of arms together with the badge  (if any) and motto: and the heralds have now begun to design such pennons according to the best 15th century models for clients who are willing to purchase them.    The designing of pennons is -no doubt proper heralds&apos; work, but it is extremely doubtful whether the heralds are authorised by the terms of their appointment to grant badges at their discretion?    and it is certainly objectionable that the exploitation of the Prerogative of profit which has long been usual in the grant of arms should be- extended to new fields of commercial enterprise.    Moreover we have recently had two cases in which the designing of pennons and the grant of badges have been combined and used in a way calculated to be very embarrassing to the Secretary of State in the discharge of his public duty.    The borough of Hertford recently put in a quite groundless claim to be a royal borough, based merely on the fact that it was once a Royal manor,  and the Secretary of State had much difficulty in convincing them that the claim could not be admitted.    A little later the Press was full of accounts of a great municipal ceremony at Hertford on the occasion of the town being formally presented with a &quot;Standard of Honour&quot;, which was represented as a rare distinction and said to be  granted in consequence of its status as a Royal manor.    The College of Arms explained on enquiry that they had merely granted a badge to the Corporation and. designed a pennon for them, and that they were not responsible for misrepresentations in the Press.    But they had sent down one of their number in Levee uniform to present the pennon and take part in the ceremony,  and it was sufficiently clear that they had not actively discouraged but had rather lent
themselves to the ridiculous delusions current in Hertford as to the nature and importance of the occasion.A little later the newspapers announced that a similar grant of a &quot;Standard of Honour&quot; had been made to the metropolitan borough of Camberwell.   Again it was represented as being a rare distinction,  given in recognition of the fact that Camberwell was once a Royal manor.    Considering the general sensitiveness of boroughs in the matter of titular distinctions and the special difficulty which the Eor-ie Office frequently has in dealing -with unfounded claims by boroughs to the title Royal,  it is most unsatisfactory that the College should adopt a practice of making grants of such a kind or in such a way as to lead boroughs to believe that they are entitled to special distinction on account of a real or fancied connection with Royalty.    In the case of Hertford, the so called &quot;Standard of Honour&quot; was obviously regarded and treated as a formal recognition by the Earl Marshal of a superior status which the Home Office had refused to acknowledge.It has been explained above that it is the long-established practice of the Secretary of State to consult Garter as a kind of technical adviser, on questions of honours, precedence &amp;c.    But in recent years he has received little help from Garter in such cases,  and sometimes the  action of the College has been such as to cause serious difficulty.    An instance of this is to be found in the many tj.mes repeated application of the baronets for the right to hereditary supporters.    This application was refused by King Edward in 1901 and 1905 and again by His present Majesty in 1912 and 1915. But in spite of these repeated decisions by the  Sovereign, Garter has continued to report in favour of the proposal;    and in 1921 and 1923 the application was put forward in a form and manner which irresistibly suggest an intrigue on the part of the College for the purpose of evading the constitutional channel of approaching the Sovereign.    A petition signed by
a large number of baronets asking for supporters and certs.:n other privileges was addressed to the Deputy Earl Marshal and requested him to take the application into consj.deration &quot;and refer it to His Majesty&quot; and the Deputy Earl Marshal appears to have sent it direct to His Majesty&apos;s Private Secretary. Thin is clearly an improper procedure?    the Earl Marshal is not a responsible Minister,  and the King could not according to const.itutj.onal practice deal with such n petition except through the appropriate Minister, who in this case is the Secretary of State .   The petition was of course sent by Lord Stamfordham to the Home Office and answered by the Secretary of State .The appli.catj.on was renewed in 1923.    This time the petition was correctly forwarded to the Secretary of State, but there was an attempt in another form to e rade the Secretary of State&apos;s jurisdiction1.    The request of the petition was that the Secretary of State would &quot;refer the matters to the Earl Marshal and the College of Arms,  the duly constituted authority for dealing with such subjects, or in the alternative would appoint a Committee&quot;.    The accompanying correspondence revealed somewhat ingenuously that the idea was that the Secretary of State should be excluded from, expressing any opinion on the merits of the application and limited to the bare duty of advising His Majesty to appoint a Committee of Investigation to consist largely of members of the College.The College has a strong motive for favouring this application of the baronets.    The fee for a grant of supporters is  55 (of which  20 goes to the  Treasury and  35 to the College).   Obviously therefore the $rant of supporters to any appreciable proportion of the 1550 baronets would bring in immense sums to the College.In view of such proceedings as this it is not surprising that the Home Office has ceased to place, much dependence on Garter&apos;s advice in regard to questions of honours.    Moreover,
exTje-experience has shown that the College constantly makes glaring mistakes in their own work on subjects with which they ought to be familiar.    It will be enough bo refer to two recent instance The Urban District of Twickenham on being incorporated as a borough, wished to retain the arms granted to them as Urban District Council, but were informed by the College that a new grant would be necessary.    The Home Office were consulted by Twickenham and found that the arms had been granted by the Xing of Arms to the Urban District Council and their successors, and that the Corporation had been constituted the successors of the Urban District Council by a scheme under the Municipal Corporations Act hazing the effect of a statute.    In the circumstances it was impossible to understand the grounds for the opinion given by the College, and Garter&apos;s attempts to explain them made the matter no clearer.Some difficulty having arisen in Australia as to the status and precedence of the Lord Mayor of Adelaide, the Lord Mayor consulted the Registrar of the College of Arms in 1924-and was advised (a)  that a Lord Mayor is entitled to the style of Eight Honourable,  and (b) that a Lord Mayor has no place in the general table of precedence,  but within his own city has precedence over all persons except Royalty and the direct representative of the Sovereign.    This opinion is unmistakably wrong in every point.    Lord Mayors have no right to the style &quot;Right Honourable&quot;,  and the advice of the Registrar is all the more remarkable as Garter had correctly advised the Colonial Office some years before on this very point.    As to precedence the Registrar had evidently assumed that the English rule applies to Australia, forgetting that the statute on which the precedence of English Mayors rests does not apply outside England and Wales,  and that in South Australia there i^ a general Table of Precedence sanctioned by His Majesty whioh places a number of persons above Ma3^ors in their own boroughs or elsewhere.
-is- 258There is one other matter which requires notice - viz: the persistent attempts of the College to establish as a rule that all petitions to the Sovereign in respect of foreign titles, precedence, and the like must be prepared by a member of the College acting as agent for the petitioner.One of the worst cases of this happened in 1910.   Major Carandini, an officer of the 5th Lancers,  applied for permission to use his foreign title, an Italian marquisate of considerable antiquity.   He had been formally recognised by the Italian Government as the rightful holder of the title,  so the case was absolutely straightforward.    Garter could not deny that the evidence of the title was valid, but said that the petition contained irrelevant and unnecessary matter,  and recommended that the usual course should, be pursued and an agent appointed at the College &quot;to see the business through and draw up the petition according to practice&quot; .   Major Carandini very naturally objected to employing a herald and paying fees for nothing.    On the petition being granted by the King the College refused either to draft the warrant  (a very simple siatter) or to register it unless the applicant paid the full fee ( 54) which &quot;would have been payable if they had conducted the business from the beginning.Ten years later (1920) a very similar case occurred. Lord Haddington, having succeeded his grandfather, applied, in the usual course for a warrant of rjrecedence for his brother and sister.    As the peerage was a Scottish one, the Home Office following the settled procedure in Scottish oases, first obtained a report from Lyon and then referred the petition with Lyon&apos;s report to Garter.    Garter wrote the following minute on the Home Office paper referred to him:-    &quot;This application is in some respects not quite in the accepted form as it should be transmitted in the first instance through the Earl Marshal&apos;s Department to the Secretary of State in the ordinary way.    I shall esteem it a favour if the Secretary of
State would inform Lord Kaddington&apos;s legal adviser to this effect.   When the case has been put through the proper channel I will report upon it when called upon&quot;.Before writing this minute and without informing the Home Office, he instructed one of the Heralds to write to the applicants and claim to take charge of the business, explaining that the petition ought to have been presented through a member of the College.    The Home Office regarded this as a very bad caser    Garter had not merely tried to assert an unfounded claim to monopolise the right of petitioning, but had ignored Lyon&apos;s jurisdiction, and had refused to comply with the Secretary of State&apos;s request for his opinion.    There has been another case within the last year or two.    A petition for licence to use a foreign title prepared by the applicants solicitors was received in the Home Office and referred to Garter in the usual course.    He took upon himself to advise the petitioner to withdraw it and substitute a new one.    It was ascertained from the solicitors that Garter got into communication with them saying that the petition had been referred to him, that it ought to have been drawn by a Herald in the first place,  that it contained much irrelevant matter which would cause trouble and difficulty, as it was necessary for him (Garter) when reporting to cert ify as to the  correctness of every detail, and that it would be better to let one of the Heralds prepare a new petition confined to the essential facts. They naturally enough complied with this advice, thinking it was authoritative.There is no reason whatever why petitions of this kind should be made a monopoly of the heralds. The work does not call for any special technical skill or knowledge, and since it is the constitutional right of every subject to petition the Crown it is obviously impossible to countenance for a moment the suggestion that a particular class of petition can only reach the Crown when drafted and submitted by a paid officer of arms.
These concrete instances, all of which with one or two exceptions have occurred, within the last 12 years,  sufficiently illustrate the difficulties which the College of Arms have put in the way of successive Secretaries of State when carrying out their constitutional duty of advising the Sovereign in these cases.    Their persistence for so long in the same attitude and the same line of action, and their obstinate refusal to pay any regard to the King1 a directions and to the intimations given by the Secretary of State of his views and methods of procedure, leave no room for doubt that the College are acting on a deliberate policy of trying to get the whole  jurisdiction in these cases into their own hands.    They aim not only at a monopoly of the right of drafting and pre senting petitions,  but at compelling the Secretary of State to accept the reports of Garter or the Kings of Arms as binding and thus obtaining control of the Sovereign&apos;s decisions and reducing the Secretary of State&apos;s duty of advising the King to a mer.e formality:    and they have shown clearly that if they attained their object they would use this power in the interests of the College alone and without regard to the merits of the applications,   the  good of the King&apos;s service,  or the public interest..The root cause of all the trouble  is perfectly plain.    It is the anomalous position of the College, who are theoretically officials of the Royal Household, but actually derive their income from fees paid by indi vi. duals for their services.    It has been explained above that the real income of the heralds depends entirely (a) on the  fees payable for grants of arms,  Royal licences &amp;c.,   (b) on payments for research into pedigrees and similar genealogical work.    The second of these is of course purely private practice:    but the fees under class (a) depend on the position of the heralds as officials&apos;.    The power to grant arms is given by their commissions from, the Earl Marshal as the hereditary holder, of one of the great feudal offices in the Royal Household, and thus derives ultimately from the King.    Broadly
speaking the College of Arms is a small and hj.ghly organised luxury trade,  dependent for its living on supplying the demand for a fancy article among the well to do:    and like many such trades it has in very many cases to create the demand before it can supply it.It is obvious that a body of men so situated, although they may be nominally officials, cannot be expected to anproach the cases which we refer to them from the civil  Service point of view or to make  very useful advisers to the secretary^etary of State. Leaving out of the question their genealogical work, which is purely private practice,  in the matter of grants of arms the traditional practice of the College for centuries past has been to grant ar^s to anyone whose social position was not flagrantly unsuitable and who oared to pay their fees.    Upon their own theory that a grant of coat armour is a grant of a patent of nobility from the King this is in effect treating the Royal Prerogative as the private property of the College and v-: exploiting it to provide incomes for the heralds;    and. it is not unnatural that they should regard the applications to the Sovereign with which the Home Office has to do,  as rarely another branch of the same business to be treated on the same lines.As long ago as IPfo,  Sir W. Hare our t was so much impressed by the unsatisfactoriness of the position that he expressed his intention of ?l cutting up this troublesome nonsense by the roots&quot;,  and gave instructions that Garter should be told &quot;that SMof S.  considers that if the College of Heralds are to advise the Grown in such matters,  it is quite inconsistent that the same persons should act as paid Agents to the Petitioners and also as adviser upon the Petition, and that great inconvenience and difficulty having arisen from this practice,  the S. of S. desires that no Petition shall be advised upon or presented or in any way dealt with by any of the Heralds but shall come to the S. of S. from the Solicitor or other Agents of the
-1S- 282Petitioner and then if the S. of S. thinks fit he can refer the matter to the Heralds as a body of persons who have no interest in the subject matter.   And S. of S. therefore desires Garter to notify all the Heralds that no Petition will be entertained which is dealt with through the paid Agency of any Herald&quot; .    But this proposal was never carried into effect:    and in any case, as the facts mentioned above sufficiently show, merely forbidding the heralds to act as agents would not go fair towards making them really qualified and willing to act as well-informed and judicial advisers to the Secretary of State on the Honours questions which come before him.    So long as the College  is paid by fees and derives the greatest proportion of its income either from these or from pedigree work done for individuals its whole attitude of mind will inevitably be entirely alien to that which is required for such work,   viz:  the consideration of these questions exclusively from the standpoint of the public interest and the King&apos;s service.It will be remembered that the Departmental Committee on Honours which was appointed by the Treasury  in 19^2 went at some length into the work and constitution of the College of Arms, The minority  (Lord Esher,  Sir A. Ellis,  Sir Schomburg McDonnell) reported strongly in favour of turning the College into a Department of the Civil Service, on the same footing as Lyon and Ulster.    The majority held that this proposal was &quot;at the present time and in the present circumstances impracticable&quot; but added &quot;we think that due consideration should be given by the Earl Marshal to the question when the issue of patents   to fresh officers of the College is in contemplation&quot; .    The then Earl Marshal was a member of the Committee and signed this Report, but it does not appear that any effect was given to this suggestion when the office of Garter fell vacant.

</content>
</cab>
