<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/287/0 images: 6-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
b(THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OP  HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT) . SECRET. CP. 119 (59).                                           COPY NO.   4&quot;4                                CABINET.                    LANDLORD  AND TENANT  (WAR  DAMAGE) BILL.                     Memorandum by the  Lord  Chancellor.       I ask my colleagues to approve the principle ofa Bill to carry out the Report of the DepartmentalCommittee on the Responsibility for the Repair of premises damaged by Hostilities (cmd.. 5934 of 1939).       The need for such a Bill arises from the factthat landlords and tenants can no longer insure againstdamage by hostilities.   Insurance companies found theextent of the risk so impossible to estimate that theycould not fix the premium, and they decided to exceptsuch damage from their policies.       The London Chamber of Commerce then wrote to thePresident of the Board of Trade asking that the Governmentshould introduce legislation to release tenants in wholeor in part from the obligations of rebuilding clauses intheir leases where there is damage or destruction by enemy action.   The President of the Board of Tradeapproached the Chancellor of the Exchequer who wrote tomy predecessor, Lord Hailsham., and as a resultLord Hailsham set up the Committee to whose Report Ihave referred.                  M Enclosure.-1-
House of Lords, S.W.I.,  18th May, 1939.       The Report was produced at a time of crisis andas the matter seemed urgent, I ventured to authorise the drafting of a Bill without previous reference to theCabinet which was then fully occupied with other matters.       The drafting of the Bill has proved difficult,but I expect to have a Bill very soon in a form in whichI should be prepared to bring it before the Home AffairsCommittee.   It seems to me desirable in the interestof the business community and the country generally thatthe proposals of the Government should be made public in peace time, and, subject to the approval of theCabinet and Home Affairs Committee, I should propose tointroduce the Bill in the House of Lords this session.                            (Intld.) M.
REPORT  OF  THE  COMMITTEEON  THE  RESPONSIBILITY  FORTHE    REPAIR    OF    PREMISES  DAMAGED  BY  HOSTILITIESPresented by the Lord High Chancellor te  Parliament by Command of His Majesty         February, 1939                      LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICETo be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses:    York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2;      26 York Street, Manchester 1 ; 1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;                80 Chiciiester Street, Belfast;                 or through any bookseller                      *939                    PRICE 6d. netCmd. 5934
                      TABLE OF CONTENTS                                                                     Page I.  Terms of Reference  ...     ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    I                       LEASEHOLD PROPERTY. 2.  Proposal to deal first with leasehold property    ...     ...    ...    i 3.  Law in England relating to repairing leasehold property suffering       war damage ...     ...     ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    1 4.  Existing practice  as to covenants to repair and basis on which       they are entered into     ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    2 5.  Recommendation of relief from liability to repair war damage ...    3 6.  General  application cri  relief from liability to  repair war  damage    3 7.  Prohibition against contracting out of statutory provisions    ...    4 8. . Practical difficulty of doing repairs in war time  ...     ...    ...    4 9.  Lessee&apos;s obligation to notify  war damage and Lessor&apos;s power to       enter premises suffering war damage for inspection and repair    410.  Future position of lease when obligation to repair war damage is       removed     ...     ...    ....    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    411.  Position where premises rendered unfit by reason of war  damage    512.  Scheme of election to retain or disclaim lease of premises rendered       unfit by reason  of war damage  ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    513.  Suspension of rent while premises unfit   ...    ...     ...    ...    614.  Application of scheme irrespective of party liable under the lease       to repair     ...     ...     ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    &apos;615.  Position of derivative interests on disclaimer and recommendation       for their protection...     ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    716.  Protection of under-lessees on disclaimer of superior lease     ...    817.  Persons  by whom powers  under the Scheme are to be exercised.       Position of assignees and prior interests ...    ...     ...    ...    818.  Position of intermediate interests  ...     ...    ...     ...    ...    919.  Position when further war damage occurs ...    ...     ...    ...   1020.  Time for service of notices, etc.    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...   10                       BLOCKS OF FLATS, ETC.21.  Application of scheme to blocks of flats, etc.    ...     ...    ...   1222.  Lessors&apos;  right to obtain vacant possession of the whole premises   12                            GROUND RENTS.23.  Ground rents  ...     ...    ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...   1324.  Relief of lessee from restrictive covenants ...    ...     ...    ...   14                       ALTERNATIVE SCHEMES.25.  Courts (Emergency Powers) Acts  ...     ...    ...     ...    ...   14   I Alternative schemes ...    ...    ...     ...    ...     ...    ...   1527. J                                                                   D
ERRATA TO CMD. 5934.REPORT  OF  THE  COMMITTEE  ON THE  RESPONSI-      BILITY  FOR   THE  REPAIR  OF  PREMISES      DAMAGED BY  HOSTILITIES.  Page 12.  Para. 21.  For &quot; paragraph  17 &quot;  read &quot; para-graph 16 &quot;.  Page 15.  Para. 27.   First line.  Omit &quot; whether &quot;.  Page 17.  Para. 32.  For &quot; paragraph 4 (iii) &quot; read &quot; para-graph 3 (iii) &quot;.                                               (13+76)
Ill	FEE FARM RENTS.			Page28.	Fee farm rents ...	15	MINING LEASES.	29.	Exclusion of mining leases ...	16	AGRICULTURAL HOLDINGS.	30.	Exclusion of agricultural holdings...... ... ......	16	MORTGAGES.		Mortgagors&apos; relief from obligation to repair war damage...	16	SETTLED PROPERTY.	32-	Limited owners&apos; relief from any liability to repair war damage ...	17	CHURCH AND ECCLESIASTICAL PROPERTY.	33-	Repair of war damage to churches and ecclesiastical property ...	17	TRIBUNAL.	34-	County Court to be the tribunal for the purposes of the scheme	18	APPLICATION TO THE CROWN.	35-	Application to the Crown	19	SCOTLAND.	36.	Scotland	19	SCHEDULE.	1.	Definitions	202.	Relief from obligation to repair	203-	Relief subject to the provisions for disclaimer and retainer	204-	Lessee&apos;s obligation to inform lessor of war damage and lessor&apos;s		right of re-entry to view and repair	205-	Right to disclaim ... ... ... ... ... ...	216.	Notice to lessor of election to retain or disclaim ...	217-	Lessor&apos;s right to require holder of lease to elect ...	21Co	Particulars to be served with notice of disclaimer.	219-	Effect of election to retain ... ... ... ...	2110.	Service of counter notice by lessor of election to repair ...	22II.	How and when disclaimer becomes effective	2212.	Result of effective disclaimer.	2213-	Application to Court as to removal of fixtures	2214.	Courfs duty as to confirming disclaimer	22	12880 A	2
                            SCHEDULE continued.                                                                       Page15.  Couifs powers of confirming disclaimer    ...     ...     ...     ...  2316.  Subsequent war damage     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  2317.  Prescribed Period     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  2318.  Exceptions    ....     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  24-19.  Agricultural holdings  ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  2420.  Blocks of flats, etc.   Position of lessees  of separate tenements in        the block    ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  24.21.  Blocks of flats, etc.  Position  of lessee of whole block  ...     ...  2422.  Ground leases  ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...  2523.  Modification of restrictive covenants      ....   ...     ...     ...  25
To The Right Honourable Lord MAUGHAM,    Lord High Chancellor of Great Britain.MY LORD,                    Terms of Reference.   i. We were appointed by you to be a Committee &quot; to con-sider the legal rights and liabilities inter se of persons interestedin buildings  in the event of the buildings  being  destroyed or damaged by  or in consequence of hostilities and to report whatlegislation, if any, is desirable &quot;.                   LEASEHOLD PROPERTY.        Proposal  to deal first with Leasehold  property.   2. We propose to deal  first with leasehold  property becauseby far the greatest number of cases of hardship is likely to arise from the strict enforcement of rights and liabilities in connectionwith this class of property.  We  have set out in the  Schedule aScheme for dealing with this class of property and we proposeto discuss in  the body of this report the reasons which have ledus to put forward that Scheme.   Law in England  relating to repairing leasehold property                   suffering war damage.   3. The law in England  as regards the rights and liabilities oflandlord and tenant in the event of the demised premises being destroyed or damaged  by  or in consequence of hostilities is reasonably clear from the decisions in Paradine v. Jane (Aleyn26), Surplice v. Farnsworth (7  Man &amp; G.  576),  Redmond v.Dainton (1922 2 K.B. 256) and Mathey v. Curling (1922 2 A.C.180) (see especially per Lord Atkinson at pp. 233 et seq.).  Inthe case of Paradine v. Jane the Court state:  &quot; But when theparty by his own contract creates a duty or charge upon himselfhe is bound to make it good, if he  may, notwithstanding anyaccident by inevitable necessity, because he  might have pro-vided  against it  by  his  contract and therefore  if the lesseecovenants to repair a house, though it be burned by lightning orthrown down by enemies,  yet he ought to repair it.&quot;  The resultof these cases is as follows:        (i)  Damage to or destruction of leasehold property by the    King&apos;s enemies or by the armed forces of the Crown does    not relieve the lessee from  his obligation  to pay rent nor    does it relieve either party from his obligation to perform a    covenant to repair  which will, if  the damage is extensive    enough to require it,  extend to  the complete rebuilding of    the premises.
      (ii)  A  lessee  cannot  compel  his  landlord  who has    entered  into a covenant to repair specifically to perform    his  covenant nor does failure to repair by a landlord  in    accordance  with his covenant absolve the  tenant from    liability for rent or  entitle him to quit;  the tenant,  of    course, has., his action for damages.      (iii) In the absence of a covenant in the lease to repair,    there  is no obligation on either party to repair or rebuild    in the case of  damage or  destruction  by enemy  action.    This follows from the general rule that in the absence of    a covenant the lessor has no obligation to  repair and that    the tenanfs liability with  regard to repairs is measured    by  the doctrine  of waste.  In no case  does  waste extend    to repairing damage resulting from any cause such as fire    or  enemy action which is beyond the  control  of  the    tenant.Existing practice as to covenants to repair and basis  on which                  they are entered into.  4. Under the existing practice an obligation to repair in termssufficiently wide to carry an obligation to repair war damage isthrown  on the lessee generally by leases for periods of 21 years or more and frequently by leases for shorter periods. Where theobligation to  repair  is  not  thrown  on the lessee  the lessorgenerally  undertakes  to do  external  repairs  (which  would include war damage) and the lessee  undertakes to do internalrepairs.  The covenant to repair is designed  primarily to cover theordinary  maintenance of the  building in normal conditions.It will also, in the absence of express exception, cover extra-ordinary damage such as damage by fire and enemy action.In accepting these liabilities the covanant or (he may, of course,be  either  the  lessor  or  the lessee) is  content to bear the com-paratively small  expense  of  making  the  structural  repairordinarily resulting from wear and tear, and to protect himselfagainst the  larger expenditure of repairing or reinstating  thepremises in the case of damage by fire by taking out an insurancepolicy which  involves him  in the payment of a small annualpremium.  With regard to damage by war action it is true thatinsurance companies have  always excluded  &quot; war, invasion,act of foreign enemy and hostilities  (whether war be declaredor not) &quot; from their ordinary  fire policies.  But  up to the last war the risk of damage by enemy action was extremely remoteand when, during the last War, the  risk became a serious onethe  Government instituted a  scheme  under  which  insurance against war damage could  be  effected.
  We therefore think it is fair to assume that as a general rule,if  the  question of damage by  war action entered  at  all intothe consideration of the parties, the covanant or undertook theliability  for  repairing such damage  on the assumption that facilities for insuring against it would be available to him.  Theinsurance companies  have, however,  announced  that, havingregard to the impossibility of forecasting witrrJany degree ofaccuracy the extent of damage which may be caused by hostileaircraft,  they are not prepared to promote, or to be associatedwith, any  scheme  for insurance against  war risks; nor, weunderstand, will the Government, for the same reasons, find itfeasible to promote such a  scheme alone.Recommendation of relief  from liability to repair war damage.  5. In these circumstances the basis  on which the  covenantorentered into  his obligation to repair  war damage  has f unda-mentally altered as  a result of  events over  which he has no control and we have therefore come  to the conclusion  that thecovenantor, be he  lessor or lessee, should be relieved by statutefrom his obligation, express or implied, to repair war damage.If the  covanant or  is to be  released from his obligation the  likerelief should be granted to persons who by reason of a guaranteeor otherwise are subject to the  same obligations.    (Schedule,Paragraph 2.)General application of relief from liability io repair war damage.  6. We have specially  considered whether this relief,, from theobligation to repair  war damage should also apply where theobligation expressly includes war damage  or where the obliga-tion is accepted at a time when the covanant or knew, or might reasonably have been expected to have known, that insurance against the risk would  be impossible.  Although it might besaid that in these  cases  the parties had agreed with their eyesopen how the loss was  to  be borne,  we nevertheless  considerthat, even in these cases, the relief should be given.   (Schedule.Paragraph 2 (&amp;).)  In practice  leases are  frequentiy not nego-tiated between parties on equal terms; the lessor is generally ina superior position to the  lessee.  For instance in  the case of larger estates the lessee may often be forced to accept a lease ina  standard  form  which will  usually  have  been  framed witha view primarily to the lessor&apos;s interests.   Furthermore, it isessential for the industrial population  that  it should live inclose proximity to its work,  and, owing to the  scarcity of available accommodation,  the tenant  may be forced to acceptconditions more onerous than he would be willing to accept ifhe  were free to  choose his  place of residence.    Again,  the lessee, who  may  not be  legally advised,  will often  fail to appreciate the significance of  the obligation he is undertaking.   12880                                               A 4
  Prohibition against contracting out of statutory provisions.  7. Nor  do  we  think that persons  should be  allowed to contract out of the statutory provisions; if that were allowed,it might become common form for lessors to force an obligationto repair  upon  the  lessees  and the statute might to a  largeextent be  nullified.       Practical difficulty of doing repairs  in war time.  8. During a war it will probably be impossible in practice forthe repairing covenants to be complied with owing to shortageof  labour and materials   and  governmental  restriction  on building.   During the  last war,  the  construction, alteration,repair,  decoration  or demolition of  buildings could not becarried  out without  licence from the Minister  of Munitionsunless the total cost  of the completed work  in contemplationdid not exceed  ^500 and  the  use of  constructional  steel wasnot involved.   It  might well be  that the  damage caused by air raids in any future war would be greater and  more  wide-spread than in the last war and that an even greater restriction on building might be in force.Lessee&apos;s obligation to notify war damage and lessor&apos;s power toenter premises suffering war damage for inspection and repair.  9. If the lessee is relieved of his obligation to repair we thinkit important that the lessor should be  given every  opportunityto minimise the war damage and, if possible, prevent the pre-mises from becoming unfit.  We therefore recommend that,wherever  war damage has  occurred, a lessee  should be  boundforthwith  to give notice of  the occurrence  of the  war damage to the lessor and that the lessor should have the right to enter upon the premises  for the  purpose  of inspecting them andexecuting, if he thinks  fit,  any repairs (whether temporary orpermanent) necessitated by the war damage.  (Schedule,  Para-graph 4.)  Future  position  of lease  when no obligation to repair war                     damage is removed.  10. Merely to exclude the obligation to  repair  war damage from all repairing covenants in leases  does not completely  dis-pose  of the matter.   It is necessary also to consider the future position of the lease  when the demised premises have sufferedwar damage and, upon the assumption that our recommenda-tions are accepted,  there is no obligation on either party to repair.  Unless provision to the  contrary  is made, the  parties would remain bound by the other terms of the lease, includingthe obligation to pay the full rent  thereby reserved.
  We  think  that there is no hardship  in  this so long as thepremises remain fit for habitation.  We do not feel justified in recommending an abrogation of binding contracts further thanthe necessities of the  case require; after all, if  a state of warexists, lessees should not in our view complain  so long as thehabitability of the premises they occupy is not  affected.Position where premises rendered unfit by reason of war damage.   II.  Where,  however,  the premises  are  rendered unfit  byreason of war damage we think different considerations apply.In such  a case damage substantially frustrates the  bargainto which the parties stand  committed and we do not  think it reasonable  that the  lease should remain  in  force unless oneof the parties is willing to  undertake,  as a voluntary act,  to repair the premises to such extent as may render them fit. Weuse the phrase &quot; fit  (or unfit)  &quot; and by this we mean, in thecase  of residential or office property,  fit (or  unfit) for human habitation, or office  purposes by the class of tenant likely to occupy the premises  having regard to all the circumstances andespecially to the fact  that a state of war is in existence and, in the  case  of other property, fit  (or unfit) for the purposes for which such property could reasonably be  used by the holder of the lease  consistently with  the terms on  which it  is held. (Schedule, Paragraph  i.)   We realise that the standard of repair required to satisfy the phrase &quot; fit &quot;,  and consequently sufficient to keep the lease in force, will be below the standard which a strict enforcement of the covenant to repair  would secure; but we think it unfair in all the circumstances to impose on a  lessor who wishes to retain his tenant or on a lessee who wishes to retain his lease a  greater obligation than to make the premises fit.  Our subsequent  references to repair are accord- ingly to  be construed in this limited sense.   Scheme of  election to retain  or disclaim lease of premises             rendered unfit by reason of war damage.   12. We think, therefore, that, if premises  are rendered unfit by reason of war damage,  the  lessee should be  entitled to elect, by notice given  to  the lessor,  between retaining his  lease,  in which case he is to come under an obligation to repair  in due course  and  disclaiming his lease.  (Schedule,  Paragraph  6.) In the latter event, however,  we think the lessor should have power either by serving a counter-notice to avoid the disclaimer, in which  case the  lease will  continue  and an obligation  to repair in due  course will fall upon the lessor (Schedule, Para- graph io (a) and (6) ), or, if he disputes the lessee&apos;s contention that the premises are unfit, to bring the matter before the Court  (Schedule,  Paragraph II (&amp;.) ).  If the lessor does not exercise  either of these powers  within the prescribed period and there
are no derivative interests affecting the lease the disclaimer willbecome  effective at  the  expiration of the  prescribed period.(Schedule, Paragraphs u  (a) and 17.)  Furthermore it seems tous unfair that the lessor  should  be kept  for an indefinite timein uncertainty as to his position by reason of the lessee&apos;s delay in making up his mind whether to disclaim  or retain his lease.We, therefore, suggest that the lessor should have the additionalpower to give notice to the lessee stating that the premises areunfit by reason of war damage and on that ground calling uponthe lessee to elect either to disclaim or to retain his lease and,if the lessee does not comply with this request, he  should betreated  as having elected to retain and be placed under liability to repair the war damage.  In the event of such a notice beingserved the lessee should have the right to challenge the lessor&apos;scontention that the  premises are unfit.  If he do  so, the Lessor&apos;notice should only he effective if the Court,  on  his application,upholds his  claim  that the premises  are unfit.  If  the  Courtdo so, it should have power to  extend the time within which the lessee may make his election.  (Schedule,  Paragraph 7.)  The person undertaking the repairs will be bound to performhis undertaking as soon as he can having regard to any buildingrestrictions in force and the shortage of  labour and materials and  other conditions then obtaining. A considerable time may,of course,  elapse before the repairs are completed.  (Schedule,Paragraphs 9 (a) and 10 (6) ).           Suspension of rent  while premises unfit.  13. The question then  arises whether  a lessee whose leasecontinues by reason of his  electing to retain his lease  or byreason of the service of a  counter-notice by the lessor should be obliged  to pay rent for the premises while they are  unfit.  Wethink that as a general rule the rent should be suspended inthose circumstances.  There may, however,  be  cases in  which some beneficial use can be made of the premises, although theyare in fact unfit and in those cases we recommend that the court should have power to assess a rent to be paid by  the  lesseehaving regard to the extent to which the premises are capableof beneficial occupation,  such rent not to  exceed the annual value of the  part which is being used or  the full rent reservedby the lease whichever is the less. The  reduction and suspensionwill last until the premises are, or, where the obligation to  repairfalls  on  the lessee, ought, if due diligence were  exercised, tohave been, rendered fit.    (Schedule, Paragraphs  9 (&amp;) and10 (c) ).  Application of scheme irrespective of party liable under the                       lease to repair.  14. We would point out that under our proposals the right ofthe lessor to require  a lessee to elect between disclaiming andretaining his lease arises whether or not the lessee is the  person
  * See Schedule, Paras.  20 and 21 dealing with blocks of flats, etc., and ground leases.originally liable under the lease to repair and that similarly alessee who elects to retain  his  lease is bound to undertake tomake the premises fit whether or not he was the person originallyliable under  the covenant to repair.  If the principle that war damage  is to be regarded as outside  the proper purview of thecovenant to repair is accepted the question on whom the liability to  repair  originally rested under  the  lease  is  in our  viewimmaterial.       Position of derivative interests on disclaimer and             recommendations  for their protection.  15. In connection with any scheme involving disclaimer com-plications necessarily arise from the fact that in respect of someproperties there may be many  interests involved.  There  may,for instance, be  a  chain of leases  and under leases and alsoassignments  and mortgages; most of the leases and underleaseswill contain  covenants  to repair and, in the case of blocks ofhouses, fiats, offices, shops and workrooms, the sitting tenantswill be sub-tenants of part only of the property demised by the superior  lease.  It must be remembered that these interests willbe  derived out of the head  lease  or  a superior underlease andtherefore, if  the head lease  or  superior underlease disappears,all  the interests derived out of it also disappear.  An  effectivedisclaimer of the head lease under these proposals would, if nofurther provision  were made,  have the effect of  terminatingall interests derived out of that lease.  (Schedule, Paragraph 12.)It is necessary, therefore, that the disclaiming lessee should berequired, in  his notice of disclaimer, to  give particulars of anyunderlease, mortgage or charge  affecting his  interest  and toinform the underlessee,  mortgagee  and chargee  that  he has reserved a notice of disclaimer (Schedule, Paragraph 8) and alsothat provision  should be made permitting access to a tribunalin all cases where the derivative interests may be affected by adisclaimer of the head lease or  superior underlease.  We suggestaccordingly that, in these cases, except where  all parties con-cerned are in  agreement, a disclaimer is not to be  effectiveunless  sanctioned  by the Court.  (Schedule, Paragraph n).Subject to the  special cases  dealt with later* the Court shouldbe  bound  to sanction the  disclaimer in all cases  where  it  is satisfied  that the premises are  rendered  unfit by reason of war damage  (Schedule,  Paragraph  14)  and should have power atthe same time to give relief by way of making vesting orders and confirming derivative interests on the lines of the powers given in  cases of disclaimer under section 54 of the BankruptcyAct, 1914, and in cases of forfeiture under section 146 of the law of Property  Act,  1925.   (Schedule,  Paragraph  15 (c) ).   The
Court should also have power to make orders as to the removalof fixtures on a  disclaimer.  (Schedule Paragraphs 13  and15 (6) ).  Protection of underlessees on disclaimer of Superior Lease.  16. We also think that additional provision  should be madefor the protection of underlessees in occupation  of damaged pre-mises  who do not wish to disclaim where  the headlease  or  asuperior underlease is being disclaimed.   These underlesseeswill in many cases be persons of limited means and we considerit unfair that they should have to incur the expense of an appli-cation to the Court in order to protect an interest of which theywould otherwise be deprived through no  action of their  own.We, therefore,  propose that, in such cases, an underlessee in occupation who does not himself  serve a notice of disclaimer before his lessor&apos;s disclaimer becomes effective should become a tenant of the nearest reversioner (that is to say the nearest person above him on the chain who has not disclaimed) on the terms  of  his underlease unless  the Court  otherwise orders.  (Schedule, Paragraphs 9 (c) and 12 (a).) The burden of apply- ing to the Court would then be placed on the  reversioner. Persons by whom powers under the scheme are to be exercised.            Position of assignees and prior interests.    17. It may be convenient at this stage to set out in more detail  how  we propose that the  scheme of disclaimer and retainer  should work and by whom the various powers should be exer-  cised.  We intend that  the scheme should apply to all  leases,  under-leases and other tenancies and to an agreement for a lease  under which a lessee is entitled to have his  lease granted;  all  these interests we  include in the expression  &quot; lease. &quot; and  the  expressions  &quot;  lessor &quot; and &quot; lessee  &quot; mean  the  person by or  to whom a lease has been granted, as the case may be, and their  respective assignees.  (Schedule, Para. 1.)     We think that the power to elect to retain  or disclaim  should  in all cases be exercised by the holder of the lease, that is to say,  where there has been no assignment, by the  lessee, and, where  there have been one or more assignments, by the person in whom  the lease is for the time being vested.     In our opinion neither an original lessee who has assigned a  lease nor any assignee  prior in point of time to the then holder   of the lease should have any voice on the question whether the   lease should be disclaimed or retained. It is clear that in every   case their interest would dictate the answer that the lease should   be disclaimed,  for their only connection with the lease is  that   they might be  called upon to implement a  default in  the  per-   formance of  the covenants contained in it.   Their dissent  to a   retainer may be assumed.
13  The question then arises whether, if the holder of  the leaseelects to retain his lease, the obligation to make the premises fitwhich then arises should attach to the  original lessee and  allassignees or only to the holder of the lease and his subsequentassignees.  The position of the lessee and the prior assignees apart from this point is that their old obligations remain exceptthat,  so far as the covenant to  repair is concerned,  they arerelieved from liability to make good war damage,  and it maybe suggested  that there is no reason why  this liability shouldnot revive  to the limited extent of subjecting them to the obliga-tions to make the premises fit, if the holder elects to retain the lease. There is, we think, a good deal to be said for this view,but on the whole we have come to the conclusion that, once theprinciple is accepted that war damage is outside the proper ambitof a covenant to repair, there is no reason for reviving it in any form except as a voluntary act on the part of the person choosingto assume  the obligation. The lessor is the only person interestedin contending that the liability arising on  retention should attach to the original lessee and all assignees.  It does not  appear tous that the imposition of this liability on the original lessees andprior assignees is really needed for the  lessor&apos;s protection.   Itmay be safely assumed that the holder of a lease will, in makinghis  election between disclaiming and  retaining,  be guided by commercial considerations as to the worth  of the lease and that he will exercise his option in favour of retainer only if there  is value in  the lease.  Failure  to perform  his  obligation  as to making the premises fit will be  enforceable, not  only by action but by a  right of re-entry.  The lessor is therefore in our view sufficiently protected without the  new obligation being thrown on the original lessee and the prior assignees.               Position of intermediate interests.   18. The position  created  by the existence  of  under-leases taking effect out of head leases has caused  us some  difficulty. We  have  considered whether it would not be possible to frame our suggested scheme on the footing that a lessee should not be entitled to disclaim unless his under-lessee had  decided to dis- claim.  In the simple  case of an under-lease comprising all the premises  included in  the head lease  for  a  term more or less co-extensive with the  head lease and on  conditions  similar  to those in the head lease, no difficulties or injustice would arise. But such  a case, while perhaps not infrequent, is not the general case. Under-leases commonly include only parts of the property included  in  the head  lease, and  are  commonly granted for a shorter term than the head lease and the commercial considera- tions which an under-lessee would take into account in deciding whether to disclaim or retain are unlikely to be the same as those that would be taken into account by the lessee.  The diversity
of cases which would have to be covered in an intelligible formrendered it to our minds impossible to frame a fair scheme on thefooting  above mentioned.    We,  therefore, propose that anylessee or under-lessee may serve a notice of disclaimer as regardshis lease or under-lease as the case may be, and suggest that,where the lessee or any  under-lessee (not being the sittingtenant)  disclaims, the sitting tenant should be protected by thecontinuance of his  tenancy unless the Court  otherwise orders and that other persons having interests derived out of the leaseshould  be protected through  a power given to the Court tomake vesting orders  and to  confirm under-lessees in  theirtenancies.          Position when further war damage occurs.   19. If after one of the parties has  assumed under our pro-posals an obligation to repair premises rendered  unfit by reasonof war  damage further damage occurs by reason of subsequentenemy action the parties may serve fresh notices as in the case ofthe original war damage and this will apply whether the originalobligation to  repair  has  been . fulfilled   or  not  (Schedule,Para. 16).                Time for service of notices, etc.   20.   It is necessary to make  specific provision as to two distinct matters       (a) The  periods within  which  notices may  be served     (Schedule, Para. 17), and       (6) The  date from which  an effective disclaimer is to     operate (Schedule, Para. 12).   With  regard  to the periods within which notices are  to be served, the notices to be considered are         (1) The notice of election between disclaiming and retain-     ing which may be served by a lessee who has received from     his lessor  a notice requiring him so to  elect  (Schedule,     Para. 7).        (2) The counter-notice which may be served by a lessor     who has received a notice of disclaimer served by his lessee     (Schedule, Para.  10).   It is  impossible to fix rigid periods of time as regards either of these notices for the state of circumstances occasioned by the war or attending the happening of the war damage may in many cases render it impossible or impracticable for a notice to be served within  a predetermined fixed  period.   Some standard period of time must be fixed for the usual cases but,  in order to meet exceptional cases, the Court should have power to extend or abridge that period.   We suggest that the  standard  period should be one month (Schedule,  Para. 17 (1) ).
  There are, however, two cases in respect of which, with a viewto avoiding application to the Court, there should be an auto-matic extension of the standard period.   Where there is a chain of leases, an intermediate lessee who has received from his lessora notice requiring him to elect between disclaiming and retain-ing his lease  may, before making  his election, wish to knowwhether his under-lessee proposes to disclaim  or to retain  hisunder-lease.   He may be content to retain his lease and assumetowards his lessor the obligation  to make  the  premises fit, if,and only if, his under-lessee is prepared to remain and assume the same  obligation to him.  To  meet this we suggest that, ifthe intermediate lessee act promptly and  serve on his under-lessee within 14 days of receipt of the  notice from his lessor, a notice requiring his under-lessee to elect, then he may make hisown election  at any  time within  seven days of receipt of  the under-lessee&apos;s notice  of  election or of the expiry of the time within which  the under-lessee may elect.   The chain of leasesmay contain  two or  more leases each derived out of a  leasesuperior to itself.  We suggest that the  times  for making  theelection should be extended so that the position throughout  theinferior links  in the chain can be known before any particularlessee or under-lessee  is required to make his election (Schedule,Para. 17 (2) ).  Similarly, an intermediate lessee who has  received from  hisunder-lessee a notice  of disclaimer may,  in order to determine whether he will serve a counter-notice on the under-lessee, wishto know whether his  lessor will accept a  notice of  disclaimerserved on him or will serve a counter-notice. He may be content to retain his under-lessee and assume towards  the under-lesseean obligation  to make the premises fit if,  and only if,  his lessorserves  a counter-notice, the effect of  which  is that the lessorcomes under an obligation to him  to make the premises fit.  Wesuggest a similar provision as to the automatic  extension of  thestandard period in this case (Schedule,  Para.  17 (3) ).  There is one further special case that requires to be providedfor.  A lessee who has received notice  from his lessor requiringhim to  elect between  disclaiming and  retaining his lease may desire to dispute that the premises have been rendered unfit by war damage.   In that event we propose that, if he gives notice to that  effect  to the lessor before  his time  for election expires,the lessor&apos;s notice is  to  be deemed to  be  cancelled unless  thelessor within  14 days of receipt  of the  lessee&apos;s notice beginsproceedings to have this issue determined.  If the lessor doestake such proceedings, the Court  should have power to extend the  lessee&apos;s time for serving a notice of  retainer or disclaimer(Schedule, Para. 7).  With regard to the  date from  which an effective  disclaimer isto operate, we think that the  date should be  the date of  the
service of the notice of disclaimer except that, in cases whichcome before the Court, the Court should have power to fix adifferent date (Schedule, Paras. 12 and 15).     &apos; :&quot;                &apos;.                   BLOCKS OF FLATS ETC.         Application of scheme to blocks of flats etc.   21. Complications arise in the case of blocks of houses, flats,,&apos;offices,  shops, workrooms and other premises where the lesseeis the lessee  of the whole premises and has  sub-let different parts thereof to  a number of sub-tenants.  In  these  cases itwill be realised that,  whereas some of the  tenements  may be rendered unfit by war damage, others may not be affected.The  sub-tenant whose tenement has been rendered unfit  willhave a  right  to  disclaim in  accordance with the  provisionssuggested  above  (Schedule, para.  20) but  the question arises whether the lessee of the whole premises should in those circum-stances  have a similar right.   He  will presumably  still be inreceipt of rent from those sub-tenants who have not  disclaimed. but he  will nevertheless  be  liable for . the whole rent  which under his  lease is payable to  the lessor..   It seems to us difficult to lay down any hard and fast rule in cases of this nature.  It may be fair in some cases to permit disclaimer  by the lessee, while in  others where  the  proportion of damage in relation to the whole is small, it  would not be fair; or again it  might be fair to  permit disclaimer as to  part only of the premises.  We think the only satisfactory solution in these cases is  that disclaimer should be  allowed  only when and to  the extent to which, having regard to all the  circum- stances, it is in  the  opinion  of the  Court  fair and equitable. (Schedule, para.  21 (ii) and  (hi).)  The Court will have power under  its general jurisdiction to make vesting  orders  and, in the event of the disclaimer being confirmed, sitting tenants who desire to remain will automatically become tenants of the lessor in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 17.  (Schedule, para. 21  (vi).)   If. the Court refuses to  permit disclaimer it &apos;should have  power to reduce  the  rent payable by the lessee  having regard to the amount of damage done and the number  of  tenements rendered  unfit by that damage.  (Schedule, para. 21  (iv).)  Lessor&apos;s right to obtain vacant possession of the whole premises.    22. There is one  further  matter  which needs consideration   with regard to premises sub-let in  different tenements.   The   result  of action taken  under  the  legislation  we suggest  may   be that a lessee has disclaimed but that sub-tenancies are kept   on foot,  the sub-tenants becoming tenants  of the lessor, or that   his disclaimer has not  been confirmed by the Court and that
he holds at a reduced rent.  In any such case it may well bethat,  having regard to the amount of the damage, the more economic course is to  pull down the existing premises and use the site for the erection of a new building.  We think, there-fore,  that the  landlord should have  a right  at any time toapply to the tribunal for an order for possession of the wholepremises and the tribunal should have power to grant the appli-cation if it is satisfied,  having regard to the  extent  of the damage  incurred  and to all the circumstances,  that it is fair and  equitable  that  vacant possession of  the  entire  premisesshould be given.   (Schedule, para.  21 (v).)                       GROUND RENTS...&apos; 23. We  have considered  the extent  to  which  our scheme should apply in the case  of leases at ground rents.   speaking generally, a lease  at a ground rent is a lease  for  a long  termof years  at a rent approximately equal to  the site  value of theland, although it  is true that  in some cases the rent may be considerably more than the site value. It is  usually  grantedon an undertaking by  the lessee to erect a  building on the land and to hand over  the building  in good repair at  the end of the term  to the lessor.   In such a  case the lessor receives through-out the term a rent for the use  of the ground and at the end ofthe term becomes  the  owner of a  building which may or  maynot be of value to  him, but the  lessee is the person to whom thebuilding  to  all intents  and purposes belongs.   In our view alessee at a ground rent should, save in exceptional cases, betreated rather as part  owner of the property than as the lesseeof property belonging  to  another.   Our suggestions, therefore,are directed to apportioning the resulting loss from war damagebetween  the lessor and the lessee.  We suggest that the generalrelief from liability to repair war damage should apply to a lesseeat a ground rent with the result that, in the event of destructionby or in consequence of war action, the lessor would be deprived of the enhanced value of the reversion by reason of the existenceof the building when  the  lease falls in.   Subject to this one exception, we suggest that the lessee should in  the  normal casecontinue subject to all his obligations as to rent  and otherwisewhich are incident to his lease.  We realise  that there  may  be  circumstances (for instancewhere the rent is more than the site value or the remainder ofthe term is quite short)  in which it would be right tiiat the lesseeshould be entitled to disclaim and we therefore recommend that,where such grounds exist, the  lessees should have the right toapply to the Court for leave to disclaim and the Court  shouldhave  power to grant this leave  on such terms and conditions asit thinks fit.   In coming  to a decision, the Court should have
regard especially to the relative value of the site and the build-ings, the length  of the original term and the period unexpired,and the nature of the property and the purposes for which it isor can be used.  (Schedule, Para. 22.,)          Relief of lessee from restrictive covenants.  24.  We also considered whether it might not be advisable to relieve a lessee whose premises have suffered war damage fromrestrictive covenants which might limit the type of building to be erected or the user to which the building might be put.    Wethink that it is desirable that some provision should be made onthis matter in regard to  ground leases and leases of blocks ofhouses, flats, offices, shops or workrooms.   We suggest that thispoint  could adequately be met by adapting the procedure which already exists under section 84 of the Law of Property Act, 1925,for discharging or modifying restrictive covenants.  At presentthe grounds on which the power to discharge or modify can beexercised are where, by  reason of changes in the character ofthe property or the neighbourhood or other circumstances ofthe case, the restriction ought to be  deemed obsolete  or wherethe continued existence  thereof  would impede the reasonableuser of the land  for public or private purposes without securingpractical benefits to  other persons.    The section at presentapplies to freehold land  and to leasehold land only where theoriginal term was for more than 70 years and 50 years haveexpired.  We recommend that the section should be  extendedso as to apply to leases  of the classes mentioned in this para-graph, whatever be the length of the original or unexpired term,when the property comprised therein has suffered war damage.(Schedule, Para. 23.)                   ALTERNATIVE SCHEMES.              Courts  (Emergency  Powers) Acts.  25. We assume that during  the war there will be in force courts (Emergency Powers)  Acts on lines similar to those passedduring the last war.  Those Acts followed two main lines:        (a) the enforcement of the payment or recovery of a sum    of money due under a contract made before the beginning of    the war and of rent of  less than  50 per annum was pro-    hibited except by leave  of the  Court, and       (6) contracts could be suspended, annulled or amended    where owing to any restriction or direction imposed by or    under the Defence of the Realm Regulations or owing to    the acquisition or user  of property by or on behalf of the    Crown for the purpose of the war any term of the contract    could not be enforced without serious hardship.
                    Alternative schemes.  26. Before deciding on  the  scheme which we have  recom-mended above, we considered whether the matter could not bedealt with on the lines of those Acts by suspending enforcement of the covenants to repair.   We think, however, that mere sus-pension,  although it affords temporary relief, does not providea permanent solution  and  leaves the parties in an uncertainty as to their obligations which is most undesirable.  It is important that lessees and lessors should know as soon aspossible what their respective rights and obligations will be in theevent of the demised  premises  suffering war damage.  If thepremises are rendered unfit for habitation the lessee will haveto find other accommodation, and he will be  severely handi-capped in  doing so if he still remains in uncertainty as to hisobligations under the lease of  a house which he cannot inhabit.                    Further alternatives.  27. We considered as further alternatives whether the simplesolution of permitting access by lessors and lessees and othersinterested to the tribunal set up under the Courts (emergency powers)  Acts or to ad hoc  tribunals,  established for the pur-pose, in  order  that  the  parties could have  their obligationsre-assessed.  If either of these courses were adopted it wouldbe  necessary,  in  order  to  secure  uniformity,  to  set  outelaborately  the  principles on  which the tribunal was to  act.While this course might  be  adopted,  the  substantial  objectionto it is that it would necessitate resort to the tribunal in every case, thus resulting in  congestion in the tribunal and delay indisposing of a matter in which the  swift determination of rightsand liabilities is essential.                     FEE FARM RENTS.  28. In some parts of the  country especially Bristol, Man-chester  and Liverpool land  is commonly transferred  by wayof grant in fee farm.  The land is conveyed to the grantee sub-ject to the reservation of a perpetual rent, the grantee covenantsto keep the buildings in repair and there is a power of re-entryon breach of these covenants.  We think that, as in the case of leases, the grantee  should not be liable to repair war damage and  accordingly  that the  power  of  entry should not becomeexercisable by reason of his  failure to do  so.  We think, how-ever, that the liability for rent should be  unimpaired.
                      MINING LEASES.                Exclusion of mining leases.  29. We recommend that mining leases should be  excludedfrom the  operation of our general scheme of disclaimer andretainer of leases on the ground that buildings form but a minorpart of the undertaking to which the leases  relate and havegenerally been erected at the cost of the lessee.  The relief fromthe  obligation to repair will, however,  apply in the case of mining leases.  (Schedule, Para. 18.)                 AGRICULTURAL HOLDINGS.             Exclusion  of agricultural holdings.  30. We also recommend that leases or tenancies of agricul-tural holdings should be excluded from the  operation of our general scheme of disclaimer and  retainer of leases on theground that buildings as a  rule form  a minor  part of thepremises included in  the holding. We suggest, however, that,where war damage has rendered unfit any buildings comprised in an agricultural holding, the Court should have  power,  if itthinks fit, to reduce  the rent.  The  relief from the obligationto  repair war  damage will apply in these cases.   (Schedule,Para. 18.)                         MORTGAGES.   Mortgagors relief  from obligation to  repair  war damage.   31. It is usual in mortgages of buildings to insert covenants by the mortgagor to  repair and, in the case of mortgages when the principal is repayable by instalments, to provide that failure to comply with the covenant to repair is to render the principal moneys immediately repayable.  In the  case of debenture trust deeds made by  companies it is again usual for companies to covenant to repair and to empower the trustees to call in the principal moneys in the event of failure by the  Company to comply with its obligations.   We are of opinion that the mortgagor should be relieved of his obligation to make good war damage and that failure to make  good war damage should not cause any acceleration of the  date  of payment of principal  or  make the  mortgage or debentures enforceable.  We think, however, that the mort- gagee should always have the right  to enter upon the premises for the purpose of inspecting them and executing, if he thinks fit,  any repairs  (whether temporary  or permanent)  for the purpose of preserving his security.    The mortgagor will  still remain liable under  his  personal  obligation to repay the principal  moneys  and  the  question whether there should be any relief from that liability raises an
entirely different point.   That  question  can,  we think, onlybe usefully  considered at a time when the extent of the war damage to mortgaged property  generally is known and in  thelight of the general economic position obtaining after a war hasended.                     SETTLED PROPERTY.Limited owners relief from any  liability to repair war damage.  32. In  the  case of settled  property a life tenant  or  otherlimited owner&apos;s  obligation to  repair is generally measured bythe doctrine of waste; he may be impeachable for waste but, as stated  in  paragraph  4  (iii), that does not extend to  making good war damage.  There  may, however, be cases where  there is  express pro-vision  in the settlement or will under which he holds imposingan obligation to keep buildings in repair.  We recommend thatin such cases  the limited  owner should be exempted  from any obligation  to  make  good war  damage and  that  the cost ofexecuting repairs occasioned  by war damage be  included inthe purposes to which capital moneys arising  under the SettledLand Act, 1925, may be  applied.           CHURCH AND ECCLESIASTICAL PROPERTY.Repair of war damage  to churches and ecclesiastical property.  33. There are certain  obligations  to  repair churches  andecclesiastical property which  require  to  be mentioned.   Theposition is as follows: (a) The chancel of a church.  The repair of the chancel  of  a church was formerly  theobligation of the Rector of  the Parish whether spiritual or  lay.This obligation  has  in  most instances ceased by virtue of theextinguishment of tithe rentcharge under the Tithe Act, 1936,but  there remain certain cases  in which the  owner of land inwhich a tithe rentcharge has merged remains liable by  virtueof his ownership of  the land to repair the chancel  (see TitheAct, 1936,  Section 31,  subsections  (3) and (4) ).    We thinkthat this liability should  be limited so as not to extend to  war damage.    In addition  certain  corporations  remain  underliability by virtue of  the proviso to subsection (2)  of  Section 31of the Tithe Act, 1936.    These include various ecclesiasticalbodies and also  universities and  colleges.  We think  that  the universities and colleges  should be exempted from liability sofar as the damage is caused by hostilities.   The liability of eccle-siastical bodies could most appropriately  be dealt with by aMeasure dealing with the whole question so far as ecclesiasticalbodies and funds are concerned.
                            i8(b) The Church other than the chancel.  The liability to repair the remainder of the church is in forma liability of the parishioners.  It is the duty of the parochialchurch council to see that the church is repaired; but as theparochial church council has no power to impose a compulsorychurch rate, it does not appear  necessary to make any  legis-lative provision at the present time with respect to the liability to repair.   (c) There is some authority for the view that a person having a house  within  the parish may be liable for the  repair of anaisle of the church as having been built for the proper use  ofhis predecessors in title, but it is impossible to state the  exactextent of this liability.  This liability should we think be dealtwith in the same way as a private liability to repair a chancel.(d) Other ecclesiastical property.  The repair of parsonages and  like property is dealt with bythe Ecclesiastical Dilapidations Measures, 1923 to 1929,  which also deal to some extent with the repair of certain episcopal pro-perty such as  an  episcopal residence.  Any question arising in respect  of such property by  reason  of  damage caused byhostilities,  should we assume, be dealt with by a Measure.                         TRIBUNAL.County Court to be the tribunal for the purposes of this Scheme.  34. It  now remains to consider  to  what  tribunal questions in dispute  under our scheme are to be referred.    We  thinkthat the appropriate  tribunal would be the County Court  ofthe District in  which the damaged premises are  situated.   Inmost  cases, however,  the dispute  would include an issue  011which the  opinion of an  independent surveyor  would be  ofgreat value.   We considered whether we  should adopt theprocedure  laid  down in Section 21 of the Landlord and TenantAct,  1927, but  we  understand that  that  procedure is not altogether  satisfactory, and that the choice given to the partiesbetween  a reference to a referee and a trial by the judge involvesdelay in  the early stages.  Moreover, as compared with litigantsunder that Act, many more of the litigants  concerned with our proposals would be too poor to  pay the fees and expenses  ofa surveyor.  Under Section 88 (1) of the County Courts Act,1934, the County Court Judge has power to appoint assessorsbut that  power is at present only  exerciseable on the applicationof a party, who has  to pay the  assessors fees.    We think itwould be advisable to  extend the power so as to enable theCounty Court Judge to appoint an assessor on his own initiative and we  recommend  a  frequent  use of this power.   But itwould hardly be fair that a party should pay for an assessor
for which he has not  applied, and in many  cases his reasonfor not applying for an assessor would be his  inability to pay.We think,  therefore, that  provision would have  to  be madefor paying out of public funds the fees and expenses  of  anassessor appointed on the initiative of the Judge.   We recom-mend that an assessor  should have power to view  the propertybefore the hearing.  We also recommend that the number of expert witnesses to be called  on either side should,  as in theAcquisition of Land (Assessment of Compensation) Act, 1919,Section 3 (1),  and the Landlord  and Tenant Act, 1927, Sec-tion 21 (4), be limited to one unless the Judge otherwise directs.  We appreciate that there may be cases which  the parties desireto be  heard in the High Court.  As it will only be necessary to resort to  the High Court in exceptional cases, we think that thepower given by section in  (1)  of the County Courts Act, 1934,under which a party can apply to the High Court to  order theremoval  of  proceedings commenced  in a County  Court is sufficient.                APPLICATION TO THE CROWN.  35.  We see  no sufficient reason why the proposals we havemade should not apply to  the  Crown.   We therefore suggestthat specific provision to that effect should be made in any legis-lation giving effect to our proposals.                        SCOTLAND.  36.  The law of Scotland  differs very materially from thelawof England as to the rights and liabilities of persons interested inbuildings in  the event  of the buildings being  destroyed  or damaged by or in consequence of hostilities.  We do not regardourselves as competent to report on any  matter of Scottish lawand we have therefore confined our consideration of this problem and our  recommendations to buildings in England and Wales.  37. In conclusion we wish to express our thanks to our Secre-tary (Mr. R. W. A. Speed) for the unremitting attention  and&apos;care he has shown in the performance of his duties which havematerially lightened the task of the Committee.
                              SCHEDULE.            SCHEME WITH  REGARD  TO LEASEHOLD  PROPERTY.                                PART I.                               Definitions.  I. &quot; War damage &quot;  includes damage  caused by enemy action or inrepelling enemy action  or by measures taken to avoid the spread or conse-quences  of  such damage.  &quot; Lease &quot; includes an underlease or any  other  tenancy,  and  an agree-ment for a lease where the lessee is entitled to have his lease granted.  &quot; Lessor and Lessee  &quot; includes, as regards a Lease, the lessor and lesseeand their respective assignees  and,  as regards  an under-lease, the  under-lessor  or underlessee and  their respective assignees.  &quot; The holder of a Lease  &quot; means, as regards a Lease, the original lesseeor,  if the lease has been assigned, the assignee in whom the lease is vestedor,  as regards an underlease, the original underlessee or, if the underleasehas been assigned, the assignee in  whom the underlease is vested.  &quot; Unfit &quot; means:        In the  case of residential or  office  property  unfit for human habitation-    tion or office purposes by the class of tenant likely  to occupy  the    property  in  question  having  regard to  all  the  circumstances  and    especially that  a state of war is in  existence.       In the  case  of  other property means unfit for the  purposes  for    which such property can reasonably be used by the holder of the lease     consistently with the  terms on which it is held.  ,&quot; Fit &quot;  has a corresponding meaning.  &quot; The Court &quot; means the  County Court within the  District of whichthe premises  or any part thereof  are situated.                                PART II.                    Relief  from  obligation  to  repair.  .2. Where war damage happens to any  premises included in  a lease no person is to be liable by virtue  of  any provision expressed or  implied inthe lease or by reason of any collateral obligation to make good such war damage  and any obligation  to repair  and  any  condition for re-entry inthe lease is to stand modified  accordingly.  This provision is to apply :         (a) whatever be the date  of  the lease;       (6) whatever be. the terms of any provision relating to repair even    though those terms  expressly cover war damage;       (c) whatever be the amount  of  the war damage.  Subject to this modification the lease is to continue in full force.       Relief subject to  the  provisions  for  disclaimer and retainer.  3. The foregoing provision is  to  have  effect subject to  the  provisionsof  Part  III.Lessee&apos;s obligation  to inform Lessor of war  damage and Lessor&apos;s right of                      Re-entry to view and repair.   4. There is to be implied  in every lease a provision requiring the lesseeto  inform the landlord forthwith of the happening of any war damage tothe premises comprised  in the lease and  a provision enabling the lessorto  enter upon the  premises  for the purposes of  inspection and  doing  any- repair  (whether  temporary  or  permanent) required by  reason of  war damage.
                                PART  III.                            Right to disclaim.  5. Where  premises comprised in a lease are  rendered  unfit  by  war damage, the  holder of  the lease is to be  entitled to disclaim the  leasesubject to and  in accordance with  the following provisions.            Notice  to lessor of Election to retain or disclaim.  6. The holder of  a lease may at any time after the premises have been rendered unfit by war  damage serve on the  lessor:        (i)  a notice  whereby he  elects to  retain his lease  (a  notice of    retainer):  or       (ii)  a notice  whereby he  elects to disclaim his lease (a notice of    disclaimer).             Lessor&apos;s right  to require holder of lease to elect.  7. The lessor may at  any time after the  premises  have  been renderedunfit  by war damage require  the holder of the lease  who has not serveda notice of retainer or a notice  of disclaimer to serve  one of such notices.If the holder of the lease does not serve one of such notices within theprescribed period the holder of the  lease  shall be deemed to  have serveda notice of retainer.  If within one  month  of the  service  of the  lessor&apos;notice the holder of the lease  serves a counter-notice alleging  that thepremises have not been  rendered unfit by war damage the lessor&apos;s noticeshall  be deemed to be cancelled unless the  lessor  within 14 days applies to the  Court for a decision whether  the  premises are unfit or  not.  Ifsuch  an application is made to the Court and the lessor&apos;s notice  is held to be justified the holder of the lease is to  have such further time as theCourt may allow for serving a notice of retainer  or a  notice of disclaimer.            Particulars to be served with notice of disclaimer.  8. With any notice of  disclaimer there are to be served particulars of allmortgages, charges  and under leases of or derived out of the lease  in ques-tion and  any other mortgages,  charges and  under leases affecting  the  pre-mises of  which the party giving the notice may  be  aware or which hecould reasonably ascertain  and the holder  of the lease, is to inform all such  mortgagees, chargees and  underlessees  of the notice served  by him.                      Effect of Election to  retain.  9. If the holder of the lease  serve  a notice of retainer the lease is tocontinue  in full force  except that:         (a) (whether  or not the obligation to  repair arising under the lease    is the lessor&apos;s obligation or the  lessee&apos;s  obligation) the holder and his    assignees are to be  under an obligation to make the premises fit so    far as rendered unfit by the war  damage  in question and to  do this    as  soon as is  reasonably practicable and any power  of re-entry or    other  right contained in  the lease is to apply on a breach of such    obligation;       (6) payment  of the rent is to be suspended as from the date of the    notice of retainer until  it is reasonably practicable for  this obligation    to  have  been  carried  out  subject to a power  in the  Court  to  fix    meanwhile  a rent  where the premises are to some extent capable of    beneficial occupation, such rent not to exceed the. annual  value of the    reasonably usable part or the full rent reserved by the lease, whichever    is the less.  In the  event of delay by  the holder of the lease or his    assignees in fulfilling his obligation to repair, the lessor is to be entitled    to apply to the Court for  a  resumption of the full  rent reserved by the    lease,  the Court having power either to grant the application  or grant    such increase as it thinks fit;
      (c)  in the case of service of notice of retainer of an underlease then,    if the uhderlessor has served  a notice of disclaimer on his lessor, the    underlessee shall  automatically  become tenant of the nearest rever-   , sioner who has not disclaimed on  the terms of his  underlease unless    and  until  the  Court on the application  of  the reversioner  otherwise    orders.       Service of Counter-notice by  Lessor of Election to repair.  10. If the holder of a lease serve a notice of disclaimer  the Lessor maywithin the prescribed period serve a counter-notice whereby he elects  tomake the premises fit.  If  such a counter-notice is served:       (a)  the  notice  of disclaimer is to stand avoided;      (6)  the  lessor is to be subject  to an obligation to the holder of the    lease  and  his assignees  to make the premises  fit, so  far as rendered    unfit  by the  war damage, in question, and  to do this  so soon  as is    reasonably practicable;      (c)  the  rent is  to be  suspended  as  from the date  of the  notice  of    disclaimer until this obligation is complied  with,  subject to a power    in the  Court  to  fix  meanwhile a  rent where the  premises are  to    some  extent capable of  beneficial occupation, such rent  not  to exceed    the annual value of the  reasonably usable part or the full rent reserved    by the lease, whichever is the less.               How and when  disclaimer becomes  effective.  II. Unless the  parties agree  to an earlier date  a notice of  disclaimeris to be effective  without an order of the  Court on the expiration of theperiod during  which the lessor is entitled to serve his counter-notice  of election to  make the premises fit:        (i)  where  there is no underlease, mortgage or charge affecting the    lease  and  the lessor has not within that period applied to the Court    for a decision that the  premises  are not  unfit;      (ii)  where  there  is an underlease, mortgage, or charge affecting the    lease  and neither  the lessor nor any underlessee, mortgagee or chargee    requires the  matter to be brought  before the Court.  Except in cases (i) and (ii) the notice of disclaimer is not effective unlessconfirmed by  the Court.                      Result of effective  disclaimer.  12. A disclaimer when effective is to operate as a termination of the lease and, subject to the power in the Court mentioned in Paragraph  15 to  fix a different date  on confirming a  disclaimer,  shall so operate as from thedate of the service of the notice of disclaimer.  All interests in  or derivedout of the lease  are accordingly to disappear except that:       (a)  the  interest of any underlessee in occupation who has not served    a notice of disclaimer is to continue  as  an  underlease of the nearest    reversioner for  the time being,  unless the  Court on the application    of the reversioner for good cause shown, at any time  otherwise orders;      (b) the  operation of  the disclaimer  is to be subject to  any  order    made under Paragraph   15.              Application to Court as to removal of fixtures.  13. Where a disclaimer is effective without an order of the  Court  theCourt is to have power to make such orders  as to  the removal of fixturesas the Court thinks just.               Courts  duty  as to  confirming disclaimer.  14. The Court is to confirm  the disclaimer in  all cases  where it is satis-fied  that  the premises have  been rendered unfit by reason of war damage.
                Courfs powers on confirming disclaimer.  15.  The  Court is to have  power on confirming the  disclaimer:       (a)  to  fix the date or  dates as from which the  disclaimer is to    operate as regards the lease, or any interests derived out of the lease;      (6)  to  impose such terms and to make such  orders as to removal of    fixtures and otherwise  as  the Court thinks just;      (c)  to  make orders vesting for the whole term of the lease or  any    less term,  the premises comprised in  the lease or any part thereof,    in any person interested in the  lease  as underlessee  or otherwise on    such conditions as to the execution of any deed or other document,    rent,  repairs and  other  matters as the Court in the circumstances of    the case thinks fit;      [d)  to  order that an  underlessee who does not  desire to  disclaim    shall hold  as  tenant to  the  person who becomes reversioner  for such    period not  exceeding the period  of his  tenancy and on  such other    terms as the Court may think fit.                        Subsequent war damage.  16.  If after the holder of  a  lease has served notice of retainer, or after a lessor has  served  a  counter-notice either:        [a)  war  damage  again happens to the premises  before  the former    war  damage has been  made good, or      (6)  war  damage  again  happens to  the  premises  rendering them    unfit,  after the former  war damage has been made  good,it is to be open to the lessor or lessee to  serve fresh notices  under theforegoing  provisions, which  mutatis  mutandis are to apply.                           Prescribed Period.  17.  The  prescribed period within  which  a lessor upon  whom there hasbeen served  a  notice of disclaimer may serve a counter-notice electing tomake the premises fit,  and the prescribed  period  within which the holderof a lease upon whom there has been  served by his lessor a notice requiringhim to elect between serving a notice of disclaimer and a notice of retainer,may serve one of such notices shall be determined in accordance  with thefollowing  rules:-      (1)  The  minimum period  shall be  one month from  the service of    the first notice.      (2)  Where the  holder of a lease upon whom there has been served    by his lessor  a  notice requiring him to elect between serving a notice    of disclaimer and  a notice  of retainer  has underleased the  premises    and  within fourteen days after being served with  such notice serves    a similar notice on his underlessee, and informs his lessor that  such    a notice has  been served, the period  within  which he may  serve on    his lessor  a  notice  of  disclaimer or  notice   of  retainer  shall stand    extended until  seven days after  the last day on which in accordance    with  these  provisions his  underlessee  may, in  response to the notice    served on him,  serve a notice of disclaimer, or retainer, or seven  days    after  service  in fact of such  notice  whichever  shall  be the  earlier    day.   In computing the  last  day on  which  such  underlessee  may    serve such  a notice regard is to be had to any extension of the period    for serving such a  notice to which the holder of any derivative under-    lease  taking effect mediately  or immediately  out of the  underlease    in question may  be entitled by reason of  the application  to him  of    the foregoing provision.      (3)  Where the lessor  upon whom the notice of disclaimer  is served    himself  holds under a  lease to  which  this part applies,  and within    fourteen  days  after being  served with such  notice  serves on his    superior lessor a notice of disclaimer and informs his lessee  that  such    a notice has  been served,  the period  within  whcih he may  serve on    his. lessee  a  counter-notice  electing  to make  the premises fit  shall
   stand extended until seven days after the last day on which in accord-   ance  with these provisions  his  superior  lessor may, in  response  to   the notice served  on him,  serve a counter-notice electing  to  make   the premises  fit or seven days  after  service, in fact of such  notice,   whichever shall be, the  earlier day.     In  computing the last day  on which any such  superior lessor may   serve such a  counter-notice,  regard is to be had to any  extension  of   the period for  serving  such  a counter-notice to  which such superior   lessor or  any other lessor superior to  him may be entitled by  reason   of the application  to him of the foregoing provision.      (4)  The Court shall  have  power to extend or abridge any  of the   foregoing periods.      (5) Any of  the foregoing  periods  may  be  extended   or  abridged    with the consent in writing of  all persons affected by  such extension    or abridgment.  -                              Exceptions.  18.  Except where  otherwise  expressly  provided in Part IV this  Partis not to  apply to  Mining Leases, Agricultural  Holdings, Leases of blocks of houses, flats,  offices,. shops or workrooms or to Ground Leases.                                PART  IV.                          Agricultural holdings.  rg. As regards leases or  tenancies  of agricultural  holdings, where war damage  has rendered any  buildings  comprised therein unfit,  the Courtis to have power to make such orders as to  reduction of rent or otherwiseas in the circumstances it  thinks just.   Blocks of flats, etc.  Position of lessees of separate tenements in the                                  block.   20. As between the holder of  a lease of a block of houses, flats, offices, shops or workrooms and the underlessees of a house, flat, office,  shop or workroom in the block Part III is to apply.          Blocks of flats, etc.  Position of lessee of  whole block.   21. As between the  lessor and  holder  of a lease (not being  a ground lease) of a  whole block of houses, flats, offices, shops or workrooms  the following provisions are to apply:         (i) The holder of the lease  may serve  a notice of disclaimer when      war damage  has  occurred  to any  premises comprised in  the lease      so  as to render those premises  or any  part  of those  premises  used      or  adapted for use as a separate tenement unfit and the lessor  may      serve a counter-notice as provided in Part III  with  the consequences      therein mentioned.        (ii) If the  holder of the  lease serve  a notice  of disclaimer which  is      not avoided  by a  counter-notice given by the lessor,  the  disclaimer      is not  in any event to become effective unless confirmed by the Court.      The Court is to confirm the disclaimer in all cases where it is satisfied      that,  having regard  to  the war  damage  suffered by the premises  as      a  whole and all the  circumstances of the case (including  any  offers      for the extension of  the term of the. lease, or  for modification of the      rent and  covenants which may be made to the holder of the lease),      it is equitable to relieve  the holder of  the  lease  from  the  burden      of  the lease.         (iii)  Disclaimer may be  confirmed  as  regards part only of the pre-      mises  comprised in the lease.         (iv) When disclaimer is confirmed as  to part  only  of, the premises       or when  confirmation of  the disclaimer is  refused,  the Court may       reduce the rent having regard  to the  extent  of the war damage and       the number of separate tenements rendered unfit by  war damage.
ej  (v)  When,  as a  result of disclaimer  proceedings, the  lessor doesnot get back the leased property free from the lease and all interestsderived out of it, the Court may,  if it think fit,  at any time make an order giving to the  lessor  vacant possession  of the property ofwhich  he has not theretofore  acquired vacant  possession on suchconditions as  to  compensation  or otherwise as the Court  thinks lit.  (vi) A disclaimer confirmed by the Court is to have the effect statedin Paragraph  12 of Part III and the Court is  to have  all the  powersstated  in Paragraph 15 of Part III.22.  In the case of ground leases:     (i) When war damage has occurred to premises included in a ground  lease so as to render those premises or  any of those premises which  .are used  or adapted for use as a separate tenement unfit the holder  of the lease may at any time apply  to the Court for  leave to disclaim  the ground lease  and the,  Court  is not to grant such leave unless  it  is satisfied, having regard to all the  circumstances of  the case (includ-  ing the length of the original term of  the  lease and&apos; the unexpired  part thereof, the amount of the ground rent in relation to the annual  value, of  the premises and any  offers for an extension  of  the term  of the  lease or for modification of the rent  or covenants), that it  is  equitable to  relieve  the  holder of the lease from the  burden of the  lease and  may as  a  condition of confirming  a disclaimer  impose such  conditions as  to  money payment or  otherwise  as  the  Court thinks  (ii)  A disclaimer confirmed by  an order is to have the effect statedin Paragraph 12 of Part III and the Court is to have all the powersstated in Paragraph  15 of Part III.  (iii) When,  as the result of disclaimer proceedings, the lessor doesnot get back the leased premises free from the lease and all interestsderived out of it, the Court may, if it think fit,  at any time make an  order  giving to  the lessor vacant  possession of the premises  ofwhich he has not theretofore acquired vacant possession on  such con-ditions as to&apos; compensation  or otherwise as the Court thinks fit.  23.  Section  84  of the Law of Property Act, 1925, is to be modified so as to apply  to ground leases  or leases including a  block  of  houses,flats,  offices,  shops or  workrooms  (whatever be the length of the  originalor unexpired term)  in cases where the buildings comprised in the lease have suffered war  damage.   The authority referred  to  in  that Section shouldbe empowered to  modify or  discharge covenants  relating to  building  oruser where building or  riser of  a different character is desirable on economic or public  grounds.Ground leases.fit.Modification  of  Restrictive covenants.A.  ANDREWES  U&apos;T.  J. BARNES.C.  GERALD EVE.E.  S.  HERBERT.A.  E.  A. NAPIEFE.  DE NORMANN.T.  MORDAUNT  SIANDREWES UTHWATT,  Chairman.J. BARNES.GERALD EVE.S.  HERBERT.E. A. NAPIER.DE NORMANN.MORDAUNT SNAGGE.R.  W. A.  SPEED,               Secretary.Dated the 26th day of September, 1938.(12880 15) Wt. 1732-386  7500 JO/38  P. St. G. 34t

</content>
</cab>
