<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/287/0 images: 39-50</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT)S C R E T.[p. 180 (39).                                            COPY NO.    Lf                           CABINET,                       FRUSTRATION- OP CONTRACTS.                     Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor                 I draw the attention of my colleagues to the Seventh          Interim Report of the Law Revision Committee          (Cmd. 6009 of 1939 )x which deals with a rule of lav/          incidental to the doctrine of frustration of contracts and          known to lawyers as the&quot;rule in Chandler v. Webster.                 The doctrine of frustration is of special importance          in war-time.  It is based on case-law, and it was greatly          developed by cases which arose out of the last v/ar.                 The rule in Chandler- v. Webster  (which dates from          1904) is that after a frustrating event the loss &quot;lies          where it falls&quot;.   In the opinion of the Committee this          rule leads to injustice, and constitutes a defect in the          doctrine of frustration which ought to be removed by          legislation.                 I recommend the adoption of the Report and as the          doctrine of frustration is of special importance in.          war-time, I ask my colleagues for authority to  give         &apos; instructions for the drafting of a Bill to carrjr out the          Report. .                                       (intld. )   M, House of Lords, S.W.I.      18th May, 1939.5i  Enclosure.
LAW    REVISION   COMMITTEESEVENTH   INTERIM   REPORT    (RULE  IN CHANDLER v. WEBSTER)Presented by the Lord High Chancellor to Parliament        by Command of His Majesty,               May 1939                         LONDON         PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses      York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2 ; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2 ;       .  26 York Street, Manchester 1 ; 1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;                   80 Chichester Street, Belfast;                    or through any bookseller                           1939                       Price 2d. netCmd. 6009
             MEMBERS  OF  THE COMMITTEEThe Right Hon. Lord WRIGHT (Chairman),The Right Hon. Lord ROMER,The Right Hon. Lord PORTER,The Right Hon. Lord Justice GODDARD,The Hon. Mr. Justice ASQUITH,Professor A. X. GOODHART, D.C.L., LL.D.,Professor H. C. GUTTERIDGE, K.G.,H. C. HALDANE, Esq., O.B.E.,A. D. MCNAIR, Esq., C.B.E., LL.D.,W. E. MORTIMER,  Esq.,Sir CLAUD SCHUSTER, G.C.B., C.V.O.,  K.C.,His Honour Judge A. F.  TOPHAM, K.C.,W. T. S. STALLYBRASS, Esq., O.B.E.,  D.C.I.H.  U. WILLINK, Esq., K.C.,Professor P.  H. WINFIELD, LL.D.     Secretary, JOHN G. FOSTER,  Esq.,     Assistant Secretary, Miss BARBARA SHARP.  No incidental expenses have been incurred in the preparationthis Report.  The cost of printing and publishing the Reportestimated at  8 12s. 6d.
 To the  Right  Hon.  Lord MAUGHAM,  Lord  High  Chancellor  of     Great Britain. MY LORD,  We were appointed a Committee on the ioth January, 1934, &quot; to consider how far, having regard to the Statute Law and to judicial decisions, such  legal  maxims  and  doctrines as the Lord  Chancellor may from time to time  refer to the Committee reqtnre  revision in modem conditions  ; &quot; and on the 3rd May, 1937, the following subject was referred to the Committee :        &quot; Whether  and, if  so, in what respect the  rule laid down     or applied  in Chandler v. Webster  [1904] 1  K.B. 493 requires     modification,  and in  particular to consider the observations     made thereon in Cantiare San  Rocco, S.A. v.  Clyde Shipbuilding     and Engineering Co., Ltd. [1924] A.C. 226 by Lords Dunedin and     Shaw at pp. 247, 248  and 259.&quot;  The Committee&apos;s terms  of reference  neither require  nor permit it to report  on the merits of the  doctrine of  frustration  generally. They are limited to  consideration of the rule,  incidental to that doctrine as received in English Courts, that after a frustrating event the loss  &apos; lies where  it falls.&apos;  That rule means  that sums paid or rights accrued before that  event are not to be surrendered, but that all  obligations  falling due for performance  after  that  event are excused.  The guillotine falls with  faultless precision but often with ruthless  effect.  The cases  of Chandler v. Webster [1904] 1  K.B. 493, Lloyd Royal  Beige S.A..  v  Stathatos (1917) 33 T.L.R. 390,  and Civil Service Co-operative Society Ltd., v. General Steam Navigation Coy. [1903] 2 K.B. 756 illustrate the harshness with  which the rule  is capable  of operating.  A contract as a rule involves benefits and burdens for each party. These need not be commensurate, but a rule  of law which, in the absence  of  a breach  of contract  by  either party,  awards all the advantages of the contract to one contracting party and all  its disadvantages to  the other, is prima facie suspect.  But this is the result which the existing rule is calculated to produce.  The rule has been criticised both hy judges and by the text book Writers.   In the  Cantiare case Lord Dunedin  said (at  p.  248) : &quot; For the purpose  of this case it is sufficient to say, as I unhesitatingly do, that  Chandler  v. Webster, if it had been tried in Scotland, would have  been decided the other way.&quot; In the same case Lord Shaw describes the rule as the  &quot; something for nothing &quot; doctrine and adds : &quot; this result  under other  systems of  jurisprudence mightbe viewed as monstrous,&quot; (at p. 258).  In Lloyd Royal Beige S. A. v.Stathatos (1917) 33 T.L.R. at page 392, Lord Atkin (then  Atkin J.)said: &quot;I think that the doctrine  in this  case, as in others, worksbut a rough adjustment of  the rights of the parties, and may involvea hardship,&quot;  and in Russkoe v. Stirk (1922) 10 LI. L.  Rep.  214, 217,x 0105B
he repeated this view as follows :  &quot;I venture to doubt whether any  two business people in the world would ever really make a contract that if certain  unforeseen  events  happen the  contractshould  be at an end and that monies paid should remain exactlyas they were.   It seems  to me impossible  that  that  should bedeliberately done by business  men:   they  would be  practicallycertain to try to make some arrangement as to the adjustment oftheir rights.&quot;   The late  Sir Frederick Pollock,  in discussing this rule, said :  &quot; Chandler v. Webster,  which would have been decidedthe  other way in Scotland,  certainly did not produce a reasonableresult.&quot;  (Contract, ioth ed., 297, note).   The  doctrine is modern and is no part of  the old Common Law,which would not have treated impossibility as an excuse for failure to perform a contract.  As Lord Atkin pointed out, the  action ofthe  Court in truth falls  into two parts in remaking the contract ofthe  parties.  It not only holds that the  contract is at an end andthat further performance is excused,  but it  also says  that moniespaid shall remain as they are.  On any view it is making a newcontract. Why should it stop where it does and make an  unreason-able contract, which  it cannot  fairly be said that the parties as reasonable  men would  have made  for  themselves  if  they  had actually provided for the unanticipated event ? If they had providedfor  dissolution of the contract, would they not also have providedfor  some conditions on which dissolution should take place,  such asrepayment  in whole or in part ?   As the principal authority for this rule is the case of Chandler v. Webster, it  is necessary to discuss it at some length here.  The facts can be stated  shortly.   The defendant agreed to let to the plaintiff for  the sum  of  141 15s.  a room for the purpose of viewing  the Coronation Procession  of  June 26th, 1902.  The procession  sub- sequently was abandoned  owing  to  the illness  of the King,  but before that event took place the plaintiff had paid  100 on account of the price of the room, the balance  remaining unpaid.   The  Court of  Appeal, affirming the  Court  of  first  instance, held that  the plaintiff was not entitled to recover the  100  which he had paid, and that the defendant was entitled to payment of the balance, inasmuch as his right to that payment had accrued before it became  impossible to  hold the procession.   The denial of recovery was based on three grounds :         (1) That this case was not one of total failure of consideration,      as the contract had  been valid  and binding up  to the time      when impossibility supervened.        (2)  That recovery was precluded by  reason of the decisions      in such cases as Taylor v. Caldwell (1863) 3 B. &amp; S. 826, Appleby      v. Myers (1867)  L.R.  2  CP.  651, Civil Service Co-operative      Socy., Ltd. v. General Steam  Navigation Co.  [1903] 2 K.B.  756,     . and Blakeley v. Mutter &amp; Co. [1903] 2  K.B. 760 n.
      (3)  That it was too  difficult  for the  Court to construct a    hypothetical  contract  by  supposing  what  terms the  parties    would have arrived at if they had contemplated the possibility    of Avhat was going to happen.  On the first point it is necessary to say only a few words.  CollinsM.R. pointed out (at p. 499) that the principle of impossibility of performance  merely discharges both the parties  from further  per-formance of the contract.  &quot; If the effect were,&quot; he says, &quot; that the contract were wiped out altogether, no doubt the result would be that money paid  under it would have to be repaid as on a failure of consideration.  But that is  not the- effect  of the  doctrine;  it  onlyreleases the parties from further performance of the contract.&quot;  the distinction between  supervening impossibility of  performance and total failure of consideration is  that the contract is void  ab initio inthe latter but not in the former case.  The claim in  Chandler v.Webster for money paid was an alternative to a claim for damages.  On the second  point concerning prior authority, it must be notedthat both in Taylor- v. Caldwell and in Appleby v. Myers the  only question before the Court was whether, under the circumstances ofthose cases,  the doctrine of impossibility excused  the promisor  from further performance of his promise.  The question did not arise and could not arise in those cases  whether the promisor was under  a duty  to return  any benefits  which  he had received from  thepromisee.   These are two entirely distinct questions and must bekept rigidly separate if the problem we are now considering  is to be properly understood.  It  is  not,  however, either  necessary or desirable for us to discuss these cases at any length; our referenceto them is only  intended to  show that a reversal of  the  rule inChandler v. Webster would not be a radical innovation, or in conflict with well-settled  Common Law principles.  It is the third  ground that the Court will not imply any termsbeyond the mere  dissolution of  the contract which is the dominantreason for the decision.  This is stated by Collins M.R.  at  p.  499 :&quot; The rule adopted by the Courts in such  cases is I think to someextent an arbitrary one, the reason for its adoption being that it  is really impossible  in such cases to work out  with any certainty whatthe rights of the parties in the event which has happened should be.&quot;To  the same effect he quotes on p. 500 from Wills J.&apos;s judgment inBlakeley v. Mutter &amp; Co. :  &quot; The process  of constructing a hypo-thetical contract  by supposing what terms the parties would  havearrived  at if they had contemplated  the possibility of what was going to happen  is, to my  mind, very unsatisfactory.   It  is  verydifficult to construct such  a contract  for them.   Probably, in thepresent case, the  defendants would have stipulated for compensationfor  their outlay, and the plaintiffs for a return of their money;  butit is impossible to say with any certainty  what the result  of  theirbargaining would have been.&quot;   On that basis  the Court  had no right to make a  new contract  at all for the  parties.  The problem
which we are considering here can, therefore, be reduced to this:would it be  difficult for the Court, when implying a hypotheticalterm that the contract should be dissolved, to go on and to imply alsoanother equally hypothetical term ? There is no doubt that a Courtwill hesitate to construct a contract for the  parties,  but,  under certain  circumstances,  it is necessary in the  interests of  justice to imply a term which was not in the contemplation of  the parties.An illustration of this is the doctrine of impossibility of performanceitself, because the doctrine is applicable only in those cases in whichit is clear that the parties did not themselves have the event  in contemplation.  In these cases, in spite of the fact that  the promiseis stated in positive terms,  the law implies a further term excusingperformance on the ground of impossibility.  Thus in Hirji Mulji v. Cheong Yue Steamship Co., Ltd. [1926] A.C. 497, at 510, Lord Sumnerspeaks of frustration as &quot; a device, by which the rules as to absolutecontracts  are  reconciled with a special exception  which  justicedemands.&quot;   (See  also  Maritime  National  Fish Ltd.,  v.  OceanTrawlers Ltd. [1935] A.C.  524, 529.)   Having implied the  term  relating to impossibility,  it is not a.radical step to imply  a further hypothetical  term  that unearned benefits should be returned under these circumstances.   That  no practical difficulty  arises where such  an implication  is  made is shown by the fact that in Scotland, in the United States, and in the Civil Law countries, the contrary rule has proved satisfactory.  (The law in  these countries is discussed in Appendix A,)   The  reason  why the  English  Courts  have refused to imply this further term has been suggested by Lord Dunedin  in  the Cantiare case  [1924] A.C. at p. 248 :  &quot;I cannot help thinking that the angle of view, if I may so phrase it, from which an English or a Scottish judge  would look at such a question  is different;  and that  the cause is to be sought in the reluctance of the English law to order the repayment of money once paid.&quot;  From the early eighteenth century, when a contract was declared to be void ab initio, the proper form of action  to  recover  any consideration paid  thereunder was  for money had and received. - It is true that this was permissible only if the contract was void ab initio so that there was a total failure of consideration.  But as the Common Law did not recognise imposs- responsibility of performance as a ground for  dissolving a contract there is  no precedent  at Common Law for such a course.   If the Court  constructs  the hypothetical  term  providing  for dissolution, it is  legitimate, and  indeed necessary,  for  the Court  to  institute  the  attendant term for repayment.  The Court is depriving  the  party  of his action on the contract and it is a natural corollary to give  him  a claim proportional  for  repayment.    It is accordingly for  us to consider  whether or not it is possible  to frame a rule less arbitrary than that stated in Chandler v. Webster.  We are of opinion that it is possible to do so and it is now necessary  to consider what positive rule should be substituted for it.
  We  have  considered  the following  possible  solutions to  this problem :       (i)  The payer should be entitled to the return of all monies    he has paid to the payee.      (2)  The  payer&apos; should be entitled to  the  repayment  of all    monies, less the value  of any  benefits  he may have received    under the  contract.      (3)  The  payer should be entitled to  the  repayment  of all    monies he has paid to the payee, less one half of any loss directly    incurred by the payee for  the purpose  of  performing the    contract.      (4)  The  payer should be entitled to  the  repayment  of all    monies he  has paid to the payee, less the amount of any loss    directly incurred by&apos;the payee for the purpose of performing    the contract.  It is  reasonable to assume  that  in stipulating for  pre-paymentthe payee  intended to protect himself against loss under the contract;and this intention would be  satisfactorily carried out if solution (4)were adopted. It is true that the payee though avoiding loss  would fail to make  the profit which he hoped to  gain  by the  fulfilment of the contract, but  in this  respect he would be  no worse off thanthe payer  who would not obtain the thing contracted for and mightfail to obtain the profit he envisaged. We have, therefore, come tothe conclusion,  after considering these four solutions, that the fourthshould be adopted.  We therefore recommend that, when performance of a contracthas been  frustrated in whole or in part and any money has been paid, or has been agreed to be paid, at a time prior to the frustrationof the contract, the following rules shall apply  unless a contraryintention appears from the terms of  the contract:       (1)  Money paid  by the  one party to the other in pursuance    of the contract shall  be recoverable, but subject to a deduction    of such  sum as represents a  fair allowance for  expenditure    incurred by the payee in the performance of  or for the purpose    of performing the contract.    In fixing the  amount of such    deduction  the Court shall include an allowance for overhead    expenses but shall also take into account any benefits accruing    to the payee by reason of such expenditure, and the amount    recovered shall not exceed the total of any  money so paid or    agreed to be paid under the contract.  Loss of profit shall in    no  case be taken  into  consideration.      (2)  When at  the  moment of  frustration  the contract has    been performed in part  and the part so performed is sever able,    these  rules shall apply only to  that part of the contract  which    remains  unperformed,  and shall not affect or vary  the  price    or other pecuniary consideration paid or payable in respect of    that part of the contract which  has been so performed.
      (3) For the purpose of these recommendations no regard shall    be had to amounts receivable under any contracts of insurance.  We do not recommend any  alteration  in  the law  relating  tofreight pro rata itineris, since the rule relating thereto, althoughfrequently criticised, has become so  firmly fixed that it would be undesirable to alter it.   For the same reason we do not recommendany alteration in the law relating to advance freight except in thecase of hire paid in advance under a time charter which, as explained in Appendix B, we  think should be recoverable in the event  offrustration of the adventure in the same manner and to the same extent as other payments in advance made under a contract.
                           APPENDIX  A.                        The law of other countries.A. The Law of Scotland.  It is only necessary to recall the words of Lord Dunedin in the CantiareSan Rocco case (1924) A.C. at p. 24S : &quot; It is sufficient to say, as I unhesitat-ingly do, that Chandler v. Webster, if it^had been tried in Scotland, would havebeen decided the other way.&quot;B. The Law of the Continent.  The  principal continental systems of law. treat the matter as  one calling for  the application of the doctrine of unjustified benefit.  The  position inGerman law is stated thus by Dr. Ernest  Schuster (Principles  of  GermanCivil Law, p.  351)  : &quot; Where the  benefit was received on a sufficient legalground, which  has  subsequently ceased to operate, or by virtue of an act-in-the-law the  purpose of which  has  not been accomplished, the person atwhose expense  such benefit was received has a right to the restoration of thestatus quo ante in the same way as if no sufficient legal ground had ever beenin existence.&quot;   He  refers to Articles 812 and 815 of the German Civil Codeand uses as an illustration of the principle the following facts : &quot; A paysB for the use  of a window on a date on which the coronation procession  isto pass it; the procession does not pass, owing to the King&apos;s illness.   A mayrecover the amount paid by him because the purpose of the hiring agreement under which it was paid was not accomplished.&quot;  The  Swiss Federal Code of Obligations (Article 62) provides in terms thatany one, who is unjustly enriched at the expense of another, must restore thebenefit  so received.  Similar  provisions are found in the Codes of many other countries.  In  French law  the  principle  applied  is that of case law[jurisprudence) which has laid it down that it is contrary to  natural justice to allow a man to enrich himself at the cost of his neighbour.   The principlewill cover a case where one of the contracting parties has got something fromthe other and is exonerated by frustration of the contract from giving any-thing in return.  He must either restore what he.has  received,  or pay somuch as represents the benefit which he derives from the impoverishment ofthe other party.   (See Planiol-Ripert ; Traite Pratique  de Droit  Civil, Vol.VII, cap. Ill,&quot;pp.  45-46, Walton &amp; Amos: Introduction to French Lawp. 202  et seq.   Cambridge Law Journal Vol. V, p.  205  et seq.).   The same principle has  been laid down by the Belgian Courts and was adopted  bythe framers of the draft Franco-Italian Code  of Obligations (Art.  73).  The  position in continental law would, broadly speaking,  seem to be asfollows.  If we assume that further  performance of a contract between  Aand B  is excused by reason of supervening impossibility, the following statesof fact may occur :        (a) A has paid money under the contract and has received no benefit    in return at the time of frustration.  B is excused from performance, but    must restore the  payment to A.  The same rule applies if something    other than money has been handed over to B.       (b) A has  paid money  and B has partly performed his  obligation    before frustration. A recovers his money less the value to him of B&apos;s part    performance (unless he restores what he has received).  If the benefit    is  worth more than what he has paid, A must also pay the balance to B.    As regards B,  he is exonerated from further performance, but  he must    refund  anything received by him in excess of the  benefit to A  of the    part performance.  If what  B has received  is less than the value to A    of the part performance, he  can  claim the balance from A.
C- American Law.  The American Law on this subject is stated  as follows in Section 468 ofthe Restatement of the Law of Contracts by the American Law Institute :        &quot; Section 468.  Rights of Restitution       (1) Except where a contract clearly provides otherwise, a party thereto    who has rendered part performance for which there is no defined return    performance fixed by the  contract, and who  is  discharged  from the    duty of further performance  by impossibility of rendering it, can get    judgment for the value of the part performance rendered, unless it can    be and is returned to him in specie within a reasonable time.       (2) Except where a contract clearly provides otherwise, a party thereto    who has rendered performance for which the other party is  excused by    impossibility from rendering  the agreed exchange,  can  get judgment    for the value of what he has rendered, less the value of what he has    received, unless what he has rendered can be and is returned to him in    specie within a reasonable time.       (3) The value of performance within the meaning of Subsections (1, 2)    is the benefit derived from the performance in advancing the object    of the contract, not exceeding, however, a ratable portion of the contract    price.&quot;                             APPENDIX B.Advance Freight.  We have  considered whether  any change  is desirable in the law relatingto the recovery  of advance payment where the  ship or the goods have been lost and the freight is not earned.   As the law stands at present advancefreight is, generally speaking, irrecoverable in these  circumstances (Byrne v.Schiller (1871) L.R.  6: Ex.  319).  The origin of the rule is obscure  : it does not seem to have been part of thelaw merchant and is not found in the law of other countries.  In Englandthere is a sentence the other way in the Admiralty  case of Le Buck v. VanVoisdonck (1554) 11  Selden Society,  93; but in the Common Law Courts the rule appears in Anon (1682) 2 Shower, 283, though it does not seem to have assumed a definite form until the nineteenth century (De Silvale v. Kendall(1815) 4 M.  &amp; S. 37).  The suggestion has been made  that  the rule was brought into being  by the vicissitudes inseparable from the  long voyagesto the East Indies in the days of sailing ships.  But whatever the underlyingreason may have been, the rule must now be regarded as well established.It was reconsidered  in 1876 by  the  appellate court  in the above-mentionedcase of Byrne v. Schiller, and was affirmed.   In delivering his judgment inthat case Cockburn  C.J. commented 011 the rule in  the following  terms (atPP-  325-326) :-       &quot; I regret that the law is  so.   I think  it founded on  an erroneous    principle and anything but  satisfactory  ....  But whatever may be    the true principle, I quite  agree that the authorities founded on the    ill-digested  case in Shower  are  too strong  to be overcome; and  if the    law is to be altered, it must be done  by the  legislature  and not by    contrary decisions.&quot;  We think that the rule is, as Cockburn C.J. said, unsatisfactory in principlebut it has been regarded as settled law for a long time past and the businesspractice of  shipowners and  insurers is to  some extent based on it.  Weconsider, therefore, that it would  be inopportune and undesirable to changeit save as regards hire paid in advance under a  time charter party, in which case the practice is different.  Most time charters, expressly or by implications-tion, provide for an adjustment of hire in the case of loss or inefficiency ofthe ship and it  is probably  only  per incuriam  that no similar provision ismade in the case of frustration of the adventure.  The resulting&apos; hardship
is illustrated by the case of French Marine v. Compagnie Napolitaine [1921]2 A.C. 494.  We therefore recommend that the general rule as to the non-recovery of advance freight be not changed, but that hire paid in advanceunder a time charter shall be recoverable in the event of frustration of theadventure in the same manner, and to the same extent, as other payments in advance made under a contract.Freight payable pro rata itineris.  Unless otherwise agreed, either expressly  or by implication, freight is onlypayable if the contract of carriage is completely performed.   So that wherethe shipowner is prevented from carrying the goods to  their destination he cannot claim any part of the freight, even though the failure to perform the contract is due to some cause beyond his control.  The ship may have arrivedat a place which is only just short  of the  contractual destination,  and the cargo owner may have  derived considerable  benefit,  amounting almost toperformance,  from the  voyage  but  no freight  is  payable.  Metcalfe v.Britannia Ironworks Co.  (1877) 1 Q.B.D. 613, 2 Q.B.D.  423.  The origin of the rule is uncertain.   It conflicts with the civil law, but was recognised by the  Court of Common  Pleas in 1611 in  Bright v. Cowper, 1Brownlow, 21.   In Luke v. Lyde (1759) 2 Burr. 882, Lord Mansfield allowedfreight pro  rata itineris  where a ship on a voyage from Newfoundland toLisbon was captured by the enemy within four days&apos; sail of Lisbon.   his decision has however been interpreted in such a way as to mean that freightpro rata is only to  be allowed where there  is either an express agreement tothat effect,  or where an agreement  can  be inferred from the circumstances(Metcalfe  v. Britannia  Ironworks  Co.,  supra).  This  sometimes leads tohardship where the goods come into the hands of their owner short of their destination.  The owner may, in that event, obtain the benefit of part per-formance without paying anything for it.  But the rule has been acquiesced in and acted upon  for so long that, although we regard it as unsatisfactory,we do not  consider it desirable or  necessary to change  it.   Therefore we make no recommendation.                                (Signed)   WRIGHT (Chairman).                                          ROMER.                                          PORTER.                                          RAYNER GODDARD.                                          CYRIL ASQUITH.                                          A. L.  GOODHART.                                          H.  C.  GUTTERIDGE.                                          H.  C.  HALDANE.                                          ARNOLD  D. MCNAIR.                                          WM. EGERTON MORTIMER.                                          CLAUD SCHUSTER.                                          ALFRED F. TOPHAM.                                          W. T. S.  STALLYBRASS.                                          H. U.  WlLLINK.                                          P. H.  WlNFIELD.      JOHN FOSTER (Secretary).   We have[signed the Report because we think that the suggested alterations inthe Rule in Chandler v. Webster would make the law fairer than it is at present.The Report contains  no  recommendation regarding the converse case wherethe promise has paid nothing;  in this case it appears the loss is still to &quot;liewhere it falls.&quot;  Presumably owing to the limited terms of reference it is notin the Committee&apos;s power to deal with either this question or the other ques-tions which arise on frustration.                                       (Signed) RAYNER GODDARD.                                               WM. EGERTON MORTIMER.        Printed under the authority of His Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office              By Eyre and Spottiawoode Limited, LondonX (431)0105  Wt 3617-24  1750  5/39

</content>
</cab>
