<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/287/0 images: 408-454</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS -DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC                MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).Copy No. . .SECRETCP. 144(39)CABINETINDIAQuarterly Survey of the Political and Constitutional              Position in British India,                For the period from           February 1st to April- 30th 1939.Circulated for the information&apos; of the Cabinet by the             Secretary of State for India.
QUARTERLY  SURVEY  OF  THE  POLITICAL  AND  CONSTITUTIONAL                        POSITION IN BRITISH INDIA.        No.  7.   For the period from February 1st to April 30th, 1939.                                     CONTENTS.                                                                          Page.I. INTRODUCTION                                                           1II. CONGRESS PROVINCES     (a) Ministries: stability and reputation         ..      ..       ..          1 2    (b) Provincial Budgets      &apos;  ..      ..      ..      ..       ..          2 3    (c) Legislatures: events of the sessions  ..      ..      ..       ..             4    (d) Relations of Ministries with the Central Congress Command    ..          4 5        The&quot; Vidya Mandir&quot; scheme     ..      ..      ..       ..             5    (e) Relations of Ministers with Governors : social contacts : special        responsibilities  ...       ..       ..&quot;      ..      ..       ..          5 6    (i) Relations of Ministers with their Secretariats : methods of business             6III. NON-CONGRESS  PROVINCES&quot;     (a) Ministers: stability and reputation   ..       ..      ..      ..             6    (b) Provincial Budgets        ..       ..       ..      ..      ..             7    (c) Legislatures: events of the sessions   ..       ..      ..       ..             8    (d) Relations of Ministers with Govern ors : social contacts : special        responsibilities   ..       ..       ..      ..      ..       ..             8    (e) relations of Ministers with their Secretariats : methods of business              iv. CHIEF COMMISSIONERS&apos; PROVINCES-       ..      ..                     8V. GENERAL SUBJECTS     (a) Treatment of the Services Service feeling    ..      ..      ..          8 9       Separation of judicial and executive functions  ..       ..       ..             9       Abolition of posts   ..      ..      ..      ..       ..       ..         9 10       Pay and allowances ..      ..      ..      ..       ..       ..        10 11       Private practice for medical officers   ..      ..      ..      ..        11-12       The move to the hills       ..      ..      ..      ...       ..            12    (b) Interference with the Administration        ..       .&apos;.       ..        12 13       The volunteer movement    ..      ..      ..       ..       ..            13    (c) Parliamentary Secretaries  ..      ..      ..       ..       ..            13    (d) Attitude of Ministries to law and order       ..       ..       ..        13 14       Remission of sentences      ..      ..      ..       ..       ..            14    (e) &quot; Political &quot; prisoners and detenus   ..      ..       ..       ..        14 15     (f) The Agrarian situation     ..      ..      ..       ..       ..        15 -16       Agrarian legislation        ..      ..      ..       ..       ..        16 17     (g) Communism       ..      ..      ..      ..       ..       ..        17 18     (h) The Labour situation     ..      ..      ..       ..       ..        18 20     (i) Terrorism         ..      ..      ..      ..       ..       ..            20     (j) Communal troubles        ..      ..      ..       ..       ..        20 23 LS2SGG(1?)
u                                                                             Page.VI, POLITICAL MOVEMENTS     (a)  The Congress Party       ..      ..      ...       ..       ..             23        The Congress President    ...      ....      ...       .,       ....        23-25  &apos;        &apos;Congress a,nd the States   ...      ....      ....       ..       ..        25 27        Congress and Federation  ..      ....      ..       ..       ..             27        The Tripuri and Calcutta sessions    ..      ..       ..       ..        27 28        Attitude to Indians Overseas        ..      ...       ..       ..             28        &quot; The National Planning Committee&quot;      ..       ..       ...             28    (b)  The Muslim League       ...       ..      ...       ..       ..             28        Relations with Congress   ..       ..      ..       ..       ..        28 29        The League and Federation         ..      ...       ..       ...             29    (c)  Other opposition to Congress       ,.      ..       ..       ..             29VII. SPECIAL PROBLEMS     (a)  Palestine          ..      ..       ..      ...       ..       .--       29-30    (b)  &quot;Prohibition&quot;  &apos;..      ..       ..      ..       ..       ..        30-31    .(c)  The Congress flag and Bande Mataram      ..       ..       ..        31 32    (d)  War and Recruiting       ..       ..      ..       ..       .,        32 34        Air-Raid Precautions     .,       ..      ...       ..       ..             34    (e)  Language in Legislatures  ..       ..      ..       ^.       ..             34VIII.  THE CENTRAL LEGISLATURES-    (a)  The Central Assembly      ..       ..       ..       ...       ..       35 36    ,(b)  The Council of State       ..       ..      ..       ..       ..       36-37IX. THE  FEDERAL COURT-  &apos;..       ......       ..       37-38APPENDICES-&apos;    I. Resolutions of the Congress Party         A. Resolutions passed by the 52nd session of the Indian National Congress              -at Tripuri, March 10th to 12th, 1939  ..       ..       ..         39-42        B. Resolutions passed by the All-India Congress Committee at Calcutta,               May 1st to 2nd, 1939        ..       ..       ..       ..            42    II.  Resolutions passed by the Working Committee and Council of the All-India               Muslim League.in March and April, 1939       ...       ,.        43 44
I - INTRODUCTION.                     Progress of Provincial Autonomy.    1. Provincial autonomy is now more than two years old.  Its capacity for good, according to a resolution passed at the Tripuri session  of  the  indian national Congress, is being rapidly exhausted.   The conduct of  the ProvincialMinistries, HOAVEVER,  tells a different story : THEY have undertaken programmes which require for fulfilment a long term of undisturbed work, in the legislaturesand outside.    When the last Survey was composed it appeared that the circumstances OFthe Congress party might, from one cause or another, lead to the demission  of office in the Congress Provinces.   In fact during the quarter resignation has morethan once been in the air : but the causes have been external to the Provinces namely, the revolt in the Congress, and the crisis induced  by Gandhi&apos;s fast.  Thecourse of provincial administration has on the whole run  smoothly.  It has been necessary AT times to assert the right and duty of Governors to make their owndecisions in the sphere of their individual judgment : and occasions have arisenwhen the  exercise of the functions of a Governor in his  discretion, of the Gov-einor General, or of  higher authority, has given dissatisfaction  to Ministers :nevertheless.  Governors  and Ministers  have performed their joint and severaltasks  without any serious danger of parting company.              11.-CONGRESS  PROVINCES.                   (a) Ministries : stability and reputation.     2. Assam. The coalition Ministry has maintained its position,  and  the opposition, which in September last when the Ministry was formed claimed 56 votes in a house of 107, has failed to cohere against it.   While following generally the principles  adopted by Congress  Ministries, the Cabinet has attempted  no ostentatious break with previous policy in  the Province.  Its  capacity  and goodwill are likely to  be  tested by the labour troubles which occurred towards the end of April.     3. Bihar. There is nothing fresh to be said about the Ministry, which still shows no great ability or  determination in dealing with its problems.  Of these, argarian discontent and communal discord have continued to be troublesome : the labour situation has been quieter.     4. Bombay. This Ministry CONTINUES to keep firm control  over  law  and order ; but its  reputation  for generally reasonable policy has been weakened by the extravagance shewn in  the extension of &quot;  prohibition &quot; and the  proposals for heavy taxation  required to make up the revenue so abandoned  and the  cost of preventive measures.   The  Parsis in particular will suffer both as consumers of alcoholic liquor and as having a big interest in the trade  ; but even in quarters which have no quarrel with  the principle of  &quot; prohibition &quot;  there  is strong objection TO meeting the  heavy cost of the steps  now  in  preparation.   The Ministry however shows no signs of being deterred from the prosecution of its design.     5.  Central Provinces. Dr. Raghavendra Rao&apos;s appointment as Adviser to the Secretary of State  removes a personality which has been regarded  as a pos- sible threat, &quot;to  the Ministry &apos;S comfort.  Dr. Khare lacks the power rather than the wall lo make trouble.  After the exciting prominence gained by organising the Tripuri session of the  All-India Congress Committee in March, the Ministry has returned to its normal tasks and in their performance has shewn its normal low level of efficiency.  In this Province as in some others communal feeling has notably AVORSENED.LS23GG(P)
    6. Madras. There is still no  effective challenge to the  Premier&apos;s  supre-macy or to the Ministry &apos;s stability, although the popularity of both is decreas-ing.   S. Srinivasa Ayyangar, who led an attack on the Ministry from withinthe Congress fold, is unlikely to. prove a. vigorous champion.  The non-Brahmanopponents of Congress still keep alive the anti-Hindi agitation : and  there  isopposition throughout  the Province to the  Government &apos;s proposals for  newtaxation, particularly the tax on sales.  The  Premier &apos;s unquahfied endorsement-jf the Prakasam Committee&apos;s proposals on behalf of zamindari tenants has. atsome cost to his reputation for sincerity, prevented a break  with  powerfulAndhra interests.  The Premier&apos;s health has been severely taxed by continuousover-work, and his temper and judgment show the effects of strain. -   7. N.-W. F. P.-The differences of opinion amongst the Ministers are keptbeneath the surface ; but the Ministry has been none.too happy in the Assembly *where its majority fell to two votes.  Hindu opinion is forming against  thePremier, through  dissatisfaction  both with the inadequacy of  the  measures taken to deal with raiding, and with the legislative policv of the Ministry.  TheAgriculturist Debtors  Relief  Act and  the Marketing Bill recently  passed  are much disliked by  Hindus, even in the Congress party.  The  Ministry ignoredthe advice of the President of the All-India  Congress to postpone the latter.    The Muslim League is making little headway against the Ministry whichin fact preserves its position through the failure of its opponents to combine.    8. -Orissa. There have befen no developments of importance.  The Premieris not the president of the Provincial Congress party ; and, though he and hisMinistry have the support of the majority of Congressmen in the  Legislature,the majority in the Provincial party favours  the other faction.    9. United Provinces- In a previous  Survey it was remarked  that  of  allthe Congress Ministries the U. P. Ministry  has  to  surmount the   greatestdifficulties. : In some respects these are increasing.   Discussion of the  TenancyBill is still proceeding, and the agrarian situation is therefore  still in suspense ;labour has made little  overt trouble in the quarter : but public order in  a num-ber of cities has been in constant danger from  the  bitterness of communal dis-sension.   The riots have been suppressed, but  only  by  such  vigilance  andstringent action on thepart of the magistracy and police (sometimes with troopsstanding by,) as can  scarcely be maintained as  normal practice ; and the  Pro,-vince&apos;s  growing notoriety as the  scene of the worst communal disorder bringsdiscredit on the Ministry. Criticism of the financial administration and opposi-tion to (he Ministry&apos;s taxation proposals are  also becoming more outspoken.    This Ministry has largely depended on  the personality and popularity  ofthe Premier -: his health is causing anxiety, and his judgment and   control  ofaffairs have been well below normal.  Another  cause that  appears  to   have affected the Ministry is the present uncertainty and indiscipline in the ranks of&apos;Congress : this is an added source of weakness  in a Province where unruly ele-ments have always been liable to give trouble,                          (b) Provincial Budgets.    10.  Assani -Revised  estimates for 1938-39 show a  deficit of 38  lakhs  asagainst an anticipated  deficit of 4i lakhs in the budget estimates for the  year.The estimates for the coming year disclose a deficit of over 17  lakhs.  It is pro-posed to wipe out the deficit by several new measures of taxation, including taxes.on agricultural income, petrol and lubricants, betting, certain luxuries, and thesale of goods.    11.  Bihar -The Province&apos;s financial position   is  comparatively  sound.Revised estimates fox the past year disclosed a better balance than had been anti-cipated, and the estimates for 1939-40 show a  nominal surplus of Rs. 75,000.  No.new  taxation is proposed, but it was announced that fresh sources of revenuewill have to be found to finance future development.    12.- Bo.wkay.-A. sensational budget was  presented, including a programmeof schemes to cost 250 lakhs, of which amount only 30 lakhs are to be found from existing revenue and 220 have to be made up by new taxation.  &quot; Prohibition &quot;is responsible for a loss of about 190 lakhs : extension of this measure in Bombaycity and suburbs alone will cost  120 lakhs.  Rural development schemes  and reduction of land revenue are to cost 80 or 90 lakhs.   New measures of taxationinclude&apos;a tax on urban immovable property, taxes on petrol, various fabrics,crossword and prise competitions, and increased electricity duty.  The finance minister also  announced that he  proposed to ask the authorities  concerned togive  the Province the full share of income-tax now instead of at  the  end  of
 10 years,-and also to-agree to a reduction in the-salaries of the services including those; under the control of  the Secretary of State, frankly admitting that   this was designed to help to meet the cost of &quot; prohibition &quot;.  The Ministry intend to complete their &quot; prohibition &quot; policy next year.     It was -soon -discoveiied -that the tax -on urban property  was going  to  hit very hard small middle-class people whose savings  are  invested in house  pre- perty.  The tax was to have been at the rate of 10 per cent, on the rateable value, but under strong pressure the Ministry agreed to  reduce the rate to 5 per cent.&apos; on property of a rateable value of less than -Rs. 2,000 in Bombay and to an even lower level -in Ahmedabad ; this reduction will mean a, loss of same 17  lakhs of -estimated  revenue.     Very  strong opposition has been aroused by this tax, as also by the extent sion of &quot; prohibition &quot;.     13. Central Provinces. Revised estimates for 1038-39  -show   a  revenue deficit of 34 lakhs instead of the anticipated surplus of  Rs.  82,000, due chiefly to a fall in land revenue resulting from  widespread remissions and  suspensions. For 1939-40 a. surplus of li laldis  is  estimated.  New  taxation  proposed includes the levy of licence fees and a tax  on  the  sale  of  tobacco,  enchanced- -stamp duties, and an enhanced rate of the sales   tax  on  motor  spirit.   Tha&apos;  elect Committee recommended inter alia  that the duration of these taxes be. limited to one year, apparently in order to force Government to  reduce  ad- ministrative expenditure.  The sales tax on tobacco has been abandoned in  con- sequence as much time is required for arranging for its levy, and the final result of the recommendations of  the Select Committee, all  of  Avhich  have  beeir accepted by  the -Government, is that the surplus has already  become a deficit.     The controversy^ concerning the allocation of revenue to Berar  was satis- factorily settled ; 41 per cent, of new expenditure  is  allotted  to Berar, the  total percentage of expenditure allotted to Berar having risen from 31  per  cent, to .34 per cent.     14. Madras. The  main  features  of  the budget, which has an estimated revenue deficit of 17 lakhs, are the extension of &quot; prohibition &quot;, and new forms of taxation.   The accounts  for 1938-39 were unexpectedly  satisfactory,  at  least on paper, in spite of heavy  remissions of land revenue ; the  raid on the Minor Ports Fund brought in 42-J- lakhs,  and the postponement of  a  substantial portion of the land revenue concessions within the  fash year to  the next financial yeaf gave a budgetary benefit in  1938-39  of Rs. 32 lakhs.  But for these  two devices, neither of which is capable of repetition, the revised estimates would have shown a deficit of 72 lakhs. The total loss of  revenue  due   to  &quot; prohibition &quot; is estimated  at. 65 lakhs.  New measures of taxation include iaxes on the sale of petrol and electricity, a tax on the sale of goods which has met with great opposi- tion, and a tax on the sale of tobacco.  The  Premier also  stated that his  Govern- ment were considering the possibility of a cut in the salaries of the Services.    15. North-West Frontier Province. The  budget   estimates  a deficit of. nearly 6 lakhs.  The only new tax proposed  is one on motor spirit and lubricants.    16. Orissa. The budget estimates  for  1939-4-0 show a deficit  of 18 lakhs Five  lakhs are to be spent  on a village  development fund.  No new taxation is proposed.    17. United Provinces. The. revised estimates for 1938-39 showed  that an estimated  deficit of 15  lakhs had  been turned into a  surplus of approximately the same amount.  For 1939-40 a deficit of  nearly 38 lakhs is estimated, which has been arrived at after taking into account  the sum of 8 lakhs to be derivedfrom the imposition of a tax on the sale of petrol.  &apos;&apos; Prohibition &quot;  is extended, and  some provision has been made for an  experimental separation of  judicialand executive functions (see para. 49).  The most important feature of the budget is the proposed  imposition of an &quot; Employments Tax &quot; on all Government and private employees earning more than Rs. 2,500 per annum.  This is expected to reduce the deficit by 30 lakhs.  The proposed tax has aroused vigorous criticism from various quarters&apos;.  While it will affect private  as   well as   Government servants, it is undoubtedly directed chiefly against  the services ;  the Minister in charge of the Bill  claimed  in the Legislature that the Ministry deserved  con- sn-atulation for devising a method of cutting salaries without the Secretary of State&apos;s consent.   The tax in fact amounts to an additional income-tax, and there is considerable doubt as to  the ooAver of a Provincial Government to  levy it. However that may be, there  can be no doubt as to the intention of the Constitn- tion as to the respective fields of taxation of the Centre and the Provinces :  andthe Bill (apart altogether from its effects on the services)  is not one  which could be nermittod to come into force.   The method of dealing with-it after it is passed in the Legislature is under consideration.
                  (cj  Legislatures : events of the  sessidns..    18. Assam. The budget session of the Assembly lasting from  March: 9th,to April 6th was uneventful.  Important legislation passed includes the Agri-cultural Income-Tax Bill, the Petrol and -Lubricants Taxation Bill, the Sales-Tax Bill,, and an Amusement and Betting Tax  Bill.    19. Bihar.-No  special  incidents  deserve mention in the session of the^Legislature which began in January and closed at the end of March.    20. Bombay. The budget session  of  the  Assembly lasted from February3rd to April 22nd.  The Finance Bill which provides for the imposition of thehouse-property tax and increased electricity duty was passed in March ; and the-Sales Tax Bill, which taxes  motor spirit, cloth, etc., in  April.  A  Bill  which-provides that Government shall  take 12-J per cent, of the total sum received bypromoters of prize competitions passed all  three readings in  one  day.   the village Panchayat Bill lias passed through both Houses ; its main features arecompulsory  establishment of. panchayats in  areas having, a population of morethan 2,000, the abolition of nominations, and constitution of village benches with-judicial powers.  At the end of the session a Bill was introduced to penalise-any one preventing &quot; Harijans &quot; from  exercising certain civil rights.    The new taxation measures  have produced some cohesion in the  opposition,,but the Ministry has  always been sure of its  majority.  The  opposition hasrecently drawn up a programme  on which it  is  hoped that all sections will unite.    21. Central Provinces^-Th.e  budget  session  lasted  from March  15th  to-April 20th.  The Select Committees limited the duration of all taxation measures;to one year, and  the Bills were  passed as so  amended,   A  Harijan  TempleWorship Bill has been circulated for opinion,    22. Madras. The budget session  of the  Legislature opened on February20th.   The Bills imposing a tax on petrol and a duty on the sale of electricity,,the Entertainment Tax Bill  and  the Tobacco Bill, were passed by the Assembl..The last named, which  extends the monopoly vend system to tobacco, has createdmuch  discontent among merchants ; but not so much as the Sales  Tax  Bill,.against which there has been a general outcry.  The latter had not been passedby the end of April.    23. North-West  Frontier Province. The budget session lasted from March17th to April 6th.  Two important Bills were passed-the Motor Spirit Taxa-tion Bill, and the Agricultural Produce Markets  Bill, which  aroused much criticism among Hindus including some Congress members of the Assembly.A private Bill  to repeal the Indian  Press   (Emergency  Powers)  Act  was defeated.    24. Orissa. The budget session began early in February,   The two mostimportant Bills passed Were the Hindu Religious Endowments Bill and   theMoneylenders Bill.  Attendance in the Assembly has been generally poor.    25. United Provinces. The  Assembly, sitting with brief intervals ever since-November last, had not risen at the end of April.  This inordinately long sessionhas proved  wearisome to the members and attendance has often  been  poor.Agrarian legislation is mentioned in paragraph 76.  Once  again  the  UpperChamber has  caused resentment by obstructing the Assembly&apos;s taxation  pro-posals ; the Motor Spirit Taxation Bill was  passed by the  Assembly,  but the Council amended it by reducing  the tax from 2 to 1-J annas per gallon of petrol. The Assembly refused to accept this  amendment.   The Bill imposing the em-ployments tax  (see paragraph 17), when it reached the Councik was referrr^ &apos;o a Select Committee, which  is expected to report by  the middle of  May.   Thisdecision was made bv a small majority against the wishes of the Ministry.  It is not unlikely that there will be a demand for another joint session to deal with these  measures.     On April 24th the Assembly chamber  in Lucknow was  invaded  by t  an? unruly crowd  of Sunni  Muslims ;  proceedings  were held  up for  some  time, find the incident created alarm and indifimation.   (See para. 93). /      (d)  Relations of Ministries  with the Central Congress Command,     26. In paragraph 20 of the last Survey mention was made of various matters in which the Congress central  command had intervened in Provincial affairs. As the Working Committee ceased to  exist  in February, the quarter now under review has  seen much less activity of  this kind.  Rajendra Prasad was present at a meeting between  the Governor of Orissa, the Ministry, and representatives of the zammdars, at which  the  possibility of a compromise on the Tenancy Bill
cyreserved for the consideration of the Governor-General was discussed ; but hisstatus, both in this matter and in an enquiry which he was conducting intocharges  brought  by a section of Congressmen  against  the  Orissa  Ministry^was for the time  being obliterated by his resignation from the Working Com-mittee.                                  -    A number of Provincial Ministers  showed where their sympathies lay mthe Congress  controversy by canvassing support openly  against SubhasBoseat the Tripuri session.  In April Bose  called upon the Congress Ministries toexplain this  conduct.  Their replies are not known.  He is  reported  also tohave  demanded an explanation from  the  Congress  Ministries  which,  duringGandhi &apos;s Kajkot  fast,  threatened to resign their offence being  that they tookthis  course without the President  being  consulted.  Further evidence of dis-obedience to Bose comes from the N.-W. F. P.; some Congress Hindu membersof the Assembly  telegraphed to both Gandhi and Bose asking  them to inter-vene  to  prevent  the unpopular Marketing Bill from proceeding ;  Gandhi didnot reply ; Bose  strongly  advised  the  Premier to postpone the considerationof the Bill, adding that Abul Kalam Azad  endorsed this advice.  The Premier,holding  that  compliance would give the  Muslim League a handle  for alleg-ing the Ministry to be under Hindu influence, paid no attention, and the bill was passed.    The rift in the Congress has given further proof that it is  Gandhi, ratherthan  the Congress President as such, who commands the  allegiance  of  theCongress Ministries.  When Bose was  left in almost sole charge on the resig-nation  of  12 members  of  the Working  Committee, five Congress Ministrieswere reported to have sent their resignations to Gandhi to use as he  thought fit, while the rest were expected to follow suit if required.     Gandhi&apos;s absorption in the Rajkot affair has left him little time or energyfor the  problems of the Provinces : and the absence of a Working Committeeand  Parliamentary Sub-Committee to give advice and exercise  control  may help  to  explain the disorganisation that has appeared  in the conduct  of someof the Provincial  Ministries.     27.  The &quot; Vidya  Mandir &quot; scheme. The Muslim  campaign of  civil  dis-obedience  in  Nagpur  continued until February 10th : over 200 Muslims court-ed arrest.  An  agreement was then  reached  after discussions  between  thePremier and the Secretary of  the Muslim  League : civil  disobedience ceasedand  prosecutions against  the arrested  persons were withdrawn.   The  Premier undertook to give equivalent assistance to any Muslim  association which might be founded  to forward  a  scheme for similar Urdu schools ; and promised that in areas where compulsory education is enforced no Muslim boy will be com- pelled to attend  a &quot; Vidya Mandir &quot;.  The  Working Committee of the Muslim League later noted  the  agreement with satisfaction.   The Bombay  Govern- ment have decided to introduce the Wardha scheme of  education in 100 schools from June 1939. (e)  Relations of  Ministers   with   Governors:  social   contacts :   special                               responsibilities.      28. There are no new developments  to report as  between Governors and their Ministers : but  it is relevant to  mention that the  Congress   President (Subhas Bose)  in April attacked prominent  Congressmen  resident in Delhi for  alleged  breaches  of the rule against social  relations with  officials.  Satva- murtt was accused of attending a party to  meet the Governor  of  Madras, Mrs. Sarojini Naidu  of lunching at the Viceroy&apos;s House, and all the Congress  mem- bers of the Central Legislature of taking&quot; tea with the Law Member.  The  de- linquents showed no  signs of penitence : and the ban is not likely to gain in strength from Subhas Bose&apos;s attempt to  enforce it.      The death  of H. E.  Lord Braboume Avas received Avith a remarkable  de- monstration of mourning throughout the  contry ; and  in BombaA&apos; as Avell as in Bengal the Ministers  Avere among the first to pay tribute to his  eminent services and personal popularity.      29. Special  responsibilities. While there have been no instances  of actual conflict arising  from the attraction  of  a  Governor^   special  resoonsibilitv. Governors are finding  more frequent occasion  to  question proposals of then- Ministers,  pat;ticularly in matters affecting the seiwices.  In  Assam the GOA-- ernor had to include  in an authenticated schedule  the  amount required in  the coming year for the  remaining post of  Commissioner, the demand for Avhich had been rejected by the Legislature  Avith  the  Ministry&apos;s approAml.  In Bihar LS2SGG(P)
and  the Central Provinces the Governors have had to apply pressure in  thematter of postings.  An attempt  of the Madras Premier to victimise the Pis-trict Magistrate in whose presence the strikers in  the  Chittivalsa  jute  millwere fired on was defeated only by the refusal of the Governor to- agree to thecourse proposed. In  this Province also the Premier at first talked of resign-ing when his proposal to cut the pay  of Government servants was vetoed.  (Itis  however worthy of mention that,  even after the  difficult Cabinet  meetingwhen these and other controversial topics were  discussed,  the   Premier,  in accepting the Governor^ suggestion  that he  should take a month&apos;s  holiday,expressed the hope that the Governor, whom he could trust rather than  anyof his colleagues, would take over part of his  work.)     Tho  unwillingness  of certain Ministries  to prevent  agitators from theirProvinces stirring up strife in neighbouring  States, particularly Hyderabad,may yet  lead to difficulties  which &quot;might involve the use of special powers.     The  U. P.  Governor has recently been enabled,  without provoking resent-ment, to take a much stronger line with his Cabinet than formerly.  The reasons are that the problems of immediate urgency are those of public order in whichthe Ministers recognise the  Governor&apos;s definite responsibility :  that  the Minis-tors, being aware that these problems have disturbed public opinion, are movewilling to accept guidance : that  the Premier,  whose irresolute  policy has been much criticised in his own party  and  outside it, is consequently easier to movethan he used to be :  and that some of his colleagues are on these matters more in agreement with the Governor than with the Premier.    (f) Relations of Ministers with their Secretariats : methods of business.     30. Previous Surveys have mentioned the  unbusinesslike   habits  of  anumber of Ministers, resulting in additional work and worry for the official staff and sometimes great delays.  Instances continue  to  arise : and in  some  Pro-vinces Ministers holding important portfolios are  in  such poor health that theyare at times no longer fully competent to perform their duties.  In the importantProvinces of Madras and the  United Provinces, for instance, public  businesssuffers from the fact that the Premiers  are sick men,  with  temper, judgmentand capacity for work impaired by ill-health.        111.-NON-CONGRESS PROVINCES.                         (a)  Provincial Ministries.    31.  Bengal-The resignation in February of Shamsuddin Ahmed, one ofthe two newly-appointed Ministers, was a relief to the Cabinet.   He had broughtwith him no support, and many of the Ministry&apos;s followers disapproved of hisinclusion.   Shamsuddin accused the Premier of failing to implement the termsof the understanding on which he had joined the  Cabinet : his inability to fulfil the conditions imposed by his Krishak Proja party wras probably the cause ofhis resignation.   On the whole Ministerial  solidarity seems to have improved :the Ministry has shown  signs of resisting  concessions to clamour, of  refusing to be stampeded by the  Legislature, and of laying down a more definite pro-gramme.    32.  Punjab. The Ministry has been noisily assailed in the Legislature and outside  it  : but its position does not seem to have  been seriously weakened.    33.  Sind. In accordance  with the decision mentioned in  paragraph 26 ofthe last Survey, the Ministry  was enlarged  early in February by the inclusion,first of  a  Hindu and a Muslim,  and shortly afterwards of Sir Ghulam HusainHidayatullah, who had been Premier till March 1938.  But no  Ministry in Sindappears to be certain of peace.  An outburst of hysteria  in the Hindu com-munity  over  a new.religious movement has proved the  latest threat  to  itsstability.  This  movement, known as Om Mandli, was accused of encouragingsexual licence among its followers ;  a demand was made that the Governmentshould  suppress  it by means of doubtful  legality ;  and this  demand Avas  re-inforced by noisy  demonstrations and the threat  of  civil disobedience.  TheUvo Hindu Ministers succumbed to pressure and resigned  on  March 24th.   by april 3rd, they were in office again, measures haying  been taken against theleaders of the Om Mandli  Avhile  a tribunal  Avas appointed to investigate itsbehaviour.  The  tribunal&apos;s  report,  submitted in  April,  upheld the allegationsagainst the Mandli.
    34. Bengal. Estimates  for  the  coming year  show a  deficit of 87  lakhs.There are sufficient investments to cover the deficit but it is proposed to conservethem by resort to a loan of one crore.  The Finance Minister uttered a warning that the resources were almost exhausted and new revenue must be found for future development.   Two new taxes are being levied, a tax on betting or dog-xacing and an ungraduated tax of Rs. 30 per annum on persons engaged in pro-confessions, trades  and employments who pay income-tax.  These  taxes  are  cal-culatod to bring in 12 lakhs.    35. Punjab. The budget revealed that the Province&apos;s finances are healthy :but the enormous expenditure for two years running on famine relief has upsetcalculations and  will be responsible for a deficit of 29 lakhs in the coming year.The famine is calculated to be costing 185 lakhs in  two years including 75 lakhson account of taccavi loans.   In  1938-39 the  direct  expenditure on famine reliefplus loss of revenue on account of remissions  and suspensions  of  revenueamounted to 55 lakhs, of which 9 lakhs was  met from the Famine Relief  Fund.This converted what would have been a surplus of 19 lakhs into  a deficit of 27.Two more irrigation projects are to be launched.  Only one new  measure oftaxation is to be imposed, a tax on petrol, to bring  in about 6 lakhs.   The intro-duction of &quot; prohibition &quot; has been postponed indefinitely.    36. Sind. Although  the budget  estimates show a surplus of nearly seveniakhs, the financial position of the Province is not satisfactory : no new schemescan be developed without fresh  sources of revenue being found ; the Premierremarks that, until a way is found of replacing the loss in excise revenue whichwould result from the introduction  of &quot;prohibition&quot;, this measure  is  notpractical politics.  No new taxation  is proposed this year.  The barrage reve-nues show no sign of being able to cope with the redemption of barrage debt aserious position.(c)  Legislatures: events of the session.    37. Bengal-The budget  session began on February 15th and was con-tinning at  the end of April.  The Finance  Bill, imposing a tax of Rs. 30 perannum on persons who pay income-tax, was passed in spite of loud protest from congress and Hindu middle-class representatives.   The budget was passed Avith-out difficulty.  A Maternity Benefit Bill has become laAV.  The much-criticisedOfficial  Records Bill,  designed to prevent  unauthorised dissemination of the contents of unpublished  Government  records, has been circulated for opinion.A Moneylenders Bill and a  Calcutta Municipal Amendment Bill, both of whichhave caused some dissent in the Cabinet, are expected to be passed before the session concludes.  The  opposition has  not caused the  Ministry much  incon-venience in the Legislature.    38. Punjab. The budget session lasted from February 27th to April 24th.The Bill imposing a tax on the sale of petrol Avas passed, as also the budget.The Bill providing for the appointment of a Sergeant-at-Arms  was passed after a  heated debate.  There have again been many disorderly  scenes  and theAssembly maintains its reputation for a IOAV level of parliamentary behaviour.Some excitement was caused at the end of  the session by the opposition filingmotions of no-confidence  against all the Ministers  ; three motions were defeatedby a majority of about 60 votes, and the  rest Avere not put to the vote.    39. Sind. The  budget session which lasted from early in February until april 1st Avas a stormy one for the Ministry.  The Congress party made severalattempts to defeat the Government.  In March a Congress cut motion to censurethe  Governmenfs   excise  policy  was   defeated  by  27   votes  to  20 ;another censure motion  a few  days later was lost by 31 votes to 23.  Duringthe session the &quot; Om Mandli &quot; controversy (see paragraph 33) threatened theMinistry ;s security ; when the two Hindu  Ministers resigned the budget hadnot been passed, but they agreed to vote Avith Government on the demands Avhilethe Governor considered their resignations, and  the budget  was  thus  safelypassed.  The attitude of  the Hindu Independent party has been enigmatical andinfluenced largely by the &quot; Om Mandli &quot; dispute ; but by the end of the session the party, which had been wavering, Avas back again on the Ministerial side.(b) Provincial Budgets.
(d) Relations of Ministers with Governors : social  contacts : special responsi-                                bilities.    40. There is nothing to report.  (e)  Relations of Ministers with their Secretariats : methods  of business.    41. It has been decided to raise no objection to the Punjab Premier&apos;s request for an I. C. S. private secretary.  His duties will be carefully denned, and thetenure of the post is likely to be limited.IV.-CHIEF COMMISSIONERS&apos; PROVINCES.    42. Ajmer-Merwara. Congress  agitation in istimrari areas (see para. 42of Survey No, 4) has had a disturbing effect on tenants, who in February weredeclining to pay customary dues.   Tenants are now aware  that  the CentralGovernment are considering new tenancy legislation and are less ready to takethe law into their  own hands than they would be if Congress were their onlychampion.  There  has  been some communal tension dining the big religiousfestivals but serious trouble has been  avoided.  The  Province (which  is an island of British India in Rajputana) has been used as a centre for the organi-sation of agitation  in Indian States, and several parties of volunteers have beensent to Hyderabad.    43. Delhi. The &quot; temple dispute &quot; agitation has continued throughout the quarter (see para.94).   Communal relations  have been  embittered  by  agita-tion directed against. Hyderabad State  ; Delhi  is used as the place from  whichvolunteers are launched from the Punjab  and parts of the United  Provinces.The arrival in the city of 3,000 Muslims migrating from Jaipur, as a demonstra-tion against alleged ill-treatment of the community there, caused  little excite-ment.    44..  Coorg. The budget shows a more satisfactory  state  of affairs, but would still be a deficit budget without the subvention from the Central Govern--ment.  Retrenchment proposals are under consideration.    45. Andaman Islands and Panth Piploda. There is  nothing  to  report.               V.-GENERAL  SUBJECTS:              (a)  Treatment of the Services :  Service feeling.    46. A recent estimate has been made of the treatment of the Services, andof the morale, in one of the Congress Provinces.  Though in this Province fewspecific attacks have developed on conditions of service, e.g., in the way of cutsin pay, the position of the Services has caused some uneasiness.   It was expectedthat the new constitution would make a material chang-e in the  circumstancesof Government servants, but the change has proved  beyond  expectation.   Inthe  Secretariat  the work of officers has most  grievously increased :  in  the  law and order &quot; departments there is a constant struggle between the perma-nent officials and the Ministers : in the &quot; nation-building &quot; departments, thoughthe work  is equally heavy, and  though  Ministers are  liable  to interfere inmatters of detail, the position is easier, and relations between the Ministers onthe one hand and  Secretaries and heads of  departments on the other are not unsatisfactory.  In  dealing with the Premier the Chief Secretary can carry hispoints, for instance in public order matters or in the posting of officers, only, if at all, after long discussion.  In the districts, officers are somewhat disheartened :a District Magistrate of distinction finds the atmosphere so dispiriting that helias decided to retire and take up private  employment in India : other british officers would probably do the same if they could find  employment : the feelingappears to be growing among British officers that it might have been better ifthey had been  paid off, as in Egypt, before the new constitution was introduced :but possibly the younger officers, who did not know &quot; the good  old days &quot;, are
 happier.  Among the Provincial Services there is the same uneasiness, parti- -eularly among officers belonging to minorities, such as Muslims : though there have been no serious cases  of  unfair   treatment, in   minor matters, such aspostings, the opinion is spreading that advantage can  be secured by getting on the rigM  side of the Premier, by fair means or foul : it is difficult for  the Chief Secretary or the Governor to resist proposals for which plausible reasons are given :  even where an officer  does not suffer by a transfer, the view undoubtedlyprevails that the motive behind  it is often personal, political, or communal.   As regards the police in particular, there &quot;has certainly been deterioration in morale : in the civil disobedience campaign they  believed themselves engaged in a fight with Congress to a finish : with the assumption of office by Congress,  a  feeling of insecurity is spreading among them i the interference of Ministers in discipline and duties,  often at the instance of   interested parties, is  demoralising : ex- perience of certain incidents has shaken  the confidence of the subordinate ranks in the capacity of their superior officers  to protect them and  in the safeguards provided by the Act.  It is however satisfactory that  on the  whole both police and magistracy are still dealing well with communal and agrarian disturbances.     It is not suggested that this picture  is typical of conditions  even  in  theCongress Provinces : but some of the circumstances which have produced it exist in some degreedn all of them, namely, Ministerial inexperience of the exercise of authority, liability to pressure from supporters, and memories of the days, still recent,  when a large part of the official  staff was  engaged  in  combat with congress : and where the Ministers are lacking in ability and personality, in any high degree of public spirit, or in willingness to&quot;accept guidance from permanent-officials, an atmosphere can easily be created in which  the maintenance of keen-ness, serenity, and integrity in all ranks  is not too  easy.     Appointments and postings, and disciplinary action, are proving to be fieldswhere constant vigilance is needed to prevent incidents liable to cause  despond-ency in the  Services.     47.  It is not only in the Congress Provinces that officers may have reason to apprehend partiality on the part of Ministers.  Communal bias is  not  unknown in the treatment of the Services in Bengal.  A possibly salutary incident came to light in March when the adjournment  of the Assembly of that Province  was moved in  order  to censure the Ministry  for a charge  made  by  the  Premieragainst Hindu officials in a letter written by him.  The letter contained  the expressions-&apos;&apos; I have found out that almost all the Hindu officers are encouraging-ing people belonging to the Congress or to the opposition because at heart they are entirely against my Government.............  Every day I  get  evidence of the disloyalty of most of theffiindu officers &quot;.  In the course of the debate,and also in the Press, the Premier tendered a full apology for these aspersions.    48.  A further development in the  move against corruption in the services is reported from Bombay, where anti-corruption committees are to be appointed in every district,  consisting  of  the  Collector,  the  District  Superintendent   ofPolice, and two  non-officials selected by  the Collector.  The rules are^ to be so framed  that the committees will be  only  advisory and  the chairmen will  invari- ably be officials ; the chief function of the non-officials will be the propagationamong the public of active discouragement of corruption, and they will have nosort of authority over Government servants.    49-  Separation of judicial and  executive functions. The proposals made by the officer detailed to examine this question in the United Provinces (see para. 3,9 of Survey No. 5) were accepted for the most part by the Minister for Justice, who, after, consulting the High Court and the Board of  Revenue, prepared a noteembodying a provisional scheme, which  was laid on the table of the Assembly at the &quot;end of February.  This note did not touch on some important points, e.g., the personnel required, the cost of the scheme, and whether the experiment should first be  tried on a small scale only. Provision for putting the scheme into opera- tion has been made  in the budget.  On April 18th, the proposals were debated in the Assembly ; the Minister announced that the scheme was provisional and might be altered.  He undertook to give the House another opportunity to dis- cuss it.     On April  22nd the Bombay Assembly held a debate on this question.  The Home Minister explained that Government  considered v this  reform  to   be urgently necessary,  but administrative  and financial difficulties  stood  in  the wav of  its adoption.   &quot; 50.  Abolition of posts. The Assam Ministry  refused  to  include in  the budget  provision for the pay of the  staff  of the remaining Commissioner,  as well as the pay for March of the staff of the  Commissioner who was to  be abolished LS2SGG(r/)
                                     1Q-  (see para. 37 of the last Survey).-  The Revenue Minister put forward a-proposal-  to transfer all the duties of the remaining Commissioner to the  (one-member)  Revenue Tribunal, arguing that membership of the Tribunal is   likely  to  be:  thrown open to the Provincial Service and it would- be anomalous to have  an  I. C. S. officer drawing a Commissioner^ pay while the member of the Tribunal  draws less.  The scheme has however not been-fully worked-out.  . The- Assembly  rejected-the budget demand, inserted by the Governor-, for the Commissioner &apos;s-establishment ; the Governor- then- included it in the  authenticated schedule.     The United Provinces  Ministry presented  at the end of January a memo-  randum containing, proposals for the abolition of all the Commissionerships in  the Province   if- this proposal  could not be  accepted they suggested  that  at  any rate four of the eight posts should be abolished immediately.  Though the  Ministers attach considerable importance to  the financial saving, their main case  is that, whatever may have been the merits  of the system in the past, it is now inconsistent with their ideas of administrative policy.   They contend-that Minis- ters are now in close touch with public opinion and do not require Commissioners to inform them of it or to advise them on questions of pokey.. They contemplate a system of increased  centralisation and  direct communication with  district  officers.  The Governor  was unable, to agree with these views and proposals ; in his covering despatch he refuted-the arguments contained, in  the memorandum. and suggested-that any  decision as  to the abolition of  Commissioners&apos;  posts should be postponed until His Majesty&apos;s Government undertake, the contemplated review of problems of recruitment and control of the Services.  The memorandum. is&apos; now under the consideration of the Secretary of State.     The Bombay Ministry also is likely  to make a request for the abolition of all  Commissionerships in the  Province, but no formal, demand has yet  been made.  The Reventie Minister does not conceal the fact that he considers the retention of officers- of this status as incompatible with the new constitution.     In the  Central Provinces the Ministry proposed that the  post of Commis- sioner  of Nagpur should be left vacant during the Commissioners absence on three months&apos;&apos;  leave and- that the charge should be combined with that  of the neighbouring, division.  They had been heckled in the Assembly for having done- nothing about  abolishing Commissioners-, and wished ;to- make a gesture to re- assure  their followers.  The Governor was not prepared to accept the proposal.     The Madras Ministry has- siibmitted a memorandum giving various grounds for  a protest stgainsf the appointment in the Province of the Central Intelligence- Officer  employed by the Intelligence Bureau of the Central Government.   The Governor has endorsed the  views of the Ministry.  In no other Province has a protest been made  against this appointment.  The memorandum is under the- consideration of the Secretary of State.     The Central Provinces Ministry has  asked for the cessation  of recruitment to the civil branch of the I.  M. S.   The  same proposal has  been  made by the Ministries of Assam,  Bihar, Bombay,  Madras and  Sind.   The  Bombay   and Madras proposals  have  been  rejected ; the Joint  Select  Committee of  both Houses of Parliament on Indian Constitutional Reform specifically considered this matter and recommended that the civil  branch of  the I. M. S. must be re- tained,  and the Secretary of State sees no reason to reconsider  their decision. The proposals of the other Provinces are still under consideration.     The Central Provinces Government  Avish to take poAver  to  retire  com- pulsorily officers Avho haA7e completed 25 years&apos; sendee, on a pension of one-half of their emoluments, for  administrative reasons or for reasons-  of economy.     The Bengal Ministers  resisted  their supporters&apos;  demand for general re- tireffient after  25 years&apos;  service, but favour a  system of  retirement after  30 years&apos;  service or at the  age of 55,  AvhicheArer is earlier.  The object of  their supporters  is apparently to accelerate the  creation  of vacancies and thereby effect more rapid recruitment particularly of Muslims.  The Sind Government has  decided  to retire compulsorilv all persons  in ministerial service at the age of 55.     51. Pay and allotvances. At the beginning of February the Madras Minis- try  submitted two  memoranda ;   one requested the  Secretary of State to im- pose a  cut of 5 per cent, for a  period of  two years in the pay  of  officers under the control of the Secretary of State  serving in the ProAdnce ; the other requesf- ed the GoA^more to agree to a 5 per cent, cut, also for a  period of  two years, in the pay of  proA-incial and subordinate service officers earning more  than Rs. 100 per month.   The main  reasons given to support these  demands Avere that the pre- \dous (interim) Ministry had given  land  revenue  concessions   involving  an annual  loss  of 75 lakhs  and that bad seasonal  conditions had had an adverse
hi s, (&quot;% effect oil ])rovincial finances.  The Ministry also asserted that they did not feel -justified, in imposing heavy taxation to balance  the budget unless they could at the same time reduce the cost of administration.     The Governor-Genera]  and the  Secretary of State were not satisfied  that any unavoidable circumstances had  arisen  in  Madras  such as would justify amendment of the Government of India Act and abrogation of the protection expressly given by Parliament to the  existing pay of members of  All-India Services so long as they continue in service.   They accepted the view taken by the Governor that the  deterioration  of  the  financial position of the  Province, which was urged as a ground for the reduction in the pay of the Services,   was properly attributable to the deliberate sacrifice of revenue involved in the Minis- ferial policy  of a rapid extension of prohibition throughout the Province,  and held that the members of the All-India Services  could not properly be called on to make a  special contribution towards  the  financing  of a  policy affecting the whole Province  over and above the share of fresh  taxation which they would pay in common with other members  of the public.     As  regards  proposals  for a cut in the pay of Provincial and Subordinate Services, the Secretary of  State accepting the advice  of (the Governor and the Governor-General authorised the former  to refuse to permit the cut.  The Secre- tary of  State attached importance to making  it clear to Ministers that the objec- tion of principle to making a cut in salary in present circumstances is precisely the same in the case  of Ail-India, Provincial and Subordinate Services.   The Governor was informed that he could property say that in his view the financial position of the Province did not demand such breach of faith with the members of the Provincial and Subordinate Services as was involved in the reduction of the scales of pay to the continuance of which they had every right to look forward when they entered service.   In their case, as in the case of the All-India Services, it was considered that no justification existed  for demanding from them a special contribution towards the cost of a policy of prohibition.  When the Governor made these decisions known to his Ministers the Premier threatened to resign, but changed his mind within 24 hours.     Nothing further has been heard of proposals for revised scales of pay for new entrants to the Services under the control of the Provincial Government iir Bengal  or the United  Provinces.  In Bombay the Ministers drew-up revised scales for new entrants  to the Provincial Services some time ago ;  it was  then. decided  to consider the  matter further, but no more has  been  heard  of  the scheme.     The employments tax proposed in the United Provinces has been  discussed elsewhere  (paragraph 17).  In the Central Provinces  an ungraded  profession tax of Rs. 7 a quarter on all persons assessed to income-tax became payable by military establishments  stationed in the Province, as  by  other Government servants.  Objection to  payment was at  first taken by the military authorities,. and there  was some  delay in consequence in serving demand notices :  in the meanwhile units  were transferred, and it is  apprehended that trouble may be made for the  civil officers responsible for the  collection of amounts which might prove irrecoverable.     It appears that no decision has been made about the proposals for reduction in  special pay and compensatory allowances  in  the  United  Provinces. In Bombay no systematic revision of special pay  has been undertaken but individual cases have been examined and the general trend of orders has been towards re- duction  or abolition.  Here, as in the North-West Frontier Province, there is little disposition  on the part of the Provincial Ministers to approach the Secre- tary of  State for permission to abolish special pays sanctioned by him.     With regard to travelling allowance the rule  made by the Secretary of State (see paragraph 38 of the last Survey), requiring  his approval for changes which would operate to the disadvantage of his officers, appears to have excited little interest  or opposition.   There is nothing further to report on this subject.     52. The question of restricting private practice  for medical officers of the Provincial Service has been further considered in consultation with the Director General, Indian Medical Service.  The principle  of the  new rules framed by the Madras  Ministry is the  substitution of consulting practice for private practice as hitherto permitted.  &quot;Cinder the original proposals medical officers  were  also required to pay to Government 15 per cent, of the fees taken and to submit, a monthly return of cases seen and fees received. An examination of the definition of consulting practice evolved by the Ministers showed that it amounted in effect almost to a total  prohibition of private practice instead of to a restriction only.Thus it introduced  a new ruling, not accepted  elsewhere, that a patient can only
 be  examined   in  a  consultant &apos;s  house  if  brought  through   the  intro- duction  of  a   registered  medical   practitioner.    The   Governor   was,, therefore,   asked   to   persuade   his   Minister,    if   possible,   (a)   to. amend the definition  of consulting- practice  in  so  far  as it was  inconsistent with the universally accepted definition, (ft) to abandon the proposal to take- 15 per cent, of the fees received, and (c) to limit the proposed restriction to  the- case of officers receiving more than the minimum pay in order to preserve   the- private practice of those who, because of their inferior qualifications, would  not be likely to be called for consultation.  The Ministers  agreed to amend the defi- nition of consulting practice and to reduce the percentage of fees to be  taken by Government to 5 per cent.   They  were unwilling-  to abandon altogether   the demand for a proportion of the fees although the objectionable features: involved in the jnoposal were explained, or to exclude the lower paid medical officers from the  scope of the new rules.   In the, circumstances, of Madras, where  there is no. dearth of qualified private  practitioners, and as it  is  believed that the average increase over salary accruing from private practice is not more than 10;  to 15  per cent., so that the lOss involved to the officers concerned is not likely to be  consider- able, it Avas decided to accept the proposals of the Ministry as modified  and they-will take effect from next year.     An even more drastic proposal has been made in the North-West Frontier Province Avhere the Ministers contemplated the complete abolition of any form of private practice  for Government medical officers,   Tho  Governor has been asked to point out to his Ministers the unworkability of such a measure in  a province where qualified private practitioners are scarce and adequate medical aid, except from Government officers, could only be obtained  in the larger towns..     Proposals are now under consideration hi consultation  with the Secretary of State for limiting the  private  practice of officers of the Indian  Medical Service throughout India to consulting practice,, and Governors have been asked to furnish their views as well as the views of their Ministers on this  question,,.1&apos;t is felt that in the new conditions I. M. S. officers as  a  Avhole would themselves. probably welcome a restriction of  this nature.     53. The move to  the hills. It has been the practice for the, Secretariats and heads of departments  of most of the Provincial Governments  to, move to, hill-stations  during the summer months.  In the  non-Congress Provinces no change has been made in past practice : but in some of  the  Congress. Provinces, changes have been introduced.     The  Bombay  Government migrated  to Poona as usual in 1938 from the  be- ginning of June till the end  of October,  and have  decided to do so again this year ; to abandon the move  would cause great indignation among the Mahrattas, and Ministers  themselves  prefer Poona  to Bombay in  the  hot weather.     In the Central Provinces orders were issued&apos; in  January  1938  that  the official move to Pachmarhi should be discontinued as such, but that all. Ministers,, Secretaries and Heads of Departments might go  up  provided they paid their own  expenses and those  of the staff they took with them.     In Madras in 1938 it was arranged that Secretaries  and . Heads   of   De-. partments should go  as  usual to  Ootacamund  for a  little over two months,, but  Avould tak.e  considerably less  clerical  and  menial  staff  with  them.  The saving Avas  estimated at about Rs.  32,000.  Most  of the Ministers also Avent up for some time on tour.   The same arrangements have  been  agreed  upon for  this year     The  United  ProAdnces Ministers Av,ere  mostly  in types^our  of  continuing the  exodus to Naini Tal, but had to yield in 1938 to pressure from their party.. They decided  hoAvever to  alloAV  Secretaries  and  recessing officers, including Commissioners, Heads of  Departments and  others,  to go up  as  usual,  on condition that  th,ey paid for  any staff they took with them..   Several Ministers, discovered the advantage  of escaping the  hot Aveather in 1938,  and this year the  provincial  Congress party  left  the  decision  to the  Ministers,  who  are still  in favour of it.  They would even have been  in favour  of  a session of the  legislature  at Naini  Tal if accommodation could have been obtained.   It has  been decided to continue last year&apos;s  arrangements.                   (b) Interference with the Administration.     54.  The Chief Justice  of the  Lahore  High Court  uttered  a strong com-. plaint against approaches  by influential persons  to  judicial officers  in order to affect decisions  in cases ; this habit, he said, is  widespread and  is  cal- culated  to undermine service morale.  The  Punjab  is  not  the only  Province affected  by such  practice.  Instances  have  come to  light, and  have, some-
times been  prosecuted  and punished, of attempted  interference particularly by Congressmen with  the impartiality of judicial officers.    55.  The only matter of those mentioned in the last Survey (paragraph 43),in which  there are  any developments to report, is  the  Volunteer Movement.A volunteer corps in Assam is reported to be training in th,e use  of guns andtarget practice ;  tb,e volunteers are mostly members of  a students&apos; federationwhich is  controlled  by socialists.  The volunteer movement  is  said to  bespreading in  Bengal,  and reports  from Bihar  indicate considerable  activity of this  kind.    The Premier of the Punjab  has mentioned to  the  Governor a  proposalfor the  formation of a social service volunteer  corps, to be organised by theMinistry.   The  corps  would be  open  to  eligible persons over  the age  of18 belonging  to  any community  and any party.  Each volunteer would  bepaid  enough to cover the expenses of training  which would include physicaldrill,  scouting, and  elementary military drill, but this would not  be a charge on Provincial  revenues as the cost would be  met by  an endowment fund.Volunteers  would be required  to  wear  a uniform.  What the Premier hasin mind is  a  corps  of  loyalists organised  as a  counterblast to the congress and  other volunteer  corps  which  are springing up.  The professed  aims  ofthe corps  would be to promote and encourage village uplift, and to keep orderat fairs and gatherings if the police had no objection.   In practice, however,a corps controlled by the Ministry  is likely to consist of partisans  and to showa  strong  political bias.  The various objections  to adding to  the number  ofunwelcome volunteer bodies none  of Avhich in any Province at present enjoysthe active support and control of  the Ministry a corps  to be organised  onthe lines  contemplated  by the Punjab Premier  have been explained to him ;and  the project  has  been discouraged.    Plans to  organise  new communal bodies are mooted  from time  to, time.For  instance  the Akali party in  the Punjab professes  to be building up   avolunteer organisation  to be known as the &quot; Akali Fauj &quot;, to perform social services to the Sikh community at religious fairs  and festivals.  The  corps isbeing raised in opposition to other volunteer  organisations which are menacingHindu  communal interests.  Military training is to be  imparted  with. retiredmilitary officers as instructors,  and volunteers will wear a uniform.   Anothersimilar  organisation to be called  the &quot;  Punjab  Kisan Fauj &quot; is being raised,whose immediate programme is to secure various kinds of agrarian reform.Both organisations will be  run for the  benefit of the Akali party and will be supported from that party &apos;s funds.  Efforts  to enlist   volunteers have been,and  are perhaps likely to  be, unsuccessful ;  but the services of  one retiredmilitar3r officer  have been  secured and the  training  school  will  be   openedshortly.    The Punjab Congress  Socialist party also  propose  to form a &quot; NationalMilitia  &apos;&apos;, intended to prevent &quot; goondas &quot;  (hooligans)  of the Unionist Partyfrom disturbing  socialist meetings.    The United  Provinces Legislative  Council  passed  without a division   aresolution urging the Government to raise and train an armed body as a &quot; civicguard &quot;, to act as an auxiliary police force in times of  emergency, in  times ofcommunal tension in particular.  The Minister  concerned  assured the house that  the Government wanted to be guided by its vote,  and that  such a force would be  under the  control of the authorities just as the regular police were.     The Bengal  Government have  a draft Bill ready (though  no  decision hasbeen  made whether to proceed with it) which prohibits the wearing of uniform and the maintenance by private persons of associations  of a military or simi-lar character.                       (c)  Parliamentary  Secretaries.     56. It is understood that three Parliamentary Secretaries have been appoint-ed in Sind.   There are  now very few Provinces where these functionaries do not exist.                 (d) Attitude of Ministries to law and  order.     57. There is nothing fresh to be said about the attitude of the non-congress ministries to law and order.  In the Punjab the (trial of the thirty-three Congress-men  involved in the Fatehwal riot case (described in paragraph 74 of SurveyNo. 3) lias ended in the conviction of 7 men and acquittal of 26 ; one was sentencedLS2,SGG(P)
to transportation for life for murder and other offences and the others receivedvarying sentences of imprisonment.  The enforcement by the Bengal Governmentof a section of the Criminal Law Amendment Act to deal with agrarian agitationseems to have aroused little criticism-(see paragraph 69).    The attitude of the  Congress Ministries has stiffened in  face of continualand  widespread communal  disturbances.   Sections of  the criminal law whichused to be dubbed &quot; repressive &quot; are now employed as a matter of course, inorder to prevent as well  as  to  quell  disturbances.  The  Press  (emergency powers) Act has been found useful by several Congress Ministries.  The imposition-tion  of punitive police as a penalty for communal rioting is an innovation which shows the degree of anxiety felt by the Governments of some Provinces.    58. In Assam the Premier&apos;s  attitude with,regard to measures necessary to check labour trouble at Digboi and elsewhere has on the whole been reasonable,though he is influenced by the fear of jeopardising his  small majority in theLegislature.  The aberrations of the Finance Minister in the handling of theDigboi  strike, which are mentioned in paragraph 79, have aroused strong com-ment in a section of the press.     59. In Bihar the labour situation has  been quieter ;  but communal tensionhas been acute and agrarian unrest continues to be a source of  danger.  The Billto repeal the Bihar Public Safety Act (see/paragraph 47 of Survey No. 6) waspassed in January.     60. Bamban has been free of  serious disturbances.   The1 action taken in sup-pressing the industrial disturbances last November was vindicated by the reportof the enquiry committee.   The Home Minister has  shown his usual determina-tion in matters of law and order, using the Press  (Emergency Powers) Actagainst several  communal offenders, and. sanctioning a prosecution under sec-tion 153-A., 1, P. C. in an agrarian case.     61. In the Central Provinces agrarian unrest though not acute is threaten-ing  ; and communal disturbances have been  serious.   This Government is thefirst Congress  Ministry  to impose punitive  police  (see paragraph  90).  ThePress Act has  also been used against communal offenders.     62. The Madras Government have not succeeded  in suppressing the- anti-Hindi  agitation, which continued quietly throughout  the quarter.   Convictions have risen to more than 900.  Labour disturbances have been causing  trouble.     63. In the North-West Frontier Province two newspapers  which published inflammatory accounts of the communal riots in Dera Ismail Khan were ordered to cease publication ;  section 144 of the Criminal Procedure  Code was used to enforce &quot;this order, and  the editors were prosecuted under section 153-A,  Indian Penal  Code.  In the Assembly &apos;a motion to introduce a private Bill to  repeal the Press  (Emergency Powers) Act was rejected ; the Premier, opposing it, criticised the press for abusing its liberty.   The Ministry have been much perturbed by the gravity of the problem of frontier raids ; and their methods of dealing with them have been freely criticised.  The Finance Minister has suggested the imposition of  collective fines on villages which have failed to oppose raiders or to give informa- tion about g&apos;angs, and has confessed  (though not publicly) that his experience of  responsibility has led him to abandon his previous  criticism of the Frontier .Crimes Regulation.  In April the Government decided  to increase the regular  armed reserve  of  police in the  Bannu and Dera Ismail Khan districts, and to  enlist 500 special police, in order to deal more effectively with raids.     64. The United Provinces Government reached an amicable settlement with  the Aligarh University  authorities  concerning the incident  described in  para-  graph 51 of Survey No.  6.  The University  contributed towards the loss sus-  tained by the police, and undertook to take steps to  maintain  discipline.  Labour  and the peasantry are,  temporarily at any rate, quiescent, but  the Province has  been the scene of widespread and serious communal unrest.  The  Government&apos;s  policy in this connection is described in paragraph 93.  Here  also punitive police  have been imposed.      65. Tismission of sentences. No further cases of importance have come to  light.  The Madras Ministry show increasing readiness to interfere  with police-  prosecutions in cases where i Congress followers are involved.                    (e) &quot; Political &quot; prisoners and detenus..      66. Bengal. On the recommendation of  the advisory committee (see para-  graph 59 of the last Survey) and with the  Governor &apos;s concurrence a large number  of terrorist prisoners have been released.  Only about 120 remain in jail.  The  committee appears to be examining cases with some care, interviewing prisoners
and ascertaining their attitude before making recommendations.  Some of therecommendaiions for the release  of persons  convicted of heinous crimes havebeen rather unwelcome : but acceptance of them has been considered preferable to a course which would have given the political opponents of the Ministry mate-rial for agitation liable to worsen  the security position.  As it is, such agitationis ineffective : and  it seems that Gandhi has been too much preoccupied to pay any attention to this problem in spite of his veiled threat  of, action after April13th (see paragraph 63 of Survey No. 5).  He did not visit the prisoners during his stay in Calcutta for the All-India Congress Committee session.   The sessionat the end of April  passed a resolution which referred to Gandhi&apos;s time-limit forhecuring the release of the prisoners and expressed the opinion that in view ofthe &quot; stiff and callous  attitude &quot;  of the Bengal Ministry, the  release of  long-term prisoners has  become an almost hopeless question : the release of political prisoners in Bengal and the Punjab would be made an all-India issue and theWorking  Committee would devise ways and means for starting a movement allover India for the release of these prisoners (for full text see Appendix I).  Inspite of these brave words the Congressmen assembled in Calcutta appeared toshow little interest in this matter : and in fact a good deal of feeling was arousedagainst the prisoners who had been released  as these were largely responsiblefor the violent scenes in and around the place of meeting.     The activities of released terrorists and detenus are surveyed in paragraph85.     67. Punjab. The  latest information regarding terrorist prisoners in the punjab comes from a statement made  in the Assembly late in March, to theeffect that there were then  only 11 Punjabi prisoners in jail in the Province  ;4 non-Punjabis had been convicted by Punjab courts, but of these only one was confined in  the Province ; one Punjabi convicted elsewhere was confined in the punjab.     Gandhi has again asked the Viceroy whether it would be possible to releasePrithvi Singh (whose previous history will be found in paragraph 79 of SurveyNo. 4).   Gandhi is prepared to make himself personally responsible for his good conduct and hinted  that Prithvi Singh&apos;s assistance, would help  him to consolidate the right-wing forces.  Prithvi Singh &apos;s demeanour since his arrival in a Punjabjail is said to have been exemplary ; but faith in the conversion of so resolute aterrorist is  not assisted by  an autobiography &quot;which he wrote recently while injail in Bombay.  In this boasting  of his own courage, ingenuity and tenacity of purpose  is mingled with violent abuse of the activities of Government police and jails with which he has been in conflict.  The Governor and the Premieragree that,  for the  present  at any rate, Prithvi Singh should not be released,though his case might be reconsidered later.     68.  Delhi. On  February 20th the three State prisoners (see paragraph 61of the last Survey)  started a hunger-strike as a protest against their continued detention, though the Central Government had warned them that resort to suchtactics would make it impossible  for their  cases to be considered.   On March15th Gandhi persuaded the  prisoners to  break their fast ; he interviewed thempersonally and satisfied  Government that they &quot; have no belief  in violence as a method of achieving political ends and have no intention, if released, of joiningany organisation whose activity is violent.&quot;  In view7 of this assurance Govern-inent released the prisoners on March 19th.                       (f)  The agrarian situation.    69. Agitation in the quarter, though vigorous in some areas, has been lessextensive than in the previous quarter.  There are a few  agitators,  such  asSwami Sahajanand, who have more than a local influence : but on the vdiole the&quot; kisan &quot; movement in British India still lacks both effective leadership andcoherent organisation.    In February a movement for the non-payment of the Damodar canal duesin the Burdwan district in Bengal is alleged to have been started at the instanceof Congress ;  agitators obstructed  officers in the performance of  their dirtiesand attempted to prevent the sales of attached property.  The Government re-garded  the situation as serious enough! to warrnat  the use of a section of the criminal Law Amendment Act designed to deal with picketing and boycotting.The effect was salutary ; by the middle of March more than half the  dues were collected.  The agrarian situation in the Province generally is not  satisfactory,and the  zamindars  cannot be absolved from some of the responsibility ; their
unsympathetic attitude to their tenants is not calculated to improve relations;.Moreover, though discontent is fostered by Congress agitation against the Minis-try, the parties which support the Ministry have themselves  aroused expeota-tions which it is difficult to satisfy : and no political section dares to risk alicn-ating the agriculturist vote.    Bihar  continues to be one of the most disturbed areas in  India.  One ofmore serious disputes was settled in March, but other disputes are numerous ;there has been further forcible crop-cutting ; kisan leaders put every possibleobstruction in the way of arbitration in disputes ; in some areas crops have beenharvested under police supervision, but this requires the  quartering of forces of armed police. Kisan agitation is increasing and rent-collection in many districts;has been reported to have come practically to a standstill.    A Bill is under  preparation which will provide an alternative procedure for dealing with land disputes to that contained in the Criminal Procedure Code.     Subhas Bose&apos;s election as Congress President was hailed by  kisans as a left-wing triumph and gave impetus to the movement.   Swami Sahajanan*d has been extremely  critical of Gandhi and his following.  He stood down for the Presi-dency of the All-India Kisan Conference held at Gaya in April, in  favour  ofAcharya Narendra Deo.  The  main feature of the conference was the obviouscleavage between the two groups headed by  the  above-named  two leaders ;Narendra Deo wished to keep the Jcisan sabha within the Congress fold,  while Sahajanand favoured a break with Congress  and  direct appeal to  the masses, intensified agitation and revolt against Congress Ministries.  The views of themore  moderate section  prevailed.  Resolutions insisted  upon uncompromising- opposition to Federation, immediate implementing by Provincial Governments of kisan demands, help to agitation in the States, organisation  of kisan volunteer corps, and the abolition of the zamindari  system.     Land  revenue in Bombay has been coming in rather slowly.  There was a strike of  agricultural  labourers in one district.   The  Government sanctioned the prosecution  of a member of the Independent Labour party under  section 153-A, I. P. C, for  delivering a speech calculated to excite  feelings of enmity between landlords and tenants.     In the Central Provinces there was a lull in the agitation for revenue con- cessions after the Government announced  its decisions.  The  situation  has been fairly quiet ; but much no-rent propaganda has been going on ; rent and revenue collections have been very poor in some districts but satisfactory in others.     In the west-coast districts of Madras  the agitation against the payment of rent has  declined.   Elsewhere  in permanently-settled  areas there has  been sporadic propaganda.     In the Punjab, an  aspirant to the leadership of the  Congress  Socialists Started a demonstration in Lahore against increased land revenue assessment. The Congress Assembly party assisted the demonstrations,  while non-ag-ricul- Agriculturists also found them a useful stick with which to beat the Ministry.  Towards the end of March kisans started civil disobedience in Lahore, and large num- bers  were arrested.   The agitation continued in April.      The strain on the financial resources of the Province caused by the famine has been  mentioned in para. 35.      The Sind Government had to allow 50 per cent, remission in land revenue in the areas affected by the frost.      The situation in the United Provinces has been fairly quiet.  The Tenancy Bill is still under discussion in the Legislature, and the lull in the countryside may be regarded as an armistice pending the enactment of  the Bill.  Revenue  collections  are satisfactory.      An All-India Landholders&apos; Conference was held in Lucknow in April ; a  new body was formed, to be known as the All-India Landholders&apos; Federation,  and  a resolution, which was passed after a heated debate,  recommended  the  formation of a committee with authority to negotiate  on behalf of this body  with Congress and Provincial Governments for  an  understanding  regarding  problems affecting the welfare of landlords and  tenants. Previous experience  does not  justify sanguine hopes of effective and concerted action by an organisa-  tion of this sort.      70.  Agrarian Legislation. Assam. An Agricultural Income-Tax Bill was  passed by the Assembly early in April.  It contains no provisions for reciprocal  relief in  the case of double taxation between Assam and the  United Kingdom.       7.1. Bombay.-c-The Tenancy Bill was referred to Select Committee early in  February, whence it had not emerged by the end of  the session.  The  Small  Holders Relief Act of 1938 has been extended up to the end of March 1940.  A  Bill to relieve agriculturists from debt has been introduced.
                                                                          9 o                                                                         6 6    72.  Central Provinces. A Bill lias been passed to provide for the relief ofagricultural indebtedness.    73.  Madras. The  &quot; Prakasam &quot; report on tenancy   conditions  in  per-manently settled estates (see para. 67 of the last survey) has been endorsed notonly in the Assembly but also (early in February) in the Council.  It is now theduty of the Ministry to carry out the terms of the resolutions recommending that immediate  steps  be  taken to implement  the committee&apos;s proposals  by legislation.  The Premier did not refrain  from strong support of the proposals in both Chambers.  This  attitude, in view of what was known as  to his realviews, must be explained by policy and policy of a somewhat tortuous kind.    If the Bill under preparation proves to be as drastic in its terms as the pro-posals of the committee, its enactment in that form is not likely to be allowed.    74.  Norih-West  Frontier  Province. An Agricultural  Produce  MarketsBill, which did not find favour among all members of  the Congress party in theAssembly, was passed  in April.   The Agriculturist Debtors&apos; Relief  Bill  wasreserved for the consideration of the Governor-General and received his  assent.    75.  Orissa. There is still some hope of a compromise regarding the MadrasEstates Land (Orissa Amendment) Bill, which was reserved forfhe  considera-tion of the Governor-General nearly a year ago.   The Governor discussed  thematter with Rajendra Prasad, the Ministry and representatives of the zamindars,early in February.   The Ministry is now in consultation with the ProvincialCongress Committee.    76.  United  Provinces. The Assembly passed the third  reading  of  the tenancy Bill on April 24th, after debate which exceeded all  expectations  in length.  The Bill will  shortly go before the Council.  An Agricultural ProduceMarkets Bill, a Bill regarding  consolidation of holdings, and a Bill to give agri-culturists and workmen further relief from debt by reducing the rate of interest on loans, were introduced in the Assembly during April.    77. The process of legislation intended to benefit agriculturists by a can-cancellation of debts and  restrictions on both landholders and money-lenders had begun before the introduction of the new  constitution.  Since that date  it  has gone fast and far in a number of Provinces.  It is too early  to  estimate  thebalance of its various  effects : but of these one  is becoming clear, namely,  thedrying-up of agricultural credit.  So far  as  this  diminishes  borrowing  forunproductive and wasteful purposes, it was no doubt foreseen and is no doubtbeneficial : but the agriculturist is now finding capital extremely shy of assistingeven necessary  and   productive  purposes.  Co-operative  and  governmentalsources can provide only a negligible fraction of the means which were formerlyprovided by the much-abused money-lender.                              (g) Communism.    78. The general policjr of  Indian Communists remains much the same : itis to proceed with the  revolutionary programme by capturing first the CongressSocialist party  and ultimately the whole  Congress organisation ; at the sametime they must  disarm all existing prejudices against the Communist party, bydeclaring a programme which  superficially is identical   with  that   of   theCongress, while &quot;reactionary &quot; tendencies are steadily opposed.  The  restive-ness of the Congress  rank  and file  will then be exploited  against conservativeleaders.  Left Aving agitation  everyAvhere  has a Communistic tendency, andIcisan  sablias, youth leagues  and the  Socialist movement generally, must  beregarded as assisting  the Communist revolutionary programme.  The result ofthe plan to conceal an extremist policy under a cloak&apos; of legitimate agitation isthat unity with the Congress  Socialists  and avoidance  of a breach Avith theCongress party become important  items in the  Communist  programme.  In-sincerity  and opportunism  thus characterise Communist activities.     There is howeA^er still  a breach in the left-Aving ranks.  A &quot; leftist &quot; con-ference held in Calcutta in  February failed to close it : and the Tripuri sessionAvidencd it, since the Communists threAv their weight on the side of Subhas Bose,while the Congress Socialists remained neutral,  being unwilliiig to commit them-selves.  The left-wing parties  remain as  usual  distrustful of one another.     Since the Tripuri  session Communists have found themselves in an awkwardposition ;  distrustful  of Bose&apos;s capacities, they have been afraid to come outopenly  in his favour unless he  surrendered to  Gandhi.  An  open breach,  withthemselves  on the wrong side,  Avould not suit  their  policy, AAliich is still to remainnominally under the cover  of Congress.  Bose, fighting only  to retain his posi-tion, gave them no firm lead, although he Avas associated with their programme ;LS2SGG(P)
        and  Communists and  Congress Socialists gradually veered   round  against        him.                   .            .   .            The Congress Socialist party has  on the whole had little success since its        inception.   Jawaharlal Nehru might have been expected to join it, but has not        done so.  Provincial bodies nominally acknowledge the authority of the central        committee  but in practice act  independently.  The line taken at the Tripuri        session on  Pandit Panfs resolution displeased some members of the party and        a number have resigned.                                         ,            Indian Communists have  recently been receiving rather  more  financial        assistance from  abroad, through an Indian students&apos;  group in England acting        under the  directions of British Communists.  Communist propaganda in  India        has developed considerably  during the past  year and  there  can be no doubt        that industrial   and  peasant  unrest is partly, at any rate, attributable to its        effect.  Communists have  recently  turned their attention also to the  struggle        in the States, and direct support for this  agitation figures prominently in the        anti-Federation left bloc programme.  According to a resolution passed by the        executive of the Congress Socialist party in February, the Federal scheme  could        be &quot; resisted successfully only by  developing the States&apos;  people&apos;s   struggle-        simultaneously with the struggle for freedom in British India  &quot;.  Other resolu-        fions passed  at the same time  reflect clearly the ideas which have been  men-        tioned above cautious criticism of Congress right-wing inactivity, and appre-        hension of a split between the two wings of Congress.            The Congress continues to  view Communists with suspicion.  The  Bombay        Government  (who suffered at  their hands in the November  industrial   dis-        turbances)  announced  in the Legislature that they had no intention of asking        the Central Government to remove the ban  on  the   Communist party of        India.                                 (h)  The Labour situation.            79. Assam. There have been  serious  developments in this Province.   The        Government&apos;s resolution on the Digboi Labour Enquiry  Committee&apos;s  report        A\Tas issued in February ; it endorsed all the unanimous recommendations and        invited the favourable consideration of  the Assam  Oil Company to various        recommendations made by  one or more members.  The Company  accepted        most of them. At the beginning of April a strike at the Oil Company&apos;s refinery        began at Digboi  involving nearly 10,000 persons.  The pretext of the strike Avas        tho dismissal of some  temporary employees  of  the  Company Avithout notice        being given to the Labour Union ; the CompanA^ was willing to make amends for        this lapse from  agreed procedure, but the Union demanded the re-employment        of all the men Avho  had been discharged since the agitation began about a year        ago.  There are  indications that the strike Avas organised by  agitators as part        of a general movement which Avas  to inA^olve many tea gardens as Avell as the        railway and  certain coal  fields.  The strike Avas  marked by  anti-European        feeling,  intimidation by numbers  of volunteers,  and a  boycott  by  domesticQ       servants and  bazar vendors of the households of both  the European and Indian        staff.  A number of European  and Indian ladies and children Avere compelled        to leave Digboi.   Ten platoons of Assam Rifles Avere  requisitioned for  protec-        tive purposes. An order Avas promulgated forbidding the carrying of Aveapons :        this Avas necessitated by picketers going armed Avith lathis.   On April 19th a        small body of Assam Rifles had to open fire Avhen they Avere surrounded and stoned        by a mob ; three persons &quot;Avere killed in the firing.  There has also been   much        unrest in certain tea gardens Avhere there have been demonstrations of  a highly        inflammable character against the  European staff.            The Finance Minister, Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed (Congress), Avas deputed by         the Premier to visit Digboi in the middle of April ; he has shown a strong bias        against  the company under the influence  of  labour  leaders and  Congress        M. L. As. Avho have been inciting the strikers.  On April 24th he urged that prohibition-        bitory orders should be issued to prevent the Company from bringing in outside         labour ; the Premier supported this proposal, but agreed also,that meetings and         assemblies should be prohibited as Avell as picketing and. activities of Red Shirt         A&apos;olunteers as such.  The Finance  Minister interpreted  these  orders in his own         sense and instructed the Deputy Commissioner to request the Company to refrain         from recruiting outside labour, Avithout conveying a corresponding request to         the strikers to refrain from meetings.   In the absence of explicit orders from the         Minister,  these  instructions Avere interpreted  as being  applicable to  bungaloAV         servants also ; and considerable publicity Avas given in the Press  to the unfortunate-
 nafce terms in which the supposed decisions of the Government were communicated to the officers  responsible for carrying them out.  Telegrams of protest  were sent to the Governor and Finance Minister, and the latter agreed to  eliminate the application of the orders to private servants and agreed  also to the convey- ance of a request to the strikers as well as to the Company. At the end of April the situation was quiet, though no settlement  appeared to be   in  sight.  The Company &apos;s terms have been made known to the Union, but the will to compromise is not yet present.  The Digboi oil fields supply a quantity of  the oil required for military purposes and any dislocation of work is liable to have serious conse- quences, especially in the event of war. The Company has taken steps to  safe- guard its stock of petrol and oil by importations from Burma.   The encourage- ment given by Congress M. Li. As. to the labour agitation is stated to be  largely attributable to the attitude adopted by the European group  in  the  legislature when the present Ministry came into office see para. 25 of Survey No. 5.  The police in  Assam are hampered by the absence of intelligence staff ; it  will  be remembered that in 1937 the Assembly carried a cut motion in the budget for the Criminal  Investigation Department with the result that about two-thirds of the total intelligence staff had to  be abolished.     80. Bengal. The strikes at the Indian Standard Wagon Company&apos;s works at Asansol, and at the Bengal Paper Mills at Raniganj, came to an end during the second half of  February.  The Bengal Jute Ordinance (see para. 74 of the last Survey) was withdrawn in February.     81. Bihar..-The industrial  situation  has been quiet,  but an undercurrent of  unrest continues.  Abdul Bari, whose activities were noticed in para. 99 of Survey No. 4, has again been active, devoting his attention to the Tata Iron and Steel Company.     82. Bombay. The committee appointed by the Government to enquire into the labour disturbances of November 7th last, submitted its report on February 3rd.  It found  that the firing by the police was entirely in  self-defence and that the ultimate responsibility for the disturbances must rest on the agitators who incited the  illiterate workers to violence.     83. Central. Provinces. A  brief strike involving some  9,000 men  at the Empress  Mills in Nagpur in  March concluded after 5,000 strikers marched in procession to die Assembly hall and obtained sympathetic assurances  from the Premier.     84. Madras. There has been a good deal of trouble  in this Province.  A serious fire on the  premises of the Western India Match Company at Tiruvot- tiyur (near Madras) on February 8th, which caused more than a lakh&apos;s worth of damage,  is believed to have been caused by  arson ; the management and the workers had not been on good terms for some time, and during the fire workers were seen trying  to hamper  extinguishing operations ;  they  also, assaulted the watchman and  tried to loot the quarters of  Europeans.     On February 9th  800 temporary workers  at the Choolai Mills  (Madras) w,ent on strike, but returned  to work on the 11th. after the Labour  Minister had intervened.  Socialist propaganda  is said  to have  been  at  the root of the trouble.   On the 23rd.  the strike was revived and the  permanent  workers joined in ;  strikers attempted to stop essential services  and a number;  were arrested.  The strike was continuing at the .end of April ; as a result of these unsettled  conditions the mills are to close  down.     On February 14th  2,000  men started  a  stay-in strike  in  the Chittivalsa Jute Mills  (Vizagapatam district) on account of the  dismissal of a worker. The District Magistrate  decided that it  was  essential  to clear the premises, and when the  strikers  resisted  he ordered the police to load but not to fire. This order was misunderstood in the confusion prevailing, and  four constables opened  fire  ; the strikers wavered, and the mill was cleared  by  a lathi charge. One man  died  from injuries  received in the firing  and others were injured. It is almost certain that the  mill could not have been  cleared  without firing, and it  is  generally agreed that it had to be cleared.  A committee consisting of the first member of the Board of Revenue, the Commissioner  of Labour, and the Inspector-General  of Police, reported  on the^ incident.     The consideration of this report  led to a difference  of opinion  betweenthe Premier and the Governor.  The Premier, while agreeing that the  mill had to be cleared and that the order to load  was correct, held that the  District Magistrate should b,e censured  and immediately transferred from the district as being responsible for the error which resulted in firing without warning.  An opportunity has arisen to transfer the officer to an important district Avithoutany indication of disfavour ; as  regards the proposal to direct his censure, the
Premier has now agreed that the officer&apos;s explanation should be obtained and referred to  the Federal Public,  Service Commission for advice.    The Chittivalsa Mill is likely to close  down permanently.  The MadrasPublishing House has  closed indefinitely, following  a  strike which  began onFebruary 23rd.  The Press was picketted and loyal workers were molested andobstructed : Socialists tried to work up feeling against the police.    A strike began at the Meenakshi Mills at Madura on  March 10th.  the mill was  kept working with. &quot; blackleg&quot; labour  supplied by  Congress social-lists.  The dispute was referred to arbitration.    During a strike at Cocanada an order was issued prohibiting the manage-ment of a company from engaging  outside labour, in view of  the danger of  aclash between strikers  and new workers.  This dispute also has been referredto arbitration.                               (i)  Terrorism.     S5. The picture of the revolutionary organisation  in Bengal has  become somewhat clearer.   Terrorist groups are  known to be trying  to  collect  sueli&apos;fire-arms as were  formerly in  the  possession of terrorists and can still  befound.    The impatience   of some   members of the  revolutionary  groupscauses  anxiety  to  Communists,   who  want   to   time  to  mature  their plans  for  establishing  revolutionary  forces on a  broad basis, and are ner-vous,  at the possibility of premature action by hot-heads of the old gangs.M. N. Roy is increasing his influence as  a practical revolutionary.  The HomeMinister, during discussions on the  Police budget in the Assembly, uttered animpressive warning.against the subversive activities of released detenus, morethan 3,000 of whom had been set free.  He said that the secret societies to whichthey belonged are as well organised  as ever, and that their aim is social revolu-tion.     In February an attempt was made to derail an East Indian Railway training the United Provinces near the Bihar  border ,- there are indications that this may have been the  work of a revolutionary gang with its headquarters in Bihar.Another  attempt at train-wrecking  was  detected  in April on the same  railwaynear the  Bihar border some 150 miles from Calcutta ; fish-plates had been re-moved and bolts loosened.  In the Punjab also  there have been attempts  at sabotage on the  railway.     Terrorists are not failing  to take advantage of the greater freedom now allowed to the Press in some Provinces.  In Bengal a terrorist group controls the  Ananda Bazar Press  in Calcutta, which produces  two papers  containing much that helps to  widen the field in which terrorism can flourish ; some .ex-State prisoners have recently revived Forivard, and two other  papers are edited by ex-detenus.  In the Punjab the managing editor of the Milan is  an ex-State prisoner  and a terrorist,  and the son of the. proprietor of  the Partap, who is now on the staff, once occupied  a &quot; condemned &quot; cell.  In the United Provinces, ex-terroilst convicts are concerned with the production of two papers.  Cruder terrorist jiropaganda still  appears in the form of leaflets, such as those  describ- cd in paragraph 81 of Survey No. 5.                            (j)  Communal troubles.     86. Ther,e has  been a marked deterioration in communal relations, affecting almost the  whole of the north  and  centre of India.  Increasing aggressiveness on the part of both Hindus and  Muslims has in many places created^  such  an inflammable situation that  only a spark  is needed to  cause a conflagration ; and three important religious  festivals  during  the quarter were the occasion for serious clashes, though there have  also  been  riots unconnected with any festi- vals.     It is particularly in  some of  the Congress Provinces that bitterness  is growing  : and, since the circumstances  of the new constitution are  themselves regarded as a cause, the remedy is hard to find.   It is difficult  to exaggerate the strain and responsibility  imposed on magistracy and police by the  conditions now prevailing in  several  Provinces.     87. Bengal-rThis Province  has not suffered severely.  The  celebration. almost simultaneous,  of the Muslim festival of Moharram and the Hindu festi- yal of Holi at the beginning of March led to  encounters,  especially, in the jute- mill area, in which at least one man was killed and a number injured.
    88.  Bihar.-During the Muslim festival of Bakr-Id at the beginning  ofFebruary, the police had to open fire on a huge mob which attempted to raid a -village in Darbhanga district in order to prevent slaughter of cows.   Two menwere killed and four were injured as a result of the firing.   The Premier madea strong speech in the Assembly in justification of the firing.  During Holi,in the first week of March, riots in Hazaribagh were responsible for 60 injuriesand one death ; and in Muzaffarpur 50 houses were burnt down and one manwas killed.  At  the end of March  there were  more riots in Hazaribagh  andGaya districts.    In April the general feeling of apprehension remained ; on April  2nd Mus-lirns attacked Hindus  in Eanclii  district in the presence of police officers and about 20 injuries were caused.  There  have been other riots,  and trouble hasbeen averted with difficulty in many places.    89.  Bombay, There have  been no serious  communal  disturbances.   TheHome Minister was criticised for ordering  security to  be demanded under thePress (Emergency Powers) Act from two Hindu and two Muslim newspapersfor publishing articles fending to embitter communal relations. Unaffected bycriticism, he instituted a prosecution under  the sam,e Act against a person whocirculated a-news-sheet inciting Hindus against Muslims.    Sholapur is being used as a centre for the concentration of volunteers chieflyArya Samaj and Hindu Mahasabha who proceed to Hyderabad State to carryon agitation against the State Administration.   The meeting of the Bombay Pro-vincial  Muslim League at  Sholapur early in May, over which  the Punjab Pre-mior will preside,  has dangerous possibilities  of  communal trouble ; it appearsthat Sholapur has been deliberately selected in order that the meeting may act,as a counter-blast to the Hindu agitation  (see also paragraph  97).    90. Central Provinces. The  situation  has  much  deteriorated.    during and after Moharram and Holi a series of riots occurred, and only excellent work by district officers  prevented worse disorder.   On March 6th,  98 persons wereinjured, of whom two died, in a fight between Hindus  and Muslims at Jubbul-pore ;  British  troops marched through the city.  Both Muslims and Hindushave become increasingly  aggressive.  The  flag incident at Jubbulpore is men-.tioned in paragraph 109.  It would be  trivial were it not for the bitterness ofcommunal feeling.   On March  17th  at Biswa, in Berar, a prominent Congress-man was murdered in broad daylight by a mob of Muslims ; the incident caused a great sensation and was the subject of an adjournment motion in the Assembly.The Government issued orders posting a force of punitive police (consisting ofone head constable and 8 constables) in the town for a period of  one year, thecost to  be borne by the local Muslims.  The communal tension in the Provincemay be partly attributed to the agitation carried on against the Nizam of Hyder-abad.   The Ministry do not always escape the appearance  of bias in communaldisputes, and the Premier himself is not free  from such bias.  In the Biswa&apos;case above-mentioned, the  Muslim mob was estimated from the beginning  tonumber about 70 ;  the Premier, after visiting the spot,  got the (Muslim) PoliceSub-Inspector transferred, and no fewer than 156 Muslims were arrested,  onsuspicion of being implicated  in  the  murder substantially  the whole maleMuslim population of the  town.  When the I). I. G. of Police  had investigatedthe case, only 45  persons were actually prosecuted.    91. North-Wesi Frontier Province. On February  2nd, during th,e  Bakr-Idcelebrations the vexed question of  cow-slaughter was the immediate cause of aserious Hindu-Muslim riot at  Dera Ismail  Khan.  Eleven persons were killed and 25  injured.  Hindus are said to have been more provocative than Muslimson this occasion.   Communal relations are  deteriorating in the Province.    92. Punjab. The passage  of  a  Moharram  procession through  a  Hinduquarter in Amritsar gave rise to a  riot  on March 2nd, in which two  persons were killed and 18 injured.  British troops were posted in the city.  About 70Sunnis were injured in disturbances at Kasur the same day, when Sunnis offeredcivil disobedience against the  authorities for permitting a particular  form ofShia procession.  The police had to make a charge on the crowd.     93.  United  Provinces. Communal feeling  has  reached a state  unparalel-led  in .modern times, and there has been frequent  and  widespread  rioting.On February 11th  a disturbance broke  out, in Cawnpore ; it is  believed that the trouble started  through Muslims objecting  to a  Hindu marriage party playingmusic outside a mosque.   During the next few days more than 40 persons were killed  and nearly  250 injured in the  riots.  The police had to  open fire several times ; British troops were called in.  The  city was in  a panic for days on end,hundreds of arrests were made, and.numerous prohibitory orders issued.  At thobeginning of March trouble began again ; stray assaults accounted for  7 deathsLS2SGG(P)
and several injuries.  At the same time a Hindu-Muslim riot beg-an in Benares,which was  eventually responsible for about 40 persons being killed and 200 in- ;injured.  Here again panic spread, arson  and looting and  stray  assaults tookplace, and  British troops had  to be  summoned.  Their  presence was invalu-able : without, them it would have  been difficult to  bring-  the  situation under control.  The police resorted to  firing 37 times during the three dayls  of therioting ;  6 persons were killed,  4 more succumbed to injuries  received,  and15 were  wounded,  in  the firing.  At the end of March more stray  assaultsaccounted for a few more deaths in  Benares, and the trouble also spread toAllahabad, where 8 persons were killed and  a number injured  in rioting.    To  add to the Governments difficulties the  Madhe Sahaba dispute hasboiled up again in Lucknow.  (This obscure  quarrel between two Muslim seelshas been described in  paragraph 103 of Survey No. 3).   Sunnis recommencedthe agitation  about the beginning of  March  and started civil disobedience.Their agitation was encouraged  by the knowledge that the Ministers were in.favour of some  concession ; both the  Muslim Ministers are Sunnis.  Arrestswere made almost daily until the end of March when about 2,500 Sunnis hadbeen arrested.  The Government then decided to allow  the Sunnis  an oppor-tunity to recite the offending verses on one  day in the  year only ; the inten-.tion was to prescribe  a route for the procession  far removed from any Shiaarea.  On  March  30th the  Government announced this  decision  ;  the  daychosen for  the procession and recitation is the Barawafat Day which will occurearly in May.  On March 31st  the police had to open fire during an encounterbetween  the two factions.   Shortly afterwards  the  Sunnis abandoned  civildisobedience, and  the  prisoners  were  released.  It was  known that the Gov-governments  decision would be resented by the Shias, but the violence  of their objection to it  came as a surprise.  A civil disobedience  movement began atonce, in which Shias of the most respectable families  and standing have beenreciting tabarra and going  to  jail.  Hundreds  havt; been arrested and thereis danger of serious disorder  on the  Barawafat  Day.    There  is reason to believe that the trouble, at first at any rate, was en-couraged by Congress in order  to  split the  Muslims ; Congress Muslims are mainly Sunnis.   But the effect of the orders now passed has been to  swing overShia opinion strongly against.  Congress.  At the  same time the  Sunnis, otherthan the Congress Sunnis, aie not likely to be grateful to Congress ; and thereare traces of a feeling that the matter has gone too. far and that something shouldbe done by the Sunnis to waives their rights in view of the strength of opinionshown by the Shias.    On  April 24th  there was a demonstration outside the Assembly Chamberin Lucknow held in protest against  the  recitation  of tabarra by Shias.  Anunruly crowd of about 50 Sunnis  invaded the  Chamber and held up proceedings for some time ; they appear to have forced their way through  the police.  ThePremier induced them to disperse..  The incident caused great alarm and indig-hation among members of- the  Assembly.  On April 26th  a Government com-munique stated  that  a force of  punitive police consisting  of  200 officers andmen is to be imposed in Lucknow for one year, the cost of wdiich will  be borneby the Shia and Sunni residents of the city.   Numerous arrests  were  made inconnection with the demonstration ; and the  sub-inspector of police,  a  sergeantand two constables, who are alleged to have been guilty of neglect  of duty inpermitting the demonstrators to  enter the Assembly, have been suspended.  Atthe  end  of April the Nizam of Hyderabad, drawing attention  to  the MadheSahaba controversy, personally requested the Viceroy to use his influence to&quot; put things right before it is.too late    There  is no doubt of the Premier&apos;s perturbation at  the condition  of eoni-munal feeling in the Province.   At the end  of March he  announced  a &quot; new policy &quot; in the Assembly : various strong measures would be taken by  the Gov-ernment and by their officers.  In fact a committee has  been appointed  toexamine the handling of the riots and to suggest what lessons  can be draAvnfrom experience : and district magistrates  are to be given practical  instruc-tion.  But the Premier still  shows a dislike of methods which offend his doctri-naire principles,   and  a leaning towards solutions  which for  success  demand&apos;a pacific and reasonable disposition which has ceased to govern communal rela-tions  in the Province.  The latest incidents,  culminating in the invasion of theAssembly Chamber, have given rise to general impatience and anger  and out-spoken denunciation even by good Congressmen of the feebleness and uncertaintyshown by  the Premier in his  handling  of the  problem.  Towards  the  end ofApril the Premier agreed to the immediate addition to the police force of 1,000
          VI.-POLITICAL  MOVEMENTS.                          (a) The Congress Party. (Tills account has been carried on to May 2nd inclusive in order to cover the            Calcutta session of the All-India Congress Committee.)    95.  The Congress President. As was reported in the last Survey (para. 85),Subhas  Bose was re-elected President on January 29th.  On  April   29th  heresigned that office.  The history of the  intervening three  months is  one  ofconfusion and dissension in the Congress party.    It was soon apparent that Subhas Bose&apos;s election was not to be interpreted as a sweeping  triumph for the left wing.  The  growing power  of   the   left undoubtedly aided his victory, but there were many other  circumstances  thatContributed to it ; of these the chief were his superiority as a popular figure toJiis mediocre opponent (Pattabhi Sitaramayya)  : his command of the Bengalvote, which was more numerous than that of any other Province : the imputa-tion that his colleagues on the &quot;Working Committee were deceiving the party onthe Federal scheme : and a general dislike of the  overbearing  Avays  of  the dominant members of the Working Committee,  in particular  Vallabhai Patel.The threat of a division  in the ranks of Congress which Gandhi uttered imme-diately  after the election was mentioned in  the  last  Survey.  With an air  ofdeference which deceived neither Subhas Bose nor anyone else, Gandhi invited him to nominate his OAVH &quot; Cabinet &quot; and &quot;  enforce his programme without let or hindrance &quot;, Avhile Gandhi&apos;s followers, if  need he, would go forth   into  thewilderness.   Bose&apos;s reply at the beginning of February professed undiminishedrespect  for Gandhi and deprecated a split in the party.    In the middle of February Bose had discussions Avith Jawaharlal Nehru  andGandhi, but failed to upset Gandhi&apos;s determination not to help him in any wayto exploit his victory.  Soon after on February 22nd twelve members of theWorking Committee, i.e.,  all  except the Bose brothers and Jawaharlal Nehru,tendered their  resignation: in their joint letter  to  &quot;dear  Subhas&quot;   they expressed deep regret  at his illness (which Avas  later to become more serious)and their conviction that he should be left entirely free to  choose a  Cabinetrepresenting his own views. On the same day JaAvaharlal Nehru issued a state-ment which Avas at the time generally interpreted as indicating his resignationalso : he sternly rebuked Bose for the insinuations made by him against  hiscolleagues in the election campaign : expressed disagreement with Bose&apos;s views in important matters (unspecified) : and concurred with those Avho thought thathe should be free to follow his own policy and choose his own colleagues.  It isbelieved that a  couple  of days later the Premiers of at least five Congress Pro-vinces sent their resignations to Gandhi to use as he thought fit.  Bose acceptedthe resignations of the twelve members of the Working Committee on Februarv26 th.    Between this date and the opening of the Tripuri session Bose issued variousstatements in answer to the charges made against him, and in the meantime hisiliness gTPAV worse,  Gandhi chose this moment  to divert the  attention of  thecountry -to Rajkot ; through the intervention of the ViceroA7, Gandhi  broke hisfast on the very day on Avhich  the meeting of the All-India Congress committee at Tripuri began.   (For  the Rajkot events see para. 96 below.)    On  March 7th the All-India Congress Committee met at Tripuri in prepara-tion for the open session which was to begin on March 10th.   On the 8th PanditGobind  Ballabh Pant, the Premier of the  United Provinces, moved a  resolutionAvhich marked the first decisive step toAvards the deposition of the President :it declared the adherence of the Committee to the past policy of Congress prac-used under  Gandhi&apos;s guidance,  expressed confidence in the defunct.  working committee and  disapproval of the aspersions cast against its members,  and armed reservists ; the proposals of the I. G. of  Police to double the number&apos;are being examined.  The Premier further  agreed  that  in communal   casesDistrict Magistrates should be allowed to  recommend action to be taken underthe Press  (Emergenev Powers)  Act    94. Delhi. Civil disobedience on a small scale  has  continued throughoutthe quarter in connection with the &quot; temple dispute &quot;.  There have been  noovert disturbances.  An appeal  has been  filed against the judgment given infavour of the Government in the civil suit filed against the sadhu.
requested the President to nominate the  next  Working Committee  in  accord-ance with  Gandhi&apos;s wishes.   (For the full text  see Appendix I.)  Numerousamendments were moved to this resolution, but it was passed in its. original formin the Subjects Committee by  218 to 135 votes j all the amendments  werethrown out by a large majority.    On March 10th the open  session of the Congress began ; as usual elaboratearrangements had  been made for  display,  which  included  a procession of52 elephants.  Bose was too ill to preside and his address had to be read out for him.  It reiterated his opinion that the time  had come to  submit  a nationaldemand r,o the British Government in the  form of an ultimatum, to be followedafter the expiry of a time-limit by civil disobedience ; the time had come  for afinal advance in the direction of  swaraj, particularly  since the international situation was favourable to the  Congress  ; the Congress attitude towards theStates as defined by the Haripura resolution must be revised and. Congress should draw  closer to the States  peoples ; the work  of guiding popular movements insthe States should be conducted by the Working- Committee.  The address endedwith a prayer that  Gandhi should help the Congress out of the present confu-si on.    Pant &apos;s resolution came before the open session on March 11th.  A suggestionthat it should be postponed on account of Bose&apos;s illness caused a wild uproarwhich led Nehru to state that never in his connection with Congress for 25  years had he witnessed such  disgraceful scenes.  On  March 12th the resolution   waspassed in its original form without  a division. The Congress Socialist Partyearned a good deal of criticism by  adopting a neutral attitude.  Though PanditPant asked that his resolution should not be  interpreted  as  a motion of no-confidence  in the President, its condemnation of the insinuations made  againstthe Working Committee was aimed  directly  at him, and the requirement thatthe members  of the new Committee should be Gandhi&apos;s nominees reduced him toa nonentity.  The acceptance of the resolution demolished the effect of the elec-tion ;  most of the delegates whose votes had  made Subhas president  ran  away from him at Tripuri : and from this moment it Avas certain that he could not retaincommand unless he could having Gandhi&apos;s fa\rour.  There  were reasons enough forthe hostility of the right Aving : and these Avere reinforced by rumours  that Bosehad taken money from agents of Italy and Japan.  But the poor shoAving of the left Asdng at  Tripuri demonstrated once more  the hopeless  divisions in  theirranks, and their lack of leadership.    The interval between  the Tripuri session and the meeting of. the All-india congress Committee at Calcutta at the end of April Avas taken up chiefly withmeetings betAveen Gandhi and the right-Aving leaders and prolonged correspond-ence between Gandhi and Subhas Bose.  In the meantime no Working CommitteeAvas appointed.   The correspondence ended Avith a letter in Avhich Gandhi,  after3 days of discussion Avith  Subhas, finally refused to nominate the members  ofthe Working Committee.  This was  on the eve of the meeting of the All-india congress Committee in Calcutta which began  on April 29th.    On-that  day Bose  opened the proceedings by announcing his resignation.Quoting the terms of the Tripuri resolution, he said he had failed to arrive at any settlement  with the Mahatma, and therefore had not been able  to  appoint  a working Committee : his own conviction was in favour of a composite Cabinetrepresenting the various views held in the Congress, but neither Gandhi nor themembers of the defunct Working Committee Avould agree to this.  Nehru moveda resolution requesting Bose to withdraw his resignation, but at the same  timerequesting  him to re-nominate the  members of  the  old Working Committee.Bose demanded power  to  include fresh blood in the Committee ; and when it became clear that the resolution as it stood Avas not acceptable to  Bose, Nehruwithdrew it.  On the 30th Bajendra  Prasad  Avas  elected  President.   Theannouncement of his election  was followed by wild disorder  and hostile  demon-strations against Pandit Pant and other right-wing leaders, caused  no  doubtby Bose&apos;s revolutionary Bengali folloAvers.   The next day the composition of thenoAv Working Committee  Avas announced.  All the  members of the  old   Com-lnittee are included except  Nehru and the Bose brothers ; Subhas Bose and Nehruboth declined invitations to serve.  The places of the Bose brothers have  beenfilled by Bidhan Chandra Roy and Prafulla Ghose, both  of Avhom belong to  pro-Gandhi&apos; Bengali parties.  The former of these is the leader of the Congress factionin Bengal which&apos;is opposed to the faction led  by the Bose brothers^    Four resolutions Avere passed with little discussion and the session ended onMay 2nd.   The text of theni Avill be found in Appendix I.  They refer to internalreform of Congress,  Avar, Indians in Kenya, and  terrorist prisoners ; all are  nien-tioned in their appropriate places in this  Survey.
                                                                        9 o                                                                        &amp; o                                     25     Such is the story of a crisis in the Congress which may be of great importance to the political future of India. In appearance the right wing, still under  the unquestioned and resolute direction of Gandhi, has not only repaired the breach caused by the unexpected election of Subhas Bose, but has established the High Command on an even more solidly conservative base : Rajendra Prasad, the new President, is the very emblem of respectable moderation : the new Working Com- mittee is the former Committee purged of any element which might lean towards Bose and the left.   Thus on the surface the  Gandhian policy of Congress has been restored and strengthened.   But it is possible that the surface is too smooth to be safe.  Matters have again been carried  with a  high hand  : for instance,  the immediate election of a new President was opposed, with a good show of reason but without, avail, as being contrary to the constitution : resentment against the &quot; Fascism   of Gandhi and his supporters may break out later with   increased force.  (It  was significant that Gandhi required Vallabhai Patel,  the  arch &quot; Fascist &quot;, to stay away from the Calcutta session).  A group of ageing men, subservient to a leader who  is over seventy, have resumed command : younger blood is still denied its chance.   Moreover,  there is reason to believe that Gandhi himself is losing his quality : some even of his more devoted followers are said to harbour doubts about the  wisdom of his recent  performances : and there is a section of Congress which does not admit his infallibility  and is  openly impatient of his domination.  The display of indiscipline at Tripuri and Calcutta  may denote  more than the bad manners of a handful of revolutionaries.  The right wing, intolerant of compromise, may have pushed its authority  too   far  for security, and the next revolt may be more  successful.  The High Command has licAvever this much justification for continuing to monopolise control that the younger and more assertive  sections of the party have  still  not produced men worthy to challenge their elders : where the best that the left wing can put for- ward is a Subhas Bose  or an M. N. Roy, the middle-aged moderates can hardly be expected either to abdicate or to welcome their  juniors as colleagues.     96. Congress  and the States. Paragraphs 83 and 84 of the last Survey described the steps taken by Congress to promote in the States such conditions as would weaken the power of the  Rulers and strengthen political organisations; with the unacknowledged aim of enabling  Congress to secure a majority in the future Federal Assembly.  During the first half of February interest centred in Jaipur, where Jamnalal Bajaj (then a member of the Working Committee) on the first of the month carried out his threat of defying  the ban on  Ms entry.  He was arrested and removed.  He re-entered the  State a few days later and wras again removed.  (on one of these journeys out of the State.he was taken iii a motor-car through a part of the United Provinces, and the Ministry of that Province showed resentment of action which it regarded as wrongful restraint by State Police of a Congress leader in the territory of the  Province.)  On  his third entry he was placed under  restraint  in  the  State, where he  is still detained.  Civil disobe- - dience in Jaipur was launched on February 4th.     In  the  meantime Gandhi and  Vallabhai Patel continued  to denounce tho administration of certain States, political  officers  connected with them, and the Paramount  Power.  It  soon&apos; became clear  that  Rajkot in particular  was to  be the scene of a struggle.  The dispute  which.arose in that State is outside the scope of this  Survey ; but it is necessary to mention the circumstances which drew into it Gandhi and the highest authority in  India,  executive and judicial. Vallabhai Patel suddenly descended on the  State by aeroplane on Christmas Day on the invitation of the Ruler, and came  to an agreement with the Ruler on the constitution of a committee to be appointed to frame a scheme of reforms.  The agreement was embodied in a notification of the Durbar of December 26th and in a note sent by the Ruler to Patel on the same date.  The settlement soon broke down, the Ruler was accused  of  breaking his word,  civil  disobedience was resumed,  and  on  February  3rd   Gandhi&apos;s wife  and  Patel&apos;s daughter,  who entered the  State in order to  court arrest, were placed in confinement.  Writing in the Harijan on February i4th Gandhi said that it was  &quot;insufferable that the Congress, which is today in alliance Avith the British Government,  should be treated  as an enemy and an outsider in the States,  which are Arassals of the British  &quot; ; and maintained that the Congress Ministries  had the right  and duty to require, under threat of their resignation, the Paramount Power to  set thingsright in Rajkot.  On February 7th Jawaharlal  Nehru, referring to the States struggle, said that  &quot; everything else is  secondary to  this major struggle, forin its SAveep it Avill  include Federation, Provincial autonomy  and other inrpedi-ments to  our freedom &quot;.  This sudden  intensification  of  the  struggle  in theStates must be related to the  success of Subhas  Bose&apos;s reArolt  a few days before.Attention was at once diverted from his Auctory, and from the dissensions withinLS2SGG(P)
the Congress party,  to a stage where it was hoped to make a better showing.Soon there were rumours  that  the  Bombay  Government would resign,  and ministers of the Central Provinces were talking openly of leading the agitation in one of the  States.  The Madras Premier, when presenting the budget  esti-mates in the Madras Assembly  on February 20th, went far out of his way tocomplain that  the inclusion of the States in the scheme of Federation had become a cause of bitter conflicts and grave anxieties,  and  that  the  activities  of  anirresponsible Central Government made it impossible for the Provincial Govcrn-ments to function with self-respect.  Towards  the end of February a certainsection of the  subjects of Limbdi State started migrating into  Bombay Provinceto escape alleged repression.     Matters came to a head in the last  week of  February.   On the 25th Gandhiset out for Rajkot, having wired to the Darbar that the Ruler&apos;s breach of  faithcoupled  with  tales of brutality were  forcing him to intervene.  Civil disobe-diencG was suspended to  enable him  to. investigate conditions in  a peacefulatmosphere,   On his arrival in Rajkot on the 27th Gandhi was given every faci-lity to enquire into alleged atrocities.   A thorough investigation was made but no  atrocities were brought to light.  On March 2nd he delivered &apos;an ultimatum tothe Thakore ; this  demanded that the Reforms  Committee  should  contain amajority of five to four in favour of the local Congress party, that Gandhi shouldselect these five, and  that one of them shordd be the president : that the Committeeshould complete  its  work  by March 22nd,  and its recommendations  should begiven effect to within a week : and that all civil disobedience prisoners shouldbe  released at once. If these suggestions  were not accepted within 24  hoursGandhi would begin a fast.   The Ruler refused  the ultimatum, and Gandhi &apos;sfast began at midday on March 3rd.     Gandhi had taken everyone by surprise, and in many quarters this move wasgreeted  with disapproval : but soon;anxiety became general, at any rate amongHindus,  and increasingly tended to grow hysterical.  At his age and in his feeblestate of health it was supposed that Gandhi could not long survive  his deathwould have  produced results  which,  incalculable  in various  ways, would doubtless have included the resignation of,the Congress Ministries.   On March4th Gandhi had sent a message to the Viceroy asking for the immediate interven-tion of the Paramount Power &quot; to induce the fulfilment  of the promise of the Thakore Sahib &quot;.   On the 7th  the Viceroy, -with the consent of the Thakore,undertook to consult the Chief Justice of India as to the construction to be placed on the two documents above-mentioned ; the  Committee would be  set  up in accordance with the Chief  Justice&apos;s  decision,  and the same authority  would decide any difference arising between. members of the Committee as to the meaning of  any part of the notification.  Gandhi then broke his fast on the afternoon of  the  7th. The relief with which this result was received was not shared by the Muslim League,  the  Council  of which deplored both Gandhi&apos;s fast and the intervention of the  Viceroy.     For some weeks after Gandhi made New Delhi his headquarters : his resi- dence (G. D. Birla&apos;s fine house)  attracted persons  of high official position as well as the usual throngs  : and with the Legislature sitting at the same time the capital of India was  full of busy political life.  The Viceroy granted two interviews to Gandhi  in March and a third in April.      On  April 3rd the Chief  Justice gave his award.  The official view had been that the Ruler&apos;s undertaking had not been free from ambiguity : and  it  had been announced that the  Ruler could  not  be  pressed  to accept a construction which he evidently  did not intend and was not prepared to accept.  The Chief Justice  however  found that the interpretation claimed by  Gandhi and  Patel was the true one :  the Ruler had undertaken to appoint! to  the committee the persons whom Vallabhai Patel  might recommend, and had not reserved to hitn- self any discretion to reject persons whom he did not approve : he was entitled to criticise the recommendations and to urge reasons  for reconsidering them, but unless it could be shewn that any of the persons recommended are neither subjects nor servants of the State, Patel must have the  last word.  A week later Gandhi returned to Rajkot : but there  he found himself confronted with promises ho had made to certain communities that they should be represented on the  Com- mittee : it proved impossible to reconcile these promises with the assurance of a  Congress majority on  the Committee :  and Gandhi in turn was  accused of attempting a breach of  faith.   The Darbar (according to popular report per- sonified in ViraAvala, the Ruler&apos;s principal adviser) refuser! to entertain certain  alternative proposals : and when towards  the  end of April  Gandhi  left Rajkot for Calcutta he admitted defeat.  He  is believed to  be intending to,return,, and  has already held out the  threat of a fresh resort to hunger-strike.
    To turn to developments elsewhere.  In the middle of March Gandhi advised the suspension of civil disobedience in Jaipur and its postponement in Travancore.In view of &quot; inhumanities perpetrated in various States &quot; he was &quot; thinking out a new orientation of civil disobedience &quot; ; and in the  meantime be must have a peaceful atmosphere.  He  pleaded guilty to  having been hfasty  in  launchingprevious campaigns.  About  the  same time  he privately expressed the opinionthat Congress interference in States should be confined  to rare and  extraordi-.nary circumstances.  The gist of the verbose resolution passed at Tripuri (seeAppendix!) is that the policy laid down at Haripura is liable to revision in viewof the   great awakening that is taking place among the people of  the states the Working Committee was authorised from -time to  time as occasion arises to relax or remove completely the restraint which the Congress had hitherto imposedupon itself.. At the end of April, there was  a lull in the agitation  in the States,except for the Arya Samaj agitation against Hyderabad.    97.  Other events connected with Indian States which have affected british india require mention.  la the Orissa States there is little change in the  situa-tion : thousands of refugees from Talcher State are still living within the OrissaProvince.  Announcements of concessions by the Ruler  have not  hitherto pre-prevailed on them to return.  Gandhi has  recently accused  the Ruler of failing to honour an agreement said to have been made between  a Congress representative and the Assistant Political  Agent ; in reality -the A. P. Agent made it clear thathe was not in a position to come to any agreement ; but Gandhi may yet take upthe refugees&apos; cause if he finds their case strong enough.    It lias.not  been found necessary to urge the Orissa Ministry to take  anyfurther action with regard to extradition of offenders wanted by  the Rulers orthe application  of the Indian States (Protection) Act.    Three persons were wounded as a result of firing by -the Orchfa State police.According to the Provincial Congress this took place  in United Provinces terri-xory, hut this is denied by the Darbar.  An inquiry through an Impartial  policeofficer is understood to be proceeding.    In Jaipur in January a number of Muslims were killed when police fired on ariotous-mob assembled in  connection with an altercation about a. mosque. Inprotest  against the results of the enquiry made  by the Durbar three thousandMuslims made their way to Delhi.  There they have  behaved quietly and wereeasily dissuaded from attempting a march to the Viceroy&apos;s House.  The muslim league has given them scant support, but their emigration from Jaipur has been encouraged by other political parties in British India.    Hindus from several Provinces, e.g., Ajmer-Merwara, Bombay, the central provinces, Madras, the Punjab and United Provinces, have been taking part in the agitation against Hyderabad State.  The Congress is no longer associated with it,Gandhi having discountenanced it on account of its  dangerous communal com-plexion.  That  has been no deterrent to the Arya Samaj and Hindu  Mahasabhawhich employed unscrupulous propaganda against the administration of theState and have organised  a  stream of invasions to fill the Hyderabad jails inprotest against alleged oppression of Hindu subjects  of the State. Prom Octo-lier 1938 to the end of April over 3,500 arrests had. been made, the great majorityof  offenders being  subjects  of  British India.   The bordering  territories of bombay and the Central Provinces are the main avenue for these parties,  andSholapur in Bombay Province is the principal centre of the  agitation.    The C. P. Ministry have  shown no disposition to check the nuisance.  the bombay Ministry have been more accommodatllng, but their assistance stopswell short of the action which might be taken under the States (Protection) Act.     98. Congress and Federation. The resolution on the &quot; National Demand &quot;passed  at Tripuri  (see Appendix I) added little  fresh to previous  statements of congress policy regarding the Federal scheme.  It reiterated uncompromisingopposition to that scheme  and demanded nothing less than independence, to beachieved through the establishment of a democratic  State by means of  a  con-stituent assembly.  Provincial autonomy affords  no scope for adequate develop-ment and its capacity for  good is being exhausted.  The  Congress   thereforeagain calls upon all parts of the Congress organisation,  Congress  provincial governments and the people  generally, to work for the speedy realisation  of theCongress objective.  The terms  of this resolution  are mild compared with the extremist programme which Subhas Bose has preached, with Its six-months  ulti-matum to the British Government, and threat of  civil  disobedience  If the demandwere refused.     99. The Tripuri and Calcutta sessions-^he 52nd open session was held atTripuri from March 10th to 12th.  Its doings are in part treated elsewhere.  as there was no Working Committee there were no official resolutions  Jawaharlal
 Nehru, in the absence of Gandhi, dominated the proceedings and was responsible for the drafting of the principal resolutions.  Even he  could not  prevent, or easily subdue, the scenes of disorder which marked one day&apos;s proceedings, and which shamed the leaders in the presence of a delegation from the Wafd party of Egypt.  (A  resolution of  welcome  to  the  delegation  was   passed :  see Appendix I).  The main business of the All-India Congress Committee meeting at^ Calcutta at the end of April  and beginning of May has been already  des- cribed. Both at Tripuri and at Calcutta resolutions were passed on the defects and corruption  which have marred the working of the  Congress  machinery. The Calcutta resolution set up a  committee &quot; to recommend measures  for the purification of the Congress &quot;. It is known that the intention has been to apply the purge in such a manner as to  weaken the unruly left wing of Congress :. and it will be  interesting to see whether the High Command is sufficiently confident after the  Calcutta meeting to carry out this plan.     100. Attitude to Indians  Overseas. A  resolution. passed  at Tripuri  (see Appendix I) expressed the concern of the Congress at the rapidly deteriorating- position of Indians overseas, &quot; especially in countries  within * the  so-called British Commonwealth&quot;, mentioning  particularly  the danger  to  Indians in Burma, the treatment of Indians in Ceylon and Kenya, and hostility displayed towards them in South Africa.  A resolution passed by the All-India  Congress Committee at the Calcutta session (see Appendix II) specifically referred to the Kenya order-in-council regarding reservation of the Highlands for Europeans  ; and stated that as the Government of India had failed in their duty the &quot;Working- Committee should take the necessary steps on behalf of   Indians  in   Kenya. Both the^ Congress and other parties in the Central Legislature have  shown keen interest in the position of Indians overseas.     101. &quot; The  National Planning Committee   The Committee made a re- quest to the Central Government for co-operation, and received the answer that it is impossible, with the resources at  the Government&apos;s  disposal,  to examine and reply to the elaborate questionnaire (see paragraph 91 of the last Survey), but that requests for specific information would be considered.  The Secretary of the Committee has  stated that, as  some Provincial Governments have asked for further time for submitting replies to the questionnaire, the next meeting of the Committee will probably be held in May.  . A member of the Committee told the Governor  of Bombay that there is a sharp division of opinion between Nehru and himself on one side and certain capitalists : the latter demand a free hand for capitalism -which the former are not prepared to concede.     102. Congress membership, according to the Congress report for 1938-39. has risen since last year by nearly a million and a half to nearly four and a half millions.                          (b)  The Muslim  League.    103. Relations with Congress. Relations between the League and the Con- gress appear to  be such that there can  be no likelihood of an early  settlement. There  have been no further negotiations  between them.  It  has  however been confirmed  that the Aga Khan  in conversation with Gandhi and Vallabhai Patel in January discussed the possibilities of an agreement, and came away with the conviction that a settlement could be reached, provided the League did not insist on being-recognised as the sole representative body of Indian Muslims or on the Congress accepting the position of a purely Hindu body.   The Aga Khan is not a member of the League, nor is he on cordial terms with its President :  and onthis subject his wishes may not carry much weight with Indian Muslims.  Con- gress machinations in Indian States have continued to cause  alarm to  Muslims, particularly Gandhi&apos;s intervention in Rajkot, and the agitation in Hyderabad ; the resolutions on the subject which will be found in Appendix II reveal an atti- tude of suspicion alike of the Congress  and of. the Paramount Power.   Thoughthe public pronouncements of the League are pitched on a note which suggests some deliberate  exaggeration, Jinnah himself  and  a number of his followers appear to  have persuaded themselves that the British Government is no friend of the Muslim community and  is prepared to  sacrifice it in  order to make terms with Congress.   There is even a suggestion of flirtation with European countriesnot at present friendly with Britain.  The two Muslims who went  to England to watch the Palestine  conference visited Italy  but failed  to  meet the  authoritiesto whom they had introductions, and are said  to have left the country in disgust.This Avas  on the  eve of the attack on Albania : and that  event  has naturallyalienated Muslim opinion in India  from Italy.
    It  is  one of the loudest complaints of the League that in Congress Pro-vinces Muslims  are  the  victims of  maltreatment usually  referred  to  as*&apos; atrocities &quot;.  These complaints have been made to the Viceroy in person, andhave  been  reduced to writing, in a document laid before the  Viceroy  by  SirJZia-ud-din  Ahmed, M.L.A. (Central).   The allegations are in particular againstthe Ministries of Bihar, the Central and United Provinces.  A number of the mare complaints  of general maladministration : the specifically  Muslim  com-&apos;plaints are of bias against the community  in various forms,  the forcing  ofHindu culture on Muslims, expenditure of public funds on Congress propaganda,and an allegation that  communal riots are started by Hindus.  Enquiries madein these Provinces are not complete, but in the Central Provinces the  conclusion reached is that while  there are numerous pinpricks there is no evidence of seriousinjustice &quot;being done  to Muslims ; it is the galling thought that their  communal&quot;opponents  are apparently to be in perpetual political domination over them thathurts them most.  It is in fact this feeling of impotence in the political fieldthat is responsible for most of the ill-feeling.    104. TJve League and Federation.- A resolution passed by  the   &quot;working committee of the League in March (see Appendix II)  reiterated opposition tothe scheme of Federation embodied in the Constitution Act,  expressed  theopinion that  the &quot; Provincial part of the Constitution &apos;&apos; had utterly failed tosafeguard  Muslim, rights, and appointed  a committee to  examine  alternative schemes and report.  Mr. Jinnah  and Sir Sikandar Hayat  Khan  head  the names on this committee, which includes also  Sir Abdullah Haroon, author ofthe scheme described in paragraph 95 of the last Survey.  A section of  thepress  gave wide publicity to  another scheme, prepared by Dr. Abdul Latif ofHyderabad State ; the details are  hardlv worth recording, as the scheme doesnot appear to be taken seriously by intelligent MUSBms one of whom describedit  as  &quot;based on poetry  and moonshine &quot;.  Sir Sikandar  is reported to  haveanother plan &quot;by which India  is to be divided into seven internally independentregions  which are to be partners in a supreme Federation.   Still another scheme,divides  India into three independent sovereign  States.   The League and  itsleaders  have hitherto  shown themselves  incapable  of  suggesting  any policy&apos;which is feasible as an alternative to the constitution imposed by Parliament :and it is doubtful whether any practical form of &quot;Pakistan &quot; will be elaborated.    105. General. In-the last eighteen months the League under Mr. Jinnah&apos;s;direction has made remarkable headway -. but there are signs that  his  leadership5s  likely to be  questioned. His crabbed personality  does not inspire liking :and during the last session of the Central Assembly his own followers could not understand his motives for the command which in effect disfranchised Muslimson some most important  decisions.   On one of  these matters the Indo-british trade Pact the Punjab Premier made public  pronouncements  which  clearlyshowed  his own dislike of policy opposed  to the interests  of Punjab agricul-Agriculturists : and it  seems not impossible that Sir Sikandar  will break with hisleader.    The last Survey mentioned, as  signs of  the League&apos;s  lack of  politicalability,  its failure to keep control of  the Provinces of Assam, Sind,  and theFrontier.   Another sign  of its ineptitude beyond the  narrow  field   of   anti-Congress polemics is seen at Lucknow, where  the continued disorders betweenSunnis and Shias are a disgrace to the community.                      (c) Other opposition to Congress.    106. There have been no  developments of  importance.  But  it is perhapsworthy of mention that in Bihar the Hindu Mahasabha organised opposition to congress in the recent elections to District Boards and won a number of seats.              VII,-SPECIAL  PROBLEMS.                               (a) Palestine.    107.  The absence of  any Indian Muslim representative  at  the  PalestineConference in London has been made a grievance.  Jinnah,  on  behalf of the muslim League, telegraphed to the Secretary of State in February urging HisMajesty&apos;s Government to give representation to Indian Muslims, and saying thatthe failure of the Conference would have grave consequences.   The Secretary ofLS2SGG(P)
                                    so-State replied that Government had with great regret reached the conclusion thatthe scope of representation could not be  extended, but were fully aware of theviews of the Muslims of India and would  bear in mind the importance they attached to the issues involved.  Jinnah replied expressing deep disappomtment..An &quot;adjournment motion in the Central Assembly which- sought to discuss thefailure of the Government of India to seeuxe representation for &quot;Indian- Muslims-at the Conference was disallowed by the Governor-General.    The Muslim League used the failure of British  policy in Palestine  as an argument for supporting the  Congress party in the Central Assembly in passinga resolution that Incite should withdraw from the League of Nations.  The Pre-;sident disallowed another adjournment motion which sought to discuss the refusal of the British Government to grant independence to the Arabs and to stop jewish immigration into Palestine.    .    The Aga Khan told the Viceroy early in.February that he was prepared to visit Palestine &quot;and discuss the situation with  the Arab leaders if he could so.help to settle the problems.  He was informed that while His  Majesty&apos;s  Govern-ment were most grateful for his offer, they could not usefully avail themselves ofit,                                    &quot;                                 /     The Congress party resolution on Palestine passed at the Tripuri session.(see Appendix I) was little more  than a repetition of the resolution passed bythe Working  Committee  at  Wardlia in December, 1938 (see Appendix I ofSurvey No. 6).  The Premier of Bihar in February  sent a cable  to the  Secre-tary of State conveying the opinions of the Muslims  of the Province about thePalestine situation and recommending concession of the Arab demands ; this action was in response to the request of  a Muslim deputation which had waitedon the  Premier.  In the  Orissa Assembly the Speaker disallowed an  adjourn-ment motion to discuss  the discontent  created in  India, especially among:Muslims, by the British policy of ignoring and crushing the Arab movement for self-determination in Palestine.  British policy in Palestine is sometimes used asan argument, by speakers discouraging recruitment to the Army, for the Muslimsof India to refuse to help Britain in the event of a war.       The Hindu Mahasabha,  on the other hand, alarmed by what it called  a &quot; proposalto settle non-Indian Jews in India, passed a resolution in february-ary suggesting that the solution of the problem was to be found in unrestrictedcolonisation of Palestine  by  the Jews, to whom the country belongs, and  urging the British Government to continue the policy of establishing. Jews in Palestine.                            (b)  &apos;&apos; Prohibition!&apos;    108. &quot; Prohibition &quot; has become  one of the Congress touchstones.  Thenon-Congress Provinces have still not  taken it up.  The Punjab has postponedit indefinitely for financial reasons, and the Sind Ministry have stated that theirpolicy depends  on the extent to which  funds are available.   The Congress Pro-vinces on the other hand are all committed, more or less explicitly, to a programme which Avithin a term of years (a very  short term in some cases)  will forgo thewhole revenue  from alcoholic liquor and drugs and incur additional charges inthe enforcement of  the laAv.   It is not  possible to say Avhat measures the. Minis-tries would have introduced if these had  been left to their  OAVII judgment : butit can safely be affirmed that but for Gandhi&apos;s insistence the pace in most Pro-vinces would haA^e  been much more cautious.    The Assam GoA^ernment hope to banish the consumption of opium from theProvince  within  two years.  Total prohibition of opium consumption is to been forced in the Dibrugarh and Sibsagar subdivisions at a cost of five or six lakhsof rupees.  There are  10,000 addicts in these areas, but of these only 8 per cent.are under 50 years of age.    In Bihar  the tapping of toddy and transport of country liquor, etc.,  havebeen banned in a few more areas.    The, most sensational programme  is that of the Bombay Government.  It isto be,completed Avithin 3 years ; in the course of this year  Bombay city, island and suburbs, will be declared a dry area, and &quot;prohibition &quot; will be extended toIAVO more talukas adjacent to Ahmedabad.  The closing of liquor  shops on pay-days ist to be extended. In  the Bombay area people of  non-Asiatic domicile Avillbe allowed permits to obtain a limited  amount of liquor, according to the system in force in Ahmedabad : the sale of liquor in clubs Avill be  prohibited : licences for supply of intoxicants in  restaurants, hotels, etc., Avill also be terminated.   Thesale and possession of  the drug&apos;charas is to.be completely prohibited.
9 o  6    These measures will cost altogether some 190 lakhs of rupees, including lossOf reveiiue and expenditure on eirforcing the law.  The steps to be taken tomake up the loss in revenue have been described in paragraph 12.  In this Pro-vince the &quot; prohibition &quot; measures have hitherto been introduced, not by special legislation as in most other Provinces, but by executive notifications under theexisting Abkari Act.    The Ministry  have decided to entrust  the  enforcement of &quot; prohibition &quot;in the Bombay area to the police instead of to the! excise department ; here, asin some other&apos;Provinces, the latter is not trusted by the Ministry, but the HomeMinister has his own rejasons for desiring an increase in the police force.  Thepolice will take charge in Ahmedabad also, and the excise department will in timedisappear.    The proposals liave aroused much criticism, especially from the Parsi com-munity, many of whom have dealt in liquor for many years.  Dr. Gilder, theMinister responsible for &quot; prohibition &quot;, is himself a Parsi, and is  faced withgreat unpopularity in his  own community.   It  is said that in  Ahmedabad thefirst flush of enthusiasm for &quot; prohibition &quot; is waning.    The introduction of the measure in  Bombay (and in any other capital of a province) will create a problem in Government House hospitality.    In the Central Provinces the extension of  &quot; prohibition &quot;  to  two districts(Wardha and  Akola)  in January last was the result of direct pressure fromGandhi.  Till  that date it had been  in force (in one whole district (Saugor) andselected areas in some other districts.  The present loss of revenue is 8 lakhs outof a total exeise revenue of 33 lakhs.   Here also  the  administration has been entrusted to the police,  for one  year as an  experiment.  It is estimated that about 75 80 per i cent, of the addicts in the &apos;&apos; dry &apos;&apos; areas have given up drinkand there is little  evidence of widespread  illicit  distillation.   So  far then the experiment  may have been fairly successful.  But there are many difficultiesahead. : the aboriginals who form a large proportion  of the population are allcongenital addicts : evasion is simple, whether by distillation from the ubiquitousmailt v a tree or by  smuggling from  contiguous  State territory : the  Ministry isapathetic and has made no real attempt to prepare the ground  : the members ofthe Legislature and general public, while approving of &quot; prohibition &quot;  will do nothing practical to further its observance ;  (and as it becomes more widely known that  sacrifice  of lexcise revenue means extra taxation, ardour for further exten-sion is likely  to cool.     In Madras &quot; prohibition &quot; is to be extended to the North  Arcot district in October next.   It will then be in force in  four districts.  No  further progress has yet been  made in the North-West Frontier Province ; further restrictions on the sale of opium are to be introduced in Orissa.     The United Provinces Government extended the measure to four more dis- tricts Bijnor, Budaun,  Farrukhabad  and Jatmpur on April 1st,, making a total of six districts.  The annual report  of the  Excise Commissioner of this Province for the year ending March 31st, 1938,  recently published,  contains tren- chant comment which has  attained some publicity.   Since it will be recognised as true for a large part of India, some of it may profitably be summarised.  Diffi- cultios in the detection and prosecution of excise offences are bound to increase : every restrictive measure makes excise  crime more lucrative and attractive even to persons of the higher  castes, and leads to its more careful organisation and greater ingenuity  : in some places  illicitly  manufactured liquor &apos;;&apos; is supplied  to customers with the regularity of milk from a dairy &quot; : the general public, though vocal in favour of temperance, is apathetic, if  not sometimes actually hostile, in its attitude to detection : if the restrictive policy  is to succeed there is urgent need of rousing the public conscience and obtaining active co-operation.                  (c) The Congress flag and Bande Mataram.      109. The Congress flag and anthem may  now be regarded as having des- ,cended to their proper level as tokens of a party (albeit by far  the  largest .party) rather than of the Indian nation, and  as repugnant to considerable sec-  tions of the nation, in particular to Muslims.      In March the Bihar Government announced its policy regarding the flying of the Congress flag and the singing of Bande Mataram  in educational institutions. .The Government  would not interfere  with the authorities&apos; discretion  in  the  hoisting- of the flag, and had no intention  of issuing- instructions  against the  wish of the  managing committee of  an institution, who   should   consider  the  feelings of all the students before  coming  to a decision.  No more than the first
two stanzas of Bande Mataram should be sang in  schools or colleges :  thosestanzas are considered to contain nothing to which Muslims  can properly takeobjection :  the singing of even that portion of the song must  not  be   madeobligatory.  This  pronouncement  however  did not have  the desired effect :quarrels over the flying of the Congress flag have been increasing in Bihar.    In the  Central Provinces an incident occurred which would be ludicrous butfor the possibilities of grave communal trouble.  Np fewer than four differentparty emblems, including the  Congress flag, were hoisted on a gateway knownas the Patel Gate in Jubbulpore ;  crowds gathered daily and feeling ran high,The latest report stated that Government had  washed their hands of the matter by declaring that as the Gate belonged to the Municipal Committee, the  Com-mittee could adopt any measures it liked  to deal with  the  controversy,                          (d) War and Recruiting.    110. In paragraph 109 of Survey  No.  5,  for the  quarter ending, October31st, 1938,  an attempt was  made to estimate  what the feelings and  actions  ofA^various classes in India, and  of the Provincial Ministries, would have been ifwar in Europe had not been averted at  the end of September.  The conclusionssuggested were that among ordinary people there was on  the  whole little fearof war, and among many an  expectation  of material advantage from it ; poli-tically,  sympathy was  with Czechoslovakia  and democracy, and  against thedictatorships ;  the non-Congress Ministries  made  no   reservations about sup^port to England  in the prosecution of a war ; the  Congress attitude was not clearly  defined, but  two alternatives were in   the  air one,  the  Gandhiandoctrine of  complete dissociation from war, in however righteous a cause : theother,  the  desire to  take advantage of the crisis to bargain with Britain for constitutional  concessions as the price  of India &apos;&amp; support  :  but  Congress helpcould certainly not be expected unless  some  approach  were  made  to the high command  and unless  the appearance could be given  of a  voluntary decision by &quot; the Indian people &quot;.    The Munich settlement was generally regarded  by  Indian opinion  as  abetrayal of Czechoslovakia and a confession of weakness  among the  demo-cracies.    In paragraph 104 of the last Survey, circumstances were mentioned  whichmight  have an increasing effect against  aloofness  from  activities in supportof Britain at war such as a growing recognition that India will not  be un-affected by a  great  war, and by its results, and an increasing interest in themilitary aspect of nationalism.    It is now possible  to  detect a more  decided bias  against  the  dictators&apos;policy of  aggression.  The theory that there  is little  to  choose between that policy and British Imperialism, though still paraded, has lost verisimilitude :there is more condemnation of Germany and Italy, and  more sympathy with britain&apos;s problems and aims : and far less is  heard of  the view that Britain isdecadent and no  longer of account in Europe and the world.    The resolution passed at the  Tripuri session of Congress early in  March(see Appendix I) condemns British foreign policy, in terms that are alreadyout of date even in  Congress circles, for deliberately aiding the dictatorshipsand subverting the democracies.  It concludes with  an  announcement of India&apos;sneed to direct her own foreign policy as an independent nation, pursuing the path of peace  and freedom.  This resolution was moved by  Jawaharlal Nehru,and it is worth while tp point out some  change in  his opinions.   No. one had more bitterly  or  extravagantly denounced the attitude of   England,   whichcould only be explained as either pusillanimity or  a  deliberate  betrayal  of democracy.  &quot;But latterly England  has taken on some merit, partly from hers-rowms- readiness to  challenge the enemies   of  freedom   (and  keep theMediterranean open for India&apos;s benefit), and partly perhaps from  the  possi^bility of her being ranged alongside  Bussia.   &quot; India !s  freedom will not be worth many days7 purchase if Fascism and Nazism dominate  the  world.  Ourown existence  is bound up with the fate of freedom and democracy in the world.Only  a union  of  freedom-loving peoples  and their  mutual  co-operation  canavert the common peril.  For  that union India must stand &quot;.   This was writtenin an article published on  March 30th.  The  Pandit  goes  on  to  denounceBritain and France  in  familiar terms as responsible for the sad  state  of theEurope of  today, but continues-&quot; England and France have  still the instinctof democracy  , .&apos;........   Their peoples still care for freedom.   If the instinct
   finds proper expression and really stands up  for  the  defence  of  democracy,   then India can certainly look favourably on it and lend her hand in support &quot;.       111. Between the Tripuri  and Calcutta dates the Bill for the amendment   of the Government of India Act had been introduced in the House of Lords  :   the  purpose of this Bill is  restricted to amendments of immediate and sub-   stantial importance  designed either to express more clearly  the intentions  of   Parliament when the Act was  passed  or  to correct  mistakes  or  deficiencies   overlooked  at  that time.  Before the introduction  of the Bill  all Provincial   Ministries were given an opportunity of expressing their views on the proposed   amendments ; three Ministries refrained from comment  on  the ground that   they opposed the whole Act and no amendments could  serve  any useful pur-   pose.  The  remainder considered the  amendments on their merits.  The Bill   was  then modified in  the light  of their recommendations.       Certain clauses have excited comment and conflicting opinions in India, but  attention has been  foenssed mainly on that amendment which provides that,  when a Proclamation of Emergency under section 102 of the Act is in  opera-  lion  declaring that the security of India is threatened  by war,  the executive  authority of the Federation shall extend to the giving of  directions to a Pro-  vince as to the  manner in which its executive authority is to be exercised, and  extending the power of the Federal Legislature to make laws for a Province  (if the Governor General in his  discretion  is satisfied   that   this  is   really  needed in view  of the nature of the emergency)  so as to  include power to con-  Jer powers and impose duties on the Federation or  officers and authorities of  the Federation, even if the matter is one  with respect to which the Provincial  Legislature also has power to make laws.     The amendment  is needed  because section  102, while recognising that the  normal distribution1 of  powers  between the  Centre  and the Provinces  would  not be  suitable  in times of  grave national emergency, assumes to the  Centre  ah such an emergency only legislative powers  that  would otherwise be Pro-  vincial  and not  executive authority.  The  amendment is  designed to secure to  the Centre (hi time of war only) the measure of control and executive authority  necessary for co-ordination of the defence  of the country.     This proposal obtained  support from the Governments of  Assam, Bengal  and the Punjab, but was objected to by other  Ministries,  either  as  being un-  necessary or as  permitting undue inroads  on the authority of Provincial Goy-  ernments.  In view of the  great importance attached by the Central Govern-  ment  and His Majesty&apos;s Government to this  amendment, it was retained in the  amending Bill in spite of the opposition evoked.     The resolution on  Avar danger Avhich Avas passed at the Calcutta session of  the All-India Congress Committee on May 1st Avas mo\red by  Nehru  but only as a last-minute  substitute for Subhas Bose who absented  himself.   The resolu- tion (see Appendix I) announced  the determination of  Congress  to  oppose all attempts to impose  a war on  India without the consent  of the Indian people. The resolution went on to express  complete disapproval of the amending clause described above  as striking at the very basis of provincial   autonomy  and rendering it a farce in case of war.  The  concluding  words  are  somewhat ominous &quot; any  attempt to impose such an amendment oh India  must   and Avill be resisted in every Avay open to Congress.   Provincial Governments are warned to be ready to carry out the policy in this respect that may  be deter- mined by the All-India  Congress Committee  or the Working Commitee as the case may be &quot;.   Nehru, as reported in the Press, dealt mostly Avith the amend- ing Bill &quot;in his speech :  and expressed the view that the Ministries,  in the event of war, should not resign but should  &quot;  fight  &quot; (i.e., against control  by  the Centre)  without  resigning.    It is possible to conclude that the Congress, though  more certainly  dis- posed  noAv than in September last to  approve the attitude of Britain towards the aggressors, feels itself under the obligation  to represent the amendment of the  Government of India Act as precluding any co-operation m Avar.    Jawaharlal Nehru, hoAvever disposed to  lean  towards  sympathy i  with Britain&apos;s stand against  the dictators, has no illusions as  to the difficulties m the way  of Congress giving aid and support in the event of Avar.  It is known that he believes conflict with the Central Government to be almost inevitable on various issues.   Had Avar  come last autumn, Gandhi&apos;s view as to the course to be followedby the Congress  party  and Congress Ministries might well have prevailed.There  seems to be little trace of his influence in  the wording of the Calcuttaresolution of May 1st.  He has professed himself &quot; quite capable &quot; of fastingunto death to prevent a war in Europe : but  the  efficacy of that device is not3LS2SGG(P)
at present placed very Mgh even by  bis admirers : and Gandhi is probablyalone in his bebef that Hitler would be converted by an exhibition of ahimsaon the part of&apos; other European nations.    Subhas Bose&apos;s political morals are those of the pickpocket :  his mean andshallow mind sees in war only a &apos;&apos; golden opportunity &apos;&apos; for India to extort in-dependenee.  At  his  instance,  before  his fall from  the  presidentship  of congress, April 23rd was announcred as &quot; Anti-War Day &quot;  : the object of thiswas  in general to reaffirm that any  attempt to involve India in war would be resisted  (non-violently), and in particular  to  denounce the war emergencyamendment pending in Parliament.  The  demonstrations  seem  to have beennowhere remarkable : bitter  speeches were  made in  some places, for instance by Bhulabhai Desai in Bombay, but on the whole the Day fell rather flat.    The opinion  of ordinary people can be  gauged by the  growing dislike of anything  that savours  of amity with the dictatorships. Dr.  Schacht  on his arrival  in Bombay had a bad Press :  it is not unusual to see  denunciation inthe newspapers of totalitarian intrigue-in India, particularly  on the part ofNazi organisations.  (At the  same time a number of newspapers and journalistsare not: above  accepting subsidies for  German, Italian, and Japanese  propa-ganda.)  The Government Bill for the  registration of foreigners, introduced inthe recent session of the Assembly, had a good reception : and an ingredient in,the hostility felt  for Subhas Bose by  some Congress leaders has undoubtedly.been suspicion  of his having taken  pay from Italian and  Japanese sources.The  Congress Ministries, if war broke out in  the near future, might be expectedat first to remain in office and carry  on the administration :  many of the Minis-ters  would no doubt be willing to go pretty  far in  co-operation with measuresnecessitated by war : but all  would be  likely to obey the High Command  and,unless there is a change of heart there, it is difficult to believe that the Ministrieswould long be permitted to perform the multifarious functions which provincial governments in war-time would find  imperative in their own interests and thoseof India as a whole.    Muslim opinion has been affected perhaps not as strongly as might havebeen expected by the Italian seizure of Albania.  If the decision as to palestine is such as to rouse no excitement among the Arabs, that source of disaffectionwill  have been  removed or diminished. Though no such indication had by theend of April been given by the leaders of the League, it may be surmised that,if in time of war the Congress organisation ranges  itself against British policyand  authority, the League would, in the absence of any fresh reasons for hos-.tility, show more cordiality  than its present attitude suggests.    A number of Muslims,  for instance some  on  ths staff of the  AligarhUniversity, have  made  no  secret of the German sympathies which they have.acquired by residence in Germany and in some cases by marriages with  Ger-mans.     112, Propaganda against recruiting in the  Army is decreasing ,- nowherehas it been necessary to enforce the Criminal Law Amendment Act which waspassed  last year to penalise dissuasion  from enlistment and  instigation  ofmutiny.  The appearance in  the United Provinces of a new vernacular weeklypaper called the &quot; Sipahi &quot;  (sepoy),  caused some alarm, as its contents are intended to cause disaffection among Indian troops and to  Incite  to mutiny in.the event of Avar : but at present its  circulation does not  appear to be Avideenough  to require insistence on Its  suppression.     A resolution was carried  In the  North-West  Frontier Province Leglsla-ture recommending that arrangements should be made to give military  educa-tion to the people of the ProAdnce.     113. Air-Raid Precautions. In  April the Bombay Government again (seeparagraph 105  of the  last SurA^ey) raised  the question whether the Centralor the  ProAdncial Government should finance  precautionary measures : the.Home Minister wished to appoint an officer to specialise  in the subject^ and asked that the Central Government should agree to  proAlde thg finances with-out  prejudice to future arrangements about  respective spheres and liabilities.&apos;This sign of a Congress GoA^governments AV;&apos;Ibigness to co-operate in Avar measuresAvas Avelcome ; and at the end of April further consideration Avas being givento the  question  of  allocation of expenditure on these  and similar measures.                        (i)  Language  in Legislatures.114.  There is nothing fresh to report.
                         (a) The Central Assembly.    115.  General. The budget session of the Assembly lasted from February3rd until April 15th&quot;.  The strength of parties in the House at the beginning ofthe session was the same as before : but the position of Government was rendered.unusually difficult, and its record in respect  of important business disappoint-ing, by the vagaries of the Muslim League, which normally holds the  balance between  Government and its opponents.   In the  first fortnight of the session the League was hostile, and helped Congress to defeat Government on a num-ber of matters.  Later Mr. Jinnah appeared to feel that he was obliging Cong-ress with no  benefit to his own party,  and for a while he supported the Gov-ernment  side : but towards the end of the session he announced an attitude of neutrality on all important  issues.  Disgust  with both Government  and   theCongress, on  grounds wholly unconnected with th,e business in hand,  was given as his reason for this behaviour : its effect was to procure a series of victoriesfor the Congress party and defeat of very important&apos;.tant Government measures.    116.  Legislation. The Income-tax Bill was passed in its amended form (seeparagraph 108 of the last Survey).  Other Bills passed provided for the standar-disation throughout British India of the weights commonly used by the railwaysand in commerce, a prohibition of the employment of young children in certainoccupations, the assurance of greater safety in coal mines by providing assistance for stowing of sand in  places left by the  extraction  of coal, and the creation ofmachinery necessary for maintaining a register of foreigners in British India (ameasure  which obtained general support  from the knowledge that the Govern-ment  need more powers in order to be prepared for dealing with enemy aliensimmediately on the outbreak of war : the Assembly amended the definition of&quot; foreigner &quot;, however, so as to include  subjects  of the Dominions, the motivebeing- the prevailing resentment at the treatment of Indians in some parts of theBritish Empire).    The  Muslim League  co-operated  with Congress in rejecting the  IndianNaval Reserve Forces  (Discipline) Bill which was intended to  create naval re-serve  forces in India and to provid,e that they should be subject to the  IndianNavy  Discipline Act.   This  action was meant as a protest  against the inade-quate regard paid to political opinion in defence matters,  in particular   themethod of constituting  and framing the terms of reference of the Indian Sand-hurst  Committee.  The  Bill was later certified by the Governor-General.  TheGovernment motion to approve the Trade Agreement signed on  March  20thbetween His Majesty&apos;s  Government and the Government of India was defeated,and also  the Bill introduced to embody its terms :  the  Muslim League  Avasneutral.    The  (private) Muslim Dissolution  of Marriage Bill was passed.   Con-siderable interest has been aroused by the discussion of a private Bill to  giveHindu women a right of divorce, which will come up again  at  the next  session.Towards the  end of the session a resolution Avas adopted recommending   theappointment of a committee to report on the  reforms which are necessary forimproAnng the  rights of Hindu Avomen relating to  residence and maintenance and the legislative measures necessary to give effect to such reforms.    117.  Budgets. The Railway estimates which Avere presented in the middleof February forecast for  1938-39 a surplus of 2-05  crores as  against  an ori-ginally estimated surplus  of 24 crores and for 1939-40 a surplus of 2-13 crores.The most important Congress cut  motion which Avas intended to censure Gov-ernment  for their failure to evolve and  follow a long-range policy in  railwayfinance was rejected : this was during the period Avhen the Muslim League party were  supporting GoA^ernment.    The  General budget  was  presented  on  February  28th.  An   estimatedsurplus of 9 lakhs during the current year had been converted into a deficit.of265 lakhs, Avhich was almost entirely clue to the fall in the receipts from customsdutv and Avhich  thus absorbed a greater  part  of the original provision of  300lakhs  for reduction of debt.  Th.e estimates for 1930-40 show a deficit of 50 lakhswhich it  is proposed to meet by doubling the import duty on raw cotton.  Theintroduction of a new system of assessing  income-tax has the effect of increasingthe tax on the higher grades of income.  Thanks to the neutrality of the MuslimVIII-THE  CENTRAL LEGISLATURES
League party five amendments to the Finance Bill were carried against Govern-nient ; one reduced the rate of salt duty, another omitted altogether the clauseproviding for doubling the rate of import  duty on raw cotton, and a third re-duced the rate payable  on postcards ; two other amendments would have  re-daced the revenue from income-tax. The amendments involved  a loss of reve-nue  amounting to more than  2J crores.  The  Governor-General recommended the Assembly to pass the Bill in almost its original form, but it was again re-jected ; the Governor-General thereupon certified the Bill.     118. Other business. Early in the session  the Assembly passed without  a division an adjournment motion to discuss the rioting in Burma  and the failureof the Government of India to secure-the safety of life and property of indians in that country.   Another adjournment motion,  adopted without  a division,discussed the failure of the Government, of India to secure the  annulment of theexisting practice with regard to the aliehation and transfer of land in  the KenyaHighlands to Indians, and the disquieting fact that non-British subjects of Euro-pean race will receive preferential treatment  as against Indians.  Among the adjournment motions ruled out by the Governor-General was one concerningGovernment&apos;s refusal to consult the House  on  the Chatfield Committee report,another to discuss the failure of the Government of India to secure  representa-tion  for Indian Muslims at the Palestine Conference, and a third to discuss the refusal of the Government to give an opportunity to the Assembly to express its opinion on the proposed  amendments to the  Government of  India Act, 1935.The  President also ruled out another motion regarding the refusal of the BritishGovernment to grant independence to Palestine and to accede to the Arab de-mand  for stopping Jewish immigration.     A resolution was passed by the combined efforts of Congress and the muslim league recommending that India should withdraw  from the League  of Nations,on the ground that the League had failed to implement Article 16 of the Cove-nant against Covenant-breaking  members of the League ; Jinnah and his partysupported Congress on this issue in  order to express disapproval  of british policy in Palestine.  Another resolution which was passed without a divisionrecommended a cut (amount unspecified) in the salaries of all  employees in theGovernment of India earning more than  Rs.  200 ;  the  Government partyabstained from voting or expressing any opinion on the ground that some  indi-cation of budget proposals might be prematurely given away.     The usual interest in military and defence matters was displayed duringquestion hours.                 - &apos;     (b) The Council  of State.     119. The proceedings during the  first  week of the session  of the council which  opened on January 23rd were described in paragraph 109  of the  lastSurvey.  The session was resumed on February 13th and closed on April  18th.All the legislation passed by the Assembly was  also passed by the Council ; andin addition  the latter passed  the certified Finance Bill and the certified  Billembodying the  terms of the Indo-British tr;ade  agreement as well as the IndianNavalBeserve Forces (Discipline) Bill in the form recommended by the Gov-ernor-General.    A resolution was adopted recommending that it should be made obligatoryfor officers of the Central Government to use for office equipment only country-made articles, if available.  Another resolution which was carried without Gov-ernment opposition recommended the Governor-General in Council to convey toHis  Majesty&apos;s Government the feelings of indignation rand  resentment  withwhich the Kenya Highlands Order-in-Council had been received in India.  Reso-resolutions which  were  defeated  included  one recommending that excluded  andparti ally-excluded areas within or adjoining the boundaries of  Provinces shouldbe converted into normal  areas  governed by the administrative  machineries ofthose Provinces and declared as  parts of those  Provinces ; another which askedfor the appointment of a  committee to  report on the desirability of legislation to make Hindu marriages monogamous ; a third, rejected &quot;without a division,was  a Congress resolution recommending  that the sale of alcoholic liquor inrefreshment rooms on railway- stations in the  centrally-administered areas should be prohibited except to license-holders  ; and a fourth recommended the replacement of the Royal Air Force by an Indian Air Force and the  building upof reserves for this force in India in sufficient numbers to meet; any emergency.     120. The President  delivered an important ruling on a question which had arisen in the Council during the Simla session in September 1938.   The point for
9 INS -1  J JL             IX.-THE  FEDERAL COURT,     121. MR. SRINIVASA VARADACHARIAR, A JUDGE OF THE MADRAS HIGH COURT, WASAPPOINTED TO BE A JUDGE OF THE FEDERAL COURT IN SUCCESSION TO MR. JAYAKAR, ANDENTERED ON HIS  OFFICE ON FEBRUARY 27TH.     122. ON MARCH  23RD  THE  COURT DELIVERED  JUDGMENT  IN  THE SECOND CASEBROUGHT BEFORE IT WHICH INVOLVED CONFLICT BETWEEN THE  CENTRAL AND A provincial government.  THE TJ.  P. GOVERNMENT ASKED  FOR A DECLARATION THAT CERTAIN PRO-VISIONS OF THE CANTONMENTS, ACT, 1924,. WERE ultra vires THE THEN INDIAN LEGISLA--TURE AND WERE THEREFORE NOT A LAW IN FORCE IN BRITISH INDIA WHEN PART III OF THEGOVERNMENT, OF INDIA  ACT,  1935, CAME  INTO  OPERATION ;  THAT ALL FINES IMPOSEDAND REALISED BY CRIMINAL COURTS FOR OFFENCES COMMITTED  WITHIN  THE CANTONMENTAREAS IN THE PROVINCE  SHOULD BE CREDITED TO PROVINCIAL REVENUES ; AND THAT THEYWERE ENTITLED TO RECOVER AND ADJUST ALL  SUCH  SUMS WRONGLY  CREDITED TO CANTON--MENT FUNDS SINCE 1924.&apos;  THE  Governor-GENERAL IN COUNCIL  DENIED  THAT  any provisions OF THE CANTONMENTS ACT WERE INVALID. ;  AND FURTHER CONTENDED THATTHE  DISPUTE WAS NOT ONE WHICH WAS JUSTICIABLE BEFORE THE  FEDERAL COURT ANDTHAT THE COURT THEREFORE HAD NO JURISDICTION TO ENTERTAIN THE SUIT.     ON THE GROUND THAT THE PROCEEDS OF FINES IN CANTONMENT AREAS WERE &quot; RECEIPTSACCRUING IN RESPECT  OF PROVINCIAL SUBJECTS &quot; (IN THE  WORDS OF THE DEVOLUTIONRULES, 1920), INASMUCH AS THE FINES ACCRUED IN  RESPECT OF THE ADMINISTRATION OFJUSTICE  (A PROVINCIAL SUBJECT UNDER  THOSE RULES), THE GOVERNMENT OF THE  united provinces IN. 1926 HAD  CLAIMED THESE AMOUNTS AND ARGUED THAT SECTION 106 OF THECANTONMENTS ACT (RELATING TO CANTONMENT FUNDS) WAS ultra vires.  THE GOVERN-MENT OF INDIA REJECTED THE  CLAIM  AND  PLEA  : THE NEW PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENTREVIVED them, AND INSTITUTED  PROCEEDINGS WHEN THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA STILLREFUSED TO ENTERTAIN THEM.     THE COURT HELD THAT THE DEVOLUTION RULES, IN MAKING CRIMINAL LAW A  CENTRALSUBJECT, GAVE THO INDIAN LEGISLATURE POWER NOT ONLY TO CREATE CRIMINAL OFFENCESBUT  ALSO TO PROVIDE FOR THE DESTINATION OF  FINES IMPOSED  IN  RESPECT OF SUCHOFFENCES :  THERE WERE NO GROUNDS ON WHICH  THE LEGISLATIVE  COMPETENCE OF THATLEGISLATURE TO  ENACT SECTION  106  OF THE  CANTONMENTS  ACT COULD SUCCESSFULLY  be challenged.  THE PLAINTIFFS WERE NOT ENTITLED TO ANY OF  THE DECLARATIONS FOR WHICHTHEY asked : THE ACTION WAS DISMISSED, WITH  COSTS.  BUT  THE  COMBINED  EFFECT OFTHE  ADAPTATION ORDER AND THE TRANSITORY  PROVISIONS ORDER  OF 1937  WAS  TODELETE FROM THE CANTONMENTS ACT,  WITH  EFFECT  FROM APRIL 1ST, 1939, THE WHOLEOF THE PROVISIONS RELATING, TO  THE CREDITING OF FINES TO THE CANTONMENT  FUNDS.ON AND AFTER THAT DATE, UNLESS THE ADAPTATION ORDER  IS AMENDED, THE FINES will no LONGER HE CREDITED TO THE CANTONMENT FUNDS BUT WILL BE CREDITED TO THE revenues of THE PROVINCES.     ON THE QUESTION OF JURISDICTION, THE COURT HAD NO DOUBT OF ITS COMPETENCE to entertain A  SUIT FOR A  DECLARATION THAT SECTION 106 OF  THE CANTONMENTS ACT WASultra vires : THE GOVORNOR-GEUERAL IN COUNCIL  HAD A SUFFICIENT INTEREST IN THE SUB-JECT-MATTER OF THAT ACT  TO GIVE THE COURT JURISDICTION UNDER SECTION 204 (1) OF THECONSTITUTION ACT : IF IT WERE ARGUED THAT  A DECLARATION GRANTED AGAINST  THE GOV-ERNOR-GENERA] IN COUNCIL WOULD NOT BIND AIRY CANTONMENT BOARD, THE COURT would decline TO  CONTEMPLATE  THE POSSIBILITY OF A SUBORDINATE STATUTORY BODY DISREGARDSING A PRONOUNCEMENT OF THE COURT OR OF THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT OMITTING  TO take all NECESSARY STEPS TO PROCURE OBEDIENCE.     123. ANOTHER INTERESTING CASE CONCERNED THE INTERPRETATION OF SECTION 270 OFTHE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA ACT, 1935, WHICH REQUIRES (IN THE CASE  OF A PERSON EM-PLOYED IN CONNECTION WITH THE AFFAIRS OF A PROVINCE)  THE CONSENT  OF THE GOVERNORLS2SGG(P)DECISION WAS WHETHER IT IS THE DUTY OF THE PRESIDENT TO REFUSE TO ALLOW THE CHAM-HER TO ENTERTAIN A BILL THE ENACTMENT OF WHICH IS, IN HIS OPINION, BEYOND THE JURIS-DICTIOII OF THE CENTRAL LEGISLATURE.  THE DECISION IS  THAT HE WILL NOT MAKE ANYATTEMPT TO SECURE BY PRESIDENTIAL RULING THE DESTRUCTION OF A PRIVATE OR OFFICIALBILL ON THE GROUND OF  ITS BEING ultra vires BUT  WILL LEAVE IT TO THE JUDGMENT and experience OF THE HOUSE  TO DECIDE WHETHER A BILL IS UNACCEPTABLE ON THE ground of LEGAL INVALIDITY.  LIE POINTED OUT THAT THE FEDERAL COURT HAD BEEN SET UP FORTHE DECISION OF QUESTIONS  AFFECTING THE LEGISLATIVE  LISTS ; HE WOULD REGARD IT AS ANINTERFERENCE WITH THE POWERS AND PRIVILEGES OF  THE COUNCIL FOR THE CHAIR TO ARRO-GATE TO ITSELF THE FUNCTION, OF ADJUDICATING UPON  QUESTIONS OF  CONSTITUTIONAL LAWFOR WHICH A SPECIAL TRIBUNAL  HAS BEEN CREATED.  (THIS POINT  HAD ARISEN IN THEASSEMBLY SEE PARAGRAPH 114 OF SURVEY NO. 5.)
in his discretion for the institution of civil or criminal proceedings against that person in respect of jany act done or purporting to be done in the execution of bisduty as a servant of the Crown before the introduction of provincial autonomy.The appellant was a member of  the Punjab Subordinate Medical Service whohad been convicted on charges of criminal breach  of trust and falsification of accounts in respect of certain medicines, the property of the  District Boardhospital of which he was in charge.  The Sessions Judge, dealing with an appeal from conviction by a magistrate, hiad come  to the conclusion that proceedingscould not be instituted except with (the Governor&apos;s consent (which had not beenobtained) and acquitted the appellant.  The Crown  appealed to the Lahore HighCourt against the order of acquittal : the High  Court held (that section 270 didnot apply and set (aside the order and returned the case to the Sessions Court for disposal on the merits.  The party then obtained from the High Court a certi-fieate under section 205 of the Act enabling him to  appeal to the Federal Courton the ground that the consent of the Governor under section!270 was necessary.The Federal  Court examined the question whether the case alleged ag*ainst theappellant or sought tolbe proved against him related to acts done or purporting to be done by him &quot; in the execution of his duty &quot;.   The Court discriminatedbetween the two offences with which he  was charged.  Regarding  the  allegedoffence  of criminal breach of trust, the Court directed that the order of acquittalpassed  by  the Sessions Judge should be set  aside inasmuch as the acts  allegedcould not be regarded as acts done or purporting to be done ih execution of his duty.  The Sessions Court was directed to deal with the appeal on its  merits.Regarding the charge of falsification of accounts, the Court held that the accusedhad been acting in the execution of his official duty inasmuch as the official capa-city was involved in the very act complained of, and that therefore the Governorsconsent was  essential.  So  far as this charge  was concerned the proceedings against the appellant were quashed.  During the course of the arguments beforethe  Court  the question was mooted  Avhether section  205 of the Government ofIndia Act,  1935. contemplated appeals in criminal (as distinct from civil) cases  ;the Court held that the wording of the section cannot be held to exclude criminal cases.     The award of the Chief Justice in the Rajkot State  dispute referred to him for arbitration has been described in paragraph  96.   Sir Maurice Gwyer&apos;s inter-veution in  that  affair was wholly outside any statutory duties imposed  on himor on the Federal Court by statute,
                                               9fl ^39                             APPENDICES.                                  APPENDIX I.                   RESOLUTIONS OP THE CONGRESS PARTY.A. Resolutions passed by the 52nd session of the Indian National Congress at Tripuri,                             March 10th to 12th,  1939.                                 1.  CONGRESS POLICY.     &quot; In view e? various misunderstandings that have arisen  in  the  Congress and thecountry  on account of the controversies in  connection with the Presidential election andafter,  and to  clarity  its position and declare its general policy, the Committee declaresits  firm  adherence to the fundamental  policies and programme which  have  governed its programme in the past years under the guidance  of Mahatma Gandhi, and is definitely ofopinion that there should be no breach in  those  policies and they  should   continue  to govern the  Congress  programe in future.    The  Committee expresses its confidence  in the work of the Working Committee whichfunctioned during the last year,  and deplores that any aspersion should have been  castagainst any of the members.    In view of the critical situation that might develop during the coming year, and inview of the fact  that Mahatma  Gandhi can lead  the Congress and the country through such crisis,  the Committee regards it imperative^ that the executive  of  the  Congressshould command  his implicit confidence.  It therefore requests the President to nominatethe  Working Committee for the  ensuing year in  accordance with the wishes  of  MahatmaGandhi.&quot;2.  THE  NATIONAL,  DEMAND.     &quot; The Congress has for more  than half  a century striven for the advancement of the people of India, and has represented the urge of the Indian people towards  freedom and self-expression.  During the past 20 years, it has  engaged itself  on behalf of the masses of the country in a struggle against British&apos; Imperialism and through the suffering, discipline  and sacrifice of the people, it has carried the nation a long way to independence that is its objective. With the growing strength  of  the people, it has adapted  itself to the changing and  developing situation  and,  while  pursuing  various  programmes,  has ever worked for the independence of India  and the establishment of a democratic State in  the country.     Rejecting the Government of India Act, and with full determination to end it, it has decided to take  advantage of the measure of Provincial Autonomy that this Act provided, restricted and circumscribed as it was, in order to  strengthen the national movement, and to  give such relief to the masses as was possible under the circumstances.   To the  Federal part of the Act, the Congress declared its uncompromising opposition, and its destermina- tion to resist its imposition.     The Congress declares afresh its solemn resolve to achieve   independence for  the Nation.  No other constitutions or attempted solutions of the problem can be  accepted by the Indian people.     The Congress is of the opinion that in view of the situation in  India, the organized strength of the national  movement,  the remarkable growth of  the  consciousness of  the masses, a new awakening among the people of Indian  States  as well  as the rapid develop- ment of the world situation, the time has come for  the full application of the  principle of self-determination to India, so that the  people of  India might  establish  an  independent democratic  State by means-of a  Constituent  Assembly. Not  only the  inherent right and the dignity  of the people demand this full freedom, but  also economic and other pro- problems, which press insistently on the masses, cannot find solution, nor  can India get rid of her poverty and keep pace with  the modern progress unless the people have  full  op- portunities of self-development and growth which independence alone can  give.    Provincial Autonomy  affords no such scope for  development, and  its capacity for good is being rapidly exhausted ; the proposed Federation strangles India still further, and will no!t  be accepted.  The Congress, therefore,  is firmly of opinion that  the whole of the Government  of India Act must give place to the constitution  of a free India made  by the people  themselves.  An independent and democratic  India will  face  the  solution  ofour great problems rapidly and effectively and will line herself with progressive  peoples of the world, and thus aid the cause of democracy and freedom.
     With a view to  speed the  realization of the Congress objective, and in order fo face effectively the national and international crises that loom ahead, and prepare the country for a nation-wide struggle, this Congress calls upon  all parts of the Cnogress  organisa- tion, Congress Provincial Governments and the people generally,  to work to this end  by promoting  unity, and seeking to  eliminate  the  disruptive  forces  and conditions, which lead to  communal conflict and national disunity, by  co-ordinating the activities of  Pro- vincial  Governments with work  outside the Legislature,   and  by   strengthening   the organisation so as to make it a still more effective organ of the people&apos;s will.&quot;                                3.  CONGRESS  MACHINERY,     &quot; As  experience has  shown that the working  of the Congress machinery is often rendered difficult by  abuses in the method of  enrolment of  members, elections and other- wise, and i(t is urgently necessary to  remove all such  defects, the  Congress authorizes the A.-I.C.C. to take tall  steps that may be. necessary to attain that end, including changes in the constitution.  The A.-I.C.C. shall have the authority to  give immediate effect to  such constitutional changes.  The Congress  directs the  Working Committee to  take all neces- sary steps  to &quot;investigate  and rectify existing&apos; membership  rolls  and to take  all further action with a view to strengthening the organisation  and making  it conform to  the  Con- gress Constitution,&quot;                                   4. INDIAN  STATES.     &quot; The  Congress  welcomes the awakening of the people of Indian  States  in  many parts of the country and considers thus  as a  hopeful prelude to  a larger freedom,  corn- prising&apos; the whole of  India, for which the Congress has  laboured.  The Congress supports- the demand for responsible government and  civil liberty  m the States and expresses  its solidarity with these movements for freedom and self-expression, which  are   integral parts of  the larger struggle  for freedom of  the whole country.   While appreciating that some rulers of States have recognised this awakening as  a healthy sign of growth, and are: seeking  to adjust themselves to- it in eo-operatioit with their people, the Congress regrets that some other rulers have sought to suppress these movements by banning  peaceful and legitimate organisations and all political activity and,  in some cases, resorting to cruel and inhuman repression.   In particular, the  Congress  deplores the   attempt   of  seme rulers to seek the aid of the British Government in India to suppress their  own people,. and condemns unwarranted  use of the military and  police forces lent by  the  British authorities.     The Congress expresses  its sympathy with the sufferings of the growing number of refugees from various States, and trusts that the public will render them ever-y assistance.     The whole of India was profoundly stirred by  the  announcement of  an indefinite fast by  Gandhiji in  order to remedy the breach by the Thakore Saheb of Eajkot of the settlement arrived at between him and  his councillors on the one hand, and Sardar Patel7 as  representing the people, on the  other1.  The Congress expresses  its gratification at the recent agreement resulting in the termination of the fast and trusts that the people of&quot;Rajkot will have their aspirations fulfilled, and  further  hopes  that  the   Princes   off Ivathiawar  and other parts of India  will march with  the times and,  in co-operation  with their people,  introduce responsible government.     The  Congress regrets that several State  Governments besides Rajkot, have gone  back upon their assurances to  their people  and their pledged word.  It  trusts   that  these breaches of agreement will be repaired and  the  assurances  given  will be honoured.     The  Congress is  of opinion that the resolution of the Haripura session  of  the  Con- gress, relating to the States,  has answered the expectations raised by it and has justified itself by encouraging the people of the States to organise themselves and conduct their own movements  for freedom.   The Haripura policy was conceived in the  best interests of the people in order  to enable  them to develop  self-reliance and  strength.  This  policy was dictated  by circumstances and by  the  recognition of the limitations  inherent   in   the circumstances,  but it was never  conceived as an  obligation.   The  Congress has always possessed the right, as it is its duty,  to guide  the people of  the States  and lend them ijts influence.  The great awakening that is taking place among the people  of the  States  may lead to relaxation or  to complete removal of the restraint which the Congress has imposed upon itself, thus  resulting in the  ever-inereas::ng  identification of the Congress  with  the States peoples.  The  Working Committee is authorised to issue instructions in this behalf from time&apos;to time as the  occasion arises.     The  Congress desires  to  reiterate  that  its objective,  complete independence, is for:the whole of India, inclusive of the  States, which are integral parts  of India which cannot be  separated, and&quot; which must have  the  same measure  of political, social, economic  and religious  freedom as  a part of India.&quot;
                                 5. INDIANS OVERSEAS.    &quot; This Congress notes with grave concern and anxiety the rapidly deteriorating posi-tion of Indians overseas, especially in countries within the so-called British  Commonwealthof Nations, and extends its sympathy and support to all Indian nationals abroad in theirjust struggle for the assertion of their legitimate rights, political, civic and economic.  ThisCongress notes with particular anxiety the danger to Indian  life and property in Burma,the hostile attitude towards  Indians in Ceylon,  the preservation of Kenya Highlands toEuropeans to the exclusion of Indians, and the attempt to segregate and pass unjust lawsagainst Indians in South Africa.    This  Congress expresses its  opinion that only a  free  and independent India  caneffectively  help its  nationals  abroad.   In the  meantime, the  Congress calls  upon  thepeople of this country to do everything in their power to help the  cause of Indians over-seas. :&apos;                                 6. FOREIGN AFFAIRS.    &quot; The Congress records its entire disapproval of the British foreign policy culminatingin  the Munich Pact, the  Anglo-Italian Agreement and the recognition of  Rebel Spain.This policy has been one,of  deliberate betrayal of democracy, repeated breach of pledges,the ending of the system of collective security, and co-operation with Governments which&amp;re avowed enemies of democracy and freedom.   As the result/of this policy, the world isbeing reduced to a state of international anarchy where brutal  violence triumphs  andflourishes unchecked and decides the fate of nations, and in the name of peace stupendouspreparations are being made for the most terrible of wars.  International morality has sunk so low in Central and South-Western Europe that the world has witnessed with horrororganised terrorism of the Nazi Government against Nthe  people of the Jewish race and the continuous bombing from air by rebel  forces of  cities and civilian inhabitants and helplessrefugees in Spain.     The Congress dissociates itself  entirely from the British foreign policy which has con- sistently aided the  Fascist Power and  helped in the destruction of democratic countries. The Congress is opposed  to  Imperialism and Fascism alike and is  convinced  that world peace and progress require the ending of both of these.  In the opinion of the Congress, it is urgently necessary for  India to direct her own foreign policy  as an independent nation, thereby keeping aloof from both Imperialism and Fascism, and pursuing her path of peace and freedom.&quot;                            i         7. PALESTINE     &quot; The Congress has previously declared its full sympathy with the  Arabs in Palestine  in their struggle for national freedom and their fight against British Imperialism and has  condemned  the  policy of the mandatory  power in  Palestine. Subsequent  events  have  disclosed continuance of a reign of  terror maintained by the British Army  and police in the  name of law and order.  The courage, determination  and sacrifices made  by the Arabs in.  the struggle have evoked the admiration of the people of India, who desire to convey to  them again their greetings  and good  wishes for complete success in attainment of  their  objective.                                  &apos;      While  sympathizing  with the plight of the Jews in Europe and elsewhere, the Congress  deplores that in Palestine the Jews have relied on British armed forces to advance their  special privileges and thus cliqued themselves on the side of the British Imperialism.   The  Congress trusts that Arabs and Jews will endeavour to find a basis for  the direct co-opera-  tion with a view to establishing the independent democratic state in Palestine with adequate  protection  of Jewish rights.&quot;                                     8. BALUCHISTAN.      &quot;  In view  of the fact that British Baluchistan is still being (governed in the old irres-  ponsible and bureaucratic  manner, the Congress demands that democratic  and responsible   form of Government be introduced in the province without any delay, and it be granted the   same constitutional status as the other provinces in India.&apos;&apos;                                 9. EGYPTIAN DELEGATION-       &quot; The Congress extends1 its cordial welcome to the fraternal delegation from the Wafd   Party of Egypt, and  considers this visit as symbolizing the  solidarity of the movements for   freedom in Egypt and  India.  The  Congress sends its greetings to the people of  Egypt   and its earnest wishes for  complete  success in achieving full  freedom.   It  trusts  that the   association of the peoples1 of Egypt  and India will ever grow  closer and more fruitful in   furtherance of world peace and freedom.&quot;
                                     10.  CHINA.     i    :   1                       .    &quot; The Congress sends its greetings to the people of China and its deepest sympathy intheir trials and privations in their struggle against a ruthless and inhuman Imperialism:It congratulates them on their heroic resistance.    The Congress expresses its approval of the sending of a medical  mission on its behalfto the people of China and trusts that this mission will continue to receive full support sothat it may carry on its work of succour effectively and be a  worthy symbol of  Indiansolidarity with China.&quot;B. Resolutions passed by the All-India Congress Committee at Calcutta, May 1st to 2nd,                                       . 1939.                               1.  CONGRESS MACHINERY.     &quot;  In pursuance of the resolution passed at the Tripuri session of the Congress regard-ing reform in the Congress machinery  the  All-India Congress Committee appoints a  sub-committee, consisting of the President, Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru, Dr. Pattabhi Sitaramayya,Mr. Narendra Deo and  Mr. J. B. Kripalani, to recommend measures for the purification ofthe Congress  in  terms  of  the Congress resolution.&quot;                                 2.  ATTITUDE TO WAR.     &quot;  In view of the imminent danger of an international  war, the All-India CongressCommittee reminds the country  and all  others concerned of the national policy in regard towar, which the Congress has often proclaimed.  This policy will be strictly adhered to andthe Congress is determined to oppose all attempts to impose a war on India and use Indianresources in a war without the consent of the Indian people.     The Committee has noted with disapproval the dispatch of a small body of Indian troopstowards Aden, as this can only  mean their  employment for British imperialist purposes.     The  Committee, in particular, records its complete disapproval  of  the attempt beingmade by the  British  Government to amend the Government of India Act with a  view toconcentrating all power, in the event of a war emergency,  in the hands of the Central  Gov-ernment  which  functions  completely  as  an agent of  British  imperialism.  While the Congress is not interested as a  rule in  amendments to the India Act, and has worked forthe whole Act to be ended, it cannot tolerate an amendment which strikes at the very basis of provincial  autonomy and renders it a faree in case of war ; which  in effect creates a war dictatorship of the Central Government in India, and  which  makes provincial governments the helpless agents of imperialism.   Any  attempt  to impose  such an amendment on Indiamust and will be resisted in  every way open to the Congress.  Provincial Governments are warned to be ready to  carry out the policy in this respect that may  be  determined by the All-India Congress Committee or the Working Committee as the case may be.&quot;                                 3. INDIANS IN KENYA.     &quot; The All-India Congress  Committee  notes with grave concern the promulgation of an order-in-council regarding reservation of the highlands in Kenya for Europeans, which is a violation of  all announcements and&apos;assurances by the Secretary  of State for the Colo- nies and the  Government  of India, and perpetuates the policy of  racial  discrimination and is an  insult to India.   The All-India Congress Committee also places on record its opinion that the  Government of India nave failed to do their  duty to Indians in Kenya.  The All- India Congress Committee is further of opinion that the situation in Kenya cannot be met by any efforts on the part of the Government of India and requests the Working Committee to take necessary steps in this behalf.&quot;                                4. TERRORIST PRISONERS.     &quot; This meeting of the All-India Congress Committee, while appreciating the strenuous  efforts made by Mahatma Gandhi to  secure the release  of  political prisoners in Bengal,  notes with regret the failure of  negotiations between Mahatma Gandhi and the Huq Ministry  on the  matter.  The time during which Mahatma Gandhi  expected to  secure the release  of all political prisoners  is  over.  In view of the stiff and oallbus attitude of the Bengal  Ministry and the policy  adopted  by it the release of long term prisoners has become an  almost hopeless question.  In  the&apos;opinion of the  All-India Congress  Committee there  is  no longer any justification  for detaining prisoners in jail who were convicted during an  emergency period, mostly under special powers, and  especially so when the prisoners have  openly expressed their aversion to terrorism.  This meeting  of the All-India Congress Com-  mittee therefore resolves to make the release of political prisoners  in Bengal and the Punjab  an all-India issue and instructs the Working Committee to devise ways and means for  start-  ing a movement all over India for the release of these prisoners.&quot;                 . .
                                  APPENDIX n.Eesolntions passed by the Working Committee  and Council of the  All-India Muslim!                          League in March  and April  1939.                                   1. FEDERATION.    &quot; Whereas the Muslim League  is opposed to the scheme of Federation embodied inthe Government of India Act, 1935 ;  . Whereas the working of the provincial part of  the  constitution  has  created graveapprehension amongst Muslims  and other minorities regarding their future because  theprovincial  scheme has  utterly  failed to safeguard  even  the elementary  rights of  the muslim minorities in various provinces ;    And whereas by a  resolution passed at  the Patna session  in  December 1938.   thePresident of the  All-India Muslim League was  authorised to adopt such course as maybe necessary with a view to exploring the possibility of a suitable alternative which wouldsafeguard  the  interests  of Mussalmans  and  other minorities, the  President, with  theconcurrence of the Working  Committee, hereby appoints a  committee of  the followingto examine various  schemes  already propounded by  those who are fully  versed in  theconstitutional  development of  India and other  countries  and those that  may  be sub-mitted hereafter  to  the  President,  and  to  report to the Working Committee their con-clusions at an  early date :    Mr.  M. A. Jinnah, Sir Sikandar llayat Khan, Syed  Abdul  Aziz,  Sir  KhawazaNazim-ud-Din,  Sir Abdulla Haroon, I. B. Sardar  Aurangzeb Khan, Nawabzada Liaqat  AliKhan (convener).&quot;                            2. MUSLIMS  IN INDIAN STATES.    &quot; In view  of the set policy  of the Congress and other  Hindu organisations to achieveHindu supremacy and their  persistence in resorting to  coercive and subversive methodsin the Indian  Slates, the Muslim League is gravely  concerned  with regard to the  fate of Mussalmans in  various States and  therefore earnestly  advises  them effectively   toorganise  themselves  forthwith  in order  to protect their  liberties,   rights  and  interestsand assures them of its  fullest  support  and assistance in  the struggle.&quot;                               3. THE  RAJKOT  DISPUTE.    &quot; The  Council of the All-India Muslim League  deplores Mahatma  GandhPs actionin launching upon  his fast in a matter  of political issue, involving amongst others  theinclusion of two Muslim representatives  on the Rajkot Constitutional Reforms Committeealready nominated  by the Thakore  Sahib.  This  Council  earnestly   urges  upon  theThakore  Sahib and  the  Viceroy, who has  thought  fit to  intervene as representing   the paramount Power and thereby has created a dangerous precedent, that in no case shouldthese  two Mussalraan members, who  are  the truly chosen representatives  of  the Mussal-mans  of  Rajkot,  now be displaced  by the nominees of Mr.  Patel.  The  Council furtherurges upon the Mussalmans  of Rajkot and the Muslim Council to do  all in their powerto resist any  change  with  regard  to  their  representation  already  declared,   as   the muslim League is of the opinion that such a change would be highly detrimental to  the vital  interests  of Rajkot Mussalmans.&quot;                            4.  HYDERABAD STATE.    &quot; (1)  In view of the revolutionary unrest  that is stalking the land as a result of  the intensive propaganda launched by the &quot; National &quot; Congress and its henchmen to estab-lish Hindu hegemony all over India,  in utter disregard of the  just and natural aspirations of Indian Mussalmans, this Council  trusts that, while giving the fullest protection to  theMussalmans of the Deecan, who constitute the main strength of Islam in His Exalted High-ness1  Dominions,  His Exalted Highness&apos;  Government  will  provide for   adequate  repre-sentation for millions of depressed classes in the impending scheme of constitutional reformsand take  effective steps to emancipate these voiceless millions from the bondage of high casteHindus,  who have  hitherto monopolised all administrative  and educative  power in  the rural  areas throughout the&apos;Dominions.
    (2) This Council views with grave alarm the united onslaught of the Arya Samajists,the Hindu Mahasabhaites and their Congress friends on  His Exalted Highness&apos;  Donii-nions on the unreal pretext that Hindu religion and  Hindu civil liberty are in dangerof extinction in those Dominions.   The Council is firmly of the opinion that the inde-fensible policy  of the Paramount Power in refusing to stop  this subversive movement inBritish India against His Exalted Highness the Nizam, who is  their  &quot; faithful  allyhas already resulted and  will go on  resulting in  inter-communal  dashes for wlliich themain  responsibility  lies on  its shoulders.    In view of the  fact that Gandhiji&apos;s direct interference  in the affairs of the indian states has for its main object the  total extinction  of the sovereign prerogatives  of  theIndian Rulers  and the  overlordship of the Congress-ridden majority, as evidenced  by  theRajkot episode and  other atrocities of the Congress in Indian State&quot;s,  the Council urgesupon  H. E. Highness&apos;  Government  not to-recognise outside  agencies.   It further empna-tically calls upon the British Government to  stop their mischievous and dangerous acti-vities as they are already  creating communal tension and  hatred and must lead to serious and disastrous consequences,&quot;LS2SGG(P)-85-1-6-39-GIPB

</content>
</cab>
