<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/287/0 images: 466-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.CABINET.Copy no government)T no cp. 1U7.C39)I.R. A.  OUTRAGES.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.     1.   I feel it my duty to &quot;bring before the Cabinet the urgent need for further powers to deal with the criminalconspiracy of the I. R. A.     2.   The long tale of outrages beginning on the 16thJanuary and continuing at intervals is sufficiently fresh notto require recapitulation - in all they amount to over 160 upto the 21+th June - but in order that the Cabinet may have a picture of the problem it may be convenient to give a briefreview of the salient features,which will show on the one hand the serious extent of the danger to life and property and on theother hand the difficulties which prevent the effectivesuppression of the organisation without further drastic powers.     3.   On the 12th January the leaders of the organisation inIreland addressed a letter to Lord Halifax as Foreign Secretarydemanding the withdrawal of all British armed forces stationed in Ireland and threatening action if the demand were not complied with within a time limit of four days.   On the morning of the16th the first outrages were committed.   Recently Sean Russell,known to be one of the principal leaders, went to the UnitedStates to collect funds for the continuance of the campaign andis reported to have boasted openly in America that he had ordered the bomb outrages and that they would continue until thedemands were met.   It is believed that the campaign has beenfinanced from monies raised in America.   The possibility ofGerman assistance has not been lost sight of but so far no evidence whatever of this has been obtained,     L\.   I have no knowledge as to the funds at the disposalof the organisation which is centred in Eire but my information is that it is now highly organised, has really substantial
dt if /resources, and is capable of pursuing the campaign against thiscountry which it has announced.     5*   As indicated &quot;by its name the organisation is militaryin character with such titles as &quot;G-cOoC Southern Command&apos;1,,!Battalion Adjutant&quot; and so on, and commanders have &quot;beenappointed to the districts into which the country has been divided.   It operates however as a secret society, every member being sworn to secrecy and being liable to be court-martialled for disobedience to orders.   No list of members isbelieved to be in this country and, so far as is known, thereis no general headquarters here, or any local premises confined to I.R, A.  members.    The members meet at Irish social clubs ofvarious kinds and hold their meetings when the rest of thecompany has gone.   A member who is given an order to commitan outrage dare not disobey and the loyalty of members iscarefully and systematically checked.   The system consists ofimparting information to an individual member of a plan to commit an outrage and, if it is observed that precautionarysteps have been taken by the Police or other authorities tomeet the danger^ the individual is then known to be untrustworthyand dealt with accordingly.   On the other hand information to individuals as to the part which they actually are to play inthe commission of an outrage is usually only given at the lastpossible moment.     6.   Documents seized when the first group of persons were arrested showed that a careful plan of action had been preparedto begin with attempts on water, electricity and other vitalundertakings, and to proceed, when these had been guarded, witha miscellaneous variety of bombings calculated to cause the mostnuisance and alarm until a further opportunity occurred ofrenewing the attacks on the essential services of the country.
*5 yj                           - 3 -The leaders declared at the outset that they wished to avoidinjury to persons, and until the bomb explosions in the WestEnd on Saturday night the truth June nearly all the bombs (otherthan incendiary and tear-gas bombs) had been placed and timedto explode in the early hours of the morning when the public would not be about.   Only one person has been killed as aresult of the explosions and that was in Manchester in January.The leaders have, however, made it clear that they would notnecessarily continue to respect human life and on Saturdaythe 20th June the bombs were exploded recklessly when therewere many people in the streets.    A number of persons wereinjured and one of the injured, is likely to lose the sight ofone eye.   It is a mere accident that many casualties have notbeen caused on other occasions.   For instance, two large bombsone found in a gutter in Piccad.illy and one in a lavatory of atube station were seized and rendered harmless with onlyminutes to spare, owing to the courage and presence of mind ofa police officer and a private individual.     7.   The total amount of damage done in earlier outrages,though extensive, was fortunately limited in character, butexperts who examined some of the worst cases formed theconclusion that it was only through good luck and a lack of technical skill that the objectives aimed at were not achieved,e. g.  the destruction of Hammersmith Bridge.    An attack made ona particular viaduct in Forth London would,  had it been whollysuccessful, have caused most serious flooding to an extensivearea with immense resulting damage.     8.   The organisation has been at pains to train members in the preparation and use of explosives, and it is known that members have been sent to Eire to undergo a special course oftraining.   There is no doubt that the organisation is in
possession of a large stock of gelignite and detonators.During the last 8 months the equivalent of 5066 2-oz sticks ofgelignite have been reported as stolen in this country and inScotland and during the same period 21+66 detonators have alsobeen reported as stolen.   Whilst the police have recoveredsubstantial amounts it can safely be assumed that there are atthe present time available at least the equivalent of L.,0002-oz sticks of gelignite and over 1,000 detonators.     It is known that gelignite and detonators are pilferedfreely and any stock required by safe-breakers can easily besupplied from this source as and when required.     9.    I am satisfied that every practicable step has beentaken to ensure the safe custody of explosives, but they are used so extensively in mines, quarries and commercial under-takings that no safety precautions by owners or police canwholly prevent determined persons acquiring stores from timeto time either by means of burglaries or through leakages inthe course of use.    10,    As regards the personnel of the organisation, some50 have been arrested and sentenced to various terms ofimprisonments some to as much as 20 years.   These arrests have undoubtedly caused temporary dislocations in the plans mappedout, but it would be entirely wrong to suppose that theresources of the organisation have been materially crippled.The arrests have only been made by the Police by straining their powers of search under the Explosives Act, I883, to the utmost,and most of the persons were arrested for being found inpossession of explosive substances, a term which is given avery wide definition under the Act.   Thus a few grains ofchlorate of potash or a balloon, such as those used inconnection with some of the explosions, have been  sufficient to
secure a conviction.   In the earliest cases incriminatingliterature was found on which a charge for conspiracy could he based.   But experience has taught those concerned toimprove their methods both tactically and technically.    Theyhave been warned against keeping anything incriminating either on their persons or in their lodgings and to have their clothescleaned frequently to remove any traces of the ingredients ofexplosives.    The task of the Police is thus becoming moredifficult as the organisers become more wary,    11.    I am informed that the Police have upwards of 100persons (50 of whom are in London) under the closest observation,whom they have no doubt to be going sabout the country plottingand planning further outrages to be committed probably bysubordinates.    The Police are however powerless and, even if theorganisation were made illegal, they could produce no proof tosatisfy a Court that these persons were members of it.    Thereare on the Statute Book some old Acts passed between 1796 and1817 which made secret societies illegal, and there is aprovision in the Public Order Act, 1936, directed againstorganisations of a military character, but these measures are wholly ineffective, and no more capable of use in existingcircumstances than the ordinary law of conspiracy,    12.    In addition to the local organisers in this country,organisers come over from time to time from Ireland to stimulatemembers to greater activity.   The English Police have virtually no knowledge and no means of obtaining knowledge about theiridentity.   No passport system between Ireland and England would secure their exclusion.   Their purposes are only discovered byPolice observation and when they are seen by the Police to bevisitSng known local leaders the Police can take no steps.Occasionally one may be found in possession of a firearm on
which a charge can he based, but otherwise they are careful tocarry nothing on them to incriminate themselves.    13.    The Police are further hampered because of thedifficulty of obtaining information beforehand of plans to commit outrages.    Plans are not committed to paper nortransmitted through the post but passed by word of mouth.Hence, postal warrants although authorised by me have for themost part produced negative results.    Recent outrages andsuch information as has reached the Police afford a clear indication that the campaign will be intensified and theserious danger to property and life which is threatened is notto be disregarded.    While there is no evidence that the firesin the City of London this week are the work of the I.R.A.  theyfollow information received from two sources only last week thatincendiarism was  intended.    1U.    Paced with this position the Police and in particular the Commissioner  of Police and the Chief Constables of liverpool and Manchester have represented to me the urgent needfor further powers.    15.    The most effective power would be one to internpersons  whom I have reasonable grounds for supposing to been gaged in this criminal conspiracy with a provision for some form of appeal to an Advisory Committee.    Such a power wasconferred during the war by a Defence of the Realm Regulationto deal with persons of hostile origin or association and was continued under the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act, 1920.A similar power is included in the Defence Regulations for usein the event of war.   It involves, of course, a suspension ofthe Habeas Corpus Act, which in this country is and has come tobe regarded as the principal keystone of individual liberty.At various times of crisis in our history Parliament has agreed
to confer on the Executive an arbitrary power to imprison orintern persons dangerous to the safety of the State hut such powers are jealously guarded and reluctantly conceded only asa temporary expedient to deal with a very grave emergency.Before they can he asked for, popular opinion must heconvinced that they are necessary.   It is difficult toestimate to what extent public opinion is so convinced at themoment.   The success of the Police in effecting a number ofarrests has instilled a welcome if unjustified confidencewhich is the greater because the most serious attempts failedto achieve what was intended, but in spite of this there havebeen indications of late that public opinion is moving infavour of more drastic powers.    There would almost certainly be Parliamentary objection to the grant of such powers in timeof peace, and it would be pointed out that even during theserious Fenian outrages in the &apos; 80s the Government of the daydid not find it necessary to seek these powers, and except forthe war period 191U-18, and the recent Irish Rebellion, theyhave not been granted by Parliament since the early years ofthe 19th Century,   Against such criticism it might be urgedthat the Governments both of Eire and Northern Ireland have found it necessary to take powers to intern on suspicion.    16.   If a power to intern on suspicion is to be ruled out,there remains the possible alternative of a power to deport and exclude persons believed to be concerned in the conspiracy.The Dominions possess powers to deport British Subjects who donot belong to them but it has been the policy of the ImperialGovernment at Imperial Conferences to discourage the deportation of British Subjects long settled  in any part of the Empire onthe ground of special hardship arising when deep ties have beenformed through long residence.   Moreover, the Imperial
ftGovernment has often resisted any general proposal thatundesirable or destitute persons belonging to any part of theEmpire should he deported from the United Kingdom to theircountry of origin, or should he excluded, because to deport orexclude any members belonging to the family would only weaken the bonds of Empire.    17.    The present problem raises, however, very differentissues, and a power to remove members of the I.R. A.might not meet the same objections as would be raised to a power of internment.    Indeed, it might be welcomed in many quarters as the most sensible and least tyrannical method ofdealing with a difficult situation.    It might be open to criticism that it would be only a partial preventive, without asystem of passport control over the traffic between Ireland andGreat Britain.   A passport control system is not to be recommended except for war conditions and in a war its main use would be to check outward-bound traffic and stop persons seeking to evade their national obligations;  under peace conditions itwould seriously interfere with business and holiday traffic, itwould be expensive to administer and persons determined to enteror return to this country would probably evade the control in anumber of ways, e.g.  by using coastal shipping or obtainingpassports or identity cards in false names.    18.    As shown in this note, the real problem is todisorganise the local control maintained by sectional organisers.If these organisers could be removed, any attempt to return totheir districts would probably be soon discovered by the police,and if they were made liable to a substantial term of imprisonment for contravening a   removal   or exclusion ordertheir activities would be brought temporarily to an end.Further, the existence of a power to deport might prove a
9 4 feJ A .)ipowerful deterrent to any sympathisers who are tempted toparticipate in the organisation.    19-   Quite clearly persons horn or resident sincechildhood in this country could not he brought within thescope of such a power, and it would he more likely to command general support if confined to persons who were believed tohave been resident in Ireland and not to have been establishedmore than  x  years in Great Britain.   To fix  x  years ath or 5 years would cover a fair proportion of the principalorganisers, hut the higher the figure the more adequate itwould be for police purposes.    Provision for the constitution .of an Advisory Committee to advise in individual cases mightbe made if it were considered that this would make the passageof a Bill through Parliament easier.    20.   I have considered carefully whether any other methodof legislation could be devised, and have come to the conclusionthat nothing short of internment or removal is likely to beof any use to deal with a highly organised Secret Societywhich incites and ruthlessly enforces fanatical obedience.An amendment of the law to secure higher penalties for the illegal possession of firearms would be useful in a few cases which are detected by the police, but it would do nothing tobreak the organisation.    21.   It might be argued that to confine the power to persons formerly resident in Ireland would be an undesirablediscrimination against Eire and inconsistent with recognitionof the position of Eire as a member of the British Commonwealth.To meet this objection the power to remove might be made applicable to all British Subjects not born in or established in Great Britain for more than  x  years.   Having regard tothe extensive powers possessed and used by Dominions in
                                                           T* .1 3                          - 10 -regard to deportation of British Subjects it does not appearlikely that any objection on their part need be expected toany such a provision.   On this basis it would also appearunnecessary to enter into the question whether there was anyparticular part of the Empire to which the person concerned could be removed.    The power taken might be simply to orderremoval from Great Britain and to make it an offence punishablewith imprisonment to be found thereafter in Great Britain.    22.   It is manifest that whllo a power on this wide basismight be more effective and less open to objection on theground of discrimination against Eire, it would not onlyinvolve a complete change of policy but might&apos; reasonably berepresented as extending far beyond the actual necessities ofthe case, i.e.  it would be a weapon which could be used by theExecutive in its  discretion against persons having no connectionwith the I.R.A. but  engaged in subversive activities generally,e.g. Communist agitators from India or elsewhere.   It would bedifficult also on this plan to define within a sufficientlynarrow compass the nature of the activities which afforded aground for  the issue of  a  removal  order.    To  limit theproposal, on the  other hand, to persons resident in Eire  wouldin  itself indicate the mischief aimed at.    23.   The problem is of course intimately  related to  Irishpolitics.   There is  no  doubt that the organisation is greatlyfeared by the Eire Government..   It has been obliged in itsown defence to pass  the  Offences against the State Act underwhich  it has now  proclaimed the organisation to be illegal.This proscription enables special measures  to be taken for theconfiscation of any  of its property and under  the Act memberscan be prosecuted for various acts, defined as seditious,before the  ordinary  courts of Justice.   But whether the
Government intends or has the power to proceed to the arrest of the principal leaders remains to he seen.Included amongst the powers are powers to set up specialtribunals to try offenders and to intern suspects withouttrial or hearing and subject only to investigation by aSpecial Commission.   But these powers cannot be used untilbrought into force by proclamation and without resort tothese drastic powers it may well prove impossible for theGovernment to check the movement.   When the outrages werecommenced in January the Dominions Office received aprivate assurance from the High Commissioner for Eire inLondon that the Irish Civil Guard would co-operate with theEnglish police and give them any information in their possession which might be useful, but so far no assistanceof any value has been given.   Whether the failure is dueto lack of will or lack of knowledge is not known but asDe Valera made it plain that he was not seeking powers becauseof events outside Eire it may be that so long as theorganisation confines itself to committing outrages in theUnited Kingdom he does not propose to take any furtherpractical steps beyond the present declaration of illegality.    21+.   In any event any active steps of suppression in eire might only compel the leaders to cross over to thiscountry and intensify their present campaign, the object ofwhich is to force H.M. Government to bring the partition ofIreland to an end.    25.   If the Cabinet were prepared to agree to theprinciple of a Bill to confer powers of deportation andexclusion, there would remain the question whether such powers should relate only to Eire or include also Northern Irelandand I would propose to discuss this matter with theGovernment of Northern Ireland.   As that Government has
                      - 12 -special powers of internment v/hich are now being vised tohold a number of dangerous members of the organisation,it might be disposed to raise no objection to the return of persons previously resident in Northern Ireland.    26,   I do not necessarily contemplate that a Billshould be introduced at once but I ask for authority toprepare and submit to the Committee of Home Affairs a Billproviding for the removal and exclusion of personsbelonging to the I.R.A. on the lines indicated in thismemorandum, in order that, if there should be any new developments, a Bill may be ready.                                 S.H.30 June, 1939.

</content>
</cab>
