<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/81/0 images: 49-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET COPY NO:CP. (56) 113 CABINET4th May, 1956 AUTOMATIONMemorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service wish to draw the attention of my colleagues to the position arisingfrom recent developments in the field of automation.      These are as follows&apos;: -(a) The policy adopted by the recent Annual Conference of theAmalgamated Engineering Uniorfs National Committee that workersdisplaced because of automation should not be made redundant.(b) The current strike at the Standard liiotor Company.     This lias beenwrongly represented as a strike against automation.      In fact,it is a strike in support of a demand that, instead of men being&quot;laid off, short time should be introduced during the processof retooling one of the Company1s factories for the productionof a new tractor.      Installation of some additional automaticprocesses is only a part of this re-equipment and is not thecause of the dispute.(c) The campaign being run by certain sections of the Press,particularly the Daily Mirror and the Daily Herald, accusing theGovernment of lack of interest in the subject and failure togive any indication of its policy on automation.2.     It seems to me that apart from the political damage which this press campaing may do the Government the danger is that, if allowed to continueunanswered, it will mislead and confuse public opinion by making it appearthat we face increasing mechanisation on a scale and of a kind which will cause serious unemployment and thus prejudice its introduction,3.      The first thing we need to do is to consider what the attitude of theGovernment should be toward automation.     My colleagues will, I am sure,agree with me on two things:-(1 )     automation, in the sense of greater use of automatic controls over processes and machines and in computation, is but the most recent form of the technological developments which have beena feature of British industry for many years.     It would not bepossible, even if the Government wished to do so, to control theintroduction of automation in industry any more than any otherkind of mechanisation;(2)     since automation, like other forms of technological development,is a means of increasing productive efficiency, it is something which we should welcome and encourage.     Moreover, it may beexpected to improve the standard of living and will therefore inthe long run be to the advantage of the workers.4.     Our object, in my&apos; vie?/, should be to try to ensure that developments inthis field take place in a favourable atmosphere and with a minimum of friction and disturbance.      The Government1s policy of an expanding economy with adequate opportunities for alternative employment is its main contribution.Apart from this, it is important to realise that the scope for useful actionon our part is comparatively limited.      One of the most important issues which&apos;the introduction of automation raises is whether workers are to be madereduntant.      This is a matter for industry itself.
5.      It is essential that the Government should be thought and seen to betaking a continuing and active interest in the development of automationand its effect on workpeople.      One way of doing this would be to institute a high-level inquiry into the subject, possibly by means of a departmentalcommittee.     An Inquiry could help to make for better understanding; aboutthe meaning of automation and the various problems associated with, it, e.g.the need for an increased supply of technicians.      It would show that wewere not lagging behind the United States, where a Sub-Committee of congress was set up last Autumn to consider the subject of automation and technological change.6.      The disadvantages which I think there would be in an Inquiry of thiskind are:-(a) It might make it appear that the Government consideredthat a new and disquieting situation had arisen calling forspecial action.(b) Unless its scope was widened to cover the general question of technological development (which is too wide to be practical),it would not be able to produce a.ny more or better informationthan is contained in the Report by the Department of scientific and Industrial Research, which is to be issued later this month.The investigations on which this report is based were started about two years ago and have been carried out by the staff of the Departmentof Scientific and Industrial Research as part of their normal resx^onsibilit]/for examining developing scientific trends.      In accordance with theirusual practice, this report is factual and makes no recommendations aboutpolicy.7.      Apart from the question of an inquiry,  there are, I suggest, fourthings the Government should do.      It should:-(l)     Conduct an educational campaign with the public to ensure thatthe problem is placed in proper perspective.(?.)     Encourage industry to adopt good management practices indealing with emplojTnent problems created by automation, e. g.early consideration of what can be done to avoid the dischargeof workers, if possible, and full consultation with theunions(3)     Help, through the Deployment Exchanges, to find fresh emplo3Tnentfor workers who mil be displaced, if possible without anyintervening period of unemployment.(4)     Promote opportunities for training for the new skills thatwill be required.       These are broadly of three kinds:     fortechnologists and technicians, for which the Government&apos;sproposals on technical education will provide; for maintenancecraftsmen, where apprenticeship training schemes in industry must be appropriately adapted;    and for operatives, where on the job training by the firm will equip thern to do the new work.8,      I would recommend to my colleagues the following action:-(-I ) To arrange straightway for as much publicity as possible to begiven to the nature and extent of the problem and what action the Government can take, and to set up a small committee consisting,it is suggested, of representatives of the Treasury, the Board ofTrade and the Ministry of Labour, to promote and co-ordinate actionon this matter.
(2)     To discuss the -whole question with both sides of industry.I suggest that this should be done with the National joint advisory Council, which is the appropriate body to deal withthe effect of automation on employment.      Through the Counciland it-&quot; constituent members authoritative advice can be givento industry.     A sub-committee of the Council is alreadydealing with questions of apprenticeship training for thefuture.     It might also be appropriate to have this matter on the agenda ?/hen the next round of talks with the T. U.C.takes place.(3)     That all departments concerned should study the report of theDo S. I.T&apos;. with a view to talcing any Government action whichmay be desirable.I. MoMinistry, of Labour and National Service.4-th May, 1-956

</content>
</cab>
