<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/81/0 images: 90-92</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1956SECRETCP. (56) 11910th May, 1956CABINETHOUSE OF  LORDS reform memorandum by the Lord chancellor am in complete agreement with the Lord Presidents memorandum(CP. (56) 116) both as to the urgency of the problem and as to the lines onwhich it should be solved. I respectfully underline what is said in his paragraph 4.Everyone who has considered this problem has his own perfect plan over which one can. almost hear the mordaunt chuckles of the ghost of the Abbe Sieyes whoinvented more logical and unworkable constitutions in a shorter time than anyone else of whom I know.2. The following points are put forward where I hoped that someamplification of the Lord Presidents paper might help.3. I have been struck by the virtual unanimity which exists among the youngerpeers in favour of reform.4. The Committee of selection might have some such terms of referenceas are set out in paragraph 2 (B) (iii) of the Appendix to this paper.5. While I see the force of the arguments contained in paragraph 7 (3) ofthe Lord Presidents memorandum I have some fears that if expenses were granted the impetus for reform might abate. I am aware that the timing of expenses must depend on various considerations which have been mentioned in Cabinet. Itis therefore for consideration whether, as a method of procedure, the Governmentshould move first by introducing fairly detailed resolutions including one onexpenses and get them passed by the House of Lords before expenses are given.I set out in the Appendix to this memorandum the sort of resolution I have in mind.6.   There are three points to which it is worth while referring:  (a) I am in favour of 200 hereditary and 200 life peers (see paragraph 7 (1) ofthe Lord Presidents memorandum).(b) I am one of those mentioned in paragraph 11 of the Lord presidents memorandum who would like to see hereditary peers who are or havebeen Cabinet Ministers sit automatically for three reasons:  (i) They would add to the weight of the House.(ii) Their automatic right to sit and vote might make it easier for a prime Minister in selecting his Cabinet.(iii) Such a rule might soothe disquiet as to their being certain of selection on the part of ex-Ministers especially of the LabourParty.(c) Although I agree that the power to swamp has little political significancewhen the time of delay is only one year, I do not think that we shoulddie in the last ditch about it if it is pressed. It has a respectableconstitutional history.K.Office of the Lord Chancellor, S.W.1,8th May. 1956.49904Copy No.    
.    - APPENDIX &apos;      :DRAFT RESOLUTION FOR REFORM OF THE HOUSE OF LORDSThis House reaffirms its opinion expressed in 1910:  &quot; (i) That a strong and efficient Second Chamber is not merely an integral part of the British Constitution, but it is necessary to the well-being of the State, and to the balance of Parliament.&quot; (ii) That such a chamber can best be obtained by the reform andreconstitution of the House of Lords.&quot; (iii) That a necessary preliminary of such reform and reconstitution is theacceptance of the principle that the possession of a peerage should nolonger of itself give the right to sit and vote in the House of Lords &quot;and resolves as follows :  1. That an hereditary peer of England, Great Britain or the United Kingdomwho has any of the following additional qualifications shall be entitled to sit and vote in the reconstituted House, that is to say,(i) is the husband or a son or grandson of a Sovereign;(ii) is chosen by his fellow peers in accordance with the provisions in thenext following paragraph;(iii) holds or has held office as a Cabinet Minister in Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom;(iv) holds or has held high judicial office as defined by s. 25 of the AppellateJurisdiction Act, 1876.2. That 200 hereditary peers including 16 representative peers of Scotlandshall be chosen to sit and vote in the reconstituted House in the followingmanner:  (A) Peers of scotland the peers of Scotland shall elect the 16 representative peers of Scotland inaccordance with the provisions of the Act of Union, 1706, in the same manner asthey now elect them.(B) Peers of England, Great Britain and the United Kingdom(i) The House shall at the commencement of each Parliament by motion of the whole House appoint a committee of selection consisting of30 peers on which all Parties and sections of opinion in the Houseshall be represented.(ii) This committee shall be charged with the duty of selecting 184 peersfrom those hereditary peers of England, Great Britain or the UnitedKingdom who have signified to the committee their desire to beconsidered for selection; and those selected shall have the right to sit and vote in the reconstituted House for the duration of the parliament in which they were selected.(iii) The committee, in making their selection, shall have regard to thefollowing considerations:  (1) That those selected should include representatives of all the mainParties in the State.(2) The service that a candidate for selection may have rendered tothe State, and that by reason of their previous membership of the public services or otherwise, certain peers may not wishto identify themselves with any political Party.(3) Regional or local connections of a candidate.(4) The probability of attendance of the candidate in the House either for its general business or for the purpose of making a specialcontribution in relation to particular subjects.(iv) The names of those selected shall be approved or disapproved en blocby the whole House but there shall be no power to amend the list.
3. That those holders of Irish peerages who have already been elected for life as Irish representative peers shall be entitled to sit and vote in the reconstitutedHouse.4. That the following persons shall also: be entitled to sit and vote in thereconstituted House:  (i) Lords of Parliament  nominated for life by the Crown  on  therecommendation of the Prime Minister.(ii) Lords Spiritual, as at present.(iii) Lords of Appeal in Ordinary and retired Lords of Appeal in Ordinary,as at present.5. That in the first instance the number of recommendations made by thePrime Minister under paragraph 4 (i) should be 70, and that in making such recommendations the Prime Minister should have regard to the number of votescast for each political Party at the last General Election; and that thereafter10 recommendations should be made each year until the total number ofnominated Lords of Parliament is 200.6. That nominated Lords of Parliament may retire and thereupon shall notbe eligible to sit and vote in the House.7. That all members of the reconstituted House shall be entitled to freerailway travel between their homes and Parliament, and  x a day expenses ofattendance.8. That women shall be entitled to be nominated as life peers, and thatpeeresses in their own right shall be entitled to be chosen to sit and vote in thereconstituted House according to the form of peerage which they hold.

</content>
</cab>
