<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/81/0 images: 168-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1956SECRET Copy No.CP. (56) 14215th June, 1956CABINETFUTURE OF THE NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY organisation memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs. The problem at the Ministerial Meeting of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation(NATO) in May, the Council appointed a Committee of Three (Mr. Pearson ofCanada, Dr. Lange of Norway, and M. Martino of Italy) &quot; to advise the Councilon ways and means to improve and extend NATO- co-operation in non-militaryfields and to develop greater unity within the Atlantic Community.&quot;2. The three Ministers are meeting in Paris on 20th June. Mr. Pearson willbe in London on 18th and 19th June and we shall thus have an opportunity ofgiving him our ideas.II.: Economic ActivitiesPresent Position3. Article 2 of the North Atlantic Treaty provides inter alia that the Parties&quot; will seek to eliminate conflict in their international economic policies and will encourage economic collaboration between any or all of them.&quot; In practice, themembers of NATO have carried out this obligation mainly through other organisations, notably the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation,which is in fact (though not in name, in order to spare the susceptibilities of itsneutral members, such as Sweden and Switzerland) the economic wing of the atlantic Alliance. At the meeting in May, however, the North Atlantic Councilagreed to undertake periodical examinations of the political aspects of economic problems, and instructed their Permanent Representatives to examine suchproblems with the help of a committee of technical advisers.What We Do NOT Want4. NATO- should1 not be converted into an executive agency for economicpurposes, nor should it set up economic machinery of its own. This would onlyduplicate the work of other organisations. Nor is it a proper forum for givingaid&apos; to under-developed countries since it is suspect to the potential recipientcountries- in the Middle East and South-East Asia.What We DO Want5. NATO should, be the place where information about the Soviet economicthreat and its political and economic importance in world affairs should be collected,, analysed and periodically reviewed. There may be scope for improvingand extending discussion of economic matters with a defence slant and for airingviews on other economic problems of topical interest to the members of the alliance. A list of economic subjects on which study, consultation andco-operation- might usefully be undertaken in NATO is annexed.50033B
III. Political ActivitiesPresent Position6. Article 4 of the North Atlantic Treaty provides that &quot; the Parties will consult together whenever in the opinion of any of them the territorial integrity,political independence or security of any of the Parties is threatened.&quot; The trendover recent years has been to increase the scope of discussion from purely NATOinterests to matters outside the NATO areas. In the past, for example, the council has considered and generally approved French policy in Indo-China. It was alsoused effectively by the United Kingdom to regulate the export of arms to Egypt.Consultation on matters of common concern is now commonplace. At the lowestit may consist of no more than a statement by one of the Permanent Representa-tives to his colleagues. At its most effective it may take the form of an intelligentoff-the-record discussion in restricted session. The most obvious example of genuine consultation was the series of meetings between the three major Powersand their allies in NATO before the Geneva meetings in 1955. Politicalconsultation also occurs in individual NATO committees: for example, informulation of a common policy in dealing with Communist-front organisations.What We Do NOT Want7. It would be a major innovation for member countries to accept an obligation to discuss national policies with their Allies before those policies were put into action. Ideally, the North Atlantic Council should exist for exactly thispurpose, and in theory the members of NATO should always be able to put theirheads together and emerge with a single agreed and cohesive policy. In practice,however, the time factor often makes such prior consultation impossible. More-over, no Government and certainly not Her Majesty&apos;s Government, is ready tosubmit every aspect of its national policy in advance of execution to the judgment of its allies. Hence it is unrealistic to think at this stage in terms of any generalobligation to consult in advance on every foreign policy issue.8. It would be equally dangerous for NATO to create machinery or to lay down rules for the settlement of disputes between its members. Mr. Dulles,the United States Secretary of State, suggested at a recent press conference thatNATO might usefully develop as a &quot; regional organisation&quot; as envisaged in chapter VIII of the United Nations Charter, with machinery for settling disputesamong its members. He may have had the Organisation of American States(OAS) in mind as a model. Regional organisations set up under Chapter VIII have certain responsibilities vis-a-vis the Security Council, which NATO would not wishto undertake; and the OAS has an elaborate though flexible treaty on the pacificsettlement of disputes, of a kind which, as our experience in the Council ofEurope shows, it would be most difficult to negotiate among Western european nations. To seek to formalise any such procedure in NATO would be contraryto the practice followed in the British Commonwealth and would be more likelyto disrupt the unity of NATO than to promote it.What We DO Want9. Our aim should be to enable NATO to play an effective part in developing the West&apos;s power and posture in &quot; competitive co-existence &quot; and in organising acommon front (diplomatic, economic and defence) against Communism. NATOcould thus serve to achieve two primary objectives of our foreign policy: continuedUnited States involvement in Europe and continued German adherence to theWest. The subjects on which the members of NATO should seek, through prior consulation, to develop community of view and identity of policy, can be broadlydefined as (a) those relating to the external threat to which NATO is exposed by the actions and policy of the Sino-Soviet bloc; and(b) those which would help to strengthen the Alliance internally so that itis better equipped to meet the external threat.10. We should, therefore, look on the North Atlantic Council as the principalforum in which to expound and justify our policies on the above-mentioned subjects.
50033Our Permanent Representative should be in broadly the position of a Minister inParliament, sometimes explaining after the event and sometimes seeking advanceapproval for some specific action or policy. On many occasions it may be neitherpossible nor desirable to go to the Council before the event. But we must try todo so as often as possible; and as problems arise, we shall have to consider in eachcase whether, as I said in Paris, we can give an indication of the way in which our minds are being made up. A case in point might be to arrange for a discussion ofthe lines on which we may propose to deal with the latest Soviet communication on Disarmament before the recipients despatch their replies. Even when we doconsult the North Atlantic Council in advance, it will be with the tacit reservation(which, on occasion, we may have to state explicitly) that national interests remainparamount. But we should be prepared to accept sacrifices of national interests in small matters; and equally we should not be shy of asking others to make sacrifices.Above all, we should always speak as frankly as possible and encourage others to dolikewise. Nothing is so destructive of mutual confidence among friends as suspicion of motive. The fundamental community of interest in NATO is strong enough to stand a considerably greater degree of frankness and discussion than is at presentthe rule.11. If we are to discuss our policies in NATO with any degree of confidence and profit, certain changes in NATO procedure will be required:  (i) Improvement in the CounciFs working methods.   We should advocatemore frequent use of restricted sessions where discussion is less inhibited.The representatives of the smaller countries must be encouraged to askquestions and in general not to hesitate to criticise if they so wish. We,for our part, must be prepared deliberately to seek advice, though in thelong run we may not always accept it. As a broad rule, our permanent representative should have discretion to speak from, and if he wishes,to initiate discussion on, any subject dealt with in a Foreign Office Intel.The Councils agenda should normally be agreed in advance, so thatall Permanent Representatives can obtain the views of their governments on the subjects to be discussed.(ii) Improvement of representation.  If discussion is to be useful, the briefingof representatives must be better than at present. Governments must bebrought to regard their Permanent Representatives as key men, who should be of first-class calibre and able to act as spokesmen of national policies on all subjects. Our Intel system plus regular visits to theUnited Kingdom has proved generally adequate for our ownrepresentative, Sir Christopher Steel, and other Governments shouldbe encouraged to make similar arrangements. Ministers and experts(including those from Departments other than the Foreign Office)should attend more often and be prepared to be interrogated byPermanent Representatives.(iii) Improvement of security.  This question is fundamental to any proposalfor developing political consultation in NATO. We must impress on all member Governments the importance of using the most secure means for reporting the CounciFs discussions and sending instructions to their permanent Representatives. It is equally essential to devise some method of preventing the proceedings in the Council from becomingknown to the Press.12. As for disputes between NATO members, the activities of NATO shouldbe limited to &quot; good offices,&quot; i.e., the provision of a friendly forum in which theparties can work out their differences outside rather than inside the regular andformal meetings of the organisation. Unless the parties agree that it should so act,there should be no question of NATO as such recommending solutions nor ofconstituting itself as an executive agency in the matter.IV. Parliamentary ActivitiesPresent Position13. A Meeting of NATO Parliamentarians was held in Paris last summer.They set up a Continuing Committee to organise further Meetings, the first of whichis due to be held in Paris in November.
What We Do NOT Want   ... . , ,A parliamentary assembly as part of NATO would want to discuss aspects of nato&apos;s activity which are not suitable for public debate, would complicate thework of the Council and would add to the proliferation of parliamentaryassemblies.What We DO Want14. Parliamentary interest is essential if NATO is to have popular appeal;and we should do all we can to encourage closer and more frequent contacts between United States and Canadian Parliamentarians and their European fellows.We therefore welcome the meetings of NATO Parliamentarians; we hope that these will become an annual event; and we should do our best to ensure that they areattended by a strong team from the United Kingdom. The initiative for these meetings should however remain with the Parliamentarians; when held in Paris,we should encourage the Secretary-General of NATO to provide facilities. If thepractical difficulties can be overcome, we should not discourage the holding of meetings in capitals other than Paris, since this might help to promote NATOsolidarity.15. In the long term we should not oppose the creation of an AtlanticAssembly, but it is too early at this stage to suggest whether it could most suitablydevelop out of the meetings of NATO Parliamentarians or by the association of american and Canadian Parliamentarians with existing European Assemblies.V. Recommendation16.   I propose to use this paper as my brief when talking to Mr. Pearson.S. L.Foreign Office, S.W. 1, -13th June, 1956.AnnexECONOMIC DISCUSSIONS IN NORTH ATLANTIC treaty organisation, There is already a certain amount of economic work dealt with in NATO, but its depth and usefulness have been limited because it has generally not been relatedin a specific and concrete way to the formulation of NATO policies. some improvement in this respect can be hoped for in view of the &quot; new look &quot; which theforegoing memorandum proposes for NATO political discussions: the samedevelopment may help also to extend the range of NATO economic work.2. Even now NATO economic work might be improved and extended in thefollowing respects:  (a) Comparative studies of the future course of Soviet internal economic development and internal economic development of NATO Powers.Some work has already been done on this in NATO. A properassessment of the potentialities and policies of the Soviet bloc and the nato Powers for competitive co-existence is obviously desirable andrelevant to the formulation of defence and other policies of NATOPowers. These studies might be made more forward-looking and comprehensive, and discussion in NATO directed specifically to the implications of the findings for NATO Powers, individually andcollectively.
(b) Studies and discussion of the lay-out of economic resources of NATOPowers appropriate to competitive co-existence.These would deal with specific aspects of (a) and provide answers to such questions as (i) Internal investment and defence are the proportions of national incomes of members individually and collectively devoted tothese two elements appropriate to &quot; competitive co-existence? &quot;(ii) Skilled   manpower  and   defence are   members   devoting   an excessive proportion of their scientific and other scarce skills to defence production, to their detriment in &quot; competitiveco-existence &quot;?(iii) External investment and defence are members devoting too little or too much of their national income to overseas investment,with a consequent weakening of their economies and their defence potential?(c) Comparative studies of external economic policies of the Soviet bloc andthe NATO Powers, in relation to important under-developed territories.Our policy is to frown upon any proposals for making NATO adirect agency for economic aid to under-developed territories and it seven doubtful whether NATO Powers together could usefully take an initiative in regard to discussion of such questions in other international bodies, e.g., UNO. We are already supporting the idea that NATOshould compile comparative statistics of the aid given by the Soviet bloc and by NATO countries to under-developed territories, so as to put their respective efforts in proper perspective.(d) Discussion of the reliance of economies of NATO Powers upon oil supplies from the Middle East (including the political implications ofthat dependence).This is probably the sort of subject which ought to have occupiedNATO in the past. In fact, the economic work now being done in this field is being done by OEEC. The main question here seems to be whether, given the great and growing dependence of NATO countries on Middle East oil, there should not be a co-ordinated NATO politicalline in regard to the Middle East.(e) Discussion of the general line to be followed in regard to Soviet offensiveson economic subjects in international forums such as the united nations and the Economic Commission for Europe.Soviet initiatives in these bodies sometimes catch NATO Powersunprepared and with no co-ordinated line and thus at a disadvantage.Discussion of general tactics vis-a-vis the Soviets and emphasis byNATO representatives in their reports to their Governments of thevalue of NATO unity of view in such situations might help.(/) Economic problems of maintaining and replacing equipment.This is a specific aspect of the general problem of defence burdensand studies on it are already proceeding in NATO. There is a special problem in regard to replacements of the large quantities of UnitedStates equipment provided free by the Americans to Europe. We mightaim to extend studies so as specifically to include balance of paymentsproblems arising out of such replacements.3. Apart from the foregoing there are few if any economic subjects for the study and discussion of which adequate provision is not already made in other international bodies such as the OEEC, the General Agreement on Tariffs andTrade and the International Monetary Fund. We should oppose starting up in nato economic work which was merely academic duplication of matters alreadydealt with in a practical manner elsewhere. For these reasons we ought to exclude from consideration in NATO such specific matters as trade liberalisation, tariffs,Imperial Preference, exchange rate policies and the like. This would, of course,not prevent general discussion in NATO (on the basis of economic reports anddata compiled by others) of political aspects of economic problems.   The topic
mentioned in paragraph 2 (d) is an example. There may also come a stage in ourrelations with Europe at which it would be useful to have discussions in NATO onthe question whether a more unified Europe could make a more effective economicand military contribution to Western defence.4. The economic tasks, mentioned in paragraph 2 could, in our view, becarried out without any addition to the staff of NATO or to the nationaldelegations. The existing NATO economic staff would continue to deal with thosesubjects which, by their very nature, are not suitable for delegating to other bodies,e.g., the review of Soviet internal and external economic policies and the economic problems of maintaining and replacing military equipment. In regard to widereconomic issues collection of statistics, aid to under-developed territories, ratesof investment in member countries, and the like NATO might make use of OEECeconomic staff: it should be possible to arrange this despite the presence neutrals in O.E.E.C. The Permanent Council of NATO could generally be assisted in economic discussions by experts drawn from the economic elements inthe national NATO delegations. When wider economic issues were involved orthe discussions are on the basis of reports and data collected by OEEC, then theeconomic experts from the OEEC national delegations could lend assistance. Inthese circumstances we should continue to share the general opposition to an italian proposal that these should be a continuing high level body of economicexperts. We should not, however, exclude the possibility that for certain topics ofparticular magnitude or complexity experts from member countries might fromtime to time assist the Permanent Council in its deliberations.

</content>
</cab>
