<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/81/0 images: 195-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.P. (56) 149 COPY NO.20th June, 1956CABINETWHITE FISH SUBSIDYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the home department, the Secretary of State for Scotland and theMinister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food we ask our colleagues -(i)  to authorise legislation to continue the white fishsubsidy after March, 1950, and to decide forhow long;(ii)   to decide certain other questions set out inparagraph 0 below affecting the payment of subsidy for 1956-57.These are bound up together.    Questions under (ii) require immediate decision since a statutory scheme must be approved by Parliament beforethe recess.background.      The subsidy is paid to the near and middle-water and inshorefleets and was first introduced in 1950 to alleviate the market collapsethat followed fish decontrol and ensure the maintenance of adequate supplies at reasonable prices.     The White Fish and Herring industries act, 1953, authorised its continuance until 31st March, 1950, and also provided grants and loans for the building of new vessels over a ten-year period ending in May, 1963: most of the money being intended to replace the ageing near and middle-water steam fleet which was mostly builtbefore 1921, consumes coal and absorbs the greater part of the white fishsubsidy.     The main purpose of the subsidy thereby became to keep anadequate fleet in being while a modern and more efficient motor fleet was built up.Present situation.      As regards the near and middle-water fleet, the number of steamvessels has fallen since 1950 from 773 to 440, and the motor fleet has grown from 69 to 140 vessels.     The rates of fall and growth alike havebeen quickening.    Last year 07 steam vessels went out against 56 and 55in the two previous years:  32 grant and loan-aided motor vessels beganfishing in 1955 and another 15 since then, while 75 more are on order.The yards can build about 30 motor vessels a year.    This rate shouldquicken in some measure if and as Admiralty work lessens.
4.      Over recent years, the near and middle-water catch has been falling less rapidly than the number of vessels.    The fall in the catchhas been largely made up by increased supplies from the inshore andseining fleets, which produce fish of as good quality though on the wholeless wide variety.     Quality fish of wide variety helps to sell the other by attracting custom to the shops;   and the lower-quality distant-waterfish is at present being over-produced.    So the near and middle-water supplies need to be kept in reasonable balance with the rest of thesupply.5.      The 440 steam vessels now left burn 660, 000 tons of best qualitycoal a year.    Each vessel burns an average of 1, 500 tons a year.    Theinshore fleet does not run on coal.    At the margin, all this coal costsdollars;   these steam vessels therefore impose a dollar burden of about 4-1 - millions on the balance of payments.6.      The annual co3t of the near and middle-water subsidy at current rates, and with the fleet at its present size, is  1. 6 millions:  theinshore fleet takes  0.7 million.     The total is  2.3 millions.Questions for Decision7.      Subsidy is adjusted to need from year to year under schemesrequiring the affirmative resolution of both Houses.    The current schemeexpires at 31st July and a fresh scheme mustbe laid early next month.An unfavourable movement of operating costs, accentuated by the recent increase in coal prices, means that subsidy must be increased for1956-57 and that the monies available under the Act of 1953 will run outwell before March, 1958.    Taken together with the limited pace at whicha modern fleet can be built up (paragraph 3 above), this means that thefleet cannot possibly be self-supporting by that date.We are agreed that fresh legislation is required both to provide more money and to extend the subsidy period beyond March, 1950, andmust be taken next session.    We understand the Treasury do not dissent from this;   and we ask our colleagues to endorse this conclusion.0,      The questions which then arise and on which we require to consult our colleagues are these:-(i) At what rate should the steam fleet of coal-burnersbe allowed to run out ?(ii)  For what period should the subsidy be extendedbeyond March, 1950 ?(iii) Should the crews share as hitherto in any increase of subsidy?These questions essentially relate to the near and middle-water fleet.(iv) Should the subsidy rate for the inshore fleetbe left unchanged or the cut made on thelast occasion be restored?
i b II9.      The Treasury, in order to keep to a minimum the additionalsubsidy that will be required, and also in order to reduce the dollar burden which the steam vessels impose on the balance of iDayments, wish the rateof run-down to be raised to 150 a year.    We think that a decline of 150 ayear is much too drastic, and do not wish the run-down to exceed 00 steam-vessels in 1956-57.    &quot;We consider that the rate proposed by the treasury would endanger the continuance of some fishing ports;  would so reducethe crews and supply and service trades as seriously to prejudice the chances of eventually building an adequate and efficient motor fleet;   andwould lead to serious unemployment, notably at Aberdeen, where the ratemight rise to 6 per cent.    On the other hand,  the Treasury point out thata run-down rate of 80 a year would represent something actually less thanthe present rate;   that taking the inshore and the near and middle-waterfisheries together, catches have been increasing, despite the decreasingnumber of vessels engaged in the near and middle-water fishing, whilstfish prices in general are now (alone of all food prices) at no more thanthe 1952 level;   and that no more than about 2, 500 men all told would beunemployed as a result of the additional run-down.    The Treasury considerthat every year that passes increases the risk that the subsidy will cometo be regarded as a permanent support for the industry.    The rateproposed by the Treasury would eliminate the old and uneconomic vessels in about three years:  that proposed by us would take about five years.The additional 70 vessels in question would cost about  250, 000 insubsidy and about  700, 000 in dollar-costing coal per annum.Duration of Subsidy10.     The Treasury&apos;s proposal would imply that the new legislation should not authorise continuance of the subsidy beyond 1961 at latest.We think that subsidy authority should be extended to 1963 and made co-terminous with the grants and loans scheme for the rebuilding of thefleet which ends in 1963 and is essentially related to the need for subsidy.Sharing of Subsidy with Crews11.     The subsidy has always counted as part of the proceeds of the vessel for settling crews1 earnings, and about 23 per cent of the totalgoes to the crews.    About half this amount goes to those who settle onthe &quot;gross&quot; (i. e. proceeds irrespective of costs) and the other half tothose who settle on the &quot;net&quot; (i. e. proceeds less voyage expenses).     Thiswas logical when the subsidy was intended to compensate for fallingprices which were reflected in a reduction in crews1 earnings, whethersettled on the gross or the net.    But for those on the gross it has become more and more anomalous as the subsidy has been raised to coverincreases in owners&apos; costs,  since those on the gross thereby get awindfall.    As the same time the system is well-established and anyattempt to modify it may well lead to trouble with the Trade Unions andwould create crewing difficulties and almost certainly lead to fresh wagedemands.    We think the crews must be allowed to retain their share ofthe existing subsidy, but despite the risks we propose, if our colleagues agree, to exclude those who settle on the gross from any share in further increases.
12.     The inshore vessels, i. e. those under 70 ft., get a landingspayment of Od. per stone.    In common with the larger motor vesselstheir subsidy was reduced by 2d. per stone from 1st January, 1956.Originally it was proposed to reduce the inshore subsidy by 4d. per stonebut the Cabinet decided on 14th December to reduce the cut to 2d. perstone (CM. (55) 46th Conclusions, Minute 7).    The Scottish inshorevessels were on the whole reasonably prosperous in 1955, the largerones making a profit with subsidy of about  400 per vessel;   the smallerones and the English vessels fared less well.    On the debit side they now have to carry the 2d. cut and an increase in costs of about per cent.    But their gross earnings have improved by 10-20 per centso far this year.    On the other hand the future course of prices isunpredictable, the crews get less than trawler crews, vessels in the highlands and outlying areas are not doing very well and there is a wide variation between different ports providing ample material forpleading hard cases.    On strict merit we would accept the Treasury&apos;view that no increase is justified.     But, since this is likely to meet with strong criticism from Government supporters, which would be all themore difficult to answer if the near and middle-water vessels were toreceive increased subsidy, we ask the Cabinet to decide.    Thealternative is to restore the 2d. cut.    Similar treatment would have tobe accorded to motor seiners over 70 ft.13.     The motor trawlers are at present making losses (apart fromthe largest vessels) and their costs have risen this year though not assharply as those of the coal-burners.    There is no reason to suppose that they cannot ultimately become self-supporting but we are agreedupon a moderate increase in their subsidy overall with some re-distribution between classes.Cost14.     (a)    The cost of the subsidy at current rates is  2.3 millions per annum.(b) If the steam vessel subsidy is geared to a run-out of150 vessels, the motor trawlers get the increase we have proposed,crews settled on the &quot;gross&quot; are excluded and the inshore subsidy isunchanged, the total cost will be increased by about  550, 000 per annum.(c) A run-out of 80 instead of 150 vessels would increase thesubsidy by a further  400, 000 per annum.(d) Restoration of the 2d. cut in the inshore (and seiner)subsidy would cost a further  160, 000 per annum.The TreasuryJs proposals therefore mean a subsidy costingin total about  2, 85 millions.    The most generous of the alternativeswould cost  3.4 millions.Summary15.     (l)    We seek authority to introduce legislation next session to give statutory cover for the subsidyuntil 1963.
(2)    We seek a decision whether the near and middle -water steam fleet should be allowed to run out ata rate of 00 or 150 vessels a year in 1956-57.(3)    We ask our colleagues to agree that crews settledon the &quot;gross&quot; should be excluded from anyfurther share in subsidy increases.(4)    We seek a decision whether the subsidy to inshorevessels (including motor seiners) should beincreased by 2d. per stone or remain unchanged.G.LL. -G.J.S.D.H.A.19th June, 1956

</content>
</cab>
