<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/34 images: 388-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  April 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)89th Conclusions.Copy No.  43TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 89  (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, April 12, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The    Right    hon. the Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The  Most  Hon.   the  Marquess of zetland,   Secretary  of   State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma (Items 10 and 11).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of State,Foreign Office (Items 1-9).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-8).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Sir  Horace J.  Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-8).General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-8).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[21143]
WAR CABINET 89  (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      The Air Situation.........      .........     289R.A.F. activity.Air attack on Stavanger aerodrome.Eeconnaissance of North-West Germany.2      The Naval Situation...............      ...     289Action by the Fleet Air Arm : Trondhjem.Enemy air attack on the fleet: H.M.S. Eclipse.Naval activity.Norwegian naval success.Disposition of enemy heavy ships.Occupation of the Faroe Islands.3      Operation &apos;&apos; Rupert &quot;..................    2904      The Military Situation        ...      .........      ...    290German troop movements.5      Sweden......       .......    ...      ...      ...      ...    291Attitude of Swedish Government.Swedish oil stocks.Allied mission to Sweden.Swedish gold reserves.6      Italy     .........................     292Probable intentions.7      U.S.S.R. .....................    293Probable intentions.8      Western Front.....................     293Attitude of Belgium.German attitude to the Netherlands.9     Poland......      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...    293Conduct of German authorities in German-occupied territory.Proposed three-Power declaration.10      India    ......      ......      ...      ...      ...      ...    294Constitutional questions.11      The Dominions.....................     296Proposal for an Imperial War Conference.12      The Press.....................    297.. False reports of events in Scandinavia. .
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 2.)R.A.F. activity.Air attack onStavangeraerodrome.reconnaissance of North-west germany.1. The Secretary of State for Air said that two Blenheimson a reconnaissance of Wilhelmsbaven at dawn the previous day hadbombed two auxiliary vessels north of Norderney without result.Six Hampdens had been sent off at noon to attack enemywarships at christians and (south), but had been unable to reach theNorwegian coast owing to lack of cloud cover.In the evening twenty-three Whitleys had taken off to attackenemy shipping between Kiel and Oslo. Preliminary reports wereto the effect that one large merchant vessel in the Great Belt hadbeen bombed, a great explosion had taken place, and the ship haddisappeared. Other ships had been attacked, but without knownresult. One aircraft had been lost. Twenty Hampdens had leftlater on the same task, but reports of their action had not yet beenreceived.Six Wellingtons, escorted by two Blenheim fighters, had made an attack on Stavanger aerodrome the evening before. the aerodrome had been hit with bombs, though the runway had notbeen damaged, and about sixty enemy aircraft on the aerodrome hadbeen raked with machine-gun fire.   One aircraft had been lost.The Prime Minister enquired whether incendiary bombs hadbeen used in this raid. He would have thought they would havebeen particularly valuable for setting on fire aircraft and hangars.The Chief of the Air Staff said that he would make enquiries on this point. He believed that high-explosive bombs had been usedwith the object of damaging the aerodrome.Continuing, the Secretary of State for Air said that a numberof patrols had been sent off by Fighter Command, but there hadbeen no interceptions. A Hudson aircraft had shot down aDornier 18 Flying Boat, and a Blenheim had severely damagedanother one.At 5-45 a.m. that morning a Hudson on reconnaissance hadsighted a battle cruiser and a cruiser, steering South-East, 45 miles west of Lister Light. Five and a half squadrons had been dispatched to attack these ships.There had been no engagements in France, but a reconnaissance aircraft, which had been sent over North-West Germany in the areaCleves-Munchen-Gladbach, had reported no abnormal activity onthe roads or railways, which had been clearly visible.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 3.)Action by theFleet Air Arm:Trondhjem.2. The First Lord of the Admiralty gave the War Cabinetinformation about the dispositions of the Fleet. aircraft from H.M.S. Furious had attacked German warshipsoff Trondhjem. The only enemy warships present consisted of oneBrummer class cruiser (training ship), one destroyer and onesubmarine. One bomb was believed to have hit the destroyer.Torpedoes had been dropped, but the ships were lying in suchshallow water that the torpedoes had hit the bottom before reaching the ships.Enemy air attack on theFleet: H.M.S.Eclipse.In the course of the afternoon the Fleet had been bombed and h.M.S. Eclipse, a destroyer, had been hit in the engine room. she had been taken in tow.[21143]b 2
Naval activity. H.M.S. Isis and Ilex, destroyers, had examined the Fjordsoutside Trondhjem. They had been fired on ineffectively by shore batteries off Trondhjem Fjord and H.M.S. Isis had been bombedwithout result.H.M.S. Penelope, which had been hunting for german merchant ships believed to be trying to enter Vest Fjord, had goneaground off Fleinver. She had been later towed off and was proceeding to Shell Fjord.   One boiler room was flooded.Cruisers and destroyers were starting a systematic searchthrough the Norwegian Leads for enemy ships.The submarines operating in the Kattegat reported very strong-anti-submarine patrols and air activity. H.M.S. Triad hadtorpedoed a 4,000-ton German steamer south of Oslo Fjord. Onesubmarine which had been attacked with 79 depth charges, and had now used all her torpedoes, was returning home.Norwegian A Norwegian warship had sunk a 10,000 ton German tanker in naval success.    Tannholm Fjord.   This tanker, which was full of oil, had probably been trying to reach Narvik.Dispositions of A   report  had  been  received   from   Stockholm   that   theenemy heavy A admiral Scheer, listing heavily, had been 20 miles west of the Skawships. at 10 a.m. on 11th April, steering East, escorted by a tug and two destroyers. It was probable that the battle cruiser which had been sighted by a reconnaissance aircraft, as reported by the Secretaryof State for Air, was the one which had been damaged by H.M.S.Renown, since the other battle cruiser had been seen going homethrough the Kattegat the previous day. If this were so, our knowledge of the whereabouts of the enemy&apos;s big ships would be nearly complete, and we could operate more freely in consequence.There had been no enemy attacks on shipping, but H.M.S.Tartar had made a promising attack on a submarine near the orkneys.Occupation of Operations for the occupation of the Faroe Islands werethe Faroe proceeding.Islands.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Operation&quot;Rupert.&quot;(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 5.)The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 4.)German troop movements.3. The First Lord of the Admiralty gave the War Cabinetinformation of the progress of Operation &quot;RUPERT,&quot; and some discussion ensued. A detailed record is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.4. The Secretary of State for War informed the War Cabinetthat a new German Division had been identified on the Saar, andthat one Division had been moved to the Aachen area from theSouth.There were reports, but no definite identification, of reinforce-ments to the Baltic Coast.There had also been movements of troops to Southern poland and to East Austria.Reports had been received as to the likelihood of an earlyGerman attack on the Western Front; but so far there seemed tobe nothing very conclusive. The information was being collated atthe War Office, and he hoped that he would be able to give a reporton the situation to the War Cabinet that afternoon.
Sweden.Attitude ofSwedishGovernment.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 7.)Swedish oil stocks.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 1.)Allied mission to Sweden.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 1.)5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto the following Telegrams from His Majesty&apos;s Minister,Stockholm, both dated 11th April, 1940 : Telegram No, 199 DIPP. Mr. Mallet emphasised theimportance of Germany and not the Allies being the aggressoragainst Sweden. As Sweden had formally reaffirmed her neutrality, an Allied attack on Swedish territory or an Allieddemand on Sweden which took the form of some unneutralaction, might force her on to the German side even thoughher sympathies were overwhelmingly pro-Ally.Telegram No. 201. Mr. Mallet reported that the swedish government had made preparations for the destruction of theiroil stocks in the event of a German attack.The Foreign Secretary said that it seemed to him most unlikely that sweden would succeed in maintaining her neutrality; thepossibilities were : (i) that she would be attacked by Germany, in which case weshould be able to help her and also to gain assistancefrom her at Narvik;(ii) that pressure by Germany on Sweden to grant facilities of various kinds might become so extreme as to lead her to open resistance in which case also we should haveher on our side;(iii) that Germany&apos;s pressure might become so strong that sweden would prefer to accept German protection asDenmark had done; in that case our hands would be free in dealing with her.In any case it was very important that the onus for any aggressionshould rest upon Germany and not upon us.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that there was afurther alternative; the Germans might abstain from making a comprehensive series of demands, preferring to put forward requestssingly, with the result that if she acceded to Germany&apos;s demands,Sweden would find herself on a slippery slope.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed; much would depend upon the effectiveness of the arrangements made by theGermans to secure their communications with Norway.The Secretary of State for War said that M. Bohemann had expressed to him the view that Sweden would resist demands byGermany that she should make either her ports or her railway system available to Germany for military purposes. It was essential, therefore, to do everything possible to render critical the communications between Germany and Oslo.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he hadacceded to a request by the French Government for the deletionfrom the instructions to the Allied Mission of the sentence statingthat &quot; so long as Sweden is not involved in war, the Allies willrespect her independence and integrity.&quot; The French government thought that these words were objectionable in that they might encourage Sweden to adopt a passive role. He had notified this change in the instructions to General Lewin at Perth, and had asked him to inform his French colleague.It had finally been arranged that the Mission should proceed in two aircraft, each carrying one British and one French memberof the Mission. The British aircraft had taken off at 12-40 a.m.that morning, having on board General Lewin and one of theFrench members of the Mission. The French machine had beenfound to be unserviceable; and Admiral Evans and the other FrenchOfficer were still at Perth. They would, however, in any case startthat evening.   Late the previous day he had sent a telegram to
Mr. Mallet, informing him that the arrival of the Mission mightbe delayed and instructing him that, if it had not arrived by 12 noonthat day (12th April, 1940), he was at once to get into touch withhis French colleague, and that they were then jointly to make a preliminary communication to the Swedish Government on the linesof the fuller communication which would be made by the Missionon its arrival.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to telegramNo. 260 DIPP, dated the 11th April, 1940, from His Majesty&quot;minister, Helsinki, giving particulars of four demands which,according to the information of Field-Marshal Mannerheim, theGerman Government had early that day made to Sweden. It was important that the Mission on arrival in Stockholm should be in aposition to inform the Swedish Government of the views of theAllies on such questions.The Prime Minister suggested that the information communi-cated by Field-Marshal Mannerheim should be conveyed to AdmiralEvans while he was still in Perth, and that he should be informedthat the Allies desired Sweden to resist demands of this kind.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs undertook tocommunicate with Admiral Evans in this sense. He would alsoinform Mr. Mallet.Swedish gold The Foreign Secretary said that he had informed Mr. Malletreserves. that instructions had been given by the Treasury to Admiral Evanspersonally on the subject of the need for removing the Swedish gold reserves to a place of safety.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.Italy.probable intentions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 8.)6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto the following telegrams bearing upon the probable intentions ofthe Italian Government : Telegram, unnumbered, dated the 11th April,  1940, fromA thens.The Greek Chief of Staff had stated that the GreekMilitary Attache in Rome had reported a strong rumour from german sources of an intention by Italy to attack Corfu in thenear future. The Chief of Staff discredited this information,which he had also received from other sources. He consideredthat the Italian troops in Albania were well below offensivestrength. He had no information from Italy to support therumours of an Italian expedition against Greece.Telegram No. 115, dated the 11th April, 1940, from Belgrade.The Yugoslav General Staff stated that there had been considerable Italian naval activity that morning off Corfu.They were investigating reports of Italian troop movementsfrom Bari to Zara and Albania, and had promised to provide further information that evening.Telegram No. 144 DIPP, dated the 11th April, 1940, fromMadrid.This contained a circumstantial report of a projectedItalian-Spanish attack on Gibraltar.
U.S.S.R.probable intentions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 77thConclusions,Minute 7.)7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto telegram No. 359, dated the 12th April, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;minister, Rome, reporting that, from a remark inadvertentlydropped that evening to the Military Attache from an individualwell placed in Italian Government circles, it seemed possible thatthe Soviet Fleet was about to co-operate with the Germans in theKattegat.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.CWestern Front.Attitude ofBelgium.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 10.)German atti-tude to theNetherlands.8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said thatM. Daladier had now concurred in the undertaking which general gamelin and M. Reynaud had previously agreed might be given tothe Belgian Government that, if Belgium were invaded, the allies would take up a more advanced position than had previously been contemplated (telegram No. 101 from Paris). The foreign secretary proposed to instruct Sir Lancelot Oliphant to inform theBelgian Government that he expected to receive further instructions on the subject of Allied aid to Belgium, but that in the meanwhilehe was authorised, in the name of the British and French Govern-ments, to give the foregoing answer to the question previously put to him by M. Spaak.The Foreign Secretary drew attention to an unnumbered secrettelegram, elated the 11th April, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;s represen-tative, Berne. The main point of the telegram was that Herr Bibra,the German Counsellor, who in previous scares had always told the netherland Charge d&apos;Affaires that he had nothing to worry about,as there would be no attack on the Netherlands, now in fact believeda German attack was imminent. Herr Bibra gave the impression that the German leaders were desperate on account of inaction andwere prepared to hit out anywhere. Norway had been the first tobe attacked, because the Germans were in desperate need ofassuring their supplies of iron ore. It was added that Herr Bibrahad recently returned from Berlin.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Poland.Conduct ofGermanauthorities inGerman-occupied territory.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 37thConclusions,Minute 9.)ProposedThree-power declaration.9. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (G.) (40) 101).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs explained that thePolish and French Governments had submitted a revised draft ofthe proposed Three-Power Declaration, an English translation ofwhich was given in the Annex to his Memorandum, together withthe earlier draft prepared after consultation with the Dominions.The only changes in the Polish redraft were in paragraphs 4and 5.Paragraph 4. The changes proposed were unexception-able subject to the substitution (for the sake of accuracy) ofthe phrase &quot; in Polish territory&quot; for &quot;territory which hasalways been Polish.&quot; No difficulty was anticipated on this score.Paragraph 5. The two amendments proposed wereunobjectionable and could be accepted.The Polish Government had intimated that they regarded the last paragraph as a statement of principle and not a contractualobligation, and that they would not base any claim upon it vis-a-visourselves or the French at some later date. He suggested that weshould obtain a formal assurance from the Polish Government tothis affect before the Declaration was issued.
The War Cabinet-Approved  the Polish-French redraft of the proposedThree-Power Declaration regarding the conduct of theGerman authorities in Poland, subject to : (i) the amendment suggested by the Foreign secretary in paragraph 4;(ii) the Polish Government giving an assurance on thelines suggested by the Foreign Secretary in regardto the interpretation of paragraph 5.India.constitutional questions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 69thConclusions,Minute 10.)10. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for India (W.P. (G.) (40) 96).The Secretary of State for India recalled that on the15th March the War Cabinet had considered, but had deferred adecision on the proposals which he had submitted with a view toeasing the deadlock in India (W.P. (G.) (40) 73). It had been thought desirable on that occasion to await a further appreciation by the Viceroy of the situation after the meetings of Congress atRamgarh on the 20th March, and of the All-India Moslem Leagueat Lahore on the 24th March. The Viceroy&apos;s telegram of 6th April,containing a statement of his views, had now been circulated as appendix A to W.P. (G.) (40) 96.The Secretary of State drew attention to the followingpoints : (1) The Viceroy maintained his recommendation though perhaps somewhat less decisively for a policy of&quot;lying back,&quot; i.e., that neither he nor His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should make any attempt, at present at all events, to make a positive contribution towards relieving the situation which had resulted from the action of theCongress, but should await developments.(2) The Moslem League&apos;s adoption of a policy of Partition hadintroduced a new and disturbing feature into thesituation.(3) The following Thursday, the 18th April, was the date fixed for the Debates in both Houses of Parliament on theMotions required to legalise the continuance in forcebeyond the end of the present month of the proclamations under which the Governors of sevenProvinces were at present exercising their powers.The Secretary of State said that he agreed with the Viceroythat, as matters now stood, no good purpose was likely to be servedat present by the adoption of a plan such as that advocated inAppendix C to WP. (G.) (40) 73. He was anxious, however, thathe should not be understood to have changed his view that, when thetime was ripe, a solution on the lines of that Appendix wouldrequire serious consideration.He intended to cover the following points in his speech in theHouse of Lords : (i) The present difficult position had arisen as a result of differences between Indians. We were, as always,anxious to assist in composing such differences, but thiswas a task which was primarily for Indians themselves.(ii) He was unable to give his blessing to the Moslem League&apos;snew policy of Partition. If carried into effect, it wouldannul in a moment the constructive work of many years.Nevertheless, he found himself unable to imagine any british Parliament seeking to impose on the Indian-Moslem community a form of Constitution under which that community declared it to be impossible that theyshould live.
(iii) It was better that the disputants should have further timefor reflection upon the course which their leaders seemedto be in process of setting for them before any new factorwas introduced into the situation.(iv) His Majesty&apos;s Government had already given India adefinite assurance that, at the end of the war, represen-tatives of all Indian interests (not of one interest only)would be taken into consultation, with a view to agreement being reached on the directions in which the1935 settlement would then require to be revised. Tothat extent we had admitted the reasonableness of the-claim that Indians should have a predominant say in theform of the Constitution under which they would live,(v) Our admission of that claim must, however, be a qualifiedadmission. There were valid reasons on account ofwhich we were unable to dissociate ourselves from theframing of the future Constitution of India. Thosereasons included : (a) our vital interests in certain matters, particularlyDefence;(b) our obligation to see justice done to the variouscommunities;(c) our relations with the Princes.The First Lord of the A. dmiralty said that he agreed with therecommendations of the Secretary of State for India, although heapproached the matter from a somewhat different angle. His view was that the awakening of a new spirit of self-reliance and self-assertiveness on the part of the different communities, of which the moslem League&apos;s resolution was a sign, constituted a hopefuldevelopment. He was also glad that the seven Provinces were tocontinue to be ruled by their Governors; that meant a continuanceof honest and efficient government. It was on lines such as thesethat we might hope to see tranquillity preserved in India.He noticed with pleasure that the Secretary of State proposedto make a sympathetic reference to the difficulties of the IndianMoslems.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he also was inagreement with the proposals in W.P. (G.) (40) 96. He was,however, a little apprehensive as to the observations which theSecretary of State for India proposed to make in the House of Lordsas recorded under (iv) above, although he realised that the Secretaryof State had not been using in the War Cabinet the precise words which he would use in the House of Lords.The Chancellor thought that, in their speeches next Thursday,the representatives of His Majesty&apos;s Government should not putforward any new or additional constitutional proposal or declara-tion of policy, nor should words be used which could possibly be interpreted in such a sense. The present was emphatically not thetime for any advances in that direction.There was general agreement both with the recommendationsof the Secretary of State for India and with the stipulation madeby the Chancellor of the Exchequer. /The War Cabinet (i) Approved generally the recommendations contained in w.P. (G.) (40) 96&quot;, on the understanding that the Govern-ment spokesmen would be careful to avoid the use oflanguage which could in any way give colour tosuggestions that the Government were making any new or additional Constitutional proposal or declaration ofpolicy.[21143] c
(ii) Invited the Secretary of State for India to take the Leadersof the Liberal and Labour Oppositions into privateconsultation before the Parliamentary debates of thefollowing week.The Dominions. 11. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs (W.P. (G.) (40) 95) pro-reference: posing that the Dominion Prime Ministers should be invited tow.M. (39) 54th  attend an Imperial War Conference in the late summer of 1940.Conclusions,Minute 12.) The Secretary of State for the Dominions said that the reasonsProposals for for this proposal were set out in his Memorandum. The Primean Imperial Minister had suggested some valuable improvements in the draftWar Conference, telegram, with which he need not trouble the Wax Cabinet. Hewas sure that General Smuts would wish to come, and he wouldprobably be able to do so, as the political situation in South Africawas improving and Parliament would shortly be rising.Mr. Menzies would certainly wish to come, too, but there was to bea General Election in Australia in the summer, and it was not clearwhom he could leave in charge in his absence. Mr. Mackenzie King,though it would be quite easy for him to a,ttend, was the most likelyto make difficulties; at the time when the autumn meeting ofDominion Ministers was being arranged he had shown considerablesuspicion and had talked of the Canadian Government having been forced in the last war into acceptance of a policy which they did not really approve.The Prime Minister said that he thought a conference, such as was proposed, would be extremely valuable, and he very much hopedthat the War Cabinet would approve the suggestion. It was important that it should be called an Imperial War Conference, andnot a Cabinet.The Secretary of State for India said that, if invitations were sent to the Dominion Prime Ministers, he would certainly wish that a similar invitation should be conveyed to the Governmentof India. If Southern Rhodesia were to be invited to send an observer, he hoped that a similar invitation would be sent to Burma.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that, in viewof the great help that they were giving us, he would propose thatan invitation should be sent to the Prime Minister of SouthernRhodesia.The War Cabinet (i) Approved the proposal in W.P. (G.) (40) 95 that invitations to an Imperial War Conference should be sent to thePrime Ministers of Canada, Australia, New zealand and South Africa, and that the Prime Minister ofSouthern Rhodesia should be invited to attend as an observer.(ii) Agreed that the Government of India should be invitedto send a suitable representative to the Conference, andthat the Government of Burma should be invited to sendan observer.
The Press.False reports ofevents in scandinavia.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 88thConclusions,Minute 13.)12. The Lord Privy Seal said that the previous day the WarCabinet had invited him, in consultation with the Minister ofInformation, to see representatives of the Press. As a result of enquiries which he had made, he had been informed as follows : A large number of enquiries from the Press had come into theMinistry of Information throughout the night in regard to the alleged recapture by the British of&apos; Bergen and Trondhjem.Enquiries made of the Admiralty had resulted in the statement that these reports could not be confirmed. The Lord Privy Sealfelt that, on the basis of this information, he was not in a positionto make strong representations to the Press in regard to thisparticular episode.In the discussion which ensued, the view was very generallyexpressed that it would be most undesirable that there should beany repetition of publication in the Press of reports of Britishsuccesses which were, in fact, entirely without foundation. It wassuggested that it was most desirable that the Ministry ofInformation should have someone in each Service Department inorder that they might obtain guidance as to what line they shouldtake when they received such reports.On the other hand, the view was put forward that it was mostimportant that no Government Department should assume respon-sibility for checking every wild rumour which Press correspondentsmight get hold of.The Prime Minister suggested that it might well be desirableto issue a public statement on the following lines : (1) There is no compulsory censorship of the Press.(2) The Press are responsible for the news which they collectand for the prominence which they give it.(3) The Press should be able, on application to the Ministryof Information, to. obtain guidance as to how they should deal with particular items of news reported to them inthe light of the information available.(4) Notwithstanding   (3),   the  newspapers  remain responsible for the news which they publish.directlyReference was also made to the publication of news by theBritish Broadcasting Corporation, and it was generally agreedthat it might be desirable that measures should be taken to ensurean improvement in the style and content of the News Bulletinsand, possibly also the talks, included in the programmes of theB.B.C.The War Cabinet Invited the Lord Privy Seal, in co-operation with theMinister of Information, to bring before the military co-operation-ordination Committee, at an early date, the questionwhether any modifications were called for in the arrange-ments in force in the Service Departments for providing the Ministry of Information with the necessary material for dealing with Press enquiries and for giving guidance to the Press.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,April 12, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
