<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/48/0 images: 16-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty-s. government   4 .19Printed for the Cabinet, November 1951The circulation of this papeiy hasjj&amp;jn^ strictly limited.   It $issued- &apos;*&amp;for the personal use of&quot;.TOP SECRET .       *        &apos;        . *-      -   v . Copy No.C. (51) 2    :     //-,. \  - . .&apos;    &apos;*    -     -     .     . . ^1st November, 1951 &apos; V   -CABINETTHE KINGS SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF parliament note by the Minister of health i circulate herewith, for consideration by the Cabinet, a draft of The King&apos;sSpeech on the Opening of Parliament, which has been prepared by the Committeeon The King&apos;s Speech.2. The Committee have decided to omit a number of references to specific measures which were in the first draft considered by them or were suggested by departments.  The principal measures so deleted were the following:  (a) The review of the system of local Government and establishment of aBoundary Commission.(b) The Bill to modernise Customs and Excise legislation.\c) The abolition of centralised purchase of raw cotton.(d) The improvement of the salaries of County Court judges and of comparablejudicial officers. -(e) The extension of diplomatic privilege to High Commissioners.(/) The Industrial Injuries Amendment Bill.(g) The preservation of historic houses.3. The Committee feel that some of these measures require examination by ministers and decisions of policy which cannot be taken at once, while others seeminappropriate for inclusion in a Speech which lays primary emphasis on the graveeconomic situation. They have, therefore, decided to make very few references, to legislation in the Speech and to leave most of the Bills which may be subsequentlyproceeded with to be covered by the general paragraph (No. 27) promising other legislation.. - -    -   - ^     H. C. C.Ministry of Health,;    Savile Row, W. 1,\st November, 1951.41398
annex the kings SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF parliament my Lords and Members of the House of commons I. It is a matter of sincere regret to Me a^4 I cannot address you in person on this Opening of a new Parliament. I have been sustained and strengthenedthrough My illness by the prayers and the sympathy of all. My peoples.2. It has given Me great satisfaction that My elder daughter, accompaniedby her husband, has been able to undertake her projected journey to Canada andthe United States of America, and I have been deeply moved by the great warmthof the reception accorded b^th to her and to the Duke of Edinburgh.3. The Queen and I are greatly touched by the sympathy and understandingshown by My peoples in Australia, New Zealand and Ceylon on learning that Wehad, for the second time, been prevented by My illness from carrying out Our plan to visit them. Happily My elder daughter and her husband will make this journeyin Our stead; and they eagerly look forward to their visit to these and other commonwealth countries through which they will pass in the course of theirjourney.4. My Ministers will ever be anxious to maintain the close ties of friendship and understanding which so happily exist between the widely varied peoples of theEmpire-and Commonwealth^5. My Government will make it their first duty to ensure the safety of our country and, in co-operation with the other countries of the Commonwealth, theUnited States of America and our European partners, will share in the commoneffort to build a more peaceful and prosperous world. They will take such measures as are necessary to strengthen our defences in both trained men and equipment,to re-establish the Home Guard and to develop Civil Defence.6. My Government will maintain this country&apos;s support for the united nations as an instrument for international co-operation and for the maintenanceof world peace and security. They will play their part in the efforts to re-establishpeace in Korea [and to repair the devastation caused by the hostilities in thatcountry]. - - . -: 7. My Ministers will make every effort to find a solution of the difficulties that have arisen in connection with the oil industry in Ipdn.8. My Government have noted with deep regret the declaration of theEgyptian Government that they regard the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty of Alliance of1936 and the Sudan Condominium Agreements of 1899 as abrogated. my government consider this action illegal and without validity. They are resolved topress ahead, in conjunction with the Governments of the United States, France and turkey, with their proposals for joint defence arrangements in the Middle East.In the meantime they intend fully to maintain their position in the Canal Zone underthe terms of the 1936 Treaty.9. The- text of the Japanese Peace Treaty signed at San Francisco on 8thSeptember will be presented to you before ratification. Legislation will beintroduced to give effect to certain provisions of the Treaty.10. My Government will introduce legislation to regulate the position of commonwealth and foreign armed forces who are stationed in this country.Members of the House of CommonsII. The estimates for the public services will be laid before you.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons12. First steps will be taken to implement the plans of my Ministers for themanagement of Scottish affairs..13. I have approved new arrangements which will bring added strength tothe counsels of My Government relative to the special problems and interests of wales. . -    -      - -----------*      -
14. My Government&apos;view with serious concern the economic situation ofthe country. The recent deterioration in the balance of payments causes increasinganxiety and must be urgently remedied in order to restore the fullest confidence in the purchasing power of the pound, so that we may continue to be able toobtain from overseas the supplies necessary to maintain employment and an increasingly high level of production. The measures to this end must includedrastic action to reduce the growing inflation in our economy, which threatens themaintenance of our defence programme anda which, if unchecked, must cause a continuing, rise in the cost of living. My Government regard this problem asovershadowing all other domestic matters. They are giving it urgent examination. and will announce their conclusions and make proposals to Parliament in theimmediate future. While pressing on with domestic remedies, including a searchingenquiry into Government expenditure with a view to reducing it wherever possible,they will also invite the other Governments of the Commonwealth to confertogether on action which should be taken in concert to remedy the adverse balanceof payments.15, My Government will seek to promote flexibility in those industries which remain under public management and to stimulate free enterprise by giving it a fuller share in our economic activity. They will be mindful of the great demands on our productive capacity, and will consider all methods for creating that sense ofpartnership between management and workers on which industrial peace and ahigher level of productivity must depend..16. My Government view with concern the serious shortage of labour, par-ticularly of skilled labour, which has handicapped production in a number of essential industries. They will review, in consultation with representatives ofthose concerned, the possibilities of making available more labour for those industries and of ensuring the most efficient use of the existing labour force.17. A Bill will be placed before you to annul the Iron and Steel Act v/ith aview to the reorganisation of the industry under free enterprise, but with anadequate measure of public supervision.18. Proposals will be introduced to facilitate the extension of private road haulage activities.19. A measure will be laid before you for strengthening and widening theactivities of the Monopolies Commission.20. A Bill will be laid before you to re-introduce in the next Parliamentrepresentation of the Universities in the House of Commons. It will provide forthe exercise of one vote only by each voter.21. You will be asked to authorise for a period the continuation in force ofcertain emergency enactments and defence regulations which are due to expirenext month, but My Ministers will examine these provisions with the object ofembodying as many as possible of those which must remain in force in legislationrequiring annual renewal by Parliament.22.  My Government will by every means in their power stimulate the building of new houses for My people and in doing so they will aim to use to the efullest extent both public and private enterprise.  Their housing policy will have regard&quot;to the desire of many people to own their homes and to the special needs of the elderly.[23. My Ministers will review the whole position of pensioners, including war pensioners, as circumstances permit.]     __________.___________&apos;............______....^1________.....24. My Government will protect the social services by every means in their power and will strive to promote economy while at the same time ensuring theutmost efficiency.25. My Ministers will take all possible steps to encourage production of foodby the basic industries of agriculture, horticulture and fisheries.26.. Further progress will be made with the consolidation of the statute law..27.  Other measures will be laid before you in due course.. I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon your counsels.



</content>
</cab>
