<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/48/0 images: 92-96</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY? GOVERNMENT65Printed for the Cabinet.  November 1951CONFIDENTIALC. (51) 1720th November, 1951Copy No. 28CABINETBREVITYNote by the Prime Minister_______9Official papers are too long and too diffuse. In 1940 I called for brevity.Evidently I must do so again. I ask my colleagues to read what I wrote then (it is reproduced overleaf) and to make my wishes known to their staffs.I also invite attention to the Foreign Secretary&apos;s recent despatch to Heads ofMissions about the length of telegrams.w. s. c.10, Downing Street, S.W.1,20th November, 1951.
W.P. (G) (40) 211     9th August, 1940.:. To do pur work, we all have to read a mass of papers. Nearly all of thenyirefar too long. This wastes time, while energy has to be spent in looking for theessential points.     &quot;       &apos;        &apos; &quot;  *        &apos;     . ..   I ask my colleagues and their staffs to see to it that thee Reports are shorter.ii) The aim should be Reports which set Out the main points in a series of short, crisp paragraphs.(ii) If a Report relies on detailed analysis of some complicated factors, or on.. statistics, these should be set out in an Appendix.(iii) Often the occasion is best met by submitting not a full-dress Report, butan Aide-memoire consisting of headings only, which can be expanded, orally if needed.(iv) Let us have an end of such phrases as these: &quot; It is also of importanceto bear in mind the following considerations ... .&quot;, or &quot; consideration should be given to the possibility of carrying into effect . . . .&quot; Mostof these woolly phrases are mere padding which can be left outaltogether, or replaced by a single word. Let us not shrink from using the short expressive phrase, even if it is conversational.Reports drawn up on the lines I propose may at first seem rough as comparedwith the flat surface of officialese jargon. But the saving in time will be great, whilethe discipline of setting out the real points concisely will prove an aid to clearerthinking.
[ YT 111/14 ]Foreign Secretary&apos;s Despatch of 7th November, 1951Sir,On my return to the Foreign Office I have remarked on thelength of some of the telegrams sent to me by Heads of Missions.I know that you have been trying to reduce the number and lengthof telegrams sent by you to the Foreign Office but many telegramsare still too long.2. If I am to read your telegrams you must keep them short.I make this appeal most earnestly to you all.I am, with great truth and regard,Sir,Your obedient Servant,ANTHONY EDEN.



</content>
</cab>
