<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/48/0 images: 152-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document -IS ^FKE P-ROFER-T-Y OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S -GOVERNMENT-)/SEC RET .        . . . &apos; &apos;     &apos; -c.&amp;.(5i) 26 . - COPY NO.l T&quot;-^&quot;&quot;v        -       .     -    fjOTH NOVEMBER, 1^51 &quot;&apos;t- CABINET   * &apos;    &quot;THE SITUATION IN MALAYAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the colonies was invited (C. C. (51) 5th Conclusions, Minute 3) to submit amemorandum on the situation in Malaya.   I have recently received an appreciation by the retiring Director of Operations, Lieutenants-general sir Harold Briggs.   This was considered by the British defence -ordination Committee (Far East) and I attach in Annex I a summaryof their conclusions.A note on the present situation prepared in the Colonial Office is in annex II; and a statement of the forces engaged in Malaya and the cost oftheir maintenance in Annex III.While in Malaya I propose to pay particular attention to the followingaspects of the situation: -(a) How to reassure the planters and miners of our determination and ability to support them by all means in our power, and tobring the anti-Communist campaign to a successful conclusion.(b) How to secure&apos; the active co-operation of the Chinese, if necessary.    by a more forceful policy towards those who fail to &quot;come off- -  the fence&quot;.(c) How to settle disagreements between the military and police authorities.   This may involve the replacement of theCommissioner of Police..(d)        How to improve the organisation and training of the police force.(e)        Who should succeed Sir Henry Gurney as High Commissioner forthe Federation of Malaya and Mr. Malcolm MacDonald as.Commissioner-General, South East Asia.v.: (f) How the division of responsibilities between the variousauthorities could be improved.I will, of course, report fully to my colleagues on my return from- Malaya, .-&apos; &apos;;;&apos;\/-/&apos;-&quot; - -O.L.Colonial Office, S.W.I., ..20TH NOVEMBER, 1951.. -ft - -
v- .106CONCLUSIONS OF THE BRITISH DEFENCE CO-ORDINATION&quot;&quot;      &apos;     &apos;        &quot;    COMMITTEE (FAR EAST) &apos; &quot;&quot;-  -(Telegram dated 15th November, 1951)1,        Our main conclusions are:-(a) Although the Briggs Plan is fundamentally sound and has achieved a certain measure of success, the Communist hold on Malayais as strong, if not stronger, today than it ever has been.This fact must be faced.(b) The crux of the problem ic the winning of the confidence and loyalty of the bulk of the Chinese population to an extent.   that they are willing to join with us actively in the fight againstCommunist terrorism.-(c) Confidence of the Chinese generally will not be gained until they feel safe from internal Communist pressure and externalChinese attack.(d) Confidence of the Chinese in their safety from internalCommunist pressure will only be engendered if policeefficiency is improved.(e) We must take every necessary step to organise and trainsufficient Chinese as settlement guards, police, members ofjungle squads, etc.2.        The first priority is the reorganisation and build up of the police. force.  During this time, the ring must be held by the army, for whichpurpose it is assumed that no reduction in present strength will be made.3.        The action required to be pressed forward in Malaya includes;(a) The reorganisation of the police,(b) . Expansion of the Chinese resettlement guards and the formationof the Chinese element of the police force.(c) Completion of the revision of the citizenship constitution.;(d) ,      Action to associate the Chinese with local government.(e) Improvement of conditions in the settlements..(f) Expansion of Chinese Affairs Department at the centre and inthe field.4.        Action in which we press for the assistance of the United Kingdom.(a)        Selection and provision of the best available technicaLadvice and. professional leadership to achieve reorganisation and build up ofthe police force and its specialist agencies.
(b) The provision of outstanding police lieutenants,(c) No reduction in the military forces at present in malaya.(d) Support for the build up of the Malaya Regiment,in particular, British officers.
AiMEX II&apos;     THB SITUATION IK MALAYA &apos;Memorandum by the Colonial office the enemy is the Malayan Corrmrunist Party, which isalmost exclusively Chinese.     The &quot;whole-time&quot; enemy force,operating in the jungle and highly elusive, is only a few thousand strong;   but there is an insidious and numorous .  .&apos;underground operating wherever there is a Chinese element inthe general population.     This underground powerfullyassists the main force   and by the intimidation and murder of peaceable   labourers and squatters is able to secure thesupplies, shelter and information which that force requires.The 500,000 Chinese squatters until recently living in.isolated areas, and without any form of police protectionor any form of settled Government, have been the main sourcefrom which the. Communists have been able to derive supplies.Almost equally vulnerable to Communist attacks has been the considerable number of estate labourers living outside anydefended perimeter,2. The intention of the Briggs Plan has been byisolating the regular bandit forces from the Chinese civilian population, to cut the enemy lines of communication, tobreak up the underground cells, and to force the enemy tofight harder for his very existence on ground of our ownchoosing.     These tasks are primarily the affair of theGovernment and its police-forces rather than of the military,and the military cannot be used in any decisive way untilthe enemy has been forced from his jungle fastness by lackof supplies and the police are able to provide the fullestinformation of enemy movements.     Some 350,000 squattershave now been resettled - in itself a considerable administrative achievement - and progress in regrouping estate labour has also been made.     The first stage of the Briggs Plan is thus nearing completion.     The immediate problem now is to   .ensure that the new settlements, which had to be put up inthe greatest haste are provided as a.matter of urgency notonly with adequate protection against direct attack and sub-versive infiltration but with fullest opportunities tobecome reasonably prosperous and contented communities, con-vinced of being much better off as the result of resettlementand willing, therefore, to give increasing and positive help to Government.     Unless this is done we may have done littlemore than present to the enemy an easy target for attack,infiltration and propaganda.     This is not an enemy to bedespised, and he has so far shown himself capable of matchingevery move of ours by a counter-move which, if unchecked, canvitiate the whole of our operations.3, Simultaneously with this consolidation of the resettlement operation, must come a new drive to bring more of the Chinese population actively on to our side.     Afternearly 3i years of warfare, we are still not within pros-pect of a definite break in the Communist ranks.   . Withoutactive co-operation from the Chinese - not only from theleaders but from people of all classes - we shall not beable to secure any rapid conclusion of the conflict.     Whilethe Malays, to whom a Communist victory would mean Chinesehegemony in Malaya, have cdme forward in their tens of thousands to fight the enemy, the Chinese - although theyhave &quot;been the main sufferers at the terrorists&apos; hands,having lost 1,200 civilians out of a total of 1,700 killed *-have made no comparable response.     The Malayan-ChineseAssociation has done excellent work, but its leaders are unlikely on present showing to rally the people openly behim
1.0.8- THS SITUATION IN MALAYA:Memorandum by the Colonial office the enemy is the Malayan Communist Party, which, isalmost exclusively Chinese.     The &quot;whole-time&quot; enemy force,operating in the jungle and highly elusive, is only a few thousand strong;   but there is an insidious and numerous .&quot;underground operating wherever there is a Chinese element in. the general population.     This underground powerfullyassists the main forco   and by the intimidation and murder of peaceable   labourers and squatters is able to secure thesupplies, shelter and information which that force requires.The 500,000 Chinese squatters until recently living inisolated areas, and without any form of police protectionor any form of settled Government, have been the main sourcefrom which the Communists have been ab?..e to derive supplies.Almost equally vulnerable to Communist attacks has been the considerable number of estate labourers living outside anydefended perimeter. . :2. The intention of the Briggs Plan has been byisolating the regular bandit forces from the Chinese civilian population, to cut the enemy lines of communication, tobreak up the underground cells, and to force the enemy tofight harder for his very existence on ground of our ownchoosing.     These tasks are primarily the affair of theGovernment and its police-forces rather than of the military,and the military cannot be used in any decisive way untilthe enemy has been forced from his jungle fastness by lackof supplies and the police are able to provide the fullestinformation of enemy movements.     Some 350,000 squattershave now been resettled - in itself a considerable administra-&apos; five achievement - and progress in regrouping estate labour. has also been made.     The first stage of the Briggs Plan is thus nearing completion.     The immediate problem now is toensure that the new settlements, which had to be put up inthe greatest haste are provided as a matter of Urgency notonly with adequate protection against direct attack and sub-versive infiltration but with fullest opportunities to &apos;   .become reasonably prosperous and contented cornmunities, con-vinced of being much better off as the result of resettlementand willing, therefore, to give increasing and positive help to Government.     Unless this is done we may have done littlemore than present to the enemy an easy target for attack,infiltration and propaganda.     This is not an enfemy to bedespised, and he has so far shown himself capable of matchingevery move of ours by a counter-move which, if unchecked, can Ivitiate the whole of our operations. [3.     &apos;       simultaneously with this consolidation of the resettlement operation, must come a new drive to bring more of the Chinese population actively on to our side.     Afternearly 3? years of warfare, we are still not within pros-      ipect of a definite break in the Communist ranks.  . Withoutactive co-operation from the Chinese - not only from the      - Ileaders but from people of all classes - we shall not beable to secure any rapid conclusion of the conflict.     While \the Malays, to whom a Communist victory would mean Chinesehegemony in Malaya, have come forward in their tens of thousands to fight the enemy, the Chinese - although theyhave been the main sufferers at the terrorists1 hands,having lost i,200 civilians out of a total of 1,700 killed - ;have made no comparable response.     The Malayan-ChineseAssociation has done excellent work, but its leaders are    -unlikely on present showing to rally the people openly behim
them.&apos;&apos;    The reasons for Chinese reluctance to show by deeds theirabhorrence of the terrorists are not far to seek;   they arise notonly from Chinese tradition and character, but from events out-side as well as inside Malaya.   Previous attempts to compelChinese co-operation have beon largely abortive, and it was feltthat a policy of sanctions against non-co-operators could not beadopted until we could offer those people a greater protection intheir towns and villages.   This we should now be able to do in greater measure, and though one may have considerable sympathy with the ordinary Chinese living in daily fear of Communist raclc-eteers and assassins, there well may be scope for a more activepolicy.   Some Chinese leaders do, in fact, now feel that theGovernment should increasingly issue instructions and enforce cony-compliance instead of relying on voluntary co-operation.   CertainChinese leaders have also set on foot an organisation working with-in the Chinese&apos; community itself, whose object would be to stimu-late a more positive reaction against Communism, and which willwcrlc in ways best suited to. the Chinese mentality.   The existence ofthis organisation is, at least for the present, of the hignestsecrecy.     The Malayan Authorities have already outlined certainmethods by which the desired objective may be furthered.     Itwill, however, be necessary that any measures adopted shouldnot be such as to give tho appearance of a bias against theChinese;   that the sympathy of the Chinese community should notbe alienated by unnecessary harshness;   and that the Chineseshould be convinced of our intention, and that of the othercommunities in Malaya, of admitting more freely to the rightsof Malayan citizenship those who show their loyalty.     Themain advantages of increased Chinese co-operation would be anincreased supply of.information and more recruits to theuniformed police forces.     It is difficult to police a country which is nearly half Chinese with a force which is 95$ Malay,and which cannot speak the language of the peoples it purportsto control.h* Annex III shows the cost in man-power and money of the malayan campaign.     Malaya&apos;s United States dollar earnings in1950 were $350,000,000 out of total sterling area earnings of$1,285,000,000, but rubber production has fallen substantially in the past year and some estates are now unworked because of.terrorist activity.     The vital replanting and maintenance is virtually at a standstill, and prospecting for tin was barelyresumed after the re-occupation of the country when it had tobe suspended because of the lack of law and order..    The presentoutput of tin cannot be maintained, let alone increased unless    r^&apos;prospecting is resumed and fresh reserves of ore discovered in     \the next year or two.     There has recently been an intensifica-tion of &quot;Communist attempts to break the economy of the country by large scale and brutal intimidation of labour.5. No one can foresee when the world situation may demanda reduction of the garrison, although in present circumstancessuch a move would be bound to have a most serious effect.     Thepolice force, which has undergone tremendous numerical expan-sion, is still far from adequate in organisation and training tomeet its full responsibilities, and until a great improvement  .has been effected the maintenance of military forces at theirpresent strength will be necessary.     The British Defence Co-ordination Committee consider that no further reduction in thetotal number of army units can be made before Spring, 1953, at   /the earliest.     Recently there have been acute differences ofopinion in Malaya regarding police policy, and the Director of   .Operations has now been given direct authority over policeadministration and training.     The Acting High Commissioner,with the agreement of the Commissioner-General, the Director of
Operations and the Army-Corjmiander-in-Chief has also recommendedthat the Commissioner of Police should be asked to resign.The Inspector General of Colonial Police will visit Malaya withthe Secretary of State and remain for some time to advise thelocal authorities on what measure of police reorganisation maybe necessary.6. Malay exasperation at the apparent inability of theChinese to help positively in countering the continuing high level of terrorists activity is liable to produce a dangerousstate of communal tension.     This is another reason why wemust strive to make the Chinese take an increasingly active.....part in fighting Communist terrorism.     Their help is essentialnot only to bring the campaign to a more rapid conclusion butalso to avoid serious communal disorders which,v/ould place afurther and grievous strain on the British forces.     Moreoverif the emergency were to end without the active co-operationof the Chinese, the hope of building, a single Malayan peoplemight never be realised.
- FORCES ENGAGED IN MALAYA &quot;The fighting forces currently engaged in Malaya (andforeseen reinforcements) are:-  t(1)-   7 British.infantry battalionav.. . - 1 8 Gurkha battalions   i &apos;      - &apos;   - ^  &apos;,   &apos;        3&apos;Colonial battalions - &apos;.(2) ;J2 Royal Armoured*Corps Regiments  -- (3)   4 battalions Malay Regiment V        &apos;&apos;*   . (5th battalion being raised) ..- &apos;    &apos;   Malayan Police Forces(h)   Malayan Scouts (h- Squadrons)(5)   10 R.A.F. Squadrons (111). aircraft)(6)   2 Royal Australian Air Force Squadrons(14 aircraft)(7)   1 Frigate, 6 Minesweepers and 2 Motor Launches.Further details are included in the Appendix. Additionalforces are being raised by the Malayan Government.2.   &apos;        The cost of the forces has been calculated on alternative bases:-(i) The cost of maintaining and operating the forcesincluding base forces and of recurring chargesbut excluding capital costs.(ii)   The extra cost involved in having these forcesengaged in operations.3.The estimated expenditure,in a full year is:-Cost of royal NavyArmy - United KingdomforcesOther forcesR. A. F. and R.A. A. F.Maintenance m.1.721.010.0( 0.9m. of extra cost m.0.if2,5.1.015.8 which i s borneby Australia)k.5
appendix the forces expected to be engaged in the Malayaemergency operations in 1952/53 are:-Royal WavyThird R. M. Commando Brigade   ... 120 officers2,000 other ranks1 Frigate .6 &quot;Algerine&quot; Minesweepers. 2 Seaward Defence Motor Launches&amp;E2SC12th Lancers \   .13/18th Hussars7 British Infantry battalions8 Gurkha Infantry battalionsMalaya Scouts2 K. A. R.  battalions) In relief of Third Commando1 Fiji battalion     ) Brigade which is due to be withdrawn next Spring.R. A. F.2 Day Fighter/Ground attacksquadrons2 Light Bomber squadrons3 Transport squadrons1 Flying Boat squadron1 Photographic Reconnaissancesquadron1 Air Observation Post squadronR.A. F. and W.R. A. F. strengthMalayan airmenAustralian Air Force1 Medium Bomber squadron1 Transport squadronMalayan Forces (forces raised as at30th September, 1951)h battalions Malay Regiment.23,000 Regular Police38,000 Special Constables175,000 part-time Auxiliary Police and Home Guard.k. It is difficult to estimate next year&apos;s expenditure by the Federation of Malaya.     In 1951 the extra cost to theFederation Government, arising from the emergency and excluding the cost of services of a normal and permanent nature, is about 13.8 m.     The major part of this is in respect of police -forces ( 5.6 m. ) and resettlement of Chinese squatters ( h.8 m.)The full cost to the Federation of all police, defence and emergency measures is about  29 m.  (out of total government expenditure of  66 m.).32 aircraft20        &quot;5        &quot;8 &quot;20        &quot;6,3001 ,1008 aircraft6       U


</content>
</cab>
