<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/48/0 images: 229-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
------- -fe^c**JL*A       ty-ffiyn.^DOCUMENT IS-THE PROPERTY OF HIS-BR-ITANNIG iviAJESTYJS -GOVERNMENT)&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;confidential.(51) 42llTH DECEMBER, 1951CABINETTIN AND STEEL NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE U.S.A.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster and the Minister of SupplySince March last the United States, in an effort to break the price,have refrained from buying tin from the sterling area.  As well as losing usdollars, this has been the cause of a good deal of ill-feeling which may increase in the very near future if, as is likely, the United States is soonforced to resume tin purchases through exhaustion of commercial stocks.In this memorandum, we examine this problem, and put forward suggestions for resolving the deadlock in a way acceptable to the Americans, as partof an arrangement under which we could secure from the United states in 1952 one million tons of steel.Nature and history of the problem, The price of tin rose steeply from the outbreak of hostilities in korea until February, 1951, when it reached  1,600 a ton.   The ReconstructionFinance Corporation, who were buying tin metal for the United Statesstrategic stockpile, considered that this price was unreasonably high and inMarch last announced that they were withdrawing from the marketindefinitely.   This was followed shortly afterwards by a further announce-ment that they had taken over the purchase of all tin for the U. S. A,   Theprice has now come down to around  900 a ton.   The position in the U.S.A.is fast becoming critical as ordinary stocks (i. e. excluding the strategicstockpile estimated at around 150,000 tons) are very low and the U.S.Government is faced with two alternatives:&quot;(a) To re-enter the market, which would send prices up again andresult in further accusations that the producers were&quot;gouging&quot; the AmericanTaxpayers.(b) To release tin from their strategic stockpile, which, besidescausing political difficulties in the U.S.A., would be a dangerous precedent as it would amount to using their stockpile as aneconomic weapon to influence prices; it would also provokeviolent reactions in Malaya and other tin-producing countries,   ________3, The,U. S.A. could not accept alternative (a) without considerableloss of face and an aggravation of the ill-feeling which has already beengenerated.   We therefore consider that the best interests of both sides wouldbe served by assisting the Americans to get supplies of tin and using the goodwill so acquired as a means of obtaining steel from the U.S.A,   Thiswould be in-line with recent American suggestions for reciprocal aid in thefield of raw materials.   We have gained much goodwill and some advantage from our recent loan of 10,000 tons of aluminium to the United States.COPY NO.167
4f It is believed that the best method of approach would be to linkthe two commodities on a partial barter basis.   Our requirements of steel,in 1952 are ij million tons above what is so far in sight.   While all of this could not come frOm the United States we need a minimum of 1 million tonsof American steel.   In making any offer of tin for steel we must, however,make sure that the steel so obtained is over and above the quantity which we might expect to obtain on the basis of the U,S, allocation for the first quarter.This is about 500,000 tons.5, We propose, therefore, that discussions should at once be started in Washington looking towards an agreement between the President and thePrime Minister on the following lines:(a) The U. S, Undertake to make available to the United Kingdom in 1952500,000 tons.of steel of types and specifications to be agreed between officials, deliveries to be made evenly throughout the year; .(b) In addition to the steel to be made available under (a), the U.S.undertake to make available in 1952 a further 500,000 tons of steelof types and specifications to be set out in the agreement, deliveries to be made evenly throughout the year.   This further 500,000 tons to be paid for by 20,000 tons of tin to be made available by theUnited Kingdom to the United States, deliveries to be made evenlythroughout the year, pari passu with steel deliveries from theUnited States;(c) The United States undertake to make available to the United Kingdomnot less than 500,000 tons of steel under (a) and (b) together in thefirst half of 1952.o, The tin for the transaction would be bought on the market.   this might involve the United Kingdom in paying prices for tin higher than those onwhich the steel/tin ratio was calculated: the result of such an increase ofexpenditure by the United Kingdom would, in effect, be payment of a higher price for the 500,000 tons of barter steel than for the other 500,000 tons.The proposal is that any increased cost arisingfrom this course should bespread over consumers of United Kingdom steel generally.   (The Minister ofSupply dissents from this proposal.) In this way the barter deal could becarried through without loss to the Exchequer.The quantity of tin mentioned (20,000 tons) would not of itself solve the American difficulties, but it would come very close to doing so if the U. S,A.set itself out to come to an agreement with its other suppliers, Bolivia,Indonesia and the Belgian Congo, with all of whom she is in dispute about price.8. The scheme will not be easy to negotiate in detail or to administer inPractice; but the countervailing advantages are in our opinion well worth while.This U,S,/u. K, co-operation in the raw material field would show how the .resources of the two countries can be used to the advantage of the joint defence&apos;effort. It would break the tin deadlock, which is the worst difficulty between ourselves and the U.S. in the raw materials field.   It would provide us with steel,^luch is our main raw material need from them.
recommendation ,       ; We therefore recommend that an immediate approach shouldbessmade in Washington to the U.S. Government along the lines-indicated in paragraphs 4 to 6 and that, if the reception is favourable^. the detailed negotiations should start with a view to the completionof the agreement during the Prime Minister&apos;s visit. -r;a,b.SWINTOND.S.Uth December, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
