<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/48/0 images: 288-294</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos; 203  OCUiviSITT IS THE PROPERTY OFHIS. BRITANNIC MAjECTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)- - - - *?**mmm**mmmm*.mmmm mm m mmm)mm**m mmmmmm.mm mm mmmmmm m -m m m m m     m m     m - m m .* EGRET. &apos; &quot;     &apos; ..&apos;HJ.&apos; &apos;:.(51)49   - -   COPYHC.   I?17TH DECEMDER,1951-   CABINET - &apos;-&apos;TRANSFER OF THE HIGH COMMISSION TERRITORIES .Memorandum-by the Secretary of State for&quot;&apos;Commonwealth RelationsDr. Malan has declared his intention to press his demandfor transfer of the Territories (Basutoland, Bechuanaland and Swaziland),early next year.   I dp not recommend any immediate action, but my colleagues should be aware of what is impending.2. A note setting out the facts and arguments more fully is annexed.3, Our position is clear.   V/e are bound by forty-year old pledges to consult the. Territories&apos; inhabitants and Parliament here.. Neither will agree to transfer.   Co our answer must be &quot;no&quot;.4. Yet two of the Territories are economically and geographicallyat Dr. Malan&apos;s mercy.   And a bad quarrel with the Union would not onlyprejudice their co-operation with us in defence and trade, but might lose us the territories.   The issue will therefore require the most careful handling.5. It is not clear how or when Dr. Malan will proceed.   He talksof getting his Parliament to submit a petition to The King in Council.   This isthe procedure specified in the South Africa Act of 1909.   But today&apos;saltered constitutional position makes it an awkward approach, since it isquite clear that His Majesty could not be advised on a matter like thisby South African Ministers alone:  and it woul! have to be arranged in someway or other that United Kingdom Ministers were brought into the matter.There is danger here of the Crown being embroiled in dispute and ofrepublicans in the Union making capital out of this.6. The Union Parliament sits from January until May or June.When it assembles next month br, IVTalan may disclose his plans more fully.   On the other hand he may decide to test our reactions before deter-mining his tactics.   He could do so and still fall back on the petition methodof approach before his Parliament risesi7*                   We could try now to dissuade Dr. Malan from raising the matter at all.   This would merely be a repetition of a move made by Mr, Attlee&apos;sGovernment which was deeply resented but resulted in brief delay on theexcuse that Dr. Malan would await a more stable Government in the UnitedKingdom.   It is unlikely to do any good and would probably make mattersworse, &quot;        --------- - - -8*. .   . Alternatively we could make known informally through theUnion High Commissioner our difficulties and express willingness to discussat any time the situation which results from our inability to transfer.
.   2034. UiviEITT IS THE PROPERTY OF HE BRITANNIC MA^ESTY^ GOVERNMENT)5 EC RET:.(51) 49 . COPY NC.17TH DECEMBER, 1951.CA3INE&apos;TRANSFER OF THE HIGH COMMISSION territories memorandum by the Secretary of State for commonwealth RelationsDr. Malan has declared his intention to press his demandfor transfer of the Territories (Basutoland, Bechuanaland and Swaziland)early next year,   I do not recommend any immediate action, but my colleagues should be aware of what is impending.2. A note setting out the facts and arguments more fully is annexed.3. Our position is clear.   V/e are bound by forty-year old pledges to consult the Territories1 inhabitants and Parliament here.   Neither will agree to transfer.   So our answer must be &quot;no&quot;,4. Yet tv/o of the Territories are economically and geographicallyat Dr. Malan&apos;s mercy.   And a bad quarrel with the Union would not onlyprejudice their co-operation with us in defence and trade, but might lose us the territories.   The issue will therefore require the most careful handling.5, - It is not clear how or when Dr. Malan will proceed.   He talksof getting his Parliament to submit a petition to The King in Council.   This isthe procedure specified in the South Africa Act of 1909.   But today^altered constitutional position makes it an awkward approach, since it isquite clear that His Majesty could not be advised on a matter like thisby South African Ministers alone: and it wouB have to be arranged in someway or other that United Kingdom Ministers were brought into the matter.There is danger here of the Crown being embroiled in dispute and ofrepublicans in the Union making capital out of this.6. The Union Parliament sits from January until May or June.When it assembles next month pr. Malan may disclose his plans more fully.   On the other hand he may decide to test our reactions before deter-mining his tactics.   He could do so and still fall back on the petition methodof approach before his Parliament rises. &apos;..7c We could try now to dissuade Dr. Malan from raising the matter at all.   This would merely be a repetition of a move made by Mr. Attlee&apos;sGovernment which was deeply resented but resulted in brief delay on theexcuse thMlDr*-Malan would await a more ^stable Government in the United  -Kingdom.   It is unlikely to do any good and would probably, make-mattersworse. - &apos;        --8. Alternatively we could make known informally through theUnion High Commissioner our difficulties and express willingness to discussat any time the situation-which results from our inability to transfer.
- - -   20*OCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY -OF HIS BRITANNIC MA jECTY *S -GG7ERNMSNT).Z E C-R E T ;-II-3.(51)49 . * - COPY HC.   V?17TH DECEMBER, 1951 ;CABINETTRANSFER OF THE HIGH.CCMlVilSSICN TERRITORIES    - .   memorandum by the Secretary of State for commonwealth RelationsDr. Malan has declared his intention to press his demandfor transfer of the Territories (Basutoland, Bechuanaland and Swaziland)early next year.   I do not recommend any immediate action, but my colleagues should be aware of what is impending.2, A note setting out the facts and arguments more fully is annexed.3.&quot; Our position is clear.   We are bound by forty-year old pledges to consult the Territories&apos; inhabitants and Parliament here.   Neither will agree to transfer.   Co our answer must be &quot;no&quot;. &apos; - .4. &apos; Yet two of the Territories are economically and geographicallyat Dr. Malan&apos;s mercy.   And a bad quarrel with the Union would not onlyprejudice their co-operation with us in defence and trade, but might lose us the territories.   The issue will therefore require the most careful handling.     5. It is not clear how or when Dr. Ivlalan will proceed.   He talksof getting his Parliament to submit a petition to The King in Council.   This isthe procedure specified in the South Africa Act of 1909.   But today&apos;s.altered constitutional position makes it an awkward approach, since it isquite clear that 1-Iis Majesty could not be advised on a matter like thisby South African Ministers alone: and it would have to be arranged in someway or other that United Kingdom Ministers were brought into the matter.There is danger here of the Crown being embroiled in dispute and ofrepublicans in the Union making capital out of this.6. : The Union Parliament sits from January until May or June.When it assembles next month Dr. Malan may disclose his plans more fully.   On the other hand he may decide to test our reactions before deter-- mining his tactics.  He could, do so and still fallback on the petition methodof approach before his Parliament rises.7. &apos; We could try now to dissuade Dr. Malan from raising the matter at all.   This would merely be a repetition of a move made by Mr. Attlee&apos;sGovernment which was deeply resented but resulted in brief delay on theexcuse that Dr.. ivlalan would await a more stable Government in the UnitedKingdom,   It is unlikely to do any good and would probably make matters, worse. ;; / -&quot; - &apos; .        - - ..:8,   A ;     Alternatively we could make known informally through theUnion\High Commissioner our difficulties and express willingness to.discussat anytime the situation which results from our inability to transfer.
But this would not help much.   Dr. Malan must know that we would notrefuse to discuss.  Accordingly I do not think that we should take theinitiative.   If it came out that we had done so, it would be strongly criticised in this country and unsettle opinion not only in the Territories but else wherein the Empire.9e I recommend therefore that we should simply watch theposition and leave Dr. Malan to raise the matter in his own time and in hisown way.   The sort of line we might then take is indicated inparagraphs 8 .- 10 of the Annex, but we cannot definitely decide how to dealwith his approach until we see what form it takes.I.Commonwealth Relations Office, 3. W. 1.,17TH DECEMBER, 1951.
ANNEX*  -.2.05--  Note on the Transfer Question1, ... The South Africa Act, 1909, provided for the possible transferof. these Territories (Basutoland, Bechuanaland and Swaziland) to theUnion at some future date, and for the machinery of transfer if it cameabout. &apos;:- i - - .Zm The Act does not constitute any obligation to transfer,   (very similar provision was made for the incorporation of the two Rhodesias inthe Union, but this has not prevented their pursuing an entirely differentpath.) The constitutional safeguards provided in the Act have gone withthe power of disallowance.   Two pledges, given during the passage of theBill through the United Kingdom Parliament, have been frequently reiteratedsince by various United Kingdom Governments and recently by the PrimeMinister,   These pledges are that transfer should not take place(i). until the inhabitants, natives as well as Europeans, have been consulted, and - .&apos;.(ii) until the United Kingdom Parliament has been given an opportunityof expressing its views.This leaves the last word with the United Kingdom Parliament,3, The Union case is that the. provision in the Act amounts to a promise and that fulfilment is long overdue.   Dr. Malan has said that noother sovereign state would today tolerate islands within its boundariesadministered by someone else.   He argues that none of the Territories couldever survive as an independent unit and that economically and geographicallythey are part of the Union.   The Union, he claims, suffers through lack of :control of what goes on inside them.   This prejudices Union defence anddevelopment.  As for pledges, the native inhabitants are not competent in hisopinion to judge an issue like this.4, For his own political purposes Dr, Malan is out to make themaximum capital out of his demand and is prepared to make it an electionissue in the Union.   This puts his opponents on the spot.   They are bound toagree that transfer is desirable.   Genera! Smuts was always a party to thedemand for transfer and his successors take the same view.   They havealready stated that on the main issue, there is no difference betweenjhem .and the Governments   The United Party&apos;s only criticism is therefore of dr. Malan&apos;s methods and timing.   The wilder men in the nationalist party may try to use our refusal to transfer as an excuse for hastening are public.5, .-- ; .... On our side the pledges are clear and categoric.   The nativeinhabitants of the Territories are very strongly opposed to transfer and theUnited Kingdom Parliament equally averse  to it.      Transfer against thewishes of the inhabitants would be a gross breach of faith and is thereforeout of the question.   On the other hand a serious breach in relations with theUnion would adversely affect their co-operation with us over defence, trade,the supply of gold, etc.6, The worst feature is that the Territories are completelyat Dr, Malan&apos;s mercy.   Two of them are hopelessly vulnerable to economic pressure by the Union,   The Union could deprive Basutoland of all contact with the outside world and starve it into subjection very quickly.
Short of this, the Union could make our continued administration verydifficult and expensive, simply by turning nasty in day to day relations,; 7. It would not he in the Union&apos;s real interests to quarrel badlywith us or to incur the public rebuff which would follow if the native inhabi-tants were consulted on transfer and declared themselves against it, as theywould.   The highly emotional Afrikaner may ignore this, but many south africans feel that their country is lonely and friendless in the world today.They would be reluctant to get seriously at odds with the United Kingdom.Apart from-&quot;tIie grave and persistent difficulties arising from a fundamental difference on native policy, there are many affinities of character andmany common interests between ourselves and South Africans of both parties, , . - 1, ;: .\  &apos;8, From this comes a hope, perhaps forlorn, that, if our difficulties were brought home to them, the Union Government might be persuaded however reluctantly to rest indefinitely on an agreement^&quot;whichrecognised the Territories1 economic and geographic affinities with the -Union.   The working relations which exist today between the territories and the Union are a credit to both.   The Union&apos;s part in this - the provisionof communications, markets, defence, etc. &quot; is seldom acknowledged.For our p^t-w^ could undertake to press on with conservation anddevelopment of the Territories&apos; natural resources and to give priority tothe things (e. g. development of the Orange River watershed in Basutolandand improved control of foot and mouth disease in Bechuanaland) which affect the Union mosti   We could offer the fullest collaboration overimmigration control, customs arrangements and defence planning.  A verycomprehensive agreement could be shaped to give formality and firmnessto the needs of an unusual situation.9. ; Even if the present Union Government rejected such anagreement, there are many South Africans who would say that in thecircumstances it was not an unfair offer.   This might take the edge off their actions to our refusal to transfer.10, .  When the Union demand materialises, therefore, we shall haveto make absolutely clear that conditions do not exist in which consistent with our pledges we can bring about transfer of the Territories.   We should nevertheless offer to meet with the Union Government or its representatives and discuss the resulting situation.   We may be able to bring home to themour understanding of their aspirations, our complete inability to meet these and our willingness to forge the closest possible bonds of co-operationbetween the Territories and them in all practical matters.  Although itwould fall far short of their desires, an agreement, formalising and improving current working arrangements between the Territories and theUnion, is the only alleviation we could offer in a situation promising suchgrave difficulties if it is not dealt with in a spirit of understanding and goodwill.


</content>
</cab>
