<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/206/29 images: 426-427</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(79) 29 COPY NO10 July 1979CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE: EDUCATIONMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Education and Science1. We face a conflict of priorities.    We are committed to reduce publicexpenditure; and we are pledged in the Manifesto and in The Queen1 s Speechto maintain and improve standards in education.    I believe that cuts ineducation of the size and on the timescale proposed in C(79) 26 - over10 per cent in 1980-81 - would make it impossible to fulfil this pledge onstandards. Since we are protecting law and order, reductions in localauthority expenditure will hit education very hard.2. The following points are relevant:-i. Fractionally less was spent on education in 1978-79 than in1973-74, our last year in office.    This was despite an increase insecondary numbers which wholly offset the fall in primary numbers,and a growth of nearly 15 per cent in the numbers in further and highereducation.    Our predecessors provided for an increase of little morethan 1 per cent in expenditure on education between 1979-80 and1981-82, with no growth thereafter.    The recent fall in primarynumbers is now extending to the lower secondary age-groups. Butbeyond 16, numbers in schools and in further and higher education(where costs per pupil or student are inevitably much higher, thoughlower than they were five years ago) are still rising steadily. Andthe plans we inherited already provided for a fall of over 30, 000 inteacher numbers over the next four years.ii. The education service is creaking badly - partly because ofunduly rapid organisational change, partly because of lack ofresources;  and the disparity in standards between different parts ofthe country is now very worrying.    As the chairman of almost anycounty education committee will confirm, there are often not enoughbooks; there are too few teachers of mathematics, science and somespecialist subjects; many other teachers are in urgent need ofretraining;  school buildings (especially many of the thousands ofiCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALprimary schools dating from the last century) are often poorlymaintained; and some polytechnics are short of essential equipment.The same is true of some universities,iii.       There are areas - the Inner London Education Authority isperhaps the prime example - where more is spent than need be intoday&apos;s circumstances.    But administrative costs in educationdepartments, at under 4 per cent of total spending by local authoritieson education, are smaller than 5 years ago.    And the number of non-teaching staff they employ (caretakers, secretaries, technicians,school meals staff, etc. ) is slightly smaller than in March 1975.3. I accept however that there are opportunities for reducing expenditureon education.    The savings would come mainly in such areas as nurseryeducation, school meals, school transport, teacher numbers and access tohigher education;   some of these measures will involve legislation thisSession.    We can secure the co-operation of our supporters in localgovernment in reductions based on this approach.    This is vital if we are tominimise the damage to educational standards, and if we are to proceed withthe various provisions of benefit to parents in the Education No 2 Bill,including the assisted places scheme.4. On this basis, I can undertake to find savings of around  250 millionor 3 per cent.    This is the figure we contemplated for 1980-81 when inOpposition and represents the limit of what is tolerable and practicable nextyear, though we should be able to make further savings in later years. Iaccordingly invite my colleagues to agree that I should discuss with theChief Secretary how cuts on these lines might be achieved and report backto the Cabinet on 26 July.M CDepartment of Education and Science10 July 19792CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
