<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/5/1 images: 20-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET.COPY NO,Vf.P. (g) (40)51.WAR   CABINET.The Shipping Situation in relation to the Food Programme.Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Food.1. &apos;I desire to make the following comments on the Memorandum by theMinister of Shipping dated 7th of February (W.P. (g)(40) 42)  regarding theShipping Situation in relation to the Supply Programme.2.The Ministry of Food&apos;s original first year programme of imports amountedto about 22-g- million tons, based on average imports 1935/37.     In December 19S9a revised programme was prepared and submitted to the Minister of Shipping basedupon a global figure of 19.8 million tons for the first year of war, a reductionof about 10/2.     This revision was consequent upon the mention of the figure   of19.8 million tons by the Ministry of Shipping in a Memorandum (\7.P. (9) (39) whichwas discussed by the Y/ar Cabinet on 17th November 1939 (Y7.M. (39)86th Conclusion),and it is referred to in paragraph six of the Minister of Shipping&apos;s Memorandumof the 7th of February.     The present programme of the Ministry of Food is approximately 19,9 million tons.between September 1st, 1939 and January 31st, 1940, when added to the total requirements for the period from February to August, 1940, upon which the loadingprogrammes sent to the Ministry of Shipping have been based, amounts approximatelyto the 19.8 million tons of foodstuffs (see Appendix to this Memorandum) which,in his earlier Memorandum, the Minister of Shipping hoped to be able to bring intothe country during the first year of the war.      Figures, however., of actual, andanticipated loadings for arrival in February and March suggest that, even if the monthly rate of arrivals provided for in the February to August programme of theMinistry of Food (set out in the Appendix) were fully implemented for the monthsof April to August, the total of foodstuff imports in the first year of war would fall short of the figure of 19,8 million tons by at least 500,000 tons.      TheMemorandum of the 7th February suggests (para. 6) that-^ in view of the possibilityof shipping shortage, Supply Departments shoutld now arrange to reduce consumption by 10^o below the level which could be maintained if total imports were to reach the U.K. at the rate of 47 million tons per annum.    (The assumption on which thefoodstuffs figure of 19.8 millions vas based.)The total quantity of foodstuffs which arrived in the United Kingdom

5. There are two principal ways in which a shortage of tonnage can be met.One i3 by a reduction of total imports and the other is &quot;by a shortening of the distance over which imports have to be carried.     If, in framing its programmes,the Ministry of Food arranges to make a greater proportion of its purchases inrelatively nearby countries, it can effect a large saving of shipping tonnagewithout reducing its total requirement of foodstuffs.     In preparing its programmes, however, the Ministry of Food is hound to take account of various considerations other than the most economical use of shipping.     In particular,it is required by the Treasury to have regard to the need for economising inthe use of dollars and other &quot;hard&quot; currencies, and by other Departments to take account of various political and economic considerations such as the urgent need of Dominions and Colonies to place their produce in their normal market and thedesirability of buying in certain countries to reduce the supply of commoditiesavailable to the enemy.     It will be obvious that to prepare a programme with allthese conflicting considerations in mind is exceedingly difficult.4. If in fact, however, a prospective shipping shortage does necessitate a reduction of 10 per cent, in total imports, and this reduction is to affectequally the Ministry of Food and the Ministry of Supply, the Ministry of Food would presumably need to adapt its programme to a maximum of 17,800,000 tons of annualimports, instead of 19,800,000 tons.     It is hoped, of course, that no such reduction will prove necessary.     Further, even if shipping capacity proves to beless than was anticipated, it might be possible to effect a sufficient economy in shipping by shortening, through an adaptation of the import programme, the totaldistance from which certain foodstuffs (such as wheat and sugar) are to be lifted.This would, of course, involve a greater expenditure in &quot;hard&quot; currencies.Assuming, however, that there proves to be no possibility of avoiding a reductionin the annual total of food imports from 19,800,000 to 17,800,000 tons, thefollowing considerations arise,5, Refrigerated tonnage is separate from other tonnage, and the effect ofthe reduction in question would fall not upon imports of meat, dairy produce andother commodities carried in refrigerated space, but upon commodities requiringunrefrigerated space, i.e, mainly on cereals, animal feeding stuffs, oilseeds and sugar.

6. The programme of sugar requirements recently submitted to the Ministryof Shipping, when added to the quantity of sugar which arrived betweenSeptember 1st, 1939 and January 31st, 1940, shows a saving of over 200,000 tonsin comparison with the Ministry of Pood&apos;s programme of December 2nd, 1939,previously submitted to the Ministry of Shipping.     Over and above this reductionin demands for tonnage it has been calculated that if the domestic ration of sugarwere reduced to ^ lb. per head per week, i.e. by 333- per cent., the monthlysaving would be approximately 24,500 tons.     If a further cut of 5 per cent, weremade in the manufacturers&apos; ration, an additional monthly saving could be effectedof 2,746 tons.     A round figure of 320,000 tons may, therefore, be taken as apossible saving in the course of a full year, on the assumption that the sugar ration and allocations to manufacturers are so reduced.     The alternative of allowing stocks of sugar to decline is not practicable because the reserves inhand are already below the desirable minimum.7. The oilseeds programme for the seven months February - August 1940 hasalready been reduced to a level which allows for consumption of margarine at separately of only 4 oz. per head per week.     But assuming that a further reduction hadto be made in the oilseeds programme, a saving of 206,000 tons might be made by substituting groundnuts for cottonseed.     Further, if margarine were rationed atthe rate of 3 ozs. per head per week, and compound lard and other cooking fats atthe rate of 2 oz. per head per week, a saving of 88,000 tons in imports of seedsfrom which soft oils are produced, and a saving of 30,500 tons in imports ofseeds from which hard oils are produced, might be effected.    Again, if linoleummanufacturers were rationed by 50 per cent, and paint manufacturers by 20 per cent,additional savings of 51,500 tons and 42,000 tons respectively in linseed importsmight also be made.     The consequence of all these changes would amount, therefore,to an additional saving on the oilseeds programme of not more than 418,000 tonsin a full year.     These changes, however, would simultaneously involve a loss ofsome 331,000 tons of oilcake;    (which are essential for the maintenance of thesupply of milk) or 20 per cent, of present requirements.8. Rationing of bread was never enforced in the last war and is clearly a last resort of a starving country, bread being the cushion for deficienciesof other foodstuffs.     There can therefore be no reduction in imports of wheat for human consumption.    At the suggestion of the Ministry of Shipping, however,the Ministry of Food is giving urgent consideration, in consultation with theTreasury, to the possibility of substantially reducing, by increased purchases3.

om North Atlantic markets, the dear&apos;, weight tonnage required &quot;by the cerealsimport programmeoSome reduction in demands upon liner space can   e expected to follow from the control of imports of fresh and canned fruit and vegetables, for whichpreparations are now being made by the Ministry     Some reductions can also be expected when other miscellaneous foodstuffs of various kinds come undercloser control.9* But it seems clear that if a total reduction in annual imports of foodstuffs approximating to 2,000,000 tons in all is to be effected, by far thegreater part of the reduction must fall on animal feeding stuffs.     It has alreadybeen shown that any reduction in the oilseeds programme, especially in imports ofcottonseed, would result in heavy losses of oilcake,,     Such losses would seriously affect the dairy herd and interfere, in consequence, with the supply of liquid milk, the production of which in January 1940, was already down to the minimum required.     But apart from such losses, a further reduction of over 1,000,000 tonsin imports of other animal feeding stuffs vrould need to be made in order to effect a total saving of 2,000,000 tons in the import programme of the Ministry of Pood,The consequences of such reduction would include the slaughter of livestock on alarge scale, especially of pigs and poultry.10. Even if the full import programme of maize and other animal feedingstuffs recently submitted to the Ministry of Shipping for the period February -August 1940 were implemented, imports of maize in the first year of war would fall short by over 400,000 tons of the programme submitted on December 2nd, 1959, and imports of other animal feeding stuffs by 72,000 tons     Moreover the programmeof December 2nd showed a reduction of some 800,000 tons in the figure for thosecommodities originally submitted, which was based on the average of imports in1935/57.11. There seem, therefore, to be only two alternative policies which couldbe followed if total imports into the United Kingdom had to be reduced by 10 percent, in consequence of shipping shortage.     On the one hand, if the originalallocation of tonnage between the Ministry of Pood and the Ministry of Supply Y/eremaintained, and in consequence the annual import programme of the Ministry of Poodhad to be reduced to 17,800,000 tons, a large-scale reduction in imports of animal feeding stuffs would result, with very serious consequences to british agriculture;   for it would not be possible, except by substantially reducing4c

feeding stuff imports, to make the necessary reductions in the total programmeof the Ministry of Pood, even if the sugar ration were reduced in the manner suggested above, drastic rationing of oils and fats were also introduced, and anumber of other reductions in consumption were effected in fruits and articles of less importance.If, however, it were decided to allow the present progranme for importsof animal feeding stuffs to remain (and members of the War Cabinet will realisehow grave is the present shortage of feeding stuffs and what dissatisfaction ithas caused) it would be necessary to continue to allocate tonnage to the Ministryof Food at the rate of about 19 million tons a year.12, The following questions, therefore, arise for consideration: -(a) Is the annual total of imports into the U.K. likely to fallsubstantially short of 47,000,000 tons, and if so is the deficit likely tobe of the order of 10 per cent?(b) If such a deficit must be accepted what share in the reduction ofimports will the Ministry of Food be asked to bear?If a reduction of more than 500,000 to 750,000 tons must be made inthe figure of annual total food imports on which the Ministry&apos;s present programme is based, still further slaughtering of livestock will become inevitable because a reduction of imports of this order could only besecured by a &quot;cut&quot; in animal feeding stuff.(c) The question arises whether this drastic reduction in food importscannot be postponed until after next harvest.20th February. 1940.

CURRSJT (19/2/40) ESTIMATE OP FOODSTUFFS IMPORTS DURMG FIRST YEAR OP WAR COMPARED Y/ITH REVISED PROGRAMME OF DECEMBER 2t ? 195&apos;.-:._____ ^__Quantities in Thousands of Tons,C 0 M M 0 D I T Y1.   WHEAT AND FLOUR.WheatFlour2.   MAIZE AND MAIZE PRODUCTSMaizeMaize ProductsDeclared Imports j Scheduled Arrivals1st Sept. 1939 to&apos; 1st Feb. 1940 to51st Jan. 194-0.     i   31st Aug. 194-0.TOTAL1,827194TOTAL3.   ANIMAL FEEDING STUFFS (OTHER THAN MAIZE)Barley-Oats and ProductsWheat By-ProductsRice BranOilseed CakeLocust Beans4.   PULSE AND OTHER CEREALSTOTALTOTAL5.   SEEDS, NUTS AND oils whale OilSeeds and NutsOils (including Tallow &amp; Prera. Jus)total.   MEAT, BACON AND HAM AND LARDMeatBacon and HamLard7.   SUGAR (RAW)8.   DRIED AND CITRUS FRUITDried FruitOrangesGrapefruitLemons, Limesj etc.9. DAIRY PRODUCEButterCheeseCondensed Milk and PowderEggs in Shell10. BEVERAGESTeaCocoaCoffeeTOTALTOTALTOTALTOTALTOTAL11. FISH (FRESH, FROZEN, CURED) AND canned salmon,Pish (Fresh, Frozen, Cured)Canned SalmonTOTAL12. MISCELLANEOUS.BananasApplesOnionsPotatoesTinned Fruit (in Syrup)Tomatoes (Fresh)Rice and Rice FlourOthersTOTALGRAND TOTAL2,0217051333332534-1154851739715892160212775044616022628649140190131936216264368234488411514442448613373110611548574109527,5783,6202743,894J1,7501,75049070349157253341,353146791,3081,3876282236857893622631929373210805611245810473818585119616086101132741016221793312,325Total Estimated i Revised First&apos;YearImports First of war year of War,     I   Programme.5,4474685,915)   2,5882,5885,0004005,4002,8002003,000743111503242426432,0682351002,0372,1371,074383281,4851,54220245332487553721449219480219211423329127551822931592111381891491196271,88519,903830606002504002,1401501001,8041862,0901,024356201,4001,7501804503050710395151991558002501001536557431003001502001751001001104151,55019,4552pEstimated increase or Decrease on first year Programme.++++4-4-4-4-4-4-+++44768515412412875197826437285474750278852082232225237739581483670128279113789499212335448NOTES.1,   This Table excludes Beer, Molasses and Livestock.2.   M^IZE PRODUCTS - Maize Meal and Edible Maize Starch.3.   WHEAT BY-PRODUCTS    Bran and Pollard, Sharps and Middlings, and Other Cereal By-products (exc. Ricemeal and Dust)4.   PULSE AND OTHER CEREALS. - Dried Peas, Beans, Lentils; Feeding Seeds and all other Grain and Flour not specified.5,   FISH l(      is included in &quot;other Miscellaneous&quot;


</content>
</cab>
