<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/17/0 images: 74-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(a.*     *    &quot;t    1     *    II   I Ml I I........      I.      I     I     I      I II.....illrandum by Mr. C.YI. Orde, Foreign Office.21st June 1917. /--- oOo--- &apos;1.   a iDoint to be considered in estimating the precise value of *Gibraltar to H.M.G. is the apparent inadequacy of the anchorageaccommodation there to meet the exceptional strain imposedby war conditions, and the difficulties with the Spanish Governmentwhich may result from this deficiency.2,   The Goveuor of Gibraltar recently reported that new rules andtariff for pilotage and anchorage at Algeciras had just been issued33y Spanish authorities.   Dues were to he claimed and various regulationsenforced on ships making use of the area shaded red on the   attachedtracing.   One of the new rules dfceolared that vessels sent to anchorin these waters by the authorities of Gibraltar owing to over-crowdingthere or to bad weather would be subject to the laws of the port and topilotage service.   The Governor pointed out that this rule appearedto conflict with article 13 of the Anglo-Spanish treaty signed at Madridin 1667, which allows ships of either country to anchor in the roads orbays of the other without being constrained to enter into port, and,if they are obliged to enter into port by stress of weather, to do sowithout being visited or molested.   He had therefore issued instructionsthat if demands for dues were made on vessels anchored through stressof weather in the area of the port of Algeciras the masters whould beadvised not to pay except under protest.   Sir. Herbert Miles report ef.that bad weather had often obliged vessels to report to the westernside of the &quot;bay for shelter in the roadsteads both north and southof Algeciras, while overcrowding had forced them to take up berthsoccasionally within the newly defined limits of that port.3., A complaint had previously been received from the SpanishGovernment, through the Spanish Ambassador against the anchoringof merchant vessels calling at; or brought intoj Gibraltar in thewaters of the bay extending from Bunta Mala westwards ( see areashaded green in the annexed tracing).   The local authorities atPuente Itfayorga.had, it was stated, complainiffthat these vessels tookpratique at Gibraltar but came an anchored -in the waters mentioned,which were Spanish- without asking leave or talcing any instructionsfrom the Spanish authorities, and sometimes so close to the shorethat fishermen had not room to work their nets.   In a supplementarycommunication from the Ambassador it was declared that a large number ofmerchant vessels which had arrived at Gibraltar had anchored betweenJunta Mala and the River Palmones, without taking pasatique, and hadloaded and unloaded cargo ignoring opahish jurisdiction.   During thenight a British destroyer cruised about the same waters keeping&apos;watch.4.   The Governor of Gibraltar lias, with the concurrence of the SeniorNAY;^.  Officer, reported in connection with these complaints.that ithad been impossible since the outbreak of war and will, he fears,i continue to be impossible to find accommodation for all the vesselscalling at Gibraltar without sending some to anchor west of PuntaMala; practically every day vessels had had to be   anchored as far westat least as Puente Haybrga and usually beyond it.   It had been necess-h ary to anchor them west of Ilirador Tower, i.e., within the lately% defined limits of the Algeciras anchorage.   Sir. H. Miles contendsthat the Spanish authorities should not be permitted to treat as being:within a Spanish port vessels forced by overcrowding tit Gibraltar to(Jpchor outside the usual limits of the harbour to Gibraltar..5.   She Senior ITaval Officer had, however, previously re-sorted to theadmiralty that every effort was being made to reioice the&apos; number of.- shl )S
ihi(fs anchoring west of Punta Mala and to avoid annoyance to theSpanish authorities; the limits of the port of Algeciras were, hhe stated,eing respected.6.   Pending the.receipt of a farther report which has been called for3 to the actual steps which are being taken to avoid anchoring shipsestward of Punta Mala:no reply has been returned to the Spanish,nbassadorxs complaint.7.   Both these&apos;complaints and the promulgation of the Algeciras portemulations raise, though in different degree, the question of the &quot;relativextent of British and Spanish jurisdiction in the bay of Gibraltar, whichas been the subject of stubborn dispute with Spain since 1825.   The arealaimed for the port of Algeciras encriaohes only to a &quot;very small extentn the waters within a three mile limit from Gibraltar, which may be regard-&amp; as the furthest limit within which jurisdiction is claimed by H.M.G,,nd does not encroach at all on the line known as   the &quot;via media&quot; (shownn the map facing pe120 in the attached volume of printed correspondence,;&apos;.0. confl. Ho 4822), which was proposed in abortive negotiations in 1880s a possible working boundary between British and Spanish jurisdiction,o be adopted as a modus Vivendi without prejudice to the claims of eitherountry.   The Algeciras regulations thus do not raise the   jurisdiotionaluestion in any serious manner, though acceptance of them, tacit or open,Jill certainly have the undesirable consequence of recognition by H.M,Gf a slight Spanish encroachment on the three mile limit from Gibraltar.8.   It may be asked, what are the chances of Spain wishing to reopenin a serious manner the question of jurisdiction in the bay?   It is-certain how far the Spanish Government are likely to push the complaints.rhich have been made.   The Ambassador, in making them, stated that theproceedings complained of would always be of a certain importance butmight in present circumstances be very serious owing to 1he possibility ofsuoh acts in neutral waters being incompatible with Spanish neutrality.Shese words appear to indicate no great eagerness on the part of CountEomanones1 Government to press the question of jurisdiction for itsjown sake, and the same disinclination may be inferred from the fact thatthe complaints have only recently been made, though the waters referredto have ever since the ^beginning of the v/ar been used as an anchorage byships calling at Gibraltar,   It may perhaps not be too much to hope thatthe present and future Governments of Spain will be reluctant, assuccessive Spanish and British Governments for some time past havebeen, seriously to reopen the question of jurisdiction.   But it isobvious that controversy on this matter is not to be avoided without good-V/ill on both sides and mayalSs&amp;jrsbe forced even upon reluctant Governmentsby questions which are&quot; dependent upon that of jurisdiction and whichcannot well be shelved. Two such further questions are actually involvedin the circumstances which have been described.9.   These are (i) that of the liability of British vessels tailing shel-in bad weather within the Algeciras anchorage to pay dues to theSpanish authorities, and (ii) that of Spanish neutrality.ter10.   The first of these questions is perhaps not very important initself.   If,however, dues are claimed from such vessels, it will nov doubtbecome necessary for H.M.G. to contend that they are- not   leviable inview of the terms of article 13 of the treaty of 1687.   It is thoughtdesirable, if possible, to avoid a controversy on this point   even, on itsown merits, and a discussion of it with the Spanish Government willba4i the farther drawback of possibly   -leading to a revival of theiurisdictional question.   Unfortunately it does not appear likely that aiispute on the Question of dues can be postponed indefinitely, snort oxtamely abandoning our rights under the treaty, though it may not ariseuntil the autumn brings bad weather and ships are forced to seek sneiterat -Algeoiras,
11,   As regards the second question mentioned above, that of Spanishutrality, the Spanish Ambassador1s representations were evidentlyspired partly by the annoyance caused to Spanish fishermen, but mainlythe fear that Spanish neutrality might be compromised by themmission within waters claimed by Spain of acts of a belligerent nature,e vessels sent by the Gibraltar authorities to anchor there are noubt in most oases sent to wait until the billigerent act of visit andarch can be carried out, and this seems to amount to a use of theaters for belligerent purposes, oven though the vessels may actuallyexamined in waters incontestably British^   0?:,e desire of the Spanishvernment to avoid exposing themselves to a charge of allowing theirtors to be used in a manner inconsistent with their neutrality is natural,d in relation to waters in the Bj:, of Gibraltar is bound to make itre difficult for them to allow the question of jurisdiction in the Wremain entirely undisturbed.IE.   To sum up, it may be said that the port of Gibraltar does notfor sufficient accommodation for shipping to meat the abnormal requirementsa time of war without encroachment on waters the sovereignty over which -a matter of ancient said so far irrecoucileable controversy with Spain,-has been necessary during the war, though this is now being avoided^send ships io anchor, temporarily in waters which are not claimed byis country and which must be regarded as purely Spanish.   ThS ships arent into the waters in dispute in circumstances which involve a utilisa-on of those&quot;waters for belligerent purposes, i,o., from the Spanishint of view, a violation of Spanish neutrality,   Ihose results areparontly inevitable in time Of war.   If the ships are sunt in similarrcumstances into waters which are Spanish beyond dispute, the violationSpanish neutrality must be admitted even from the 3ritish pituat of view.13. further, the east side of the bay of Gibraltar does not provideequate, shelter from westerly and south-westerly gales, as it is1essary fB* ships to take refuge on the west side, in waters which, asthe north, are already, or, as on the south, may at any moment hereafter, claimed by the Spaniards, as forming part of the port of Algeciras.appears to be this practice that has led to definition of the limits ofis port which encroaches, though slightly on waters hitherto claimed&quot;asitish.   This encroachment, the natural desire of Spanish Governments,en neutral, to avoid the charge of allowing. IMilT waters to be used forlligerent purposes and the probable controversy, undesirable in itself,t difficult to avoid, as to the right of the. Spanish authorities tovy dues from ships taking shelter from bad weather in the Algeciraschorage are each and all of them matters liable to birng about a revivalthe old dispute as to the respective limits of British and Spanishvereignty in the Bay of Gibraltar.   Hie insufficient size of the poaGibraltar,ff. whicil is an irremovable condition has produced theseiiicuities and must continue.to produce similar difficulties in theortt

</content>
</cab>
