<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/17/0 images: 77-78</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
INDIA!EXPLANATORY NOTE.1. New Formations.-Oi the 13. new battalions raised to replace thosesent to Mesopotamia nine are now complete, and the remainder within 350men of completion.It will be noted that the number of eligible Indians who ha Ye applied forenrolment in the Indian Defence Force is only 1,137.4. Internal Condition. The Governor of Madras has directed theservice of Orders on Mrs. Annie Besant, Mr. G. S. Arundale, and B. P.Wadia prohibiting them attending meetings or publishing any writings, andplacing their correspondence under censorship. They are also directed tocease to reside in Madras.Telegram from Viceroy to the Secretary of State for half monthending 15th June 1917.8923. In continuation of our telegram of the 1st instant, 8083.Following submitted : -1. New Formations. Officers. Seventy-nine posted to 18 new Indianbattalions being raised.Artillery. LFormation of twro Royal Field Artillery Brigade AmmunitionColumns for two new Divisions Ordered.Infantry Battalions. Of 13 new battalions formed January last, ninecomplete, one within 50 and three within 100 men of -completion. Of 24battalions sanctioned in your telegram of: the 22nd ultimo, 1052, ordersissued for formation of 17 ; orders for remainder will issue when accommo-dation settled.Sappers ;and Miners. No change, except that orders issued for formationof two remaining,Field Companies referred to in last report.Signal Units.^No change.Jndian Defence Force.-Actual number called out, military duty, 1,755.Total registered to date, 47,584. 1,137 eligible Indians have applied forenrolment. Orders issued for embodiment -of one -Indian Company atMadras.&apos;Recruiting.-4:,!Indian combatant recruits enrolled for Indian imitsfortnight ended .10th June. Total labourers recruited Army up to 11th June27,108, of whom hoped to despatch 22,000 end of June and 2,000 middle ofJuly.Medical. Three temporary commissions given Indian Medical Service;17 dressers engaged Indian Subordinate Medical Department.2. Munitions.   Munitions Board. A controller appointed to regulatedistribution of indents which can be complied with within India, and acontroller of textile supplies about to take up his duties.Railway Materials for Egypt. 1\ miles of 75-1 b. fishplates, shipped in&quot;Kurmark,&quot; and 25,000 sleepers in &quot;Kwongsang.&quot;Railway Materials for Mesopotamia. V Hinsang &quot; sailed from Bombay31st May with 13 miles of 41^-lb. rails, completing requirements for Kut-Baghdad railway. During May four metre-gauge locomotives shipped toBasra.qt 508 &apos;      ----  -
River-craft for Mesopotamia Barges.-On 13tli June four arrived atBasra, three left Karachi, and two left Bombay for Basra. Under re-erection,&quot; Karachi: four English, eight Indian. In transit from Calcutta toKarachi, eight. Building at Calcutta, 30; at Bombay one; at Rangoon,one.. Hospital Motor Ships. --Calcutta, two.3. Sutplies. &quot;Hides. Exports of tanned hides from Madras and Bombayto War Office are increasing. During May Madras shipments were 3,967 balesof army selection, and 588 bales- of non-army selection, additional quantitynon-army selection hides being stored. Raw hide purchases under Govern-ment scheme commenced (at) Calcutta, and commencing (at) Rangoon andKarachi. 3,000 hides expected to be ready for shipment end of June atCalcutta. Arrangements being made to take over stocks of exportingfirms.Wool. Purchase, of Tibetan wool at Kalimpong for Upper India millsexceeded 60,000 maunds since 1st. November, and expected to reach 70,000maunds end of June, when season closes. 15,000 maunds obtained by otherroutes ; imports this season largest on record.Timber. Since Munitions Board took over timber supplies, indents for9,800 tons received and being dealt with. Estimate of timber supplies tobe provided next six months, about 14,000 tons monthly besides largesupplies of bamboos and poles. Organisation being developed for meetingthese large war indents by purchases on favourable terms within India.Satisfactory test of three or four Indian woods for aircraft manufacturecompleted, supplies being arranged.Marine. Following are details of marine transport work during pastfortnight: Transports sailed, 69. Troops and men, all classes, embarked,18,196. Tons of stores shipped, 149,359. Animals shipped, including sheep,1,188.   River craft despatched, 9.4. Internal Condition.-Cireular issued by Madras Government regardingattendance of students at Home Rule meetingti, and speech on the subject ofHome Rule hy Governor, have been followed by violent criticism in Press ledby Mrs. Besant. Latest development amounts to public defiance of Govern-ment by Mr. Iyer, late Judge of High Court, President of League, whichMrs. Besant published in newspaper &quot; K!ew India.&quot; She is also workingthrough lew lady followers different parts India to organise agitation amongwomen of India. She has further published scheme for national unrestrictedindependent Government.Agitation against planters in Bihar met for time being by appointmentof strong Committee of Enquiry upon which Mr. Gandhi has seat.Recent enquiries show that Hindustani fanatics on the frontier largelyfinanced by widespread Wahabi organisation centralised in Bengal. Actionagainst them held up in view of situation on frontier.Arrest of a &quot;desperate revolutionary effected in connection with dacoityin Calcutta reported in previous telegram.Maharaja of Patiala has.offered Rs. 1,01,000 for flotilla of motor boats forMesopotamia; Maharaja of IndoreRs. 50,000.for war purposes; MaharanaDanta Rs. 50,000 worth of War Loan Stock for war expenses; and Raja ofFaridkot Rs. 40,000 for comforts of troops Mesopotamia.

</content>
</cab>
