<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/17/0 images: 124-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Mm. SMUG TH-i WORK BONg BY THEORGANIZATIONS S&quot;^T UP WITHIN TRiJ MINISTRY 0? SHIPPINGFOR DEALING WITH THJii A0CPI3ITI0N 03? ADDITIONAL TONNAGEBY CONSUMPTION OR PURCHASE AT HOMg OR ABROAD PRIOR TOm TRANSFER OF RESPONSIBILITY TO THii CONTROLS OF THuMEL (DECEMBER 1916 TO MAY 1917.) ,
A.   SHTPHITLDIMr BRANCH,The Shipbuilding programme of the Ministry was carriedout so far as work in the United Kingdom was concerned, under thegeneral supervision of the Shipbuilding1 Advisory Committee whichwas composed as follows;-Mr. G.J. Carter. W.S. AbellMr. F.M. Henderson.Mr, James Marr.fir. A.C RossMr, C.J.O. Sanders.Mr.     Rowan Thomson.Mr. A.P. Duncan.Managing Director of Oammelllairc. &amp; Co. Ltd., Shipbuilders &amp;Engineers, Birkerthead&quot; (Chairman).Chief Surveyor to Lloyds Eegisterand Technical Adviser to theShipping Controller.Chairman of D &amp; I. Henderson &amp; Co.Ltd., Shipbuilders &amp; Engineers,Glasgow.jing Director of J.L.Thompson&amp; Sons. Ltd., Shipbuilders, Sunder-land- Sir James Laisg &amp; Sons Ltd.,Shipbuilders, Sunderlend, and theSanderland Fprge Co.Sunderland.Director of Hawthorn Leslie &amp; Co.,-Ltd,v Shipbuilders and i&amp;gineers,Newcas tle-on-Tyne.Director of Shipbuilding Work,Ministry of Shipping.Senior Partner of David Rowan &amp; Co.Marine Engineers, Glasgow.Secretary, Shipbuilding Employers1Federation, (Secretary).The Committee was responsible for the design, constructionand placing of orders of Government standard ships.
PERMANENT HEADQUARTERS STAFF.Mr. C.J.O, Sanders, Lent by the Marine Dept.(Director of Shipbuilding V*ork)..,,of the Board of Trade,Mr, W,S, Abell(Technieal Adviser)............... Lent by ^loyds Register,Two Ship Surveyors toLloyds Register.................. Lent by Lloyds Register.One Ship &amp; Engineer Surveyor........... Lent by the Marine Dept.of the Board of Trade.with clerical staff.DISTRICT STAFF.The members of the Advisory Committee were recognised asthe general representatives of the Ministry on all matters relatingto merchant shipbuilding in their respective districts and technicalquestions were referred to them by the various shipbuilders andmarine engineers.     In addition surveyors were appointed to look-after steel supplies and to hasten progress,
The Ministry further had the advantage of the servicesof all the Board of Trado expert ships and engineer surveyorsand also all the similar officers belonging to the variousClassification Societies.      Each vessel being built by theShipping Controller was put under tho supervision andclassification of one of the recognised Classification Societies.In this connection it may be mentioned that the repair ofmerchant vessels in the United Kingdom so far as necessary wasdealt with under the supervision of the Shipbuilding Departmentof the Ministry of Shipping.OUTLINE OP S3HIPHJILDINC HQRK.(l)        Review of vessels under construction.In the Act under which the Shipping Controller was appoint-ed it is laid down that he was to take steps for the maintenanceof the supply of Merchant Ships.to meet National needs,Consequently on his appointment he took over from the Boardof Trade the supervision of the construction of Merchant Shipsthen building. There were a large number of -Merchant Shipsalready under construction and in view of the National heeds it ?/asnecessary to concentrate.upon the completion of suitable cargovessels which could be completed within a period of about sixmonths or in approximately tho same time as the new Standard Shipscould be completed.The building programme af each shipbuilding yard in thecountry was reviewed and owing to the necessity of conservingsupplies of steel for the vessels which would meet the foregoingCconditions,
The Ministry further had the advantage of the servicesof all the Board of Trado expert ships and engineer surveyorsand also all the similar officers belonging to the variousClassification Societies.       Each vessel being built by theShipping Controller was put under tho supervision andclassification of one of the recognised Classification Societies.In this connection it may be mentioned that the repair ofmerchant vessels in the United Kingdom so far as necessary wasdealt with under the supervision of the Shipbuilding Departmentof the Ministry of Shipping.OUTLINE OF SHIPBUILDING Z/QBK.(l)        Review of vessels under construction.In the Act under which the Shipping Controller was appointed it is laid down that he was to take steps for the maintenanceof the supply of Merchant Ships to meet National needs.Consequently on his appointment he took over from tho Boardof Trade the supervision of the construction of Merchant Shipsthen building. There were a large number of llerchant Shipsalready under construction and in view of the National needs it wasnecessary to concentrate.upon the completion of suitable cargovessels which could be completed within a period of about sixmonths or in approximately tho same time as the new Standard Shipscould be completed.The building programme af each shipbuilding yard in thecountry was reviewed and owing to the necessity of conservingsupplies of steel for the vessels which would meet the foregoingCconditions,
ftconditions, the construction of a large number of vessels of alarge typa which would take comparatively long periods to complete,was for the time being suspended,(2)       Government Standard Ships.The policy of building Standard Ships having beenadopted, suitable types were designed as follows:-Type.	&quot;A&quot;  -	-  Single deck steamer carrying about 8000:  tons deadweight           (39 ordered)Type	&quot;B&quot;  -	-  Two-deck steamer carrying about 8000 tons deadweight           (69 ordered)Type	&quot;0&quot;  -	-  Single deck steamer carrying about 5000 tons deadweight           (20 ordered)Type	&quot;DM  -	-  Single deck steamer carrying about 3000 tons deadweight           (20 ordered)Type		-  Two-deck steamer carrying about 7000 tons deadweight           (1 ordered)It may be mentioned that type &quot;D&quot; was designed in collabora-tion with the Admiralty in order that they might in case of needtake up certain of the vessels to be used for Naval purposes.Other types were under    consideration.It should be observed that the material for thebuilding of Standard Ships was standardised in as few sizesas possible and throughout the whole design the object inview was to produce as quickly as possible with the leastexpenditure of labour and material, an effective freight carryingmachine for the present needs of the country. Greatdelay having occurred in the past in the completion of MerchantChips owing to engines not being ready when the hulls were ready -the machinery of the Standard Ships was designed in standardsizesK
sizes so as to make it possible for the first set of engines togo into tho first hull.     Arrangements were made whereby theauxiliaries and outfit of the ships were ordered in groups andas far as possible without creating monopolies.   These too, sofar as possible, were standardised,(3)  Certificates under the. Munitions of War Act. -The foregoing wore tho two main items of shipbuildingwork but it ought to bo montioncd that no merchant ship can beconstructed or repaired in the United Kingdom without acertificate issued under Section 9 (l) A of the Munitions ofWar Amendment Act 1916.    These certificates ma&amp;e the work&quot;Munitions work&quot; and the provisions of the-Monitions Act thonapply.    The certificates are to be issued by tho Board of Tradobut by arrangement they were issued under the direction of thoDirector of Shipbuilding Work.(4)    Allocation of Orders. -Before the Shipping Controller was appointed therewas an arrangement between the Board of Trade and the Admiralty .that all orders for Naval Military and Merchant Shipbuildingshould be allocated by a Joint Delegation consisting ofrepresentatives of the Admiralty and of the Board of Trade.   Theobject of the work of the delegation was to so allocate theorders as to prevent overlapping and to endeavour to utilisethe shipbuilding resources of the country in tho best possibleway.       The representatives &quot;for the Board of Trade were -Mr. Abell
Mr, Abell and Mr. C.J.O.Sanders and they continued toact on the delegation on behalf of the Shipping Controller.(5)   Miscellaneous.    A constant stroam of proposalsand suggestions reached tho Department for the construction ofspecial types of vessels or for special fittings to vessels andthese were dealt&apos;with by the Committee and the Staff.The Director of Shipbuilding Work advised theMinistry of Munitions on quostions of priority of manufactureof shipbuilding accessories and the War Trade Department onquestions of export of shipbuilding materials.In addition to his duties as Director ofShipbuilding ;/ork, Mr.Sanders represented tho Shipping Controlleron the following Committees:-Stool Consultative Committee   (Ministry of Munitions)Priority Committeo   (Ministry of Munitions): andLabour Priority Committee   (Ministry of Munitions.)
In 1916 the aggregate gross tonnage of Merchant Ships completed was about 550,000 tons. Thefollowing statement gives an estimate oirtfco amount to be completed during 1917 according to presentprogramme.ESTHviAICED EOTKRS. ACTUAL RETURNS.Ho. of Vessels.   Gross Tonnage Ho. of Vessels. Gross Tonnage.J/JUARY	13	475000	tons	13	47,000 tonsFBBRUABT	24   .	78,000	II	24	78,000   &quot;MARCH	13	47,000	II	22	115,654   &quot;APRIL:&apos;	16	58,000	ft	18	60,212   &quot;	16	73,000	tl	18	74,808   &quot;JIM	21	95,000	If		JULY	18	80,GC0			. AUGUST	24	110,000	Tt			.27	120,000	II		OCTOBER	27	120,000	II			30	135,000	II		DBOTIBBH	28	125,000	II		2571,160,700 tons
B. OVEBSEAS SHIP PURCHASE .BBAMOHi    *M      HI I   I &apos; &apos;   &apos;    &apos; ... i   . i   m      i-TMCfDUQTION-This Department was initiated for the purpose ofbuying Second-hand steamers, steamers already under constructionabroad, and the placing of orders for new vessels to be built inthe various Colonial and Foreign shipbuilding centres.The Staff consisted of the following:-Mr,JQBfl MSMAJOR S*B.PITOEyMr. J.O.WRIGHTMr, JAMES 3Mr.Mr. PtBffPTYPISTS, CLERKS, 3TC.Director of Overseas Ship Purchases,primarily responsible for all pur-chases and the work of the Department.Assistant of Ship Purchases, and thocontrol of the StaffsAssistant of Finance, responsible forall payments and financial recordskept by this Department.In charge of all wooden vessels andresponsible for their general design,construction and purchase.The Controller^ technical adviser inU.S.A. and Canada, responsible for alltechnical matters, types of vessels,constructional arrangements and thehull and machinery specifications.Technical engineer sent to America togenerally assist Mr.James Esplen.Naval Architect responsible forarmament of vessels technical returns.Engineer responsible for technicalengineering matters at home, andpreparation of statements.Chief Clerk to the Director, in chargeof all cables and correspondence.Chief recording clerk responsible forall statistics and book-keeping carriedout by the Department.
 . value32,107,250217,4244,686,3254,050,0009,976,1252,803,998167,600464,072515,00054, 987,794The methods of negotiations and purchase adopted weregenerally as follows:-Offers of proposals for construction were secured fromthe U.S.A.by Mr.Sparks and reliable brokers in the United Kingdom,from Canada by&quot; the Imperial Munitions Board and from Japan byreliable brokers in this country.    These offers as received weresubmitted to the Controller and his Committee for considerationand decision, and upon their authority purchase was effected bythe Director of this Department.    No unusual difficulties weremet with in carrying on under this procedure beyond those occasionedby the limitations of our demands upon the Treasury and latterlyoperations were curtailed in view of this Department being notifiedof the inadvisability of filling up further turns in U.S.A. Ship-yards, and in Japan by the exorbitant prices demanded.In Canada all available turns have been secured fordeliveries up to the end of the year 1918.AmericaWORK ARRANGED FORBuilding in      No.                         . TonsP. ST.V.S.A.            160 Steel freighters 960,000JAPAN 24 Steel     &quot;K&apos;l ,g Oj1 Inkersn    j   r,         10 Steel Barnes in nnnAlready Built     3 Foreign Freighters M2 Foreign Oil Tankers 13,700286 Vessels of Tons     1,556,220
jjMIM (STEEL SHIPS)On the inauguration of the department it was found that thepossibilities of building in America far exceeded those of anyother country, and the Controller appointed Mr.T.Ashley Sparkes  -Chief Representative of the Cunard Line in New York as his CommercialRepresentative in arranging for the purchase of steamers buildingin U.S.A. and in the placing of new contracts for tonnage in thevarious shipbuilding, yards in the States;   Mr.James Esplen actedas technical adviser.These gentlemen rendered very valuable assistance to thisDepartment.It was found that the Norwegians had booked up a largeportion of the output of the shipbuilding yards in the U.S.A.,A number of their contracts for steamers were purchased by thisDepartment through Mr. Sparkes while others were purchased direct.In the framing of the Contracts Mr.Sparkes had theassistance of Mr.Kirlin  a well-known New York barrister.Instructions were given to Mr.Sparkes to book up allavailable turns in the Tf.S.A. Shipbuilding yards for delivery wellup to the end of the year 1918, and where prices have been foundreasonable, this aim has been accomplished, it being stipulated atthe time the contracts were made that Mr.Sparkes should be thoroughlysatisfied that the delivery of the necessary building materials wasassured.In connection with these new contracts, it was foundnecessary in the case of the majority of steamers for 1917 delivery,to accept the builders standard type of vessel.
IIt was possible however, in many of the new contractsvessels for 1918 deliveries placed by Mr . Sparks to cover for animproved steamer - more of the liner type with a speed approachingll/l2 knots, but throughout these purchases it was recognised thatdelivery must be a prominent factor, and the types ordered wereselected generally to avoid delay , and to obtain the maximumoutput from each shipbuilding centre.In order that the name of the British Ministry ofShipping should not figure too prominently, all purchases effectedin the U.u.A. were made in the name of the Cunard Steamship Co., andthis practice was also adopted for our purchases of Norwegiantonnages at home by using the name of the Federal Navigation Co. Ltdand for our purchases of Japanese tonnage by using the names ofFurness Withy &amp; Co. Ltd., and Dodwoll &amp; Co.AMERICA WOODEN SHIPS. .Orders for two wooden steamers had been placed in theStates when we were advised by cable from Mr. Sharks that tho NationalShipping Board of U.S.A. who wore busy on a wooden.shipbuildingprogramme would take exception to us buying or contracting forfurther woodon tonnago and operations in this direction were suspendedPANADA STEEL SHIPS.It was arranged that the Imperial Munitions Board ofOttawa should act as purchasing agents to the Shipping Controllerand conduct all active negotiations, our communications with theImperial Munitions Board being through the Ministry of Munitions,and through this medium all the available output of steelshipbuilding yards in Canada has been secured.    The ImperialMunitions Board were requested to satisfy themselves that eachbuilder was covered for steel before placing an order.     Mr. Jas.Esplen acted throughout as Technical Adviser to the ImperialMunitions Board.
f. &apos; &apos;      &apos; &apos; -$a-&apos;Owing to the large percentage of shipbuilding yards inCanada being situated on the shores of the lakes and tho limitationsof the canals through which vossols built there must pass to reachtidal waters, the majority of our Canadian purchases were restrictedto a 3,500 ton type on about 19!6&quot; draft and standing 10 to 10J-knots at sea.    This type was selected after careful considerationby the Controller and Committee and was consil ered the best all-round type out of many proposals submitted.A number of steamers were building in Canadian shipyardsto Norwegian account, but arrangements were made at the in-stigation of the Controllerjwhereby the Government of the Dominionof Canada will commandeer all vessels building in Canadian ship-yards for neutral account.    In the case of steamers building forallied account in Canadian shipyards purchase has been effected bythis Department to avoid any undesirable complications arising.PANADA WOODEN SHIPS.A large number of proposals were put forward for theconstruction of wooden steamers in Canada but were rejected by theController on questions of draft, etc.    A design was finally acceptedfor a wooden vessel carrying about 2,800 to 3,000 tons on 19&apos;6&quot; draftwith a sea speed of about 9jjr knots and fitted with steam-driven gearedturbines.The Imperial Munitions Board anticipate that they will beable to contract im. the construction of about fifty of those vesselsand authority has already been given.   The delivery of the earlierof these vessels will take place in about six months1 time and we areawaiting definite advice as to the delivery of the remainder of thisorder.It is anticipated that the turbines and boilers for thesevessels will be purchased from U.S.A. but it is possible that theequipment12.
and aaatiliarles may have to be manufactured in this country andsent out to Canada, but the matter is at present still in theprocess of negotiation.flHINA &amp; HONG KONG.Negotiations were in progress with Shipyards situated atShanghai and Hong Kong for the construction of vessels to theorder of this Department.A number of new steamers were purchased in variousshipbuilding centres in Japan, Varying in size from 5,000 tons toJ5,000 tons, with delivery spread over the next twelve months,and while  it is still possible to purchase steamers building inJapan, this market was latterly not by any means so favourablefor operation owing to the increased demand among Japanese ship-owners for tonnage, and owing to enquiries being received fromneutrals (largoly owing to the absence of restriction of transferand registration to purchasers flag) the prices have risen stillfurther.As the Japanese shipbuilders are dependent - on the steelmanufacturers of the U.S.A. and the United Kingdom for theirbuilding materials, it has been suggested that action be takenby tho Allies to prevent the delivery of materials   for vesselsbuilding in Japan for other than Allied accounts.aiCWHANP TCHMttg,Generally soeaking very little action has been taken withregard to secondhand tonnage owing to the excessive prices demandedby neutral owners.,CCMFBTITION FOR PURCHASE AMONGST ALLIED BUYERS.It was hoped, as a result of the recent Regulation under
f. figthe Defence of the Realm Act (Order in Council 16 Feb/17)prohibiting purchase or negotiation for purchase of any vesselwithout authority of the Shipping Controller, this would largelybe avoided.   In spite of the Regulation,however, it was foundthat sellers were working up market prices by various methodsof playing one Allied buyer off against another so the formationof an Inter-Allied Purchasing Committee was decided upon.A working arrangement with the Italian GovernmentCommission was quickly made but owing to its being necessary forthe French Government to take powers to deal with the matter, ageneral arrangement was somewhat delayed.A Committee has now however been formed consisting of twoRepresentatives of U.K. France and Italy and it is proposed to addthereto representatives of other Allied nations.The procedure agreed upon provides that Tonnage offeringshall with the consent of the Meeting be allocated to a certainNation&apos;s Representatives.   This nation will authorise thenegotiation for purchase by a buyer of that nation, but prohibitmore than one negotiation being proceeded with at the same time.It is further decided that the Committee shall limit theprices which may be paid for any given vessel.   In this way itis hoped that sellers will be made to realise that their advancingexorbitant demands are non-productive of sales.Arrangements for defensively arming all overseas purchasewere being  carried out by this Department in conjunction with theTrade Division of the Admiralty.   Suitable arrangements were alsomade by this Department acting with the managers and wirelesscompanies for suitable wireless installation tc be fitted in eachvessel, the detail, arrangements being carried out in conjunctionwith Mr.James Bsplen in Hew York.
OJL TAM&amp;RS *.On behalf of the Admiralty the purchase of second-handand new Oil Tankers under construction was effected by thisDepartment, and we were negotiating at the request of theAdmiralty for the purchase of hulks for Admiralty service.S3S MRG1S.In addition to the above, this i/epartment was instructedto place orders for  1000 tons D.w.,Steel Barges to desigos whiohhad been approved by the admiralty and Inland TIater TransportService, and orders for 10 of these vessels were placed.It would havo been possible to place about 30 to 40more of these vossols, the Builders assuring us that their constructionwould not interfere with the vessels placed by the Admiralty or theStandard ships placed by tho Controller,OQKCME BARG&amp;SNegotiations were in hand for the construction of ConcreteBarges of about 500 tons D.V/,mm.The method of  payment for vessels purchased was arrangedwith the Finance Branch of the Ministry.    The Overseas Ship PurchaseBranch was kept advised by Lr,Sparks of the funds he required andalso of payments made by him, this information was passed on tothe Finance Branch, and they were kept fully advised of the position.The payment of all Canadian Purchases was made by theImperial Munitions Board Ottawa, the Ministry of LunitIrons advisingthe Financial Department of the 1 inistry of Shipping of the sumsrequired for this purpose.
MNA&amp;MMT AND SUPMNMMOBIt was arranged that the vossols as purchasedshould he allocated to the management of various shipowners inthis country, care being taken to allot vessels of the jrype towhich each owner is accustomed.Under this scheme each manager has been provided with acopy of the contract, principal plans, hull and machineryspecifications, when roceivod and will act generally as thoughsteamers allotted to him were building to his own account.As each manager has already attached to his staff menexperienced in the suporintendenco of the building of hulls andmachinery, it was arranged that he would appoint his own hulland machinery superintendents to attend to the carrying out ofthe specifications and generally attend to the completion of thecontracts; reoorting at short intervals as to the  progress of thework, and keeping this Department well advised as to the positionof each contract.aistry of Shipping.

</content>
</cab>
