<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/17/0 images: 142-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Telegrams-&quot;SHIPMINDER, VIC, LONDON.&quot;tAny further communication on thissubject should be addressed to The Secretary,Ministry of Shipping,St. James&apos;s Park,London, S.W. 1,and the following number quoted.bir,In continuation of my letter of the 15th instant,I am directed by the Shipping Controller to report for theinformation of the War Cabinet as follows:-Docking Facilities.   The question of improving theexisting facilities at the various ports is receiving closeattention and in particular the development of the Westernand South Western ports in order to relieve London and theEastern ports as much as possible and enable ships to avoidthe dangerous channel passage.   Mr. L.A.P. Warner of theMersey Docks and Harbour Board whose appointment   under thisMinistry as Director of the rort Branch was reported in myletter of the 25th May, has just returned to London from atour of inspection in the course of which he visited anumber of. ports on the Western and South Western coasts.   Mr.WarnerTs report is being considered.A -full reply to the allegations contained in theResolution of the Dock, Wharf, Riverside and General workersUnion referred to in my letter of the 25th ultimo has Weencommunicated to the Union, and the Labour Advisors to thisMinistry,-Mr. John Hill and Mr. A. Wilkie,        have beenconsulted in the,matter.Gpastal Services,0 Secretary,War; Cabinet.
Coastal Services.    Mr* A.H.Bead who has been appointedDirector of Home Trade Services of this Department has submitteda report on the subject of tho control to be exercised overvessels engaged in the Home Trade of 250 tons and over.It is hoped that the steps to be taken by this Branchof the Ministry will result in the release of a number of shipsnow engaged in coastal trade for more essential purposes and theelimination of unnecessary competition in existing trades whichcan bo served by a smaller number of ships.Foreign (Neutral) Tonnage.   An agreement in principlehas been arrived at with Norwegian interests whereby His -lajestyVsGovernment will obtain the services of Norwegian ships now engagedin the Anglo-Norwegian trade, and ships engaged in overseas tradeto neutral countries other than Norway.   His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwill also obtain the right to disapprove of the renewal of thecharters of a large number of Borwegian ships now on time-charterin distant waters and provided our interests can be adjusted..ith those of the United States the services of a certain number ofthese will be obtained.In return His Majesty&apos;s Government undertake to placein the Anglo-Norwegian trade sufficient British ships to carry toNorway about 230,000 tons of coal and coke a month.   The delaysinevitable with neutral shipping will thus be avoided and it isanticipated that the amount of British tonnage required willconsequently be considerably less than the Norwegian tonnagewithdrawn.   The rates of freight charged for the carriage ofcoal to Norway will be calculated to cover the cost to us of,running
running the corresponding Norwegian ships extracted fromthe North Sea trade whether by requisition or time charter,Timber Supplies,    Proposals submitted by Messrs,Martin Olsson &amp; Sons for bringing large quantities of timberfrom &apos;Sweden to this country in rafts have been consideredin consultation with the Admiralty and Controller of TimberSupplies (Board of Trade),   It was agreed that if it couldbe found possible to make adequate arrangements for the towingand protection of the rafts from Sweden to this Country, theproject should receive the support of His Majesty5s Government.It is however stated to be impossible to spare for the purposeany tugs at present engaged on the service of this 8ountry, andMessrs. Qlsson can hold out no hope of obtaining tugs inSweden.   The Admiralty have also stated that owing to the slowrate of motion of the rafts (estimated at 2\ knots) it wouldbe impossible to provide efficient -protection.   The proposalhas therefore been abandoned so far as this Ministry isconcerned.I am,Sir,lour obedient Servant,(Signed) JOHN ANDERSON.

</content>
</cab>
