<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/17/0 images: 252-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
**ju    23117SECM WAR   CABINET.G.T. 1161SHOMAS BF OATS AND FORAGE IB ITALY *(Note by Sir E. Wyldbore Smith)I think it my duty to inform the War Cabinet that theshortage of oats and forage in Italy has become so acute thatit is likely to seriously affect military operations.I am informed by the head of the Military Mission that ithas been necessary to reduce the daily ration for horses andmules from 5 kilos, or 11 lbs, to 1-g- kilos, or 3.3 lbs per diem,a ration which is quite inadequate for animals on service.   Theminimum quantity required to be imported each month in order tomaintain the normal daily ration of 11 lbs per horse is 60,000tons.During the first 5 months of this year, the quantity of oatsand forage actually imported into Italy only amounted to 62,500tons, cr approximately 20fo of their requirements.The enormous deficit is accoimted for in the main by wantof tonnage, while of the tonnage that was obtained, approximately30,000 tons was sunk during the 5 months referred to, and owingto the seriousness of the wheat position it was found necessaryto divert to that service.a quantity of tonnage amounting to45,000 tons which had been originally intended for oats.The quantity of oats and forage which it was antici-patedwould arrive in Italy during the current month of June &quot;was52,000 tons.   Unfortunately, however, a large steamer carrying7,000 tons has been sunk, and even if no further disasters occur,this quantity would be reduced to 45,000 tons.So far as can be seen at present the amount of tonnageavailable for allocation for July shipments under the mostfavourable circumstances &quot;Will not amount to more than IS,000 ton3.The matter has been laid before the Shipping Controller whohas, however, replied that it. is impossible for him to allocateadditional ship&apos;S to this&apos; service, in view of the pressing needfor July loading of other essential services of the Allies and ofthis country.     In this connection Sir Joseph Maclay points outthat recent requirements of Italy for additional collier tonnage -and the heavy demands of her wheat service have already absorbedmany vessels which were only provided with the utmost difficulty.On the 25th May, the Italian Minister of Agriculture report-ed that the available stocks would only suffice for 15 days1supply of reduced rations.     These stocks must now have been .consumed.     A telegram received from Rome states that tho newcrop of oats will not be available before the beginning ofAugust and that in any ease it is anticixmted that this cropwill be inferior to that of previous years.The question for the consideration of the Cabinet thereforeis what immediate measures can be takon to make uo the Jiuiedeficit of&quot;15,000 tons and tho July deficit of 40&quot;,000 tons ?
Tho Shipping Controller has suggested that pressure shouldbe brought to bear on the United States Government for assistanceby means of American tonnage..     3hould such assistance beforthcoming,, it will not, I fear, be of the immediate characterwhich would appear to be essential.     The only sources of promptassistance would appear to bo :(a) The French (Jove mutant.(b) The British War Office,(o)     The British Civilian 0at3 supply.With regard to (a) I am making representations to the FrenchDe 2*6 gate 3 on this Commission.(b) The War Office have undertaken to see whether itwould be possible to divert one of their cargoes.to Italy.(c) The stock of oats in this country for civilianrequirements amounts to&quot;, I understand, approximately sixweeks1 supply,, and I think that it is a matter for theconsideration of the Cabinet whether the situation in Italyis not sufficiently serious to warrant the diversion toItaly of a few cargoes of oats destined for British civilianrequirements during the months of June and July.(Signed)E. 7/YLDBOBE SMITH.23/6/17,.

</content>
</cab>
