<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/17/0 images: 337-337</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret 288protection gy trade bst1t5en holland ahd great britainG.T.1179The question of protecting the convoys between Holland andGreat Britain depends in the first instance on the strength ofthe force tho enemy can use to attackj^onvoys and the naval,resources available to protect them.In order to run convoys more frequently it would be necessaryfor the Admiralty to reduce the number of vessels protectingthem.     It requires 18 modern destroyers and 3 light cruisersto afford adequate protection to a convoy, having in view %hdstrength of tho force the onemy can quickly concentrate to attackit.    Should a weaker British force be used there is a very graverisk of its being&apos; annihilated by superior enemy forces and theconvoy being sunk, thus giving the enemy a naval success and theBritish a troublesome reverse, ,with all its attendant consequences,moral and practical..   . The British vessels lost .could nojt Wreplaced without weakening our forces in other directions, andthe. enemy would be able to prevent any further trade &quot;with Hollanduntil ourescvehdoncy&apos; was re-established,     &quot;&quot;The Harwich force which furnishes protection for the con-voya has also other important duties to perform:   it is impossibleto protect convoys every, four or five days and yet keep the forceavailable for.&quot;these duties also: . the ships act as a coveringforce for operations on the Belgian coast, such as the recentbombardments of Zeebrugge and Ostend;   they provide reinforcementsfor the Dover force during the period of dark nights with a viewto preventing raids, by enemy destroyers on the Kentish Coast orthe shipxiing. in the Downs;   the force is .sent out whenever thereis. ac/tivity on the part of the enemy destroyers dr.other res sols,and is used also to protect minelayers and to operate &quot;againstsubmarines.The sailings of the convoys.have to be arranged with dueregard, to. these other duties and also with reference &quot;to. the activityof the enemy vessels and submarines: it is.impocsibleto&apos;$reat them.as a purely commercial concern or to run them onRegular dates arranged some, time beforehand. ;;;    ,:nHowever, desirable regularity may be in business, it is :absolutely contrary:to the principles .of naval warfare;:&apos; if the..convoys.were run regularly the enemy would;forecast their sailingsmid could bring out a force sufficient to deal&apos; with the whole ,Harwich&apos; fo r ce by sending&apos; a squadron from&quot;(xerman.;.&apos;tbr,ts &apos;&quot;to supplementthe :veesela fr 6m. Belgian Ports,    ;The&apos;;present,&apos;&quot;arfaingeme-aits&apos;&apos;:&apos;areonly adequate to cope.with the forces which the enemy&apos;^an eoncen-. trate from Belgian /Ports and.short.notice-andIirregular &quot;datesfcave to be relied on to a large extent for socuxityThe safetyof vessels trading .wita Hblland would be easily a ecured &quot;if theBelgiaa;Ports were in&quot; Bri13.sh hands or rendered untenable for the&quot;enemy.    It would then ba&quot; necessary, for enemy vessels to startfrom German Ports to intercept the trade and return&apos;to&apos;themafterwards;   time and distance would be toiour advantage aad therisk of being cut off would teter the enemy/aTtaeking&apos; the tradewith surface vessels except with large forces.es a major operation.If no enemy vessels were based on the Belgian Ports the trade would -follow a route many miles to the southward of the routes which,have: to be adopted under present conditions and sufficient noticeof the&quot;movement of the enemy forces would almost certainly bereceived from our scouting vessels to enable the trade to reachPort and avoid attack.AMIHLATY.  ,25th June, 1917

</content>
</cab>
