<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/194/24 images: 598-607</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s government cp(77) 24copy no March 1977cabinetPUBLIC EXPENDITURE PRIORITIES IN THENEXT SURVEYMemorandum by the Central Policy Review staff. This paper is concerned with public expenditure priorities withinwhatever total of expenditure Ministers may approve.    It is not about what the totals should be.2. Ministers take their main decisions on public expenditure in the context of the annual Public Expenditure Survey.    This is the exercisewhich is now being launched.    If decisions on the Survey over-commitresources, this is likely to lead to ad hoc and (possibly inadequatelyconsidered) changes in programmes and priorities.    These can be of twokinds: -a. Decisions during the year about claims on the contingency-   reserve which can affect both the current year and subsequent years.b. Special exercises, such as those of last December, to effect widespread reductions.3. The time for taking operational decisions on priorities is the summer when the PESC report is available to Ministers.    No firm decisions are required now.    Nevertheless, if Ministers wish to be able tomodify their priorities in the summer they may need to have appropriateground rules for the PESC exercise or to set particular studies in motion inthe spring.    Ministers therefore have the opportunity to discuss theirpriorities now, when the annual PESC exercise is about to be launched.4.        At their meeting on 24 February (CM(77)^fth Conclusions, Minute 3)the Cabinet discussed the economic background to the next Survey.    they agreed:-a.      that decisions on levels of expenditure for the first twoyears (1977-78 and 1978-79) had already been taken.    TheGovernment is committed to keeping within the totalsannounced in the recent White Paper (Cmnd 6721);
b. to take as a planning assumption increases of 2 per cent a year in total expenditure for the last two years of the Survey(1980-81 and 1981-82);c. to consider further the planning assumption for the transitional year 1979-80.THE ROOM TO MANOEUVRE5. The growth in the totals from year to year clearly affects Ministers&apos;room to adjust their priorities.    As will be seen below, the small growth in the totals which Ministers have agreed upon inevitably circumscribes theroom to manoeuvre.    For the first two years of the Survey (1977-78 and1978-79) there is unlikely to be much scope for changes in priorities.    Theallocation of the contingency reserve allows some choice of priorities buton a very limited scale.    Apart from this remaining reserve, decisions toincrease one programme would have to be offset by savings elsewhere.After all the changes of the past 18 months, it is doubtful how much additionalswitching is possible, particularly over such a short period ahead.6. For the last three years of the Survey (1979-80 and after) a planningassumption of 2 per cent growth would allow welcome, though by paststandards relatively modest, increases in total expenditure.    Part of thatincrease is likely to be pre-empted by the open-ended commitments(eg social security) or by overspending in areas where the Government doesnot have direct control (eg local authority current expenditure).7. Apart from these programmes which are particularly difficult tocontrol or forecast, it is important that any changes whether to increase or decrease programmes should, as far as possible, be a matter ofconscious decision by Ministers.    The ground rules for this year&apos;s Surveyhave been drafted to make this possible and expenditure options, upwardsand downwards, will be identified as issues for decision.PRIORITIES8. Despite the vicissitudes of the past 18 months, the Government hasin general managed to adhere to the broad priorities agreed at Chequersin August 1975.    The Annex shows the effects of the Government1 s decisions on the growth of programmes and on the distribution between capital and current expenditure.9. In considering priorities for the years 1979-80 onwards, ministers may wish:-a.      to consider how far they are concerned -i.     to restore past cutsii. to make a small advance on a broad frontiii. to select a few programmes for more rapid growth and make room for this by holding back on others;2
b.       to note there are a number of recent major policy reviewswhich will have implications for priorities.    These include theHousing Policy Review, the Review of Transport Policy and thework which is being put in hand to relate main areas of policy tothe industrial strategy.    The CPRS Report on Population andthe Social Services should also help Ministers to take account offoreseeable changes in population size and composition in the1980s.PROGRAMMES DIFFICULT TO CONTROL OR FORECAST10.       A number of policy issues pose particular difficulties.    Someprogrammes are not directly controlled by central government.    Open-ended or demand-responsive programmes, which do not lend themselvesto control by cash limits, also pose problems both in estimating them inthe Survey and in the control of expenditure throughout the year.    other things being equal, it is desirable to reduce the extent of such programmes and to improve the methods of control.    The main programmes concerned are:-a. Social Security expenditure accounts for over a fifth of total public expenditure and is open-ended.    Recent experience shows the difficulties involved in making any downward adjustments which require legislation.    Ministers will need to consider whether, giventhese constraints, their commitments in the social security fieldshould be limited to what is required either by statute or by existingundertakings.b. Industry and employment.    In December Ministers agreed to additional provision of  200 million in 1977-78 and 1978-79.    this included extra resources for the not for initial funding of the selective Investment Scheme, for industry schemes, and for measuresto alleviate unemployment - for example the Temporary EmploymentSubsidy.    Cabinet has subsequently approved Stage I of the revisedInterim Strategy for Shipbuilding.    There are also proposals forfurther employment measures.    Pressure for additional expenditure under these heads is likely to continue while unemployment remainshigh.    The nature of some of the expenditure makes it difficult to predict its amount.c. Housing.   In the case of council house building, which was previously open-ended as a matter of policy and not because it did notlend itself to control, it has now been agreed that cash limits shouldbe applied.    Housing subsidies, on the other hand, including subsidiesfrom the rates, are open-ended and can fluctuate widely with changesin interest rates.3
d. Local authority current expenditure.    When local authoritieshave all settled their local budgets for 1977-78, it will be possible tosee whether, in total, their current expenditure is likely to be consistent with that underlying the rate support grant settlement.There is, however, no direct Government control, and there can beno assurance that expenditure limits will be observed.e. Export Credit Refinancing.    Forecast expenditure onrefinancing fixed rate export credit has already been reduced forthe next two years (from 1977-78).    The programme will nolonger be completely open-ended as in the past.    Nevertheless, itwill continue to be sensitive to demand and difficult both to forecastand control.PRIORITIES WITHIN PROGRAMMES11.       In general, the priorities between programmes have been held overthe past two years.    In some cases they have had to be modified - to take account of the need to cut where it seemed least difficult to do so.Inevitably, therefore, one effect of the cuts has been to cause a significantswitch within programmes from capital to current expenditure.    (Annex,Chart C).    Ministers will have to consider whether this change has produced a better balance between capital and current expenditure or whether they will want to change the balance, at least within some programmes, when moreresources are available.IE.       There are several important outstanding issues which may involvere-assessing the priorities within the major programmes, for example:-a. Defence:    The defence budget ha6 been cut four timessince the Defence Review related our commitments and capabilitiesto the resources available.    The figure for 1978-79 is nearly8 per cent below the &quot;critical&quot; level for the year agreed in theDefence Review.    The measures needed to secure the cut of 230 million announced in December 1976, about which NATOmust be consulted, are being considered.b. Transport:    The review of transport policy is in progress and a White Paper is expected in the spring.    Within a reducedmotorway and trunk road programme, the emphasis is being placed on schemes which assist industrial, export and environmentalobjectives.    It would obviously help if more could be done to reducethe subsidies to British Rail by raising productivity.4
CONCLUSIONS13.       In considering their approach to priorities in the 1977 PESC,Ministers have to operate against a background of virtually no room tomanoeuvre in the first two years of the Survey (1977-78 and 1978-79)and of the resumption of modest growth in public expenditure in the last three years (1979-80 and after).    Some of the room for choice of prioritiemay well represent-empted by programmes which are open-ended, difficult to predict, or outside the control of the Government.14.       Given this position, Ministers might wish to consider:-a. How far, 1979-80 and after, they are concerned -i.     to restore past cuts in programmesii.     to have a small expansion on a broad frontiii.     to select a few programmes for more rapid growth and hold back the others.If they wish to be selective, what criteria would they adopt?b. How far the extent of open-ended and uncertain commitments(eg social security) means that new commitments in these fieldsshould be avoided?c. Whether the balance between capital and current expenditure needs to be considered in some programmes?    if so, which programmes?d. Whether any additional action is needed on prioritieswithin major programmes - eg defence, inner cities,transport, greater selectivity in industrial and employmentprogrammes ?e. In the light of their discussion, do Ministers wish togive instructions for any work additional to the PESC Surveyto assist decision-taking on priorities when they receive thePESC Report next summer?Cabinet Office9 March 1977
1.   Ministers had a comprehensive discussion of their priorities at chequers in August 1975&quot;   Their main conclusions were to give high priority to the industrial programmes, housing investment and innercities and relatively low priority to parts of the education, and road and transport programmes.   They also agreed that there should he a move towards greater selectivety in the social services and that eventhe high priority programmes could not he exempt from cuts or treatedas an open-ended commitment.2.   The first two charts show the growth of the main programmes between1973-74 and 1978-79 in volume terms (Chart A) and in cost terms (chart B).The charts show the fastest growth in the Social Security, Trade,Industry and Employment, and Personal Social Service programmes; andactual falls in Defence, Education, Roads and Transport, and environmental services.*3*-   Rates of growth are at best only rough and ready indicators of priorities.   But the pattern shown in Charts A and B are in generalconsistent with the priorities agreed at Chequers, and endorsed by theMinisters in their discussion of priorities in March 1976&quot; (CC(76) 12thMinute 3.)   The balance has been, somewhat affected by the demands of open-ended programmes (in particular Social Security) and newexpenditures (eg in the field of employment.   The housing programme hasnot grown at as fast a rate as some ofthe other priority programmes,but it was already at a very high level in 1974-5 (particularly if the big relative rise in construction costs and interest rates is takeninto account); and that level has been broadly maintained in 1975&quot;and 1976-7-4. Chart C shows the change in the proportion for capital and current-expenditure in 1978-79 between the White Paper of 1975 (CMD 5879) andthe current White Paper (CMND 6721) in six major programmes.ooupiraasTTAi.
Notes on Chart A      1.  Trade, Industry and EmploymentExcluding refinancing of shipbuilding lending and fixed rate export credits and support for the nationalised industries.2.  Overseas aid, etc.Excludes contributions to the European Communities, etc. (net) and sterling Area guarantees.CHARTAGrowth of programmes 1973/74 to 1978/79 : Volumeterms  million at 1976 survey prices0        3,000     6,000     9,000    12,000Annual average growth rate6% 4 2 0i r5.04.73.33.12.82.011.4-0.2-0.2-2.2-3.2Social securityTrade, industry and employmentPersonal social services law, order and protective servicesHousingOverseas aid etc.HealthDefenceEducation and librae science and artsRoads and transport;j    other environmentalservicesLmmm1973/741978/796%0        -2-4%0        3,000     6,000     9,000    12,000
Notes on Chart B     1.  Trade, Industry and EmploymentExcluding refinancing of shipbuilding lending and fixed rate export credits and support for the nationalised industries.2.  Overseas aid, etc.Excludes contributions to the European Communities, etc. (net) and sterling Area guarantees.CHARTBAnnual average growth rate6% 4 2 0Growth of programmes 1973/74 to 1978/79 : Cost terms  million at 1975/76 outturn prices5.04.13.32.430.20.20.1-2.0-3.90        3,000     6,000     9,000    12,000-1-1-1-Social securityTrade, industry and employmentPersonal social services overseas aid etc.HealthLaw, order and protective servicesDefenceEducation and libraries, science and artsHousingRoads and transport^   Other environmentalservices1973/741978/79J6%-2-4%0        3,000     6,000     9,000    12,000
CHARTCPublic expenditure 1978/9 : Selected programmes change in current and capital expenditure between CMND 5879 (1975) and CMND 6721 (1977)8,0006,0004,0002,000  million at 1976 survey prices(CMND 5879)CapitalCurrent(CMND6721)Capital1Current21RoadsandtransportOtherenviron-mentalservicesHousingEducationandlibraries,science and artsLaw,order andprotectiveservicesPercentage change21Healthandpersonalsocialservices8,0006,0004,0002,000104-o1020304050r


</content>
</cab>
