<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/28/8 images: 104-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for&quot; the War Cabinet.   October 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. .(42).138th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEYlit is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 138 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street.S. W. 1, on Monday, October 12, 1942, at 5 - 30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson, I The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Lord President of the Council. J    M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce, Repre-- sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.H.H. the Maharaja Jam Saheb of nawanagar, Representative of India.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Sir Ramaswami Mudaliar, &quot;Represen-tative of India.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. , Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, R.C.,M.P., Postmaster-General (Item 3).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[24483]
WAR CABINET 138 (42).Contents. . .     .minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations........      .........      79Air Operations:Home theatre.Malta.Egypt.Pacific.Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations:-  Egypt.Madagascar.Pacific-Russia.2      Naval Operations      .......&apos;.      ....      .....    ....       ...      79Protection of South Atlantic convoys.3      Air Services    ................      ....      ......&apos;..      79Middle East.4      Home Front   ....................      ....      ....      80Publicity policy.
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(Previous   .Reference:W.M; (42) 131stConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations..Home Theatre.Malta.Egypt.Pacific.naval operations.Shipping Losses.MilitaryOperations.Egypt.Madagascar.Pacific.Kussia.1. The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of thepast week.Bomber,Command had attacked Aachen (450 tons of bombs)and Osnabruck. (460 tons of bombs). A number of daylight attacks had been carried out by Mosquitoes. 456 mines had been dropped and reports had been received, that 12 small ships had been sunk.Coastal Command had made several promising attacks on U-boats.Fighter Command had carried outjover 2,000 sorties, of which 650had been when accompanying the United States Fortresses in their attck on Lille. (A fair assessment, on our standards, of thenumber of enemy fighters destroyed by the United States Air force during this attack would be between 12 and 20.) In the hometheatre the enemy had lost 8 aircraft destroyed, 2 probably destroyed and 10 damaged. Our losses had been 4 fighters, 24 bombers and3 Coastal Command aircraft.On the previous day a large number of German and italian aircraft had made 6 attacks against aerodromes on the Island. Thefirst 5 attacks had caused no damage. The results of the last attack had not yet been reported. Enemy losses against Malta for the weekhad been 17 aircraft destroyed, 5 probably destroyed and28 damaged. Our losses had been 1 fighter destroyed and 3 damaged.Our activity against enemy landing grounds had increased.Enemy losses had been 28 aircraft destroyed, 16 probably destroyed and 31 damaged. Our losses had been 27 fighters and bombersdestroyed and 8 damaged.Rabaul had been bombed by our aircraft and heavily damaged.During the&apos; previous 7 days our merchant shipping losses amounted to 228,000 tons. This figure included the Orcades andthe Duchess of A tholl, which between them totalled some 43,000 tons.It was thought that there had only been 4 missing from theDuchess of A tholl and that practically everybody had been saved from the Orcades. There had been no news of the Oronsay sincemaking a distress signal off Freetown cn the 9th October.There had been active patrolling during the past week.Our forward troops were now south of Antsirabe and had met with some -opposition.Australian troops advancing through the Owen Stanley Rangewere in contact with the enemy, who continued to retire.At Stalingrad the infantry and tank fighting had been lessintense, but there had been more artillery fire. In the Grozni areathere had been no change and on the Terek River the Russians had had a success. The Germans had made slight progress towards theGeorgian Pass and also in the Tuapse area.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.naval operations.Protection ofSouth atlantic convoys.2. Arising out of the previous Minute, the War, cabinet discussed certain arrangements in regard to convoys in the south atlantic. A record of the discussion and the conclusions reachedis contained in the S.ecretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Air Services.Middle East.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 118thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. At their Meeting on the 25th August the War Cabinet had invited the Secretary of State for Air, in consultation with theFirst Lord of the Admiralty, to submit a scheme for providing theadditional aircraft required to enable a firm allocation of 6,000 lbs.a week to be made, as from the end of September 1942, for the carriage of mails for troops in the Middle East.The War Cabinet how had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Air dealing with this matter (W P(42)436).In his Memorandum, the Secretary of State explained that thescheme for the expansion of the total load-carrying capacity set out
in the Report of the Committee on Air Services to the Middle East(W.P. (42) 275) could only be fulfilled by a reinforcement of theB.O.A.C. fleet by the allocation of 6 Sunderland flying-boats and14 Warwick land planes. These planes, however, would not be readyuntil the New Year, and (since they were required to ensure fulfil-ment of the existing programme) were not available to carry troopmails.In the circumstances, he proposed that the aircraft required toprovide a firm allocation of 6,000 lbs. a week for the carriage of mails to the Middle East should be met by allocating furtherLiberator aircraft to 1425 Flight.The Postmaster-General referred to the paragraph in theSecretary of State&apos;s Memorandum in which he said that he couldnot accept the obligation that all troop mails should be taken by the direct route through the Mediterranean unless the War Cabinetruled that troop mail was in all circumstances to have absolute priority over other urgent traffic. The Postmaster-General saidthat it had been agreed inter-Departmentally that, while the newair letter service to the Middle East would be sent via West Africa,the airgraph service should be taken by the direct route throughthe Mediterranean. He also hoped that there would be no undue or&apos;unnecessary delays in the service of land planes taking the air letterservice from West Africa to Cairo.The Secretary of State said that the Air Ministry would do all they could to ensure the success of the new service.The War Cabinet-      *Approved the proposals set out in the Secretary of State&apos;sMemorandum.Home Front. 4.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the publicity Policy. Minister of Information (W.P. (42) 454).War Cabinet Took note of this Memorandum, and asked the Ministerof Information to furnish, for their information, aMemorandum explaining the system adopted in the com-compilation of these reports, more particularly from the pointof view of ensuring that due weight was attached to thevarious opinions reported.(Previous TheEef erence:W.M. (42) 119thConclusions,Minute 11.)Great George Street, SWT,October 12, 1942.



</content>
</cab>
