<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/44/6 images: 96-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1943.W.P. (43) 558.Qth December, 1943.WAR CABINET.REPORT ON DEMOBILISATION.Memorandum by the Minister of Health and the Secretary ofState for Scotland.1. We have read the report of the Demobilisation Committee (W.P. (43)494) and the memorandum by the Minister of Works giving an estimate of thenumber of building craftsmen to be demobilised from the Forces under theCommittee&apos;s proposals (W.P. (43) 543) and we are seriously concerned about theeffect of those proposals on house building after the war.2. On the basis of the paper submitted by the Minister of Works to theCommittee on Reconstruction Priorities (P.R. (43) 44), it was estimated that itwould be possible to carry out only a comparatively small programme of about30,000 houses in Great Britain as a whole in.the first year after the war and170,000 in the second year. The Minister of Works points out. that if effect weregiven to the scheme now proposed by the Demobilisation Committee the number ofhouses which could be built in the first year after the war would be reduced toabout 13,000 and the number in the second year to only about 100,000. a programme on this scale would be wholly inadequate and impossible to justify to public opinion.3. In the memoranda (W.P. (43) 489 and W.P. (43) 497) which were sub-niitted to the War Cabinet on the 30th October on the question of building labour for housing work concern was expressed as to the seriousness of housing conditions at the present time, and it has been repeatedly emphasised that new building isthe only effective remedy for these conditions.4. A par&apos; altogether from demobilisation, the progressive increase in thedischarge of married men from the Services as casualties are incurred and theimmediate reunion of civilian husbands and wives at the end of the european war will together make a situation calling for immediate and evident activity.It is our considered view that the Government will be faced with a dangerous andexplosive situation unless a very substantial programme of new building isinitiated immediately the war ends and it can be made clear to those in need bythe visible evidence of houses in course of construction throughout the country thatthe Government are taking energetic action.5. A further point is that the scheme proposed by the Demobilisation Com-mittee would probably have a very serious effect on the Government&apos;s plans for extending the building industry by importing special trainees, in accordance withthe proposals in the White Paper on training for the building industry. In ourview it would be very difficult to put the training scheme into operation at a timewhen large numbers of skilled building workers were being retained in the Forces.6. We wish to express the strongest possible disagreement with the recom-mendation in paragraph 31 of the Demobilisation Committee&apos;s report and&quot; wesupport the recommendation of the Minister of Works that a review should beundertaken of the assumptions in regard to demobilisation on which the estimates in P.R-. (43) 44 were based with a view to enabling an extended programme ofnew housing to be carried out. We also support the suggestion made by certain members of the Demobilisation Committee in paragraph 37 of the Report thata publicity campaign should be.carried out with the object of getting men in theForces to accept the overriding need in the national interest of giving priority in release to building trade workers.H. U: W.&apos; &quot; 1    t. j.Qth December, 1943.[26539]




</content>
</cab>
