<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/51/16 images: 96-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of ....l.J^k^^B^*^&apos;^.....&apos;TOP SECRET Copy No. .3.......W.M.(45) 16th conclusions confidential. Annex(8th February, 1945 - 5.30 p.m. and 10.30 p.m.)fFERENCEps ofSENMENTSOF1. The War Cabinet had beforetelegrams from ARGONAUT:-them the followingevious(ference:M. (45) 15thnclusions,nute 1)let RussiaJASON 190,  191, 220, 221,  222, 223, 228 and 229.They considered seriatim as follows the questions raised by these telegrams., (1) JASON 220, paragraph 3 - Proposed Assurance tothe Soviet Government regarding the Ukraineand White russia the Russians had now accepted the whole ofthe proposals of the Americans for the DumbartonOaks constitution and had reduced their demand for16 votes in the Assembly (to represent the 16 soviet socialist Republics) to two.      They based their claim on the plea that the Ukraine and White Russia had suffered so much &quot;and fought so well that they shouldbe included among the founder members of the new world organisation.      The President, who obviouslysaw difficulties from the American standpoint,    - ..nevertheless by no means rejected this idea,proposing that it should be submitted to a conferenceof the United Nations to be convened during March.The Prime Minister felt that our position was somewhat different and that we asked a great deal ofan Assembly of this kind in having four or five members (six if India was included; when Russia had only one.     It was not too much that Russia   should ask for two besides their chief, while he wouldlike to be able to make a friendly gesture in thematter to Russia in view of other important concession;by them which were achieved or pending.     Moreoverwe should derive advantage from not being the onlymultiple voter in the field.     He accordinglyinvited the War Cabinet to authorise the foreign secretary and himself to give the Russians an assurance in the nature.of a gentleman1s agreement that when this matter came to decision, whetherhere or at the American conference in March, weshould favour their view.The following points were made in discussionj.-(a)    The- present Russian proposal represented asubstantial improvement on their original demand forplaces for the whole sixteen Soviet socialist republics.      It was clear, apart from this, that thePrime Minister attached&apos;importance to being able tomake a friendly gesture to Russia in view of other important concessions by them which were achieved or which were pending. ...

813 Isi &apos;-\ W&amp; 48(b) The great importance of taking the President&quot;and the United States with us was emphasised.     Whilefrom JASON 220 it might perhaps be assumed.that thePresident was aware of and would support thearrangements proposed, could we be certain that hewould be able to hold to that position if opposition  .developed in the United States?.     If he was not, andwe were by then.committed to support the Russianthesis, our position might be difficult..(c) THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR DOMINION affairs pointed out the close interest of-the Dominions inthis matter.    He was uneasy at their possiblereaction-to a decision taken on it without consultation,  though he recognised the impossibilitybecause of the timetable of consulting them.If we were to accept the Russian thesis, it would be unfortunate if thereafter we were unable to secureDominions support with the result that they mightbe in opposition at the March Conference.(d) While the   Russian demand/was in respect oftwo or possibly three (see JASON 223, paragraph 2)of the Soviet Socialist Republics,  there was no difference in principle between the position ofthose selected and that of the remaining fourteen.If the principle was now conceded in their case,might&apos;not the Russians claim that the others shouldbe brought in at a subseqguent date?     The testoriginally proposed had been that the states concerned should enjoy real independence in&quot; foreignpolicy.      It was pointed out that White Russia andthe Ukraine both had European and not internalRussian frontiers, and that a differentiation couldbe justified on this extent      It should not be overlookedthat even so Russia, with her vast population, wouldhave three seats only while the British Empire wouldhave five or six, including India, and the UnitedStates (though she could influence the south american Republics) would in her own right have oneseat only-.     Our position in resisting the Russiansuggestion might be very difficult to defend.     Thealternative would be to agree to three places for russia, allowing her to choose whom she pleased.THE WAR CABINET agreed that we should not go beyondthe admission of two of the Soviet SocialistRespublics viz.    the Ukraine and White Russia, as originally proposed by the Russians;    but that theimportance of securing an understanding from theRussians which would protect us-from subsequentsimilar claims from any other Soviet socialist republics should be represented to the Prime Minister.After further discussion the War Cabinet -Agreed that the Prime Minister-&apos; s &apos; proposal should be approved, subject to the pointstaken in (b), (c) and (d)  above.THE MINISTER OF LABOUR&quot;,  THE SEGRETARY OF STATEFOR WAR AND THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE DOMINIONS,while accepting the decision of the Cabinet, were .anxious that the Prime Minister should know that theywere not themselves in agreement with it.     TheDominions Secretary was concerned with the possible  -effect on the Dominions, while the Minister of Labourand the Secretary of -State for War would have preferred that we should not commit ourselves inadvance of the United States Government. - .

findeviousference:M. (45) 10thjnclusions.,Lnute 1)The War Cabinet next .considered the Polishposition.      In--paragraph 5 of JASON 220 the PrimeMinister had informed them that a reply had beenreceived from the Russians to a proposal by thePresident that the existing Lublin Government should give place to a new all-Polish Government, containingboth representatives from the Poles abroad and thosewithin Poland, which did not in principle challengeany of the broad issues.     A counter proposal tothe original Soviet proposal for settling the polish question, had now been drafted by the foreign secretary,, The text was given in JASON 221.      ThePrime Ministorand the Foreign Secretary felt thatif eight or ten of the Polish element with which wehud at present been associated,  together with anumber of Poles in Poland who had been listed bythe Americans, could be incorporated in the lublin government,  it would pay us to recognise thatGovernment straight away.     He expressed the hopethat the War Cabinet would give the Foreign secretary and himself full liberty to act and manoeuvre on this difficult groundsThe War Cabinet agreed that the foreign secretary&apos;1 s proposal was a great improvement on theoriginal Soviet proposal,and1s WesternndarySome uneasiness was felt,  on the other hand,as to a cornmitment that Poland should receive inthe mainland of Germany,  in. addition to theadministrative district of Oppeln,  &quot;the lands ;desirec1 by Poland to the east of the line of theOder;t,      It was felt that the difficulties seen by the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary inthe discussion in the War Cabinet on 26th January(W. ii, &apos;..K&apos;:-) 10th Conclusions, Minute 1), had lostnone of their force.      Vast transfers of population would be involved;    it was uncertain whother.poland would be able to populate and develop territoriesso extensive, and Germany/&apos; s dependence on food imports would be greatly increased.      Moreover,public opinion, both in Parliament and in thecountry, was increasingly critical of the exaggeratedterritorial demands, which had been put forward bythe Lublin Poles,      It would be preferable ifpossible to avoid tying our hands at this stage morethan was actually necessary, and to leave the finaldecision to the Peace Conference.e PolishernmentAfter discussion, THE WAR CABINETsuggest to the Prime Minister that the   FSecretarys revised proposal, as set outparagraph 2(b) (1&apos;i)  of JASON 221,  should bby the substitution for the words, &quot;and thdesirec  by.Poland to the- east of the lineOder&quot; of the words &quot;and such other landseast of the line of the Oder as at the PeConference it shall be considered desirabtransfer to Poland.&quot;   - The effect would ba decision on this matter in the hands ofUnited.Nations and not to leave it to thePoles. .decided tooreignine.amendede landsof theto theacele toe to keepthePublinThe War Cabinet fully agreed with the PrimeMinister as to the necessity for&apos; a sovereign and independent Polish Government, based ultimately onfree elections.     &quot;Attention was drawn to thepossibility that between the formation of.the   -Provisional Government now in view and the &quot;date when

the elections had been &quot;held, that Government might beso reconstituted as to eliminate wholly or in part the non-communist elements with which we -had been associated, and in whose interest it was that free elections should be held.      The War Cabinet agreedthat this point should be touched on in the reply tothe Prime Minister, and that the hope should be expressed&apos;that, as part of any such arrangement, he might be able to secure that the- balance of the newProvisional Government should be maintained in itsintegrity until after the elections had been held.ridganisationreviousjference:M. (45) 4thinclusions,nu-te 4)The War Cabinet -Took note with great satisfaction of theagreement that had been achieved by thePrime Minister and the Foreign Secretaryover the voting problem, and warmlycongratulated them on it.membermentGermanyIn JASON 190 and 191  the Prime minister informed the War Cabinet of the developments in thediscussion at the Conference of Heads of Governmentsabout the dismemberment of&apos;Germany.     Marshal stalin had strongly pressed for dismemberment, and hadreceived a degree of support from the Americans.It had finally been agreed that the. Foreign Secretariesshould consider how a reference to dismembermentshould be inserted in the terms of surrender, and thebest method of studying the question.      It was furthersubsequently settled that a Committee to consist ofthe Foreign Secretary and the Russian and UnitedStates Ambassadors in London was to be set up to workout &quot;the study of questions regarding procedure ofthe p.1 smemberment of Ge rinany&quot;.In discussion the following points were made:-(a)    It was by no means clear what precisely was involved in &quot;dismemberment&quot;.     Was it the severancefrom the pre-war German Reich of areas such as Austria,East Prussia and those.parts jf Silesia that it was proposed to give to Poland;    or the breaking-up of theunitary Government in Germany,  or the breaking-up ofGermany into a number of&apos;small states?     It was difficult,  in the absence of fuller information,  toreach a final conclusion.(b) The general issue of dismemberment raisedeconomic and political questions of great importance.It had not so far been considered in Cabinet or (saveas affecting East Prussia, etc.) in the A.P.W. committee it was desirable to avoid any commitment until thematter as a whole could be reviewed by the Cabinet.(c) It was pointed out,  on the other hand, that the&quot;term &quot;dismemberment&quot;, appeared to be intended merely, to-cover a wide range of possibilities which would have tobe examined and discussed in the proposed LondonCommittee under the Foreign Secretary, before any commitment was made.      It would be desirable incidentallythat the French should be represented on this Committee.

The War cabinet invited the Deputy Prime Minister toinform the Prime Minister of the sense of the discussion, and that the WarCabinet were anxious to be able toconsider the implications ofdismemberment, however defined, before any binding commitment was enteredinto.After further discussion the War Cabinoinvited the Deputy Prime Minister toarrange for the draft of a telegram tothe Prime Minister and the foreign secretary to be prepared for their consideration.The War Cabinet resumed their meeting at10.30 p.m.  on 8th February and,  subject to various amendments, approved a draft telegram tothe Prime Minister which was despatched asFLEECE 324 of 9th February.

3.      The War Cabinet had before them(a) Telegram No* JASON.226 of 8thFebruary containing -J       -a Soviet proposal for the composition and terras of reference of an Allied Reparation committee at Moscow and the principles toform the basis of the detailedplan for the exaction of.  reparations from Germany. &apos;   .....(b) Draft of a telegram from theChancellor of the Exchequer and theForeign-Office to the Foreign      - -Secretary, commenting&apos;on theSoviet proposal, together with a- revised proposal for the basis and principles to govern the proposedAllied Separation Committee.A general discussion took place.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that hedisliked principle 2(a) proposed by theSoviet in JASON 226 and regarded 2(b) as -quite unsound.    Indeed, the.Russian   ,presentation of the reparations case was   -in many respects fantastic.    We should,however, have to handle Russia in this&apos; :matter with some -delicacy.    We did not yetquite know what the attitude of the. UnitedStates would be.    In one important respectthere had been a modification in the originalRussian draft since JASON 228 showed that it-had now been agreed that in paragraph&apos; 1 of theSoviet proposals mention should also be madeof sacrifices borne.In the ensuing discussion the followingpoints were made:-(1) Was it wise to contemplate pressing for reparations at all?   We were going to imposevery hard terms on Germany under the peace treaty.    We must carry public opinion with ushere.   Extravagant demands for reparations might at once lose us the support of public opinionwithout giving us the^ reparations which wewere promised on paper.    The&apos;&apos;history&quot; of reparations after the last war was a warning.(2)    The Russian demand for reparations on the

scale that they had indicated Was hardly-compatible; with their proposal for thedismemberment of Germany.    A dismemberedGermany,deprived of all save 20 per cent of her machinery and equipment would surelynever be able -to pary reparations&quot;on thescale proposed.    The only effect&apos;of trying to sec\ire them would: be to destroy hereconomy, reduce her to the position of aslavy nation and, in the interests ofEurope as a whole, make it necessary forthe Allies at a later stage, as happened afterthe last war,, to come to her financialand economic assistance.(3) To the extent that we did decide&quot; torequire reparations, we should do well(apart from items such as timber andpotash) as regards the removal-ofmachinery and equipment to confine ourselves to industries which had a war potentialvalue such as synthetic oil and the like.We should have public opinion behind us inbreaking up selected industries of thatcharacter, and the balance that would beleft to Germans&apos;- would give her a        ,sufficiency on which to build up her economic life.    We.should, however, bear inmind the risk, by withdrawing obsolescentor heavily worn machinery and equipment fromGermany, of making it necessary for -her indue course to re-equip herself with modernmachinery to our disadvantage..(k) So far as we were concerned, there were strong arguments against considering anyreparations etc. over a long period (though in the case of Russia she might have astrong case for drawing on German labour for a -considerable time).    The wise course was to get all that we thought it wise toremove from Germany out of that country during the first two years after the war,and thereafter give her a chance to do whatshe could with the balance.    It was relevantthat the destruction of industry in germany would, at the end of this war, have beenoon an infinitely greater, scale &quot;than at the  -end of the last war.(5) It was urged, on the other hand, that whatever our own feeling might be as to the wisdom of the Russian tactics, it was questionable whether we could stop Russia,from stripping the Russian zone of machineryif she desired to do so.  &quot;Russia had very strong moral claims to restitution and rehabilitation.    If-we were unable to steerher into more moderate courses, it might benecessary for us to let her go her own wayafter stating her own point of view.

&apos; The Deputy Prime Minister said he thought the general sense of the War Cabinet was as follows;-(1) Reparations must be considered together with, and as partof, any policy of dismemberment.(2) The two objects which the Russians had in view, thedepletion of the manufacturing capacity of Germanyand. the preservation of her ability-to make largeannual reparation payments, were really essentiallyincompatible with one another.     The wise course, andthe one we should concentrate on, would be the maximumwithdrawal from the German potential over a period of,say, two years.     The history of what happened overreparations at the end of the last war, and thepossibility that the United States of America might, at.a relatively early date, cease to take part in-theoccupation of Germany, were strong arguments for ensuring that -anything we were to secure should besecured in- the first two years after the end of the war.(3) While it might, be&apos; possible for, the U.S.S.R. and other allies to absorb deliveries of manufactured goods from current production over a longer period^ our own economic situation would only permit us to accept-certain raw materials.(h) We must decide whether or not we wanted Germany tocontinue to have an economic life in the future.     in deciding what, machinery, equipment etc, to remove fromGermany the criterion should be its value,  or thevalue of the industry which it served, for war potentialWe should, concentrate on removing material of this kind,together with overseas investments.(5) We, rather than the United States or the U.S.S.R., were concerned with the future of Europe and the creation vof a decent Europe was one of our aims.  *(6) We should oppose the Russian idea of a priority class,to consist of the U.S.A.., U.S.S.R. and U.K., while&apos;the balance was left for division among the small Allies(7) We should&apos; agree to the setting up of a Committee to workout the application of the -principles, and see thatthe French and the smaller Allies should be associatedwith.this Committee. - .The./War cabinet agreed with ti-s Deputy Prime Minister and invited the Foreign -Office to arrange to submit reviseddrafts for consideration in the light of thediscussion.(6) THE PAYMASTER GENERAL felt that while 2(b)  and 3 of theprinciples proposed by the Soviet in this matter were -in conflict with 2(a) and the figures in 3 were&quot;fantastic, thegeneral.intention to de-industrialise Germany was in our interest &quot;and should not be discouraged.

iberation by    r   3* THE DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER read to- thej/ar    .ussians of Cabinet the text of.JASON 502 containing a personal,ritish Empire       message from the Prime Minister to. the Primerisoners of War   Ministers of the Dominions and the Viceroy regardingthe employment, pending their repatriation, on workin connection with the war of British Empireprisoners of war liberated by the Soviet advance.The message stated that Clause Vf of the proposed agreement With the Soviet Government had been&apos;redrafted so as Jto make sure that any work wouldo. only be permitted oh a voluntary basis and hopedthat the Prime Ministers and the /Viceroy would agree to their Governments being bound by the termsof such an Agreement.     Pending a reply, the PrimeMinister would reserve the position of the^. ,.   Government concerned in any discussions which there&quot;might be with the Soviet Government.There was.general agreement that the basisproposed by the Prime Minister was a satisfactoryone. &apos;        . . - -, &apos; &quot;THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION affairs said that the Prime Minister&apos;s tele-gram had-^crossodcertain communications which had already passed in which the same sense with the Dominion Governments.Certain of these had already accepted an. arrangement of the type proposed by the PrimeMinister, and he suggested that it .would bedesirable that in passing on the Prime Minister&apos;s&apos;personal message to the Prime Ministers concernedhe should prefix it in the case of the governments in question with a brief explanatory note... - The War Cabinet -Took note with approval of the course. - .of. action proposed in JASON 502 and 503,and agreed that the Secretary of Statefor the Dominions to take action in the sense proposed by him, and that theSecretary of State for India should communicate the Prime Minister&apos;message to the Viceroy.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
