<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/53/17 images: 142-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1944.SECRET./Copy No.W.P. (44) 417.28th July, 1944./WAR CABINET.REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON BLACK-OUT RESTRICTIONS.1. The Committee on Black-out Restrictions was appointed inFebruary 1944 &quot; to consider the possibility of making further relaxations in thepresent lighting restrictions,&quot; with a view to having ready before the end of double summer-time any plans for the further relaxation of black-out restrictions which may be consistent with security.  The membership of the Committee was the Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security (Chairman),the Secretary of State for Air,the Minister of Supply,the Minister of Aircraft Production,the Minister of War Transport,the Minister of Fuel and Power, andthe Parliamentary Secretary, Department of Overseas Trade,assisted, as necessary, by representatives of the Admiralty, Ministry of Labourand National Service, Ministry of Production and any other Departmentsconcerned.2. The Air Ministry submitted a report by the Joint Intelligence Sub-Com-mittee which stated that the bomber force which the enemy could employ against this country during the next six months was unlikely to exceed 200 long-range bombers and 35 fighter-bombers. The maximum number which might be used inone night was 100 long-range bombers and 15 fighter-bombers; intensive attackon 3-4 nights per week might be made with 80 long-range bombers and 5-10fighter-bombers, and sustained attack by 25 long-range bombers and 5 fighter-bombers. The Air Staff considered that the enemy would be likely to attack thiscountry with piloted aircraft if (a) The Germans could no longer attack by means of flying-bombs orrockets, or(b) the black-out in this country were lifted.In the latter case it was considered that the enemy would hear immediatelythat the black-out had been lifted and would probably attack with pilotedaircraft, either because they felt compelled to counter the propaganda effect oflifting the black-out, or because they hoped that the black-out would be imposedagain with its resultant effect on the morale and the war effort in these islands.3. The Air Staff considered that, with enemy bases so near to this island, no part of the country could be considered as free from the danger of air raids, butthat the northern and western counties were less likely to be attacked than theSouthern and Eastern counties and especially the London area. They considered,therefore, that any appreciable relaxations which were made in black-out restric-tions should be confined to the area roughly north and west of the line St. DavidsHead-Bracldey-Goole-Falldrk-Dingwall-Strathey Point.4. Soundings of public opinion have been taken on the subject ofrelaxations. Generally, it would appear, the public dislike the black-out, but have become convinced that it is an essential means of defence should attack bemade by piloted aircraft. They would be glad of any reasonable relaxations, butif appreciable relaxations were to be made, especially in respect of street lightingand domestic lighting, which could not be wholly extinguished on a warning, theimpression would be gained that the Government considered that the areas inwhich relaxations had been made were unlikely to be attacked.   Should such[27907]b
relaxations be followed by attack, as the Air Ministry appreciation suggests, therewould undoubtedly be an immediate demand for a reimposition of the black-out,and criticism of the Government, and of the Minister of Home Security inparticular, for taking precipitate action &quot; in the last few months of the war &quot;which increased the danger to the civil population.5. The Committee considered that on the whole it would be desirable to&apos;make relaxations in the less vulnerable parts of the country. They discussed indetail the division of the country in two parts, a vulnerable and a less vulnerablearea, the south and east of the country falling within the former zone and thenorth and west in the latter. They considered relaxations in the latter zonecould be greater than those in the former, and administratively it was essentialthat the bound cirv line sliOi ild coincide with local authority areas. The boundaryline recommended is as shown on the attached map, and all areas to the northand west are in the less vulnerable area those to the south and east in thevulnerable area. The boundary line is roughly St. Davids Head-Bletchley-Goole-Falkirk-Dingwall-Tongue.Street Lighting.6. It was considered undesirable at this stage to allow unrestricted street-lighting because of the glare which would be produced over cities and &quot;becausethe introduction of relaxations gradually would be less likely to cause anxiety to the public.In the less vulnerable area a substantial improvement could be allowed wherelights could be immediately switched off on a warning, but insistence on this requirement would restrict the benefit to the small number of towns which haveinstalled a system of central control before the war -or were aole to -obtain thenecessary materials for such an installation now (as in Liverpool). In the latter case it would only be possible to light small -areas in towns because of materialdifficulties. The Committee considered that where a centrally controlled systemalready exists, or could be installed without heavy expenditure of material andman-power, it would be possible to allow an intensity up to 0-2 f.c. subject onlyto screening above the horizontal and switching out on the purple warning. a standard of 0-2 f.c. compares favourably with much pre-war average street lighting.As regards uncontrolled street lighting, the Committee felt that, in theabsence of arrangements for prompt extinction on a warning, no standard higherthan starlight could be regarded as entirely free from risk. There would certainly be criticism if a town should be attacked with its lights on and it would -not bepossible to give any guarantee to local authorities that the lighting would beinvisible from the air if, as is likely, enquiries were received as to the securityaspect. Nevertheless, having regard to the fact that the probability of heavy attack in the less vulnerable zone is now much diminished and that in the majorityof cases no improvement can be secured except by the use of a higher standard ofuncontrolled street-lighting, the Committee consider that local authorities mightbe allowed, if they so wish and can make the change without the excessive useof materials and labour which are not readily available, to instal lighting up tothe 0-02 f.c. category. This lighting must &quot;be screened above the horizontal, andis roughly equivalent to pre-Tvar side-street lighting.The Committee realised that as soon as local authorities were informed thatthey might instal higher standards of street lighting, they would make demands for materials and man-power which, under existing priorities, cannot beprovided: also, since it would take some time to make the change, it would benecessary to inform the local authorities of the position now so that they mightcommence their preparations forthwith.The Committee considered that no priority beyond that existing at presentshould be accorded for the material and labour needed to instal the higher standards of street lighting.Internal Lighting (Domestic, Factories, &amp;c).7. Under Article 2, Lighting (Restrictions) Order, it is an offence to useany light in roofed buildings, &amp;c, which is visible from outside the premises.There appeared to be three possible courses which might be followed in the less vulnerable area : (a) The retention of the present requirements of complete black-out.(b) The complete lifting of restrictions.
(c) The adoption of an intermediate course, e.g., the relaxation of restric-tions subject to such provisions as that windows should be so screenedthat the lighting fittings are not directly visible and that roof lightsand external lights should be prohibited, i.e., a &quot; dim-out/&apos;We do not think that we have yet reached a position where restrictions canbe wholly withdrawn. The total volume of light that might be displayed from theuncurtained windows of private houses and factories in a papulous area would-be very great, it would be liable to mark the position of a town from a considerable distance, while the modified restrictions proposed elsewhere in the report forstreet, vehicle and industrial lighting would be rendered futile and possiblydangerous. No form, of central control could be applied, and it would not therefore be possible to ensure that the whole of the lighting was immediatelyextinguished on a warning. In the ease of factories, in particular, it would oftentake a considerable time to black-out, while in country districts no warning isgiven.On the other band,, the introduction of a modified system, as in (e) above,would have- considerable advantages, especially in . private houses, where a relaxation would relieve the general public of what is felt to be a depressingrequirement, would be of assistance to pedestrians in the street and in manycases would obviate the renewal of worn-out black-out material, which is now in short supply. The practical difficulties involved in any intermediate course are substantial, but it is thought that a way out can be found, in the less vunerable areas, by substituting, for the present requirement of complete obscuration, aprovision that windows and doors should be screened in such a way that the actuallight fitments are not visible from outside. Such a provision would allow the use ofany ordinary peace-time curtains or blinds, except those of the flimsiest kind, and,seen from the streets, the black-out would be replaced by a dim-out.&quot; As even this, in thickly populated areas, would mean a considerable total spill of light,though substantially less than a total relaxation, we consider that completeobscuration must still be required on a warning. This could be secured either by drawing, the black-out curtains, or, where they have been removed, byextinguishing the lights, but it is recognised that the provision would be ineffective in areas where there are no sirens, and that elsewhere individual casesof failure to obscure lights may be frequent. It is also appreciated that relaxationon these lines makes enforcement difficult.Despite these disadvantages we recommend this policy  of &quot; dim-out &quot; in theless vulnerable areas as a first step in raising restrictions rather than maintaining a complete black-out or a complete relaxation.External Lighting for Industry.8, Under this head come docks, shipbuilding and repair yards, railwaypremises, Royal Ordnance Factories and factories of all sorts. The lightingnsed externally for working purposes at these establishments is controlled,, is subject to the grant of an exemption by the Chief Constable, and can be immediately extinguished on a warning.. It was considered that a maximum wellin excess of any standard permitted hitherto and high enough to include allnormal lighting requirements could be allowed. We therefore propose thatpermission should be given for the general use in the less vulnerable areaof lighting up to the standards of 1 f.c. over working areas and 0-02 f.c. forgeneral illumination and movement. This lighting must be screened above thehorizontal and capable of extinction on a purple warning.Establishments should be informed of the decision on this matter as soon aspossible so that they may make the necessary preparations.Vehicle Lighting.9. The Committee considered that conformity should be maintained in theuse of headlamp masks over the whole country and that there should be norelaxation in this respect. Side lamps, however, could be used everywhere with one sheet of tissue paper behind the glass without limit of size or distance ofvisibility. Cycle lamps in the less vulnerable area could be used without anyobscuration provided the reflector Was rendered matt white to prevent glare toother road users.  In the vulnerable area no change is suggested.Internal lighting in trains and public service vehicles has already been increased and no improved lighting is recommended at present, particularly inview of the great shortage of material and labour-[27907] b 2
10. The Committee also reviewed the progress of the substitution ofremovable for permanent black-out in factories which is now progressingsatisfactorily.11. The Committee considered whether it was necessary to make any alterations in the public warning system in the areas affected by the proposedblack-out relaxations, but came to the conclusion that none was necessary.Arrangements for Relaxation in other Areas.12. The relaxations discussed in this report can all be introduced very quickly in other parts of the country, with the exception of street lighting andexempted industrial lighting, which require a period of preparation. If it ispossible, therefore, to forecast which areas are likely to become less vulnerablein the near future, it would be desirable to inform the local authorities, and others concerned in those areas, that relaxation of street and other lighting on the scalenow recommended for the north and west of the country may be permitted forthem at a later date so that they may examine and prepare their fittings. Weconsider that Devon, Cornwall and South Wales might be invited to makethe necessary preparations if it is decided to relax now in the north and west of the country.Date relaxations should come into force.13. We considered the time at which the relaxations recommended above should come into effect, and in view of the fact that the strategical situation maybe considerably modified in the course of the next two months, unanimously agreedthat action should be deferred till the end of September. As mentioned above,warning would have to be given now to the local authorities, factories and other authorities concerned of the relaxation of the black-out restrictions which it was proposed to introduce on a date to be appointed so that they might make thenecessary preparations.14. It was the general view of the Committee that Parliament should beinformed of the proposals before the recess, so that Parliament should share theresponsibility for the decision. It would probably be desirable for the announce-ment to make clear that the Government realised that the enemy might be tempted to attack when lighting restrictions were relaxed, but in their view the advantages to be gained from the relaxations of lighting restrictions recommended were greater than the risks.   A draft statement is attached (Appendix).Effect on other Services.15. In considering black-out relaxations the Committee realised that anything which was done on an appreciable scale would have an important effecton other services. Lifting the black-out, in part or completely, would be taken asa sign that the Government considered no more raids were likely, and if after ashort time, no raids in fact occurred, the effect on other defence services, especially the part-time services such as wardens, fireguard, Home Guard, &amp;c, would be-serious. It would be argued that if raids were so unlikely that the black-out is not necessary as a means of defence, then there is equally no need for wardens, fire-guards and Home Guards in the areas concerned. In that event the disintegrate-tion of these services must be faced or, if they are retained, a criticism of illogicalaction on the part of the Government. However, we must determine to hold suchposition in this respect as we wish.16. Summary of Recommendations.(1) That relaxations of lighting restrictions should be allowed in the less vulnerable areas, i.e., north and west of a line roughly St, DavidsHead-Bletchley-Goole-Falkirk-Dingwall-Tongue (paragraph 5).(2) That street lighting in the less vulnerable area should be allowed at0-2 f.c. for centrally controlled systems and at 0-02 f.c. for lightswhich cannot be switched off on a warning, the lighting to be screenedabove the horizontal (paragraph 6).(3) Local and other authorities should be informed so that they can make their preparations forthwith, but no priority beyond that existing atpresent should be accorded for the material and labour needed to instalthe higher standards of street lighting (paragraph 6).
(4) Internal lighting in houses, factories, offices, &amp;c, should be relaxed froma black-out to a &quot; dim-out &quot; subject to no roof lights or external lightsand complete obscuration on a warning (paragraph 7).(5) That external exempted lighting should be allowed at a maximum of1 f.c. for working areas and 0-02 f.c. for movement in the less vulnerable area (paragraph 8).(6) (a) No change should be made in regulations governing headlamps;(b) Side lamps of cars should be allowed with one sheet of tissue paperonly behind the glass throughout the whole country;(c) Cycle lamps in the less vulnerable areas should be used unscreened.provided the reflector is rendered matt white;(d) No change should be made in train and public service vehicles lighting(paragraph 8).(7) No change is necessary in warning arrangements in connection with&apos;the relaxation proposed (paragraph 11).(8) Local authorities and others concerned in other areas which may laterbecome less vulnerable areas, particularly South Wales, Devon andCornwall, should be invited to prepare for relaxation in street andindustrial lighting at a date to be announced (paragraph 12).(9) The period at which the relaxations recommended above should commenceshould be the end of September (paragraph 13).(10) That Parliament should be informed of the proposed relaxations inoutline before the Recess without the mention of specific dates(paragraph 14).H. M.(Chairman of the Committee).28th July, 1944.APPENDIX.Draft Statement on Black-out.The Government have recently reviewed the Black-out Regulations in thelight of the latest developments of the war situation and the probabilities of attack by piloted aircraft.2. It is realised that the risk of attack has not been completely removed and that any relaxation of the black-out may in fact tempt the enemy to attackas a propaganda effort. Nevertheless, in view of the improvement in the positionit is considered that a relaxation of the black-out is possible in a part of thecountry. It has therefore been decided to divide the country into two zones;the more vulnerable zone will consist of the Southern and Eastern parts of GreatBritain (including the London area). In this zone no changes in the black-outare yet considered advisable but the dividing line is not intended to be permanent and areas will be transferred from the more vulnerable to the less vulnerable zoneas circumstances permit.3. The rest of the country, on the other hand, gives some scope for relaxation-tion. This does not mean that the northern and western areas can now beregarded as beyond the range of attack and that complete relaxation of restric-tions can now be allowed. The risk of heavy attack has, however, diminished toan extent which the Government consider sufficient to justify the followingrelaxations.4. Firstly, street lighting. There is no doubt that the gioom of thedarkened streets is a major factor in producing depression and war-weariness.The Government have come to the conclusion that, in the less vulnerable zone, the black-out can now be relaxed by allowing new standards which, though not equalto pre-war lighting in some of the cities, will enable the public to move aboutwith greatly increased comfort and safety. The standards allowed will varywith the type of equipment already installed in the particular town. Where thereis a system of central control or where one can be installed without heavy expenditure of man-power or materials, so that the lights can be promptlyswitched off on a warning, the standard permissible will be comparable with thatseen before the war in the streets of the smaller towns. WThere there is no central control the lighting must be of a lower standard, and what is proposed is a
$standard: equivalent to that used before the war in side streets or to- bright moon-light. The introduction of these standards will be optional and I must make itclear that no diversion of materials or mam-power from the- war effort can be permitted m the installation of this lightiMg.5. The complete black-out of houses,, offices and other buildings is alsoburdensome, but the total volume of light produced by a complete relaxation ofthis requirement would be liable to mark the position: of towmS&apos; at considerabledistances, exposing the population to unnecessary risk. This risk, can be considerably reduced and a substantial measure of relief secured in the less vulnerable zone if, for the black-out, there is substituted a &apos;&apos; dim-out..&apos;&apos; Thismeans that the necessity of drawing curtains will be retained,, but complete black-out will&apos; not be insisted on. The emission of light throughi doors and windows willnot be prohibited provided that the source of light iac not itself visible from outside: This relaxation will not extend to- skylights or lights on the outside ofhouses, and in the event of a warning complete black-out will still be required.6. The relaxations proposed for the less vulnerable^ zone also includeimportant improvements of the external lighting&apos; used m industry and transport for vital work such as ship-bniMirig and repairing, railway marshalling yards,docks and factories.7. As regards vehicles, further relaxations must, for the present, be confined to the side-lamps of motor cars and1 to1 cycle&apos; lamps. Throughout the country, motorcar sid!e-lamps wilt require to- be dimmed by one sheet of tisstce paper only, andthere will be no- restrictions as to size or distance Of visibility. Cycle lamps inthe less vulnerable area may be used unscreened if the reflector is&quot; painted mattwhite. -8. The exact area to be covered by the vulnerable and less vulnerable areas will be communicated to local authorities concerned and through them to thepublic, but it is obviously undesirable to disclose particulars to the enemy.9. . It is not possible to give immediate effect to these changes, nor can thedate on which they will be introduced yet be stated, as there are many administra-tive details to be worked out. They will,, however, be brought into force as quickly as possible, and it is hoped that they will be operative in time to be ofmaterial assistance both to the general public and to production during theforthcoming winter.July 1944..


RELAXATION   OF   BLACKOUTRESTRICTIONSPROPOSED    LINE    of demarcation




</content>
</cab>
