<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/12/0 images: 170-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAR CABIBET.The position of this question is a thoroughly bed cue .at present.     IJo doubt wo ail desire to avoid adding one more thorny problem -to the -innumerable difficulties already on our backs, but the fact is that trouble over this question cannot possibly be avoided, and delay in taking it seems to me certain to render the trouble worse.All we want - all that, from the point of view of war policy is immediately necessary, is complete Government control of the manufacture end distribution of liquor.     In practice this means be or, as we have a large stock of spirits and it is not being added to, and there is no reason for adding to. it.     But the beer question is very urgent.     If we could exercise complete control, we ought, and no doubt would :-(1) As quickly as possible close a very large number ofsuperfluous public houses and shut up the smaller breweries, thereby making an immense saving in labour, in carriage, in cost of distribution, and setting free a number of men and women, who would-be readily absorbed and arc badly needed in war industries.(2) Insist upon the production of weaker beer.     By thismeans the material for 10 million standard barrels, which Is all wo have got left, could be used to produce at least 15 million barrels, perhaps even more, of wholesome and palatable light beer, which would keep beer drinkers supplied at the present reduced rate of consumption, probably to the end of the year, certainly all through the hot season when the demand for light beers is greatest, also most wholesome and natural.     The lighter beers ffeere introduced, have been found popular among the munition workers, and I believe they would be popular generally.     That they are much wholesomer, especially in hot weather, needs no argument to prove.If we don; x,   do this, our remaining stock&apos; of material will be rapidly used up In making unnecessarily heavy beer, in many cases above standard strength., and we shall run out of beer very much sooner.Legally as I understand, v/e can dc both these things with our present powers under the Defence of the Realm Act, but politically and morally it is impossible to do them, because ho should be cutting across innumerable private Interests and ruining any number of people, not only those whose businesses were closed down, out those whoso goodwill was destroyed by making them, for instance, brew a light beer when their whole reputation and custom rests upon a strong one - Guinness, Bass etc.     If wo.are to exercise the powers which we legally possess, we can only do so by dealing with these private interests - in other words, by purchase of the breweries and public houses, aid in some cases, though this is a minor matter from the point of view of finance, by compensating those dealers in liquor whose continued services.would not be required.
It is this dilemma which has forced us to consider the question of purchase.     It must be noted, however, that there is no necessity to carry out the purchase immediately. She one thing we need immediately is complete control.     A -treat-number of traders, indeed undoubtedly-,a majority In number though not a few specicily strong ones, would welcome a settlement,. by which the Government pledged itself to purchase at some future date and settled&apos;now the terns of purchase without actually carrying it out.     If we did this, we should to able to deal with the whole question without any further o-r;osition from the trade.     To get rid of that opposition as fir-as it is legitimate and would meet with general public sympathy - as rdistance to the destruction of people:s business without,any compensation undoubtedly would - is essential to any effective dealing with the subject.     It is just as essential to prohibition, for instance, a policy to which wo may have to come, as it is to the more moderate policy above proposed- in fact, as far- as I can soe, nothing can be done without it except to drift to certain trouble...The position now is that we are encountering vehement end&apos; grov/ing criticism from the Temperance people for doing nothing, and throe or four months hence, when the stock of beer runs out, v/e shall be met with equally violent, or even more violent attacks from tho dr inker sr.\    We are. thus, making sure of the maximum of hostility from both parties.I suppose it was these considerations which led the Cabinet some weeks ago to decide, in principle, that, subject to the result of certain Deputations tkxSSl which tho Prime Minister was going to receive., our polity should be *-(1) Purchase.(2) State Control.(.3) Local option.-.In the meantime I was Instructed to get a draft Bill prepared to carry out this policy..     That Bill, with, a Covering Kemoran-diim by Mr.?eddar of the Home Office, I now lay on the table. It will be observed that it deals only with tho question of Purchase and future purchase, the terms of it, however,,,to be settled now.     This is the essence of the&quot;scheme. &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; o provision is made for State Control because, as I have explained, we already have full powers of controlling.     The difficulty is that, until private interests aro eliminated, there is no practical possibility of exercising them any further than we have done already.This 2 clause Bill has teen drafted by Sir A.Thring tad is confined to all that is now absolutely necessary.   After tho war a Bill will be needed for tho establishment of permanent machinery, but as soon as the second Koading is passed, id ost, S3 soon as Parliament is pledged to the principle of compensation, the Government can control the Trade undor the Defence of the Soalm regulations without waiting for the final stages of the Sill,    Tho experience gained during&quot;, this period of control Jxring the war will be ox the greatest assistance in determining the form of the permanent system of control to be established if aiter it.All that tho Bill roally does is to commit Parliament &quot;J0 the principle of purchase after the war, and to settle the ofcsis of it - e.g., the number of years1 purchase for oac^h Merest.     This basis will be set forth in the schedule, which ^st be framed by a Government Finance Committee, in consultation v?ith the Trade, before the Bill is introduced,.    &apos; This, however, can only be done when the Cabinet has decided upon the principle.4th.May, 1917.(Initialled)   M.
T^no^snduD by Hr.?eddar.LIQUOI. (STATE COITTBOh) BILL.The object of this Bill is to settle the principle that at a convenient time and on an agreed basis of purchase the State shall buy the Liquor. Trade and thereafter keep the manufacture and sale of intoxicating liquor within its own hands..The purchase money is to be paid end the formal transfer of business is to take place on the appointed day or days which shall be.within three years after the end of the war and may be different days for different areas cr different classes ef the Trade (Clause 1 (l) and 2 (&apos; )&apos;.  )The assessment&apos; of the purchase money for each, licensed &quot;business and for any premises taken over by the State is to be determined by a special Tribunal (Clauses 1, 2 and 3 and Schedule, ^eragraph l].The basis on which the purchase money is to be calculated must be.agreed before tho Bill reaches Parliament.     Paragraphs 2, 3 and 4 of the Schedule contain merely one suggestion for this basis.     Per the present these paragraphs need not be considered.As soon as State purchase is decided upon e.go when the Bill has received, a Second Beading, complete State Control could be brought into operation by means of a Defence of the Be aim Regulation giving power-to a Minister, e-.&apos;g. the Home Secretary, to.give any orders and directions which may be necessary in the public interest as to the carrying on of ail classes of the Liquor Trade.To administer such a Regulation there will be needed a small. Central Commis-sion .(working, under the authority of the Home Secretary) with staff and expert advisers.     Separate representatives or sub-Commissions or even perhaps separate Commissions will be necessary for Scotland and Ireland as dis-tinct from England (including Wales.)     Under the Central Corn-mission or Commissions there will be formed Boards of the Members of the Trade for. a number of districts into which the country will be.divided for Trade purposes.     These Boards will arrange and recommend and, subject to the Central Commission, carry out the necessary concentration of breweries,, closing of surplus licensed.premises, production of suitable and uniform qualities cf beer and distribution according to the needs of the people.&apos; The organisation which will thus be set up will form the basis for the administration of the liquor trade when It passes into the possession of the State, and there will be time before then to settle the permanent organisation carefully and to determine what alterations of the licensing Law,  etc. etc., will eventually be required.Among other things which will be required to be so settled yilL be the question of local option, as to which the Bill (Clause 1 (5)Ogives a sort of pledge that there shall be legis-lation enabling localities to decide whether they will have liquor sold within their boundaries at ell, and to determine the restrictions under which the sale, if allowed, shall be carried on.

</content>
</cab>
