<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/12/0 images: 244-248</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. G.T. 657



ANGLO-FRENCH CONFERENCE, May 4, and 5, 1917.



Resolutions proposed by the Prime Minister.



Salonica

(1) The British Government, after continuous study of the present shipping situation, and after cutting down imports to the irreducible minimum, have been forced to the conclusion that the essential needs of the civil propulsions of the Allies can only be met by a reduction of the force at Salonica to that required to hold an entrenched camp surrounding that harbour.

(2) The British Government agree that the method of reducing the Salonica force, which will be carried out in accordance with the military situation, shall be settled later, but they consider it imperative to make arrangements forthwith for the withdrawal of 1 division and 2 cavalry brigades, commencing on 1st June next. The military advisers of the British and French Governments have expressed the opinion that this reduction can take place as soon as the offensive operations now in progress have been completed without alteration in the existing front.

(3) It is agreed, however, that if General Sarrail&apos;s forthcoming offensive operations should be attended by such measure of success as to render it reasonably certain, not later than the end of May, that Bulgaria would come to terms, the decision in paragraph (1) will be reconsidered.



 prolonged discussion on the questions of Salonica and Greece, the Prime Minister presented these resolutions as representing the maximum concession towards the French point of view that he and Lord Robert Cecil (subject to to the approval of the War Cabinet) could make. M. Ribot accepted ad referendum to the French Cabinet and promised an early reply. It is ? that No. 14. dealing with the policy on the Western Front, was definitely agreed to.

(Initialled) M.P.A.H.

5.5.1917.

1.


(4) The French Government undertakes to direct General Sarrail to commence his offensive operations against Bulgaria at the earliest possible date.

(5) It is desirable that, while ensuring the safety of the Army at Salonica, the Allies shall secure the goodwill and friendship of the Greek nation.

(6) In the opinion of the French Government, the first step in order to obtain guarantees for the good behaviour of Greece is for General Sarrail to send adequate contingents to secure control of the harvest in Thessaly. Provided that the procedure is that indicated in the next paragraph, the British Government assent to this proposal, and to the proposal that a small British force not exceeding 500 men shall take part in these proceedings. It is understood that in the event of complications arising in consequences of General Sarrail&apos;s operations, the French Government will not call upon the British Government for any further naval or military assistances, direct or indirect, beyond the nominal contingent originally furnished. They also wish to make it clear that they cannot increase the naval forces in the Salonica district for the purpose of the establishment of a naval base at Velo.

(7) The Allies will announce their intention to the Greek Government to raise the blockade, provided that they are permitted to purchase the harvest of Thessaly without obstruction. They will further undertake that the harvest of Thessaly shall be divided proportionally between Royalist Greece and that portion of Greece under the control of the Provisional Government, the distribution of the respective shares being made by an International Commission in Athens. In order to secure control over

 
the disposal of the harvest, the Allies will insist on the establishment of military control posts at Larissa, Velo, and at such other points on the roads, railways and ports of Thessaly as may be necessary.

(8) Whether the Greek Royalist Government agree or not the military control posts will be established under the orders of General Sarrail, where representatives will only allow the passage of grain-stuffs to Royalist Greece under permits signed by the International Commission in Athens.

(9) Having regard to the Declaration made by the Allies at Rome on January 7, 1917, which was communicated to the Greek Government, the forces of the Provisional Government under M. Venizelos will not be utilised for the military control posts, since their employment might be interpreted as a military occupation of Thessaly and a violation of the said Declaration. It is agreed, however, that in the event of a subsequent spontaneous movement in any part of Thessaly in favour of M. Venizelos the introduction of Venizelist troops for the maintenance of order, after the establishment of a Venizelist regime, shall not be barred.

(10) The French Government undertake to instruct General Sarrail as proposed in Aricle (8). They further undertake to direct General Sarrail to carry out the establishments of the military control posts in the most pacific and friendly manner possible, and to do all is his power to avoid civil strike.

(11) At the request of Mr. LLoyd George, who was the Minister responsible for the conclusion of the agreement with General Sarrail at Rome on January 9, 1917, the French Government undertake to transmit to General Sarrail the recognition by the British Government of his loyal


 adherence to the letter and the spirit of his undertaking to take no military action against Greece without the consent of the Allied Governments.

(12) In view of the failure of the policy pursued by the Allies in Greece hitherto, and of the frequent misunderstandings which have occurred, the principle is accepted that, for the present, one Power should undertake the diplomatic lead in Greece. Since it would be difficult in existing conditions to separate diplomatic from military predominance, the British Government is agreed that the representative of the French Government in Athens should be definitely recognised as the principal medium of communication on all questions of common policy between the Allies and the Greek Government.

(13) In order to facilitate the above arrangement the French Government undertakes to recall their present diplomatic representative in Athens and to replace him by a man of exceptional position, acceptable to the British Government. The British Government also undertakes to recall its present representative, and to replace him either by a Chargé d&apos;Affaires, or by a Minister of subordinate position. The Conference invite the Italian and Russian Governments to consider a similar procedure.

(14) The British and French Governments undertake to continue the offensive on the Western Front in accordance with the principles agreed to by Generals Petain, Nivells, Robertson and Field Marshal Haig, set forth in the attached document, and to devote the whole of their forces to this purpose.



May 5, 1917.

 

4.


Statement by Sir William Robertson.

I conferred this morning with Generals Petain and Nivelle and Field Marshall Sir Douglas Haig. We reviewed the whole situation, including the situation in Russia and Italy, and the entry of America into the War, and we arrived at the unanimous opinion that it is essential to continue offensive operations on the Western Front. A large portion of the enemy’s reserves have already been exhausted by the French and British attacks. If the enemy is given time to recover, the fruits of this success will be lost. He will be free to attack either Russia or Italy, neither of whom are at present in a condition to resist an attack in great force. His present object is certainly to encourage his people to hold out until the submarine warfare has taken effect, and if he is left free to gain easy successes where he can, and allowed to proclaim to the world that he has defeated his two principal enemies, he will attain this object. This might be fatal to our chances of winning the war. We are, however, unanimously of opinion that the situation has changed since the plan for the offensive, begun in April, was agreed upon by the two Governments, and that this plan is no longer operative. It is no longer a question of aiming at breaking through the enemy’s front and aiming at distant objectives. It is now a question of wearing and exhausting the enemy’s resistance, and if and when this is achieved to exploit it to the fullest extent possible. In order to wear him down we are agreed that it is absolutely necessary to fight with all our available forces, with the object of destroying the enemy’s divisions. We are unanimously of opinion that there is no half-way between this course and fighting defensively, which, at this stage of the War, would be tantamount to acknowledging defeat. We are all of opinion that our object can be obtained by relentlessly attacking with limited objectives, whilst making the fullest use of our artillery. By this means we hope to gain our ends by the minimum loss possible.

Having unanimously agreed to the above principles, we consider that the methods to be adopted to put them into practice, and the time and place of the various attacks, are matters which must be left to the responsible generals, and that they should at once be examined and settled by them.

Paris

May 3, 1917





</content>
</cab>
