<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/49 images: 520-533</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
$ pOCU^BWT JS THE PROPERTY OF KIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVltttHMENT[ The circulation of this paper has been strictly limitedIt is issued for the personal use of...SE9 *) Q6 6. copy No../aW.P.f 45)  29912TH MAY 9   1945WAR CABINETVENEZI^ GIIJLIANote &quot;by the secretary i have teen directed hy the Prime Minister to circulate the attached exchange of telegrams betweenPresident Truman and the prime Minister.(Signed)    NORMAN BROOKOffices of the War Cabinet,S .W 1 *1STH MAY a  1945.

T. 891/5PRESIDENT TRUMAN TO THE PRIME MINISTER        No. 34Personal and Top Secret 12.5.45Since sending you my telegram of April 30 Ihave become increasingly concerned over the implicationof Tito&apos;s actions in Venezia Giulia.   You are no doubtreceiving the same reports which indicate that he hasno intention of abandoning the territory or of permittinga peaceful solution of this century old problem aspart of a general Pacific post-war settlement.   I have come to the conclusion that we must decide now whether we should uphold the fundamental principles of territorial settlement by orderly process againstforce, intimidation or blackmail.   It seems that Titohas an identical claim ready for South Austria, inGarinthia and Sbyrla and may have similar designs onDarts of Hungary and Greece if his methods in VeneziaGiulia succeed.   Although the stability of Italy andthe future orientation of that country with respect toRussia may well be at stake the present issue, as i see it, is not a question of taking sides in a dispute between Italy and Yugoslavia or of becoming involvedin internal Balkan politics.   The problem is essentiallyone of deciding whether our two countries are going topermit our Allies to engage in uncontrolled landgrabbing or tactics which are all too reminiscent ofthose of Hitler and Japan.   Yugoslav occupation of trieste, the key to that area and a vital&quot; outlet for large areas of central Europe, would, as I know youwill agree, have more far-reaching consequences than theimmediate territory involved.   In these circumstances believe the minimum we should insist upon is thatField Marshal Alexander should obtain complete and exclusive control of Trieste and Pola, the line ofCommunication through Gorizia and Mo ritual cone, and an area sufficiently to the east of this line to permit properadministrative control.   The line suggested by Alexanderft Allied Force Headquarters in March extended toinclude Pola would, I believe, be adequate.   Tito seemsunsure of himself and might not put up more than a show01 resistance, although we should be prepared toconsider if necessary further steps to effect hiswithdrawal.   I note that Alexander, who has lostPatience with Tito&apos;s latest moves, is prepared to goGnead if we agree.I suggest...

I suggest that as a first step we instructour Ambassadors&apos;at Belgrade to address Tito along the following lines:&quot;The question of Venezia Giulia is onlyone of the many territorial problems in Europe tobe solved in the general peace settlement.     the doctrine of solution by conquest and by unilaterialproclamation of sovereignty through occupation, themethod used by the enemy with such tragic con-sequences, has been definitely and solemnlyrepudiated by the Allied Governments participating in this war.     This agreement to work together to seek an orderly and just solution, of territorialproblems is one of the cardinal principles for whichthe peoples of the United Nations have made theirtremendous sacrifice to attain a just and lastingpeace0     It is one of the cornerstones on which their representatives, with the approbation of world public opinion, are now at work to build asystem of world security.The plan of Allied Military Government ofVenezia Giulia was adopted precisely to achieve a peaceful and lasting solution of a problem ofadmitted complexities.     It is designed to safeguard the interests of the peoples involved.     Itsimplementation, while assuring to the military forces   *of the Allied Governments the means of carrying ontheir further tasks In enemy territory, would bringno prejudice to Yugoslav claims in the&quot;final settlement.With these considerations in mind, and inview of the previous general agreement of the yugoslav Government to the plans proposed for this region, my Government has instructed me to inform you it expects that the Yugoslav Government will immediately agree to the control by the supreme allied Commander in the Mediterranean of the regionwhich must include Trieste, Gorizia, Montfalconeand Pola, and issue appropriate instructions to the yugoslav forces in the region in question to co-operate with the Allied Commander in the establish-ment of military government in that area under theauthority of the Allied Commander.I have been instructed to report most urgetitjytO      s   ,  0

to my-Govornment whether the Yugoslav Governmentis prepared inniiediately to acquiesce in the. foregoing,- &quot; &apos;I-also suggest, we both inform Stalin inaccordance with the- Yalta agreement for consultation.If we stand firm on this issue,, as we are doing on poland, we can.hope&apos; to avoid a host-of other similarencroachments.Distribution:The KingForeign Secretary-Sir E. BridgesGeneral JsmayFor Information:Defence Committee,

T.899/5PRIME HINISTSR TO PRESIDENT fMiM No. 45Personal and Too Secret 12.5.45Your No. d4:1c     I aaree with every word you say and will work with all&quot;my strength oh the line you propose,     Youwill have received by now my Mo. 44, which showsdew qravely We doth view the situation.     If it ishandled firmly bsfore our strength is dispersed,Europe nay bo saved another bloodbath    otherwise the whole fruits of our victory may be cast, away and none of the purposes of ^orld Oraanieation toprevent territorial&quot;aa- ression and future wars willbe atcaiped.2.     I &quot;:&quot;rust that a standstill order can be aivenon the movements of the American trmies and airForcos from Europe, at any rate for a few weens.To will also coniorAi in our demobilization.     Evenif this standstill order should become known, itwould do nothing but wood.3. Alexander&apos;s HAF 959 asks urgently what partof his present troops, the loth Arriy Group, willbe at his disposal in the event of&apos;hostilitiesagaihst Yugoslavia.     He ha:- available tor action 7United Stapes divisions, 4 British divisions, one new Zealand division, one South African division,2 Prifish-Tndian divisions., 2 Polish divisions andone Brazilian division, total IS divisions.     Seehis PAF 960.     I have no doubt that if these woreplaced at his disposal he would feel himself in agood position to carry out a-y policy which ourGovernments may order,     I must of coarse obtain permission from the ; ew Zealand and South african governments in respect of their two divisions anaI cannot doubt that this would be accorded,especially to any policy in which Groat Britain andthe United States would be acting together.4.     Tn accordance with your suggestion I aw instruct-thg our Ambassador at Belgrade to address Tito onthe lines which yon have s-t forth end to keep instep with your Ambassador at every state . whether inoral /oresentations or the delivery of icle political orparallel notes o:r of a joint note.5.     The . , o

5.     The only minor amendment I would suttost to thearoposed message to Tito would be towards the end,after the words -which must include Trieste, OoriziaInonfalcone and ?ola,:;, to a 0. the words &quot;the lineof communications through Oorizia end uurfalccne to austria and on area sufficiently to the east of this line to permit prorjer acbiinis t rative centre1 !?.This is what you say in your introductory message to me excent that I have suggest &quot;d the add it ion&quot; cfand dispatch without, further reference to me.Distribution:The KingForeign Sec\ etarySir Edward BridgesGeneral IsmayFor Information;Defence Committee.




</content>
</cab>
