<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/19/5 images: 56-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1941.SECRET Gopy No, 2tW.P. (41). 232.October 4, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document. /JWAR CABINET.THE SENUSSI AND CYRENAICA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.THE Grand Senussi (Saiyid Idris) made contact with the British authoritiesin Egypt in July 1940 when the outlook was particularly gloomy. Shortly after-wards a &quot; British Senussi Force &quot; was raised from exiles in Egypt, Transjordanand Syria, for service against the Italians in the Western Desert. These exileshad fled from Italian oppression at various times since the end of the last world war. The force subsequently grew to four battalions and a depot. It took no part in actual fighting, but did useful work behind the lines.During the course of an Address which General Sir Maitland Wilson madeto the Senussi chiefs in 1940, he said : &quot; We shall co-operate .... with sincerity and loyalty so that the Arabsmay be entitled to regain their freedom and take back their lands from theItalian oppressors and restore their independence once more.&quot;This gathering afterwards adopted resolutions in favour of (a) the establishment of a Senussi Emirate in Cyrenaica;(&amp;) the formation of a temporary Senussi Government under Saiyid Idriswith power to negotiate with His Majesty&apos;s Government.These resolutions were never given any official cognisance, and no specificpolitical engagements beyond that of General Wilson were made with theSenussis.Ever since August 1940 Saiyid Idris has endeavoured to extract some officialpronouncement from His Majesty&apos;s Government, especially on the question of recognition. He argues that the Senussis gave their aid without advancebargaining for political concessions, relying on the declared sympathy of Great-Britain with the aspirations of small nations.The Senussi suffered severely from having supported us, and have so far gotnothing in return.   Their desiderata may be summarised thus : (a) Permanent freedom from Italian rule.(b) The establishment of an Arab Emirate under British protection on thelines of Transjordania.General Headquarters, Middle East, now wish to transfer two battalions ofthe British Senussi Force from the Western Desert, where they are now stationed,for service in Syria. The Grand Senussi is unwilling to agree unless he canreceive some form of recognition as an ally of Great Britain, which would carry with it assurances regarding the future of his people.11503   [22985]
I have discussed this question with the Minister of State, and we have agreedthat it would be well to meet the Grand Senussi on point (a) above, but that itwould be premature to pronounce on point (b) at the present time.&quot;We therefore propose to make an early declaration to Saiyid Idris in thefollowing sense : (1) His Majesty&apos;s Government welcome the association of his forces withtheir own in the task of defeating their common enemies.(2) At the end of the war he and his followers will in no circumstances beagain placed under Italian domination.We feel that such an announcement would have a good effect in the arab world generally.A. E.Foreign Office, October 4, 1941.



</content>
</cab>
