<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/46/0 images: 11-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IB  11i-&quot;Si                                          Intelligence Bureau,                                            Department of Information.SECRET.                                            SF&apos;W/030,                     WEEKLY  REPORT  OH  SPAIN, XX.                             (March 21st, 1918)   The situation in Spain is too obscure to encourage much usefuldiscussion at present.   The outstanding fact about it is that it isnot yet a month since the General election took place and during thattime the Cabinet has resigned three times.   The last resignationoccurred cnSy a day or two ago and it seems improbable that the crisiscan again be got over by the same Ministers resuming office.   At themoment of writing it is not known what the immediate cause of theresignation was.   Possibly the u irest among the postal and telegraphworkers and the drastic treatment it met with from the Minister ofWar, Senor La Cierva, who seems to have taken command of the wholebusiness.   He gave them 24 hours to sign an undertaking not to be-long to any :JuntasT or Committees, (practically what we should callunions), and on their refusal dismissed them all and tried to do thework of the Post Office by soldiers.   The latest report however isthat the men have been reinstated and their demands granted.   Whatever the truth about this may be,  it is obvious that the markedcontrast between the treatment of the officers &apos;Juntas1 which havebeen allowed practically to depose Cabinets,  to appoint their ownMinister of War and to dictate the reforms which they desired,  and thatof the Committees of the civil servants will  still  further exasperatethe feelings of the Liberal and Constitutional elements in Spanish life,especially those of the workmen.    And it is  fair to say-that all thestatesmen, and Senor I-aura quite as strongly as&apos;Count Romanonos.  haveprotested against the policy by which Senor La Cierva seems to  allowthe Asmy a kind of control over the actions of the  Civil Government.The second of the three recent resignations was brought about bySenor La Cierva&apos;s defence against a vigorous  public attack on the
officers made by an influential Conservative, Senor Sanchez Toca.And when the King consulted Senor Maura among other leaders, as isusual during a crisis,  that generally reactionary statesman declaredthat nothing would induce hi^ to take the responsibility of officeunless the officers&apos; Juntas v/ere dissolved, and his advice to theKing was to insist that they should either accept being dissolved orform a Ministry themselves, so that the visible responsibility ofgovernment might rest on the shoulders of those who insist onhaving the real power..   The King must now make his choice.   La Cierva made it clear fromthe first, even publicly in a note to the Press, -that he was theKing&apos;s man, appointed by the King and serving the King, in a directand personal way,  not as a- mere member of the Cabinet.  He hasworked and is working in every way to unite the officers in loyaltyto the King.   The banquet mentioned in the last Report which wasutilized for that purpose is to be followed, it seems, by an organishurst of military loyalty i  the Queen appears at the head of herregiment at the swearing-in. of recruits...  All this is, in itself, tothe good,   It is a great improvement on the situation in the summerwhen the officers took up an almost open attitude of menacing dis-loyaity,  But if the King and La Cierva, in whose mind a statesmanis a sort of super-policeman, mean to use this military loyalty asa weapon against the Constitution and the civil elements of thenation, they will plainly be making a revolution after their ownfashion which is only too likely to lead to another of a differentsort, less to their liking.   It is certain that good judges regard the situation as grave.  Astatesman who was in office a few months ago speaks despairingly ofSpain as no longer under a reign of legality and describes the pros-fject as simply a  &apos;deluge?..   A foreigner (not an Englishman) yrho haslately!left Spain, where he had the best opportunities of judging,expresses the opinion that Spain is marching straight to revolution.-
Others equally well-informed are distinctly less alarmist but stilldescribe the situation as a very serious one.   The officers are un-doubtedly very much excited and in private indulge in-wild talk aboutkidnapping or otherwise mal-treating the Statesmen who have been mostoutspoken in criticizing them.   &quot;Society&quot;, which probably, as so                                                 ioften, has more influence with the King than is in his interest, isinclined to sympathise with the officers and to regard La Cierva asa strong man who is practical and not like the other  statesmen a  merephrase maker playing a game, ostensibly Of politics,  really ofself-interest.   Can the issue between La Cierva with his personal  system ofGovernment and the. other statesmen be any longer postponed?-  That iswhat the result of the present crisis must show.   Some well-in-formed people think it will end in a Maura and La Cierva combination,:Maura:s face being saved by a nominal dissolution of  the officers&apos;Juntas.   But it is very difficult to believe that this is possiblein view of Maura&apos;s declaration during one of the recent crises &quot;ToLa Oierva I will give neither a vote nor a man nor even advice&quot;.  SgCount Eomanones has repeatedly declared that he and his party willnot co-operate with La Cierva,   Colonel Marquez, the late Chief t*fthe Military  Juntas, who is now head of the Civil  &apos;Juntas 1 and isadmittedly still a powerful man, has issued a manifesto obviouslyaimed at La Cierva, saying  that if the Army Committees allow them-selves tolbe used as a pedestal or stepping stone for  one man&apos;s am-bition they will be a curse and not a blessing to the country.  Mean-while Senor Dato stands aside refusing any idea of Coalition with any  -one and bides his time.   His avowed goal is a homogeneous Cabinetwith  a homogeneous Parliament, which seems to be out  of the range ofpossibilities except through a return to the old Rotative system andto elections  managed from Eadrid.  Probably he both expects and de-^f sires  that revival as the only practioal way of governing Spain.Whether  it&apos; is any  longer a  possible way will only be  seen if and when
it is again tried,    Meanwhile the King has got to find a way out.And unless he can persuade the present Prime Minister to go on withthe farce of acting as a screen to La Cierva, it looks as if he wouldhave either to trust himself openly to La Cierva and unconstitutionalreaction or to insist on a combination either- of Liberals withoutLa Cierva, or of Dato or Aomanones on a friendly pro-Ally&apos;basis.  Thelatter is unfortunately the less probable of the two.  Either wouldhave to face and settle the Army difficulty and defend the CommercialTreaties lately concluded by Exchange of Notes with the Allies.  Forhowever little the pro-Germans like them they are necessary to thelife, of the country.  And German influence can hardly have keen in-creased by the recent revelations as to the German Embassy&apos;s dealingswith anarohists.P.S.   As these words are written news arrives that Senor Maura has beenasked to form a Ministry and has agreed to trv to do so.  It will beinteresting to see whether he does after all combine with La Cierva.If not he must make a coalttion of some other sort, for he has on&amp;y27 followers of his own in the Cortes,  If he is successful at all hewall probably get help from Count Romanones, who was willing to serveunder him when he was trying to form a Government in December.  Thiswould be a safeguard for the Allies against the. pro-German tendenciesof the llaurists.   Will he turn to Cambo, thought by some people to bethe strongest man in Spain?  In that case he would have to adopt amore or less Segionalist policy.  Anyhow he shows great courage in at-tempting a very difficult task.  He is a great orator, a man of highintellectual qualtities &amp; finer culture, perhaps, than any of the otherpoliticians, and of a very strong will.  He was Prime Minister someyears ago at the time of the great Barcelona disturbances,  and he &amp;La Cierva, then his Minister of the Interior, became extremely unpopu-lar on account of their methods of repression &amp; in particular of theexecution of the alleged Anarchist Ferrol.  After that he retired fromthe leadership of the official Conservative Party,  in which he wassucceeded by Serior Dato.  He is regarded as a reactionary and is stillvery unpopular with the working-classes.

</content>
</cab>
