<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/46/0 images: 59-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Telegrams &quot;SHIPMINDER, VIC, LONDON.   ^---  Any further communication on thissubject should be addressed to    The Secretary,      Ministry of Shipping,          St. James&apos;s Park,             London, S.W. 1,and the following number quoted: MINISTRY  OF SHIPPING,23rd March, 1913.1\ KV^tytL1      Sir,               In  continuation of my letter of the 18th instant,  I  am      directed by  the  Shipping Controller  to report, for the  information      of the War Cabinet as follows.1.    CONVOYS          (a) Homerard Bound Convoys.    Since the last report  9      convoys consisting of 117 ships  (915,200 tons deadweight) have      arrived.   There were no casualties  of any kind.               There  are now on passage  home 19 Convoys consisting  of      309 ships.          (b) Outward Bound Convoys.   Since the last report  5      Convoys consisting of 93 ships (568.300 tons deadweight)  have      been escorted through the danger zone.   There were no      casualties.               There  are now in the danger zone 8 Convoys consisting      of 123 ships. 2,   FINANCE.               During the week ended the 16th instant, the sum  of       3,487,483 was  paid in compensation  for loss of requisitioned      ships, making  a total of  53,555,692 paid on this account      since  the  1st April 1917, 3.   NORWEGIAN  TONNAGE REQUISITIONED.               The s.s,&quot;CRN&quot;, and &quot;ECHO&quot; have been requisitioned.SECRETARY, vWAR CABINET.
-4.    STANDARD SHIPS.               The  s.s.&quot;WAR VIPER&quot;  built at Belfast,  and the      s.s.&quot;WAR EXPERT&quot;  (Oiler)  built at Glasgow,  have been      delivered. 5.    NEUTRAL TONNAGE LOST.               The  Danish steamship &quot;ALICE&quot; was sunk  by collision      on the  18th instant. 6.    RUSSIAN VESSELS REQUISITIONED.               The  following Russian Vessels have been requisitioned.            s.s.  TOBOLSK.                 s.s. EKATERINOSLAV.         -   S.s.  CONSTANTIA .            s,s. VERONEJ.            s.s.  TAMBOV.                  s.s, BJARMIA.            s.s.  CLAUDIUS AULAGNON.       s.s. SIRIUS.            s.s.  ODESSA.                  s,s, L/EDA.            s.s.  CZARITZA.                s.s. TRIO,            s.s.  AGNES.                   s.s. UMBA.                          s.s,  SIBIR. 7.    REQUISITIONING OF DUTCH TONNAGE.               The  details  connected with the requisitioning  by      His  Majesty1s Government  of the available Dutch vessels now      detained in British ports have been settled and the necessary      instructions  issued. 8.    COAL POSITION IN  SOUTH AFRICA.               The  position reported in my  letter of  the 9th  March      is maintained,   A  few cargoes of coal are  being exported to      South America for British bunkering firms,  and  railways in      which British capital is  concerned. 9.    SHIPMENT OF COAL  TO FRANCE.               The  arrangement  recently concluded by  which France      gives Italy 350,000 tons  of coal  pen  month subject to Great      Britain, France and America being able to ship  350,000  tons      extra to France  in  the next six weeks, is being put into      effect, and some  60^000 tons have been shipped  or allocated      by Great Britain  to France already.10.    STORES  FOR  THE BRITISH ARMY IN FRANCE.               The  quantity of  military stores discharged in  France      during the  week  ending 16th : larch was 173,919 tons.                                                          11./
(Sgd ,)   John Ande r s on.         The vessels arrived at Boston on their seventh tripon the 14th instant, and disembarked the following EnglishPrisoners:-               114   Civilians               _3   Mental cases               117and the &quot;body of an English civilian prisoner who died on thepassage.         The following German prisoners were embarked at Bostonon the 16th instant:-               700   Civilians                10   Mental cases               710&quot;TUSGANIA&quot;         With reference to the sinking of this vessel bysubmarine attack, it has been ascertained from the Americanauthorities that the actual number of military personnel savedwas 1971 and the number missing 211.ITALIAN PASSENGER STEAMERS FOR NORTH ATLANTIC TROOPING.         The Italian Government has now definitely agreed tothese vessels being brought into the North Atlantic for thetransport of American troops.                         I am,                                  Sir,                         Your obedient Servant,

</content>
</cab>
