<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/46/0 images: 110-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
     BATTLE SITUATION AFTERNOON OF 25th MARCH, 1918.brought by Staff Officer by aeroplane from G.H.Q., France,,     North of the SOMME the situation is in hand.     We have established a continuous line from CURLU on theSOMME, east of MONTAUBAN and MARTINPUICH to GRSVILLERS,  Westill hold BAPAUME with advanced troops,- but will probablyhave to withdraw,-     North of BAPAUME the line runs through SAPIGNIES andERVILLERS to HENIN on the COJUEL river.  The enemy has beenattacking heavily between MONTAUBAN and MARTINPUICH, but weare holding well.  He has also been attacking north of BAPAUMEbut without success.     South of the SOMME we are holding the line of the riverfrom FRISE opposite CURLU to MORCHAIN.  South of MORCHAIN theenemy have driven back our 5rd Corps and the  French who controlthis sector.  The enemy are reported to have capturedGUISCARD and NESLE and to be advancing on NOYON and ROYE,     The general situation appears to be that the Immediatedanger of a breach between the 3rd and 5th Armies, is over andwe should succeed in checking an advance on AMIENS.  Thedanger, point has now shifted to the area between the OISE andSOMME, but this is the nearest point to the French reserveswhich are coming up.  The enemy has managed to Intercept, therailway lines about AMIENS by aeroplane bombs which has delayedtraffic but the damage is being rapidly repaired.                                                    The
General Staff,     War Office,25 th March, 1918 5The morale of our troops is good and they are fighting splendidly.Everyone praises the work of our inachine guns.   The Germantroops are said to be very tired.  The guns have been withdrawnwell.   We have lost.no more Korth of NESLE, but the 3rd Corpsin their retirement with the French, south of that place? mayhave lost some.   We lost a number of tanks near PEROlTlTEo     Our casualties up to this morning are estimated at75*000.

</content>
</cab>
