<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/46/0 images: 315-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                                (9IS DOOUMT  13  TS3 PR GESSO?? OF HIS BRIT Aim IC MA.JB3TY&apos; S  GQVar?I^:cT,1                                                           -     25453 C R 2 T.:7AR GABIM2T.T.-409I,       Committee on the Amendment  of the  Military Service Acts                           (Third Meeting)           Minutes of the  Third Meeting of the  Committee           hold&apos;at the Home Office on  Saturday,  March           30th, 1918, at  3.p.m.The Rt.Hon.Sir  George  Cave,  M.P.     (Chairman)Tho Rt,Hon.&apos;The  Viscount  Milher.  G.C.B., G.C.M.G.,The Ht.Hon.Sir  Auckland  Geddes,  ICCB,. M.P.,Tho &quot;!t.Hon.H.(^Duke, ICC, K.P.,Tho Bft.Hon.R.aimro, K.C.. M.P.,The Rt.Hon.&quot;&apos;.Hayes Fisher, LI.P.,The ^t.Hon.G.HRoberts,  M.P.,Jlr. A.C.Beck, ji.P.ySir .J-Seymour Lloyd, ICB..3.-,  C.M.G.,Sir J.U.Bodds,  1I.C.B...Sir H.M\girov i vC.B*Mr. I.G.GibbonLlr. &quot;V.M.Graham  HarrisonMr * P.Roeo..Ur, T, Jones    (Secretary)
1. THE COMMITTEE resumed the consideration of the revised   Draft Bill.lEirriOUS 2. Section 3 (3)TORS.THE COMMITTEE considered various methodsof dealing with conscientious objectors.The effect of 3 (3) as drafted was togive power to call up conscientious objec-to-ra but an assurance would be given tothe House of Commons that they would notin fact be called up.  Conscientious objec-tion could be dealt with as a standardisedground for postponement into a late group-or.  in addition to the proposed Five Groupsa Sixth Group could be created into which                                ir militaryai.person s            permanently unfit fservice could be put and conscientious ob-jeotors conid be placed apart in a specialclass in this Sixth Group. (In any case in4-Flew of the provisions of the tiepresenta-x---^n of the people Act it was necessary tohave them definitely labelled.) Anothermethod would be to make the existing pro-visions for conscientious objectors applyto peisons deemed to be enlisted under thepresent Bill.Ultimately it was agreed that (d) of sub-section (1) of Section 2 of the firstMilitary Service Act should not beand that A Section 3 (3) of the newshould stand as drafted with the omissionof the words:-&quot;Granted or renewed before the passing ofthis Act.&quot;eoealedBillHi c ATI oi?ICT TO3. Section 4,MR. DUO suggested that in dealing withIreland there were at least three possiblecourses:- .(a)   The Bill might contain     tending the provisionsa section exto Irelandsimpliester,a r r an g e m en t swx oh tne afor tribunals.lition of(b)  Power might be taken to apply the Act     to Ireland by Order in Council,  after     a short period of grace during which     voluntary enlistment might be stimu-     lated.(c)  His Majesty might by Order in Council     provide for the selection of men by     ballot to maintain the effective     strength of the Irish regiments.MR. DUKE thought, and the Committee gener-ally concurred, that there was much to besaid for adopting the second course,  andit was agreed to submit (b) together with(a) for the consideration of the WarCabinet.As to the precise method  of giving effectin the Bill to the course adopted thefollowing alternatives were discussed;-
(a)  To include Ireland in Section (l)     of the Bill as part of the general     application of the Bill to the     United Kingdom, and to make a subse-     quent modification in the Bill when     providing for the Irish case.(b)  To omit Ireland in Section (l) and     insert later a substantive Section     dealing with Ireland.SECTION    4. Section 4 (l) BALLOT. mSLING    5. Section 4 (2) PEEL STEERS.The first course was the more logical,but the general opinion was in favour of(b) on parliamentary grounds.  If Ire-land were included in the first Sectionopposition would begin at once beforeany progress had been made with the Bill;whereas if the Irish clause came later itwould be possible to postpone in somedegree any opposition to the extension ofthe Bill to Ireland.It wa3 agreed to omit this Sub-Sectionand also the consequential SecondSchedule.The Sub-Section was approved. ..6. It was agreed that the Bill should be redrafted as above   amended and circulated on Tuesday.   THE COMMITTEE adjourned until Tuesday,  April 2nd, at 4 p.m.(Signed)   T.JONES,     Secretary;Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.  30th March, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
