<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/136/0 images: 41-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT)C(68) 4323rd February, 1968COPY NO,CABINE&apos;EUROPE:  THE FRANCO-GERMAN DSC LARA TION OF l6th february and THE BENELUX PROPOSALSNote by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for my colleagues consideration the attached paper,prepared by the Official Committee on the Approach to Europe.G.B0Foreign Office, SoW0l,23rd February, 1968
europe the FRANCO-GERMAN DECLARATIONOF 16 february and THE BENELUX PROPOSALSIntro-duct ion the Cabinet agreed on 20 December that in the light of theFrench veto, the aims of our European policy in the immediatefuture should bes-(i)    to maintain the long-term objective of full membership of the Communities as a valid andcredible policy in the eyes of public opinion here and in Europe;(ii)    to ensure as far as possible that the communities are prevented from developing,particularly in ways which would make it moredifficult for us to join later;(iii)    to preserve to the greatest extent compatible with (i) and (ii) our freedom of action in theeconomic field pending full membership.2.    On 19 January the three Benelux countries jointly presentedproposals to the other Community countries and the four countries
which had applied for membership of the E.E.C.  (Britain, Norway,Denmark and the Irish Republic) with a view to establishingcontinuing procedures for consultation about Community develop-ments and joint action where this was possible.   H.M.G. acceptedthe Benelux proposals on 25 January, and this acceptance was confirmed by the Foreign Secretary at the W.E.U. meeting in brussels on 30 January.    The W.E.U. meeting showed a wideconsensus of view that a meeting should be held at ministerial level, to be attended by those countries involved in the benelux proposals which wished to attend, and that this meeting should beprepared by officials.    The Cabinet accordingly decided on1 February that preparatory work should be put in hand for apossible meeting with Community. countries and other countrieswhich have applied for membership.3.     Meanwhile, Chancellor Kiesinger has held discussions withGeneral de Gaulle, and the German and French Governments haveissued a joint declaration.    A translation of this declarationis at Annex A to this paper.k.     This paper sets out what we know about the discussions which led up to the Franco-German declaration; and considers what our policy should be.The Franco-German Declaration5.     This is a declaration in very general and imprecise terms.It is not a proposal (it has not been communicated to any government formally), and what we have so far learnt from theFrench and from the Germans about the discussion which led   up toit underlines the uncertainties which surround it: so far it isclear that it has no substantial definition or content and thatit is not a proposal to Governments.    A first attempt may bemade at the E.E.C. Council on 29 February to give content to&quot;the declaration.   But the process may well take a long time,if it can be done at all.-2-
426.   These uncertainties m&amp;ki a clear statement of advantages and disadvantages difficult.    Among the factors which are relevant to what at this stage must he a tactical judgementrather than one on substance are the following?(a) the Germans say that they have been encouraged by their discussions with the French, and clearlyconsider that they have won a real concession,particularly in that the French have said that they desire the enlargement of the Community.    If we takea negative attitude to tire joint declaration before its content or lack of it has been demonstrated,the Germans will be disappointed, or will affectdisappointment, and may well take the line thatthey have done their best for us and sufficientlydischarged their duty.    It will be easier for theFrench and perhaps others to maintain that we areadopting an unreasonable attitude;(b) the French have told us that the declarationrepresents no change in the French attitude towardsthe British application to join the Communities.General de Gaulle, whose anti-Americanism clearlyworried the Germans, stated that Britain was stilltoo wedded to the Atlantic idea to be truly European;(c) the Germans have said that &quot;a kind of&quot; free trade area was envisaged in their discussions withthe French.    (They have emphasised &quot;a kind of&quot;.)But we a^e without any details.    The declarationitself does not refer to tariff arrangements at all.The Secretary-General of the Qual d&apos;Orsay has saidthat the French have made no detailed studies ofwhat would be involved; that there was no discussionof complete abolition of tariffs, and that no provision for this was contemplated at present.-3-
State Secretary Lahr has told us that the French andGerman Governments were agreed that whatever arrange-ment emerged would have to conform to GATT and he spoke of negotiations for a free trade area.    Heclaims that it would &quot;be open to us and the othercandidate states to transform this into a customs union merely &quot;by the device of applying theCommunity&apos;s common external tariff to ourselves.We have been told that the French Prime Ministerexpressed himself as favourable to agreements ontariff reductions, but spoke of exceptions and ofa &quot;sector approach&quot;.    If something on these linescould be achieved, it could be of significantassistance to British industry. As regards agriculture,we do not know what the French or germans have inmind.    But   Bu&quot;t i-t appears to be the purchase byBritain of quantities of agricultural produce fromE.E.C. countries, and it Is difficult to suppose thatthis would not be at Community prices.     This wouldhave serious implications for our balance of payments,and for either the Exchequer or the continuation ofour present agricultural support system;    and our trade relations with other overseas suppliers could be seriously affected;(d)   as regards E.F.T.A. participation, the onlyfirm evidence we have is in the second and thirdparagraphs of the Franco-German declaration.    (Thesecond paragraph speaks of the enlargement of the communities to &quot;other European countries andnotably to those who have already posed theircandidature&quot;; and paragraph 3 refers to arrangements to be concluded by the Community &quot;with the candidatecountries&quot;.)    To the extent that our E.F.T.A. partners-k-
were able to participate in  the discussion of any1arrangements which might result from the Franco-German-declaration,  this would be welcome to them-(e) from State Secretary DuckwitsVs first account ofthe discussions to ELM. Embassy in Paris, it emergedthat the Germans&apos;  idea in putting forward a proposalfor a kind of free trade area might be not so muchto bring about such a free trade area as to get into a negotiation with France in the hope &quot;that as some stage  (perhaps after de Gaulle&apos;s disappearance)it would be possible to convert this negotiationinto one for our entry into the Community.    Butthis idea has not been reflected in subsequent discussions with representatives of the GermanGovernment.    The Secretary-General of the Quai d&apos;Orsayspoke of a &quot;long-term task&quot; and of economic arrange-ments of the kind envisaged not being possible without Governments one day coming to the politicalgoal of a united Europe.    Whatever there may be inthis argument, it suggests that we cannot take tooseriously the suggestion that we might succeed in negotiating any kind of free trade area.    And it also suggests that both the French and the Germansenvisaged a very long negotiation before results would appear; Lahr has spoken of the need for greatpatience; Monnet, who knows the Communities well, hasspoken of a two-year negotiation;(f) it might be argued that &quot;a kind of free trade area&quot; could give us a close and legitimate interest inat least the commercial and agricultural policies of theCommunity.    But we know that General de Gaulle expressed himself as opposed to the creation of any new institutions.&apos;!/e cannot yet tell whether the kind of partial and
electoral tariff reductions and agricultural arrange-ments which seem to be envisnged by the French would give us an adequate opportunity for expressing iews about Community developments even in the tarifffield.     It would be unlikely to do so in theagricultural field.
(g) nothing in the declaration or in what we know of thediscussions which lead to it suggests that the Frenchare any further committed, even in principle, to accept-ing Britain as a full member of the Community;    paragraph2 of the declaration could equally well mean that arelationship different from full membership would be appropriate for Britain.     Still less is there any suggestion of a review of the possibility of full membership or automatic commitment to full membershipafter a period;(h) we cannot tell whether what emerged would be compatible with the G-.A.T.T.     The U.S., whichhas always objected to increased economicdiscrimination if the political unity of Europewere not enhanced at the same time, would certainlydislike these ideas.     But the extent to which wecould show that they constituted a genuine stepon the road to political unity might mitigate U.S.objections;(i) unlike the Benelux proposals there is no provisionfor technological co-operation, nor for consultationwith the Community on developments in Communitypolicy.     State Secretary La.hr has told the Italiansthat co-operation with Britain in technologicalquestions was mentioned as a possibility when this involved &quot;concrete projects&quot;.     But we have heardnothing of this from the French side;(j) in the absence of adequate arrangements for consulta-tion on developments in Community policy, such as are suggested in the Benelux proposals, we would be unable to achieve objective (ii) in the policy laiddown by Cabinet (paragraph 1 above).     This is the clear implication of the first paragraph of the-7-
Franco/German declaration, and is in line with pastCommunity experience.     The French have already discussed with the Germans the possibility of making progress on company law without regard to our views.The Benelux proposals.     The Franco/German declaration has not eliminated the benelux proposals.     The French made it clear to the Germansthat they did not like the Benelux proposals, but they remain as one possible subject for discussion at the E.E.C. Council meetingon 29 February.     What the French have succeeded in eliminatingis any immediate discussion of them between Community and non-Community countries interested.8.     The Benelux proposals were for;-(:&apos;.) the Commission to complete its study ofthe possibilities and problems raised bythe Candidature of Britain, Denmark,Norway and the Irish Republic;(ii) institutional arrangements to provide foran opportunity for. consultation on community developments and for possiblejoint action In fields (patents and company law) covered by the Community Treaties;(iii) joint action in non-Community fields, whichwould be open for participation by countries other than those which had applied for full membership;(iv) political consultation which would be openon the same basis as (iii).9.    The Benelux proposals might give us some prospect of influencing the development of the Communities, and of taking part in joint action with Community countries while waiting forthe possibility of membership to revive, without increasing the limitations on our freedom of economic action.     But to achieve-8-
this result, it will be important that at least all community countries, except Prance, should be prepared to participate.(We need not oppose French participation;    and her inclusionwould be useful;   but her participation is not essential to thesuccess of the exercise.)      If Germany were to refuse toparticipate, consultation on Community developments could stillbe useful since for the foreseeable future it will be open to any single Community country to block progress on major developments in the Communities.     But this would be much less attractiveanthan/arrangement in which Germany took part;    and the decisionto proceed without Germany would be an awkward one which would haveto be taken in the light of the whole range of interests embodied in our relations with Germany.     Further, it must be recognisedthat in practice there might be little enthusiasm among the benelux countries and Italy for pursuing the Benelux proposalswithout Germany.     And this could well lead to their collapse.10.   The question of E.F.T-A-  participation also raises uncertain-ties.    Our interest is in making a success of consultation on community policies.     If those in the Community prepared to argue our case are to justify their doing so, they will base their argument on the undesirability of doing anything whichwill make British (and Norwegian, Danish and Irish) membershipmore difficult.     This argument cannot apply to countries whichhave not applied to join the Communities.     It will therefore bein our interest that participation in consultative machinery should be limited to countries which have sought full membership.But,in the interests of our relations with E.F.T.A. countries, wemust avoid opposing the desire of other E.F.T.A. countries, should&quot;they maintain it, to pursue in some manner and to some extent anyconsultation arrangements under the Benelux proposals.     Actionon joint projects and political consultation is another matter,since the Benelux proposals make it clear that these items are open to other European countries, and so are open to E.F.T.A.countries which have not sought full membership.-9-CONFIDENT1AL
11.   Our aim. in pursuing the Benelux proposals would he to makea reality of consultation with the Community countries participating, and to undertake what joint action we usefully andprofitably could pending full membership, in accordance with thepolicy aims set out in paragraph 1 of this paper.     To achieveeffective consultation on Community developments we should haveto he prepared for some duplication of consultation which isalready taking place in other international organisations., forexample the International Monetary Fund, U.N.C.T.A.D. , and theD.A.C. as well as other O.E.C.D. bodies.     Although this might lead to some duplication of effort, it will be a small price topay if we can secure thereby the opportunity to express viewseffectively on Community developments before they are decided bythe Six.Conclusion12.   It is difficult to believe that there has been any significant change in France&apos;s policy regarding Britain&apos;s relations with theEuropean Communities.     The French have avoided any commitment indetail.     Even if the Germans were able to win French agreement toa partial free trade area we should be faced with all the disadvantages in this course which we have long foreseen and which ministers have developed publicly and in numerous conversations: with European Ministers.     Most recently the Prime Minister said, in answer to a question in Parliament on 20 February (Hansardj Col. 235);    &quot;We made clear our position about association with; the Economic Community.     If by that the hon. Gentleman meansI Article 238, we have made clear that we regard this as anI unsatisfactory alternative to our main application.     The proposals
from Paris so far at any rate seem a good deal vaguer than a straight Article 238 association.&quot;    In an earlier written answer on 23 November (Hansard Col. U28) the Prime Minister stated themain objections to anything short of full membership.13.   If we express readiness to consider sympathetically the sort of idea that seems to have been discussed between the French andthe Germans, we will risk provoking a proposal which we may haveto turn down.     The French would then have succeeded in what musthave been their major objective last week - to drive the germans from the favourable attitude which they had adopted to the benelux proposals.     The French were worried by the Benelux proposals andworried by signs that France was becoming increasingly isolatedin the Community.     For the moment, they have reversed this position without any concession of substance.Ik.   On the other hand if we now take a negative attitude to the franco/German declaration, the Germans may well refuse to take part in the Benelux proposals, and may be won over to the Frenchview that we are being unreasonable in adopting an &quot;all or nothing&quot;attitude to membership of the Communities.15.   It is therefore suggested that we should adopt the followingposition.     We should take the line that we have been interested to see the text of the Franco/German declaration.     We remainsceptical about the chance of Germany achieving anything on theselines with the French Government (as the Foreign Secretaryexplained to Herr Brandt on 19 January).     If, however, theGermans do succeed in winning the French over to acceptance of aconcrete and precise proposal of this kind, we should, of course,be ready to consider it.     But for the moment there is no proposalto consider, and no detailed ideas, and we are not called upon totake up a position.     Naturally we would not be prepared toconsider proposals which had not first been accepted in Paris.Uhe long and unhappy history of our efforts to achieve asatisfactory relationship with the Community make French agreementI -11-
in detail to any proposal an essential condition for us to give it our consideration.):     We would go on to say to the Germansthat we would regard a proposal of the kind which they discussed in Paris as covering different ground from that covered by the benelux proposals.     We should need at leas4&quot;  some features ofthe Benelux proposals (their provision for consultation, thepossibility of action in the technological and defence fieldsand political consultation) whether or not the French agreed tosome free trade area proposals.     We therefore hope that, inreturn for the assurances which we would give the Germans of our readiness to consider any detailed ideas approved by the French,the Germans in turn will be ready to go forward with the substance of the Benelux proposals in parallel, as agreed by Herr Brandt atthe W.E.U. meeting on 30 January.16.   The E E.C. Council will meat on 29 February, and willhave these questions on its agenda.      It is recommended that ministers should defer a final decision on the recommendations in this paper until the results of -this meeting are known.-1 2-CONFIDENTiAL
52TRANSLATION OF FRANC0/GERMAN DECLARATIONThe two Governments affirm their determination to pursue the work undertaken by them and their partners since thecreation of the European Economic Community.     They intend to devote all their efforts to the completion and development ofthe Common Market:    they re-affirm in particular their intentionto achieve the fusion of the three existing Communities.2.     In this spirit they desire the enlargement of the Communitiesto other European countries and notably to those who have alreadyposed their candidature, as soon as these countries are, accordingto their circumstances, in a state (en mesure) effectively toenter the Communities or to link themselves to them under adifferent form.     This applies in particular to Great Britain and means that the evolution already begun by this country shouldcontinue.3.     While waiting for the enlargement to become possible, thetwo Governments are ready to envisage that arrangements shouldbe concluded by the Community with the candidate countries of a kind to develop between them exchanges of industrial and agricultural products.     Such arrangements which would entail for industrial products progressive lowering of obstacles to trade,would be of a kind to facilitate the evolution mentioned above and in any case to contribute   to the development of therelations between European countries.h. In setting out their position on the development and. desiredenlargement of the E.E.C. the two Governments have in mind anessential objective of their policy which is to make a strong and united Europe play the role which it should, that is to say to bean organised, independent and active factor for world equilibriumand in consequence for peace.-13-


</content>
</cab>
