<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/136/0 images: 85-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
if.;(THIS81DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT)C(68) 4727th February, 1968COPY NO.CABINETCOMPENSATION FOR LOSSES FROM FOOT-AND-MOUTH DISEASEMemorandum by the First Secretary of state ask the Cabinet to resolve a difference of view in theAgricultural Policy Committee on a proposal by the Minister ofAgriculture relating to compensation for farmers from losses resultingfrom the foot-and-mouth epidemic.2.      Compensation for stock slaughtered to prevent the spread of theepidemic is at present calculated, under the relevant legislativeprovisions, on the basis of the market value of the stock at the time of slaughter.    Any payments not on this basis would have to be madeex gratia.    The Minister of Agriculture argues that farmers whosestock had to be slaughtered in the early weeks of the epidemic (i. e. inOctober and November of last year) have suffered disproportionatelybecause market values for cattle have risen by 25 per cent since then.The rate of compensation received by these farmers has thus been substantially less than the rate received by farmers whose stock wereslaughtered later, and the Minister argues that this is inequitable.These farmers have also been out of business pending re-stocking forseveral months instead of the usual six weeks.     He therefore proposes,as a matter of common justice, that their compensation should bebrought up to the level received by farmers whose stock had the disease later.    He estimates that this would cost the Exchequer 800- 900, 000, of which a proportion - possibly about  200,000 -would be recovered in tax.3.      I should mention a dumber of other relevant factors -(i) Existing compensation is subject to income tax, and it isestimated that the Exchequer will recover a substantialsum in this way.    The Minister of Agriculture is notchallenging this, but points out that it is causing greatresentment among the farming community and argues thatthis strengthens the case for his present proposal.(ii) The position of farmers who have suffered losses has alreadybeen eased by two measures designed to take the pressure offimmediate re-stocking: first, a ploughing grant of  10 an acreto encourage a switch to arable farming;  and second, a grant for replacing slaughtered dairy cattle by &quot;dry stock&quot;, i. e.cattle which will not produce milk for the farmer for a further period.    These two measures will together cost aboutS.j million.-1-
(iii) It is open to farmers to insure against loss of income (though not specifically against the incidence of foot-and-mouth disease).    But the Minister of Agriculture informed theCommittee that, because of the high premiums and the limitedcoverage, few farmers in fact take out such insurance.4.      Some members of the Committee were opposed to the proposal.They argued that -(i) To depart from the existing statutory basis of compensationaccording to market value would set a dangerous precedent.(ii)  The rise in the market value of cattle had brought anuncovenanted bonus to farmers whose stock were not affectedby the epidemic, and if there was any case in equity for highercompensation to those affected earliest, the cost of this shouldbe met by a levy on other farmers rather than by the taxpayer.(iii) Account should be taken of the fact that compensation wasnormally paid within three weeks of slaughter, and those affected earliest had had the benefit of a return on theircompensation payment during the interval before re-stocking.5.       Other Ministers argued that -(i) A departure from the market value formula was justified bythe exceptional length and severity of the epidemic,(ii) A levy on other farmers was not practicable and would in anycase require fresh legislation,(iii)  The return on compensation payments in the interval beforere-stocking was insignificant compared with the losses of income incurred.6.      There was some support in the Committee for a middle course -i. e. to accept the proposal by the Minister of Agriculture and invitehim to discuss the details of a scheme with the Farmers1 Unions, but to limit the total amount of payments to  500, 000 (of which, of course, a proportion would return to the Exchequer in the form of tax).    on balance, this is the course I would recommend to my colleagues.70 Whitehall, S. W.l.26th February, 1968-2-


</content>
</cab>
