<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/136/0 images: 226-229</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Sli5U2 COPY NO. ^CABINETPRICES AND INCOMESg LOW PAID WORKERSM^H^^JE^B^iB-kL^^S.^6SJ3^TYJ?L.State for Economic affairs and the Minister of LabourWe weighed ca.refully the considerations involved in allowingany exception to the ceiling other than that for genuine productivity agreements.    We decided that there were powerful reasons against an exception for low paid workers and, in doing so, we agreed toincrease family allowances.2.     These powerful reasons against such an exception were;-(i)   We use the term &quot;low paid worker&quot; but there Is nodefinition of it and no prospect of being able toagree with the Confederation of British Industry (CBI)and the Trades Union Congress (TUC) on a workabledefinition.(ii)   An additional exception for low paid workers wouldmake it extraordinarily difficult to resist pressure from unions in the public services to treat the criterion of &quot;fair comparison&apos;2 as another exception to the ceiling making the ceiling look more like theaccustomed &quot;norm&quot;, or automatic entitlement to aminimum increase.(iii) Employers would be exposed to intolerable pressure from unions who are only too ready to use the low paid as a &quot;stalking horse&quot; to obtain all roundincreases with preservation of traditionaldifferentials.(iv) Although some of these differentials have no realjustification today, there is increasing concern overthe narrowing of differentials which do reflectgenuinely skill and responsibility.30     In looking again at the presentation of the policy without an exception for low paid workers, we should be clear that it doesnot mean the pay of these groups of workers will increase by amaximum of Z\ per cent when prices will be rising by twice as much.-i-
(i)   Many low paid workers will benefit from increasedovertime and piecework earnings as industrial activity picks up.(ii)   A good many low paid workers will be able to receiveabove-ceiling pay increases arising from genuineproductivity agreements at plant level,(iii)   It is open to a group containing low paid workers tonegotiate above-ceiling increases for the low paidwithin a settlement which overall was within the ceiling.    This is what the National Board for prices and Incomes (NBPI) recommended for theengineering industry.    For example, the 3 3 per cent increase could be given as a flat rate increase which would ensure that proportionately the lowestpaid received larger increases.5,     Presentational^ the family allowance increases are of greatimportance because the most vital area of public concern about thevulnerable groups of workers relates to family endowment.     We are proposing a further increase of three shillings a week from Octoberin addition to the seven shillings increase from April,6.     With pay increases of up to 3f- per cent, these increases in family allowances should give substantial protection to low paid workers with families of two or more children.     For example, aman earning  15 a week (this is the target of the TUC for guaranteedminimum earnings) could receive a pay increase of 3j per cent plus a family allowance increase of 10 shillings (3y per cent) if he has two children or  1 (6f per cent) if he has three children.7.     Of course, there are the Budget tax increases but these havebeen designed, as far as possible, to bear less hardly on the leastwell-off workers.    It is estimated that the effects of the Budget taxchanges on a married couple with an income before tax of around  15 a week will be to reduce their atsacual isccme after tax by about1.25 per cent (about  8.   7s. Od).     The corresponding figure for a married couple with two children on the same level of income is less than 1 per cent (about  7.  10s. Od).     This calculation does not take into account the effect of the increases in family allowances.8.     Notwithstanding these important factors which will apply toa considerable number of low paid workers, we have to recognisethat there will be little flexibility for above-ceiling increases for thelow paid workers in industries in which the low paid predominate,for example Agriculture and a number of Wages Councils industries.We have again considered whether anything could be done to devise a limited form of exception to cover such cases - but one which would stand a chance of restricting above-ceiling increases to the genuinelylow paid.-2-
90     We have had practical experience, however, of trying to restrict pay increases in these  industries to the low paideparticularly during the period of severe restraint,    There is oftena wide gap between the statutory minimum wage rates and average earnings, and the distribution of earnings is such that increasesgiven to all the workers could not really be justified on low paidworker grounds.    We referred to the NBPI the case of the R.etailDrapery, Outfitting and Footwear Trades Wages Council covering340,000 workers.    The Board found that workers in these tradesas a whole were no^amongst the lowest paid in the community,although the minority whose remuneration was at the level of thestatutory minimum were among the lowest paid.    Other wages councils would be in a similar position,10.     Even in the case of Agriculture, where average weekly earnings including overtime are well below those in any otherindustry for which such figures are available, the NBPI found somegroups where there was no case for applying generally a pay increase intended to assist the lower paid,11,     It should be kept in mind that Wages Councils industries(together with the Agricultural Wages Boards) account in all for some4 million workers;  of these Z\ million were women.12.     We have considered whether these problems might somehowbe mitigated by fixing a minimum earnings level of say  12 for menand  10 for women (excluding overtime) and allowing above-ceilingincreases only for earnings below these minima.    But the difficultyhere is that workers with earnings below these minima are verywidely distributed between industries and bargaining groupsc    in industries where there are relatively large numbers of such workers,it would probably be impracticable to squeeze differentials to theextent required,13,     If overtime earnings were included - which would bring the 12 minimum up to about  14 - there would inevitably be a   great many borderline cases due to fluctuations in overtime and it wouldbe impossible to differentiate clearly between those workers on one side of the line entitled to an above-ceiling increase and those on theother who would receive no more than 3j per cent,14,     The problems we face in applying firmly a general ceiling of 3i per cent are considerable! those associated with maintaining a dual ceiling to allow some form of exceptional treatment for thelow paid would be insuperable.    We have been forced to the conclusiontherefore that, fcr the time being at least, there is no effective way in sight of departing from our previous decision wit&amp;out running the gravest risk of undermining the ceiling concept on which our new policy is based.But we think it right that officials should press on with the currentstudy of a national minimum wage and that, following this,, we shouldenvisage talks with the CBI and TUC about the problems of gettingsome workable definition of low paid workers,P0S.R, Jo G.Department of Economic Affairs, S. W. 1,20th March, 1968-3-SECRET


</content>
</cab>
