<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/38/0 images: 249-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PR0PERTY OF HIS BRITANIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

G.T. 3256.

SECRET.

T.3256 WAR CABINET.

Intelligence Bureau, Department Department of Information.

Notes on Finnish Delegates on Recognition of Independence.

Taking the names of the delegation as published in the daily ?ross, I have received the following notes upon them from my Finnish correspondent:

Mr. E. Wolff: well-known business man, paper mill owner and exporter of pulp, board and timber: University man resident at Wiborg. When the Imperial February Menifesto was issued on 15th Feb. 1899 depriving the Finnish Diet of its legislative competence in all matters that may be declared to have a bearing on the interests of the Russian Realm, Mr. Wolff headed the Deputation which went to Petrograd to beseech the Tsar to reconsider this violation of the Finnish Constitution. At that time he held the honorary appointment of British Vice-Consul at Wiborg: to revenge himself on this "boldness" of Mr. Wolff, the Governor-General Bobrikoff had the Russian Government apply to the British Government for Mr. Wolff&apos;s dismissal on the ground of his taking part in political propaganda. Mr. Wolff was dismissed, whereupon all the other British honorary Vice-Consuls sent in their resignations from all parts of Finland.

Mr Lorenzo Kihlman (pronounced Tcheelman) is a former Attorney General, or as we call that official, Procurator of Senate.

Mr Holste, about whom I know very little. I am under the impression that some years ago he studied at the British Museum being a man of science and quite young. He is indeed the son of his father who was a Senator and a rather capable man. It is to be hoped that the apple did hot fall from the tree - unless there was at the moment a strong wind blowing.

Professor Julie Reuter, who really belongs to tho deputation to Washington, is accompanying the above members to London. He is Professor of Sanscrit at the University of Helsingfors. He has made several long visits to England, speaks English almost without accent, and has many English friends.

All the above belong to the Swedish Party except Mr, Holste, who is, I believe, a young Finn.

?7th January, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
