<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/38/0 images: 299-305</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.

?en.No./6687.

WAR CABINET.

The Cabinet Committee on Man-Power.

Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War.

I took the opportunity of sending copies of the report of the War Cabinet Committee on Man-Power to the Military Members of the Army Council, and enclose a note which they have drawn up on the report, and in which I concur.

9th January, 1918.

DERBY.
Memorandum by the Military Members of the Army Council on the draft Report of the War Cabinet Committee on  .MAN-POWER. 9 ^ ________.____________ d \1. As the Military Members of the Army Council-have beengiven an opportunity of seeing the draft Report of the War Cabinet Committee on Man-Power, they think the War Cabinet would desire to have an expression of their views as to the effect of the Committee&apos;s recommendations on the strength of the British Armies in the Field during the current year.2. Para. 70 (1)&apos;.     The recommendations giving absolutepriority over the Army to the personnel requirements of the various other services mentioned is presumably based to some extent upon the general conclusion referred to in para 18, and notwithstanding what is said in paras. 15 and 16 the Military Members fear that the Committee have been more influenced by numerical factors than by the moral and many other conditions which affect the fighting power of the Armies.3* Para. 52.   . The Military Members observe with graveconcern that, exclusive of 120,000 boys who will not be available for service abroad during 1918, only 100,000 Category A men are to be allocated to the Army during the year as against 615,000 estimated as being required to keep the Field Armies up to strength.4&quot;.        Para. 70 (6.).   There is nothing in the experience of this war or In any other to support the argument that a defensive policy necessarily entails fewer losses than an offensive policy, once fighting begins, and therefore in. the-opinion of the Military Members the adoption of a defen-sive policy does not justify making provision for a lowerrate
rate of wastage than that estimated by the War Office. The Adjutant-General&apos;s estimate of wastage is based on the experience of the past three years, and the wastage incurred during 1918 will depend, as always, upon the intensity of the fighting, and this in its turn will depend not solely upon the policy adopted by the Entente but primarily upon- the - policy-of the enemy.     We have had to adopt, a defensive policy for the time being not from choice but from necessity, and the initiative has, therefore, passed temporarily to the enemy.     If he forces the fighting - as he is almost certain to do - the Entente must also fight, and there are no grounds whatever- for supposing that, in that event, our rate of wastage this year will be less than In the past three years.5.     Para.50*   The Committee rely upon the rate of estimated French wastage as a further reason for justifying the lower e-stimate of British wastage.     As they have not the necessary data before them the Military Members are unable to express a definite opinion in regard to the French figures, but they are inclined to think that the comparison between French and &quot;British-estimates of Y/astage in Table H on page 12 is entirely misleading, for the reason that in the French figures every man who returns to any kind of duty in the Army is reckoned as a deduction from the gross wastage, whereas in the British calculation the only deductions from the gross wastage are the Category A men returned to the fighting line.After further careful consideration of the above and other circumstances the Council are unable to accept any lower basis of calculation of wastage than the actual past experience of the present virar.
O,6,    Paras, 40 and 70(7)     The Military Members are satisfied that the organisation of the British Divisions has well stood the test of the present war and. that it Is very undesirable to change itk     The French reduced the number of battalions from 12 to 9 chiefly,, if not entirely, because they had insufficient men to maintain 12.     The Germans reduced from 12 battalions to 9 when they were forming a large number of new divisions,- and although they utilised for this purpose the 3 battalions withdrawn from each division as well as a certain amount of&quot; artillery, nearly one-half of the personnel placed in the new divisions was raised in Germany and was a definite increase to the German field armies.7.     As to the feasibility of our forming additional divi-sions so as to create a larger  &quot;mobile reserve&apos;, the Comm-ittee appear to have overlooked tho fact that about one-third&apos; of the personnel of a division consists of artillery and other non-infantry units, and our shortage of men in tite artillery and other divisional units is becoming as great in proportion as it is in the Infantry,8.&quot;     A still more important matter is personnel for the in-fantry. The deficit in all theatres on the 1st instant was130,000 men and even after allowing for the reduction ofthe number of battalions in the divisions in France andItaly from 12 to 9 battalions, excluding Pioneer battalions,and for a correspondingly reduced proportion of casualtiesthe Adjutant-General estimates that there may still be adeficiency in those two theatres alone of -100,000..&apos;on 1st April,. 1918, 140,000 on 1st July, 1918, 202,000 on 1st October, 1918, 264,000 on 1st January, 1919,It
It is clear from these figures that the reduction o  ffiatfaLsTr^ from 12 to 9 will not only not enable additional divisions    to be formed, but will not even admit of the existing divisions at the reduced establishment of 9 battalions being maintained at strength, unless far more men are provided than those mentioned in para 52.      If these are not provided it will be necessary in order to keep divisions up to strength to bre;ak up 10 divisions and thus reduce the number to 42.   Further, as 5 of them are in Italy there will remain 157 in France in 1918 as compared with 52 in 1917 and they will have 25% less infantry than they had in 1917.9,      In these circumstances the Military Members cannot help thinking that the Cabinet Committee have failed to realise the perilous situation in regard to drafts for the Army and they suggest that the War Cabinet is not justified in accepting the statement at the end of para 71.     The Military Members feel that they will neglect their duty if they omit to warn the War Cabinet again of the results that may ensue from the inevitable diminution of the fighting forces at the front which must occur unless a far greater number of men are made available than that foreshadowed in the draft Report,10.    There Is every prospect of heavy fighting on the Westernfront from February onwards, and the result may well be that evenif the divisions successfully withstand the shock of theearlier attacks they may become so exhausted and attenuatedas to be incapable of continuing the struggle until the Americanscan effectively Intervene.       In short the Council would regard thacceptance
acceptance of the roc emendations in the draft Report without further effort to provide the men they consider necessary for the maintenance of the forces in the field during 1918 as taking an unnecessarily grave risk of losing the Far and sacrificing to no purpose the British Army&apos;on the Western front.ELi. As regards the other recommendations of the Committeearrangements have already been made to reduce the force of cavalry under the orders of Sir Douglas Haig (paras 35 and 70(8)), and the War Cabinet have already decided to reduce the Home Defence Forces by 4 Divisions (paras 36 and 70(10)).12 o The effect of the proposal in para.70(11) that menwho have been more than once severely wounded should, not be sent back to the fighting line, would, be that a monthly deduction of some 2,000 men would have to be made from reinforcements, with a resulting increase to the deficits referred to on page i^/^/^e^nafrJu^Logically a further 40,000 men who are now in the fighting line in the theatres of war would have to be withclrawn and replaced by fresh drafts, thus still further increasing the deficits B13P The effect of the proposals in paragraph 70 (9)and (12) will be small, for the reason that action has already been taken in rege,rd to the reduction of the Home Forces, and the number of &quot;Bn men retained will be barely sufficient to maintain those Forces.Further
9Q 3War Officeo 7.1-18.Further, as in paragraph 47 of the Report it is contemplated to transfer a large number of men from the Army to Shipbuilding, the combined effect of the reduction of the Home Forces and the drain that may be expected for the Ship-building industry will be that the number of &quot;B&quot; men remaining available will not much exceed the number required to meet substitution for &quot;An men within the Army itself.

</content>
</cab>
