<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/86/0 images: 58-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
State of Trade since the A R M I S T I C E. and the* ....PRESENT   POSITION.
STATE of TRADE sinoe the ARMISTICE and the PRESENT POSITION.Next to the Peaoe Settlement far the most pressing and considerable problem calling for solution is the complex industrial and commercial problem with which the country is , now confronted.   In order to realise this, and understand why it is so important to take up immediately the consideration of industrial and commercial policy, it is necessary to have a full knowledge of the facts and a clear conception of the essential features of the present situation and how it has been brought about.   In the present memorandum an attempt is made to set out the relevant facts and draw attention to the most salient points.The memorandum is divided into the following.parts and sections :-:PART. I. .Fssential features of the situation.PART II.The problem after the Armistice and the action, taken.PART III.Present conditions - facts and figures. ., 1-.   Prices2.   Foreign &quot;Exchanges - 3.   Imports and Exports .-4,   employment.   Industrial Conditions and Prospects.
i ,:S.K x     I *Essential Features of trie Situation.An immense change Ins taken place, as a result of the war, in industrial and commercial &quot;conditions,. : The magnitude of this change is apt to he overlooked, because we have gradually become accustomed to it, and there is consequently a tendency to underrate the task involved in the restoration of &quot;normal conditions. &apos; The most significant facts to be taken into account in estimating the position are as follows(1)   Before the war reached its close, millions of men had been taken for the Army and armies of women had been incorporated in -the industrial and commercial life of the communityc   The economic system has to be &quot;rapidly rendered capable both of absorbing the men returning from the Army and of furnishing employment for the women who desire to remain in employment.(2)   Broadly speaking, the industries of the country hadbeen transformed, both in respect of their plant and of their manual operations, in the process of adapting them to serve the needs of the War.   Everything has now to&quot;be turned back to meet ordinary requirements.   The change to war organisation was accomplished in the course of years and as a result of special exertions directed and fortified by Government action,   What has taken years to transform has to be retransformed in a comparatively short period when the country is less capable of making an effort and the Government cannot play so large a part(3)   Before the war the United Kingdom was dependent to amuch larger extent than any other big industrial&quot; country upon its export trade.   The truth of this statement is brought out by the following statistical comparison of the export of manufactured goods in 1913 per head of population from the principal countries:-finder&apos; the pressure of war necessity, we had to cut down our exports ruthlessly, thus reducing our means of payment for imports,   payment could only be made by borrowing abroad or selling foreign securities; and, as a result of war borrowings from abroad, the necessity to export is now far greater than it was before the war.   Our credit and our position in the world of commerce and finance can only be re-established by exporting goods to meet the animal charges on account of war indebtedness abroad, to pay off our debt and provide new capital for investment in the Empire oversea and abroad.   We have, therefore notUnited KingdomGermanyFranceUnited StatesItaly Japan9.0 5,5.c it Cj2 ii 5 1.6 1*0
only to re-establish our old export trade, but also to add many millions to it,&apos; and to do this under enormous difficulties.   Many outlets for trade in Europe will remain contracted for years, in consequence of the disorganisation and impoverishment caused by the war; and certain other oountries, notably the United States, are in a stronger competitive position than ourselves because they have suffered less from the war.   The present level of our exports is not nearly sufficient for what is needed,,(4)   Similarly on the side of imports there&apos; is some menace in the&apos; outlook.   Germany will be compelled to make every effort to sell abroad to satisfy her pressing needs and meet her obligations.   Also certain of our   v Allies have problems to face of which the solution is to be found in extensive sales abroad.   It is true that our incapacity to pay with our exports should soon erect around us a high exchange barrier which it would be difficult to surmount; but there would remain the fact that Germany, through being so needy a seller, would tend to secure a great part of the trade, in the absence of counteracting influences.   Again, there is dumping.   This practice, which was doing damage before the war, and causing a feeling of insecurity that probably did even more harm, is likely to be increasingly prevalent during the continuance of the unbalanced conditions that must be exi)ected for years to come.(5)   Further the war has revealed - or caused the&apos; country more fully to realise - the fact that there are weak spots in the national economy on account of the inefficiency or insignificant scale of certain fundamental industries.   The vital need of outstanding efficiency in these &quot;backward fundamental industries is greater than ever, not only with regard to our exports and general economic stability but also with regard to national security.   Efficiency in these industries must be brought at once to a high level if the solution of our problems is to be placed on a permanent footing.   Most of them are &quot;key&quot; or small industries, but there are one or two notable exceptions,(6)   Also it must not be overlooked that combination, which at its best promotes efficiency&apos; but may inflict damage on the community, has been fostered by the &quot;War and is likely to play an exceedingly prominent role.(7)   Striking as are the features to which attention has so far been directed, nothing in the present position is more significant than the great changes that have taken place in the ideas and sentiments of the population.   They affect profoundly the relations between capital and labour and the output.   The unmistakable indications of these changes are too numerous to mention.   On the continent there is the Bolshevist movement, and in this country the new ferment of ideas has created labour restlessness or caused it to be easily excited.   It must not be supposed that this state of agitation will rapidly subside.   It is undoubtedly an important factor to be taken into account in the formulation of an industrial policy.
The question of the industrial output is involved. It is stated that this is far from being in a satisfactory position; that instead of production per hour having increased,&apos; in consequence of higher wages and the reduction of hours, it has actually diminished I in too many cases,   Suspicion on the part of the wage-earning classes that if they worked harder they would merely add to profits, it said to be one cause, and it is certainly important that conditions should be such as to satisfy the workman that he is getting a fair share.   Otherwise there is bound to be sullen discontent and slackness,   More information is demanded with regard, to production and the earnings of capital.. Labour resents being kept so completely in ignorance; and ignorance is apt.grossly to exaggerate suspected grievances.   This, of course, is not the sole reason for the low output per houa\,   There- is, in addition, war-weariness, and the unsettled feeling accompanying transition,   Moreover as -Workpeople are not yet sure of the stability&apos; of their employment, there is a disposition to spread work over as long a period as possible,   This disposition on the part of labour&quot; will &apos; not disappear until it is evident that the business enterprise of the country is again firmly rooted,(8)   For the time being also we are in a thicket of difficulties connected with prices.   Unquestionably the prices charged for many things in ordinary use are outrageous.   One of the most serious consequences is that an attitude on the part of labour is Induced which diminishes output and therefore raises labour costs.   In the majority of cases, no doubt, prices are not out of the way, but the cases in &quot;which they are include commodities imrchaSed largely by the wage-earning classes.   The cause of these unreasonable charges is not entirely the import restrictions - to which fuller&apos; reference will be made later,   prices were forced up where there was still scarcity by the extensive demand that appeared shortly after the cessation of hostilities; and, in the absence of effective competition, there is a tendency for them to stick after rising- instead of falling when circumstances justify a fall.   Moreover, it appears to be the case&apos;that there are frequently agreements or understandings even when there are no strong combinations in the background. When competition is not strong, it is an easy&quot; matter to keep prices up without any machinery to secure the observance of agreements,,   The further admission of competition from overseas would undoubtedly have a large effect in tending to destroy the support lent to excessive prices by these understandings.   But though import restrictions are not exclusively to blame for the high charges that are being made for a number of the things in common use, it is obvious that they cannot be entirely exonerated.   To my&quot; mind the&apos; position . is serious and will become the more serious the.longer the causes are suffered to operate unchecked.   Demands for further increases of wages on account of these high prices may be brought forward any day. and conceding them would mean starting again the vicious cycle of rising wages and rising prices.   The prices and profiteering question can only bo dealt with either by-
striking at its roots, or by adopting extensive schemes of price regulation which would place upon the Government a task of enormous magnitude and complexity and cause such interferences with the ordinary course of trade as seriously to impede business and undermine initiative and enterprise.(9)   Finally there are claims on the part of the overseas parts of the Empire .to reckon with.   Reports of recent public speeches are sufficient evidence that av different attitude on the part of the mother country will be expected.   Nobody who has been in touch recently with representatives of the Dominions and India will fail to realise this.It must be evident to all who have made an attempt to envisage, the present position and the outlook that it is fallacious to conceive of our economic resettlement as a simple restoration of pre-war conditions.   And, even if it could be correctly so regarded, there is no doubt that a stable resettlement could not be brought about in a reasonable time, without a severe depression or possibly financial and other disasters, in the absence of active interest and co-operation on the part of the Government.   It may be assumed that the business community cannot of itself, on its own initiative directed solely by competition, solve the export problem, enable the high wages that are now demanded to be paid, satisfy the ether claims of labour, cause the expectations of the overseas parts of the Empire, with regard to their development&apos;to be met, and at the same time secure the firm establishment in this country of the industries on which our powers of defence.and our economic security dependoAt present the situation is manageable; soon it may become most awkward to handle.   I foel no hesitation in affirming that the main task before the Government is the solution of this vast and complex economic problem, and in urging that consideration should be given to it without delay.   If the Government is not early in the field with proposals that are appropriate to the new situation there appears to me to be a real danger of opinion in the country running to extremes or at least crystallising along the conflicting lines of obsolete controversies.   It must not be supposed that the action already taken by the State for the restoration of trade, which will be dealt with in Part II of this Memorandum, is sufficient to meet the situation for-some time to come,These are the broad generalisations to which my study of the position as it has developed has led me; but to make my presentation complete, it is necessary to supplement my reading of the facts with an account in more concrete terms of the course of events and the present position.
^......ii. -   59The problem after the Armistice and the action taken.Except for social legislation in the interests of workpeople and of the oonununity, commerce and industry before the war were left substantially untrammelled oither by government assistance, direction or restraint.   After the outbreak of war, however, it was soon recognised that control and direction Of industrial effort were necessary to an extent approximating to the direction and control which are essential in strictly military affairs, and only limited in reality by considerations of what was practicable.   At first slowly, but later with steadily increasing speed, industries, commercial operations and labour were taken under control and directed, as far as possible, to the attainment of the one -general object of victory,,   At the time of the armistice, the chief characteristic of our economic organi-sation, formerly so free, was its constraint and artificial-ity.Almost every staple article had been brought under control.   Priority was secured for government requirements, and private consumers were rationed according to the urgency of their needs and to the supplies available.   Tonnage for imports was allocated between various commodities with a very careful marginal adjustment between different classes of goods and different soa routes.   Machinery had been set up, and brought into operation, to secure that the needs of the Allies should bo satisfied in equal degree, and inter-Allied purchasing arrangements were in force to eliminate competition in the world&apos;s markets.   Prices were everywhere high and supplies (especially of imported goods and of goods mado from imported materials) were scarce.   The system of rationing and of prioe control, however, prevented supplies of essential goods and materials in this country from becoming unobtainable.   As regards labour, there was no lack of employment except in one or two industries (notably the cotton industry where scarcity of material necessitated short time); and there was a large unsatisfied demand for labour especially for munitions and other Government work -a demand which had to be met by the rationing of labour to different undertakings.Such an elaborate system of control could obviously be maintained no longer than was necessary to achieve the pur-pose for which it had been established, but the Government had to consider carefully how to minimise the dislocation which must accompany the transformation from war to peace conditions and how far it was desirable to return to pre-war methods and organisation in the new circumstances.   In any event, however, control had to be cut down to a minimum; the industrial and commercial system could not regain its vigour while hampered in every direction.The necessity for Government action was emphasised by the business stagnation and depression which followed the armistice.   This was due, for tho most part, to the following causes(1)   Expectation of a general fall of prices.(Z)   General uncertainty as to the future.(3)   War weariness and exhaustion and labour restlessness.
(4) Loss of old trade outlets and destruction of business connections and especially of the Old. organisation of credit facilities.(5)   Ti;.\o dislocation and the temporary stoppage accompanying the change over in some industries from war to peace work,This enumeration of causes calls for little comment. The expectation of a general fall of prices naturally induced buyers to hold back, and manufacturers could not continue to manufacture for stock on&apos;a falling market.   General uncertainty as to the future as regards international politics, labour, and government action with reference to trade both at home and abroad, accentuated the normal risks of large contracts and lengthy commitments.   War weariness was evident everywhere, and especially marked among workpeople who v/ere also dis-oontented with their condition and anxious about their wages and employment.   The suspension or severanco of business connections which resulted from the war, especially in the export trade, could not fail to be another important factor in a country so largely dependent on its exports of manufac-tured goods.   Again, the change over from war to peace work necessitated extensive changes of plant and other adjustments in many factories.By wages and hours of labour concessions, the Wages Act. unemployment benefits and the Coal inquiry labour restlessness has been reduced.   But on the trade side the situation continued bad..  Consequently an inquiry was made by the Cabinet into &quot;Unemployment and the State of Trade&quot;, and as a result of the inquiry, an interim policy was formulated and announced in the House of Commons on March 10th.   The chief measures decided on were:-(1)   Rapid abolition of surviving controls.(2)   Continued import restrictions on many manufactured goods, with liberation of other imports.(3)   facilitating of exports by opening outlets, improving cable services, and restoring means of trading.Abolition of controls.   At the time of the armistice, as has been explained, practically all the principal articles of commerce were subject to some form of control.   In several cases their dissolution was begun before the end of the year, and as a result of the definite interim policy adopted, the only commodities now controlled (apart from some foodstuffs and apart from restrictions on imports and exports) are:-Egyptian Cotton (till 51st July, 1919) FlaxCoal, Coke and Gas Hay and StrawLeather and Leather Material (partial) Pitwood Tungsten Ores Turpentine SubstituteWool (a limited control in respect of Australian and New Zealand Wool)Glassware PotashArms and Ammunition
Similarly the control over shipping has been largely released.(S)   Import Res tr i c tions.. These, it was decided, should be remoVe d&quot;so&quot;Far&quot;as^tlfey &quot;af iccted raw materials.   It was very strongly urged, however., that - the immediate removal of. restrictions on the import of manufactured goods would affect most detrimentally-home industries which had been dislocated for the purpose of the war or were disorganised while passing from war to peace work, together with industries which had been created or encouraged owing to circumstances arising out of the war.   Consequently it was decided to continue until September 1st restrictions on the importation of many manufactured goods, so as to shield British manufac-turers during the period of readjustment while they were getting bach*to peace conditions,   A Consultative Council was appointed by the Board of Trade at the end of March to advise on import restrictions, and, pending its recommendations in each particular case, a tight hold was kept on imports. Its work is now complete, ana the full list of restrictions, which are considerable, was published in &quot;The Board of Trade Journal&quot; of June 5th,As a result of this policy of exclusion, trade in the shielded industries has recovered rapidly, but in many of them, as already indicated, there is in consequence a problem of prices and profiteering which has aroused considerable feeling and will become most serious if it continues much longer. .The policy of import restrictions was admittedly a somewhat rough-and-ready general method of dealing with -immediate troubles.   It is effective for a short period, but as time passes, the necessity which called for it - that ox shielding home manufacturers under exceptional conditions during a transition period - diminishes, while the dis-advantages associated with the policy increase.   At its best, it is full of defects.   Some miscalculations are bound to be made in deciding on the quantities of different commodities to admit, and, in the wake of these errors, problems of high prices and profiteering unavoidably arise. Manufacturers are tempted to concentrate on the secure home market and to neglect the export trade, so vital to our stability.   There are cases of individual hardship on whatever principle licences are distributed, and constant irritation&apos;is caused by the mere fact that permission to import has to be applied for and certain formalities have to bo observed.   Ho particular harm is being done at the present time, and no: very violent protests are being received, but this is because the existing arrangements are recognised as designed to meet exceptional circumstances and are expected to cease at the end of August.   The difficulties which would arise in the event of the continuance of the policy of restriction would include diplomatic difficulties. Some countries, notably the United States, have objected even to the interim restrictions and would be strongly critical of their prolongation.Those are serious considerations but even more serious is that already touched upon, the uncertainty that must exist so long as merely temporary measures are in force.   It was sufficient at first to secure immediate activity on the part of industry to meet immediate demands.   This was
secured to a large extent.. Industry restarted and the immediate problem was solved.   But producers are now looking further ahead and the uncertainty about the State policy that will be in operation at the time when undertakings now entered into.come to maturity is undoubtedly having a damping effect.   Commerce under the new world conditions must venture into almost uncharted seas; without confidence, it will not set forth.   Complete knowledge of the conditions of the future cannot be obtained but knowledge of the Government1s plans can be given and this would at least provide a point d&apos;appui.   Many representations have been made to the Board of Trade to the effect that business is being held up, and unemployment ensuing, because it is not known what the country&apos;s trade policy is to be*   There is little chance of a rapid restoration of normal conditions so long as no announcement is made, and until this is done even a relapse into -depression is possible.In connection with any proposal to continue the policy of import restrictions, it must be borne in mind that legislative powers would probably have to be sought. Similarly legislative powers are required for the continued control of the export of things of which we may be short. The present position is as followsImports are prohibited under Section 43 of the Customs Consolidation Act, 1876, but it may be questioned whether the interpretation of the Act on which the prohibitions rest can be maintained after a state of war has definitely ceased to exist - or at any rate maintained without exciting increased protestations-   Moreover, there is no power to prohibit imports from any particular place and differentiation against any country in the issue of licences is of very, doubtful legality,   In the case of exports it is certain that we should have no powers at all to prohibit any exports beyond a limited list of specified articles after the war technically ceased (as existing powers are given by Special Acts and confined to the time when a state of war exists). (3)   Exports * The policy as regards exports&apos; ht*z been to allow complete freedom of trade to non-blockade countries, except in munitions, goods required for home consumption, and goods benefitted by State subsidy or purchase.   In the case of blockade neutrals; as many manufactured articles as possible have been put on to the free list, the list of goods permitted to be exported under licence has been extended, and the system of rationing has been discontinued though pledges not to export to enemy countries are still required.   Also trade has been opened with occupied portions of Germany, Turkey and Bulgaira, and with Poland, Czecho--Slovakia, Jugo-Slavia, etc.   Re-exports were also allowed so far as possible.i......Partly as a result of the steps that were taken, but partly also as a result of other causes such as the marked recovery of world prices, the immediate outlook has greatly improved.   But we are only at the beginning of the solution of our difficulties.   Complicated processes of readjustment are in train, and even industries which are of themselves in a position to recover rapidly, are still held back by the continued effects of dislocation, in others-   Inability to meet retirements on the part of one industry or service,
due to whatever cause, means diminished output and increased cost of production in all kinds of other industries and services.   For example, lack: of export cargoes of coal hinders the import of iron ore, and is causing diminished output in the iron and steel trades.   Moreover, intornal transport is in an unsatisfactory position.   There is serious congestion particularly where &quot;the alternative of coastal service has been largely ruled out, by its relatively high cost and otherwise.   It is urgent that the arrangements that the solution calls for should be made as soon as possible.It is clear that output generally cannot reach normal dimensions until the various causes of dislocation inherited from the war are removed.   Loss of output is no doubt partly attributable to labour causes, but this is by no means the sole retarding&quot;influence.   War weariness is passing, and the old outlets for trade and business connections, or new ones to replace them, are gradually appearing, but there are again difficulties, connected with the means of payment, which prevent use being made of many of the opportunities that offer.   The change over to peace work is also approaching completion, except insofar as extensive reconstruction is required, but uncertainty as to the future remains almost undiminished, and must, inevitably be felt to an unusual exten for a long time to come.   Unexpected occurrences of a political or economic character are liable to throw business which is Just reviving back into a state of depression. Business conditions are therefore still unstable.   It is hoped that the signing of Peace and the oomplete removal of the Blockade and the Censorship will have a stimulating effect, and one cause of instability will be removed when . the Government has announced its intentions.
PART 111*Pi&apos;esent coxjditions *- facts ai::d^ f igur 1.&apos;   Prices.For nearly twenty years &quot;before the War the general level of world prices had been rising, and prices in this country had been moving up in accord with them.   Prom the lowest point in 1896 wholesale prioes had risen some 40 per cent at the eve of wartThis movement of prices was the resultant of a number of forces not all pulling in the same direction,   forces tending to raise prices were the expansion of the world&apos;s gold production which was bound up especially with the development of the Transvaal mines, and the extension of banking and credit arrangements the effect of which was to economise gold by enabling an increased number of trans-actions to be performed upon the basis of a given quantity of gold.   On the other hand, the worldls monetary require-ments were increasing with the growth of population and the opening up of new countries.   In this connection it is to be noted that the United States no longer contained vast tracts of virgin soil for cultivation.   Tho law of diminishing returns was beginning to come into operation there. To open up new agricultural areas it was necessary to go further afield, to Canada, Argentina, Australia, etc and in the decade before the War rapid expansion, promoted largely by European capital and by emigration from Europe was witnessed The effects of this expansion upon the world&apos;s trade were not sufficient, however, to counteract the forces tending to raise prices.A general rise of prices, it should be noted, has considerable economic and social consequences.   It alters the effect of many contracts by diminishing the value in terms of commodities of all pre-arranged money payments. It tends thus to benefit borrowers at the expense of lenders It tends similarly to injure classes .with fixed salaries and fixed incomes from property. Also, it tends to injure those sections of the working classes whose wages are not rapidly adjusted to changes in prices.   At the same time it stimulates the enterprise that looks far ahead - but it may stir up unhealthy speculation - whereas falling prices causa business men to&apos;look most cautiously at undertakings the yield of which is comparatively distant.In 1914* as has been said, wholesale commodity prioes were some 40 per cent higher than they had been in 189-S. There is nothing to suggest that the rise would not have continued had there been no war.   Had it gone on at the same&apos; average rate the prices of 1919 would have b^en approximately 8 per cent higher than in 1914.As a consequence of the war the rise of wholesale price all round has been not 8 per cent, but about ISO per cent in this country.   This percentage increase is 30 - 40 per cent greater than that which has occurred in the United States and is greater also than in many other countries - distant from the theatre of war.   On the other hand, it is
smaller than in other European belligerent countries^   Thus in April 1919 French prices were even estimated to have r.isen 230 per cent above the level of 1913, compared with a rise of 114 per cent at that time in the United Kingdom. The increase of prices in jtaly is probably greater than in France.   The effeot of the war has undoubtedly been to drive up the level of world,,prices to a very great extent, in so far as a general level of world prioes can at present be said to exist, but forces have been at work in the most actively belligerent countries to raise, priee3 more than the averageoThe factors which have driven up world prices include the withdrawal and replacement by paper of gold in circulation;   the liberation of hoards and centralisation of their contents in banking reserves where they can act as a basis of credit; the tacit or avov/ed adoption of incbnver-tible paper currencies for the time being by several countries;   the expansion of credit, or inflation, which has taken place in many countries on the basis not only of forced ourrency paper but also of gold.   At the same time, the output of most kinds of goods ha3 materially diminished. The changes in the legal tender monetary system of the United Kingdom betv/een 1914 and the middle of 1918 were shown by the Committee on Currency and foreign Exchanges to be as follows;-1.   The amounts on 250th June 1914 were:-Fiduciary Issue of Bank of England  16,450,000Bank of England Notes issued againstgold coin or Bullion    ...        ,..  38v476,000Estimated amount of gold coin held bybanks (excluding gold coin held inthe Issue Department of the Bank ofEngland) end in public circulation  123,000,000C-rand Total      ...        ... ...  179,926,0002.   Eas amounts on 10th July 1918 were:-Fiduciary Issue of Bank of England   18,450,000Currency Notes not covered by gold 230,412,000UTotal Fiduciary Issues .... 248,862,000 Bank of England issues against coinand bullion      ..c                      ... 65,368,000Currency Notes covered by gold 28,500,000 Estimated amount of gold coin held bybanks (excluding coin held by IssueDepartment of Bank of England)... 4-0,000,000Grand*!otal      ...                      ... 382,730,000Thus legal tender money had more than doubled by last summer.   Since then there has been a further great expansion. The Total Fiduciary Issues, have increased from  248,862,000 oh 10th July 1918 to  334/729,000 on 18th June 1919, owing
to continued issues of Treasury Notes; and assuming that the amount of gold held by the Banks (excluding coin held by the Issue Department of the Bank of England) remains unaltered at  40,000,000, the Grand Total of legal tender money amounts no?/ to  489,000j000, i.e. about 2 % times as much as on 30th June 1914,   It is not wholly coincidence that this represents approximately also the increase of commodity prices.The increase of Bank deposits has been somewhat smaller in proportion than the increase of legal tender money. Deposits at the Bank of England and at the English, Scottish and Irish Joint Stock Banks grew by about 96 per cent between the end of 1913 and the end of 1918, from  1,077,240,000 to  2,109,757,000,The enormous rise of prices during the war has had far-reaching effects, by altering the distribution of property and income among different classes of the community and furnishing increased opportunities of profiteering. Moreover as a creditor owning large amounts of foreign securities bearing fixed interest,&quot; the country as a whole has suffered at the expense of foreign debtors.   Vfeges, and more particularly the earnings of the working classes, have on the whole, perhaps, risen in proportion to the increase in the cost of living, but there is much diversity among different groups of workpeople.   According to the labour Gazette, percentage increases on 1914 in rates of wages range from 60&apos; per cent to over 150 per cent, these being extreme figures.   The general average increase in rates of wages is estimated to be between 100 and 120 per cent, apart from enhancements of hourly and piece rates in certain industries the effect of which on weekly wages has been neutralised by reductions in the weekly hours of labour.During the war the normal relations between prices of different commodities have been to a 0&apos;considerable extent disturbed. &quot; Some goods have been in great demand or in short supply; others have been plentiful or little sought after. Again Government control has affected the price of some commodities and not others, while the prices of controlled commodities bore varying relations to pre-war prices. In a few cases prices were kept artificially low by means of a subsidy.   The rise in the wholesale price of a number of important commodities between July 1914 and June 1919 is indicated by the following figures:-Increase Per cent.English wlieat      ... ...           ,,.         114Flour (incl. Subsidy),,. ...                  55Barley                ... ...           ...         14VOats         ...            ... ...                145Potatoes             ... ...                         5g2ea           ...             ... ....                  72Coffee                ... ...           ...           71Sugar       ...           .... ....               309Butter             -   ... ...                        140Tobacco     ...             ,&apos;,, ,,,                 104American Cotton   ... ....          ...         160Egyptian Cotton         ... ...                160Cotton yarn         ... ...           ....         295
Cotton ClothAustralian WoolS i Ik .. . ...Flax ... ...Hemp ... ....J ut 9 ... ...Pig IronSteel Ship Plate3 Welsh Steam Coal (to Allies) &quot;Welsh Steam Coal (to Spain &amp; South Spelter      ... ...Lead Tin CopperBaltic Timber English Hides Potroleum Palm Oil Linseed Rubbererica)Increase per cent. 270 249 119 476 112 111 212 19686 13381196842 27783 132 159 38413It will be seen that the articles whioh have risen most include a number of textiles, (notably, Flax, Wool, and cotton yarn and cloth), sugar, Baltic Timber, and Linseed. Among the articles which rose leas&apos;t are (apart from rubber which actually fell in price) Potatoes, Tea, Coffee, Spelter, Lead, Tin, Copper and English Hides.Since the armistice prices have undergone substantial modifications.   The extremely high quotations of certain imported articles, especially those required for war purposes, (e.g* Copper, Spelter, Lead, Hemp) have eased with the improvement of the shipping position and the cessation of Government requirements.   Government Department hold large stocks of certain materials and the sale of these tends,to reduce prices.   Consequently prices have eased somewhat, but they have not shown that rapid and substantial fall which the public generally expected.   The following figures illustrate the general course of prices sinco last autumnEnd ofOct.1918 Nov.Dec Jan. Feb. Mar. April Mav.1919Economist Index No. Labour Gazette basedwholesale prices on working class(fo increase on July budget (f0 increase1914.) on July 1914,)142 142 138 128 126 122 125 133133 129 130 120 115 110 105 105It will be noticed that during April and May general, wholesale prices have again risen somewhat,   In the near future they may rise still further.   Demand has recovered; and it is not unlikely that the resumption of trade with enemy countries will also tend to keep prices of many -raw
materials up., eye?.: if it does not raise them above their present level, because competition for available supplies will be increased,.   Certainly it is a striking fact that trade periodicals are predicting higher prices in a number of staple tradesoShe depression of trade has been in large part due to the fact that the business world and the public, both here and in the overseas markets, misread the futureft   They expected a great and rapid fall of prices; but the conditions which caused high prices continue0The fall after the armistice seems likely to be ephemeral and was no doubt largely due to a reduction in freights.   The business community and the public, realising that they were mistaken in their expectation as regards the immediate outlook have begun to buy0   But an actual rise of prices, though encouraging buyers to embark on commitments, is likely to havft disturbing reactions on exports.   Even as things are, the nome market is in many instances relatively too attractive, with the result that the exports which are so sorely needed tend to be kept down0   Moreover, further advances would start again the vicious circle of wages rising with prices and prices with wages, and increase apprehensions as to the magnitude of the ultimate fall.What will be the ultimate fall?   Hobody can say.   But it is certain, in view of the development of credit machinery and the dissipation of gold hords, that with the resumption of gold payments the level of 1914 would not be nearly reachedb   This question does not, however, appear to be of urgent practical importance at the moment.   Presumably it may be taken for granted that immediate deflation of the currency is out of the question for financial reasons alone. Moreover, grave social disturbance would in all probability accompany the inevitable fall in money wages (when a fall became legal), and given a sudden collapse there would be grounds for apprehending the greatest business crisis that has ever been experienced.One urgent question connected with present prices, consists of the high prices charged for many things in common use, such as clothing boots and many household requisites, and the excessive profits that are being made out of the production and distribution of several of these thingse   This problem has been discussed on PP0 5-60 Regulation, which would be exceedingly difficult and might entail rationing, or increased supply and more competition, appear to be the&apos;only means of removing the trouble which is causing widespread resentment,.2c__Foreign Exchanges,The importance of a country5s foreign exchanges is that they regulate its imports and exports.   If the exchange value of the sovereign rises in terms of other currencies, then, other things being equal, imports are encouraged and exports are discouraged,,   But if on the contrary the exchange value of the sovereign falls, imports are discouraged and exports are encouraged,,In order to make this quite clear, a particular&apos;example may be given.   Suppose that exchange with America dropped
from 4f Dollars to the pound sterling- to 4  Dollars, then-&apos; obviously there would be less disposition, if other things remain the same, for American producers&apos;to sell in this country..   Because whereas previously an article that sold in this country for a sovereign meant a receipt in America of 4-J dollars, it would mean after the Change a receipt in America of no moire than 4-i- dollars3   (The 4f dollars might cover the cost of production in America and transport to this country while 44 might not.   Hence imports from America are curtailed.   Similarly exports from this country to America are stimulated, because the thing that can be sold in America for no more than 4-g- dollars and can be produced here for what is left of a sovereign after paying carriage to America can now be exported, as 4^- dollars in America will procure a sovereign here, whereas previously this thing could not be exported because as much as 4f- dollars was then needed in America to yield sufficient in this country to cover the cost of production and transport, namely a sovereign^   Consequently it is necessary in representingoncmio outlook, to show the position and prospects of the foreign exchanges0It is mast important, however, to bear in mind that it is not the foreign exchanges alone which regulate imports and exports but the relation of these to the levels of prices in the countries in. question,,   Consequently it has been necessary in the brief exposition given above to use such phrases as 1 other things being equal1, and 1 if other things remain as-before1.   feat regulates the Imports and exports between any two countries-is the relation of the rate of foreign exchange to the price levels of the two countries or, in other words,&apos;. the relation between the home exchange rates of money in the two countries and its foreign exchange rate0Thus, if the exchange value of the franc falls from 25 to 50 to the pound sterling, French exports to this country would be increased and her imports from this country reduced were prices in this country and in France to remain at the previous level.   But if it should be ,the case that prices here remained at the old level, while, prioes In  ranee doubled, then the effect on the foreign trade between the two countries would be precisely nil, because nothing would have happened beyond a reduction to the extent of one half in the value of the franc both at home and for foreign trade purposes,,   In short what had been 50 oentimes as a unit of account would have become a franc in effect, which in itself could not alter the balance between home and foreign trade.   It is vital that this should be borne in mind in interpreting the present position of - the exchanges.-V/ith the franc at 30 to the pound there may be no inducement at all&apos;to increase the quantity of goods sent to this couutrya   On the contrary there may actually be the opposite,, for prices in France may have risen so far in excess of the rise in this country as to counteract entirely the fall, in the foreign exchange value oi the franc.Another important point to bear in mind in connection with the foreign exchanges is that the more normal trade becomes the greater becomes the dependence of one foreigr exchange on another, so that, in relation to any one country, they tend to move sympathetically.   This is
6-9explained by two facts.   In the first place payments for a country&apos;s Imports can be made indirectly by the export of bills on other countries, as well as directly, and the cheapest form of payment is the one naturally selected.   In the second place trade is shifted from one quarter to another by the movement of one exchange, and movement in the other exchanges is consequently induced.   Should, then, the American exchange go to say 4 dollars 50 cents to the pound sterling, the number of francs to the poxnd, to give one example, would also tend to become less. -This 1the case, holding up the American exchange with us indirectly holds up our other exchanges, and therefore tends to place this country in a depression, in respect of the exchanges towards which goods from the rest of the world are naturally drawn.It is true that these are not normal times, and. that for a period, therefore, counteracting influences might prevent the expected results from following on the collapse of a particular exchange.   For example, there is reason to suppose that the franc in terms of the pound sterling is asgivenbecause extensive credits are beingwere50 centsvaluable as itto France privately in this country, the pressure on the French exchange being thereby relieved.   3ut for these credits, the French exchange might be say, at 35 francs to the pound instead of in the neighbourhood of 30. the English-American exchange to go to 4 dollars the&apos; tendency for the English-French exchange to move, to say, 27 might be entirely counteracted if one consequence of the collapse of the American exchange was a large reduction in the credits given by this country to France. Indeed, this in itself might have so large an effect on the-English-French exchange as to bring it about that instead of a movement to 27 the French exchange might fall to &quot;31 or 32.   It should be noted, however, that hitherto in this particular case the disturbing factor in question appears to have had only a very limited influence, as witness the close correlation between the costs of making French payments to America direct and via London which is revealed, by the following figures&amp; value of 100 francs on direct payment.i value of 100 francs on payment via LondonPercentage gain or loss in direct payment.Jan.30th 1919   18.33Feb. 6th 18.33&quot; -13th 18.33&quot;   20th 18.33&quot;   27th 18.29Mar. 6th 18.28&quot;   13th 18.20&quot; . 20th 17.45&quot;     27th 16.72Apl&apos;. 3rd 16.78&quot;   10th 16.64&quot;   17th 16.64&quot;   24th 16.481st 16.488th 16.2715th 15.71Ma,18.34 18.34 18.34 18.34 18.31 18.30 18.23 17.32 16.79 16.84 16.78 16.73 16.53 1.6.55 16.23 15.77.05 .05 .05 .05 .11 .11 .14 .74 .41 .35 .36 .30 .33 .42 .24 .37
tMay Junerr itITDate.2&amp;n&amp; 1919 29th 5th 12th 19th 26th&amp; value of 100 francs on direct payment.14.90 15.44 15.37 15.64 15.39 15.46i value of 100 francs on payment via London.14.85 15.55 15.45 15.60 15.43 15.39Percentage gain or loss in direct payment..33.71.52 r .26 -      .26.45Taking the chief exchanges, and comparing their present position with the pre-war par, the pound sterling is roughly at the percentage premium shewn in the following cases:-Percentage premium on pound sterling.LondonH &apos;!! TJ TtParisGermany... Brussels Lisbon ...18 46190 (approx.) 22 75In the following cases there is approximately the discount shewn:-Percentage discount on pound sterling.London   -lew York Yokohama ... Amsterdam Stockholm... Greece Switzerland Madrid Buenos Ayres5.56;62.4 2.0 3.1 1.4 7.9 6.2The extensive premiums and discounts shown in these tables are rendered possible by the fact that in many cases the gold basis has become a fiction for the time being, and gold movements are largely under control.   Important exchanges are being kept up by Government arrangements.   Thus the sovereign would be far more depreciated in terms of a dollar were it not that a large part of our necessary-imports wore being carried on credits furnished by America. Were all support of this kind withdrawn, there is no knowing to what point the exchange would fall.   As has already been explained, the direct and indirect effects of a substantial fall would be ,greatly to reduce our imports and increase our exports.   But the cost.to us of food and raw materials would rise, bo far as they were carried on the exchanges affected, and as regards food at any rate there would be nothing &quot;to set against this on account of the premium on exports.As has already been explained these tables of premiums and&apos; discounts tell nothing in themselves of the flow of international trade that is being set going.   To bo able to infer $his, it is necessary to know in addition
what the price movements in the several countries have he en.   With regard to Prance, it may he affirmed, on the basis of such imperfect evidence as is available, that conditions just now aro probably favouring exports from the United Kingdom.   Prices in Prance have risen much more than they have here, and it is doubtful whether this difference is wholly counteracted by the loss involved in remitting money from Paris, &apos; The case of Italy is more doubtful.   With regard to Germany the tendency is alomst certainly the opposite.In the case of the United States, imports by us are being on the whole encouraged,   This can be shown by the following rough calculation-,   Wholesale prices in the United Kingdom have increased during the war in the ratio of about 100 to 2 2 according to tho Economist Index number for May 1919.   In the United States tho increase was only in the ratio of 100 to 196 according to BradstreetTs Index lumber.   Thus British prices are IE per cent, higher than their normal relation to American prices.   Clearly, therefore, the export of goods from this country to the United States must be discouraged unless the difference in the levels of prices is fully compensated by the gain on exchange secured when remitting the proceeds of goods export-ed back to this country    In fact the difference is not fully compensated, the gain on exchange at the ond of May in remitting from 2?ew York to London^being only 4-^- per cent,Finally, in connection with this particular matter, it must be borne in mind that the position of the exchanges which encourages importation from countries producing articles that compete largely with the products of this country is far more serious than a similar state of the exchanges with regard to countries whose production is rather complementary to ours than in competition with it.A farther point to note in this section is the importance of re-establishing foreign exchanges with the disorganised parts of Europe.   Also reference must be made to the problem of the London money market, though it is not proposed to discuss it here.   Before the War London was by far the most important financial, centre of the world, an enormous amount   of business being done in the way of financing trade and settling accounts between foreign countries.   During the war the position of London has been much weakened and consideration will have to be given to the conditions under which these operations will be facilitated.3.   Imports an&amp;^Exports-After a period of inexpansiveness during the later years of the 19th Century and the earlier years of the 80th Century, foreign trade began to increase rapidly from about tho year 1905.   Except for a depression in 1908-9 the figures increased unintermittently.
	Imports	British	Re-exports		Exports		 1,000,000	 1,000,000.	 1,000,0001904	551. 0	300.7	70o31905	556.0	329,8	77.81906	607.9	375.6	85.11907	645.8	426,0	91.91908	593.0	377.1	79.61909	624.7	378.2	91.31910	678.3	430.4	103.81911	680.2	454.1	102.81912	744.6	487.2	111.71913	768.7		109,6Between 1904 and 1913 imports had grown in value 40 per cent, exports 75 per cent and re-exports 56 per cent.    The actual increase in the volume of trade, on account of the rise, of prices (approximately 20 per cent) wculd he less than is shown by the above figures.During the decade under review British Capitalists were actively engaged in promoting the development of the Empire oversea and of foreign countries by the investment of capital and this partly accounts for the large percentage growth of exports.    The statistics of new capital for oversea investments publicly subscribed in London during the period are informing:- 1904	72,925,0001905	120,497,0001906	81,906,0001907	90,560,0001908	142,152,0001909	163,675,0001910	207,143,0001911	165,614.0001912	165,514,0001913	160,586,000This capital was exported largely in the form of manufactured goods which comprise 75 per cent of all British exports, and it is natural that exports to the countries mainly attracting this capital should have grown to a greats proportional extent than aggregate.British exports.Exports to	1904           1913	Increase		per centCanada	10,624,000 23,795,000	124Argentine	10,845,000 22,641,000	109Brazil	5,975,000 12,465,000	109Australia	17,335,000 34,470,000	99British India	40,641,000 70,273,000	73Straits Settlements	3,129,000   7,175,000	129Ceylon	1,411,000   4,185,000	197Nigeria	1,371,000   3,734,000	172Russia	8,230,000 18,103,000	120l&apos;lor similar reasons it was to be expected that imports from these countries, consisting mainly of foodstuffs and
raw materials in the production of which British capital played a prominent part should have greatly expanded.   The extent of this expansion is shown below:-Imports from 1904 1913 Increaseper centCanada	23,300.000	30,488,000:	31Argentine	23,407,000	42,485,000!	81Brazil	6,434,000	10,000,000	57Australia	23,660,000	38,065,000	61British India and   )			Straits Settlement)) Ceylon	42,704,000	67,794,000	59	4,133,000	7,797,000	89Nigeria	1,759,000	3,890,000	121Russia	32,981,000	40,271,000	22The decade preceding the war witnessed also a great expansion of British trade with certain neighbouring countries on the Continent of Surope, notably Germany, Belgium and Switzerland.   This trade in the main was of a different character from that referred to above between the United kingdom and the countries which are being newly opened up.   Both the import and the export trade consisted largely of manufactured goods including goods to bo used for further manufacture.   Inability to obtain some of these goods from Germany after the outbreak of war was the cause of great inconvenience and threatened even to be disastrous. The following figures show the growth of British trade with certain European countries between 1904 and 1913.Imports into United Kingdom1904  ; 1913 Increaseper centProm:    Germany 49,512,000       80,411,000 62Belgium 16,740,000       23,382,000 40Switzerland 7,454,000       11,070,000 49Exports from United kingdom to:Germany 25,101,000       40,677,000 62Belgium 7,859,000        13,240,000 68Switzerland 1,277,000 4,212,000 230There was also an Important expansion of trade of a different character with Norway, Sweden and Denmark.It is reasonable to assume that had there been no war, the developments which were in progress during the years immediately preceding 1914 would have continued without substantial modification.   Imports and exports would have been somewhat larger all round, and the amount, of British capital invested in the empire oversea and in foreign countries would have risen from something less than  4,000 million to perhaps not far short of  5,000 million at the present time.The continuance, of this development was interrupted by the war and during the past five years the trade of the
world and of the United Kingdom in particular has heen thoroughly upset.   On the whole, the export trade was disturbed more than the import trade, great though the disturbance to the import trade was.   The continuance of a large part of the import of goods and materials was essential to the existence of this country, while a large part of the export trade could at a pinch and for a short time be sacrificed provided that payment could be made for imports-in other ways,   The movements in the values of imports and exports during the war are perhaps less significant than the figures of quantities, on account of the enormous increase of prices.   They are, however, of considerable interest:-	Imports	Exports and	Excess of	768,735,000	Re-exports	Imports  1913		634,820,000	133,915,0001914	596,635,000	526,195,000	170,440,0001915	851,893,000	483,930,000	357,963,0001916	948,506,000	603,846,000	344,560,0001917	1064,155,000	596,757,000	467,408,0001918	1319,339,000	529,429,000	789,910,000	The Statistics of	imports in the years	1914-1917 are tosome extent incomplete, in that they omit certain goods imported on public account.   It is estimated that about  10 millions should be added to the imports for 1914 to allow for this account; some  40-45 million for 1915;  190 million for 1916, and  135 million for 1917.Perhaps the most interesting feature of the above figures is the increase in the excess of imports over exports.   Before the war the excess of imports was fully accounted for by shipping freight receipts of British vessels, commission charges and various other earnings which do not appear in the trade statistics or are included in the value of goods imported.   In addition the receipts on account of interests and profits on capital invested outside the United Kingdom probably amounted to nearly  200,000,000 and that sum approximately represented tho amount.of new investments made abroad during the year.During the war the position has changed greatly to our disadvantage.   It is not possible to analyse exactly the various items whose aggregate effect was an excess of imports during 1918 of nearly  800 millions, but the main features of the change that has taken place in our international indebtedness are known.   During the war about  1,000,000,000 of our foreign securities had to be sold, and a further  1,300.000,000 had to be borrowed abroad to meet current liabilities.   This has involved an immense weakening of our economic position, and while we formerly drew an annual income of roughly  200 million from overseas, the net amount must now be well under  100,000,000.   It is true that a large part of the capital which we have borrowed or withdrawn from investment has been loaned to our European Allies and to the Dominions for war purposes.   .The amount so loaned had reached  1,739,000,000 at 3lst March 1919.   If this debt could be taken at its face value, our position as a creditor nation would have been comparatively little impaired; but in fact the value of a large part of it is problematical.
While the value of imports increased greatly, the quantity was enormously diminished during the&apos;latter part of the war, owing to the scarcity of shipping..  All but the most essential imports had to be cut off, steps being taken, to increase home production of goods (especially bulky goods) which were formerly imported.   Before the war the aggregate weight of goods imported amounted to about 54,000,000 tons.   In 1910 it fell to about 43,000,000 tons, in 1917 to 37,000,000 tons and in 1918 to 35,000,000 tons.This decline of imports has been spread very unevenly as between different commodities.     Certain things, needed for war purposes, were imported in larger volume than before the war, but most things were imported in much smaller quantities, and some things were no longer imported at all.While the importation of articles of luxury had been curtailed at an earlier date, the policy of exclusion did not assume large dimensions till February 1916, and as at the end of 1916 it was found necessary to restrict imports still further.   An additional scheme of restriction was approved by the War Cabinet and put into force on 1st March 1917. Nor was this the last step.     Again in 1918 further large restrictions were decided upon, but fortunately the shipping situation proved better than was anticipated, and imports for 1918 were only 2,000,000 tons less than 1917.The war has affected the volume of British export trade even more markedly than that of imports.   The weight of all articles exported has been calculated and the reduction is shown in the following table, in which coal coke and manufactured fuel, which account for the major part of the weight of exports, are shown separatelyEstimated weight of Exports.Year	Coal, Coke and Manufactured Fuel	All other Articles	Tons	Tons1913	76,688,000	15,394,0001914	61,831,000	12,541,0001915	45,771,000	9,394,0001916	41,158,000	9,519,0001917	37,801,000	6,941,0001918	34,174,000	4,976,000The export trade which remained was very largely re-distributed to meet the needs of our Allies,   Its distribution by weight has not been ascertained, but the following table showing the changes in money values, brings out the broad facts.
p. 1DestinationDeclared Value of United Kingdom ExportsIn1913In 1918Increase (-) or Decrease in 1918 compared with 1913.Allies of the United &quot;KingdomPrance &amp; Italy-All&apos; other allies Russia Neutrals British Dominions and posses-ions. , 1,000112,376 18,103 92,777205,112 1,000 1,000   Per cent43,542      157,324   (-)   113,782 f-) 261.382,753 298 79,585(-) (-) (-)29,623 (-) 26.4 17,805 (-) 98.4 13,192 (-)   14.2178,513   (-)     26,599 (-)   13.0EnemyCountries53,335(-)     53,335 (-) 100.0Total525,245      498,473   (-)     26,772 (-)     5.1, The increase and decreases in this table must be read in relation to the changed level of prices.   Measured by the quantity of goods exported, the loss of exports in the trade with the other parts of the British Empire and with Neutrals would probably be expressed as 40 per cent or more.   The exports to &apos;all other Allies&apos; decreased by  29623.000. About half of this was due to the practically complete loss of our export trade to Belgium, Roumania,, and Serbia, while the remainder of the decrease was due to the partial loss of exports to the other, mostly non-European, countries associated with this country against the Central Empires. The rate of this partial loss was not very different from that to neutrals and to other parts of the British Empire.of export to France and Italy in 1918 was that recorded for 1913 to the same countries,The value about 3^ times and it is probable that the deduction which should be made in respect of the higher level of prices in 1918 would still give the measure of the increase as something like a doubling of the volume of export.   The value of exports to Russia In. 1917 had been nearly 3. times what it was in 1913, but in 1918 the export trade was almost entirely suspended as a consequence of the Bolshevik revolution.   In 1913 France and Italy accounted for only 8 per cent of our total exports, while in 1918 they accounted for nearly one-third. To all our Allies we sent, in 1913, barely 30$ of our total exports,&apos; while in 1918 they received nearly one-half the total sent to all countries.   This change was very largely due.to the needs of our allies for war materials, which we were able to supply in considerable quantities.The resources of our mines and&apos; factories, and the carrying power&apos;of our mercantile marine,, have.been-placed unreservedly at the&apos; disposal of France and our other Allies, but in supply them with materials for the prosecution of
the war, and concentrating British shipping more and more on the Atlantic trade route, we have had to make large reductions in the amount of goods sent to neutral and Colonial markets.   There are numerous examples of this,hut the following cases are of special interest.In the very earliest stage of the war, the German advance overran the Lens and other coal-fields, and the Longwy-Briey iron district of Northern France.   To aid France in this extremity, the United&quot;Kingdom increased Its export of coal to France from 12,776,000 tons in 1913 to 17,515,000 tons in 1917 and 16,511,000 tons in 1918, an increase of 29$ in 1918 In spite of a reduced output caused by the calling of thousands of coal miners to the Colours. To effect this we reduced our exports to other foreign countries and to British Overseas Possessions, and rationed the British people themselves in respect of coal.In the same way our exports to France of iron and steel and manufactures thereof increased from 203,000 tons in 1913 to 1,505,000 tons in 1917.   Figures for 1918 are not at&apos;present available.   To Italy, the increase was from 14,400 tons to 209,000 tons in 1917.   On the other hand, our exports to British India fell from 850,000 tons in 1913 to 119,000 tons in 3.917, those to Australia from 565,000 tons to only 53,000 tons, while those to Argentine dwindled from 358,000 tons to 43,000 tons.The changes are eajually striking in the case of boots and shoes.   Our exports to France increased by 83.4$ between 1913 and 1917: from 56,566 dozen pairs to 103,747 dozen pairs.   To Italy the exports rose by no less than 604$i, from 25,125 dozen pairs to 176, 288 dozen pairs.   These increases were secured at the expense of our Colonial and neutral markets, where the decreases in exports to British South Africa, India, Australia and Argentine combined amounted to 540,741 dozen pairs, the -proportionate decline being for British South Africa 60.2 % for British India 76,0$, for Australia 67.4^ and for Argentine 86.0$.V/hen the more effective prosecution of the War demanded the withdrawal of ships from long distance voyages and the earmarking of production to Allied needs, the United King-dorn did not hesitate to yield up valuable markets.   Thus between 1913 and 1917 the value of the exports of the United Kingdom to China declined by nearly one-third, while those to Japan fell by 9,000,000 or over 60$.   Other countries as a consequence have been able to increase largely their ex*? ports to those markets.   There has been a similar loss of trade to the United Kingdom and gain by foreign countries in other markets, e.g. in South America, our exports to all the countries of that continent having fallen by more than one-third.Since the Armistice, there has been some revival of our export trade, and of the re-export trade, as is shown by the following figures:-Exports of Exports of ForeignBritish Goods. &amp; Colonial Goods.-    -  Sept-Nov.1918         126,192,000 6,766,000Dec-1918-peb.1919   132,540,000 12,792,000March-May 1919       175,935,000 33,791,000
,The figures for each month of the last quarter show a continuous&quot; growth of British exhorts.   The totals are: March, &quot; 53,108,000:   April,    58,492,000:   and May,  64,345,000,vVhile this improvement is satisfactory so far as it goes, it will have to go a long way further before exports reach the pre-war level.     This is brought out by the following comparison between the weight*,of goods exported in the first &quot;five months of 1913 and the weight of goods exported in the corresponding months of 1919,.Estimated v&apos;/eight of Exports (in 1000 tons).Period	Goal,	! Coke &amp; Mailt Fuel	lfdj     Other ! Articles		! Total	1913	1919	1913	;   1919	1913 j  1919January February March April May	! 6,374 i 5,823 ! 5;831 1 6,605 1 6,148	! 2;550 2; 946 i 4;131 2,782 4,088	11,210 ;i,084 11,147 11, c)29 1,320	!   495 !   399 !   509 i   637 643	1 7,504:3,045 I 6,907 3,345 ! 6,97814,640 I 7,93413,419 1 7,468!4,731 !                jJan. &amp; Ma Total	i &apos; 130,781	16,497	6,090	2,683	j                                                 j 36,871 19,180Imports remain at a very high level as regards value, but their weight is even less than it was in 1918.   This is accounted for by big reductions in some bulky items, notably petroleum, iron ore, and some chemical materials, which were required for war purposes.     Other goods, including some materials and foodstuffs which have a high value in propor-tion to their bulk, have been imported in larger quantities. Imports of wool alone have doubled in quantity and represent an increase for the first five months of the year of  24,000,000 in value.     Raw materials used in a number of staple industries of the country will have to be imported in very large quantities to make up deficiencies of stocks and to provide for the current requirements of factories when they resume production at full pressure.In conclusion I must emphasise again that the chiefmenance of the future lies in the doubtful prospects of exports on a sufficient scale, and with regard to this the gravest anxiety must be felt.Fortunately there are some bright spots in the out-look.   Many foreign markets have been starved of manufact-used goods during the war, American, Japanese and other foreign manufacturers having been able to supply only a small part of the demand.   There is no doubt a considerable pent-up demand which will readily absorb British Manufaet-urs as soon as confidence is felt that prices are not going to fall rapidly.      A further favourable point may be noted namely that foreign made goods are not always identified-cal with those of British manufacture which go by the same name.      Generally speaking British goods excel in quality, durability and workmanship.      While foreign pur-chasers during the war have had to buy what they could get,or,
it must not &quot;be assumed that they will not in many cases       * readily take British goods when these appear again in hulk on the market.   But, these considerations notwithstanding, the outlook is serious *   Our present exports are not nearly enough for our needs and we have to set out to make good our position faced &quot;by the fact that a number of markets are either completely disorganised or at any rate impoverished &quot;by the war, and handicapped &quot;by having to compete with rivals who are already widely established and well equipped, &quot;both productively said in respect of finance.The significance for British trade of the impoverish-ment of Eupopean belligere3.1t countries may be realised by glancing at the statistics of pre-war trado with them   The figures show that European Allies and enemy countries together furnished in 1913 ever one quarter of our total imports, took one quarter of our exports and nearly half of our re-exportsw -Imports from enemy countries alone exceeded  93,000,000 amounting to about one eighth of Our total imports; and exports to them exceeded  53,000,000 reaching about one tenth of our total exports; and re-exports to them amounted to one fifth of our total re-export trade.4.   UNEMPLOYMENT.Except during the opening weeks, practically nothing was heard during the war of unemployment.   The demand for labour was, in many industries, greatly intensified, while many men were withdrawn from the labour market for service with the forces; and all except the most incapable, could obtain employments  Only in a few industries, where there was shortage of material, was labour turned off or put on short time during the latter part of the war.After the Armistice, the situation soon changed.   Most war work died down fairly rapidly, but peace work could not be resumed in full swing at a momentTs notice, and many v/ar workers found themselves unemployed.   Coincidently, the labour market began to receive a steady flow, of men demobilised from the force so   Unemployment became fairly acute, and for two months the total number of persons unable to find work remained over a million.   The number of women engaged in industry diminished and the number of men increased, as is shown in the following estimates based on returns made by employers to the Board of Trade :-
Employment in November 1918,  March and April,  1919 with percentagechanges since November for each of the latter dates  (000Ts omitted^3Males Numbers employed inOccupation	Nov	March		i April   .	M	arch   !			april:	1918	1919.		) 1919.	1919.				1919Intrust r i e s.              j									Building                   I	4-38		554	!      601	f	26*	4 !	4-	37.3Mines &amp; Quarries    \	1, 039	1,	201	L 1,223	t	15.	5 1	4-	17 c 5	1,872	1,	903	\ 1,944	4-	1 -i.  o	5 \	.*	3 a 8Chemicals                 j	161		172	!      174	f	6*	6 !	4-	7o9	408		444	459	t	8&apos;.	8j	4-	12.3Clothing                   i	181		211	!      223	t	16.	/V 1	x.	22 c ^Food,Drink &amp;            \	246   ;		289	1      360	t	17.	4j	4-.	21.8Tobacco !									9 7   ?Paper &amp; Printing	158   ;		194	I       201	t		6!	4-,	Wood                          [	173   I		208	220	J-	20.	7 1	-f-	27.other Industries									&amp; local									20.3-Authorities.	305   !		357	367	t	17*	o]	t,	Total of above	4,983   i	5,	553	1 5. 712		11.	o)	4-	14. 6Government estub									(Dockyards, Arson-									38.8al3 ,Nat 5Facts ,ete )!	274		177	!      168	-	35 o	2;	-	TOTAL	5S 257   1	5,	710	1  5,880	1          4-	8c	6;		11.8$Change between Nov. 1918 andFemales. Eumbers employed inNov.191831 13 596 103 819 558 23014183-155 2,731245March 191915 1269 793 585 243142 68492,976    I 2,405April 191914 12 302 67 798 5 69 247143 68137 I 137 ,356   j  2,35839 2, 397fc change between Nov. 1918 and march 1919-53-2- 4.0 -47.-4 -33.6- 3.-2 1.-2- 5.-2- 0.5 18.3-12.-2-13. &amp;-80.1Ap ril-1919.-- 54*4- 4*0- 49.-4- 34.-7- 2-5 * - 1.-8 t 7.1f 1.-5- 18 .-312.-2 13.-7- 84.0-19.2- 19.5
It is estimated that in industries under private --       i u ownership there were employed, in November 1918, 20$ fewer men and 25$ more women, and in April 1919, 8*3$ fewer men and. 8.2$ more women, than in July 1914*Men,.,therefore, have been steadily absorbed into ordinary industry during the last few months, but not in sufficient numbers to counteract the flow from war worlr and the forces, and considerable unemployment, has ensured, . Its demoralising effects, however, have been partly mitigated by the unemployment donation scheme; and in any case, a certain period of Idleness unaccompanied by immediate anxiety as to the means of livelihood, appears to have been not altogether unwelcome or harmful to a proportion of the overwrought war-workers,   The demand for labour has recently been reviving.The severity of the depression during last winter,, and the extent of the subsequent recovery, are partly indicated by the following figures of employment, but it should be explained that the decrease during May in the number of policies remaining lodged is partly accounted for by the exclusion of all policies lodged., by persons working short time (about 100,000 of whom a proportion were included in the earlier figures), by the abandoning of claims to extended policies on the expiry of the first period of thirteen weeks, and by the review of policies.At end of ? Unemployment DonationPolicies lying lodgedMen h Boys.   Women &amp; Girls   TotalDec.1918 142,000 238,000 380,000Jan,1918 253,000 425,000 678,000Feb. 421,000 527,000 948,000Mar, 541,000 519,000 1,060,000April 640;000 453,000 1,093,000May 548,000 223,000 771,000During this period there has been, of course, a large and steady flow into the labour market Of demobilised men. The numbers demobilised (men) from all services, are shown below.End of&apos; Total DemobilisedTotal lumber[Total Per Absorbed     jcentage labsorbedI Monthly ! absorption i expressed as (percentage &apos; of monthlydemobilisa-tion!Jan, 19*19	1,035,500	980,000	94,, 8Feb.	1,899,000	! 1,733,500	!    91,3              87clMar &amp;	2,318,500	1 2,013,000	!    86,8       1     66.6April	2,688.000	i  2,285,000	85,9        j     73,6May	2,888,000	j 2,503,000	86,7       1   109o0The rapid absorption into industry of demobilised men is a very satisfactory feature of the pros ant situation. At the end of May well under 400,000 polioies of men demobilised from the forces remained lodged.   Of other.men
149,000 policies remained lodged, compared with 178,000 at the end of January and 828,000 at the end of February.Of women, boys and girls there were only 237,000 policies lodged at the end of May, compared with 448,000 at the end of January and 555,000 at tho end of March.   It is noteworthy that during May more demobilised men were absorbed into industry than were demobilised during the month.According to tho latest available statistics, there were 665,000 persons in the aggregate drawing donation in the middle of June, of whom 500,000 were adult males.   A continued revival of home and export trade should result in a further substantial reduction of these figures.   The number of persons who are no longer entitled to benefit but who remain unemployed is understood to be at present quite inconsiderable, as the Uemployment Donation Scheme was. continued in force for a further period of 13 weeks after the first quarter had elapsed, making six months in all.5.   Industrial Conditions and Prospects in theUnited Kingdom.Whilst it is possible to make fairly definite state-ments as to the conditions at present prevailing in the more important branohes of British industry, any attempt to forecast the course of events in the next year or so must inevitably be of a very speculative character, in view of the great uncertainty as to some of the factors which need to bo taken into account.In the period immediately following the Armistice the recovery of industry was retarded by the difficulties connected with the changing-over from war to peace production in many cases; by the holding-back of orders consequent upon a wide-spread expectation that prices must fall appreciably at an early date - except in the case of Iron and Steel, 7/here it was certain that they must rise with the cessation of the Government subsidies, so that producers were unwilling to accept orders except at such prices as might be ruling at the date of delivery; by doubt as to the future of Government control; by shortage of labour and materials; by transport difficulties; and by uncertainty as to the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government .in respect of the importation of foreign manufactured goods. Confidence has now been re-established in some measure, and substantial progress has been made towards industrial recovery, but a number of disturbing factors are still in operation, and of these the most important is the rising cost of production in almost all Industries.   Whilst some materials of industry (e.g. copper, lead and zinc) have shown a downward movement, others (e.g. iron ore, pig iron and wool) have shown a strongly marked tendency in the opposite direction.   Labour costs have advanced rapidly in many industries, under the two-fold influence of advances in money wages and reduction in working hours; there has been no time as yet for changes In manufacturing methods -even where organised labour is disposed to acquiesce in their introduction - to offset these movements, nor is there so far any indication that higher wages and shorter
hours will result in greater productivity of labour.   Tho whole of industry is seriously affected by the high price .and reduced output of coal,   Consequently nothing approach-ing price stability appears likely to be reached for some time: and although the world is 1hungering for goods1 of all kindsj it remains to be seen how far the high level of prices, the likelihood of further advances and the reluctance or positive inability of British manufacturers to quote definitely for deliveries at any except quite early dates, will check the worldvs demands or deflect it to other countries whose costs of production,, and conse-quently price quotations.; are lower than those of the United Kingdom or whose conditions are such as to make possible definite quotations for delivery even at distant dates.   The foreign competition regarded with anxiety; by British manufacturers is not so much from Continental Europe, except in   certain special cases, as from the United States and Japan.   Both of these countries enjoyed great industrial prosperity during the war. and their manufact-manufacturers were able in many oases to build up large reserve funds, which can now be used for competitive purposes: both were able to enter upon foreign markets hitherto largely in the hands of British manufacturers and traders, who were prevented from supplying them by the circumstances of the war; both have- largely increased their competition with British manufacturers in the United Kingdom market. The low price quotations of Japan are due primarily to the low level of wages in that country; the ability of American Manufacturers to undersell their British competitors is due apart from a temporary policy of unloading accumulated stocks, partly to the lower cost of fuel, in the United States, but chiefly to larger scale production, better organisation; and greater productivity of labour.The general considerations thus briefly indicated apply with more or less force to all the branches of industry which will, now be passed in review.Coal Mining.   The position of the Goal industry is complTcated^Ty^a number of special circumstances, which need not be discussed in this place0   The seriousness of the situation is sufficiently shown by the fact that whereas in 1913 the output,was 287 million tons, it is estimated that for 1919 (on the basis of the production during the first 20 weeks of the year) it will not exceed 242 million tons    In 1913 the,exports from the United Kingdom amounted to 77 million tons.; for 1919 they are estimated at 28 million tons.   The average output per man per four weeks in 1913 was 19.8 tons, in the first 20 weeks of this year it was 16.8 tons.   The shortage of coal, and the high price, are having a serious effect on all branches of industry, and inability &quot;to export coal from Scotland and the Horth-East Coast of England is preventing the iron industries there from obtaining adequate supplies of iron-ore, especially from Spain, since shipowners who previously carried inward cargoes of iron-ore and outward cargoes of coal will not send their ships to Scottish and North Bast English ports if they have to leave in ballast.   This is only one illustration - though the most pressing one - of the reaction of the fall in coal exports upon the import of commodities required by British industry.
Iron and Steel., Before the war, our iron and steel tradestEougETslowly increasing their total output, were not able, to maintain their former proportion of the world18 supplies.   In 1900 Great Britain, the United States, France and Germany produced 34 million tons of pig iron, of which Great Britain!s share was 9 million; in 1912 Great Britain produced 10 million out of 66 million^   Of steel, the oombined output for 1900 was 23 million tons, Great Britain*s share being 5 million; in 1913, the figures were 63 million and 7-g- million respectively,,During the war, the enormous Government and Allied demand more than made up for the lo3t commercial export markets, and considerable Government assistance was given to the trades to enable them to increase their output, The numbers employed, despite enlistment, increased steadily in most branches..   Blast furnaces in November 1918 employed 1804$ more labour than in July 1914; steel works employed 4802$ more*   Production, as a result, increased during the war, especially in steel, though the level of 1917 was not maintained in 1918c   The production for the last six years, and the estimate for 1919, based on the first eighteen weeks, are shewn in the following table.,Year,,. Pig Iron, Steel Ingots &amp;Castings.1913 10,482,000 tons 7,664,000 tons1914 9,006,000 &quot; 7,035,000 &quot;1915 8,794,000 &quot; 8,351,000 &quot;1916 9,048,000 &quot; 0,992,000 &quot;1917 9,332,000 &quot; 9,717,000 &quot;1918 9,083,000 &quot; 9,539,000 ?T1919 (estimated)      7,965,000 &quot; 8,621,000 &quot;After the armistice, the war orders gradually diminished but civilian needs, strictly rationed under the priority system during the war, were so pressing that activity was fairly well maintained.   The demand for shipbuilding and repairing material, and for structural material, was very great, and the industry was further assisted by the continuance for a time of the subsidies paid during the war, whioh kept down prices and 3&amp;oouraged demand.   They were withdrawn in two stages, half at the end of January and half at the end of April.   Their withdrawal raised prices for domestic consumption (a dre; back corresponding to the subsidies was levied on iron and steel exported) and further advances have taken place in consequence of increases in wages and reductions in hours, the shortage of haematite ore (partly in consequence of the low exports of coal, as already explained) and the restrioted output of pig iron0   The extensitns to steel works arranged for by the Ministry of Munitions during the war have not all been oompleted as yet:   they will result in a large increase in our capacity for steel production, but progress in the extension of blast furnaces has lagged far behind, with the consequence that our steel works must be largely dependent upon foreign pig iron.   Thus the production of steel ingots and castings was in 1913 7,664,000 tons, and in 1918 9,539,000 tons:   the output of pig iron on the other hand, whioh amounted to 10,482,000 tons in 1913, was only 9,083,000 tons in 1918 and for 1919 is estimated at about
8,000,000 tons., a figure very seriously lower than that of last year..,  The dependence of the British industry to any considerable extent upon foreifn supplies of pig iron (other than certain special kinds) is obviously a matter requiring serious consideration,- especially as foreign combinations may by declining to supply pig-iron and offering steel instead prevent that development of the British iron and steel trades which is essential if our industrial basis is to be secure.The shortage of ore (foreign) and pip-iron, tho increases in labour costs, and the intensity of the demand in certain directions, have resulted in a continuing tendency for prices to rise.   Manufacturers of pig-iron are unable to meet all the demands upon them, and whilst buyers ,are eager to place orders up to the end of the year, producers will not commit themselves beyond the end of September.   The shortage of supplies of foreign iron ore in Scotland (which depends very largely upon imported, ores) and on the ftorth-East Coast is causing serious difficulty and unless the situation improves will cause the shutting down of furnaces and considerable unemployment.      The . shortage of pig-iron (in spite of the fact that the export trade which was of considerable importance before tho war is being severely restricted) in its turn is affecting the iron and steel manufacturers, who are now faced with American competition; bar iron and steel billets are being offered from the United States at prices substantially below the quotations of British manufacturers.Present quotations for basic pig and for Bessemer in Eastern Pennsylvania are, at present rates of exchange, more than 30$ below corresponding quotations in this country.   ,. It must be remembered, in this connection, that the. American cutout of pig iron rose from 30-,996,000 tons in 1913 to 39,05?,000 in 1918, and the steel outout from 31,301,000 tons to 45,073,000 tons.The output of pig iron in the. United Kingdom for 1919, at present rates, will be, 1,118,000 tons and that of steel ingots and castings 918,000 tons below the figures for 1918, although the numbers (men and women) employed in the iron and steel trades have risen 8.9$ between November 1918 and April 1919,-  The increase in productive capacity should be greater than this, as the proportion of men to women has increased, from about 8 to 1 to about 26 to 1.   Complaints of inadequate output due to labour are, however, almost as frequent as complaints of shortage of material and. prices of coal.   The average number of shifts worked in iron and steel works in May was 5.60, as compared with 5.65 in April, and 5.74 in May 1918,   The number of furnaces in blast in the pig iron industry is declining.   In May 1913 it was for&apos; the firms making returns to the Ministry of Labour, 332; in May 1918 294; in-April 1919,  69; and in May 1919, it was only 263,It is noteworthy also that at the present time (end of June 1919) basic pig-iron is being offered in substantial quantities from Prance.Our exports of iron and steel and manufactures thereof for the first five months of each of the last seven years, have been :-
Five months ended 31st MayTonsValue1913 1914 1915 1916 1917 19.18 19192,090,000 21018,000li180,000 11045,000 1,005,000665,000 812,000 23,382,000  21,426,000  14,345,000  23,701,000  19,501,000  14,756,000  21,755,000How severe American competition is likely to become, and how long it will continue^ it is at present impossible to estimate, but for the time being it is impossible to meet our requirements by domestic production.The subsidiary iron and steel trades, are of course, vitally affected by the position in the basic industries.Tinplate.   The tin-plate trade was severely cut down by the war; the number of males employed fell from 24,900 to 15,100,.while the number of females remained almost unchanged;.and at one period in 1918, 97$ of the workers remaining were employed on Government orders.   The scarcity of tonnage gave America an additional advantage, and our export market, which had widened steadily before the war, has been almost completely closed.Immediately after the Armistice the home demand for tin plates was so great that there was little available for export, but the competition we shall have to face is shown by the fact that South Wales works recently accepted and distributed among themselves an order.for 350,000 boxes at a price expected to result in a loss of  19,000 in order to maintain a hold on the Far Eastern Markets.Japan is already erecting tin plate works; America has almost trebled her output during the war; and costs in both countries are lower than hore.   The price and the supply of steel are, of course, of the utmost importance to the industry. ,Galvanised Sheets. This industry lost 30$ of its numbers of males employed during tho war; it has now recovered a large part of them, but 40$ of the plant was reported idle at the ena of March; this was partly due to the fact that only 22$ of the workpeople were engaged on Government contracts, as compared with 98$ in November, partly to shortage of male labour, .and partly to the high cost of billets, which one very large firm declares &apos;is strangling this important industry&apos;.   Active competition is threatening from the United States in markets which before the war were entirely in British hands.It must be noted that before the war some nine-tenths of the United Kingdom production of galvanised sheets was exported.High-speed steel. ,The demand is very dull., owing to the substantial stocks in this country (the production was greatly stimulated by the war) and the development of production in what were previously important markets of the British makers.   The efforts to produce Tungsten (tho alloy
for high speed steel) in this country, which was previously dependent upon Germany for that commodity., combined with the development of similar production in France and Italy, have had the result that the capacity of the plant is greatly in excess of the demand&apos;, and some of the makers are likely to be very adversely affected.Other Metal Industries. The position in respect of tho Kon Ferrous metals varies greatly; in some cases prospects are pood, whilst in others they are far from satisfactory.^Ii2^.?2 lJ:AE^* *s particularly uncertain.   Before the war only three-Tenths of the United Kingdom&apos;s requirements of Sine were met by domestic production, mainly from im-ported ores or by recovery from zinc ashes or hard spelter: in a number of, works operating on a small scale for the rest we ,dependod upon Germany and Belgium.   The high prices ruling in the early part of the war led to a very great increase in production in the United. States, which had not hitherto appeared as a seller in the world&apos;s market: efforts were made by the Ministry of Munitions to stimulate pro-duction in this country, but without marked success.     When prices fell in the latter part of the war, the cost of production by British smelters had risen (in consequence chiefly of advances in the price of fuel and labour) to such an extent that they could, not continue to produce except at a heavy loss.   They were accordingly subsidised by tho Ministry of Munitions, and this subsidy has been continued until November next: and unless by that time there has been a very substantial decrease in the cost of production, which appears very unlikely, or a very considor-able advance in the world&apos;s price of spelter, it will be impossible for the smelters to carry on without Government assistance in one form or another.   The price of spelter which has fallen as a result of the unloading of the surplus stocks of the United States has recently, (beginning of July) shown an upward movement, but it is unlikely to rise to a point at which production will be remunerative to British refiners with their present costs,   A subsidiary difficulty is the shortage of skilled labour and tho difficulty of supplying it owing to the reluctance of British workmen tc engage in the industry owing to the generally unpleasant conditions.   It is essential that the Galvaniscrs (whose difficulties have already been mentioned.) and the Brass trades should have their supplies of Spelter at tho lowest prices possible: and for that reason American competition and the revival of production in Belgium, for which the United Kingdom was the chief market before the War, arc not unwelcome.EoM, Government have entered into a contract which gives thorn control of the exportable surplus of Zinc conccn-trates from Australia: and they have&apos; advanced a large sum of money towards the erection of a large scale refining works at Avonmouthc   The difficulties set out above have however prevented any definite arrangements being made as yet for the treatment of the concentrates in the United Kingdom, and the future of the Avonmouth works (which are not yet completed) is somewhat uncertain.Tin Smelting and Mining.     Tin smelting has not been carried on extensively in tho United Kingdom,  (the very
strong position of the British Empire in respect of the tin, industry &quot;being due to pro auction in the federated Malay States and smelting in the Straits Settlements) hut so far as it has been carried on it has depended upon tin ore imported from Bolivia and the tin production of Cornwall. The desire of the United States to develop a tin-smelting industry has led to efforts to acquire control of the tin-mines of Bolivia, and may impede the supplies to British smelters.   At the same time the Tin-Mining Industry in Cornwall is faced with a serious crisis owing to the rise in money wages (owing inter alia to the extension to Metalliferous Mining of certain wages awards made by the Coal Controller):   the increased cost of fuel and timber: the increasing charges for pumping (many of the mines are heavily watered);   the low metallic yield of the ore mines: the heavy fall in. the price of tin since the Armistice and the cessation of various subsidies, given by the Ministry of Munitions during the war in order to maintain and increase production.   A number of mines have closed down,- and others are1 likely to do so.The position in respect of Lead., Sine and Barytes Mining is much the same.   All the--Non-Ierrouirmines&apos; in the United Kingdom have been operating under the same general conditions, and are now faced with&apos;the same problem: they are all small and their financial resources aro in most cases very limited.   The general standard of efficiency in management is not high; little systematic prospecting work has bean done in recent years, and there has been small attempt until recently on the part of the mine owners to co-operate for common purposes.   Some financial assistance in the form of loans and bonuses on production was given by the Ministry of Munitions during the war, but that has now ceased, and the results were not very appreciable.   A comprehensive enquiry into the conditions and. prospects of the Industry has been decided upon, and some temporary financial assistance in approved cases has been authorised: but unless the enquiry reveals large deposits of tin, lead and ainc which can be commercially worked if the industry be properly organised, equipped and managed it would appear that not only British lead and ftinc Mining, which was moribund before the war and only galvanised thereby into a not very fruitful activity, but also the ancient Tin-Mining Industry of Cornwall must disappear or be suspended for such a period as will make recovery extremely doubtful.   It may be mentioned that, as regards lead mining, the most hopeful prospect of development is in the completion of a drainage scheme in the Halkyn district:   a substantial Government advance has been made to the Drainage Company, but the progress of the scheme is at present hold up by the need for further capital.The Lead and Brass Working Industries.   Ar e gene rally active&quot;and will become increasingly so with the development of activity in the Building Trades.   The production of Aluminium in the United Kingdom - from imported ores - has made considerable progress during the War, and there is an increasing demand for it for the manufacture of domestic utensils of various kind.   The production of Aluminium in this Country is almost entirely in the hands of one Company, which is engaged on a scheme for a much enlarged output, wnich involves a large extension of its present hydr electric pov/er scheme in Scotland. * The Kick el refining
a.)Industry is in &amp; position of   considerable uncertainty owing to the large increase of production during the war and the fact that hitherto the metal has found its chief use in the production&apos;of armour plates and munitions of war.   If the output is to he maintained other uses will have to &quot;be found, and attention is &quot;being directed to the manufacture of nickel domestic utensils, an Industry which has made appreciable progress in Germany before the War,, . Temporarily there is over production and output (and consequently em-ployment) is being curtailed.   Copper is.not refined in the United Kingdom, and the production of copper ore within the Bmpire is very small:   for supplies of copper we have hitherto been dependent mainly upon the United States and to a limited e3-r&apos;cent upon Spain,   It is understood that schemes for the establishment of copper refining in the United Kingdom upon a significant Scale and for securing the requisite supplies of material are being considered by the interests concerned.file ling in- In 1913 our engineering shops were working at theirearing      fullest capacity In locomotive, marine, electrical and Trades.     motor engines; yet it is probable, though data for a g.c.m.g.-pa risen are not available, that their output was greater &apos; in 1918 than in any previous year.   The large output for War purposesj however, meant a considerable dislocation in many branches in the return to peace work, and, indeed, in April there was still a considerable amount of plant idle owing to difficulties in the change over.The industry, moreover, did not, as might have been expected, receivs after the Armistice a great accession of orders to fill the arrears of war.   Business was held back by the general anticipation of a fall in prices, and many orders already booked were cancelled,   But though selling prices were to some extent reduced to obtain business, costs remained unaltered, or even increased; and buyers recognis-ing the error of their forecast, have again come forward and manufacturers in certain branches have plenty of orders.The general instability of labour conditions, the high cost asd short supply of materials, the impossibility of estimating how these will stand even a month ahead, and the adoption by many British engineering firms of a clause in their contracts calling for an increase above contract prices should Government action in raising wages or 3.owering hours affect the original tender, are having a very marked adverse effect on the placing of orders for exportf   It is probable that only the very large world demand is keeping many of our shops going; with a reduced demand, or an increased output elsewhere, their present conditions and production costs would not enable them to compete success-full y.     The demand for railway material is growing;   the makers of agricultural machinery are very busy, as are also tho makers of woollen and worsted, f1  ^.and.. jn/te ma chinery: much h c f - the&quot; woo 11 en. ma chin er y is f o r f r an c e, an d oT the&quot;Jute machinery for Calcutta,   The position of the Cotton siachinery makers is not so satisfactory, though there is ascertain amount of business for India and Japan the domestic demand is not active.   The motor engineering and motor vehicle trades are very busy; out&quot;some of&quot;the makers of cars have been placed in a position of considerable difficulty by the fact that during the war the requirements fcf the army have been so great that car-makers have been
prevented not only from producing cars for civilian purposes, but even from preparing new models-, whilst their American competitors have been working, under no such restriction and have enormously increased their output of civilian cars.   Whilst the producers .of expensive cars with established reputations may not be seriously affected by American competition, it is likely (even with the present import duty in force) to make the situation very difficult for the makers&quot;of the cheaper kinds of cars, and in fact -it is&apos; doubtful if the, latter, with a domestic market very small in comparison with that of their American rivals, can expect to meet that competition successfully on equal terms.&quot; At present the demands on the car makers (and consequently upon the accessory makers) are very great, and a considerable number of large extensions are being made and important new concerns are coming into the field.   A new industry which has been practically the creation of the war, and of which the peace future is difficult to forecast is the manufacture of aircraft; a number of manufacturing concerns which have been active for war purposes are making preparations for considerable activity in connexion with civilian flying.   In this connexion it may be mentioned that very substantial progress has been made in the domestic manufacture of Magnetos and magnet steel, for which before the war we were eirETrely dependent upon Germany: and there appears no reason why after a short time this industry, which though it does not represent a large volume of employment is of. great national import-ance, should not be firmly establislied in this country.Further details of. the present, position and the prospects in some of the principal branches of the engineering trade are given below.Locomotives. The locomotive manufacturers are at present  till&apos; of &quot;orders, the completion of which will last for about 12 to 15 months from now, but they will be able to give delivery for new orders in the latter part of 1920. It may be remarked that the orders they have now in hand are very largely for Indian railways and certain other railways in which British capital is interested.   They do not seem to have obtained orders from neutral countries, the trades of which were formerly in the hands of Germany and America, and such orders e.g. for Spain, the Government of Argentine etc appear to be going to U.S.A. firms.   The Maryport and Carlisle railway recently wished to order two heavy goods engines, but found that the cost was Just four times as much as before the war, and that no delivery could be made for a long time.There is a considerably greater capacity of output than before the war, as two important firms, Messrs. Armstrong Whitworth So Co. and Messrs. W. Beardmore &amp; Com-pany are now equipping large works for the manufacture of locomotives.Railway Rolling Stock. The same remarks generally apply as above, and new worksPhave been established to deal with the increased output which it is hoped will be required.In regard to locomotive and rolling stock, the British Owned railways in the Argentine appear to be withholding their orders, possibly to see if prices will come down.   .
Bails. The rail makers generally appear to be in a position ^0 execute orders if they can obtain them, but prices are against them, the American quotations being considerably lower, and earlier delivery being promised.   Considerable public attention has been drawn to two recent cases in which municipalities have placed or proposed to place orders with American concerns chiefly for the latter season.   One large United Kingdom firm has stated that new prices were fixed from May 1st for.the heavy steel trade in an effort to get as near to American prices as possible, and that these prices would leave the trade generally with a heavy loss which no matter could endure for long.   They also added that this state of affairs was, in their opinion brought about by the attitude of the Government towards the labour demands, the result being that for everything they buy, including labour, they have to pay treble the pre-war prices, and as they cannot get anything like treble the pre-war price for the finished article against American competition, it is only a question of time before (according ;to their own statement) they will be compelled to close down.Generally speaking, the British rail makers woiild be , only too glad to get work.In regard to American prices for steel rails the British Conmercial Attache at Washington reports under date May 30th that the U.S.A. Railroad Administration had just given contracts to six companies for supplying 200,000 of open hearth steel rails at $47 per ton, but that the orders had been placed under protest and with emphatic disapproval of the prices.Assuming that the price quoted is for American tons of 2000 lbs, the price of $47 works out at.about  10.18o6c per British ton of 2240 lbs6   The home prices in the United Kingdom at the same date (the last week in May) were  15 per British ton for steel rails, and therefore the American home price is more than 27$ less than the United Kingdom home yet the U.S*A. Director General of Rail Roads complains that he has to pay an unreasonable amount.Switches and Crossings.   The manufacturers of these are very ahxioiis to obtain orders and are extremely short of work.   Here again the price question is against them, the ,-1 raw material1 in their case being rails.   Overseas Railways outside Europe and also in several European countries use flanged rails, which are the usual type used in the U0S.A..an&amp; consequently when such switches and crossings are required the U.3.A. manufacturers, for the reasons given above, have a great advantage.Wheels and Axles.   A case lias recently occurred in which a London firm oFliierchants placed an order for wheels and axles in Belgium as the price of British manufacturers was-described as much too exorbitant.   It is, of course, likely that the British manufacturers could not help themselves in regard to the price quoted owing to the conditions mentioned previously.Tramway Rails.   A number of enquiries have come through for these from Switzerland, Italy, Hong Kong etc.   The difficulty in this case is that the.sections of rails
required were such that the British makers did not possess the rolls and it would certainly not pay them to make special rolls. In many cases the original rails were made in Germany.Ironworks PlantA   A large steel, works is about to be erected in Holland and it is understood (though this has not been confirmed) that the Germans have secured part of the order at prices which United Kingdom manufacturers oould not touch. In this case the value of the Mark is exercising a prejudical effect on British trades. The same remark applies to other neutral countries such as Switzerland, where a considerable amount of railway material is required, and german prices are 15 to 20$ lower than British prices.Motor cars &amp; Cycles. The trade, employed almost entirely on Government work, was very prosperous during the war. The numbers of males employed increased from 117,000 before the war to 143,300 in Hovember 1918 and of females from 10,500 to 65,800; and in April 1918 it was estimated that over 95$ of the work people were engaged on work for Government contracts*The decline in Government orders after the armistice was compensated by large private orders suspended during the war, though some delay accompanied the alterations and reorganisation necessary for peace work.   The.home demand is bigger than manufacturers can fill, especially with restricted imports and the 33.1/3$ duty on the imports admitted. The figures given above show how the industry has been entirely directed to war work, and how necessary was a period of shielding during recovery.Prices are very high, but reports show that good business could be done in many overseas markets if we were in a position to deliver.   Though efforts are being made by massed production to lower costsa American prices are distinctly lower, and American competition will be very serious.The home demand, moreover,,is at present almost entirely either for the very high price or for the small sporting type, so that as conditions return to the normal, it will be especially difficult to meet competition in the ordinary touring car.Cutlery. Before the war the competition in this industry came from Germany, especially in the cheaper lines, but the reputation of, Sheffield Steel was responsible for a large export trade.The elimination of the German export,trade, and the huge requirements of the allied armies, gave an impetus to the industry, and as the demand became far greater than the supply, other competitors namely American and Japanese, . entered into the field of foreign markets.The present position is that there is an undoubted world shortage of cutlery, and United Kingdom manufacturers are working at full pitch,,but as yet cannot supply the demand, and business is being turned away. Particularly is this so as regards the demand for cheap varieties, and
the high prices necessarily demanded by the manufacturers partly hinders the full exploitation of foreign markets. Sheffield manufacturers are now devoting their attention to increasing bulk production in the commoner lines, and it is anticipated that even allowing for American and Japanese competition, factories will be fully employed for some years to come. Blanks formerly imported&quot; from Germany and finished off in this country, are now being made in the United Kingdom.In the Electrical Trades generally business if fairly active,   During the war Mere have been considerable developments in various branches of the manufacture of electrical plant, apparatus and fittings; large concerns previously engaged in the industry have extended their operations, and other important manufacturing companies have come into it.    In this particular industry, perhaps more than in any other at the present time, there is a strong tendency towards consolidation by important concerns obtaining control of companies engaged in allied or subsidiary branches of production, or in other ways. The general result appears likely to be that the British industry will come very largely under the control of a very small number of powerful groups; and in view of the facts that the domestic demand, though capable of considerable expansion, cannot afford a sufficiently broad basis for a powerful industry, that such a basis requires a large export trade, and that in foreign markets the British electrical manufacturers will have to encounter the highly organised competition of very powerful American and&apos; German competitors, possessed in the former case (whatever the future German position may be) of great financial resources, it is evident that such a movement as that described is essential if the British electrical industry is to have full opportunity of expansion.   It should be added that before the war there was a large importation of German electrical plant and apparatus into the United Kingdom, and a certain amount of American competition also; the German competition may not become acute for some time, but that from America may be expected to increase *Whilst electrical manufacturers are generally well occupied, and works have as a whole several months orders in hand, there is some tendency for electric light and power companies to hold back development schemes, pending the passage of the Electricity Supply Bill and the determination of Government policy on the general question of power supplyo   That there is room for a very large development of electric power supply, and consequently of the manufacture of electric piantxand apparatus, In this;country is beyond question.The number of males employed has risen between November and April from 89,300 to 94,700 a rise of 5,400.   The number of females has fallen, on the other hand, from 55,600 to 35,cc, a fall of 20,000,Agricultural. Engineering.   Makers of agricultural machinery have been controlled&apos; almost entirely in the interests of home production; the export figures in 1916 were 2,890 tons, in 1917. 976; in 1918, 816. There is at present plenty of work in the trade, and when the export business is resumed,
it is hoped, that the devasted regions and the Wear East . will supply markets to replace Russia.   Business is so brisk that there is as yet little complaint of prices of material.Shipbuilding. The position in this industry is fairly satisfactory, though progress has been by no means rapid. The cancellation of naval orders has to some extent involved delay; new construction is hampered by the &quot;enormous arrears of repair work accumulated during the war: there have been labour disputes on the Clyde and Tyne; there is a shortage of shipbuilding steel.   Many orders have been placed, and at the end of March there were under construction in the United Kingdom 2,222,000 gross tons of &quot;merchant shipping (as compared, however, with,073,000 gross tons in the United States.) for the reasons given, however, the recent rate of output has not been high: for the six months November 1918- April 1919 it was 552,000 gross tons as compared with 703,000 gross tons in the corresponding period of 1917-18.The monthly figures of merchant shipping completed this year, for the whole of the U.K,, are:-Mqnth; Ho. of vessels Gross tonnageJanuary &quot;T6 66,908February 8 29,522March 25 126,266April 26 105,555May 30 140,946Before the war, the monthly output had reached am average of about 160,000 gross tons. There is ground for hoping, however, that the rate of production will be substantially increased in the near future.The numbers of men employed in shipbuilding and repairing, and in marine engineering rose from 434,600 in November 1918 to 454,700 in April 1919; the number of women fell from 31,800 to 11,400.Cotton. In the cotton trade, the outbreak of war caused almost &quot;a panic, but the market re-adjusted itself.   Later however there was a shortage of raw material through lack ofshipping, which necessitated regulation under tho Cotton Control Board to secure more equitable distribution of cotton than would have remitted othonyise and at the same time provide assistance for the operative.The amount of business dome was of course very severely reduced.   Our exports of cotton piece goods, which in 1913 had been over 7,000 million yards, had fallen by 1918 to little over 3,500 million; and our experts of cotton yarn fell from 210 million lbs (244 in 1912) to 102 million.For some months after the Armistice there was stagnation, a big fall in prices being expected but recently there has been material improvement on a resumption of buying orders especially from India and China.   Cotton prices fell until March, but since then the revival of demand for cotton goods has been accompanied by a rise of price.   Government control has been entirely removed, except in regard to the disposal of Egyptian cotton for whioh it continues till -the end of July.
Our monthly exports of cotton yarns and. fabrics this year have been :-Month ValueJanuary 1919  15,999,500February  16,897,500March  15,247;000April  18,973,500May  16,619,000and a further improvement under normal conditions is to be expected.The following table gives imports of raw cotton and exports of manufactured goods in May 1919, and a comparison with April 1919 and May 1913.May April May      Increase or Decrease on1919 1919 1913    April 1919      May 1913jorts of raw ...ston flOOlbs) 1,248,805     1,256*776 1,460,027    -7,971        -   211,222jo rts. OottonfTT,0001bs)      16,056 16,006 17,777      t   50    ,  -      1,721ton thread forjing(lpOOlbs)        1,731 1,709 1,809      t   22 78iton piece goods000 yards)        258,337        268,459        606,254   -10,132        -   347,927.....................-.................._______............._____4....................................................._____________._________...........______.............;.......m..&apos; lm......... ;........;,, ______1...............;_______.......................^The dispute as to the increase in wages and reduction in hours demanded by the workers is still ( July 5 ) unsettled.     It remains to be seen what effect the increased cost of production resulting from the concessions made to the ?;orkers will have upon Lancashire^ competitive power in overseas markets, in some of which the competition of Japan and the United States manufacturers is being severely felt.    As is well known the cotton industry is mainly an exporting industry.Wool.     The necessity for large scale production to supply The needs of our own and the allied (especially at first the Russian) armies, kept the woollen and worsted industries very busy throughout the war.     The War Offioe found itself involved in so extensive a control of the industry that it initiated schemes for the supply of civilian clothing and blankets in standard qualities at standard prices, as, to a lesser extent, it had to do in boots.Difficulties in the shipment of Australian wool, rises in price and freights and the enormous demand for war purposes, very severely restricted the supplies for civilians, and prices of clothing reached very high figures, leaving a large demand unsatisfied.When the military demand lessened on the conclusion of the armistice, this civilian demand became effective, and
it has been easy to dispose of all that can he produced. The industry however, is not free from difficulties.   For a time the position as regards raw material remained tight. Recently imports have been on a large scale, but facilities for the transit of wool from London and in its early stages of manipulation haye been deficient.   Raw material is so far behind machinery that-top-makers are compelled in order to protect themselves to- ask extreme prices for forward business.    Spinners appear to be unable to turn out sufficient fine yarns &quot;to keep manufacturers going and prices of yarns are very high.Cloth-makers in turn are advancing their prices (since March most materials have advanced between 1/- and 2/- a yard).The consequences of these conditions is that all descriptions of woollen raiment are expected to show an appreciable increase in cost next autumn and winter and there is likely to be a further rise in the Spring.     It is evident that a good many months must elapse before there can be any appreciable reduction.     In some branches of the industry there is a shortage of labour and in view of the already intense demand the reduction of working hours from to 48, by restricting production until the reorganisation necessary to meet the new conditions can be carried through, must tend to drive prices up.    foreign competition in the United Kingdom market is very limited, and is likely to continue so at least until the woollen industries of France and Belgium are re-established.Hosiery.     The hosiery trade as a whole is extremely busy, and&quot; appears likely to continue so for some time as the demand is very great.     At the moment (June - July 1919) output is being checked by a strike of the dyers and finishers, in consequence of which very large stocks of undyed goods are being accumulated and manufacturers are reaching the point at which they are indisposed to continue piling up stock.    Apart from this temporary disturbance, the prospects of the industry are very good; though there is some anxiety as to Japanese and American competition particularly in cotton hosiery, which has developed greatly during the war and appears likely to increase still further.     in connexion with this industry it may be observed that very marked progress has been made in England in the development of a particular process of fast black cotton dyeing, which was an important German speciality:   and that efforts are being made with consid-erable promise of ultimate success in establishing the manufacture of Hosiery Needles for which we were before the war almost entirely dependent upon Germany.The Lace industry.     She position in the lace industry of Ho&quot;u:6ingImm&quot;anT district was for some months after the Armistice extremely bad:   much machinery was standing idle and there was widespread unemployment,,     There has recently been a distinct improvement, with the recognition among buyers that prices are not likely to fall:   there is some revival of the export trade.     But the situation generally is still far from satisfactory:   though employment is better there is still a large amount of idle machinery, and the strike of the dyers is having the same effect as in the
Hosiery trade   The trade encountered strong foreign corn-petition before the war, both from France and Germany and Switzerland and at present manufacturers seem to fear chiefly the rivalry of the first-named country, especially in view of the increasing cost of production in England, owing to.changes in the wages and hours of labour * -The Bleaching,, Dyeing, -Printing: and finishing Trades *   The condition of these industries follows upon that of the textile tradesB   At present they are well occupied, and likely to continue so,,   During the past five years they have been very prosperous owing to the war, which has out off the competition not only of Germany (in certain classes.of dyed goods and in printed goods from Alsace-) but also of Northern France,:   In some directions there have been important developments in the production of now classes of fabrics.   The main problem for these trades is the provision of a supply, of dyes adequate in quality and quantity, - This is a problem which has engaged the constant attention of HiM,Government throughout the war9 and the steps which have been taken by the Board of Trade to promote the dye making industry have met with considerable success5 though the home manufacture is not yet in a position to supply all our requirements, particularly in respect of special kinds of dyestuffs0   The assistance now being given consists in (l) the prohibition&apos; of the import of synthetic dyestuffs except under licence and this as a safeguard against the efforts which the Germans will undoubtedly make to recover their control of this industry: (2) Government participa-tion as a shareholder in the British Dyestuffs Corporation, now being formed to consolidate the two principal dye-making concerns, British Dyes ltd0 (a company in which the shareholders are almost entirely dye-users to which the Government has advanced money on debenture) and Levinstein Ltd: and (3) the allocation of  2 millions for loans and grants in aid of development and research to dye makers generally^   There is every prospect that the industry which is of vital importance, will make a rapid progress.,The Clothing Trades0   The demand for clothing of all kinds is&quot; so great that all branches of the trade are fully occupied, and there is room for large development,,   Although, prices for cloth are higher than ever, and tending to rise still further, this seems in no way to check demands Supplies of cloth ere coming forward only slowly, and there is a lack or skilled workmen..   The industry is to a large extent in the hands of aliens or firms of alien origin and employing foreign workmen at very high rates of wageseThe Linen Industry,,   The position of the Linen industry lias been one of great difficulty, in consequence of the complete cessation of Government orders, the shortage of raw material, and the adverse effect on buyers of the very high prices rulings   There is much short time, and though the latest reports are slightly more encouraging there does not appear to be any immediate prospect of a substantial improvement, unless raw material be forthcoming in much increased quantities0   In order to meet so far as possible the situation created by the cutting off of supplies of flax from Russia (by far the most important source of the world1s supply) His Majesty1s Government have during the past two years taken action (1) to promote the growing of
flax for seed in Canada: (2) to extend the area of flax .... growing in Ireland, by guaranteeing a minimum price to the grower: (3) to assist attempts to improve the methods of flax growing and treating in Ireland&apos;: and (4) to promote flax growing, both for seed and fibre, In Great Britain.r^is is another case of an industry wMcirTfa3&quot;&apos;Wry&apos;&quot;seriously affected by the cessation of Government orders.   Civilian orders were for a time almost non-existent, owing to the .very high prices quoted by the Dundee jute manufacturers and Indian-competition: and there was very considerable unemployment0   In view however of tho fact that the Government were supplying manufacturers with raw material from their stock at a price much lower than the true replacement price, the high prices quoted were not warranted, and on their reduction there was a marked revival of demand and an increasing number of mills are now resuming standard hours of labour,.   The serious problem before the industry is the competition of the Jute mills of Calcutta: the gap between the costs of production at Dundee and Calcutta respectively has been very greatly increased during and since the war by the advances in wages in the former city (the general level there previously was admittedly unduly low) and reductions in hours of labour, and then higher efficiency of Dundee labour is not sufficiently marked to offset the advantage to the Indian millowner of his low-priced labour.   Whilst there appears to be no warrant for the very alarmist views expressed in some quarters there is little doubt that the Dundee industry will not only find expansion very difficult in the face of Indian competition, but may oven find its markets considerably curtailed.The Silk Industry, is doing fairly well, but is adversely affected by the competition of cheap Japanese silks: there appears no likelihood in present conditions of any con-siderable expansion of the British industry, though the trade is well organised and is making collective efforts to bring about development.   The Artificial Silk Industry is making marked progress.The Chemical Trades have been affected perhaps more than any other branch Ox British Industry by the circumstances of the war, which on the one hand cut off supplies of important chemical products, such as synthetic dyestuffs, fine chemical and synthetic drugs for which we had previously relied almost entirely upon Germany, but also caused a vastly increased demand for certain classes of heavy and other chemicals for use in the production of high explosives and for trench warfare.   To meet this latter demand not only did existing acid manufacturers largely increase their output with or without Government assistance but great Government plants were created, with the result the acid-producing capacity of the country is now greatly in excess of any demand that can reasonably be anticipated in the near future, and this capacity must necessarily be increased if there is any large development of the Spelter-refining industry in this country since sulphuric acid is an important bye.-product thereof.   By far the largest use of sulphuric acid is in the manufacture of fertilisers, and though efforts are bfftng made to stimulate their use, the increase of consumption is not likely to be very rapid.
Icid manufacturers are therefore faced with the likelihood of overproduction, though this turns in part upon the ultimate decision as to the future of Government owned plan to   A commencement has been made in the manufacture of Nitric Acid, Mti;ates and Ammonia by Synthetic processes and it is very desirable that this should be developed so as to mitigate the country&apos;s dependence upon Chilean nitrates^As regards Fine Chemicals, which may be classified as (I) Reagents, (2) Pharmaceutical and (3) Technical, the bulk were imported before the war, almost entirely from Germany, but efforts have been made to produce them here with the result that in many cases the country1s requirements can now be fully met from home manufacture, whilst in other cases it is only a question of installing further plant.-.   luring the war, however, attention was necessarily directed rather to rapidity of output than to cost, and it is now.requisite that manufacturers should devote themselves to the improvement of processes and the reduction of costs,.   There is of course tevery likelihood that the great German chemical manufacturers will make every effort to recover their trade, and in view of their groat experience and large scale production their competition with the British makers is likely go be. severe. American competition is also expected to i&amp; lceena. 1Reference has been made earlier in this memorandum to tho position in respect of Synthetic Dyestuffs - which is&apos;that whilst very substantial progress has been made, it has been chiefly in the production of the more ordinary classes of dyes though there are some notable exceptions, and so far little has been accomplished in the special dyes which though the consumption is small are nevertheless of great importance for some branches of the textile trades (especially calico printing)*   $he dye industry is receiving special -Government assistance, financial and others and now that the demands for explosives have ceased the industry should be able to make much more rapid progressoIn connexion with the Chemical Industries reference may be made to (1) the manufacture/of fiinc Oxide, chiefly important for the production of Paints, which is being developed in the United Kingdom&apos;; (2) the advance in the production of Permanganate of Potash; and (-3) the attempt to establish the production of Potash.as a British industry especially by the treatment of blast furnace d.ustu   This latter development, should it prove a commercial success (as there is reason to hope) is the outcome of efforts to meet the difficulty created by the cutting off of supplies of potash, for which we depended upon Germanyc.   The nascent industry will, however, be exposed to active competition from that country, and also from Prance owing to her acquisi-tion of the Alsace deposits0PotteryyBefore the war our great competitors in the Pottery Industry in foreign markets were Germany and Austria, and the only line in which United Kingdom had a virtual monopoly in export trade was in Sanitary ware0   The general reliability of English pottery was largely responsible for our hugs export trade, upon which the industry practically depends for its existencea
The elimination of Germany and Austria gave great impetus to United Kingdom production, but the shortage of transport facilitated the competition of the United States and Japan in foreign markets.   The present outlook for the industry is, however, exceptionally good, and manufacturers are fully booked up with orders, and in some cases have had to refuse business,,The existing difficulties in the industry are;- fa) Shortage of coal -,this is by far the most serious; and (b) Old fashioned methods of production - but there are signs that these are being done away with.Increase in the present export trade in the Pottery depends on:- (a) Superiority of United Kingdom productions over foreign productions: and (bj Cost of Production.   In this case manufacturers are alive to the competition they must expect,&quot;and are devoting their attention to increasing bulk production to limit cost.A hopeful sign in this industry is that owing to shortage of raw materials, it may bo some time before Germany is able seriously to enter into competition again in foreign markets, and that stocks abroad are vory depleted. Prices rose greatly during the war, and have recently made a very great advance.   Special efforts are being made by manufacturers, collectively and in association with the Departments of Industrial and Scientific Research, to develop the production of Hard Porcelain, a continental specialty for which there was a very large pre-war demand.Building materials.(a) Brinks,   During the war the shortage of Labour com-pellcd many&apos; ofthe smaller concerns to close down, and the output of the larger concerns was taken over by the Govern-ment for Munitions Factories etc.    At the time of the Armistice there was an undoubted shortage of supply of bricks in the country, and the plans for the National Housing Scheme have proved a stimulus to the industry,and the present condition is that sufficient output is being made to provide for home requirements including the housing scheme, and a moderate export trade.(b) Timber.   The removal of the restrictions on importation of wood have &quot;cleared the air&quot;, and the only difficulty in meeting the ready demand is tHe- shortage of freight for im-portation:   prices are, of course, very high.(Q) 01her materia1s. Stocks were absolutely depleted during the&quot;war, but the removal of the restrictions has led to a greater output in practically all lines.The outlook for the Building Industry is exceptionally good, owing to the national shortage of houses.     The chief existing obstacles are the high prices of materials, the dif-   . ficulty of obtaining ready transport, and the shortage of labour for briekmaking, which is a heavy trade to which men appear reluctant to return.At the time of the Armistice there were 55$ fe?;er men em-ployed in the building trade than in July 1914, and at the end of April about one third of these had returned,
Funiture* The furniture trade has during the war devoted most of its energies to large-scale production of barrack and office furnishings, and of aeroplane parts. Despite the high costs of all kinds of wood, it is already fully engaged on peace orders;   but wood workers,are very unsettled - they have opposed with peculiar bitterness all attempts to introduce piece-work or bonuses on,output..Glass and Glassware. The Glassware production of the . country may be &quot;divided into (1) Optical Glass; (2) Chemical Glassware for use in laboratories; and for medical * purposes; (3) Illuminating Glassware (including glass for . miners lamps and electric light bulbs; (4) Plato and Window -Glass; (5) Table ware (6) Glass Bottles.   In none of these branches of production was British industry in a strong position before the war; for optical and scientific glass and important kinds of illuminating glassware the country was almost entirely dependent upon foreign sources of supply, whilst in the other branches domestic production fell far short of requirements.   Much attention and Assistance has been given by His Majesty&apos;s Government to the industry during tho war, and very considerable progress has boen made but some time must elapse before the . new branches of production roach the stage at which the quality and quantity of output and the cost of production    . . will be such.as to enable the British manufacturers to meet foreign competition which came before the war from Germany, Austria and Belgium and France and is now boing encountered from Japan with low pricos.. At present these now branches of the Glass industry are suffering from inexperience, the shortage of labour and machinery, and high prices, but the demand for all kinds of Glass ware is very great (the home market is extremely short and foreign enquiries are large) and manufacturers aro generally extremely busy.   A more detailed statement of the position in the different branches is given below,1*   Optical Glass. -At the outbreak of hostilities Britain was largely dependent on Goiman and;French supplies of optical glass, the output in this country being small and comprising only a few types.    As a result of the develop-ment of the industry during the war to meet the constantly increasing demands for optical munitions, the output was increased from undor 5,000 lbs. in 1912 (comprising only 11 different types) to cover 210,000 lbs. in.1918 which included no less than 73 types. &apos;   The quality, has in addition boen Improved, so that some of the more recent meltings are in every respect equal to the finest products of the Jena works-    As a result of:the increased output it was possible in 1918 not only to meet all the demands for glass for British optical munitions.; but also to provide supplies for tho American forces. -With the cessation of hostilities the demands diminish-ished to a large extent, and, except for certain special glasses now being made,&apos; the reserves available are sufficient to meet the present demands for some time, with the result that the   output has now been largely reduced.2*   Chemical and Scientific.   Glasses of these types were not made&quot;ln this country before the war.     Universities, colleges and schools are large consumers and with the resumption of their activities, which have been dormant during the war, there are now big demands.
3.   I^uminajing, Boforo the war incandescent electric lamp malceFOF^i&quot;ne3&quot;pructically all their supplies of bulbs and tubing from enemy sources, only two firms malting part of their own requirements.   Supplies have been largely in-creased and now meet essential requirements, while the installation of further bulb making machinery in the near future should make the country quite independents   Further with increasing skill on the part of the blowers, the percon-tage of faulty bulbs should be reduced and so improve the output available for lamp makers,The manufacture of heat resisting glasses for miner1s safety lamps, which was practically non-existent before the war, lias now increased to such an extent that it has been possible for the Home Office to withdraw the permission granted early in the war to use unapproved glasses.As regards heat resisting globes and chimneys and position at-present is not satisfactory0   Development is, however, delayed through firms being unwilling to put down the. necessary plant until they know what the policy of the Government is to bec40   Plata and Sheets There are at the moment large demands for window&quot;glass to replace breakage caused by air raids. Increased building will mean continued, demands^For table and decorative glass, for pressed glassware, for medical bottles and for bottles and jars there are at the moment big demands which for reasons already given can only be met with difficulty..The present position of the glass industry as a whole is to a certain extent critical,,   In spite of the difficul-ties of the past five years verv great progress has taken place both in the manufacture (,f:; lasses for which previously we were dependent on foreign supplies and in increasing the output of glasses of which our home made supplies were in-adequate, but time is required for the steps which have been taken to produce their fuller results.   Technical research has also been undertaken especially with regard to furnaces and refactories but though valuable results have been ob-tained again there lias not yet been time for these to have their effect,Tho Leather Industries (including bopt and shoe manufacture).,. This industry. Has been very strictly&quot;*con&quot;&amp;roiled the greater part of its activity being turned, to Government work it is estimated that nearly 70,000,000 pairs of Army boot have been manufactured in England during the war?   Imports and exports are now entirely free, all controls having ceaSed on the 30th June aThe demand for leather and leather goods of all kinds is very great and seems likely to continue so for some considerable time prices are very high and there is no immediate prospect of a fall:   they may even increases Some anxiety is felt as to the sufficiency of the supply of raw materials in spite of the Government purchases in Amer- . ica, owing to the great American demand (it is believed that United States interosts took the opportunity of tho res-trie-tions upon Tritish buyers to make very largo purchases,,)   In
tho boot and shoe industry, which is quite unable to cope fully with the demand, there is a shortage of supply of high grade upper leathersa   Attention may be directed to two developments during the war which promise to be of substantial value to British industry - (1) the establishment of Chrome Tanning and (2) the growth and improvement of the production of light leather goods suoh as handbags of all kinds - a manufacture which was very largely in continental especially Austrian hands.Paper, Control has been removed, but new restrictions had to i EiTTmposed from May 1st on the import of foreign paper, as many of the mills were dosing down,,   Practically the whole of the mills are now working at full pressure, so much so that a large order from Brazil for the News mills could not be accepted,   Labour troubles are developing, however, and ono of the unions has given in notice to oease work on July 1st, the paper makers having been unable to agree to a 42 hour week,.Shale Oil industry a.   The Scottish Shale Oil Industry, which Falf&quot;be&apos;en prosperous during the war owing to the high prices of imported oils is adversely affected now by (1) the increa-sos of wages of the Shalo Miners and (2) the reoont fall in prices of oils and paraffin wax9   The production of shalo amounts to some 3 million tons annually.   Yielding some 250,000 tons of oil products, including about 24,000 tons of paraffin wax, and also over 20,000 tons of sulphate of Ammonia; and the total value of the products of all kinds is at pres-ent prices about 3f million pounds0   The recent abolition of the excise duty on home produced motor spirit was ex-pected to be advantageous to the industry, but it is now stated that the extension to shale miners of the recent Sankey award to coal miners will with tho fall in price of oil and oil products make it impossible for the Shale Oil Companies to work at a profit, and may cause closing down in some cases0Oil Crushing and Refiningo There has been during the war a very large extensTdn of the vegetable oil industry in this country (it may be noted that the imports of ground nuts rose from 11,000 tons in 1913 to 135,000 tons in 1918) and there does not appear to be any reason why this development should not be maintained.   The demand is very great, partio^-particularly for the manufacture of soap and margarine - the production of the latter commodity has boen greatly increased by the establishment of a number of important worksc The cessat-ion of the demands for glyoerine otc; for munitions purposes has set free large quantities of oils for industrial and food purposes.Soap0   The soap trade is prosperous and is rapidly recovering its exportSo   Lever Brothers are issuing  40,000,000 new capital, and intend to make themselves self-sufficient in supplies from the Belgium Congo and the South Sea Islands.Paints and Varnishes0 The production of all kinds of Paint-eirsr dolours and materials was necessarily subject to severe restrictions during the war, and exports declined very heavily from     million tons in 1913 to only i million tons in 1918.   There is now a great general demand, which manufac-turers are finding it difficult to meet.   There is a short age of some materials, especially Fine White Barytes, which
Q pihave to be imported largely since the British production is adequate neither in quantity nor quality (in some grades) to meet requirements,The Linoleumi;.IMwtry, which is carried on mainly at Lanoastei;^an&quot;d&quot;KirFcaIdy was very much cut down during the war by the withdrawal of labour., the great shortage of linseed oil of which it could only be given a very small ration and the shortage of jute.   Its export markets were adversely affected by American competitions   The demand is great, and the industry is recovering rapidly.Pubbsr Indus tries.   The trade is very busy in practically aiT departments-   There is a great demand for rubber tyres, but makers who were debarred until the Armistice from producing tyres other than those required for military purposes have naturally been delayed in putting new tyres upon the market and are encountering severe competition bbth in the home and foreign markets from the great rubber tyre manufacturers of the United States, who have not been subject to the same restrictions and have the advantage of a very large domestic market,Miscellaneous Ind u8 tries.   There are a number of smaller industries&quot;which have&apos; developed during the war in consequence of the cutting off of supplies from Germany or other continen-tal sources.   Attention may bo drawn to the following in particular(a) Gas Mantles.   The supply of these was mainly German, and there has-been a large expansion of the manufacture in this country.   An essential material for the manufacture is Thorium Nitrate, a commodity produced before the war largely by Germany, which controlled the Monazite sand&apos;deposits of India,   The German control has been eliminated, and the production of Thorium Nitrate is now being succes-fully developed in this country.^ Toy-making,   This is an industry which has developedextensively during the war, and has witnessed substantial improvement in the quality of the goods produced.   It has been widely hoped that it would afford a valuable outlet for the labour of disabled soldiers.   There is considerable competition in cheap toys from Japan, and there is &amp; possibility of the recrudescence of competition from Germany, whose pre-war production of toys was very large in quantity, good in quality and low in price,Diamond-cutting. This industry which was carried on before the&quot;war almost entirely in Antwerp and Hambury, has been developed in the United Kingdom partly by Belgian refugees, and partly as an occupation for disabled soldiers, for whom training schemes have been set up*   The industry seems likely to meet with considerable success, and is viewed with some anxiety by the Belgian interests.   The position may be effected by the attempt now being made in South Africa to create a similar industry there.
P 0 S T-W A RSummary Statement showing the Post-War Progress of the Americas France and Germany, respectively, in certain hranc of 1919 compared with 1913 and 1918, so far as the particulBranch of Economic Activity.Monthly Average.Country      1913,1918.   I January, j FebrProduction of Coal: &quot;&quot;Ti^ousanoTs^of &quot;Tons)Production of Pig Iron: jE&amp;ous aMs o iHBbh. s,.)Ships under Constructlon: &apos;&quot;tW6usand Tons -Measurement)Imports (Neth [Thousancl I s)ifccpprts (Domesjtio) : &quot;TThousaWS sj*Moyerne nt o f ^h^uiug fatrahoesT Thousands of Tons)IndosJlos^^Ojf &quot;who e-&quot; sa IT Tri c eslDates of ^^an^ge: yiTes* I^r Average ft ewYtfayjfc&apos; on 1 one!on lew York on Paris Paris on LondonU.K.U a S i JX .France Germany-U. S * .L.Franc e Germany 3,953 42,408 3,350 15,710855 2 j 581427 1,585U,K.France GermanyU.E, U o S. A.France GermanyU.&amp;. U * S. .1. Fi-anc eGermanyU.X. (With cargo)U.S.A. (With cargo) &amp; in halias t) France. (With cargs)Germany.U a IL.U.S.A.France Germanyh 1,957 f 236 f    175f     54254,390 30,501 28,071 44,12943,770 42,505 22,934 41,3744,089 4,4402,876[- r&quot; &quot;*18.999 50,993 c 2,202 13,161753 3,209a215652 39,774 2,258h 19. 33, 2,-964a    744 !b3,302 j     2,(art mtt501 Id 1,980) Id 3,646). [Returns made d      52) I quarter!?/.100 100 100 100100 100 100107,365 50,872 66,38341,539 105,005 13,8111,934 3.6661,654129,958 42,077 65,07847,343 127,472 12,0281,634 3, A 9,01,753225*0 203 0 2217.3 201.334197.95.! 92,56 ! 105,53 I96.0395,53 102,56101,&apos; 46,1 74 ,146/ 120,111 ,i1,&apos;215,1 191.1 348 - 198] 95,1102,Statistical DepartmentBOARD OF TRADE.
P 0 S I-W A EPROGRESS.-War Progress of the United Kingdom, the United States of jly, in certain branches of Economic activity, in each month far as the particulars are available.ly Average,19 19.118,January, j February-   March.i..... i i! i (4 weeks)April.May,Remarks.999 9953 202 151a21,652 ib 19.472   lb 18,685 39,774 I    33,181   j   32,565 2,258 I     2,004   :     1,860980) 646) 52) )1365 1872 13831539 1005 1811934 16661654(Heturns made I quarterly.I 129,958 ! 42,077 j   65,07847,343 127,472 12,0281,834 8,6801,753;5o0 o o 2t/7.95 ^2,56)5*53101,954 46,759 74,04346,915 120,560 11,6091,819 2,4581,605217.3 201.334196.03 95,53 102,56215.3 191.534898.03 95.47 102.56(e 2,253)(e 4,186)(e 110)f -   )96,823 53,503 93,16253,108 123,780 16,364.1,940 2B7531,644212.0 187,1 34297,03 91.97105,14(4 weeks) I (4 weeks)b 17,270    ! 19,303 32,200 1,589753	j a     744 It	)      626. !	624   1	603209	3,302 1	.   2,940	3,068   1	--964	501 1	469	545   1	434Returns maids quarterly.98,864 49,70158,482 141,6922,207124,16264,3452,380214 c 4187, * 33895,54 86.49 110.56222,4 187.2 33195.9082,23 116,07a Ipivo weeks b &quot;(Pour1    &quot; c Average of eleven men.a Exclusive Nov.and Dec,output in the occupied distriots of the Saar Lorraine &amp;&apos; Luxemburg.d 31st Dec.1918. e 31st Mch.1919. f   1st Jan.1913. g   1st Apl.1919.-h 31st Deo.1913.(Economist) I (Bradstreet)

</content>
</cab>
