<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/86/0 images: 797-797</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
From Viceroy, $th August&apos; 1919.Clear the line.   164 A.   Following from Grant, dated 8th August:-&quot; Peace /tlpMv was signed to-day at 11 o&apos;clock.   Full text is as follows: -&apos; Following is text pgvctee treaty signed this morning : T&amp;aty or peace between the illustrious British Government and the independent A Mian Government concluded at Rawal Pindi on the Stli August 1919, corresponding i^jWllth Ziqad, .1337 Hijra.WV^ The following Articles for the restoration of peace have been agreed upon by the British Government and the Afghan Government:  Article 1. From date of signing of this treaty there shall be peace between the British Government on the one part and the Government of Afghanistan on the other.Article 2. In view of the circumstances which have brought about the present war between the British Government and the Government of Afghanistan the British Government, to mark their displeasure, withdraw the privilege enjoyed by former Amirs of importing arms, ammunition, or warlike munitions through India to Afghanistan.Article 3. The arrears of the late AiruVs subsidy are furthermore confiscated, and no subsidy is granted to the present Amir.Article 4. At the same time the British Government is desirous of the re-establishment of the old friendship that has so long existed between Afghanistan and Great Britain provided they have guarantees that the Afghan Government are on their part sincerely anxious to regain the friendship of the British Government. The British Government are prepared, therefore, provided the Afghan Government prove this by their acts and conduct, to receive another Afghan mission after six months for the discussion and (?) amicable settlement of matters of common interest to the two Governments and the re-establishment of the old friendship on a satisfactory basis.Article 5. The Afghan Government accept the Indo-Afghan frontier accepted by the late Amir. They further agree to the early demarcation by a British commission of the undemarcated portion pf the line to the west of the Khyber, where the recent Afghan aggression took place, and to accept such boundary as the British commission may lay down. The British troops of this side will remain in their present positions until such demarcation has been effected.&apos;&quot;Afghan delegation leave Pawal Pindi on Monday night.&quot;^ument is the Property of

</content>
</cab>
