<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/4/14 images: 192-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S 3- MOST SECRET -DW.M.  (39)  86th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE confidential Annex.SUPREME WARCOUNCIL-STATEMENT BYTHE PRIMEMINISTER ONTHIRD MEETINGAir Policy.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the French delgation had arrived late and had had to catch a train soon after 3 o&apos;clock.    This had severely limited the time available for the discussion.He had put the case for air attack on military objectives in the Ruhr very fully, but, as had been expected, the French Government had not been preparedto change their ground;    they had not, however, beenin the least disagreeable about the matter, or treatedour proposal lightly.    It was  clear that they were fully impressed with the importance of keeping as muchof Belgium as possible out of German hands, and withthe importance of the scheme prepared by theRoyal AirForce, of which he had given a detailed description.The French did not raise objection to the scheme onmoral grounds (e.g., that it might involve killingcivilians)..    They took their stand on military grounds,and it was.on   military grounds that they objected tothe scheme being put into operation at the present timeThe real point was, in their view, that neither we northey were in a sta.te in which we could stand punishmentwhile the Germans out-numbered us heavily in bombers.They therefore hoped that we should not press thepoint at the moment.    They did not, however, suggestthat the scheme should be put permanently into cold storage, but rather that it should be reserved, foruse at a later period.    They appreciated that in afew months&apos;   time the position might well be different  .

THE MINISTER POR CO-ORDINATION OP DEFENCE saidthat M. Daladier had stressed the tremendously strongdefences of the Ruhr, and had thought that our airmen-would suffer at least 50$ casualties in carrying outthe attach.   The French also differed from us in thinking that the bombing of the Ruhr would not prevent a German invasion and occupation of Belgium.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that the PrimeMinister had. stated the ease most forcibly.   He addedthat the French thought that retaliation for an attackon the Ruhr would fall on them before it fell on thiscountry.   He thought that the Meeting had had. thegreat advantage of familiarising the French with thescheme, and. that if we found ourselves in a meleethey would be ready to agree on the scheme being putinto operation.THE PRIME MINISTER said, that the matter had been left as indicated, and would be taken up at a. later stage.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL hoped that the Secretary ofState for Air would, take action to ensure that theFrench continued, to be interested, in the scheme and did. not forget about it.    If Germany invaded holland and Belgium he felt sure that we should have to carryout this scheme, and. he hoped that.we should lose no time in giving effect to it.THE SECRETARY OF STATE POR AIR said, that he saw noreason to be d.is appointed, as a result of the Meeting.The War Cabinet took note of theab ov e s t at ement s .Richmond Terrs,ce, S .W. 1,17th November, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
