<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/144/0 images: 256-261</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[document IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC majbSITS GOVERNMENT)C(69) 120COPY NO.6722nd September. 1969CABINETEQUAL pay memorandum by the First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Cabinet agreed (CC(69) 42nd Conclusions,, Minute 3) that legislation on equal pay should be introduced in the next Session on the broad lines indicated in my memorandum C(69) 113.    I was asked to elicitviews of the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and Confederation of BritishIndustry (CBI) on the need for legislation and the form it might take withoutrevealing the cabinet decision on legislation? and to report the outcome to cabinet in time for them to take decisions about the timing and form oflegislation before the Labour Party Conference.2.      I have now had meetings with both the TUC and CBI,    Neither partyconsider that a joint discussion would be helpful at *;he present time and I didnot therefore press them to have a joint meeting with me.    Both the tuc and CBI made it pretty clear that they could not take a diecxsssion of thesubject much further without some indication of what the Government thought should be done.TUC views3,      The TUC put before me a four point programmes-(i) A Declaration of Intent by the Government to the TUC and the CBIon the establishment of equal pays(ii) Action by the Government to establish equal pay in the industrial civil Service?(iii) Enabling legislation which would give the Government power to bring into line employers who decline to co-operate in achieving equal pay voluntarily!(iv) Ratification of the International Labour Organisation (ILO)Convention on Equal Pay6
4.      In discussion, the TUC admitted that they saw little prospect of anyjoint declaration of intent with the CBI unless the Government took a firmlead and indicated a firm date by which equal pay would have to beestablished,,    They accepted that their points about equal pay in theindustrial Civil Service and ratification of the 11*0 Convention would flowautomatically from any legislation (though I am clear that they will re-open the question of equal pay in the industrial Civil Service even if we announcedthat there would be no early legislations they do not accept that this couldnot be done on its own).5.      As regards the nature of the legislation, they assume it would fix a date by which equal pay would have to be established and would providemachinery for requiring individual employers to give equal pay.    As far aspossible e they would wane to see the actual arrangements in individual industries and firms settled by ordinary negotiations with trade unionswithin the time scale of the legislation.6,      On timing, the Congress Resolution refers to Implementation in aperiod of two years.    They know very well that this is unrealistic.    in private conversation Mr. Feather said that they would regard a three or perhaps four year period as reasonable.7,      The TUC are strongly opposed to the introduction of equal pay beinghandled under the incomes policy in such a way that equal pay results in areduction in the general rate of increase in pay that would otherwise beallowed.Views of the CBI8.      The CBI took the general line that while equal pay would have to beintroduced in time it would be wrong to start on introduction until theeconomic situation had been consolidated in (say) two years1 time.Implementation should then be phased over seven years, and even so, thereshould be provision for still further extensions for individual firms whichwould face particularly large wage increases in their wage bills.    Underthe incomes policy the cost of introducing equal pay should be taken fully into account in deciding the general rate of increase in pay which waspermissible.9.      The CBI assumed that there would be legislation  being a date bywhich discrimination in pay on grounds of sex would have to ceasec    they want to have detailed discussions with us on precisely what would be involvedin the concept of *discriminationt but my impression is that their views arenot significantly different from the ideas I set out below.    They wouldcertainly not be taking a stand on a very narrow definition of equal pay foridentical work.-2-
10,      The CBI are also very concerned that the nature of the legislation should not cut across the negotiation of equal pay arrangements in individual industries and firmsj and that there should be a large measureof flexibility left for ordinary negotiations.Timing and form of legislation31.       In the light of the reactions of the TUC and CBI - which were prettymuch as might have been expected - I have reviewed the proposals on timing and form of legislation set out in my memorandum C(69) 113.(0 General form of legislationBoth the TUC and CBI are expecting that the legislation wouldbasically take the form of fixing a date by which discrimination in pay on grounds of sex would have to cease? and to establish machinery by which individual employers could be required to give equal pay to their women workers,,    I am also quite clear that this legislation needs to be introduced at the beginning of the programme and not just left as a statement (that indue course such legislation would be passed at a later date.,(ii) Timing of programme in my previous memorandum^ I suggested that legis3.ation should provide for equal pay by (lie end of 1975 - in effect providing a 5^year period after the passing of the legislation.    I still think this in the right timing.The TUC will say it is too long and the CBI too short.    But I think this is aperiod which would be practicable both economically and politically,(iii) Meaning of equal payThe legislation would be concerned basically with removingdiscrimination in pay on grounds of sex and in general it would be left to independent Tribunals to decide whether in any particular case the  actsrevealed such discrimination.    However^ it would be desirable to make itclear what kind of situations would clearly be regarded as involvingdiscrimination,    I think the main cases are as followss-(a) In a collective pay agreement^, the existence of separate ratesfor men and women for any class or description of work would be treated as discrimination.    One could not forexample simply have one minimum rate for &quot;unskilled men&apos;and a lower rate for funokilled women1,(b) In any particular establishment different rates for men andwomen v/orkers doing the same or broadly similar work would be discrimination.    In general^ it would not be possibleto draw comparisons between one establishment and anotherunless they were governed by an identical pay structure.
(c)    Where rates of pay have been determined on the basis of ajob evaluation exercise, there could be no discriminationon grounds of sex in the pay given for jobs which had beenestablished as being of equal value in terms of skill,effort, responsibility and so forth,    (But the independent tribunal would not itself set out to do job evaluationexercises where they had not been used as the basis of apay structure by the employers),,V/orking out the details of this approach will require full discussions with the tuc, CBI and other major interests.    This will only be possible when theGovernment has announced its general decision.(iv) ILO ConventionLegislation on  he lines I have suggested would enable us to ratifyILO Convention 100 and we should do so when the legislation was passed.The introduction of equal pay on these lines v/ould bring us into line withthe developing practice in the European Economic Community countries,(v) Incomes policy the TUC and CBI hold diametrically opposed views on the handling of equal pay under the incomes policy. I have told them both that I would discuss this matter with them as part of the consultation I would be havingwith them shortly on the draft of the next White Paper on Incomes Policy.Nature and timing of the announcement12.      In. the announcement of the Governments intentions, I v/ould proposeto say that we would introduce legislation next Session requiring &apos;discrimination in pay on grounds of sex to end by 31st December, 1975$that v/e were considering whether there should be an intermediate phase;and that diocuscions would start immediately with CBI, TUC and other interested parties on details of the legislation.13,      As regards timing of the announcement., it was agreed in Cabinetthat there would be great advantage in announcing it at the labour party conference but that a decision on this would have to be taken in the light ofthe international monetary situation at the time.    I hope that my colleagues will agree to this in principle while leaving me to clear the exact date withthe Chancellor.14.      It is most desirable on practical grounds that the announcement should be made as soon as possible,,    It is clear that no effective discussions about the details of the legislation can take place with industry and tradeunions unfcSl the announcement is made.    We must give both sides reasonable time to discuss the details with us before the legislation is introduced.9 4&quot;&quot;&quot;
Conclusion15,       I therefore ask the Cabinet to agrees-(i) That I should make an early announcement thai the government intends to introduce legislation next Session providing for fullimplementation of equal pay by the end of 1975s(ii) That I should embark immediately thereafter on discussions with both sides of industry about the details of legislation,,B0A0C0Department of Employment and Productivity t S. W.1,22nd Septembers 1969


</content>
</cab>
