<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/139/0 images: 26-31</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[-HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJE5TYTS GOVERNMENT)C(68) 104 COPY NO.    ^11th October, 1968CABINETTHE QUEENS SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OFPARLIAMENTNote by the Lord Privy seal i circulate, for the consideration of the Cabinet, a draft ofThe Queen&apos;s Speech on the Prorogation of Parliament.T.F.P.70, Whitehall, S.W.1.11th October, 1968
THE QUEENTS SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OFPARLIAMENTMY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS -1.       My Husband and I were glad to welcome to this country thePresident of the Republic of Turkey.2.      My Government have contributed positively to the wide-rangingwork of the United Nations.    They have been active in seeking asettlement to the dispute between the Arab States and Israel.    Theytabled the Security Council Resolution on the Middle East which was unanimously adopted in November, 1967.3.      My Ministers have welcomed the opening of discussions in Pariswhich they hope will lead to the end of the Vietnam conflict.4.      My Ministers played a leading part in negotiations which led tothe successful conclusion of the treaty on the Non-Proloferation of nuclear Weapons, and have made proposals for further measures of disarmament.5.      My Government have maintained their application for membership of the European Communities and regret that the attitude adopted by oneof the present members of the Communities has so far prevented theopening of negotiations.6.      My Government have announced their intention of withdrawingBritish forces from Malaysia, Singapore and the Persian Gulf by the endof 1971.      They intend that over the next few years there should be ameasure of redeployment of national resources and that Britain^defence effort should in future be concentrated mainly in Europe and theNorth Atlantic area.    My Ministers took part in a successful conference with Ministers of Australia, New Zealand, Malaysia and Singapore inKuala Lumpur, where the problems arising from that decision were considered.7.      My Government have continued to play their full part in theNorth Atlantic Alliance.    They expressed their condemnation of the invasion of Czechoslovakia by the Soviet Union and some of its allies in violation of international law and the Charter of the United Nations,/jfaragraph on NATO and Eastarn-jCur-opu 4o be gjupplicd by the Foreign8.      My Government worked for and welcomed the restoration of diplomatic relations with the United Arab Republic, the Somali Republic,Sudan, Guinea, Algeria, Mali, Mauritania, the Democratic Republic ofthe Congo (Brazzaville), Iraq and Tanzania.9.      /My Government have continued to seek by all practicable means to bring about a return to constitutional rule in Rhodesia in accordancewith the multi-racial principles approved by Parliament.    To this endlegislation has been passed giving effect to the Security CouncilsResolution of 29th May .7-1-
10.      Three of our overseas territories became independent in the last12 months - Mauritius, Swaziland and Aden (as part of the PeopledRepublic of Southern Yemen).    Both Mauritius and Swaziland remained in the Commonwealth.    A revised constitution was introduced inSeychelles.11.       Last November, at the invitation of My Government in Malta,My Husband and I visited Malta and renewed our happy memories ofMy People in Malta and Gozo.    In April of this year My Governmentin the United Kingdom welcomed the successful settlement, to which they made an important contribution, of the Malta Dockyard ownershipproblem.12.      My Government welcome the improvement in relations betweenthe parties to the Cyprus dispute.13. Despite economic difficulties, My Government have sustained our programme of aid to less developed countries.14.      The announced reductions in the size of the Services will mean the retirement of some officers and men and lead to the disappearance of some famous regiments.    I am deeply grateful to all those concerned for their distinguished and selfless service.    The need for recruitsfor the Forces, however, remains as pressing as ever, and my government will not relax their efforts in this field.MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS15.      I thank you for the provision which you have made for the publicservice s.MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS16.      Following the devaluation of sterling in November 1967, my government have taken the measures necessary to ensure a progiessiveimprovement in the balance of payments and to maintain the strength of sterling at its new parity.17,      My Government have taken an active part in international discussions about reform of the international monetary system.Agreement has been reached with members of the Sterling Area and members of the Bank of International Settlements on arrangements to consolidate the stability of sterling.18.      A further Act has been passed to provide support for the productivity, prices and incomes policy.19.      The growth of industry in the development areas has been encouraged and special measures have been taken to reduce the impact of colliery closures in these areas.20,     An Act has been passed to provide for a better integration of road and rail transport and to promote higher standards in the road transport industry.    The Act will also enable improvements to be madein traffic management and the financial and other arrangements forthe railways and nationalised inland waterways,wm 2 *&quot;*
21. An Act has been passed to promote industrial expansion by enablingMy Government to assist probjects likely to benefit the economy.22.      Legislation has been passed to assist the exploitation of natural gas from the North Sea.23. Major new developments have been promoted in the United Kingdomaluminium smelting industry.24.      Legislation has been passed to strengthen the lav/ on misleadingtrade descriptions and on restrictive trade practices.25.      Legislation has been passed to clarify the law in its applicationto hovercraft; and to enable further measures to be taken to controlaircraft noise and supersonic flight.26.     An Act has been passed enabling provisional action in accordancewith international agreement to be taken against dumping.27.      My Government took steps to stamp out the very serious epidemicof foot and mouth disease and to ensure that the farms affected couldresume production on a sound basis.28.     An Act has been passed to enable additional payments to be madeto tenant farmers whose land is needed for development, to safeguard the welfare of farm animals, and for other agricultural purposes.29.      My Government have taken steps to protect the most vulnerablemembers of the community from the effects of price increases by improving supplementary benefits, rate rebates and family allowances.30.      Legislation has been passed to promote the better provision anddevelopment of health and welfare services; and to make newcomprehensive arrangements for controlling the safety, quality anddescription of medicines.31.      Legislation has been passed to establish a comprehensive social work service in Scotland; and appropriate provision has been madewherever necessary in other Acts to meet distinctive Scottish needs.32.     An Act has been passed to improve the government of colleges and special schools,33.      My Ministers have continued the revision of the machinery ofgovernment to meet the changing requirements which are placed upon it.    The Foreign Office and Commonwealth Office have been merged.An Order has been made /proposals have bean laid before you/ for the amalgamation of the Ministry of Health and the Ministry of social security.    My Government have welcomed the report of the FultonCommittee on the Civil Service; and an Order has been laid before you for the transfer   of the necessary functions to a new Civil service department which will be closely engaged in the reshaping of the CivilService following the recommendations of the Committee.
34.     An Act has been passed providing for more effective planning control of development in England and Wales and for increased publicparticipation in local planning.35.      Legislation has been passed to establish a Countryside Commission,to provide for the conservation of the countryside and for greater opportunities for leisure and recreation there;  and for the appointmentof a Welsh Committee of the Commission.36.     An Act has been passed strengthening control over immigration from other parts of the Commonwealth.37.     An Act has been passed to make discrimination on racial groundsunlawful in employment, housing and the provision of goods, facilities and services and to encourage the development of harmonious community relations.38.     An Act has been passed to reform the law on gaming and tostrengthen control over commercial gaming clubs and gaming machines.39.     Further progress has been made in the systematic reform of thelaw, including that relating to theft, evidence and justices of the peace inEngland and Wales and to succession and evidence in Scotland,MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF commons I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may attend you.-4-secret


</content>
</cab>
