<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/139/0 images: 79-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
iXHlSDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST YTS GOVERNMENT)C(68) 109 COPY NO.       Ui15th October, 1968CABINETTHE CONCORDE CRITERIAt  THE NEXT STEPMemorandum by the Minister of TechnologymumAt its meeting on 1st August (CC(68) 37th Conclusions, Minute 3)the Cabinet invited me, in consultation with the Foreign Secretary, thePresident of the Board of Trade, the Chief Secretary, Treasury, andthe Attorney-General, to prepare criteria in the light of which the futureof the Concorde project would be determined, and to seek the agreementof the French to such criteria.The two criteria adopted2,       The two criteria subsequently agreed with my colleagues were:-(i) An upper limit of  600 million (1966 prices) on development cost which if it looked like being exceeded would call intoquestion the wisdom of continuing with the project and wouldfree either Government from an automatic obligation to continue;and(ii) firm orders by 31st December, 1969 from four major airlines ofwhich one must be an American airline.We considered a third criterion relating to engine noise, but for a numberof reasons based on difficulties of definition and of tactics vis-a-vis theFrench, decided not to pui sue it.Negotiations with the French3.      I met M. Chamant in London on 24th September.    Our discussionsoccupied eight hours and were devoted entirely to the question of the criteria.    The atmosphere throughout was cordial.4.      He stressed that the French Government had never regardedConcorde simply as a prestige project but nevertheless hoped that it willbe a source of pride.    It must in their view be a useful operationjustifying itself on commercial and economic grounds.    He agreed thatthe time had come to establish criteria.    But went on to say that until we had had the results of flight trials at sustained supersonic speeds wewould not know the truth about performance and whether the aircraft wouldbe acceptable to the airlines.    The crunch would probably come at about-1-
the end of 1969.    K then the airlines did not order the aircraft it wouldbe evident that the project could not be pursued.    He agreed therefore that it would be sensible to establish now a criterion based on airlineorders and tabled a document (translated as Annex A) proposing that adecision on the continuation of the project should be taken before the endof 1969, on the basis of its commercial prospects,, as follows;(a)    Orders from four major airlines, of which at least one to be an american airline:  the project to be continued.(b) No hope of orders;  the project to be stopped.(c) Hope of orders, but at the price of modifications to the aircraftinvolving additional development cost and a further delay tothe programmes  the Ministers to discuss the continuance of the project on the basis of a comparison between the hope of orders and the increases in costs and time scales.This was a good start but his proposal contained no reference to our firstcriterion (development cost).5.      We discussed development cost as a criterion at great length.M. Chamant was not easily persuaded of its validity.    He argued thatthere were too many uncertainties for it to be possible validly to determinenow a figure of cost which, if it looked like being exceeded, would automatically halt the project; any such figure could only be arbitrary.Everything would depend on the aircraftTs performance and sales prospects.I think I finally convinced him of the validity of our argument for settinga limit to the development cost on the basis that a point could be reached at which it was clear that a major measure of redesign would be necessaryto make the aircraftTs performance acceptable to airline customers andthat, if this happened we should be confronted with a new situation.    Iagreed that it was not possible to forecast with precision at what level of cost this would arise, but he accepted  600 million (at 1966 prices) as areasonable estimate of the probabilities.    He could not however agreethat this figure (or any other) should be set as a limit which., if it lookedlike being exceeded, would free either Government from any automaticobligation to continue with the project.    He made it clear that it wasbeyond his authority to make such an agreement since it would be a major change in the Concorde Treaty.    Nevertheless, he accepted the force ofmy argument and wished to be as helpful as he could.    After lengthy-discussion of possible ways of expressing a development cost criteria,he finally proposed than if (at the end of 1969) he and I agreed that thedevelopment cost would probably exceed  600 million (1966 prices), wewould each propose to our respective Governments that the twoGovernments should free each other from all automatic obligations to pursue the project.    It would then be for the two Governments to considerthe situation and decide whether extra resources should be madeavailable or the project stopped.6.      We argued at length about the date at which the development costcriterion should come into play.    I pointed out that the question could arise before the end of 1969.    He agreed but claimed that this possibilitywas covered by paragraph 3 of his proposal (Annex A) in which he was prepared to incorporate a reference to development cost.    He was,however insistent, for the reasons already given about the need to have theresults of supersonic flight trials, that the special provision for an agreedMinisterial recommendation to the two Governments should not apply untilthe end of 1969,-2-
7o      At the end of the day, therefore, although we had moved closer together, what he was offering fell short in certain significant respects,which I discuss below, of what the Cabinet had instructed me to seek.He made it clear that he could offer no more.    I therefore proposed,and he agreed, that we should each report to our colleagues.    He has since sent me the letter at Annex B, to which he attached a draft basedon his original document amended in the sense of our discussions(Annex C).Comparison of French proposal with our suggested criteria8.      Our tactics were governed by two somewhat conflicting aimsviz?-(i) to seek agreement on criteria in the light of which the future ofthe project could be determined;   and(ii) to establish a strategy of withdrawal while at the same timeminimising the risk of damages in the International Court inthe event of unilateral withdrawal by ensuring that the proposals we put forward could not be construed as a breach of the Treatybut rather as a reasonable way of implementing it while settingreasonable limits to the commitments under it, having regardto the cost escalation and delays that had already occurred andto the continuing risks and uncertainties (technical, financial,and commercial) of the project.9.      It was to meet the second of these objectives that (i) we framedour ordering criterion in precise terms and related it to a specificdate (31st December, 1969) and (ii) described the cost criterion assetting a figure which &quot;if it looked like being exceeded would call intoquestion the wisdom of continuing with the project and would free either government from an automatic obligation to continue110.      We failed to reach agreement with the French on these twcaspects because the French may not be concerned to establish for themselves the possibility of unilateral withdrawal.    They may reckonthat there is no need for them to do so; believing that if they wanted towithdraw they would have no difficulty in persuading us to agree.    their proposals are therefore directed solely to showing their reasonablenessin agreeing to the establishment of criteria in the light of which the futureof the project should be determined.    They proceeded on the assumption(which I did not and could not challenge) that both Governments would wish to carry the project to completion if it showed reasonable prospects of success.    The essential criterion for them is therefore airline orders and this is put forward (reasonably enough) not in precise terms of automatic obligation but in terms of the recognition of a need forjudgment of the possibilities when the data necessary to judgment is available.    A judgment will have to be made of the worthwhileness of proceeding in the light of probability of sales and the extra cost in timeand effort likely to be involved in realising them.-3-
11.      M. Chamantrs proposals therefore fall short of our objective ofestablishing a strategy of withdrawal under which, in agreement with theFrench, if certain criteria were not met, we would be free to withdrawunilaterally.    The next question we have to consider is whetheracceptance of M. Chamanfs proposals would improve our position,worsen it, or leave things much as they are.    This is best consideredby examining the courses open to us.Possible course a12.      The possible courses open to us are;(i) to seek further discussions with the French with the aim ofsecuring our original objectivesI am satisfied that M, Chamant has gone both to the limit of his authority and as far as he is prepared to recommend his Government togo.    I think therefore that further talks would have to be put on a moreformal Government-to-Government basis to seek through diplomatic channels a negotiated amendment to the Treaty.    In my view such talkswould not be likely to succeed.    The French Government would I am convinced stand firm on the line of M. Chaman^s proposal and we shouldbe confronted, more formally and finally than we are now, with a choice between accepting or rejecting this proposal.    Whatever disadvantagesthere may be in accepting it now, would be increased if we were unableto obtain any concession in more formal negotiations and were forcedto accept it nevertheless.(ii) Immediate unilateral cancellationWe ruled this out before and should do sc now.    To v/ithdrawunilaterally now would aggravate the breach in the eyes of theInternational Court, firstly because of the apparent rea-sonableness ofthe French response to our request for criteria and secondly because itwould look as though my discussions with M. Chamant had not been undertaken in good faith.I rule this course out.(iii) For me to reply to M. Chamant restating our position and thereasoning on which it is based and to say that if the FrenchGovernment cannot accept it, rather than agree to M. ChamantTsproposal, we would prefer to leave his proposal and ours on the record as indicating the views of the two Governments(iv) To accept M. ChamantTs proposal but in doing so to restate ourposition and to make clear how we would interpret this situationin practice, i. e. that if it became clear to us that the criteriacould not be met, we should feel free to withdraw, after further consultations.-4-
I consider (iii) and (iv) together as (iv) is only a modified version of (iii).    K we were to proceed in this way, I would prefer (iii) as the stronger course.    If we adopted course (iv), the French would be boundto react and would probably themselves take the line that, in that event,they would withdraw their proposal and reaffirm their reliance on theTreaty.    Courses (iii) or (iv) have the disadvantage that they preclude the possibility offered by M. Chamanfs proposal of proceeding inagreement with the French to keep the programme under review by reference to agreed criteria as the basis for judgment.    Having ruled out immediate unilateral withdrawal it would be necessary to continue with the project until our criteria carne into play and then decide whetheror not to withdraw unilaterally.    Moreover these courses have considerable political risks.    I cannot recommend them.    They wouldnot save money, nor strengthen our hand at the International Court but would destroy the measure of agreement already reached.(v) Agree on the basis of the position now reachedAlthough the compromise falls short of securing all that we sought,the French have been drawn a long way towards our view.    For the first time we have got them to agree to criteria by which the continuingvalidity of the project is to be judged.    Should the eventuality (of theestimated development cost exceeding  600 million at 1966 prices) arise and should we then decide unilaterally to withdraw, we would be in astrong position in the International Court as we could show that the responsible French Minister had recommended, or had agreed torecommend, to his Government that in that eventuality we should be freed from our obligation to continue.In my judgment, having ruled out immediate unilateral withdrawal,the difference in practical terms between our criteria and the compromise is marginal.    We would not in any event expect thedevelopment cost criterion ( 600 million at 1966 prices) to be invocablebefore the summer of 1969,  if at all.    But in the discussion by theWorking Group of Ministers the view was expressed that at the end of1969, by which time we should have spent some  200 million on development,  25 million on production and would face cancellationcharges of up to  50 million, the political pressure to continue would be virtually impossible to resist.    Accordingly we considered thepossibility of seeking to establish a position whereby the provisions ofparagraph 2(d) of the compromise proposal might be invoked at someearlier time if the estimate for development exceeded  600 million at1966 prices.Attention concentrated upon paragraph 3 of the French proposal which had been amended by M. Chamant during the course of discussionso as to Include a reference to the cost criterion in order, as he said,to meet my point about the cost estimate exceeding  600 million at 1966prices before the end of 1969.    A comparison between Annex $-and annex (J,shows the amendment that was made.    Although M. Chamantsaid this amendment should meet our point it does not bind him torecommend to his Government before the end of 1969, that each government should release the other from its automatic obligations under the Treaty if the estimate exceeds  600 million at 1966 prices as provided in paragraph 2(d).    It simply provides that in that event theCDC will report to Ministers and that they will consider the situation.-5
M. Chamant made it clear at our meeting that he would not accept any further amendment to paragraph 3.    The only remaining way bywhich we might secure at least part of our objective would be for me, in accepting the compromise proposal, to write placing on record our understanding of how we should proceed if the estimated development cost rose above  600 million at 1966 prices during 1969.    I have prepared a draft letter in the sense which is attached at Annex D.,The draft in effect says two things: first, that if the costcriterion comes into play before the end of 1969 then we would expectM. Chamant to consider whether we should not act as provided inparagraph 2(d), and second, that we regard our acceptance of the compromise as without prejudice to such freedom of unilateral action as we already possess.    At one point during our meeting M. Chamantwent so far as to imply that he could certainly envisage circumstancesunder which a very steep rise in development costs could lead to hisrecommending to his Government before the end of 1969 that the project should be cancelled.    But M. Chamant was nevertheless adamant in refusing to include a reference to this possibility in the compromise proposal itself, and I have no doubt that part of the price the Frenchintended to exact for agreeing to the criteria was to ensure that wereaffirmed our commitment to the project up to the end of 1969.There is thus a real risk that the French will not accept a letter in the terms of Annex D without comment.    There are three possibilities(i) M. Chamant might reply merely noting our views.    We should the whole preserved our freedom of action, such as it is, but thiswill be as clear to Mr. Chamant as it is to us and from hisclear rejection at our meeting of my attempt to amendparagraph 3 along these lines, I am sure he would not allow theletter to pass unchallenged.(ii) M. Charaant might reply saying that he regarded the letter as adisguised attempt to achieve by correspondence what we had failed to achieve at the Conference table, and that if weinsisted on this interpretation of paragraph 3 he would have no alternative but to withdraw the compromise proposal.    Since,however, the letter does not go as far as the amendment wesought to paragraph 3 the French would probably not regard this as so good a tactical position as possibility (iii) would give them.I therefore think it is unlikely that M. Chamant will do this.(iii) He might reply rejecting my interpretation of paragraph 3 andrestating his views.    Unless we chose then to withdraw our acceptance of the compromise proposal (in which case we wouldbe back in the position of proceeding without agreed criteria)our position in relation to possible further unilateral withdrawal,before the agreed criteria came into operation, would be worse than if we accepted the compromise now without raising thequestion of the interpretation to be put on paragraph 3.-6-
I regard (iii) as the most probable outcome.    In other words, by-writing in the terms of the draft at Annex D we would run a serious riskof ending up in a worse case than we would if we simply accept the compromise without comment, and some risk of our being forced back into the position of proceeding with the project without any agreedcriteria and no better prospect of being able to withdraw unilaterally,without paying damages, than we have had in the past,I do not regard the limited potential gain of my writing as at annex D as sufficient to outweigh the very real danger than we may losesome or all of the gains which an unqualified acceptance of Course (v)now offers.    In shorty the compromise proposal, with its agreedcriteria, is extremely valuable and should not be put at risk without a clear prospect of further advantage which in my judgment a letter onthe lines of Annex D would not offer.Conclusion and Recommendation13.      I therefore recommend that we adopt Course (v) without qualification.    In my judgment, unless we do so it will be impossiblefor me to work effectively with M. Chamant as being jointly responsiblewith him for the project, and this mutual Ministerial distrust will reflectitself in all official contacts, thus destroying the joint managementoperation which has to be maintained while the two Governments continueto finance this project,    A Ministerial and inter-Government deadlockcannot seriously be contemplated,    Only in this way can I discharge the cabinet&apos;s decision that I should be seen to be working for the success ofthe project, a situation that must continue until it is cancelled, if thathappens.A.W.B.Ministry of Technology, S.W.I.14th October, 1968
COrlnUb^IlAL,85TRANSLATION OP DOCUMENT TABLET) BY If..&apos; CHAMANT ATHIS MEETING V/ITH MR. Y/ED07K)OD 3ENN ON 24th SEPTEMBER 1968COMMERCIAL CONFIDENTIAL 1 . London, 24th&apos; September, 1968CONCORDE PROJECTOAt their meeting on the 24th September 1968 in. London, Mr. AnthonyV/Wedgewood Benn, British Minister of Technology, and Monsieur Jean Chamant,French Minister of Transport, arrived at the following agreement in regard the Concorde project. -lo-    The project to be pursued vigorously until the second halfof 1969) by which date the flights at Match 2 will have&apos;provided the necessary information on the actual performance of Concorde. - .2o    A decision on the continuance of.the project to bo taken before the end of 1969? based on the commercial prospects.(a) Orders from 4 major airlines, of which at&apos; , least one to be an American airline: the ; .project to be continued.(b) No hope of orders: the project to be stopped.(c) Hope of orders, but at the price of mod-ifications to the aircraft involving additionaldevelopment, cost and a further delay to the,programme: the Ministers to discuss the conltinuance of the project on the basis of a comparison between the hope (of orders) andthe increases in costs and-time scales.3.    Of course, if meanwhile the Concorde Directing Committee con-siders that there is no longer any hope of sales, it will report this to. the Ministers who will then examine the situation,&quot;but the Ministers do not require to follow step by step thedevelopment of sales prospects between now and the end of 1969.
CONCORDE&apos; Translation of a letter fromE.Chamant dated 27th September.Following our mooting on the 24th Sop-bomber I should like to tollyou again how pleased my colleagues and I were at the atmosphore offrankness and understanding in which our conversations took placo,V/e have not so fax arrived at a complete identity of vIgwo, butI am confident that our respective attitudes are so close that wo shallnot bo long in arriving at identical viewpoints and that we shall veryquiokly roach full agreement.The attached note ia a summary of my views and tho concoeoionowhich I am aocept.   I should be glad to know your feeling in thismatters(Sgd)    Jean CHAMP
CONCORDS&apos;   Trans la ti on, ,cf, the a 11 a chm ent t oM.Chamant&apos;s letter of 27th September.Mr, Anthony Wedgwood Benn, British Minister of Technologyland M. Jean Chamant, French Minister of Transport have arrived;at the following understanding in regard to the Concorde;1.   Active continuation of the project until the second half of 1969, by which date the Mach 2 flights of the aircraft &apos; ;jv/ill have provided the necessary information on the actual &apos;^performance of the Concorde,2.   At the end of 196*9* a decision to be taken on the^continuation of the project based on commercial prospects:   -a.   Orders from k major airlines, including at least oneAmerican airline: project to be continued.I     b.   No prospect of orders:   project.to be terminated.i   :,. c.   Prospect of orders but at the price of modifications to the aircraft involving increased development costs . &apos;:&apos; and a further delay in the programme:   Ministers todiscuss the continuance of the project based on a. . comparison of prospects and increased cost and (time-     -   -v  &apos;    -    scales. &apos; ,d.   In the event of the estimated development costs at:I      &apos; . that date being more than  600M (8,300MF) in January    ;1966 - conditions, each of the two Ministers to propose to&apos;:-        ,   their respective Governments an amendment to the ;!:Memorandum of Understanding of 1962 releasing each government from any automatic obligation to continue the ;project jointly. - .5.y If in the meanwhile the Concorde Directing.Committee considers that there is no longer any hope of sales or ofmaintaining the development costs below the limit-of  600M (8,300MP)Sin January 1966 conditions, it will, of course, report to the      :Ministers who will then, consider the&apos; situation but will not -   - $:; ;require to be informed step by step of the development of salespospects between now. and the end of 1969;
ANNEX DDRAFT LETTER FROM MINISTER OF TECHNOLOGY TO M. CHAMANT,&quot; FRENCH MINISTER OP TRANSPORTThank you for your letter of September 27th and its attachment.I think your note reflects very fairly the sense of our discussion,and after consultation with my colleagues I am for my part content to accept it without further amendment as a record of theagreement which was reached between us.You will recall that during our discussion we considered theproblem   of what would happen if the CDC reported before the endof 1969 that the development cost was likely to exceed the criterion figure.   You took the view that this possibility was covered by paragraph 3 of your proposal, and that to go further and stipulate that in this event the two Ministers should recommend to their Governments that they should release eachother from their obligations under the 1962 Memorandum of understanding was unnecessary and could be prejudicial to our continuing efforts to make the project a success.     We for our part feel that we can accept your wording because it seemed clear from our discussion that there was no difference between us as to what would happen in practice.     But since it isnot self-evident from the wording of ;/our proposal as now agreed, it would, I think, be well if I could spell out our understanding of how we would proceed in this eventuality./If .. ..
CONFTOENTIALIf estimated development costs were to rise above  600M(1966 prices) it would imply that a major re-design would benecessary.        It would therefore be necessary to decide quicklywhether such re-design should be put in hand or whether the project should be cancelled.     In this event we would I am sure wish to consult together, and we would have to consider, inthe light of our agreement over the significance of the figureof  600M (1966 prices)   whether we should not then recommend toour Governments that the 1962 Understanding should be amended in the sense of para 2(d).     This is I know a remote contingency,which we all hope and believe will not come to pass.     But, as you yourself recognised at our meeting, our agreement on yourproposal should not be taken to imply that, if faced with sucha radically nevi situation, we would not consider terminating the project before the end of 1969, and I think it important that this should be clearly understood between us.


</content>
</cab>
