<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/139/0 images: 186-189</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC IvlA.JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(68) 11316th October, 1968COPY NO.iabinetEUROPEAN policy note by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs my colleagues may wish to see, as background to our discussion on Thursday, 17th October, the attached copy of rnytelegram of 13th October to the Prime Minister from New York.M.S.Foreign Office, S.W.1.16th October, 1968
Copy of TELEGRAM No. 2491 of 13th October, 1968, from United KingdomMission, New York, to Foreign OfficeEuropeFollowing for Prime Minister from Foreign Secretary.The presence in New York this week of the Foreign Ministers ofall six e.c. countries has enabled Harmel to advance his ideas for dealingwith the deadlock in Europe,    You will recall the talks which you and Ihad with him in London on 18th September, and his determination, if the eec Council Meeting on 27th September showed the French to be asnegative as ever, to see what progress could be made in the fields outsidethe Rome Treaty, and so outside the reach of a French veto.    this approach is of course essentially that of the Benelux memorandum of19th January which we welcomed and agreed at the time, and which mightwell have led to earlier progress if the Germans had not been diverted bythe February meeting between de Gaulle and Kiesinger and the laboriousmonths which followed while the Six explored the possibility of agreeingproposals for a trade agreement,,    It is clear that, with the exception ofthe Germans) everyone now regards the trade arrangements approach asdead.    Brandt will probably go on with it in the e.c. Council but he nolonger regards further clarity on a trade arrangement as a necessarycondition for considering other approaches.2.      Essentially the Belgian pioposal is that we should now see whatscope there is fox- closer co-operation on a European basis in foreignpolicy and defence.    Other subjects could also be considered in due course,    Harmel says he has Debreh? assurance that France will not object to a procedural decision when V/EU Ministers meet in Rome on21st October to establish a group to report on the possibilities in timefor consideration in January.    Debre has however said that France willoppose decisions on substance being taken on 21st October.3,      In the light of this, German, Italian and Belgian officials (thelatter acting informally for Benelux as a whole) discussed here this week with our own officials both the general political objectives which weshould have in mind and the text of a mandate which we might adopting Rome on 21st October, calling for studies to be submitted to ministers by January.    Informal agreement was reached on objectives and on procedure.    It was agreed that consideration should be given to thepossibility of a new agreement to be concluded between &quot;the interestedEuropean States&quot; to strengthen co-operation particularly in the fields of foreign policy and defence.    (This formulation leaves open thepossibility of bringing in Norway and Denmark, for example, in due course).    As far as foreign policy is concerned, there was agreement that something like the formulation of the final point in the benelux proposals was the right approach:  to aim for consultation before decisions on questions of common interest which could be defined in advance.    In defence, problems of European defence strategy and standardisation and production of armaments are subjects which,it is suggested, it would be advantageous to treat on the European plane.A simple institutional structure would be necessary if, because ofFrance, it proves impossible to operate in V,rEU.    In all this, the need to act within the Alliance and in a way which v/ould reinforce thefunctioning of NATO was recognised.-1-
4,       The draft mandate which would set work in motion on all this, andwhich the Five have all now agreed, will be given to the French by Karmel,56      So far, so good0    The French may either withdraw their agree-ment, and veto progress in Rome:  or they may obstruct progressbetween the October and January WEU meetings.    There are no illusionsamong my five colleagues about the likelihood of a co-operative Frenchapproach.    But for the moment, the result of IvL Debre&apos;s apparentreadiness to contemplate decisions of procedure is that it has beeneasier for the Germans to join in the operation.    This is in our interest,and indeed it may well be essential if useful work is to be done.    our task now will be on the one hand to avoid sacrificing the essentialobjective - putting in hand effective work in foreign policy and defence -while on the other hand making it as difficult as possible for Germanyto withdraw.6.      I am sure that this is the right approach.    I have no doubt thatthe present is a favourable moment for Britain to resume a more activerole in European affairs.    My talks here this week have confirmed myimpression that irritation with French obstruction is running high in theFive.    Even Brandt was quite frank about the major differences betweenthe French and German Governments.    The conviction that czechoslovakia and uncertainties about US policies next year mean that Europe must showa greater sense of purpose makes it essential for us to try to breakFrancels hold on the other Five Community countries and establish a healthier atmosphere for co-operation in Europe while there is tiine0That is why I regard foreign policy and defence as the most promisingfields for action.    If we do nothing now, Italy and the Benelux countries may well lose heart, and the Community may then resume its develop-rnent, under French leadership today, under German leadership later.,7.      If we now follow up Harrnel&apos;s ideas, we shall sooner or later haveto face the question whether we should proceed without France.    I anclear that we must be prepared for this, and I have told my colleagueshere that this is my view.    Medici and Luns agree with me:  so doesHarmel though the Belgian Government as a whole has not taken adecision.    Brandt, when I saw him on 10th October, said that ifinitiatives came from others and provided that they avoided appearing to try to exclude France, Germany would decide on her attitude in thelight of her national interests.    And he was of course more specificabout readiness to go ahead, if necessary without France, when he spoke to Jackling immediately after the Kiesinger/de Gaulle meeting,(Bonn telegram No, 1344 of 30th September),


</content>
</cab>
