<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/43/13 images: 98-103</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  July 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (44)97th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 97 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet War Room,S.W. 1, on Thursday, 27th July, 1944, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P.,  Secretary of  State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply.The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Lord Portal, Ministerof Works.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Marshal of the Royal Air force sir Charles F. A. Portal, Chief ofthe Air Staff.The Rt. Hon. A. V. Alexander, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.Mr. Duncan Sandys, M.P., joint parliamentary Secretary, Ministryof Supply.Admiral of the Fleet Sir andrew cunningham, First Sea Lord and chief of Naval Staff.Field-Marshal Sir Alan Brooke, Chiefof the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.General Sir Hastings L. Ismay.Mr. W. S. Murrie.f27959-1]
WAR CABINET 97 (M).Contents.minute no.    . Subject. page 1      Military Operations   ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    219Normandy.2      &quot;Crossbow&quot;    ................      ............     2193      Parliament............................    220Proposed Motion about Political Warfare in relation to Germany.
1. The Prime Minister referred to the statement in the morning newspapers that there had been a serious set-back toBritish troops on the Orne. The War Cabinet were informed thatthis statement had been given out by a spokesman of SHAEF atmidnight on the previous night. In fact, all that had happened wasthat on part of the front our forces had had to withdraw about1,000 yards and that two villages had changed hands twice.The general view was expressed that a statement of this kind atthe present juncture was unfortunate, more particularly in view ofthe feeling of disappointment in certain circles that our advancefrom the Normandy bridgehead had not gone faster.The Prime Minister said that he was sure that the statement made was not in accordance with General Eisenhower&apos;s wishes, and undertook to raise the matter with the Supreme Allied Commander.2. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary and Minister of Home Security (W.P. (44)&apos; 412)proposing that the Government plans for dealing with attacks on london by long-range rockets should be re-examined.After a discussion, which has been recorded in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions, the War Cabinet agreed as follows :  (1) Plans should be made to meet the contingency of rocketattacks on the scale which now seemed possible; andcertain action should be taken at once.(2) The following were the matters in regard to which action should be taken forthwith :- &apos;(a) The evacuation of the priority classes should be stimulated, and these classes should be extendedto include mothers with schoolchildren.(&amp;) An estimate should be made of the extent to whichthe population of London had been reduced byofficial and unofficial evacuation since the flyingbomb attacks had started. Enquiry should bemade as to the considerable movement of popula-tion into London which was reported by railwaysto be taking place, and as to the reasons for this* movement, with a view to a decision on whether any steps should be taken to check it.(c) Steps should be taken, without publicity, to movepatients from the London hospitals to hospitals in other parts of the country. This might involvedrawing on the hospital accommodation set aside for Service casualties.(d) The process of shifting production from factories inLondon to factories elsewhere should . continue,particular attention being paid to key factories.(e) The 10,000 Government staffs at present housed in poor accommodation with no form of sheltershould be moved to other accommodation either in London or elsewhere.(/) In his forthcoming statement on the war situation,the Prime Minister would give particulars of the casulties caused by flying bombs, and would emphasise that members of the priority classeswould do well to take advantage of the facilitiesfor evacuation. He undertook to considerpassages submitted to him by the Home secretary and Minister of Home Security and- the Ministerof Health.(g) In addition, editors might be reminded confidentiallyabout the danger of rocket attack in such a way as to keep the public aware of its possibleMilitaryOperations.Normandy.(previous reference:W.M.(44)95thConclusions,Minute 1.)&quot; Crossbow.&quot;(previous reference:W.M. (44) 95thConclusions,Minute 4.)
Parliament. 3.   The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs informed theProposed War Cabinet that the Bishop of Chichester had sought to put downMotion about    the following Motion for Wednesday, the 2nd August: ^litioal . &quot;To ask His Majesty&apos;s Government whether they havear are in any information to give about the use of political warfare at the relation to present time, particularly in relation to Germany, and to moveGermany. for paper g &quot;The War Cabinet thought that it would be undesirable in thepublic interest that there should be-/a discussion of this matter at thepresent time, and expressed the hope that the notice of motion wouldnot be put down.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs was invited toinform the Bishop of Chichester accordingly.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,21th July, 1944.imminence while taking special care not to causealarm.(h) The Lord Presidents Committee would considerwhether, from the point of view of defence against flying bomb and rocket attacks, it wouldbe advisable to continue double summer time fora further period after the 13th August.(3) Plans should be prepared to meet the contingency of rocketattack on the following lines :  I(I(a) Transport and accommodation should be available in   ^1order to enable up to 2 additional million persons to be evacuated from London to safe areas overa period of three to four weeks. Alternativeplans should also be made for moving the same number in a shorter period to a distance of some20 miles from London.(b) The emergency arrangements for dealing with alarge exodus on foot from London should bebrought into a state of readiness.(c) Arrangements should be made to enable the supply ofbuilding labour available for the clearance ofdebris and the repair of damaged houses inLondon to be reinforced from both civilian and.Service sources.(d) The co-ordination of the shifting of production fromfactories in London to factories elsewhere withthe transfer of the civil population under theevacuation arrangements should be studied.(e) Arrangements, to be operated in the event of rocketattack, should be made for the evacuation from london of non-essential Government staffs andfor the allocation of the most highly protected accommodation to those staffs who must remain inLondon.(4) A meeting would be held on the following day to review and confirm the Conclusions set out under (2) and (3)above and to settle the Ministerial responsibility foreach item.



</content>
</cab>
