<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/153/0 images: 129-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.68APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED REPORT No. 107.BRITISH  EMPIRE  AND AFRICA.Canada.The death of Sir Wilfrid Laurier removes from public life one of the most outstanding statesmen who have figured in Dominion politics, and will exercise a profound influence upon the future of the Liberal Party, which Sir Wilfrid did so much to create in its present form. Of possible successors in the Liberal leadership, Mr. W. S. Fielding may perhaps act immediately, but a strong element of Liberal opinion has for long favoured the claims of Mr. Martin, the present Premier of Saskatchewan.The subject of the deportation of aliens continues to agitate public opinion. Other items of interest in this Report relate to the sale of liquor and labour matters.New Zealand.The publication of enlistment and casualty figures has emphasised the extent of the Dominion effort in the war.The information regarding cadet training is of interest.South Africa.The refusal of the crew of the Durham Castle to sail with the Nationalist Delegation no doubt came as a relief to General Hertzog and his associates, who were thus provided not only with an argument against British intolerance, but with a happy exit out of a mission which gave promise of no political capital. The offer to the would-be Empire-wreckers of passages on a British warship possesses a distinct element of satire.The debate on Republicanism in the House of Assembly has probably done good. The debate in the Senate was made notable by the declaration of the President, whose views in favour of Republicanism, so weU known to his associates, have^now been brought into the light.India (excluding External Affairs.)There appears to be some tendency towards the renewal of the Bombay strikes. The campaign against the Sedition Bills was only to be expected.Foreign Colonies in Africa. The views of the German Government representatives and others regarding Colonial policy should be noted.H. d&apos;E.February 20th, 1919.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Pointed for the War Cabinet. 0^SECRET. For Reference only.BRITISH   EMPIRE   A1ND. AFRICA   REPORT.No. 107.   Week ending 19th February 1919 (night).Contents.Self-Governing- Dominions.Canada.Death of Sir W. Laurier. Opposition Leader. War claims. Deportation of aliens. Farms for soldiers. Sale of liquor to soldiers. Prohibition in Quebec. labour and extremists. Labour conditions.   Revenue and debt.Australian Commonwealth.Mr. Hughes and Peace Conference. Influenza: results of epidemic. Increase iu cost of living. Repatriation.New Zealand.Enlistment figures.   Cadet training.South Africa.Republicanism: debate in House of Assembly ; debate in the Senate. The Nationalist Dele-gation.   Immigration of tuberculous soldiers.   Land for soldiers.India.Revival of Bombay strikes.   Passenger rates.    Sedition Bills.Foreign Colonies, &amp;c, in Africa.German Colonies.Government policy : debate in National Assembly. Views of Yon Kuehlmann. German Press and Colonial Empire.Liberia.   &apos;Wireless station at Monrovia.10  f33)7378-3,1   Pk       120   2/19   E &amp; S A
yBRITISH  EMPIRE   AND   AFRICA  REPORT.SELF-GOVERNING  DOMINIONS.CANADA.Death of Sir W. Laurier. Sir Wilfrid Laurier, Leader of the Opposition in the Dominion Parliament, died at Ottawa on February 17th. Arrangements have been completed for a State funeral. Parliament will open ou February 20th, but will adjourn after the Speech from the Throne until February 24th as a mark of respect to the memory of the dead statesman. The body of Sir W. Laurier will lie in state in the Senate Chamber after the opening of Parliament till the morning of February 22nd.Opposition Leader. The choice of a leader of the Liberal Party in succession to Sir Wilfrid Laurier may, it is stated at Ottawa, be deferred until the meeting of the National Liberal Convention. Amongst those mentioned as possibly leading the Opposition in the House of Commons are Mr. &quot;W. S. Fielding, Mr. Rodolphe Lemieux, Mr. Mackenzie King, or Mr. W. M. Martin, the present Premier of Saskatchewan.- War Claims. According to a statement issued at Ottawa the Dominion&apos;s war expenditure to the end of last mouth reached S 1,122,000,000 and the claims for-damages against the enemy to -f 18,000,000.Deportation of Aliens. The Executive of the Great War Veterans Association brought to the attention of the Government a number of resolutions forwarded by branches of that organisation, principally in the West, urging the deportation of undesirable aliens, the examination of those suspected of enemy sympathies, and the curtailment of the civil rights of those who are permitted to remain in the country.The Acting Prime Minister (Sir Thomas White) has replied as follows : &quot;-Some of the resolutions, while embodying ideas which have our general support and sympathy, present great practical difficulties in carrying out, particularly at the present time.&quot;The Governments attitude towards the general situation regarding enemy aliens as it now exists is briefly : &quot; &apos; With respect, to interned enemy aliens, the deportation of those who are dangerous and undesirable is being carried out as speedily as international conditions permit. Pending the conclusion of the Peace Conference, this work must necessarily be slow, as in addition to the shortage of shipping there is the fact that the enemy countries are still closed except to the admission of such of their nationals as it is possible to arrange for. The Order-in-Council authorising the internment of all enemy aliens who are dangerous or a menace to the peace of the community is still in full force and operation.il&apos; --.___Sir Thomas White added : &quot; The Government have brought to the attention of the Prime Minister and his colleagues at the Peace Conference the question of the provision of shipping and passports for those alien residents who desire to return to their countries at their own expense, but who are unable to do so owing to their inability to obtain transportation.&quot; The Government have also requested the Prime Minister to have the Conference specially-consider the stipulations which may be necessary in the Peace Treaty in order to enable the deportation from Canada of all dangerous or undesirable persons of enemy nationality.&quot;As to the measures in actual operation in the Dominion, an official statement has been issued in which it is pointed out that special regulations have been enacted by the Governor-in-Council under the powers conferred by the War Measures Act of 1914, &apos;&apos; and there is now in force a law whereby, with respect to localities to be designated
by the Minister of Justice, power is conferred upon County and District Court judges, and in Quebec upon the judges of the Supreme Court, to direct the internment as -prisoners of war of all persons of alien enemy nationality residing or being within the designated localities.[farms for Soldiers. In order to provide for the immediate wants of returned soldiers who desire agricultural land, the Government have adopted appropriate legislation under the War Measures Act. This will be followed by a Bill to be introduced into Parliament.By the provisions of a new Order-in-Council the Soldier Settlement Board is in a &quot;position to take action regarding the men who are ready to take up a farm, this season. The Board is vested with authority and provided with funds for the purchase of land suited to the immediate settlement of soldiers. It is also empowered to purchase stock, ecpripinent and building material for sale to soldier settlers.The total of the amounts granted to any one soldier may reach $8,000, but the Board seeks payment by the soldier of 10 per cent, of the land value, which would make the total advances S7,500. The Board divides the advances into the following maxima: Land, $5,000; stock and equipment, S2,000 ; permanent improvements. 81,000.All such stock, equipment and building materials will be purchased by the Board, and sold to the settlers at cost pric^, and it is the intention of the Board to allow the settler to select his own land, subject to supervision.Before the assistance of the Board can be obtained a soldier must pass a qualification council, which determines whether or not the applicant is reasonably certain to succeed as a farmer.   These councils are established in every province.The Board will take every precaution that the soldier shall not be the victim of aggressive or unscrupulous salesmanship.Sale of Liquor to Soldiers. rPenalties for the sale of liquor to officers or men in uniform in the Dominion are contained in the provisions of an Order-in-Council just passed. The Order provides that any person other than a medical officer or practitioner selling liquor to soldiers in uniform shall be tried by military court-martial, and on conviction he will be liable to a term of imprisonment not exceeding 12 months or a fine of $300, or both. The Order-in-Council draws attention to the fact that in view of the great number of troops returning to Canada, it is necessary in the interests of the soldiers themselves, as well as necessary for discipline, that further regulations be made in regard to furnishing troops with liquor.- Discussing the Order-in-Council preventing the sale of liquor to soldiers in uniform, the Minister of Militia (Major-Genera! S. C. Mewburn) stated that so far from it being a reflection on the men, it was passed at the instance of many of them for their own protection. &quot; The Order was designed to apply particularly to the operations of bootleggers,&quot; said the Minister. &quot;I have had many complaints about these people meeting trains on their way through and selling poisonous liquids, such as &apos; high-wines&apos; or wood-alcohol. Several cases of serious illness have resulted among the troops.&quot;The Minister added : &quot; I intend stamping out the illegal trafficking in bad liquor at the expense of the men&apos;s health and best interests. The action was taken largelj?-at the instance of the-Great War Veterans.&quot;Proliibition in Quebec-The Quebec Opposition Leader (Mr. Arthur Sauve) has given notice to present in the Legislature an amendment to the prohibition law. If it is adopted the amendment will allow the manufacture and sale of light wines and beer, containing 5 per cent, alcohol, in Quebec Province.Labour and Extremists. The President of the Trades and Labour Council (Mr. Tom Moore), speaking at Montreal last week, stated that he was opposed to all extremists. He had no sympathy with the proposal that the workers should go back to home industry. &quot; The problem is not to decentralise industry hy taking it back to the homes,&quot; he said, &quot; but to centralise all industries so that they can be taken out of the homes and carried out under the best sanitary conditions and general safety.&quot; He favoured a scheme of Industrial Councils and any plans for bringing the employer and the employed -closer together. Reforms, he said, lay largely through the trade unions, and the day was coming when the producer would be recognised and given, a share in, the production.
Labour Conditions. The conditions of the labour market in Canada, so far as skilled workers are concerned, continue satisfactory, according to reports received by the Department of Labour at Ottawa, The information received indicates that less than 3 per cent, of this class of labour is unemployed. The conditions in unskilled labour are less satisfactory but are believed to be improving. The Department-is now engaged in gathering reliable data on this matter, on the completion of which process they will be better able to meet the situation.Revenue and Debt. The current Revenue of the Dominion for the 10 months ended January 31st, reached a total in excess  of $ 249,000,000, and the total -expenditures, exclusive of outlay on the war, aggregated nearly 8179,000,000.   The war expenditure during the same period totalled nearly $245,000,000.   The net debt of the Dominion at the end of January was slightly in excess of $1,302,000,000.AUSTRALIAN&apos; COMMONWEALTH.Mr. Huglies and Peace Conference. The Executive of the National Federation has passed a resolution recording its appreciation of the services of Mr. Hughes in the cause of civilisation generally, and of the Peace Conference, also asserting that posterity will gratefully acknowledge its indebtedness fo Mr. Hughes for his efforts to keep Australia free and white.Influenza: Results of Epidemic. According to reports published in the Press, influenza in Victoria is increasing in virulence, and the whole State is now affected. The mortality in Victoria for all cases is now 10 per cent., and 40 per cent, in pneumonic cases. In New South Wales and South Australia there is only a small proportion of cases, and the former State is establishing a moratorium, while granting half-rent and board to employees thrown out of work by the epidemic. Inoculation, enforced masking, the prohibition of public meetings, and the isolation of patients are promising to save New South Wales from the full severity of the epidemic. -Coastal shipping is coming to a standstill on account of the seamen demanding increased wages in consequence of the epidemic.Increase in Cost of Living. The Commonwealth Statistician shows that the increase on the cost of living in Australia during the war, including house rent, has averaged 19&apos;5 per cent., and excluding house rent, 34&apos;5 per cent.Repatriation. A review of repatriation for the nine months ended in December shows the following results :: There have been 33,516 registrations for employment; 26,557 positions found ; 6,693 registrations for vocational training. The sum of 358,304L has been advanced as gifts, including sustenance; 133,9221. on loan ; and 11,781L in general assistance.NEW ZEALAND.Enlistment Figures. -The Press have published official figures in the Dominion -showing that the total number of men mobilised was 124,211 11 &apos;4 per cent, of the population and 50&apos; 5 per cent, of the total number of men of military age. The total&quot; number sent oversea was 100,444 9&quot;3 per cent, of the population. Voluntary recruits numbered 91,941 74 per cent, of the total number of men mobilised. New Zealanders who enlisted in the British and Australian Forces numbered 3,370. &apos;lhe establishment abroad on November 12th last was 24T138 men. The total wastage of men who embarked was 41,435, including 16,302 dead and 356 prisoners. The casualties at Anzae during April and May were 2,800; at Gallipoli in the August offensive, 4,000 ; in Samoa, 8,000; in the British offensive of August to November, 9,000.
Cadet Training. It is stated in the Press that owing to the large percentage of medical rejections of candidates for the New Zealand Expeditionary Force, the Govern-ment will establish a system of cadet training, which will aim at producing physical, mental, and moral rather than military fitness. Compulsion will be limited to 70 hours yearly.SOUTH AFRICA.Republicanism : Debate in House of Assembly. There was a large attendance in the House of Assembly on February 11th for the debate on Republicanism. The Leader of the Opposition (Sir Thomas Smartt) was loudly cheered on rising to submit a motion condemning republican propaganda. He quoted Mr. HofmeyFs - declaration that. Afrikanders had an actual interest in the maintenance of the British Empire and the protection of a powerful British fleet, and asked &quot; AVhere would the liberties of South Africa be to-day but for the British Navy ? &quot; Sir Thomas Smartt went on to say that English-speaking people at the National Convention had accepted the assurances of the Dutch, and these assurances had been sealed by the blood of both races. The British entered the Union knowing that they were in a minority and trusting implicitly to the pledges of Mr. Steyn and others. Nevertheless, some of the Dutch had mournfully failed and embarked on a policy of betrayal of the basest possible character. The Leader of the Opposition proceeded to refer humorously to the wild-goose chase on which the Nationalist deputation was going to Europe and said it would meet with a well-deserved fate. Sir Thomas Smartt emphasised the fact that General Hertzog had allowed himself to be jockeyed into republicanism and hatred of the British by Tielman Roos and a section of his party. The old cursed race hatred was being fanned, and all this turmoil had been caused by wounded vanity and disappointed ambition. It was about time, he said, that this campaign was stopped by the Government, and he proceeded to comment upon the Nationalists sailing to Europe with Government passports protected by the British Navy, to ask President Wilson to break up the Union of South Africa.Sir Thomas Smartt paid a tribute to Great Britain&apos;s intensely generous policy throughout to South Africa, mentioning the splendid way in which the Imperial Government had allowed the Dominions to participate so largely in the Peace Conference. Sir Thomas Smartt then asked, &quot; Who are the people who are trying to break up the Union? They are. a section of one section of the people of South Africa. Are the millions of natives and hundreds of thousands of coloured people to be ignored in such a decision ? Must the English sit still and utter no warning against it, against those who did all they could to assist the enemy &apos;?.&quot; The danger of civil strife and bloodshed was appalling, he said, if this protest were not made and the great assistance of the sister Dominions invoked. &quot; Are not Australia, New Zealand and India,&quot; Sir Thomas Smart asked, &quot; interested in the tremendous strategic importance of South Africa in the Southern Seas ? &quot; The sooner the scales fell from the eyes of the Nationalists regarding their policy of gaining political power the better. The sooner they realised the impossibility&quot;of Republican aims and that all the power available would be against them, the better. The Nationalist campaign of treachery and calumny must now be stopped and all necessary powers taken. &quot;Every Englishman and every loyal Dutchman,&quot; Sir Thomas Smartt declared, &quot; will light to the last to maintain the Union, and so we invoke all the power of South Africa and the Empire to maintain the South African Constitution.&quot; Sir Thomas Smartt concluded by reading the motion of which he had given notice on January 22nd, viz., &quot; That this House condemns the agitation now being carried on for the dissolution of the Union and the severance of the connection at present existing between South Africa and. Great Britain, and further expresses its opinion that such agitation if persisted in, will lead to civil war and bloodshed in South Africa.&quot;The Acting-Premier (Mr. Malan) then moved the following amendment : &quot; That this House while welcoming all constitutional development which will make the Union in the fullest sense a self-governing Dominion, emphatically condemns the present agitation for the disruption of the Union, and the severance of the connection, between South Africa and Britain, and also repudiates all attempts to invoke inter-ference from any outside Power.   The House wishes to record its opinion that,737S-3a B
notwithstanding all the protestations to the contrary, this agitation is in its essence subversive of the fundamental principles of the constitution as laid down bv the South Africa Act, which was framed by the representatives of, and freely accepter! by the people of South Africa, and sounds a grave warning that this agitation is against the true interests of South Africa, and if continued will inevitably lead to a state of unrest and racial friction in which civil strife may easily be engendered.&quot;Mr. Malan said that in his opinion it was essential that the House should express itself, with no uncertain voice, before the Nationalist deputation, which was demanding independence, left South Africa. Parliament was the only body which had the right to decide on the question. Moreover, Parliament should speak out, because those whodoved South Africa realised that the great expectations of the Union were in clanger of being wrecked. Mr. Malan strongly emphasised the basic idea underlyinp-tke establishment of the Union, which was the agreement between the Dutch&quot;and English-speaking peoples to regard South Africa as their Fatherland, on a basis of equal rights. Under the Union they had the destin;/ of South Africa in their own hands, South Africa had independence to-da3T, and it was not necessary for any deputation to go to the Peace Conference or to Mr. Wilson to ask for further freedom. Since the Union, South Africa&apos;s relationship to the outside world had greatly improved. At the Peace Conference, representatives of South Africa were sitting with represen-tatives of Canada and Australia with the same right of say in the discussion, while the Premier of the Union could enter into direct communication with the Premier of Great Britain. The possible impression that South Africa was merely a kind of Crown Colony had been altogether removed. - If the League of Nations were estab-lished, South Africa would claim the same-representation in it as she had to-day at the Peace Conference. How could their position be better, if they were an independent republic ? Mr. Malan claimed that not only had South Africa&apos;s external relationship improved since the Union, but that also internally the Union had been a success.General Hertzog claimed, Mr. Malan observed, that the fact that Natal did not desire to leave the Union should not shackle the liberty of the Free State in renouncing the Union. General Hertzog thereby enunciated a fundamental error, inasmuch as Natal had as little right to break up the Uniomas the Free State had. No integral part of the Union had the right to separate from the Union as a whole. It was not even, a question for the majority. The Union could only be broken up by the consent of the whole. Mr. Malan admitted that Dutch-speaking South Africans, especially those horn under a Republic, could not be expected to have the same love for the British connection as the British. Nevertheless, Avhat was to be expected was that General Hertzog and his followers should stand by their oath. &quot; We enjoy,&quot; Mr. Malan exclaimed, &quot; the protection of the British connection. We shall also carry out &quot;our obligations under it.&quot; Nobody seemed to know, Mr. Malan continued, why a Nationalist deputation should proceed to England to claim a return of rights or to plead that there had been a violation of rights. Originally, the Nationalists had pinned their faith to President Wilson&apos;s words regarding violated rights. They then discovered that they had mane a mistake, inasmuch as no rights of South Africa had been taken away. Hence their new policy was to split up the Union. Mr. Malan said that he wondered what General Hertzog and his party would say if the English-speaking South Africans, or the natives, or the Indians approached Downing Street, asking the Imperial Government to interfere in the affairs of South Africa.The Leader of the Nationalists (General Hertzog) in his speech quoted at great length The Commonwealth of Nations by Mr. Lionel Curtis, saying that the- author affirmed that the ultimate destiny of the Dominions was made or marred in London. General Hertzog denied that the state of South Africa had been improved by the Union. -If the Peace Conference finished to-morrow their subjection would remain. He argued at some length that there had been no attempt to break up the Union, and he opposed anyT reversion to pre-Union&quot; conditions. However, he claimed separate liberty for the Free State and the dropping of the British connection, and he declared that America had entered a federation as Free States, but that the Transvaal and the Free State had-entered the Union as slaves. England, he said, took away the freedom of the Free State in 1902. To-day she could give them freedom. The Union Parlia-ment could not give them freedom, therefore they went to Europe where they could procure it., -Reverting to the Peace Conference, General Hertzog declared that General Smuts represented merely Great Britain and not South Africa, while General Botha&apos;s
attitude was that the Union must remain, because it bad sufficient freedom,   What the Nationalists wanted was freedom and a free Republic for South Africa.On the debate being resumed next day, Mr. Patrick Duncan pointed out that it was impossible to gi,ve back freedom to the Free State. No more fitting restitution could-have been made than the Act. of Union. A reversion to pre-Union conditions was impossible. The Constitution was the basis of the coining South African nationality, whereas General Hertzog would throw the country back into the old confusions, the old chaos, and the old conflicts. The day of choice for South Africa would not come till it had solved the question whether it would be one people or two peoples. The Hertzogites were prepared to break up the Union in order to get illusory freedom.The Leader of the Labour Party (Colonel Ores well) moved a long amendment to the effect that the House recognised, firstly, that the status of the Union as a self-governing Dominion within the British Commonwealth secured to the peoples the fullest power to deal with all questions affecting their national development and also security against external danger ; secondly, that the status established by the South Africa Act was accepted by leading representatives of the two races as the settlement of racial quarrels disastrously affecting progress and peace for over a century ; thirdly, that the permanent welfare of the people- demanded the unremitting attention.of the Parliament and people to grave domestic, social, economic, and land problems. The amendment proceeded : &quot; The House accordingly records the conviction that the present movement for the abrogation of the South Africa Act and the disturbing of the existing status of the Union, having particular regard to the circumstances in which the movement originated, will inevitably endanger the country&apos;s pieace and result in the continued neglect of pressing domestic concerns with disastrous consequences.&quot;Colonel Creswell attributed the strength of the Separatist movement to a wide-spread feeling of dissatisfaction that the country&apos;s affairs were not attended to in Parliament: It was said that the Union was a failure. He answered that the Union had not been given a fair chance. In answer to General Hertzog, he contended that the British connection really enabled South Africa to look all the better after her own affairs. He regretted, however, Sir Thomas Smartt&apos;s references 1o Canada and Australia, and he affirmed that Sir Thomas&apos;s assertion that the British would bring in other Dominions to wallop the secessionists would tremendously strengthen the secession movement. Colonel Creswell contended that South Africa had greater power to deal with internal affairs than she could have as an independent republic, instancing the deportation of nine Johannesburg strike leaders in 1914-. He concluded with an appeal to fulfil their destiny as a bulwark of civilisation, and to say that neither the, Dutch nor the English had a right of priority in the countiy. *Dr. Malan, the leader of the Cape Province Nationalists, who was elected to Parliament last month for Calvinia, contended that in the by-elections the Republican movement had received great support and was therefore not concerned about the decision of a dying Parliament. If the Union was to be destroyed, it would only be to build on a better foundation. The present foundation was one of violence and robbery ; they wanted a foundation of freedom, liberty and righteousness^Mr. J. X. Merriman showed that the Union Parliament had greater freedom than the Transvaal Republican Volksraad, and asked what tangible advantage could emerge from a Republic. The on!y effect would be to break the country into two sections. Moreover, the Nationalists left natives and coloured people entirely out of account.The debate was continued till late in the evening, when Mr. J agger charged the Nationalists with being traitors, and characterised their attempt to invoke interference by an outside Power as treason. He predicted that, if a crisis came, the loyal Dutch in their thousands would flock to the side of the English.On the -resumption of the debate on February 13th, the Minister of Justice (Mr. de Wet) affirmed that although the Nationalists claimed the secession movement to be constitutional, it Avas clearly revolutionary. Great Britain, he added, could not restore to the Boer Republics their former independence, as the Union, of which the Transvaal and the Free State were but parts, also had a say therein.Replying to Dr. Malan, the Nationalist member for Calvinia, Mr. de Wet declared there was nothing to prevent the Union having its own flag as it had already had at sea. There was a very real danger, he said, of&apos; the Nationalists&apos; speeches inciting the less educated ,of their followers.
sOn February 14th the Minister of Railways and Harbours (Mr. Burton) continued the debate and condemned the misrepresentation spread in country districts by the Nationalists who, he said, referring to the relationship of South Africa and the Empire, had asked, &quot; Was South Africa going to lie down in a bed made by British Ministers ? &quot; &quot; No,&quot; Mr. Burton said, &quot; we are going to lie down in a bed made for us by our own Ministers, with a Share not only in proportion to the importance of our status as a Dominion, but also on a basis which really gives South Africa an advantage.&quot; Admitting that South Africa was technically committed to war when Great Britain declared war, Mr. Burton emphasised the point that the Union Parliament could always have said to what extent it could take action, and Parliament did take action.&quot; Air. Burton commented on General Hertzog&apos;s statement on Tuesday that he only agreed to the Union to minimise slavery. Mr. Burton added that if General Hertzog went into the Convention with this reservation, then he grossly deceived those who went in with him in -good faith. The attitude of the Nationalists was driving the peoples further .apart, and the result was the destruction of the confidence of the English-speaking people in their good faith and sense of honour. The Nationalists proposed to treat the Constitution as a scrap of paper.The Nationalist mission was foredoomed to failure, he said, because its members had broken their word. The Nationalists had lost a golden opportunity of strengthen-ing the position of South Africa, and had deliberately cut themselves off from a glorious community of sacrifice and -suffering. &quot; We shall allow,&quot; the Minister concluded, &quot;no tampering with our rights under the Constitution, which is the best piece of work ever done in building up the people of South Africa.&quot;The debate was eventually adjourned.Republicanism: Debate in the Senate. The Government Resolution (see preceding-paragraph) was adopted in the Senate by 23 votes to 3. The sitting of February 14th Was rendered notable by a declaration from the President (Senator Reitz) in replying to a Senator who had put a question concerning the presence of the President at the Nationalist gathering at Stellenbosch (vide Report No. 106). Senator Reitz in the course of his observations said : &quot; As President of the Senate, I have undertaken to conduct the proceedings of this House impartially and irrespective of- political parties.&quot; But I.have not placed my soul in bondage; I am a free citizen of the Union, and as such I also claim the right of freedom of action in my private affairs and unofficial capacity. As former President of one Republic which lost its independence, and as ex-State Secretary of the other, I should be untrue to my past political career and to my conscience if I did not,- now that I am publicly challenged, admit that I am still Republican at heart, and that I should welcome a Republic in South Africa, provided it be obtained by peaceful, or, in other words, constitutional, means.&quot;The Nationalist Delegation. The Nationalist delegation to Europe were prevented from sailing by the Durham Castle on February loth owing to the decision of the crew to strike if General Hertzog and the Nationalists sailed on the ship. Many of the men contended that the Nationalists had favoured the enemy. Strong- repre-sentations were made to the men by the Government, the Leader of the Labour Party (Colonel Ores well), the Leader of the Opposition (Sir Thomas Smartt), Trade Union representatives and others, but the men maintained their attitude and the ship sailed without the delegation. The loyal sections of the community deplored the action of the men, which it was realised would play into the hands of the disloyal and pro-German sections who could thus denounce British interference and intolerance. The Admiral saw General Hertzog on February 17th and offered to convey the delegates on H.M.S. Minerva, which is under orders to sail for England. The Governor-General has informed the Secretary of State that the position will be greatly eased by this offer.The matter was referred to at the commencement in the House of Assembly, when the Minister for Railways and Harbours (Mr. Burton) stated the Government considered it desirable that no obstacles, should be placed in the way of the delegation proceeding.Immigration of tubercidous Soldiers.  With reference to the immigration into South Africa of soldiers and sailors suffering- from tuberculosis (a subject which has provided capital for Nationalist attacks on the Union Government) the Acting Prime Minister (Mr. Malan) read a statement in the House of Assembly on February 13th, denying that 1 he Government had decided to waive the regulations on the subject. He stated that since March 1916 when Sir Rider Haggard made representations to the Government, only 19 men suffering from tuberculosis had received permits
to enter the Union and that.no more such permits would be issued. Mr. Malan added that neither he himself nor any Government department had received any communication from thelmperial Government on the subject.Land for Soldiers. It is stated that the Natal Government intend to purchase land in Northern Natal and Zululand to provide 105 allotments of from 400 to 700 acres each, for the settlement of returned soldiers, a number of whom are already training at Cedara Agricultural College.INDIA.(Excluding External Affairs, which are dealt with in the Eastern Report.)Revival of Bombay Strikes. It is reported from Bombay that on February 3rd the employees at four mills struck because on receiving their wages for December they were not paid the bonus promised in the terms of settlement of the recent dispute. There has also arisen a demand for a readjustment of the bonus. The millowners have issued a notice stating in more definite terms the scale of bonus y-hich will be paid with the January wages, but it is not supposed that this will influence the strikers. Some 15 mills, with about 15,000 workers, are now involved in the strike.It is asserted in the Press that the resumption of the strike will probably reproduce the insanitary conditions which accentuated the cholera epidemic.Sedition Bills. It is stated in the Press that a considerable agitation, accompanied by gross misrepresentation, is taking place against the proposed legislation on the Sedition Committee Report (vide Report No. 10-1).FOREIGN COLONIES,   &amp;c. IN AFRICA.GERMAN COLONIES.Government Policy : Debate in National Assembly. The German Prime Minister (I I err Scheidemann) in the programme of Government action, introduced into the sitting of the National Assembly at Weimar, outlined as the second item &quot; the restoration of German colonial territory.&quot;The Minister for Foreign Affairs (Count Brockclorff-Rantzau) in his speech in the National Assembly on February 14th, is reported by German Wireless to have said :  &quot; Just as little could Germany enter the League of Nations without colonies as without a mercantile fleet. According to Mr. Wilson&apos;s programme, colonial questions are to find a broad-minded and absolutely impartial settlement. . In the sense of that programme we await the handing back of our colonial possessions which we have had taken from us, partly in contravention of International Treaties, and partly under threadbare pretexts. We are prepared to negotiate regarding the cession of this or that colony, but only as the legitimate owners.&quot; Future colonial pobcy is to be one of more humane treatment of the natives. In this direction, we must admit, we have made mistakes. . The activity of the missions which Germany formerly had, and which have unfortunately been severely reduced by the war, must, in the interests of the natives, be assured. In this connection we agree with the idea of international control over the tropical colonies, under the condition that all colonial Powers are subject to it, and that Germany takes a proportionate part in the administration and in the products of the colonies.&quot;
\LIBERIA.Wireless Station at Monrovia. The Liberian Government have reopened the German Wireless Station at Monrovia, and operations were begun, under Liberian Government control and with a Liberian staff, on February 12th.,r ,:v In the course of the debate in the Assembly Herr Haase, the Independent Socialist, was reported by ReuteFs Basle correspondent on February 17th to have declared, &quot; We have no need of colonies.&quot;Views of Von Kuehlmann. Sir W. Townley informed the Foreign Office ou February 12th that Baron von Kuehlmann was at The Hague, and in discussing the subject of the German Colonies, he [said that Germany wotdd be prepared to give up Tsingtau and the South Sea Islands, but that Colonies in West and East Africa were essential : the former because of supplies of palm oil and the latter for purposes of emigration. Von Kuehlmann expressed his conviction that no German statesman would dare to sign a peace which entailed &quot;a surrender of all German Colonies.German Press on Colonial Empire. The Frankfurter Zeiiung on January 30th complained that it was only the German Colonies that were going to be subjected to the control of the League of Nations. The journal continued : &quot; Indeed, there is only one chance for us, besides Wilson&apos;s desire to refer the question to the League of Nations, and this lies in the disunity of those who want to divide their spoils among themselves. But we must, unfortunately, reckon with the probability of the pre-liminary Paris Conference being able to settle the claims and conflicting interests of the Great Powers and other nations who have put in colonial demands if only to avoid a settlement by the future League of Nations, which Wilson is aiming at-and of our being faced by the Entente at the general Peace Conference with an irrefutable programme of colonial distribution, perhaps with a few small concessions in our favour.&quot;The Frankfurter Zeitung declares the right of Germany to a colonial Empire, and that Germany will never enter a League of Nations, except on an equal footing. A colonial law that favoured others and disregarded Germany would be a mockery of the spirit of a league and could not be accepted by Germany.

</content>
</cab>
