<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/228/7 images: 65-70</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL



HIS  DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



COPY NO 81



CABINET



Lpjcpp GOVERNMENT FINANCE:   THE JULY STATEMENT

Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Environment



The Ministerial St



Committee on Economic Strategy, Sub-



Committee on Local Goverrunep^f  (LG)) discussed my proposals for

the  1991/92  Local  AuthorityO0*J*ence  Settlement  for  England and



the   review   of   the communii



large,    on   4    July (E(LG)(90)



2nd meeting). This note briefly^^^^arises our conclusions. I

propose to announce the conclusions/   a Parliamentary statement

on 19 July.  //



Spending and central support



2.     in recent years there has been substanti Dwth in local



authority spending. In the current year local airaSorities have

budgeted to spend  36.6 billion, an increase of 14% 1989/90

following a 9% increase in that year. Such rapid\^tt^!yth in

spending   cannot   be   justified   and   local   authorities nH^gk^play



1



S7/



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



their   part   in   restraining   expenditure   if   we   are   to maintain

;onomic   progress   and   limit   the   burden   of   local   and national

it ion.



this background and following discussion in E(LG), I

propos^ ^\announce that I consider that local authorities in

England sh^old spend no more than  39 billion in 1991/92. This is



^?//  



a substantiaY/ 9% increase over the equivalent figure for 1990/91

and 7% above M.ocal authority budgeted spending for 1990/91. It

is an achievable level which takes account on the one hand of

proposed spendingKmrL^local authorities in 1990/91, spending

pressures from demographic change and new burdens, and pay and

price pressures; and ^/a^/Xthe other hand of the scope for

efficiency and other savinas^v authorities



4. On Aggregate External Fir^jnj2t^ (AEF) - the total of business

rates, specific grants, speciai^^j^ants and general Revenue

Support Grant - I propose to announa^^total provision of  26.05



billion for England in 1991/92. Thi^^S an increase of  2.950

billion or 12.8% over this year&apos;s provision and nearly  2 billion

higher than provided for in the Public Expenditure White Paper.

E(LG) noted that the substantial increase i^AER will constrain

severely the scope for other increases in spenQ  j )in the public

expenditure survey.



CONFIDENTIAL




m



CONFIDENTIAL



5.     Taken together,  these figures mean that the Community Charge

&gt;r  Standard  Spending  in   1991/92  will  be  about    379,   a little

re   the   actual   average   charge   for   1990/91   of    363 before

I believe that these decisions put local authorities in

m to deliver an actual average charge in 1991/92 close

to thi^%*el.



6. The Y^^V&gt; Authority Associations have told me that they

expect spending to be around  40.7 billion (excluding community

care). That cannot be justified, following as it does several

years of large ir^rei^ses in spending. I therefore propose to

announce that I sha^^))^e my powers to cap charges vigorously

next year should that^i&amp;oke necessary. The strength of these

powers has been shown in tnjeotecent Court cases, and next year I

shall be able to cap exce^y^Aincreases in budgets as well as

budgets which are excessive in\absolute terms.



7. I propose to use my power on ^xp^fisive increases to limit to

about the rate of inflation, year on^^: increases in spending

for those with budgets above but near tk&gt; their Standard Spending

Assessment (SSA), and to limit the largest overspenders to

tighter increases. I believe that we must (j^l^Qbust in our de-

termination to use these powers and to make ou^ir^tentions clear

in advance, with the aim of deterring authorities M?&amp;$\increasing

spending and charges unjustifiably. It is obviously j^p^^rable to



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



produce the necessary self discipline on the part of authorities,

ther than to have to use the capping powers themselves - though

should not shrink from that if necessary.



nity charge review



8. We hav^/also looked at possible changes in the way which the

community chafrgte affects individuals. Many of the proposals put

to us, for instance reducing the liability of non-working wives,

were neither justified in principle nor good value for money. I

shall however anr{&lt;^uni)e^ a package of measures which will give

further help to tho^^jtej^ticularly affected by the change to the

community charge.    In suimaxv these are:



recalculation of trar^L^onal relief from 1991/92 to limit

losses from the structur^^dhange to  2 rather than the

present    3,   a  moratorium  on(XWji\ planned    13   per recipient



withdrawal of relief



in 1991/92 ^d 1992/93,   and extension of



relief for a further 2 years until^29^C4/95. As a result many

couples will be  78 better off itt 1991/92 than they had

expected. The changes will cost an extra  310m (a doubling of

relief in 1991/92) and help 4 million n^^^Qipients as well

as the existing 7h million;



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



limit  withdrawal  of  the  area  safety net  to   25  an adult

where   it   would   otherwise   have   been   larger.       This costs

4 million in 1991/92 and is included within the AEF figure

aragraph 4;



J^peopl



e   who    &apos;live   above   the   shop&apos;    by   making the



business^^Wpe transitional arrangements more generous from

April 1991\&gt;for small composite hereditaments. Their maximum

increase in business rates will be limited to 10% plus the

rate of inflati(jjn7^)rather than the present 15%;



prescribe lower^niicxiinum standard charge multipliers from

April 1991 for some hara^iit categories of people. Local

authorities have discrete set lower multipliers but have



not been using it appropria^e&amp;yO This change will help people

such as: clergymen, teacher s(^^^^?vicemen and others whose

accommodation is provided with tt&gt;^pgb but are buying a house



for their retirement; those who ha^Ej/a  empty ,granny flat&apos; in

their home; those who find a property difficult to sell; and

those who have a flat over a shop which^cannot be let for

security or other reasons;



improve the presentation of the community (d^pk$^e bill to

make it clearer which authority in an area/fears the

responsibility for high charges.



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



Conclusion



believe that this is a package which balances the interests

B!ryice provision, chargepayers and the national taxpayer. It

off&amp;&amp;C?ihe prospect of average community charges at near to this

year&apos; sC^^k^s in real terms (and lower in some areas) and it

improves tra^effect of the charge on individuals, particularly

the llh million who will benefit from the improvement in

transitional rtelief.



CP



Department of the Environment

16 July 1990



CONFIDENTIAL





</content>
</cab>
