<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/91/3 images: 33-42</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

CC(8^W

Concl1%y^

COPY NO

CABINET

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet

held at 10 Downing Street on

TUESDAY 1 NOVEMBER 1988

at 9.30 am

^ PRESENT

|Ab Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP

Prime Minister

The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe

Secretary cf State  for Foreign a^^^

Commonwealth Affairs 4^0^.

The Rt Hon Lord Mackay of Clashfern^^ ^

Lord Chancellor

The Rt Hon Peter Walker MP

Secretary of State for Wales

The Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP

Secretary of State for Employment

The Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP

Secretary of State for the Environment

The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker MP

Secretary of State for Education

! and Science

The Rt Hon John MacGregor MP

Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries

and Food

The Rt Hon John Moore MP

Secretary of State for Social Security

The Rt Hon The Lord Belstead

Lord Privy Seal

The Rt Hon John Major MP

Chief Secretary, Treasury

The Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP

Chancellor of the Exchequer

.The Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP

^Secretary of State for the Home Department

The Rt Hon George Younger MP

Secretary of State for Defence

The^R^kon Tom King MP

Sec M^Wof State for Northern Ireland

The Rt^Hl^Lord Young of Graffham

Secreta^^B^rjBtate for Trade and Industry

The Rt Hon Clarke QC MP

Secretary of^Rfc for Health

The Rt Hon Paul Ct^(%n MP

Secretary of State*&quot; for Transport

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP

Lord President of the Councii^

The Rt Hon Cecil Parkinson\^^|L

Secretary of State for Energ^^%^

The Rt Hon Antony Newton MP ^^.^A

Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaraj^^


THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT

Tjh^Ln David Wadding ton QC MP

arltamentary Secretary, Treasury

The Rt Hon Peter Brooke MP

Paymaster General

SECRETARIAT

Sir Robin Butler

Mr R T J Wilson (Items 2 and 3)

Mr A J Langdon (Item 1)

Mr G Monger (Items 2 and 3)

Mr S S Mundy (Item 1)

CONTENTS

:tem 1.	PARLIAMENTARY AFFA^j^k Health and Medic%Qpfc	Subject	Page 1 1

2.	1988 PUBLIC EXPENDITURE		3

3.	TOP-UP LOANS FOR STUDENTS		7




1. The Cabinet were informed of the business which was expected to be

taken in the House of Commons in the following week.

\

alth and

dicines

11

evious

ference:

(88) 26.1

^Tflp^&amp;CRETARY OF STATE FOR HEALTH said that the House of Commons would

i^ep&gt;\hat day consider amendments by the House of Lords which sought to

st^te^pyt from the Health and Medicines Bill the provisions to enable

charsM^o be imposed for dental examinations and sight tests for those

who c^wj^af f ord to pay.    Under the Government&apos;s proposals about

one-thiXrf^i the population would be exempt from the charges. This

would beva^ very difficult occasion since several dozen Government

backbenchers had gone on record as opposing such charges.    He had made

strenuous efforts to persuade them that people who stood to be charged

would not be detexred by the modest fees of  3.15 for dental

examinations any^abVut  10 for sight tests and that anyway many

opticians would\cJia    to absorb all or part of the cost of sight tests

in order to attra^itcwstom.    However, many of the Government supporters

opposed to charges^wgyjjc^not susceptible to reasoned argument on the

issue.   The savings ^fA&amp;Ki 4 million which would be generated by the

introduction of charg j jSra\e required to finance some extremely

worthwhile improvement^^j^ rimary health care services.    If the

Government should lose the^e&apos;te, however, he would wish to reflect on

the best response: an imm^wfaoe announcement either of offsetting

increases in other charges^t^erj^reductions in allocations to the health

authorities would cause furtrf f&amp;&lt;ttfficulties with the Government&apos;s

supporters. X^f?

In discussion, the following maw^^s were made:

a. The proposed charges would^^^pequired only from those who

could afford them.    All previou&lt;^J^ ence suggested that, apart

perhaps from some minor short-terA^rf&gt;ects, the imposition of

charges of the modest levels propovj^d would not deter people

generally from obtaining the medicaVcare which they needed.

Maintaining free examinations simply in order to protect the

irresponsible minority was redolent of thedependency culture.

b. It would be essential to make clear VJn_.aJwmce of the

Vote that, should the House of Commons refus ^tajagree to the

introduction of charges, there could be no q\Jg2&gt; dto of allocating

any further resources to the National Health S^ryjk^ (NHS) on top

of those already provided for in the proposed Au p jM^6tateuient.

The impact of the Autumn Statement would be seriotfZs^^yVJamaged if it

were thought that additional funding might be made ajrtH&amp;able to the

NHS because backbenchers on the Government&apos;s side hM^rfoVj supported

the Government.

THE PRIME MINISTER,, summing up the discussion, said that the^^MUenance

of the Government&apos;s strategy on public expenditure was of paramonW^y

importance.   The introduction of charges for dental examinations^aiidX\

sight tests was part of a carefully considered package under whicl^fhe^


money generated from charges would be used for highly desirable

^ improvements in the primary health care services.    In his opening

y\ speech in the debate, the Health Secretary should leave the House of

^?Kpmmons in no doubt that, if the Government were defeated, there could

&apos;VsPv no question of increasing the very generous settlement to the NHS in

^proposed Autumn Statement, and that the money which would have

C^AhfyA from the charges would accordingly be lost to the NHS.    If the

Sfinepkt^xxX. were then to lose the vote, the Secretary of State, in

ac^ ptj?*g the decision of the House, could refer back to that clear

stat^Mnt: he would then need to consider how to re-order priorities in

NHS ]S$^g?4mmes.

The^abinet -

Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of the

discussion.jand invited the Secretary of State for Health to

proceed aa!&gt;6?Wingly.


EXPENDMUR^

SURVEY

2.      The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chief Secretary,

Treasury (C(88) 13) on the 1988 Public Expenditure Survey.

j^THE CHIEF SECRETARY, TREASURY said that at their meeting in July,

Wmbinet had set the objectives of keeping as close as possible to the

^V^gting planning totals, and of ensuring that public spending as a

^oJ rtion of national  income continued to fall over the three Survey

^ears. At the start of the Survey total additions sought to programmes,

including those which had already been agreed, had been  8.7,   13.2 and

 18.7 billion in the three Survey years.    These additions were very

large but in the Survey discussions it had been possible, with the

cooperation^f colleagues, to reduce them substantially, while still

reflectiocWw Government&apos;s priorities.    The final outcome,  subject to

the agree J)SAf Cabinet, was  for additions  to programmes of  3.5,  6.8

and  11.3 l2B^Mp.    The prospective outturn of the planning total in

1988-89 was^^^t  153.6 billion,   3.3 billion below the plan.

As to individuHkn^fcBrammes, he had agreed an increase  in provision for

health of about ^^pL billion in  1989-90 and  1   l/2 billion in the

following year. programme would also benefit from new cost

improvement programlKk^^nd sales and a reduction in employers&apos;

superannuation contr^fcitj^s.    The result would be to increase resources

for the National Healt^^Ce^/ice (NHS)  in England alone by  1  3/4 billion

and over  2 billion respectively in the two years.    These were the

largest increases ever made for the NHS.    The Home Office would receive

increases of  246 million,   354 million and  324 million in the three

Survey years, mainly for prison building and prison manpower. For

housing,  receipts  from councilABm and other sales would yield some  4

billion over the three years, AJoAre would be additions to gross

capital spending on housing of a^P^w^O million a year.    There would

be a step change  in expenditure by^r^M^partment of Transport on the

national roads programme,  rising to ^p^Mcrease of  406 million in the

Department&apos;s programme  in  1991-92.    ^kjjit Department of Education and

Science he had agreed an addition of s^^^M per cent in the Science

Budget between 1988-89 and 1989-90, refl^R^B the Government&apos;s view of

priorities  for science and technology.    inHbv of Defence expenditure

would increase by  160 million,  610 millic^ a^^ 1024 million in the

three years,  and would also benefit from suba^mwial efficiency

savings.

These were substantial additions and had been possible within a

satisfactory overall settlement only because colleagues had helped by

reducing other bids and because of the savings resultinfl^rom the

Government&apos;s policies.    For example,  the fall in uneiA^k^ment had

produced considerable savings in the social security aTR|^^^oyment

programmes;  the right to buy policy had produced very lJ^g^jJeceipts;

the trading results of the nationalised industries had imw^^^; and

savings had been obtained on the Common Agricultural Policj^^MB

reduction of debt was also bringing substantial savings in &quot;^WT^

interest.    But notwithstanding these benefits,  difficult policJ^A

decisions had still been necessary on almost all programmes. yf[


The discussions on running costs had been difficult, and there would be

a higher increase in 1989-90 than in previous years.    But the

^ settlements were within the agreed objective of keeping the running

^^costs share of the planning total roughly constant.    He was grateful to

l^^st colleagues  for agreeing three year cash settlements on running

^^ ^JANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER,  after laying before the Cabinet the

p^^ss notices which it was proposed that the Treasury should publish

that afternoon, said that the outcome of the Chief Secretary&apos;s

discussion was an increase in programme spending of  3.5 billion in

1989-90 and  6.8 billion in 1990-91, compared with uncommitted reserves

in those ye^s of  7 billion and  10.5 billion.    Reserves should be at

least equ KB those fixed after last year&apos;s Survey,  at  3.5 billion,  7

billion a^|fu|^5 billion in the three years.    This meant that there

need be no ^flG^e i  the reserve,  or the planning total,  in 1989-90,

and an increl^e^P^ 3.3 billion in 1990-91.    The planning totals would

be  167.1 billKi,Btl79.4 billion and  191.6 billion in the three years.

The increase in^^^0kamme expenditure, at over 3 per cent a year

in real terms durW^Aie Survey period, was at the limit of what could

be afforded.    Neve^hAis,  the outcome was generally satisfactory. In

particular,  the Gove^H^ ^^&apos; s success  in avoiding an increase in the

planning total  in 198^-9fiJ^uld be welcomed by the markets, who were not

expecting so good a red^xt.

The Cabinet&apos;s objective of ensuring that public spending continued to

fall over the three Survey years as a proportion of national income had

proved to be demanding.    This was^hecause the ratio in the current year,

at 39 per cent, had proved fr^TO the lowest for twenty years, partly

because spending was turning ouUyif plans and partly because growth

in the economy had been higher th^^B^ected.    The outcome was however a

*     declining path for the ratio, whicmp&amp;phd fall to 39 J/4 per cent, 39

per cent and 38 per cent  in the VrelSurvey years.

The outcome on General Government Expeil^^^Me had also been helped by an

expected decline  in debt  interest.    Debt^^5 nent  in 1988-89 would be

about   10 billion,  and the Government woul^^^kin surplus even

disregarding privatisation receipts.    There^woujL clearly have to be

another substantial repayment next year. ^^^^

The Autumn Statement would also as usual contain the decisions on

National Insurance Contributions for next year, which he had agreed with

the Secretary of State for Social Security.    The only new element in the

decisions this year was that the Treasury Supplement, ^jf^ had been 18

per cent when the Government took office and now stooMM^Lper cent,

would be abolished.

THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the Autumn Stat^jj^r^ould

also contain his economic  forecasts.    Demand in the current^fiOT^iad

grown faster than expected.    It would however be useful to enyEme in

public discussion that  investment was growing twice as fast as J^^^L

consumption,  as it had done during the last five years.    Indeed ^P^^d

grown faster throughout the Government&apos;s period of office. Thi3^j^^^^


reverse of what had happened under the preceding Government. Inflation,

as measured by the Retail Price Index (RPI) was now expected to reach

k 6 I/4 per cent in the fourth quarter of the current year as against the

4 per cent earlier forecast.    Over half the deterioration was due to

J^ocreases in mortgage repayments.    The current account deficit for the

PV%r was now forecast at   13 billion.

next year, he expected growth to fall back, to 3 per cent.

Inflation would edge up in the first half of the year but decline again

to 5 per cent in the fourth quarter.    The main impact on the current

account of the measures recently taken would not be felt until 1990, and

he forecast a deficit of  11 billion next year.    The world outlook was

reasonably^hod, with a slight fall  in growth and a slight upturn in

inflatioiAjM^cted next year, but neither on such a scale as to cause

alarm.    TrWR^^preoccupation of the international markets  in the short

term would B^^^h the result and aftermath of the United States

Election and ?j^^kmight be some turbulence until they gained confidence

in the new AdmLsnation.

Altogether there va^eood prospect that the United Kingdom economy

would achieve a  1 scW^W^ding1 .    But it was essential to retain

international confid^^^j^gspecially to finance our trade deficit. This

required continued pursud^^f sound policies,  and especially control of

public expenditure.    TlreAutumn Statement would be a contribution to

this.

In discussion the following main points were made:

a. The Chief Secretary w%5^LDe congratu-lated on an outcome to

the Survey which was satisMR^^both economically and politically

and combined a satisfactory I^^Wment on overall expenditure with

a recognition of the Governmer^^Pl^orit ies.

b. The very substantial rece ipt^d^  the right to buy policy had

made a major contribution to the sTt^^^ftory outcome of the

Survey.    But the stock of cheap housWdW^r renting was being

reduced by the sale of council houses^EkaSto serious shortage could

develop.    This could become a s ignif icOTt^JBoblem in the medium

c. The inclusion of mortgage interest payments in the RPI raised

difficult questions.    It could be argued that increases in such

payments had a major effect on the ordinary househo^er. who would

therefore expect  them to be  in the Index.    Also t|BVl would

benefit  from a future fall in mortgage in teres t, ^MUiLing the

effect of the recent rise.    On the other hand,  it &quot;4^^^?ar tnat

the inclusion of mortgage interest payments in the ^^fl^ it an

incorrect measure of inflation and was not the practic^a pted in

most other countries.    It also led to the perverse resJS^^pmt

measures,  like the rise  in interest rates, which were ai S^pL

reducing inflation had as their first effect an increase ^-W^0^

published Index.    It would be difficult to make any change ^^^P^

RPI without the agreement of the RPI Advisory Committee.    It wouJk

5


probably be necessary at some time to raise again with the

k Committee the inclusion of mortgage interest payments.    This could

best be done when their exclusion would make no difference to the

Index.    Meanwhile the Secretary of State for Employment had agreed

^K^L      that when the RPI was published he would also state, for

^^^^^   information, what the figure would be if mortgage  interest payments

^khad not been included.    There was also a question whether the

^^^^resent composition of the Advisory Committee was appropriate.

d. The reduction below 40 per cent of the ratio of public

expenditure to Gross Domestic Product was a major achievement and

there was a case for drawing special attention to it in public

discus^^n.    But the level of the ratio depended on what happened

to ewwQic growth.    If that declined,  the ratio would probably

rise^M^^ was essential to avoid any sense that discipline could

be rell^^kj^^ On balance it seemed unwise to give undue prominence

to the ^j^^^k the ratio.

e. The h^Sd^^rel of increase in earnings was one of the least

satisfactory^^BK^res of the economy at present.    It was true that

unit labour C^4EV!^&gt; because of high productivity,  increased only

modestly in rec^^jS^rs.    But the record of our competitors was

better, with manyjJLing a fall in unit labour costs.    It was

important that increases in the pay round just starting should not

be excessive, and a number of difficult negotiations were in

prospect in the public sector.

THE PRIME MINISTER,  summing up th^^liscussion,  said that the Cabinet

congratulated the Chief Secreta^^M the outcome of the Survey. They

endorsed the agreements he had on individual programmes, and his

conclusions on running costs, and^HkJfc the estimated outturn on public

expenditure for  1988-89.    They alss^a^P^d with the recommendations made

by the Chancellor of the Exchequer a^to^bhe content of the Autumn

Statement, and noted that he would de^wd^kan oral statement in

Parliament that afternoon, with publica^^LpPof the  full printed version

on 8 November.    She would arrange for th J^Jk6 to be told that the

Cabinet had today successfully concluded WMck on the  1988 Public

Expenditure Survey,  and that the Chancellor^broj^ed to make his Autumn

Statement to the House that afteroon, setting0ou(r the outcome of the

Survey and the prospects for the economy.

The Cabinet -

1. Endorsed the recommendations in the memoran^^^y the

Chief Secretary. ^35^.

2. Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer^tf^j^make

his Autumn Statement later that day. ^[^k


[OP-up w&amp;Pyi

FOR STUl&amp;iW,

3.     The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of State for

.Education and Science (C(88) 14), to which was attached a draft White

*o?aper on top-up loans for students.

 ^M^SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE said that the draft

/wfrlfo. Paper proposed that from October 1990 all full-time home students

in^Pfgher education, other than postgraduates, would be eligible for

top-^p^loans.    At the same time they would lose their entitlement to

socTgK^wcurity benefits.   All other students now entitled to claim

benefnlv^J^ld also be disentitled from that date.    Three Access Funds

would ^^established, along the lines described in the draft White Paper

and administered by the education institutions to provide students with

assistance on a discretionary basis.    The White Paper illustrated a

figure of  420 for the size of a full year loan, for students not at

home and not y&lt;^fc5todon, on the inception of the scheme.    The proposal

was that ther^fcft * anY uprating of students&apos; total resources in grant

and loan would T?|ya&quot;ppd.ied to the loan facility only, until it equalled

the grant and pa&amp;fl^a^contribution taken together.    It was important

that the scheme shoj^Mybe administered by the financial institutions.

They were being difr/eWftVin negotiation but if the Cabinet approved his

proposals he proposea^pq^ove the White Paper was published to see the

Governor of the Bank of J r   nd and the Chairmen of the Committee of

London and Scottish Ban^^^(fa\of the Building Societies Association and

press them to co-operate

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR E^U^lON AND SCIENCE said that opinion in

the educational world was nowwaara^to accept the proposals he was

putting forward.    It would be a^g^e^K prize for the Government to secure

them.    The withdrawal of students^^om^the social security system, which

Beveridge had never intended to covje^^hem, would be especially welcome.

He believed that the proposals couic^^presented positively to

students, parents, universities and tHe^w( blic at large and he hoped

that colleagues would endorse them and&lt;ureree to early publication of the

White Paper. V

In discussion the following main points were made:

a. In presentation, it would be wrong ^V_pAL-the main emphasis on

the eventual savings, important through therfr^waye.   The point to

stress was the educational advantages and tR^-^raftee in culture

which the scheme would bring about, by giving ^tfMeAts more

responsibility and freedom of choice.    The staty^J^Nin the White

Paper that 77 per cent of students now drew socia^^ecwnrity

benefits was striking.   The generosity of treatment &gt;e  ^tudents in

the United Kingdom, in comparison with other countri&gt; fjmould also

be stressed.

b. Repayments would be comparatively low, even in the^&amp;nfl years

of a student&apos;s working life when his income would probably^M^^.

modest and he would be acquiring new responsibilities. ^&gt;&gt;VV

Nevertheless, there would inevitably be hard cases and there^rast^


be some means of adjusting repayments to students&apos; resources.

X There were objections to operating through the tax system.

?Vv Probably the best solution would be to provide that where earnings

were low - for example, less than 85 per cent of national average

income - repayments would be deferred, and the period of the loan

\S^jS)  extended.   After consultation an incentive to early repayment could

^)A^also be considered.

It was undesirable to extend the loan facility to post-

j?^auates.    They could be in their late twenties or even early

^rti&gt;*yies.    Their needs could be dealt with through their Access

FuV^^or which funding was being proposed at a generous level.

d. vPresent plans were that the necessary legislation would be

announced in the Queen&apos;s Speech at the start of the 1989-90

Session, and carried in time for the scheme to start in autumn

1990.    Tha^Wtn^e Paper must however be so drafted that it did not

anticipat^v^h^Queen1 s Speech.

e. Some of jafting of the White Paper contained infelicities

and needed to t&gt; ^lrf}tened up.

THE PRIME MINISTER, sujJjjriA^Oup the discussion, said that the Cabinet

endorsed the proposals in JZ$%) 14, and noted that the Secretary of

State planned to publish Xn^ftftite Paper in the week of 7 November, on a

day to be settled in detai\^&gt;^\cussion.    Any further detailed

drafting amendments should b^sx^eyed to the Secretary of State

urgently. \&gt;s^f)

The Cabinet -

&lt;y% ...

Took note with approval of the &gt;P^lme. Minister&apos;s summing

up of their discussion and invi&lt;3GKfcne Secretary of State

for Education and Science to proc^^^cordingly.

Cabinet Office

1 November 1988



</content>
</cab>
