<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/185/19 images: 442-542</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75)119COPY NO     0 16 November 1975CABINETDEVOLUTION TO SCOTLAND AND WALES;THE WHITE PAPERfJote by the Lord President of the council. We are committed to publishing a White Paper giving details of how we propose to implement the undertakings we gave last year (in the white paper Cmnd 5732 and in our election manifestos) to set up elected assemblies for Scotland and Wales, and to devolve extensive powers tothem.2. I attach the draft of the White Paper.    It reflects the intensiveprogramme of work, involving all Departments, carried out during the past year under the supervision of the Ministerial Steering Committee onDevolution (DS).    I have taken account of comments sent to me since thelast DS discussion.3. My colleagues may wish to note in particular paragraphs 5 and 288,which make clear that the proposals are open to debate and detailedmodification;  and paragraph 6, which makes clear that we do not plan to legislate in haste.4. Passages relating to the role of the House of Lords in &quot;override&quot;procedures and to future responsibility for the probation service in Walesare in square brackets pending discussion by the Ministerial Committee onDevolution Questions (DQM) on 7 November.    I shall report the outcome tothe Cabinet separately.5. I envisage that the White Paper, if approved by the Cabinet, would bepublished on Thursday, 27 November. It will be published simultaneously in Welsh. The main White Paper will be followed by a popular version, tobe distributed free through public libraries and post offices.1
6. The Secretary of State for the Environment and I will be puttingproposals to the Cabinet in other papers on the publication of a discussiondocument about devolution in England.7. I invite the Cabinet to approve the draft of the White Paper for publication.E privy Council Office6 November 19752
OUR CHANGING DEMOCRACY:Devolution to Scotland and Wales
(comfidemtsal)CONTENTSParagraph        page part I: INTRODUCTION part II: THE GOVERNMENT1S APPROACH                           4PART III: SCOTLAND 10A   THE BACKGROUND TO DEVOLUTION 10B   CONSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTS 11The Scottish Assembly 29                 11The Scottish Executive 40                 13Scottish Assembly Legislation /;8                 15Delegated Legislation 6                  19United Kingdom Reserve Powers inExecutive Matters 68                 19Assembly Committees 73                 21The Civil Service in Scotland 77                23Complaints Machinery 83                24European Community and other international Aspects 84                24C   FINANCE AND TAXATION 26The Basic Concepts 91                26The Block Grant 98                28Taxation 103                29Other Sources of Finance 108                30Financial Control and Audit 109                31confidents
ParagraphD   THE DEVOLVED SUBJECTSThe General Approach 111Local Government 115Health 118Social Services 119Education, Science and the Arts 122Housing 127Physical Planning and the environment 128Roads and Transport 131Development and Industry 134Natural Resources 138Law and the Legal System .                         140Tourism 148Other Matters 149Nominated Bodies 151General Standards 156Pay in the Public Sector 157Regulation of the Professions 158Statistics and Other Information 160Tribunals and Inquiries 164E   SUMMARY OP THE SCHEME FOR SCOTLANDPART IV: wales   THE BACKGROUND TO DEVOLUTION IN WALESB   CONSTITUTIONAL arrangements the Welsh Assembly 173Executive Powers and Committees of the welsh Assembly 184Legislation for Wales 192Delegated Legislation 196United Kingdom Reserve Powers 202
Paragraph page the Civil Service in Wales 206 57Complaints Machinery 213 58European Community and other international Aspects 214 58C   FINANCIAL ARRANGEMENTS 60The Block Grant 217 60Taxation 221 61Other Sources of Finance 224 61Financial Control and Audit 225 62D   THE DEVOLVED SUBJECTS 63Local Government &apos;                          229 63Health 232 63Social Services 233 64Education, Science and the Arts 236 6AHousing 239 65Physical Planning and the environment 240 65Roads and Transport 244 66Development and Industry 245 66Natural Resources 248 67Water in Wales .         249 6?Tourism 251 68Other Matters 252 68Nominated Bodies 254 68General Standards 261 70Pay in the Public Sector 262 70Statistics and Other Information 263 70Tribunals and Inquiries 267 71E   SUMMARY OF THE SCHEME FOR WALES 12iii
Paragraph        Pa^ePART V: DECENTRALISATION - THE EXECUTIVEROLE OP SCOTTISH AND WELSH ministers in THE GOVERNMENT 73PART VI: COSTS 76PART VII: WHAT&quot; SCOTTISH AND WELSHDEVOLUTION WILL MEAN FOR THEUNITED KINGDOM 78APPENDIX A   SCOTTISH AND WELSH ASSEMBLIES:QUALIFICATION AND DISQUALIFICATIONFOR MEMBERSHIPAPPENDIX B   COMPLAINTS MACHINERY IN SCOTLANDAND WALESAPPENDIX C   PUBLIC EXPENDITURE AND BLOCK GRANTCONSULTATIONS: AN ILLUSTRATIVEANNUAL CALENDARAPPENDIX D   OUTLINE OF SUBJECT FIELDS TO BEDEVOLVEDAPPENDIX E   SCOTLAND: LIST OF NOMINATED bodies in DEVOLVED SUBJECTSAPPENDIX F   WALES:    LIST OF NOMINATED bodies in DEVOLVED SUBJECTSiv
apart I:    introduction.     A healthy democracy is a living and developing system.     Our democraticinstitutions have been admirably stable, but that does not mean that they areperfect and unchangeable.      In particular, over a lengthy period centralgovernment has accumulated an array of powers and functions some of which couldbe exercised at a lower level, closer to the people.     The case for this isespecially strong in Scotland and Wales, where there remains a sense ofhistorical identity included within, but distinct from, the consciousness ofbeing British.     This was the philosophy which underlay the decision announced by the Government in a White Paper* in September 1974 to set up elected assemblies in Scotland and Wales.2.     The 1974 decision to devolve certain governmental responsibilities to scottish and Welsh assemblies, which flowed from a determination to bringdemocratic authority to bear more closely on policy and administration inthese countries, was taken after wide public discussion on a consultative document, and clearly met the aspirations of the majority of Scots and Welsh.That decision was however only the beginning.     The constitutional change proposed is the most fundamental of its kind in Great Britain for centuries.It would have been folly to propose hasty and over-simplified answers to detailed and complex problems.     The task the Government set themselveshad few previous parallels in any country, namely the division between twolevels of Government of the powers and functions exercised centrally in a unitary state.     The new system must work efficiently as well as democratically,and it must stand the test of time.3.     The White Paper of September 1974 indicated in general terms the rolesand powers that Assemblies for Scotland and Wales would have and the subjectareas in which they would operate.     This White Paper turns those general principles into detailed proposals.     It explains how the relations of thenew structures with the Government would work, what subject areas would be devolved, how continuing United Kingdom interests would be looked after, and how the financial principles outlined in the earlier White Paper would be implemented.     The proposals rest on intensive studies of great range and1* Democracy and Devolution:Proposals for Scotland and Wales (Cmnd 5732)
(confsdemt8al) Jcomplexity. The activities of every G-overnment department have beer,examined in detail to establish how devolution should affect them. There!have been studies of the involved economic problems relating to expenditrand taxation by devolved administrations. Nor could each study proceed!isolation; the preferred solution in one area of governmental activity s-.interact with those in others, and great care has been necessary to ensurethat the final proposals form a consistent package.4.     The G-overnment believe that this White Paper sets out coherent andworkable proposals which provide a sound basis for legislation to set upelected Assemblies in Scotland and Wales.     The implementation of theseproposals should make government in Scotland and Wales less remote, more Iopen, and more responsive to the needs and desires of the people - and hencmore effective.     It will help to preserve and foster the distinctivenational traditions of Scotland and Wales, which everyone in the UnitedKingdom should value as part of our common heritage.     The proposals givepractical recognition to the differing needs and desires of the peoples o!Scotland and Wales, and thus should both reassure them that their wishescan never be overlooked and help to preserve the unity as well as thediversity of the United Kingdom.5.     The Government recognise however that these proposals raise issues o! jgreat significance for all the people of the United Kingdom.     Two issues are of particular importance - getting a sound and stabledistribution of responsibilities between Westminster and the devolvedadministrations;   and ensuring that the proposals meet the reasonable neeof Scotland and Wales, while maintaining a fair balance between theinterests of those territories and of the rest of the United Kingdom,Achieving this has naturally resulted in many complex, detailed and speci Iprovisions that could not have been identified at the time of the earlierWhite Paper.     The Government now want to see full public and Parliamentsconsideration, because of the extreme importance of the issues for allth jpeople of the United Kingdom;   the novelty of the arrangements proposed;and the need, in constitutional matters, to get right first time the essentials of legislation that will inevitably be complicated.     The mainstructure of the schemes is clear, but they need not represent the lastword in every respect.     The Government will accordingly be very willing2
to listen to representations about their proposals which are consistent withthe. approach set out in Part II of this White Paper.6.     Work is in hand on drafting a Bill, which will take accountprogressively of points made during consultation.     It will be published as early as possible in the spring of 1976.     It would not however be feasible then to carry so major a Bill through to Royeil Assent in the1975/76 session.     Moreover, the Government believe that it would be wrong to legislate in haste on issues of such very special and lastingconstitutional importance.     The Bill, when published, will provide theopportunity for debate and for focussing opinion more closely on specificlegislative proposals;   and the Government will take account of all this in further refining the schemes.     They will then introduce a Bill inParliament at the start of the following session.7.     Maintaining the integrity of the United Kingdom does not entail uniformtreatment for all its parts.       This White Paper is about devolution to scotland and Wales, and its proposals are related to their needs.     Asthe White Paper of September 1974 made clear, Northern Ireland comes into adifferent category.     Its history and geography distinguish it from otherparts of the United Kingdom, as does the presence of two separate communities.Its problems are not those of Scotland or Wales, and therefore do notnecessarily require the same treatment.     England is different again, andthe Government will publish separately a discussion document on the way-forward there.8.     Part II of this White Paper outlines the Governmenfs general approach to devolution.     Part III sets out the scheme for Scotland and Part TV thescheme for Wales;   to make each reasonably self-contained, there is inevitably a good deal of repetition between them.     Part V reviews thedecentralised responsibilities of Scottish and Welsh Ministers in theUnited Kingdom Government - the Secretary of State for Scotland and theLord Advocate, and the Secretary of State for Wales.     Part VI deals withthe cost of implementing devolution in Scotland and Wales.     Part VJJdiscusses the implications which the proposals for Scotland and Wales willhave for the United Kingdom as a whole.3
n!alPART II: THE COVER?-! IIK-IT&apos; S APPROACH9. Political and economic unity has been maintained and deepened throughmGreat Britain for over two and a half centuries, generating a deep social lij]and giving the component countries a common history, heritage and way of iffricher than any of them could have enjoyed on its own.10. The Government are firmly committed to maintaining this unity. It in ^powerful and constructive force shaping the daily lives of us all; and thosexvho advocate destroying the United Kingdom, for the sake of a real or iir:agiijshort-term gain to some, rarely spell out the long-term loss to all. TheGovernment reject entirely the idea of separation for Scotland and Wales andthe break-up of the United Kingdom, as advocated by the nationalist parties^believe that the great majority of Scottish and Welsh people endorse thisrejection. As the Government made clear in the White Paper of September 1qIthey agree wholeheartedly with the Kilbrandon Commission^&quot; in rejecting also!federalism within the United Kingdom.11. Unity does not .however mean \miformity. Within the United Kingdom Scotand Wales have kept their own identities, with distinctive elements of tradiculture and institutions. Respect for these diversities has strengthenedlhUnion far more than an imposed conformity could have done.12. This respect underlies the long tradition of decentralisation of Scottigovernment - that is, the practice whereby large areas of government work foScotland are carried out not in London but in Edinburgh, under Ministers whowhile members of the United Kingdom Government and answerable to Parliament);Westminster are nevertheless distinctively Scottish.   The Labour Government^last in office, extended this system to Wales; and its scope in both countries&apos; Ehas recently been widened, with the transfer to the two Secretaries of Statferesponsibility for selective assistance to industry under section 7 of theIndustry Act 1972, and the establishment of the Scottish and Welsh Develop^Agencies responsible to them.13. Decentralisation remains a useful means of ensuring that administration in Scotland and Wales is founded on an understanding of the needs and wishes4
PART II: THE OOVDRITOI-?TT1S APPROACH9.     Political and economic unity has been maintained and deepened throughout great Britain for over two and a half centuries, generating a deep social unit-and giving the component countries a common history, heritage and way of lifc.richer than any of them could have enjoyed on its own.10.   The Government are firmly committed to maintaining this unity.   It is a powerful and constructive force shaping the daily lives of us all; and thosewho advocate destroying the United Kingdom, for the sake of a real or imaginarshort-term gain to some, rarely spell out the long-term loss to all.   TheGovernment reject entirely the idea of separation for Scotland and Wales andthe break-up of the United Kingdom, as advocated by the nationalist parties, believe that the great majority of Scottish and Welsh people endorse thisrejection.    As the Government made clear in the White Paper of September 1974,they agree wholeheartedly with the Kilbrandon Commission^ in rejecting alsofederalism within the United Kingdom,11. Unity does not-however mean tmiformity. Within the United Kingdom Scotkand Wales have kept their own identities, with distinctive elements of traditiculture and institutions. Respect for these diversities has strengthened theUnion far more than an imposed conformity could have done.12. This respect underlies the long tradition of decentralisation of Scottishgovernment - that is, the practice whereby large areas of government work forScotland are carried out not in London but in Edinburgh, under Ministers whowhile members of the United Kingdom Government and answerable to Parliament iWestminster are nevertheless distinctively Scottish. The Labour Government,;last in office, extended this system to Wales; and its scope in both countries:has recently been widened,&quot;with the transfer to the two Secretaries of Stateiresponsibility for selective assistance to industry under section 7 of ^eIndustry Act 1972, and the establishment of the Scottish and Welsh DevelopmaiiAgencies responsible to them.13.   Decentralisation remains a useful means of ensuring that administration in Scotland and Wales is founded on an understanding of the needs and wishes&apos;---Royal &quot;Commission on the Constitution 1969-73: Cmnd 546O and 5460-1
these countries; the Government will continue to use it and indeed, in some respects to extend it, as Part V explains. /14. &apos; The Government believe however that something more is needed - the creationof elected as well as administrative institutions distinctive to Scotland andWales.   This is what devolution means.   There will be new democratic bodies,directly chosen by and answerable to the Scottish and Welsh people for very wide areas of government business.    Decision talcing in the devolved matters will bebrought closer to the people, and the lines of democratic accountability willbe shorter and more responsive to their wishes.15.   The central task on which the Government has concentrated in developing the devolution schemes is to define those areas of activity where decisions affectprimarily people living in Scotland and Wales.   It would be plainly wrong todevolve to the new Scottish and Welsh Assemblies powers over activities whichsubstantially affect people outside Scotland or Wales, or the well-being of theUnited Kingdom generally.   The need is to achieve balance - to reconcile unity and diversity in a stronger and better system, offering   more achievement andsatisfaction to the parts whilst improving the efficiency and stability of thewhole.   In working this out the Government have observed the principles whichflow from acceptance of the essential unity of the United Kingdom.   They have alsokept in mind the need for a consistent and coherent pattern of government, whichwill be clear and understandable to the public whom it serves and the people who work in it.   Throughout the Governments consideration of their proposals,the key criterion has been the long-term advantage of the people of Scotland andWales within a unified British state.16.   Under the Governments proposals, the Assemblies will control policies andspending prioritj.es in a very wide range of services, including for example mostaspects of local government, health, personal social services, educa/fcion, housing,physical planning, the environment and roads, and many aspects of transport.   TheScottish Assembly will also be able to make new laws or amend present ones in thesematters, and since it will be a legislative body it can be given responsibility in addition for most aspects of the distinctive private and criminal law ofScotland.I?. All these powers will enable the new Scottish and Welsh administrations tobring very great influence to bear on the whole physical and social environment5
it/of their countries.   That influence, together with the large spending power which the administrations xvi 11 directly control will enable them to have a veimarked effect also on their economic environment       In addition, they will beable to debate economic matters and frame proposals for discussion XV ITH theGovernment,18.   The new powers will not however be conferred at the expense of thebenefits which flow from the political and economic unity of the United Kinguc19.   Political unity means that The Queen in Parliament, representing all thpeople, must remain sovereign over their affairs; and that the Government oftday must bear the main responsibility to Parliament for protecting and further the interests of all.   In particular the Government must be able to do what exis needed for national security; they must conduct international relations,including those flowing from our membership of the European Community; and themust maintain the national framework of Law and order, guaranteeing the basicrights of the citizen throughout the United Kingdom.   Political unity also uesthat British citizens are at home throughout the United Kingdom; the Scotsmanand the Welshman living and working in London as much as the Englishman living and working in Edinburgh or Cardiff.20. Economic unity plainly means that the Government must manage the nation^external economic relations - the balance of payments, the exchange rate, extassets and liabilities, and economic, trading and. other arrangements with oticountries. But the principle has to go much further. The Government must beto manage demand in the economy as a whole - to control national taxation, to&apos;public expenditure and the supply of money and credit. The Government must toable to regulate the framework of trade, so as to maintain a fair competitivebalance for industry and commerce everywhere. Within the wider commom market which the European Community is developing xve already enjoy a common market-throughout the United Kingdom, and any nexv and artificial barriers within thailong-established market could be seriously damaging. And the Government raxalso keep the task of devising national policies to benefit particular parti*ln 1974-75 public expenditure on the services proposed for devolution wasabout  2000 million in Scotland and  900 million in Wales.---------------------ucm 1 lALj
the United Kingdom, and of distributing resources among them according torelative need.    Relative need can he judged only by talcing an overall view,and that viev; has to be taken by the Government; this inescapable factcrucially affects the scope for devolving responsibilities in economic matters.21.   Against this background the Government have studied with great care howfar the new administrations could be given direct powers over the economy in Scotland and Wales since this is a matter of great importance to both countries.   They have had to conclude that the scope for this kind of devolution is strictly limited by the fundamental needs of unity.   Pulleconomic autonomy would mean abandoning the basic United Kingdom approach,which all governments have adopted for decades past.22.   Our people are less and less ready to tolerate extremes of wealth andpoverty alongside one another in our society.   This applies betweengeographical areas, not just between individuals.     Unplanned, economic forces,changes in world demand and the discovery of new natural resources can bringfortune or misfortune to large areas, and over the centuries almost every partof the United Kingdom has experienced this ebb and flow.   In recent timessuccessive Governments have increasingly sought to diminish inequalities;the fact that Scotland and Wales, like Northern Ireland, are at presentclassified in their entirety as assisted areas is evidence of this.23.   Regional policies have been formulated and implemented for the UnitedKindgom as a whole, and only in that way can true priorities be judged and theresources of the whole country be deployed to help solve problems as they arise anywhere within it.   Nor would it be practicable simply to leave particular areas to draw up their own schemes of economic support and. assistance within an overall allocation of funds, since divergences in approach would inevitablyresult in distortions of. competition which could not be accommodated within a unified economy.   For these reasons it is not possible to give the new scottish and Welsh administrations substantial direct economic powers.24.   The powers to be devolved will nevertheless enable the Assemblies to havemarked influence on the economic environment of Scotland and Wales.   Thearrangements for the Scottish and Welsh Development Agencies described in
njtiaOparagraphs 134 and 245 respectively will give the Assemblies an importantrole in the work of these new bodies, which are intended to give a newstimulus to industrial and environmental regeneration.    At the same timethe transfer of manpower functions - so crucial to economic development -add an important new dimension to the decision making in the economic fieldcarried out in Scotland and Wales.24A.   The complete schemes for Scotland and Wales are set out in Parts III    iand IV respectively.   They are designed to give maximum freedom to the newadministrations in domestic matters whilst preserving the United Kingdomdimensions where it is needed.   But   the Government do not contemplate a future in which, once the new system is set up, they and the administrationswill deal with one another at arm&apos;s length.   Every effort will be made inadvance to cut our overlap and uncertainty, and to avoid the problems whichill-defined relationships would cause; but there will be many matters on whichcontinuing close contacts will be in the common interest.24B.   Arrangements for extensive but flexible consultation will be required on many subjects and at all levels, political and official.   Through these theGovernment and the devolved administrations will keep one another informed anawill work together as closely as possible.   Interests will sometimes differ, agive and take will be needed.   But the Government see no reason to fear thatthe longstanding spirit of partnership within the United Kingdom vail be replaby confrontation.   They look forward to working out effective two-wayconsultation arrangements with the devolved administrations as soon as possiViand to operating them over the years in a spirit of goodwill and   co-operation24C.   At the same time the Government cannot shed their responsibility for the jinterests of the United Kingdom as a whole.   They must ensure that they andtheir successors remain able to act freely and promptly in those interests.Reserve powers are therefore built into the constitutional schemes to enablethe Government of the day to intervene, subject to the approval of [parliament in actions by the devolved administrations which the Government judge serious! jto the Secretaries of State for Scotland and fi for Wales (paragraph 276) willharmful.8
confidential)24D.    It is impossible to predict what situations might lead to their &quot;use,and it is largely for this reason that the Government propose to provide thesereserve powers rather than attempt to deal specifically in the Act with every possible eventuality.   Their use should not therefore be regarded as a last resort implying a seriotis confrontation.   But if the schemes of devolutionfulfil their objectives and there is goodwill on all sides, the necessity touse reserve powers should arise only sparingly and need not be a source of conflict.   The future of us all turns upon harmonious co-operation in.achieving national success between all the people of the United Kingdom andtheir elected representatives, whether in Parliament or in the Assemblies.
PART III: Scotland a.   THE BACKGROUND TO DEVOLUTION25.   Ever since the voluntary union of Scotland and England in 1707 thearrangements for the government of Scotland have differed in some respect:; fK.those for England.    In modern times these arrangements have centred on theoffice of the Secretary of State for Scotland.   A Secretary for Scotland was created in 1885, but the present system dates effectively from the opening in1939 of St Andrew&apos;s House in Edinburgh.    It gives to the Secretary-of State,who is a member of the Cabinet, a wide range of responsibilities for theadministration of government in Scotland.   These include most of the functions which in England are the responsibility of the Home Office, the Department ofEducation and Science, the Department of the Environment, the Ministry ofAgriculture, Fisheries and Food and the health and personal social service sids Iof the Department of Health and Social Security, as well as (more recently)some functions of the Department of Industry.    In addition, the Lord Advocate as Ia Scottish Minister within the United Kingdom Government has always had widefunctions in the field of law.26.   This system has achieved much for Scotland.   It gives Scotland a strongvoice in the Cabinet and separate representation on interdepartmental committee\where policy options are worked out.   The Government intend that there should remain major roles for the Secretary of State and the Lord Advocate, as Part V jof this White Paper shows.   Bat the present system, based on Westminster withits wider burdens, cannot always allow responsively enough for distinctively    JScottish problems and Scottish characteristics.   Factors like these have be cob\more significant as the scope of government business and the calls on Parliameiltime have grown.27.   The best way of improving matters in the particular circumstances of Scotis by legislative and executive devolution.   This means an elected scottish assembly which can pass its own laws and supervise their working.   Scottishinstitutions and practices will be largely in the care of a purely Scottish   1body directly answerable to the Scottish people.    It will be able, for example jto find more time than Westminster now can for Scottish legislation.tailored *fit the distinctive law of Scotland and the separate legal system.10
B.   CONSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTSt28.   Many features of the constitutional scheme proposed are modelled onParliament, where they are well tried and have evolved over the centuries in apractical blend of efficient government and democratic rights.    Parliament mustendow Scotland with a comparable blend.   But the Government do not intend thatthe new Assembly should be forced to be a carbon copy of Westminster,   Withinthe main features which the Act must lay down and which only Parliament canchange, the Scottish Assembly and the Executive answerable to it wiH.be free to develop their own ways of working as they judge best.The Scottish Assembly29.   There will be a directly-elected single-chamber Scottish Assemblyconsisting, to begin with, of 142 members - two for each of the 71 Parliamentaryconstituencies in Scotland.   There will not be time before the Assembly comes into being for the Boundary Commission for Scotland to complete the thoroughscrutiny needed to divide the Parliamentary constituencies fairly.   At thefirst election therefore each elector will be able to vote for two candidates,and in each Parliamentary constituency the two with most votes will becomeAssembly Members.30.  For later elections the Boundary Commission will divide Parliamentaryconstituencies as necessary into single-member Assembly constituencies, on abasis which will improve the fairness of the system by taking more account ofthe number of voters in each constituency.   Each Parliamentary constituencywill be allotted one, two or three Assembly seats, according to a formula basedon the average size of Parliamentary electorates in Scotland.   The formula willbe this:-a. Parliamentary constituency whose electorate is less 1 Assemblythan 75% of the average electorate                                       constituencyb. Parliamentary constituency whose electorate is not less     2 Assemblythan 75% and not more than 125% of the average electorate constituenciesc Parliamentary constituency whose electorate is more 3 Assemblythan 125% of the average electorate constituenciesOn present electorates, this system would give an Assembly of about 138 members.The formula will be re-applied, and any necessary re-division made, wheneverParliamentary seats are re-distributed.   The divisions into Assembly
constituencies will be embodied in draft Orders in Council laid beforeParliament by the Secretary of State.31*   Everyone entitled to vote in &quot;Westminster&apos;elections, and also peers, willbe able to vote in Assembly elections; but no-one will have a vote in more thanone constituency.   The Secretary of State for Scotland will be responsiblefor general oversight of Assembly elections and for making rules for them onelection expenses and the like.32.   The Assembly will be elected for a normal fixed term of Sur years, but theSecretary of State will have power to make minor adjustments either way to yielda convenient election day.33* The time, place and other arrangements for the first meeting will be set by the Secretary of State, &apos; Thereafter these matters will be for the Assemblyitselfto decide.34&quot;   Matters affecting Assembly membership, such as the miles about qualification,disqualification, expulsion and resignation, will be dealt with in the Act,as will the special safeguards which members will need to do their job, suchas protection against actions for defamation.   Membership of the Assembly willnot be barred to Members of the House of Commons or the House of Lords.   practical considerations will often prevent them from standing for election to the Assembly,but it does not seem right that they should be excluded by statute. Qualificationand. disqualification are dealt with in more detail in Appendix A.35*   Every candidate elected to the Assembly will have to swear or affirmallegiance to the Crown before taking his seat.36.   The pay and allowances of Assembly Members will be determined initiallyby the Secretary of State, and thereafter by the Assembly itself,37&apos;   The Secretary of State will make interim Standing Orders to get the Assemblystarted, but thereafter it will make its own, subject to any requirements inthe Act - for example on the use of Committees (paragraphs 73&apos;--76 below).38. The Assembly will elect from among its members a presiding officsrj likethe Speaker in the House of Commons. The Assembly staff will be answerable tothe Assembly not to the Executive.
39*    The Secretary of State will not he an ex officio member of the scottish assembly.    But the Assembly and the Secretary of State could arrange by.agreement for him to attend and address meetings from time to time.The Scottish Executive40.    Executive powers in the devolved fields (including the power to makedelegated legislation) will be exercised by a Scottish Executive.   these powers will be vested in Members of the Executive, with each&apos;of them exercisingwhatever responsibilities are allocated by tie head of the Executive - theChief Executive.41*    The Executive will normally be formed after each election.   The Secretaryof State for Scotland will invite a prospective Chief Executive to form an executive which will command the support of the Assembly; in the ordinary coursehe will invite the leader of the majority-party.   The prospective Chief Executivewill submit the names of his proposed Executive to the Assembly, which willapprove or reject them as a whole.   If the Assembly approves, the Secretary ofState for Scotland will formally appoint them as the Executive.   If theAssembly rejects the proposed team, the Secretary of State will at his discretioninvite the same person to try again, or someone else.42.    The Secretary of State will also appoint Assistants to the Executive, onthe recommendation of the Chief Executive.   These Assistants will be politicalin character but will not be members of the Executive, nor require Assemblyapproval.43*    Executive Members and Assistants will normally be members of the Assembly,but there will be no rigid rule about this.   Some flexibility is desirable toleave room for possible appointments from outside the Assembly.   It may bedesirable to include a distinguished person, or one with special expertise (forexample in the law), who is not an Assembly Member; and there will be no second chamber upon which to draw, as there is at Westminster.   Political pressuresshould ensure that the scope for appointing non-members to the Executive isnot over-used.   The Assembly1s right to approve or reject the Executive as awhole will be a strong factor.13
44.   Executive Members and Assistants who are not Assembly members will hzs,ble to sit and speak in the Assembly, but not to vote.45*    Maximum numbers of Executive Members, and of Members and Assistantscombined, will be laid down in the Act.   The Secretary of State will havepower to increase the numbers later by Order.   The pay and allowances of executive Members and Assistants will be set initially by the Secretary ofState and thereafter by the Assembly.46.    Changes in the Executive (including dismissals) will be made formallyby the secretary of State on the recommendation of the Chief Executive;Assembly approval will not be required.   If a Chief Executive misused his power of individual change to create a whole new team without Assembly approve:the Assembly could pass a vote of censure or no   confidence.   The members ofthe Executive will hold office formally at Her Majesty1s pleasure, and theSecretary of State could in the last resort dismiss the Executive- if he j\id,geait was holding on to office without commanding adequate support in the Assembl;47*   Any departure of the Chief Executive from office will entail the resignation of the whole Executive and the Assistants.   The Secretary of state will have power, without needing Assembly approval; to appoint a &quot;caretaker&quot;Executive to carry on business until a new Assembly^approved Executive canbe appointed.14
Scojfc^^slv A^sernbly Legislation48.    In subjects not devolved, Parliament will continue to make and controllegislation for the whole of the United Kingdom.     In devolved subjects,however, the Scottish Assembly will become responsible for legislation.     Atthe outset the Executive will administer the law as it now stands;   but theAssembly will be free to amend or repeal existing law and to pass new laws of its own.49.   As at Westminster there will be two kinds of legislation - primarylegislation in the form of Scottish Assembly Acts, and secondary legislation in the form of Scottish statutory instruments.     These statutory instrumentsmay be made under the authority either of Assembly Acts or of WestminsterActs still applying to Scotland.50.    There will be no second chamber.     Within the Assembly, however, theprocedure for introducing and considering Bills will be very similar to thatat Westminster;   but having passed through all their stages in the Assembly,Bills vri.ll be submitted for Assent by Her Majesty in Council through theSecretary of State for Scotland,     The follov/ing paragraphs set out the processleading up to Assent.51.    Either the Executive or individual Assembly Members will be able tointroduce Bills (though if Bills introduced by individual Members entailexpenditure they will be able to proceed only with the Executive&apos;s agreement).Any differences in handling will be for the Assembly itself to settle.     The-Act will lay down in broad terms various stages for the handling of legislation by the Assembly.     There will be -(a) a general debate on each Bill, with an opportunity for Members to vote on its general principles;(b) consideration of, and an opportunity for Members to vote on andamend, the details of the Bill;(c) a final stage at vdiich the Bill can be passed or rejected but notamended.Further details will be left to the Assembly&apos;s own Standing Orders.52.    Some special procedure involving the Government will be needed for anyAssembly Bill seeking to bind the Crown in respect of matters not devolved.The Government are considering what form this procedure should take, and at15
what stage of the Assembly&apos;3 legislative process it should operate.53*   The Assembly&apos; s presiding officer, on./the advice of his counsel, will report to the Assembly on the vires of a Bill (that is, vh ether it fallswithin the devolved powers) when it is introduced, and again before theAssembly stage;   if the report is adverse it will not stop the Bill but nilserve as a warning to the Assembly and the Executive.     The Government willnot be formally involved at these stages, but they will be aware of the- 3jTand the presiding officer&apos;s report and may wish to give informal warning ofany difficulties about vires which they foresee.     The Scottish authorities will be similarly free, if in doubt, to consult the Government informally,54.   7.hen a Bill has passed its final stage in the Assembly it will be forwarded to the Secretary of State for Scotland. The Government will then consider,  with advice from the Lav/ Officers, whether any part of the Bill Liultra vires. In accordance with normal legal principles, ancillary provisitreasonably incidential to a main purpose falling within a devolved field niltreated as intra.\^ires even though they may not strictly relate wholly todevolved subjects.   The Government will also consider whether the Bill is acceptable on general policy grounds.In order to be submitted for Assent the Bill must be both int ra vires!and acceptable on policy grounds.     If it contains ultra vires provisions,;is unacceptable on policy grounds, or both,, the Secretary of State will ssit back to the Assembly with a clear statement of the reasons.56.   It will be for the Assembly itself to decide how to handle any Bills 1referred back to it.     If a Bill referred back as ultra vires is re-submit&apos;to the Secretary of State in terms still adjudged to be ultra vires, he mltell the Assembly so and the Bill will not go forward for Assent.     If a.;.llreferred back on policy grounds is resubmitted in terms which the Governs $are still not prepared to accept, they must within a set period from the bill&apos;s receipt by the Secretary of State lay it before Parliament with a notice of motion praying for its rejection.     If both Houses of Parliament;;affirm this motion the Assembly will be told that the Bill will not besubmitted for Assent.     If either House rejects the motion the Bill will. 11forward.q16
(confidential)57*   The Government1 s reserve powers to halt the progress of Assembly Billshave necessarily been explained at some length.     But this does not reflect the spirit in which the Government expect devolution to work, nor thefeatures ?;hich will be most conspicuous in practical operation.     In theordinary course Assembly Bills will be presented for Assent v/ithout anytrouble or delay.58.   Underlying all these arrangements there will remain the final legislativesovereignty of Parliament, in which all parts of the United Kingdom are represented.     Parliament will remain able to pass laws on any natter andfor any part of the United Kingdom.     Any surrender of this sovereigntywould imply federalism, not devolution.     Against a background of co-operation and goodwill, however, Parliament would normally legislate on a devolvedmatter only where this was agreed with the Scottish administration asbeing the convenient course.55,   The Scottish Assembly will be constitutionally subordinate to Parliament..It will have been created by Parliament and will always remain subject toParliament&apos;s laws, and it will not be free to change the main features of the devolution Act.     The Government intend however that the Scottish assembly should effectively assume, in the devolved field, the task cf making laws forScotland.     Bills of the Scottish Assembly will be scrutinized, as explained in paragraphs 53-54, to see whether they are within the devolved powers.The question arises whether, after Assent has been given, an Assembly Actshould be open to review in the courts on the grounds of vires - that is,whether the courts should have jurisdiction to declare, at the instance of alitigant, that an Assembly Act goes outside the powers conferred by the devolution Act.     The issue is more than just a legal technicality, andthere are arguments both ways,60.    In favour of judicial review, it can be argued that this is a normal and natural accompaniment of the operation of a legislature whose powers are limited by law;   that the right of the citizen to challenge in thecourts any possible excessive use of power should not be abated;   that the boundaries of what Parliament intended in the devolution Act should be policedby the courts as specific situations arise in litigation, not merely by government Ministers inevitably exposed to political pressures and making their judgments17
(confidential)in the abstract before experience has been gained of how particular Asser-Acts will work in practical application; and that excluding judicial rrvwill complicate the task of the courts, which will in any event have to feaccount of the devolution Act when they interpret Assembly Acts,61. Against judicial review, it can be argued that its exclusion wouldmthe merits of simplicity and finality and would therefore reduce doubt an;given the unavoidably complex division of responsibilities in the devolutijscheme;   that the Assembly will be taking over the normal practicalresponsibilities of Parliament, and the citizen should be able to rely on]its la,ws as he now can on those of Parliament;   that judicial review causeijproblems in the operation of the Government of Ireland Act 1920 and wastherefore deliberately excluded by Parliament in enacting the NorthernIreland Constitution Act 1973;   and that the three successive checks on vijbefore Assembly Bills become lav; (see paragraphs 53-54 9-&quot;00V9) should be asufficient safeguard.52. The Government would welcome&quot; public discussion before reaching a finaldecision.53*   There remains private legislation, promoted by private persons and bodies such as local authorities on particular matters which affect them put not the general public interest.     In the devolved fields the Scottish!Assembly should clearly have power to pass private as well as publiclegislation.    But the procedures are complex, and it would be hard tc fitthe detail into the Act.     The Government therefore envisage that the Act;should contain a general provision enabling Her Majesty by Order in Counoito provide for the handling of private legislation by the Assembly in Scot!as soon as a suitable scheme has been worked out.     If that has not been jachieved by the time the Assembly takes over its main responsibilities, siScottish private legislation, including that on devolved subjects, willcontinue meanwhile to be dealt with by Parliament.     Present proceduresalready allow for hearings in Scotland.room for argument, which might otherwise18
(confidential)Delegated Legislation64.   The Scottish Executive will be able.to make delegated legislation underenabling powers contained either in Assembly Acts or in United Kingdom Actsstill in force in the devolved fields.65.   It will be for the Assembly to decide what should go into its own Actsand what should be left to delegated legislation, and also to lay doym anyprocedure required for delegated legislation under its Acts.     Anyprocedure in the Scottish Assembly for delegated legislation under UnitedKingdom Acts will be required initially to correspond as closely as possibleto whatever may be required in Parliament by the relevant Act;   it is right that the Scottish Executive should at that stage be bound by the procedures for control of delegated legislation which were considered to be a necessarypart of the Act when it was passed.     &apos;The Assembly^will later be freehowever, in the devolved fields, to pass Acts changing the procedures laiddown in the original United Kingdom Act.66.   Where a United Kingdom Act in a devolved field lays down, in order tocontrol expenditure, that delegated legislation shall be made jointly by two or more Ministers or with the consent of the Treasury or the CivilService Department, the power will pass simply to the Scottish Executive.Where a United Kingdom Act confers a power exercisable by Order in Council,that power will be exercisable by Order of the Scottish Executive.67,   The Assembly will be required in general terms to make arrangements forthe scrutiny of delegated legislation comparable to those operated at westminster through the Joint Committee on Statutory Instruments.     TheAssembly will be able if it wishes to use its &quot;subject&quot; Committees(paragraphs 73-76 below) for this purpose, or could set up a specialcommittee.United Kingdom Reserve Powers in Executive Matters68.   Paragraphs 53-57 above have explained the arrangements there will be toensure that in primary legislation the Assembly does not exceed its powers or act in a way judged to be seriously damaging.     Some similar provision is required to cover other actions - that is, executive acts or omissions.(For this purpose the term &quot;executive&quot; is taken to include delegated legislation. )
confidential)69.   There is no point in devolving substantial powers and then maintaigdetailed oversight from the centre.     The Government could not monitoreverything the Scottish administration^ &apos;do, nor indeed should they v:i:.vNevertheless, the Government must have power to step in where necessary!either because matters not devolved - such as defence - are beingprejudiced, or for wider reasons of their ultimate responsibility for sMthe people of the United Kingdom.70. The Government will have open to them three methods, for use eitherseparately or in combination:a. For actions in prospect, whether involving a proposed subordir.c.tlinstrument or some other proposed executive act, they will beable to issue a direction prohibiting the action or requiring aparticular course of action (including the reversal of a previcujaction), subject to an affirmative resolution by /both Houses 0?Parliament/ within a specified period,b. For subordinate instruments already made, they will be able toan annulment Order following an affirmative resolution by /JothHouses/.    In case of urgency the Order can be made without askiaj^Parliament/ first, but subject to affirmative resolution ivithiaspecified period,c. For other actions already taken, or for omissions, the GoverniMwill be able, if the Scottish administration decline to nut theimatter right, to resume responsibility for the devolved subjectquestion to the minimum extent necessary - for the required plaitask or period - with power to require and direct the use of theadministration&apos;s staff and facilities for the purpose.     They v;ildo this by Order, subject to affirmative resolution of ^/both Hoiof Parliament&quot;/.     The powers which the Government will be able tjtake by such an Order will be any powers available within exist!* For convenience, here and elsewhere in the white Paper (except Where 1jcontext clearly indicates otherwise) the term &quot;administration&quot; in rel;to Scotland is used in a broad sense to cover both the Assembly and tHExecutive in their complementary roles.20
statute law applying to Scot lard, though any requirement for Assemblyapproval (for example by affirmative resolution on a particular sort of sub-ordinate instrument) will be suspended.71*   As with the reserve pov/ers relating to Assembly Bills, these general procedures for intervening in the business of the Scottish administration should need to beused only rarely.     They will be there in the background as reserve powers;   andthey permit wider devolution than would otherwise be possible.     Their use willrequire the specific agreement of /^Parliament/.72.   All this is about circumstances in which the Government need to intervene on grounds of policy as distinct from law.     The legality of executive acts will beopen to challenge in the courts just like that of the executive acts of theGovernment themselves.As assembly Commit tee s73.   The Government are keen that there should be the maximum scope for allelected representatives to take a constructive part in the work devolved to theScottish administration.     The Assembly will therefore have a highly-developedrsystem of committees to advise the Executive and investigate what it is doing.74.   There will be a Committee of Assembly Members corresponding to each ofthe main subject fields of the Scottish Executive - education, health, and so on.The composition of these subject Committees will broadly reflect the politicalbalance of the Assembly as a whole;   and they will be chaired by Assembly members from outside the Executive.     Their staff will answer to them and the Assembly,not to the Executive.75.   Before the introduction of major new policies or Bills,  the Executive Memberresponsible will have to consult the relevant committee of the Assembly, except where the matter is especially urgent or confidential.     Before a Bill is introduced the committee may discuss its principles and report on it to theAssembly, as a prelude to general consideration of the Bill in plenary session.The Assembly may remit the detailed examination of a Bill (equivalent to theCommittee stage at Westminster) to the main appropriate subject committee with arrangements to associate any other committees whose subjects are affected.The committee may also scrutinise statutory instruments in its particular&apos; field.21
confidentialIt will have the right to offer suggestions to the Executive, to initialdiscussion and enquiries on particular topics, and in general to oversee t!work of the corresponding Executive department.76.    Officials and documents of the Executive will be under the Executive1;control;   but committees of the Assembly will no doubt ask for ExecutiveMembers and their officials to give oral and written evidence, and it willbe in the Executive1s own interest to co-operate.22
The Civil Service in Scotland77*   Members of the Executive will hold office under the Crown, and theirofficials will therefore he civil servants.   The Government have considered whether these should constitute a separate Scottish Civil Service, or be part of the United Kingdom Civil Service.   Most of them will in practice bepeople who are now United Kingdom civil servants in the Scottish Office.78.   The Kilbrandon Commission thought that there would have to he aseparate civil service, on the grounds that a devolved administration would wish to choose its own senior officials, might not be content for generalpersonnel matters to be handled by a United Kingdom Department, and would want to be able to rely on the undivided loyalty of their officials dealingwith the Government, for example on the block grant.79*   There are however strong arguments for maintaining a unified service.It would help the consultation and co-operation on which the success of devolution will heavily depend.   Present experience does not suggest thatwith a single service there need be divided loyalty; civil servants bytradition give wholehearted service to whichever Ministers are in chargeof their Departments.   We cannot assume that all staff will wish to transfer to a service entirely separate from that to which they were recruited3where the work, conditions and prospects might become substantiallydifferent.80.   Other factors must be taken into account.   A separate service would need more staff (for example to handle personnel matters new dealt withcentrally).   A unified service would enable the Scottish Executive to drawits officials more easily from a wide pool of talent and experience.   Thewishes of the Scottish administration itself xri.ll be important, and thesecannot be known until it is in being.   Finally, even if a separate Scottishservice were desirable it could not be set \xp for some yearsf it is an option only for the longer terme81.   The Government have therefore decided to keep a unified United Kingdomcivil service.   Any proposal for subsequent change would be a matter fordiscussion with the Scottish administration; staff representatives would be consulted at all stages.   It would be essential to maintain the traditionalindependence of the recruitment system.23
confidential)82..   Numbers and costs of staff are dealt with in Part VI.Complaints Machinery83c   Complaints against United Kingdom Departments can be investigated &quot;bythe Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration, the &quot;Ombudsman&quot;.Corresponding arrangements for the devolved subjects will need to be laiddown in the Act.   The details are outlined in Appendix B.The basic system for this important safeguard of the citisen&quot;s rights willbe laid down by Parliament; but in practice the new Scottish commissioner will report to the Assembly.European iiiCpmmunity jand Other International Aspects84*   The Government must remain responsible for all international relations,including those concerned with our membership of the European Community;no other course would be compatible with political unity.   Every member state !of the Community - including West Germany, for all its internal structure of federalism -is represented solely by its central government on thevarious bodies which deal with Community policy. It is the United Kingdom as 1whole which is a member of the Community,. and its Government must remain itsspokesman, in the Community as in other international business.85.   Nevertheless, both in European Community and in other contexts inter-national business touches increasingly on matters which x^all be devolved, iviews of the Scottish administration on these matters, reflecting their ovmcontacts with others concerned within Scotland such as local authorities.sus: Itaken into account.86.   No formal statutory machinery is needed for consultation; it will bebetter to develop pragmatic arrangements between members and officials ofthe Scottish administration and the Government.   These might operate most effectively through the Secretary of State for Scotland and through theparticular Ministers representing the United Kingdom in Brussels or elsewhere.87.   There remains the question of how to ensure that any relevant inter-national obligations are observed in the devolved fields in Scotland.There are two aspects to this: firstly ensuring that existing obligations__24^___.____fidential) , - ---^ . - y
are not breached, and secondly arranging that any positive action needed to fulfil new obligations is taken.88.   Breach of international obligation will be avoided in the normal way through the close consultation which the Government intend to maintain withthe Scottish Executive.   If, exceptionally, this does not work for any reason, and the Scottish Assembly sends forward a Bill or the Executivetakes some action contrary to the United Kingdom*s international obligations,the Government will be able to use their reserve powers for dealing with matters unacceptable on policy grounds.   These powers have been explained in paragraphs 55-56 and 70 above.   However, since international obligationis essentially a matter of fact and law (often involved and technical)rather than of general political judgement, the use of reserve powers inthese cases will not require the approval of Parliament.89*   Ensuring that positive action is taken as needed to fulfil newEuropean Community or other obligations is complex,.   On the one hand, theGovernment are answerable for getting this done.   On the other, the scottish administration, which will best know their own circumstances and legislation,ought not to be completely cut out of particular matters within devolvedsubjects whenever international commitments(including the increasing numberof European Community ones) happen to touch on theme   The best way of resolving this is for the Government to keep formal responsibility for all matters relating to international obligations, even when these matters arise in fields otherwise devolved; but for there to be power for the government at their discretion to delegate to the Scottish administration, by Order,the job of taking any necessary action, whether legislative or executive,to implement the obligation.   The power will be a flexible one, which canbe used to delegate action either on a particular item, such as an individual -dual European Community directive, or on a general area of business.   TheGovernment envisage that in practice it might well become the normal course to delegate implementation by agreement to the Scottish administration.The devolution Act will add the administration to the category of those who can be designated as implementing authorities under the European CommunitiesAct 1972.25
C.       FINANCE AND TAXATION90.   Financial arrangements lie at the heart of any scheme.   Those whichthe Government have chosen reflect their general approach to devolution,recognising continued political and economic unity and the need for close co-operation.   Paragraphs 91-97 &quot;below explain the basic concepts, which arethe same for both Scotland and Wales.   Paragraphs 9&amp;-110 then set out their detailed application to Scotland.The Basic Concepts91 *   The White Paper of September 1974 proposed that, as recommended by theKilbrandon Commission, the financial allocation for the devolved services should be in the form of a block grant voted by Parliament, taking accountboth of local needs and of the desirability of some uniformity of standards and contributions in all parts of the United Kingdom: and that it should thereafter be for the Assemblies to judge among competing claims,92.   Further study has confirmed that this is inescapable.   Economic unityrequires a system which considers the expenditure needs of the whole UnitedKingdom, including the claims of regions with special problems.   Thisrequires a decision each year on public expenditure for all parts of theUnited Kingdom by the Government, answerable to Parliaments93*   In theory one might base public expenditure for Scotland on revenuesarising there.   But even if they could be identified unequivocally, sucha system would be quite incompatible with distribution according to needo94*   The Government are well aware that the discovery of major oilfieldsunder the North Sea has given rise to ideas of a quite different kind,.There are some who argue that oil revenues should be controlled directly by those parts of the United Kingdom off whose shores the oil is found,whatever the effect elsewhere.   Let there be no misunderstandings such aproposal - whether its advocates realise this or not - would mean the break-up of the United Kingdom.   Unless oil is treated in the same way as other national resources (like the big coal deposits recently found inEngland, and the natural gas off its shores) and the benefits brought into -the national pool for distribution in accordance with relative needs, there .can be no economic unityf and without economic unity there can be no26
ntialpolitical unity.   Those who wish to reserve to Scotland oil or other revenuesarising there are in effect demanding a separate Scottish state.   The circlecannot he squared: it is not possible for Scotland - or any other part of theUnited Kingdom - to enjoy rights which can only go with separatism yet not tohave separatism itself.95.   For their part, the Government rule out separatism.   Even if on a narroweconomic calculation Scotland might be better off materially.for a time by keeping the benefits of oil exclusively to itself - and such a calculation wouldbe at best highly precarious, resting on limited reserves of a single commoditywhose value varies with the world market - the Government are convinced thatthe Scottish people are overwhelmingly opposed to destroying the Union.   TheGovernment repeat their pledge that all the regions most in need will receivetheir full and fair share of the benefits from the energy resources of thecontinental shelf, which belong to the United Kingdom as a whole.   In 1974-75expenditure on the services proposed for devolution was almost  2000 million.Had the proposed financial arrangements been in operation the block grant wouldhave accounted for at least  1300 million; local taxation for  300 million; andborrowing, charges for services and the like for the remainder.   Expenditureon the devolved services would have come to about three-fifths of totalidentifiable public expenditure in Scotland.96.   The Government accordingly intend that Scottish public expenditure shouldbe settled as part of the annual public expenditure review for the United kingdom as a whole.   The amount will be a matter for political judgement, on the basisof an assessment of relative needs made jointly with the Scottish administrationthrough close and continuous collaboration.   Once the relative amounts of public expenditure are established, Parliament will be asked to vote the appropriateelement for the devolved services in the form of a block grant.97*   No neat formula could be devised to produce fair shares for Scotland (andfor England, Wales and Northern Ireland) in varying circumstances from year to year.   The task involves judgements of great complexity and political sensitivity.Nevertheless, objective information on standards and needs would help the scottish administration, the Government and Parliament to make their judgements.   Variousarrangements might be adopted for collecting such information, and the Governmentwill discuss possibilities with   the Scottish administration.27
The Block Grant98.   Once the block grant has been voted by Parliament, it will be paid overat regular intervals during the financial year.   Accountability for theexpenditure will run not to Parliament but to the Assemblies.   The devolutionAct must lay down certain basic features of the financial control system, but its running will be overseen by the Scottish Assembly.99.   The Scottish administration will have the fullest possible freedom todecide, how the money from the block grant should be spent - how much, forexample, should go on roads, houses, schools and hospitals, and where in Scotlandit should be spent.   As the figures in paragraph 96 demonstrate this is a ms,joreconomic as well as social power.   It will give the administration a powerfulnew instrument for shaping developments over a wide range, of services,.100, The Governments decision on the total amount for all the devolved services will not be a, matter of simply imposing an arbitrary figure.    It will be the outcome of a close and thorough process of consxiltation each year with theScottish administration.   Appendix C outlines how the process might run in atypical year.101. The administration itfill base their proposals on their view of Scottishneeds in the devolved fields.    But the Government must take account; also ofother needs, both elsewhere in the United Kingdom and in non-devolved fieldswithin Scotland.   All these needs must then be related to what the United Kingdomcan afford for public expenditure against other claims, including the balance ofpayments, private investment and private consumption, as well as the needs ofpublic industries such as coal and steel which will continue to be very important to Scotland.102. With understanding on both sides agreement should usually be reached on atotal accepted as fair both to Scotland and to the rest of the United Kingdom.If agreement is not reached the matter will have to be settled by the Government,answerable to Parliament.   Parliament, with its Scottish MPs alongside those from all other parts of the United Kingdom, is the right body to vote the amountfor the devolved services, and to settle the statutory limits on total borrowing.28
(confidentialTaxation103. Scottish taxpayers v;ill contiruo to pay United Kingdom taxes at UnitedKingdom rates, and these payments will contribute to the central pool of national resources from which the block grant and other national expenditure will be financed according to needs.10/J. The Government have particularly considered whether the scottish administration should be able to levy taxes.   As already explained, therecan be no question of sharing responsibility for taxation generally or ofreserving for Scotland revenues raised there. The issue is rather whether theadministration should have power to levy limited additional taxation, in orderto finance extra expenditure which they think especially important.   The burden would have to fall solely on Scottish taxpayers, as the people getting thebenefits of the extra expenditure,105. The Government doubt whether the people of Scotland will want to pay more taxes regularly year after year in order to finance more public expenditure than   the assessment of their needs in the United Kingdom contextprovides.   Nevertheless, some powers for the devolved administrations to levyadditional taxation would give them greater freedom.    It is however difficultto identify suitable forms of tax.   There is no point, for example, in choosingtaxes unlikely to yield enough revenue to give much extra discretion; and itwould be wrong to choose ones which would fall too narrowly on particular groups.Among the specific possibilities which have been considered, the two found tomerit the most detailed study were a retail sale?.! tax (distinct from VAT) and asurcharge on income tax.    The studies shewed that, for either of these, therewould be great administrative complexities for both taxpayers and taxadministrations; and also heavy costs, falling on retailers or employers as wellas on the devolved administrations, for collection systems which would still need to be mai.nta.ined and paid for whether or not any extra taxes were levied in aparticular year.   Both possibilities were therefore unsuited for use assupplementary taxes to be applied at a low rate and truned on and off fromtime to time.   The Government have therefore concluded that the only taxpower suitable for devolution is a general power to levy a surcharge on localauthority taxation, whether on the rates as at&apos; present or on any now systemintroduced in the future (for example after the Committee of Inquiry into LocalGovernment Finance - the Layfield Committee - have reported)3   No tax is popular,99
, &quot;TTfl   ]in  mm- WWW B 1* II mm-11 mi mi 111 Mn. aWtWinii 1^confpf^TfAibut a power of this kind would give the Scottish administration a useful do*rHof discretion.   They will not have to use it unless they run into deficit ordeliberately aim for a higher level of expenditure, for example to meet some particular Scottish priority for which they judge taxpayers would be willir;?to accept higher burdens.106. Local authorities, who will run many of the devolved services, can settjtheir own levels of taxation, so that there will in any event be some flexiiin the total amount available for the services in Scotland.   The scottish administration will decide both how much of the block grant should bs district to local government and how to allocate it among individual authorities.   in calculating the block grant the Government will simply assume that scottish local authorities require as much grant in relation to their.needs and theirtaxable resources as authorities in England; whether they in fact levy more ogless local tax, and are assigned more or less stibsidy from the block grant, xbe a matter to be settled in Scotland.107* The sources of local authority taxation will be laid down in the Act, on!the.same basis as in England. The Scottish Assembly will however have powersto legislate on the system of rating and valuation for rating, so that it canadjusted to local conditions; but only Parliament will be able to authorise njforms of local taxation.Other Sources of Finance108, Capital expenditure by local authorities and by other public bodies indevolved fields will continue to be financed by borrowing.   Local authorities will continue to have access to the Public Works Loan Board.   Other public bodies will have access to a new Scottish Loans Fund for longer-term borrowin)financed from the National Loans Fund and controlled by the scottish administration.   The main condition on its use will be that on-lending should!not be at a lower rate of interest than the corresponding loan from the NatioLoans Fund.   The only long-term borrowing transactions controlled individual!by the United Kingdom Government will be those involving foreign currency oroverseas sources.   However, the Government must also control both the total amount of long-term borrowing and within this the total of borrowing from ofisources by local authorities and public corporations.   These controls are essential for the management of the United Kingdom econcomy.30denti
Financial Control and Audit109. The Act will lay down certain basic features to ensure that there isa sound system for authorising expenditure and reporting on the accounts.    Inaddition to the Scottish Loans Fund, there will be Scottish counterpartsof the Consolidated Fund, the Comptroller and.Auditor General and the public accounts Committee. The Assembly will have power to appropriate funds to individual services by Assembly Order, corresponding to Appropriation Actsat Westminster.110. Responsibility for controlling issues from the Scottish Funds and for supervising the arrangements for monitoring and audit will rest squarelywith Scottish bodies.   The reports of the Scottish Comptroller and AuditorGeneral will be presented to the Assembly and considered by the ScottishAccounts Committee, and it will be for the Assembly to decide where torequire comments or proposals from the Executive as a result..    The Actv/ill however require the publication of these reports, so that expenditureon devolved matters undergoes the same public scrutiny as the correspondingexpenditure does now.31
P.   THE DEVOLVED SUBJECTSThe General Approach111*   It is important to recognise what legislative devolution will mean.Where a subject field is devolved, responsibility for the activities ofgovernment in that field will be transferred to the Scottish administration,The present law will be inherited, but the administration will be free to change it.   They will not be confined to the activities going on now; theycould end activities, or create new ones, or run present ones in now ways;Devolving a subject field in Scotland is therefore not at all like justtransferring functions between United Kingdom Departments or between local jauthorities; it means much more.112.   The Government intend to apply this far-reaching concept to a massivehand-over of responsibility for Scotland&apos;s affairs.113.    The Act will devolve certain subjects; anything not shown as devolvedwill remain the direct responsibility of the Government and Parliament asat present.    The Government have in general approached the task of decidingwhich subjects to devolve from the positive standpoint of devolving where-ever possible, and keeping subjects back (or making exceptions withinsubjects otherwise devolved.) only where there is cogent reason for doing so - for example where devolution might risk damaging basic unity and thefundamental rights of United Kingdom citizenship, or where wider uniformityis plainly needed, or where devolving or dividing a subject would be veryawkward to work.114*    Paragraphs 115-164 below set out the effect of applying this approach, ,and Appendix D gives a tabular summary.   The Government believe that theresult is well suited to the interests of Scotland and of the United Kingdot Ias a whole, and that the -scale and character of the devolved responsibilityhwill enable the Scottish administration to take a broad and comprehensiveview of their tasks in serving the people of Scotland.Local Government115.    Responsibility for central government supervision of most aspects oflocal government in Scotland will be devolved.   The administration will-32
oversee the work of local authorities in devolved natters, will allocaterate support grant to them, will control their capital investment in the devolved fields and. will he responsible for the application of the local taxation system as explained in paragraphs.106-107*    The Government believethat it would not be in the interests of either the Assembly or Scottish localgovernment   for the new structure of local authorities and the distribution of functions among them to be radically revised yet again in the next few year.These must however be matters for the Assembly; and. it will be empowered to legislate on local government administrative and electoral boundaries, theapplication of the rating system and the division of devolved functions between local authorities and the Scottish Executive, as well as on the structure oflocal government itself.116. Responsibility will not be devolved for determining the qualifications for voting in local government elections; the qualifications for and dis-qualifications from membership of local authorities; the voting system for localgovernment elections; and the frequency with which they are held.   These basicdemocratic features of the local government system s?would remain under the direct authority of Parliament.117. The Scottish administration will not of course be responsible for anyfunctions Scottish local authorities continue to carry out in matters which arenot devolved; these will remain under the control of the Government,Health118. The Scottish administration will be   responsible for health matters inScotland, including the National Health Service.   This means that they willbe free to determine the arrangements for and priorities within the provisionof health care, including the resources to be allocated.   In this as in other fields (see paragraph 156 below) certain United Kingdom arrangements and standardswill continue to apply - for example on medicines and drugs - but in generalthe administration will be able if they wish to vary the scope and characterof current arrangements, and to decide policy on such matters as family planning,transplant surgery, abortion, private practice and the control of nursing homes.33
119*    The Scottish administration will &quot;be responsible for the social workservices, such as the care of children, the elderly, the handicapped   and iothers in need of special care or support.   They will be able to control the standards of private provision in these fields, and to make grants to voluntary bodies.120.    The social security system, which provides.a network of cash benefitspayable to individuals and families, will not be devolved.    It is necessaryto keep a single system of cash benefits designed to maintain a decentminimum standard of living for every citizen throughout the United Kingdom,The war pensions scheme will also remain on a United Kingdom basis.121.    Some problems arise because of the close and often complicated inter-:action between social security benefits and schemes for rent and raterebates, rent allowances, and the minimum charges and personal allowances for those living in local authority homes.   The Government&apos;s approval willbe required for any changes in such schemes which would affect wholly or mainly people receiving supplementary benefits, or people who would receive them if the changes were made.    The reason for this special provision isthat the burden would then fall directly on United Kingdom funds, not the block grant or the rates.    It is a more open question whether, because ofthe complexity of the interaction with social security generally, it wouldbe better not to devolve powers relating to such schemes at all.   TheGovernment a,re inclined in favour of devolution, but would welcome commentsfrom bodies working in this field.Education^ Science and the Arts122.    The Scottish administration will be responsible for all educational and cultural matters other than those noted in paragraphs 124-126  below-They will control the schools system in Scotland, and will be able if they wish to determine (for example) its standards and structure, its curricula)its attendance requirements such as age levels, and policy for privateschools and nursery education.   They will be responsible for all further and higher education except the universities, and for youth and community services.-34
123. The administration will he responsible also for the arts (except theexport control of works of art) and for national and local libraries, museums and galleries.124. Responsibility for the universities will not be devolved.   The government believe that it is in the best interests of the United Kingdom, including Scotland,that they should continue to be run as part of a wider United Kingdom system andunder the supervision of a single University Grants Committee.   At the name time,the Government attach importance to close and effective liaison between the ScottishUniversities and those other parts of the higher education system which will come under the control of the Scottish administration.   The University GrantsCommittee will therefore be asked to devise arrangements recognising the specificScottish dimension of their business, and linking the Scottish administration withthese arrangements.125. It would make no sense to break up the five Research Councils, and responsibility for them vii11 not be devolved.   The Scottish administration wouldbe able (preferably in consultation with United Kingdom departments concerned)to commission research from the Councils.   Responsibility for the NatureConservancy Council will similarly not be devolved.126, Partly because of the decisions explained in paragraphs 124-125, andpartly also to avoid difficulties or friction in the present wide inter-changeof students among higher education establishments throughout the United Kingdom,responsibiltiy will not be devolved for postgraduate awards and for awards to scottish domiciled students on courses of advanced further education (thoughthe Scottish administration will be responsible for policy on awards made byeducation authorities to students following other courses of further education)for postgraduate awards.52HSi2S127. The Scottish administration will be responsible for all aspects of housing,except that in order to maintain proper management&apos;of the United Kingdom economythe Government will keep control of housing finance by the private sector(building society mortgages and the like), and also a reserve power toprevent or restrict increases in public and private-sector rents wheregeneral economic and counter-inflationary policy makes this
necessary.    These limited qualifications apart, the Scottish administration will &quot;be able to have their own laws and policies, for both the public andthe private sector, on the provision and upkeep of accommodation, the con-t;rol of rents, subsidies to local authorities and housing associations,renovation, building standards and slum clearance.Physical Planning and the Environment128. -The Scottish administration will be responsible for physical planning Iand the environment.   They will deal with all general aspects of land use -how to manage development and control, how to coordinate its use with (forexample) transport planning, and how to provide the general infrastructureneeded for Scotland&apos;s prosperity.   They will deal with the general improve-ment of the environment; the rehabilitation of derelict land; all aspectsof water such as supply, amenity planning, arterial drainage, sewerage anasewage disposal; new towns; and the protection-of countryside amenity and land129.   The administrations powers over land must however be qualified.Firstly, it is essential that the new community land legislation should apply uniformly; divergences could lead to damaging economic distortions.The Scottish administration will however have substantial supervisoryfunctions under the legislation.   Secondly, the devolution of planningpowers will be subject to a continuing right - which should not need to beused often - for the Government to &quot;call in&quot; any particular planning issuefor their decision if the general United Kingdom interest is affected, forexample on non-devolved matters like defence or energy.   The Governmentwill probably also need to keep the right to settle any disputes over coa-pulsory purchase affecting such matters.130.   The Scottish administration will be responsible for sport and recreation, parks and open spaces, ancient monuments and historic buildings public and civic amenities, and a variety of other matters like refusecollection and disposal, cemeteries, markets, fairs and allotments.\ Theywill be responsible also for dealing with natural emergencies (though any use of the armed forces to help in these must of course remain a matter for aGovernment).   They will be responsible for protecting the environment, in- Ieluding preventing nuisances, atmospheric pollution and noise, except in36
relation to aircraft, motor vehicles and ships; some aspects of these arethe subject of international agreements and others raise defence or other national considerations, so that they must remain matters for the Government.Roads and Transport131*   The Scottish administration will be responsible for a wide range of matters in the transport field.    These will include the planning, con-struction and standards of roads; the application of traffic rules (except on motorways, where uniformity throughout Great Britain is important forsafety); road safety publicity; local transport planning,including matters relating to passenger transport areas; road service licensing, includingappointing Traffic Commissioners and hearing appeals from them; bus and shipping services of the Scottish Transport Group; subsidies for shipping and air services to the Highlands and Islands, and for impro\ring piers andboatslips; inland waterways; examining and paying claims for new bus grants;the current powers to pay fuel duty rebate to bus operators; and generaloversight of local authority powers to subsidise passenger transport ser-vices, including rail and bus services.132.    There are certain matters in the field of road transport where, forsafety reasons, practice needs to be the same throughout Great Britain.These include framing (as distinct from applying) rules for traffic manage-ment; motoring offences; the Highway Code; the system for testing andlicensing drivers and public service vehicles; and the transport of dangeroussubstances.   Responsibility for these will not be devolved.133*    Responsibility for local authority airports will be devolved fromthe&apos;outset.   For airports owned and operated by the British airports authority the Government will discuss future arrangements with the scottish administration, and aim to achieve a transfer of responsibility while retaining the managerial expertise of the Authority in Scotland.    similar arrangements would be made for aerodromes owned and operated by the CivilAviation Authority.Development and Industry134.    The Scottish Development Agency will have a key role in both theenvironmental field and the industrial field.   The devolution Act will not37
change the powers of the Agency.    Its environmental functions will be fulldevolved, and so will its factory building functions, expect that terms ondisposal must remain under United Kingdom Government control - it would Jbe in the interests of any part of the United Kingdom to create the poosijbility of a price war in making industrial premises available to attractincoming firms.    The other industrial functions of the Agency cannot be devolved, because of the need to preserve economic unity; the arrangementsfor dealing with these are set out in Part V, on the role of the Secretaryof State for Scotland.   Half the members of the Board of the Agency willbe appointed by the Scottish administration, which will also be consulted before the Secretary of State appoints the Criairman.135*   Fon the Highlands and Islands Development Board., which deals with a range of specialised problems,   responsibility for both economicand. social activities will be devolved.    The Scottish administration will appoint the   Chairman and members, and in devolved fields such as tourismwill have full discretion in supervising the Board&apos;s activities.    But for board activities in reserved fields,, for example assistance to industry,fishing and agriculture, the Government will lay down a system of guide-lines and cash limits on individual projects within which the Board andthe Scottish administration will decide their own priorities: major iridusjtrial projects will be reserved to the Scottish Development Agency and thjSecretary of State.   Changes in the Board&apos;s powers and the geographicalarea which it covers will also be a matter for the Secretary of State.136.   There can be no question of breaking up the main nationalised inclus-tries or splitting responsibility for them, but the Government envisagethat there should be informal contacts between them and the Scottish adnirstration on matters of joint interest.   The industries will no doubt besympathetic to requests that their reports should give information on recent developments and future plans for Scotland.   The administration wibe able to consider these reports, and to make representations to theindustries or to Ministers.137*   relations with industry and commerce are an important element of managing the United Kingdom economy as a whole.   Central departments ofthe Government will therefore keep their present statutory functions; hutthey will consult the Office of the Secretary of State or the devolvedadministration on matters of common concern.38
Natura1 Resources138.    The Scottish administration will &quot;be responsible for functions rela-ting to land and natural resources now carried out by the Department ofAgriculture for Scotland.   These will include crofting end freshwater fisheries, and also forestry - especially important in Scotland - with theregulatory and international aspects-   The Act will maintain the forestry commission, already based in Edinburgh, as the instrument for carrying outScottish policies.   For these it will be financed by and accountable to theScottish administration.139*    The administration will be responsible also for agricultural estate management and the improvement of fisheries harbours. The main aspects ofagriculture and sea fisheries are however too bound up with overall United-Kingdom economic management and international agreements for devolution tobe practicable.exception (an essential consequence of United Kingdom unity) of fiscal39
Law .&quot;o,d the Lggal S,73torn140   The separate character of Scots law and of the Scottish legal system was specially recognised in the Union between Scotland and England,and in this distinctively Scottish field the Government believe that extensidevolution is particularly appropriate.141   The Scottish administration will have wide responsibilities in the range of subjects constituting Scots private lav;, such as the law of personsdelict, contract, property, trusts and succession.   The Government recogniseimportance of the development and reform of Scots law as a coherent anddistinctive system.   There is however a complex interaction between-these subjects and areas such as company law, industrial relations and consumer protection where consistency with law in the rest of the United Kingdom isparticularly important, for example in order to maintain a common framework for trade.   Further study is proceeding to find the best way of reconcilingmaximum devolution in the field of private lav; with these wider United. Kingdttinterests.142   The Scottish Lav; Commission will after devolution have a major role inthe coherent development of the whole of Scots law, both devolved and non-devolved.   Because the Commission&apos;s functions will span both fields, legislat:responsibility for its constitution and structure must remain with parliament the Scottish administration will however be responsible for appointing thechairman and members of the Commission, for its running and for its general programme of work, though the Government will remain able to refer non-devobmatters to it.143   The Scottish administration will also be given responsibility for thegeneral criminal law, including the right to create new offences, to redefireor abolish existing offences, to determine penalties and to regulate thetreatment of offenders (including prisons).   There will however be certain exceptions.   First, there are those touching on the security of tho state, 1:the lav; on treason, espionage, and measures against terrorism.   Second, theffare areas where the lav; can work efficiently only if it is uniform, such asexplosives, firearms, and dangerous drugs and poisons.   Finally, there areoffences relating essentially to subject fields which will not be devolved,-taxation and road traffic.law.40
144   The enforcement of the criminal law through the police and the prosecutionsystem - which in Scotland is not in any way under the control of the police -is part of the responsibility of the United Kingdom Government for the maintenanceof law and order and the security of the state, and will extend to offenceswithin both devolved and other fields.    It would not be right that responsibilityfor law enforcement should rest with members of an administration who are not directly answerable to Parliament.   The Secretary of State and the Lord Advocatewill therefore retain their present responsibilities with regard to police andprosecution respectively.   The police will retain their existing status and theirrelationship with local authorities, and the- function of prosecution will continueto be exercised through the Crown Office ani the procurator fiscal service.14&apos;)   The Government have considered with special care where responsibility should lie for the main Scottish courts - the supreme courts (the High Court ofJusticiary and the Court of Session), the sheriff courts and the district courts.The Government are satisfied that responsibility for the different levels ought not to be split - separation would pose difficult problems over such matters asjurisdiction, procedure and administration.   They believe that the supreme court judges should continue to be appointed by The Queen on the recommendation of theGovernment, and that responsibility for their tenure and conditions of office should not be devolved.   The Government also believe that questions affectingthe right of appeal from the Coxirt of Session to the House of Lords - which isimportant as a court of final appeal in civil matters from the courts of every partof the United Kingdom - must remain a United Kingdom responsibility.146   There remains however the question whether responsibility for the courtsystem and its administration should remain with the Government and Parliament,or should be devolved (with the qualifications noted, in the previous paragraph).Powerful arguments conflict.   The courts are a distinctive part of the Scottishlegal heritage, and may therefore seem wholly suitable to be entrusted to the care of Scotland5s hew Assembly, under Parliament5s continuing ultimatesovereignty.   The concept of the development of Scots lav; as a coherent systemargues in favour of devolving the courts and the legal system along with the substantive law.   It may be difficult, if responsibility is split, to decide thea,llooa.tion of such border-dine topics as court procedure and the law of evidence.41
On the other hand, it is arguable that the courts are essential elements in the core of constitional unity of the United Kingdom and in the fabric if-&apos;lav: and order; and that since they have to deal with disputes involving boBdevolved and non-devolved law, they should not be the responsibility of anlAssembly which has no function&apos;.-; in the&apos; non-devolved fields. The same factBof public policy and national security which are relevant to the police anBprosecution functions (paragraph 144 above) point towards maintaining UnitedKingdom responsibility for the courts and their jurisdiction, administratiBprocedure.147 The Government would welcome public comment and discussion beforetalcing a final decision on. the&quot; question.Tourism1.48   The Scottish administration will be responsible for tourism in Scotlandincluding the Scottish Tourist Board.   Overseas promotion will remain theresponsibility of the British Tourist Authority, which will receive funds ftthe Government for promoting tourism to Scotland as vie 11 as to England amiWales.    If the Scottish administration want to give the Authority extra fuatfor specific promotions overseas, or to give work to other agencies, they sibe free to do so; but they will not receive extra United Kingdom funds for!these purposes.Other Matters149 The administration will be responsible also for a wide variety of ot.%matters such as fire services; betting, gaming and lotteries; fixing public holidays and summertime; the registration of theatrical employers; controllcharitable collections; Sunday observance; shop hours; the functions now caIout by the Registrar General for Scdtland such as the registration of birthmarriages and deaths and the administration of marriage law (but not the )i- jcensus - paragraph 161 below); and licensing theatres, cinemas, taxis, iimmusic and dancing.
150   It will not &quot;be possible to decide whether the administration shouldhave a role in relation to broadcasting until the committee on the futurestructure of broadcasting, under the chairmanship of Lord Annan, has reported.Technical factors and international obligations will in any event make it essential to keep United Kingdom control of frequencies and transmitter power.Nominated Bodies151   The Scottish administration will be responsible for nominated bodiesoperating wholly in Scotland on devolved matters unless, exceptionally,- itproves necessary in a particular case to set special limitations.   this responsibility will include, financing, accountability, reporting and appointment(though recommendations for appointments by the Crown will need to be made througthe Secretary of State).   The administration will inherit all powers under existing legislation affecting those bodies, and will be able to change that legislation if they wish, including abolishing the bodies or creating new ones.If changes are needed in bodies constituted by Royal Charter or Warrant, these bodies will themselves have to apply for the necessary amendments to theirconstitutions.152   Bodies operating in Scotland in devolved matters but organised on a united Kingdom or Great Britain basis raise more complicated problems. - Theywill continue initially to operate as they do now; they will have no formalaccountability to the Scottish administration and, where they are financed nowthrough Parliament, this will continue.   However, by normal consultation and agreement the Government will be able to secure changes their activities andmembership, and executive bodies will be able to act as the agents of theScottish administration, provided all this can be arranged within the broadscope of the bodyfs general policy, its legal powers and,where appropriate, itscontinuing primary responsibility to the Government.   There will also be provision for the Government, by Order subject to affirmative resolution ofParliament, to make any legal changes which may be needed to the formal structure and powers of a particular body in order to reflect any agreement between themand the Scottish administration, in consultation with the body itself.In the last resort, however,    if agreement is not reached on43
either informal or formal adjustments, the Scottish administration will be free (unless exceptionally the devolution Act provided specially for themaintenance of a particular body, like the Highlands and Island Itevolopetjn.Board) to make quite new arrangements and terminate a particular body1 sresponsibilities in Scotland.153. The staff of a nominated body operating wholly in Scotland in a devolvedfield who are civil servants will be treated like other civil servants in tiiedevolved fields; they will continue to belong to a unified United Kingdom senwhile there is one. Any consultations between the administration and theGovernment about setting up a separate Scottish Civil Service (paragraph 81 alwould include the future of civil servants serving with nominated bodies.The Scottish administration will inherit whatever responsibilities the Govern:now have in relation to staff who are not civil servants.154. With nominated bodies opera/bing on a United Kingdom or Great Britain basi(paragraph 152), there will be no change in responsibility for staff matters,155&apos; Appendix E lists the nominated bodies to which the arrangements in paragr,151-154 above are expected to apply.General Standards156. There are a number of matters in which common rules and standards are important, either for safety or to maintain a fair and consistent framework for industry and commerce everywhere.   They cover the regulation or statutorystandards of marketing, composition, labelling and performance of commonly te:articles or goods, including in particular food (and its handling), medicines,drugs, animal feeding-stuffs and pesticides; construction standards for vehicl;and safety standards for fuel-burning appliances, for the use of gas, and forarticles used in the home such as inflammable textiles.   They also include thelaw on trade unions, labour and industrial relations; consumer credit; exportcredit; competition policy; fair trading; insurance; patents, trade marks, desand copyright; weights and measures; and shipping and civil aviation.       [  jResponsibility for these matters, even where they affect fields otherwisedevolved., mast in general remain with the Government, though as explained inparagraph 141 above the relationship between the Governmenfs responsibility&apos;the responsibilities to be devolved in the field of Scots private law needsfurther study.44
(confidential)Pay in the Public Sector157   The Government must retain in their hands all the means necessary tofight inflation, including the degree of control or influence they now have over public sector pay and related conditions, including pensions.   TheScottish administration&apos;s powers over pay and conditions in the devolved services cannot therefore be unlimited; their decisions vail need to be related to wider considerations of national economic or pay policy.   Accordingly,there will be a general requirement in the Act for the administration to take account of any such wider considerations brought specially to their attentionby the Government.    In addition, in fields where the Government now exercise,in one way or another, general control over pay and conditions of service(as in the health service ), the consent of theSecretary of State will be required for any changes.   Moreover, the Governmentexpect that, where pay in any area of the public services is now settled by national negotiations covering $he whole of Great Britain, such arrangements- -with appropriate representation for the Scottish administration - will continueafter devolution, whether or not the Secretary of state&apos;s consent is requiredto the outcome.Regulation of the Professions158   There are certain occupational groups whose training is controlled by statute, or which have legal powers of self-regulation whereby only peoplerecognised by the group can lawfully claim to be qualified to practise itsskills.    The question arises how far the Scottish administration should be ableto legislate about the regulation of such groups.159   The Government wish to hear comments from appropriate professional bodiesbefore reaching a definite conclusion; but they provisionally favour devolvingpower to legislate about the control only of professions which in scotland will be mainly employed by or under contract tothe Scottish administration orbodies subordinate to it; examples would be teachers, the health professions and town planners, but not, say, architects or engineers.   The Government alsoprovisionally favour devolving power to legislate about the control of thedistinctively Scottish legal profession.45
(confidential)Statistics and Other Information160 The right to collect,, relevant statistics and other information goesnaturally with responsibility for particular services; and the scottish administration will have this right in the devolved fields. The Governmentexpect that, through consultation, the administration would seek to avoidcollection demands overlapping with United Kingdom ones, and to achieveconsistency and compatibility with data from other parts of the United kingdom?The Government for their part would seek to respond helpfully to any needs whjjthe Scottish administration had for information on matters not devolved.16.1    The population censuses gather important information relevant to bothdevolved and non-devolved matters.      They must therefore remain basically amatter for the Government.     The Government would however take into accountany views of the Scottish administration in determining the scope and content of census-taking, and would hope to continue to conduct it through the registrar General for Scotland, whose other functions will come under theScottish administration.162   The Government will continue to need information on devolved services,for example on matters where they have to provide consistent United Kingdomdata, to international organisations.     Such information would be suppliednormally through consultation end agreement;   but to ensure that they remainable to meet their responsibilities there will be a general provision in theAct requiring the Scottish administration to furnish information to theGovernment on request.163   The law on the protection of official information will apply in the devolved fields as it does now in Government business, and the scottish administration and the Government will be bound to safeguard each other&apos;sconfidential information.     The Assembly could however make new laws if itwished about information in devolved matters.Tribunal s jtnd iInquiries164   Within devolved fields, the Scottish administration will inherit any existing statutory powers relating to the establishment or constitution of tribunials and inquiries.     They will be able also, if they wish, to changethese inherited powers, to set up new tribunals and to make rules.     TheCouncil on Tribunals and its Scottish Committee, which cover matters that
will not be devolved as well as those that will, will remain a United Kingdomre spons5.b ility.2.    SU&apos;1&apos;APY CP THE SCHEME ?0K SCOTLAND165   These proposals create for Scotland an elected Assembly which acrossa great range of subjects will take, over the job now clone by Parliament;   andthey create a Scottish Executive which, in these subjects, will have the wideresponsibility now borne by the G-overnment.166   There are some specific restrictions and some general constitutionalsafeguards.     But, in practice, formal intervention by the Government shouldbe exceptional.      Close and constant co-operation should be the keynote.Within the devolved fields - notably local government, important lav.&apos; functions,health,  social work,  education, housing, physical planning, the environment,roads and traffic, crofting, most aspects of forestry and many aspects oftransport - the Scottish Assembly will pass laws and the Scottish Executivewill control administration.      Organisation and policies in these fieldswill be a matter for them.      To finance what they want to do they will have a block grant from United Kingdom taxation which they can allocate as they wish.      They will be able, if they choose, to levy a. surcharge on localgovernment revenue.167   Scottish Ministers in the Government - the Secretary of State forScotland and the Lord Advocate - will continue to have a major role, asPart V explains.     In broad terms, however, control of the great bulk ofpublic services which affect the people of Scotland will be in the hands ofthe new Scottish institutions.47(confidential)
(confidential)PART IV: wales.   THE BACKGROUND TO DEVOLUTION IN WALES168   Wales has been politically united with England for much longer than has Scotland, and has been more closely associated in matters of law and administration.   Nevertheless, the distinctive traditions and needs of wales have led to increasing pressure for separate governmental arrangements.More and more government work has been moved to Wales, and more and morebodies set up to deal with.Welsh problems.     In 1951 the office of Ministerfor Welsh Affairs was created and allocated to the Home Secretary alongsidehis other duties;   and in 1964 the Labour Government appointed the first secretary of State for Wales.   The work of his department, the Welsh Office,now covers such matters as housing and local government, some industrialdevelopment functions, town and country planning, highways, health, personal social services, and primary and secondary education;   and he shares respon-sibility for agricultural policy and its execution.     The Secretary ofState also has a general role of keeping in touch with government business in Wales which is not his executive responsibility, and representing Wales&apos;interests.   This is particularly important in the economic field.169   The presence of the Secretary of State in the Cabinet and Welsh Officerepresentation 6n interdepartmental committees has brought great advantages to Wales.   These advantages must not be lost.   The Secretary of State will carry out many important functions.   But a Welsh Assembly is needed to administer a wide range of other major matters, so as to make governmentin Wales more open and more directly accountable to the Welsh people, andto preserve and foster the rich national heritage of the Principality.170  Plans for the Welsh Assembly represent a major advance from the presentposition.   That position is however not the same as in Scotland.   There is ntseparate legal system and therefore no general problem about distinctivelegislation needed for Wales.   Moreover, the Governments consultationssuggest that whereas public opinion in Scotland favours a legislativeassembly, the situation in Wales is different.   The desire is for betterdemocratic control over the government already carried out in Wales, par-ticularly by non-elected bodies.&apos;    48(confidential)
(confidential)171   The Government have therefore decided in favour of a Welsh Assemblywith very substantial policy-making and executive powers and wide res-ponsibility for democratic oversight.     The Government believe that sucha body will meet the needs and aspirations of the great majority of thepeople of Wales.172   The description of the scheme in the following paragraphs is self-contained.   For brevity, however, where features are essentially thesame as those for Scotland they are set out in factual terms withoutrepetition of all the reasons set out earlier in this White Paper.Cross-references are given where appropriate.49
(confidential)B. CONSTITUTIONAL arrangements the Welsh Assembly173   There will be a directly-elected single-chamber Welsh Assembly consistto begin with, of 72 members - two for each of the 36 Parliamentary constituencies in Wales.   At the first election each elector will be able to vote for two candidates, and in each Parliamentary constituency the two with aostvotes will become Assembly Members.   For later elections the Boundary Corn-mission will divide Parliamentary constituencies as necessary into single-member Assembly constituencies.   Each Parliamentary constituency will be allotted one, two or three Assembly seats, according to a formula based onthe average size of Parliamentary electorates in Wales.   The formula vailbe this:-a. Parliamentary constituency whose electorate is less 1 Assemblthan 757&amp; of the average electorate                                       constituency!b. Parliamentary constituency whose electorate is not less 2 Assemblythan 75/^ and not more than 125% of the average elec- constituenttor atec. Parliamentary constituency whose electorate is more 3 Assemblythan 125% of the average electorate constituencyOn present electorates, this system would give an Assembly of about 75   &amp;e.- begThe formula will be re-applied, and any necessary re-division made, wheneverParliamentary seats are re-distributed.   The divisions into Assembly constituencies will be embodied in draft Orders in Council laid before Parliament trjthe Secretary of State.174 Everyone entitled to vote in Westminster elections, and also peers., willbe able to vote in Assembly elections; but no-one will have a vote in morethan one constituency. The Secretary of State for Wales will be responsiblefor general oversight of Assembly elections and for making rules for them, onelection expenses and the like.175 The Assembly will be elected for a normal fixed term of four years, butthe Secretary of State will have power to make minor adjustments either wayto yield a convenient election day._ 50_(confidential)
176   The time, place and other arrangements for the first meeting vail hedetermined by the Secretary of State.   Thereafter these matters will befor the Assembly itself to decide.177     Matters affecting Assembly membership, such as the rules aboutqualification, disqualification, expulsion and resignation, will bedealt with in the Act, as will the special safeguards which members will need to   do their job, such as protection against actions for defama-tion.   Membership of the Assembly will not be barred to Members of theHouse of Commons or the House of Lords.   Practical considerations willoften prevent them from standing for election to the Assembly, but itdoes not seem right that they should be excluded by statute.   Qualificationand disqualification are dealt with in more detail in Appendix A.178  Every candidate elected to the Assembly will have tc swear or affirmallegiance to the Crown before taking his seat.179 The pay and allowances of Assembly Members will be determined initiallyby the Secretary of State and thereafter by the Assembly itself.180   The Secretary of State vail make interim Standing Orders to get theAssembly started, but thereafter it will make its own, subject to anyrequirements in the Act - for example on the use of Committees (paragraphs184-191    below).181   The Assembly will elect from among its members a presiding officer,Like the Speaker in the   House of Commons.182  The Secretary of State will not be an ex officio member of the Assembly.But the Assembly and the Secretary of State could arrange by agreement for him to attend and address meetings from time to time.183  The use of the Welsh language in Assembly proceedings and workingdocuments will be for the Assembly itself to decide.
CONFlDEMTiExecutive Powrers and Committees of the Welsh Assembly184   Executive powers in the devolved matters will be vested in theAssembly as a corporate body (and a Crown body).   This means that therewill not be a sharp distinction between an Executive sponsoring policies and an Assembly discussing and questioning these policies.   Instead allpolicy discussion and decision-making will rest with the Assembly itself,Moet of its work, ..however, will be carried out through Standing committeesset up to deal with particular devolved subjects, like health and education. IThe Assembly1 s powers will be exercised (like the Secretary of State&apos;snow) in a variety of ways - political or administrative decision, issuingof circulars, resolutions of the Assembly or Committees, and delegated legislation.185   This system, which is well suited to a body which will not have todeal with primary legislation, will allow maximum democratic participation in making decisions, since all members will have a positive role.   the detailed pattern will to a great extent be for the Assembly itself todecide, but the Act will lay down the general framework.186 The Act vail empower the Assembly to delegate its functions to the cos-mittees. The Assembly will be required to set up committees to cover all themain devolved subjects, and to ensure that representation on the committeesibroadly based, so as to. reflect the political balance in the Assembly.187   Each subject committee will have a chairman, to conduct the businessimpartially;   there will also be a leader (to be known as the Executive Memtfwho will take the main initiative on policy and administration and will he it Imain link with the officials working on the committee1s particular subject,;committee will be able to delegate powers to sub-committees or to theExecutive Member.188  The committee chairmen and the Executive Members will&apos;be appointed &quot;bythe Assembly.189  There will be a central co-ordinating committee (to be known as the Etc representative Committee) to oversee general policy and the allocation of   resources. Ivail provide a body of manageable size to draw business togetherjto ensure tilcohesive proposals are presented to the Assembly and to act for the Assemblyas a whole on major issues affecting several subjects, including discussion!with the Government on the size of the block grant. I
confidential)190   The Executive Committee vail comprise all the Executive Members from the major subject committees plus any other members (not exceeding a quarter of thetotal)   specially appointed by the Assembly.   The Assembly vail also appoint the Chairman, to be known as the Chief Executive. There will be no formal limits on the powers of the Executive Committee;    but its main purpose will be tosettle the allocation of resources between the services administered by the subjectcommittees, and to see that policies are consistent.191   The control of officials and documents&apos;will be formally vested in theAssemblyfwhich will have, as a body, the formal right of full access todepartmental papers and officials.   However, it would obviously not be con-sistent with practical government for every   Assembly Member to be able to demand the attendance of any official or insist on seeing any document.   TheAssembly will therefore be empowered to confer right of access only oncommittees acting in their particular fields of responsibility   or throughthose committees, on Executive Members or sub-committees similarly acting.Individual Assembly Members will have no general right of access.Legislation for Wales192   Parliament will continue to legislate for Wales in the devolvedsubjects as well as in others.     The Welsh Assembly will therefore work within the limits of Westminster Acts.   But in controlling the devolved services it will take over powers conferred by those Acts on centralgovernemnt, including the power to make delegated legislation.193   This division of responsibility for primary legislation and for executionpresents some problems.     The formal position is qu ite clear:    the assembly will be able to do anything in relation to devolved matters that doesnot require new primary legislation.   This means that its powers will vary from service to service, depending on the degree to which primary legislationlays down detailed requirements.   In some subjects Wesminster Acts are infairly general terms, leaving plenty of scope for discretion in day-to-day administration;   in others they are drawn more tightly.   So the degree of freedom which the Assembly will enjoy at the start of its life vail to someextent be uneven.
(confidential)194   As the work of the Assembly develops, new factors will come into play.The Assembly will take a close interest in proposed United Kingdom legislateaffecting Wales.    It will debate such documents as White Papers and GreenPapers outlining the Governmenfs plans for legislation.    Its officials willbe consulted by their government counterparts as appropriate when new legis-lation affecting devolved matters is being prepared.   The Assembly will beable to debate United Kingdom Bills as they are published. It will no doubtmake representations to the Secretary of State for Wales and to others, suchas Welsh MPs and Government Departments, suggesting how Bills might be improve!to fit Welsh needs. It may sometimes take the initiative itself and press for new Westminster legislation.   In time Parliament might wish to give theAssembly greater discretion, by passing legislation which would lay dov;n onlybroad guidelines, leaving the Assembly to fill in the rest.195   None of this can be exactly planned.   Since Parliament cannot bind itssuccessors, there can be no commitment for the future to alter United KingdoaBills to suit the Welsh Assembly, to introduce legislation for Wales different from that for England, or to implement any concept of &quot;framework&quot; legislation,The pattern must evolve naturally.Delegated Legislation196   In devolved matters the Welsh Assembly will have general responsibilityfor framing and passing delegated legislation under   powers conferred by existing or future United Kingdom Acts.   There may be some exceptions, butthey will be few.   In general, the Welsh Assembly will deal with all classesof delegated legislation.197  Where a United Kingdom Act in a devolved field lays down, in order tocontrol expenditure, that delegate! legislation shall be made jointly by twoor more Ministers or with the consent of the Treasury or the Civil service department, the power to make instruments will pass simply to the Assembly.Where an Act confers a power exercisable by Order in Council, that- power willbecome exercisable by Order of the Assembly.198 The general procedures for making and controlling delegated legislation will need some adaptation to the Welsh situation, where there will not bea separate Assembly and Executive.   At present a subordinate instrument is54
confidential)prepared in the appropriate Department, is made by the Minister of ministers concerned and undergoes any necessary Parliamentary procedure and scrutiny.After devolution all these stages will take place within the Welsh Assembly.199   All delegated legislation which at Westminster would be subject tothe affirmative or negative resolution procedure will require a resolution by the Welsh Assembly in plenary session.   Some provision will be needed to enable subject committees to act, and report back later to the full Assembly,in specially urgent cases.   The committees will in any case play an important part in framing statutory instruments and  considering their merits.200   Some equivalent is required also to Westminster&apos;s Joint Committee onStatutory Instruments.   The Assembly will therefore be required to set up,for the general scrutiny of secondary legislation, a committee broadlyrepresentative of the Assembly as a whole and not including any member ofthe Executive Committee.   The committee will thus be as independent aspossible of those primarily responsible for promoting the statutory instru-ments which it will examine.201   At present local authorities, certain statutory undertakings likenationalised industries and a fev; other bodies like the National Trusthave a right to petition Parliament against some orders which affect them.After devolution petition against Assembly Orders would have to go to theAssembly itself.     The Assembly might intheoryappear to be acting asjudge in its own cause;   but to make Parliament or the Secretary of Statefor Wales the judge would be inconsistent with genuine devolution.   Whateverarrangements the Assembly sets up for hearing such petitions will be expectedto provide the greatest possible impartiality.55
(confidential)United Kingdom Reserve Powers*202   The Government have no intention of monitoring everything the welsh assembly does.   Nevertheless, the Government must have a last-resort powerto step in where necessary, either because matters not devolved - such asdefence - are being prejudiced, or for wider reasons of its ultimate res-ponsibility for all the people of the United Kingdom.203   The Government will have open to them three methods of intervention,for use either separately or in combination:a. For actions in prospect, whether involving a proposed subordinateinstrument or some other proposed executive act, they will be ableto issue a direction prohibiting the action or requiring a particula:course of action (including the reversal of a previous action),subject to an affirmative resolution   by /both Houses of Parliament?within a specified period.b. For subordinate instruments already made, they will be able to make an annulment Order following an affirmative resolution by ^/both HousIn case of urgency the Order can be made vdthout asking /?arlia?.ent/&apos;. first, but subject to affirmative resolution within a specified period.c. For other actions already taken, or for omissions, the Government .will be able, if the Welsh Assembly declines to put the matterright, to resume responsibility for the devolved subject inquestion to the minimum extent necessary - for the required place,task or period - with power to require and direct the use of thestaff and facilities of the Assembly for the purpose.   They will do this by Order, subject to affirmative resolution of /both Houses ofParliamentT&apos;.   The powers which the Government will be able to takeby such an Order will be any powers available within existingstatute law.204 These general procedures for intervening in the business of the Assemblyare not intended for frequent use. They will be there in the background as*See also paragraphs   68-7256(confidential)
reserve powers;    and &quot;they permit wider devolution than would otherwise be possible.   Their use will require the specific agreement of Parliament.205   All this is about circumstances in which the Government need to inter-vene on grounds of policy as distinct from law.   The legality of the Assembly&apos;section will be open to challenge in the courts just like that of the Govern-ments own actions.The Civil Service in Wales206   The Welsh Office itself will continue to exercise major functions in wales, and it will also have an important linking role between the Governmentand the Assembly, particularly in relation to primary legislation.   But policy-making and administration in devolved fields now the responsibility of the welsh Office will be taken over by the Assembly;    and the Assembly will thereforeneed substantial numbers of staff, including many transferred from the welsh office.207 The Assembly will be a Crown body. Its officials will therefore be civilservants. The question arises whether they should form a separate Welsh CivilService, or should be part of the United Kingdom Civil Service.208   The Kilbrandon Commission thought that there would have to be a separatecivil service, on the grounds that a devolved administration would wish to &quot; .choose its own senior officials, might not be content for general personnelmatters to be handled by a United Kingdom Department, and would want to beable to rely on the undivided loyalty of their officials dealing with theGovernment, for example on the block grant.209   There are however strong arguments for maintaining a unified service.It would help the consultation and co-operation on which the success of devolution will heavily depend.   Present experience does not suggest thatwith a single service there need be divided loyalty;    civil servants bytradition give wholehearted service to whichever Ministers are in chargeof their Departments.     We cannot assume that all staff will wish to transfer to a service entirely separate from that to which they were recruited, wherethe work, conditions and prospects might become substantially different.57
210   Other factors must &quot;be taken into account.   A separate service would need imore staff (for example to handle personnel matters now dealt with centrally) !A unified service would enable the Assembly to draw its officials more easilyfrom a wide pool of talent and experience.    The wishes of the Assembly itself i will be important, and these cannot be known until it is in being.   Finally,even if a separate Welsh service were desirable it could not be set up intime for the start of the Assembly&apos;s work;,   it is an option only for the longer term.211   The Government have therefore decided to keep a unified United Kingdomcivil service.     Any subsequent change would be amatter for discussion with the Welsh Assembly;     staff representatives would be consulted at all stages.    It would be essential to maintain the traditional independence of the recruitment system.212   Numbers and costs of staff are dealt with in Part VI.Complaints Machinery213   Complaints against United Kingdom Departments can be investigated bythe Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration, the &quot;Ombudsman&quot;.    Corres-ponding arrangements for the devolved subjects in Wales will need to be laid idown in the Act.   The details are outlined in Appendix B.   The basic system will remain a matter for Parliament;    but in practice the new &quot;Welsh Commission;will report to the Assembly.European Community and Other International Aspects^214  The Government must remain responsible for all international relations,including those concerned with our membership of the European Community. Therecan therefore be no question of seeking for the Welsh Assembly any right of formal access to Community or other international bodies.   Nevertheless^ bothin Community and in other contexts international business touches increasinglyon matters which will be devolved to the  Assembly     Its views of theAssembly must be taken into account.   Pragmatic arrangements will thereforebe developed for consultation between members and officials of the Assembly_M-_58 _^_ J*See also paragraphs  84-89(confidential)
confidential)and the Government.   These might operate most effectively through the   -Secretary of State for Wales and through the particular Ministers representingthe United Kingdom in Brussels or elsewhere.215   It is necessary to ensure that any relevant international obligationsare properly observed in the devolved fields in Wales.   Breach of internationalobligation will be avoided in the normal way through the close consultationwhich the Government intend to maintain with the Welsh Assembly.   If,exceptionally, this does not work for any reason, and the Assembly takessome action contrary to the United Kingdom&apos;s international obligations,the Government will be able to use their reserve powers for dealing with matters unacceptable on policy grounds.   These powers have been explained in paragraph20&apos;3   above.   The use of reserve powers in these cases will not however require the approval of Parliament.216   Positive action is sometimes needed to fulfil new e.c. or other obligations.    The Government will keep formal responsibility for all matters relating to international obligations, even when these mattersarise in fields otherwise devolved;   but the Government will be able attheir discretion to delegate to the Welsh Assembly,. by Order, the job of taking any necessary action to implement the obligation.   The power will bea flexible one, which can be used to delegate action either on a particularitem, such as an individual European Community directive, or on a generalarea of business.   The Government envisage that in practice it might well become the normal course to delegate implementation by agreement to theAssembly.   The devolution Act will add the Assembly to the category ofthose who can be designated as implementing authorities under the european communities Act 1972.59
(confidential)-C   FINANCIAL ARRANGEMENTSfThe Block Grant217   Central government finance for the devolved services will be providedessentially by United Kingdom block grant.    The Assembly will have the fullespossible freedom to decide how the money should be spent - how much, forexample, should go on roads, houses, schools and hospitals, and where in wales it should be spent.   This is a major economic as well as social power,and will give the Assembly a powerful new instrument for shaping developmentsover a wide range of services.   Expenditure in 1974-75 oh&apos; the services pro-posed for devolution was about  900 million.   Had the proposed financial arrangements been in operation the block grant would have been about  600million, with the rest coming from local authority taxation, borrowing,charges for services and other receipts.   Expenditure on the devolved services would have come to close on three-fifths of total identifiable public expendi-ture in Wales.218   The Governmenfs decision on the total amount for all the devolved services will not be a matter of simply imposing an arbitrary figure; it willbe the outcome of a close and thorough process of discussion each year withthe Assembly.   Appendix C outlines how this might run in a typical year.219   The Assembly will base its proposals on its view of Welsh needs in the devolved fields.   But the Government must take account also of other needs,both elsewhere in the United Kingdom and in non-devolved fields within Wales.All these needs must then be related to what the United Kingdom can affordfor public expenditure against other claims, including the balance of pay-ments, private investment and private consumption, as well as the needs ofpublic industries such as coal and steel which will continue to be very important to Wales.220   With understanding on both sides agreement should usually be reached ona total accepted as fair both to Wales and to the rest of the United Kingdom,If agreement is not reached the matter will have to be settled by theGovernment, answerable to Parliament.   Parliament, with its Welsh Membersalongside those from all other parts of the United Kingdom, will vote theamount for the devolved, services, and settle the statutory limits on totalborrowing.*See also paragraphs gjfclj 0 60(confidential)
Taxation221   Welsh taxpayers will continue to pay United Kingdom taxes at UnitedKingdom rates, and these payments will contribute to the central pool ofnational resources from which the block grant and other national expenditure will be financed according to needs.222   Local authorities, who will run., many, of the devolved services, can settletheir own levels of taxation, so that there will be some flexibility in thetotal amount available for the services in Wales.     The Assembly will decideboth how much of the block grant should be distributed to local governmentand now to allocate it among individual authorities.   In calculating the block grant the United Kingdom Government will simply assume that Welshlocal authorities require as much grant in relation to their needs and theirtaxable resources as authorities in England;    whether they in fact levy moreor less local tax, and are assigned more or less subsidy from the block grant, will be a matter to be settled in Wales.223   The Assembly will have an optional power to make a surcharge on localauthority taxation;    but it will not have to use this unless it runs intodeficit or deliberately aims for a higher level of expenditure, for example to meet some   particular Welsh priority for which it judges taxpayers wouldbe willing to accept higher burdens.Other Sources of^Fijiancje224 ^Capital expenditure by local authorities and by other public bodies indevolved fields will continue to be financed by borrowing.   Local authorities will continue to have access to the Public Works Loan Board.   Other public bodies will have access to a new Welsh Loans Fund for&apos; longer-term borrowing,financed from the National Loans Fund and controlled by the Assembly.   Themain condition on its use vail be that on-lending should not be at a lower rate of interest than the corresponding loan from the National Loans Fund...The only long-term borrowing transactions controlled individually by theGovernment Will be those involving foreign currency or overseas sources.However, the Government vail also control both the total amount of long-term borrowing, and within this the total of borrowing from official sourcesby local authorities and public corporations.
Financial Control and Audit225   The Act will lay down certain basic features to ensure that there isa sound system for authorising expenditure and reporting on the accounts.In addition to the Welsh Loans Fund, there will be Welsh counterparts ofthe Consolidated Fund, the Comptroller and Auditor General and the public accounts Committee (whose membership will be entirely separate from that ofthe Executive Committee).   The Assembly will have power to appropriate funds to individual services by Assembly Order, corresponding to Appropriation Acts?at Westminster.226   Responsibility for controlling issues from the Welsh Funds and for supervising the arrangements for monitoring and audit will rest squarelywith Welsh bodies.   Reports by the Welsh Comptroller and Auditor general will go to the Assembly and will be considered by the Welsh Accounts CommittedIt will be for the Assembly to decide what action should be taken on theCommittee*s reports.   The Act will however require the publication of these reports, so that expenditure on devolved matters undergoes the same publicscrutiny as the corresponding expenditure does now.
D.   THE DEVOLVED SUBJECTS227   within the fields to be devolved to the Assembly and subject only to the framework established by Acts of Parliament, the Welsh Assembly will have fullpolicy-making and executive powers of the kind now vested in Ministers.Provided that their actions are not inconsistent with the statutory framework,they will be able to develop their own distinctive policies and approaches,and to develop new tasks if they wish.228   This is a concept of wide authority and freedom, and it will be appliedto a great range of subjects, as the following paragraphs explain.   Appendix Dgives a tabular summary.local Government229   Responsibility for central government supervision of most aspects of localgovernment in Wales will be devolved.   The administration will oversee the workof local authorities in devolved matters.   It will allocate rate support tothem, control their capital investment in the devolved fields and be respon-sible for the application of the local taxation system.   The Act will make no change in the structure of local government in Wales.230   Local government administrative and electoral areas and boundaries willremain the responsibility of the Secretary of State, advised by the LocalGovernment Boundary Commission for Wales.   The Assembly will be able to alter the allocation of functions among local authorities only so far as this ispossible under statute.231   The Assembly will not of course be responsible for any functions Welshlocal authorities continue to carry out in matters which are not devolved;the responsibilities of central and local government in these matters vailremain unchanged.Health*232   The Assembly will be responsible for health matters in Wales, includingthe National Health Service.   It will be free to settle arrangements and priorities for the provision of health care, including the resources to be allocated, and to develop its own policies on such matters as family planning,private practice and the control of nursing homes.   In this as in other fields(see paragraph 261 below) certain general United Kingdom standards will howevercontinue to apply - for example in relation to medicines and drugs.*See also paragraph 118
. (confidential)Social Services&quot;&quot; . &quot;  -233       The Assembly will be responsible for such social services as the care ofchildren, the elderly, the handicapped and others in need of special care and protection like the homeless.    It will be able to supervise private provision inthese fields, and make grants to voluntary bodies,   /it will not however beresponsible for the probation service^234      The social security system and the war pensions scheme will remain on a united Kingdom bo,sis.235 Some problems arise over schemes for rent and rate rebates, rent allowances and the minimum charges and personal allowances for those living in local authorithomes. The Governments approval will be required for any changes in such scher.eswhich would affect wholly or mainly people receiving supplementary benefits, orpeople who would receive them if the changes were made. It is a more open quesxiowhether, because of the complexity of the interaction with social security general it would be better not to devolve powers relating to such schemes at all. TheGovernment are inclined in favour of devolution, but would welcome comments fronbodies working in this field.M^gtA?&quot;.?. .Scien,c.e ajrcljth^Arts^23*5 The Assembly will be responsible for all educational and cultural matters;:(including the welfare of the Welsh language) other than those noted in paragraph&apos;below. It will control the schools system in Wales, and will be able to determine:the structure of the maintained sector and policy for private schools and nursery education. It will be responsible for youth and community services, and for all further and higher education except the universities. However, since England andbales operate virtually as a unit in the supply of teachers, the Assembly will he required to conform with guidance &quot;from the Government on the total output of teaclin Wales.237 The Assembly will be responsible also for the arts (except the export contiof works of art) and for national and local libraries, museums and galleries.*See also paragraphs 119-121**See also paragraphs 122-12664(confidential)
. (confidential)233      Responsibility will not be devolved for the Research Councils and theNature Conservancy Council; for the universities; for national policy on mandatoryawards to students on higher education courses (though the Assembly will beresponsible for policy on discretionary awards); and for post-graduate awards.Hm Inspectors of Schools in Wales will continue to be appointed by the Queen onthe recommendation of the Secretary of State.Housing^239      The Assembly will be responsible for all aspects of housing, except that theGovernment will keep control of housing finance by the private sector (building society mortgages and the like) and will also have a reserve power to prevent orrestrict increases in public and private sector rents where general economic and counter-inflationary policy make this necessary.    These limited qualificationsapart, the Assembly will be able to have its own policies, for both the public andthe private sector, on the provision and upkeep of accommodation, the control of rents, subsidies to local authorities and housing associations, renovation, buildingstandards and slum clearance.Physical Planning and the Environment^240      The Assembly will be responsible for physical planning and the environment.It will deal with all general aspects of land use - how to manage development andcontrol, how to co-ordinate its use with (for example) transport planning, and how to provide the general infrastructure needed for the prosperity of &quot;Wales.   It will deal with the general improvement of the environment;    the rehabilitation of derelictland;   new towns;   and the protection of countryside amenity and landscape.241 The Assembly will have substantial supervisory powers under the new communityland legislation, and will appoint the members of the Land Authority for Wales.     e242      The devolution of planning powers will be subject to a continuing right -which should not need to be used often - for the Government to &quot;call in&quot; anyparticular planning issue for their decision if the general United Kingdom interest is affected, for example on non-devolved matters like defence.   The Government willprobably also need to keep the right to settle any disputes over compulsory purchaseaffecting such matters.*See a,lso paragraph 127**See also paragraphs 128-13065(confidential)
243-     The Assembly will be responsible for sport and recreation, parks and open spaces, national parks, ancient monuments and historic buildings, public andcivic amenities, and a variety of other matters like refuse collection and disposal, cemeteries, markets, fairs and allotments.    It will be responsiblealso for dealing with natural emergencies (though any use of the- armed forces tohelp in these must remain a matter for the Government).    It will be responsible-for protecting the environment, including preventing nuisances, atmosphericpollution and noise, except in relation to aircraft, motor vehicles and ships.Roads and Transport5&quot;244.     The Assembly will be responsible for a wide range of matters in thetransport field.    These will include the planning, construction and standards of roads; the application of traffic rules (except on motorways, where uniformitythroughout Great Britain is important for safety); bilingual road signs; road safety publicity; local transport planning; road service licensing, includingappointing Traffic Commissioners and hearing appeals from them; powers to subsidisbus and railway passenger services, to be exercised concurrently with similarlocal authority powers; inland, waterways; examining and paying claims for newbus grants; operating the current powers to pay fuel duty rebate to busoperators; and the supervision of local authority airports.Development and Industry&quot;&quot;245.     There will be no change in the powers of the Welsh Development Agency.   Itsenvironmental functions will be fully devolved, and so will its factory buildingfunctions, except that terms of disposal will remain under Government control.The other industrial functions of the Agency will remain with the Government.  H:the members of the Board of the Agency will be appointed by the Assembly, whichtialso be consulted before the Secretary of State appoints the Chairman.246.     There can be no question of breaking up the main nationalised industries c:splitting responsibility for them, but the Government envisage that there shouldbe informal contacts between them and the Assembly on matters of joint interest.The industries will no doubt be sympathetic to requests that their- reports shouligive information on recent developments and future plans for Wales.   The Assembly*See also paragraphs 131-133**See also paragraphs 134-137 ^(confidential)
confidential)will be able to discuss these reports, and to make representations to theindustries or to Ministers.247.     Central departments of the Government will keep their present statutoryfunctions for industry and commerce; but they will consult the Office of theSecretary of State or the Assembly on matters of common concern.Natural Resources*248.     The Assembly will be responsible for freshwater fisheries, for agriculturalestate management, and also for forestry with the exception of fiscal, regulatoryand international aspects.    The Forestry Commission will remain as the instrument for carrying out Welsh policies, for which it will be financed by and accountable to the Assembly.Water in Wales249.     Decisions taken about water services in Wales can radically affect water supplies in extensive and heavily populated areas of England.    In order to matchriver basins the area of the Welsh National Water Development Authority has toinclude parts of England and that of the Severn-Trent. Regional Water Authorityto include parts of Wales.   The Government envisage that both authorities should remain in being within their present boundaries and should be responsible to the welsh Assembly for their operations in Wales and to the Government for their operations in England.    Substantial water development and policy changes anywhere in Y/ales will be subject to the Assembly&apos;s agreement.    Unresolved cross-borderdisputes v/ould have to be referred to the Government.    The Assembly will provideor nominate the majority of the members of the WNWDA and some members of the STRWA,and will be responsible for water recreation and amenity planning within the wholeof Wales.250.     The Government are currently conducting a general review of the waterindustry in England and Wales.   The details of the arrangements described above may need to be altered in the light of that review.*See also paragraphs 138-13967
pnfipential)tj3urigm251.     The Assembly will be responsible for tourism in Wales, including the WalesTourist Board.    Overseas promotion will remain the responsibility of the BritishTourist Authority, which will receive funds from the Government for promotingtourism to Wales as well as to England and Scotland.    If the Assembly wants togive the Authority extra funds for specific promotions overseas, or to give workto other agencies, it will be free to do so; but it will not receive extra UnitedKingdom funds for these purposes.:;.:v:: - V::^^-.v..r;:\:- -:v,,:;;/ - ; /.y.,.v;..:/&quot;Other Matters----  -252.     The Assembly will be responsible also (to the extent that there are currentgovernmental functions conferred by primary legislation) for a wide variety ofother matters such as fire services; betting, gaming and lotteries; public holidays&apos;and summertime; the registration of theatrical eraployersj controlling charitablecollections; Sunday observance; shop hours; and licensing theatres, cinemas,taxis, liquor, music and dancing.253*     It will not be possible to decide whether the Assembly should have a role in relation to broadcasting until the committee on the future structure of broad-casting under the chairmanship of Lord Annan, has reported.   Technical factors and international obligations will in any event make it impossible to devolveresponsibility for allocating frequencies and controlling transmitter power.Nominated Bodies254.     The Government attach particular importance to giving the Assembly themaximum role possible in the democratic supervision of nominated bodies now operating in the fields to be devolved.    The following paragraphs set out thearrangements which the government propose for the future treatment of existingbodies.   These arrangements aside, the Assembly will of course be free to set upnew non-statutory bodies as it chooses in the devolved fields.255* The Assembly will be responsible for nominated bodies operating wholly in wales on devolved matters unless, exceptionally, it proves necessary in a partioulcase to set special limitations. This responsibility will include financing,accountability, reporting and appointments (though recommendations for appointmentby the Crown will need to be made through the Secretary of State). The AssemblyMJjinherit all Governmental powers under existing legislation affecting those bodies.If changes are needed in bodies constituted by Royal Charter or Warrant, these hoiwill themselves have to apply for the necessary amendments to their constitutions
2^6.     The Government intend that the Secretary of State should have power, by Ordersubject to negative resolution procedure at Westminster, to provide that the welsh assembly itself should assume the functions of a particular nominated, body in Wales.This power would be used in consulation with the Assembly.257.     Bodies operating in Wales in devolved matters but organised on a United KingdomGreat Britain or England-and-Wales basis raise complicated problems. The Government atpresent envisage that these bodies will continue initially to operate as they do now; theywill have no formal accountability to the Assembly and, where they are financed nowthrough Parliament, this will continue.    However, by normal consultation ana agreement the Government will be able to vary their activities and membership, and executivebodies will be able to act as the agents of the Assembly, provided all this can bearranged within the broad scope of the body&apos;s general policy, its legal powers and,where appropriate, its continuing primary responsibility to the Government.-  Therewill also be provision for the Government, by Order subject to affirmative resolution of Parliament, to make any legal changes which may be needed in the formal structure and powers of a particular body to reflect any agreement between then and the Assembly,in consultation with the body itself..258.     The staff of a nominated body operating wholly in Wales in a devolved field whoare civil servants will be treated on devolution like other civil servants in the devolved fields; they will continue to belong to a unified United Kingdom service.Any consulationsbetween the administration and the Government about setting up aseparate &quot;Welsh Civil Service (paragraph        above) would include the future of civilservants serving with nominated bodies.   The Assembly will inherit whateverresponsibilities the government now have in relation to staff who are not civilservants.259*     With nominated bodies operating on a United Kingdom or Great Britain basis(paragraph 257), there will be no change in responsibility for staff.260.     Appendix G lists the nominated bodies to which the arrangements in paragraph255-259 are expected to apply.69
General Standards^261 . There are a. number of natters in which common rales and standards are essential and to which responsibility mast therefore remain with the Government. . These, include,for example, the regulation or statutory standards of marketing composition,labelling and performance of commonly traded articles or goods, including in particulafood (and its handling), medicines, drags, animal feeding-stuffs and pesticides;construction standards for vehicles; and safety standards for fuel burning appliances,for the use of gas, and for articles used in the home such as inflammable textiles.Pay in the Public Sector**262.   The Assembly will be required to take account, in determining pay and relateconditions in devolved services, of any wider considerations of national economic orpay policy brought specially to   their attention by the Government.    In addition,in fields where the Government now exercises, in one way or .another, general controlover pay and conditions of service (as in the health service), the consent of the Secretary of State will be required for any changes.Moreover, the Government expect that, where pay in any area of the public services is now settled by course of national negotiations covering the whole of Great Britain,such arrangements - with appropriate . representation for the Welsh Assembly - willcontinue after devolution, whether or not the Secretary of State&apos;s consent isrequired to the outcome.Statistics and Other information*** -      ...2&amp;3*     The right to collect relevant statistics and other information goes naturallywith responsibility for particular services; and the Assembly will have this right in the devolved fields.264.     The population census for England and Wales must remain basically a matter for the Government.   The Government would however take into account any views of theAssembly in determining the scope and content of census-talcing in Wales.265.     To ensure that the Government remain able to meet their retained responsibilitythere will be a general provision in the Act requiring the Assembly to furnish informa-tion to the Government on request.__&apos;__* See also paragraph 156** See also paragraph 157*** See also paragraph 150=163       ...........................
onnil I&amp;    e us:&apos; liraIA   lb266.       The lav; on the protection of official information will apply in devolvedmatters as it does now in Government business, and the Assembly and the Governmentwill be bound to safeguard each other&apos;s confidential information.Tribunals and Inquiries26&quot;/.       Within devolved fields, the Assembly will inherit any existing powersconcerning tribunals and inquiries, and will be able to set up non-statutory inquiries71x?nfidentiai
E.    SUMMARY OF THE SCHEME FOR WALES268   The scheme will create an elected Welsh Assembly.   While the assembly will not bo, able to pass primary legislation, there will be a major devolutioof policy-making and executive powers covering a great range of subjectsnow controlled by the Government.   The devolved matters for Wales willbecome the responsibility of the Assembly, working through specialised coshin which all members can take a constructive part.269   Mainly through the Secretary of State, the Assembly will be able to influence the shaping of United Kingdom legislation which applies to wales in the devolved fields; and Welsh Members of Parliament will take part inits scrutiny and passage.   Within this legislation, and subject to a limited number of specific restrictions and to general constitutional safeguards whoseuse should in practice be exceptional, the Assembly will have wide freedom.These fields will include most aspects of supervising local government, healt!social services, education, housing, physical planning, the environment and forestry and many aspects of transport and water.   In these fields the Assentwill be able in general to do anything that does not need new primary legislaTo finance the devolved services it will have a block grant from United Kingditaxation, which it can allocate as it wishes.   It will be able, if it chooses,levy a surcharge on local government taxation.270  The general effect will be to increase greatly the range of the servicesrun in &quot;Wales for Wales under immediate Welsh democratic involvement and supervision.   This will include bringing under the Assembly*s control many ofthe appointed bodies now operating in Walesa271   The Secretary of State wi 11 continue to have a major role, as Part Vexplains.   In broad terms, however, control of the great bulk of public services which affect the people of Wales will be in the hands of theirAssembly.72nfidential
PART V:    DEC13?i&apos;RAJlSA?ICT&apos; - TIT. EXECUTIVE ROLE OFSCOTT ISTi V.T-.L3H MI-IIfTER-i IT I TI-IE G 0733?T272      Parts III and TV above have sot out the subject fields to be devolved tothe Scottish and Welsh administrations.     All other matters will be reserved tothe Government.     The Government have however reviewed/ed the full range of these other matters, and intend to allocate considerable new responsibilities to the secretaries of State for Scotland and Wales.273      Decentralisation is not a substitute, for devolution.     But where it isnecessary for powers to remain with the Government, decentralisation enablesdecision-taking within the framework of collective Ministerial responsibility to be moved to Scotland and Wales.     It will also make it possible to havesimpler and more effective arrangements for informal consultation with the devolved administrations on matters of common concern.274      Some of the powers which cannot be devolved are already exercised by the secretaries of State for Scotland and Wales.     The Secretary of State forScotland will remain responsible for the electricity industry.     Ke will alsokeep the main agriculture and fisheries functions.     These are essentialnational industries and to avoid market di.. portions in the United Kingdompolicies must be determined by the Government for the United Kingdom as a whole.There are also important international and European Community aspects.Devolution is accordingly impracticable.     Where powers are at presentexercised in Scotland by the Secretaoy of State, but for Wales by the Ministerof Agriculture, Fisheries and Food (sometimes jointly w. th the Secretary ofState), those for Wales will be transferred to the Secretary of State alone.275      The Secretaries of State will keep their responsibilities for economic planning and industrial steering and promotion, as well as powers of selectiveregional industrial assistance, where they could at their discretion arrangefor the Scottish and Welsh Development Agencies to act for them.     They willalso keep their powers of control over the investment and industrialparticipation activities of the Development Agencies, though all the other powers of the Agencies will be under the direct control of the Scottish and welsh administrations.     The combination of devolved and reserved functions inthe Agencies is reflected by the arrangement whereby the Secretaries of state will appoint half the members of the Boards, and will also appoint the73
nfidentiaChairmen after consultation with the administrations.     ResponsibilityHighlands and Islands Development Board&apos;s activities as a whole v,ill be devolved, but the Board&apos;s geographical area will continue to be defined bythe Secretary of State for Scotland and he will lay down a system of m.;il;&apos;and cash limits for their activities in non-devolved fields such as assist-to industry, fishing, and agriculture.276   The rain new function which will be transferred both to the Secretaryof State for Scotland and to the Secretary of State for Wales will beresponsibility for the activities in Scotland and &quot;Wales of the ManpowerServices Commission, the Training Services Agency and the Employment Servi:Agency.     Within the requirements of a single labour market this transfer:ihelp these bodies to give full emphasis to special local conditions.     TheGovernment intend to develop with the Scottish and Welsh administrationsinformal arrangements for co-ordination between these activities and relateones for which the administrations will be responsible, including further education.277 The Government have considered decentralising to the Secretaries of for Scotland and Wales responsibility for some or all of the activities ir.Scotland and Wales of those nationalised industries which.cannot be devolvjThese include industries which form part of a closely integrated nationalin some cases international network (railways, airways, posts arid tele-communications) and others (steel, coal, gas) which serve wide markets arcmust for efficiency continue to be run on a United Kingdom or Great Britaiilbasis. In these cases (and also with ports, for vhich the Government vailsoon be bringing forward nationalisation proposals) transfer to the secretaries of State of formal responsibilities for a geographical part ofthe operations would make little sense. The Secretaries of State alreadyshare however in Government decisions affecting these industries (includinlappointments to their associated consumer bodies) in Scotland and Wales, athe importance of this involvement will be enhanced hy their hew economicfunctions. \278  Since the Government bear the prime responsibility for protecting theinterests of all citizens of the United Kingdom and the security of the wlthere are other functions outside the economic field where devolution is fiiffeasible;    certain lav; and order functions in Scotland - such as those relto the police and the prosecution system - are notable examples.     However,
. (confidential)most of these will continue to be exercised by Scottish Ministers in theUnited Kingdom Government -the Secretary of State or the Lord Advocate,279      Taken together, the decentralisation proposals will give the secretaries of State for Scotland and Wales an enhanced and Very substantialeconomic role, monitored by Parliament with its full complement of scottish and Welsh Members of Parliament.    The Secretaries of State and the Lord Advocatewill also retain a wide general role, even in matters where it has not been necessary to create formal arrangements,  in advising their colleagues in theGovernment on particular Scottish and Welsh considerations.    All this willcomplement the devolution schemes in ensuring that decisions on a very wide range of Government activity are made in Scotland and Wales, whether by the devolved administration or by Scottish and Welsh Ministers and that decisions which have to be made elsewhere take full account of the Scottish and Welshdimension.75
(confidential)PART VI;    COSTS230      There must &quot;be uncertainty about the long-term cost of devolution in man-power and money.   No one can forecast how successful the new administrations willbe in providing devolved services economically, or what changes they may choose to make in the organisation and conduct of business,   Estimates made now con bebased only upon an assessment of how the devolved administrations, and theScottish and Welsh Offices in their new form, are likely to operate immediatelyafter their creation.   Furthermore, the main policy decisions are still recent;there must be continued study of detail, some of which could have costimplications.281      Devolution must mean some increase in the direct costs of government.There will be entirely new activities, not least the running of the Assembliesthemselves; there will be some loss of economies of scale in support services;there will be new and sometimes unavoidably complex divisions of responsibility;and it must be likely that in some of the devolved fields the new administrationswill wish to make less use than the Scottish and Welsh Offices do of the specialised expertise of London-based Departments,282      It would however be quite wrong to suppose that devolution means vastnew bureaucracies.   In essence, it is not the creation of new administrativemachines but the transfer of responsibility for existing ones to new centres of democratic accountability0283      On provisional estimates made so far, the scheme for Scotland might mean a capital outlay of some  2-3 million (for the conversion of the former RoyalHigh School building in Edinburgh to house the Assembly), extra staff of aboutannual ,1,000 (including 200 for the Assembly itself) and extra/jrunning costs around  lOrjj284      The picture is different in Wales, since there has been less decentral-isation hitherto, and what exists is a relatively recent creation; the welsh office remains far smaller than the Scottish Office.   The extra requirement in wales is therefore both larger (because extra functions will be transfered tothe Principality) and more difficult to estimate closely.   Broadly, however, the extra staff might be around 600 initially, rising thereafter to about 1,600 whenthe ,the Assembly gets into its stride.    At the earlier level extra running costs wouldbe around  5 million, rising&apos;at the later stage to around  12 million.   Preparing
. (cqnfidentiathe Temple of Peace and Health in Cardiff (if it can be made available) for theAssembly might mean a capital outlay of  1-2 million.285.   The transfer of responsibilities to the new administrations will affect the tasks of other Government Departments as well as the Scottish and Welsh Offices.It is not yet possible to estimate these wider effects, even broadly, but there ought to be net savings, particularly in relation to Wales,.286.&quot;   These last effects apart, the schemes for Scotland and Wales together might mean, in total, capital costs of up to  4 million, extra staff in the range2,500-3.000 end annual costs building up to around  22 million.    Such costs are naturally in themselves unwelcome,  especially in current economic circumstances.They must hov?ever be seen in perspective; they relate to a major gain in democraticcontrol and accountability for public services which last year cost around  2,900million.   Against this background, the Government do not regard them as disproportionate-tionately heavy.
PART VII:    WHAT SCOTTISH AMD WELSH DEVOLUTION WILL MEANFOR THE UNITED KINGDOM287.    The Government.*s proposals for Scotland and Wales envisage powerful andranging new systems of democratic control to meet the desire of the Scottish aWelsh people for more direct and effective involvement in the running of their affairs, recognising their distinctive identities within the wider framework 0which they will remain part.    The proposals however will rightly evoke inheres-in those countries alone, hut throughout the United Kingdom.    The government therefore welcome wide discussion and comment.    The essential economic and secunity of the United Kingdom has the corollary that what happens to the part rb-of concern to the whole.     It is to the benefit of all our citizens, whereverlive, that that unity should he preserved; this has been one of the stars bythe Government have steered in devising their proposals.    Irrespective of any 1plans for England or Northern Ireland, devolution must never been seen as desi,to confer unfair advantages on Scotland and &quot;Wales.288. The Government look forward to wider public debate on their proposals. ;proposals are designed to strike a careful balance - in particular, between tindesirability of allowing the maximum local freedom and initiative and the needsafeguard the social ana political unity of the Kingdom; and between maximisinglocal democratic control over the allocation of expenditure on the public serviand the continuing responsibility of the Government for managing the economy,suggestions for modifying the proposals will also have to pay regard to these considerations if they are to command widespread acceptance.289. After devolution to Scotland and Wales, each part of the United Kingdom!have a different form of government. There is nothing new about this. NorthsIreland had a separate Parliament from 1920 to 1972, and more recently its ovmAssembly. Scotland has had its own Minister in the Government for&quot;very many yand a wide range of powers and functions have been decentralised to him. Thesystem in Wales is similar in principle, but newer and less extensive. Arrangin the English regions are different again, with regional offices of centralgovernment backed up by advisory bodies such as the regional economic planning councils.290. The unity and coherence of British society will not be destroyed. Changour democratic machinery not only will not harm, but positively depend for the&apos;success upon, the deep sense of allegiance to the United Kingdom as a whole Uby our peoples.   Nothing in the Government*s present proposals will
weaken the powerful social and cultural influenceswhich help to build unity - highly developed communications;   widely-circulated newspapers;   radio and television;   and above all a close web ofties in family and friendship throughout the Units:&quot;! Kingdom.      Sue peoples ofScotland and Wales will, find it welcome that, within a larger unitarystate, they will have their own Assemblies, concerned to foster theirculture ana traditions ana to satisfy their needs in the ways they wish.The United Kingdom will still be one state;   the Scottish end Welshadministrations will have no separate authority in international relations.Parliament will remain ultimately sovereign in all matters, whether devolvedor not, and will continue to include the present complement of Scottish and welsh Members.291   The United Kingdom economy will continue to be managed as one unit,with all contributing through the tax system according to their means forthe benefit of all.     It is not the purpose of devolution to give Scotlandand Wales more and more while England and Northern Ireland get less and less.The object is rather to give Scotland and Wales more freedom to decide what to do with their fair share - a discretion to improve the use ratherthan to raise the consumption of resources.     The economic position ofa country or region will not depend on the tax revenue which it happens toproduce at a particular period;   vigorous regional policies will continue,with the aim of achieving the fairest possible division of jobs and investment between different areasof the United Kingdom.   And the secretaries of State for Scotland and Wales, alive to the traditions and needs of their countries and charged with both constitutional and economicfunctions, will help to ensure that relations between the Government andthe new administrations are marked by creative co-operation.292  Any change in the machinery of democratic government must bring newproblems in its wake.     The Scottish and Welsh Assemblies will no doubt have teething troubles, and there will be a financial-price to pay.     Thishowever is well worth accepting for the sake of more sensitive government,closer to the people and attuned to their needs.     The Government are seeking to meet differing needs in differing ways;   that is why they do not propose a system of administration uniform throughout the United Kingdom.Such flexibility is the enemy of uniformity,   but it will give renewedvigour and strength to our unity.79
t C r - &quot;if C&quot; tt P &apos; &quot;* v.i ii uVci* V-^s&quot; li  \i li    b u-*&apos; lot U  vi   il   U(   l- - APPENDIX a scottish AND WELSH ASSEMBLIES:QUALIFICATION AND DISQUALIFICATION FOR MEMBERSHIP1      The rules on qualification and disqualification for membership of theAssemblies will be the came for both Scotland and Wales.Qualificaticn for mombarship2-     Candidates should be (as for the House of Commons).&apos;.(a) at least 21 years of age; and(b) a British subject or a citizen of the Republic of Ireland.Disqualifyication for membership3      The following persons will be disqualified:(a) persons who are disqualified from House of Commons membership asholding any of the offices set out in Section 1 of the House of CommonDisqualification Act 1975i such as judges, civil servants, and membersof police forces or of the regular armed services;(b) persons holding certain other listed offices, including chairmanshipor membership of a wide range of commissions, boards, administrative tribunals, public authorities and undertakings.   The general criteria for drawing up the list are described in paragraph 4;(c) persons under sentence for treason;(d) persons whose estate has been sequestrated or who have been adjudgedbankrupt; and(e) persons who are guilty of corrupt or illegal practices at electionsunder Part III of the Representation of the People Act 1949t whichwillbe applied to the Assemblies..  .   4  &apos;   The general criteria for drawing up the list of disqualifying officesmentioned in paragraph 3(b) above will be these:(a) Paid office, holders whoss functions are confined to Scotland or wales and.who will in futrue be appointed by the Scottish or Welsh admin-istrations will normally bo disqualified from the Assembly of the coy;:&apos;:. in which they perform their functions and generally also from the Hou::-&apos;of Commons, but not from the other Assembly..1
&apos;   - - ft(b) Persons who hold paid office in bodies appointed by the United Kingdom \GovernTiient and v;ho are disqualified from the House of Commons will normally be disqualified from the Scottish or Welsh Assembly if thefunctions of the body extend to Scotland or Wales respectively, but not otherwise. &apos; x(c) Unpaid office holders will be disqualified only if the office might mai:fit impossible for its holder to fulfil his Assembly duty satisfactorily or if it is particularly important that the holder of the particularoffice concerned should be seen to be free from political bias.   Where jdisqualification is regarded as appropriate for these reasons, itsterritorial application will follow that for paid offices.5      Members of the United Kingdom Parliament, including peers and peeresses, winot be disqualified.   Nor will a member of one Assembly be disqualified from membership of another.6      No clergy of any denomination will be disqualified from the Assemblies.7      The proposed rules on disqualification are in substance the same as those for the House of Commons, except in respect of clergy and peers.Alterations to the scone of discmalification8      There will be two ways of altering the lists of disqualifying offices.   On:will be primary legislation by Parliament, for example when new public officesare established whose functions extend to Scotland or Wales.   The other will b3by Order in Council.   It will be open to the Assemblies to resolve that the list should be altered, for example in consequence of a new -Scottish Assembly Act; ar.the Government would take note of any such resolution.Exclusion and expulsion of members from the Assemblies9      An Assembly will be able to exclude for a limited period members who areobstructing business to an intolerable extent.   This will be done under theAssembly&apos;s own Standing Orders, as part of the day-to-day conduct of business.In additional on, the Act will lay down that failure to attend meetings of the Asscm.or its committees for any period of six consecutive months will result in themember1s seat becoming vacant, unless the absence is specifically approved bythe Assembly.Repercussions on&apos; membership of the House of Commons10    Members of the Assemblies will not be disqualified from membership of theHouse of Commons.   But some office holders under the Assemblies will need tobe added to the list of those disqualified for the House of Commons. i&apos;  err
confidential)APPENDIX BCOMPLAINTS MACHINERY IN SCOTLAND AND wales.     The existing complaints, machinery (the &quot;Ombudsman&quot; system) is an importantprotection for the citizen, and the Government will establish comparablemachinery to investigate complaints of maladministration by the Scottish and welsh administrations in the devolved functions.2.      Scottish and Welsh Assembly Commissioners will be appointed by KerMajesty.     Action will be initiated by a complaint to an Assembly member whichwill then be passed to the Commissioner;   in Wales, -where the Assembly will bethe executive and can itself be the body complained against, there will be additional provision for the Commissioner to accept a complaint direct from thepublic where an Assembly member declines to pass it on.3.     Subject to exclusions comparable to those applying to the parliamentary commissioner, the Scottish Assembly Commissioner will be able to investigateany action taken in the exercise of administrative functions by a departmentserving the Scottish Executive.     The Welsh Assembly Commissioner will have asimilar power in relation to action taken by or on behalf of the Welsh Assemblyby members, committees, or officers.4.     The Commissioners will make periodic general reports to the respectiveAssemblies.     They will also be able to make special reports, for example oncases where the injustice has not been or will not be remedied.5.     The investigation of complaints about the activities of the scottish and Welsh Offices and other United Kingdom departments will remain theresponsibility of the Parliamentary Commissioner.6.     Where a United Kingdom department or one of the devolved administrationsis acting as agent for the other, or where a complaint covers both devolvedand non-devolved matters, the United Kingdom department&apos;s actions will be investigated by the Parliamentary Commissioner and the administration&apos;section by the appropriate Assembly Commissioner.7. The offices of Health Commissioner and Local Government Commissionerfor Scotland and for Wales will continue as at present.1
8.     Legislative responsibility for all these Commissioners will remaijwith Parliament.      In the longer term, when the Government and the devolved administrations have had some experience of operating afterdevolution, there may be scope for them, in collaboration, to considerstreamlining the present system.2
APPENDIX CPUBLIC SXPffiiDlTURE AKD BLOCK GRA?I? CONSULTATIONS:All ILLUSTRATIVE ANNUAL CALENDAR*Februaryi. Start of new annual public expenditure review cycle.   Repricing andupdating by officials of figures in the last annual United Kingdom white paper on public expenditure, which will have covered the financial yearabout to close and the subsequent four years.   Discussion of appropriatebasis for extending the horizon forward to include the new fifth year.Kay-Juneii. After joint technical appraisal, officials report to the Scottish and welsh administrations and to the Government on the prospects for expendi-ture in the new four-year period ahead, including the new fifth year.Jun e-S opt e rnb e riii. Proposals for modification of the public expenditure projections for future years assessed and discussed at official level.    Outstanding issuesdiscussed at Ministerial level with members of the Scottish and &quot;Welshadministrations.    (At the same time, within the Government, assessmentand discussion of the proposals affecting the non-devolved services, in-cluding those for which the Secretaries of State for Scotland and wales will be responsible.)Sept embe r-0cfoberiv. Cabinet decisions on expenditure priorities.December-january- - -    -  -    -   r   - - - -   - - i   i i i a iiv. Publication in the annual United Kingdom White Paper of outcome of thepublic expenditure review for the subsequent four financial years, ir.-cluding the levels of provision for devolved services in Scotland and Wale-.vi. Publication by the Scottish and Welsh administration, if they so wish, oftheir own proposals for allocating Scottish and Welsh provisions to individual devolved services.February-Marchvii. Publication of Supply Estimates setting out the White Paper decisions forwhich provision is required in the next financial year.    Submission ofthe Scottish and Welsh block grant Estimate for approval by Parliament.(Allocation of the   block grant when approved by Parliament would be amatter for the Scottish and Welsh Assemblies, using their own Assemblyprocedures for appropriation to individual services.)Mote: Arrangements will be made during Ihe financial year for Sur.nlement ;..yEstimate r.roc.i:i.-ivr&amp;3 to vote any int.--rojjriate additional fin-jnee to the-________ devolved services. ___________ ______       ______________w_____________________^ ^
(confidential)APPENDIX DOUTLINE OP SUBJECT FIELDS TO BE DEVOLVEDNotes:    i.    The references to the main matters are to the functions as they exist now.    The Scottish Assembly will be ableto legislate to develop new, or to modify or to abolishexisting functions, within the scope of each devolvedfield.    In Wales the Assembly will be able to act vii thinthe framework established by current or future Acts ofParliament.ii. This list should be- taken in conjunction with relevantsections of the White Paper, including paragraphs 84-39and 151-164 (Scotland) and paragraphs 214-216 and 254-267(Wales), which deal with certain general matters affectingseveral or all subject fields.1.   LOCAL GOVERNMENT - see paragraphs 115-117 (Scotland) and 229-231 (Wales)The structure of local government, including the allocation among localauthorities of functions in devolved fields and, in Scotland, localgovernment administrative and electoral areas and boundaries.The financial arrangements of local government, including the amount anddistribution of rate support grant and the approval of capital investment,and the detailed application of the local tax system.    (Legislation on the sources of local taxes, and on borrowing, will not be devolved).2.   HEALTH - see paragraphs 118 (Scotland) and 232 (Wales)The main devolved matters will be:(i) . the structure and operation of the National Health Service(ii) policy on private practice (including its supervision) andof infectious diseases and control of nursing homes(iv) policy on such matters as abortion and the use of dead bodies and organs(v) radiological protection3.   PERSONAL SOCIAL SERVICES (in Scotland, Social Work) - see paragraphs 119-121(Scotland) and 233-235 (Wales).The main devolved matters will be:(i)     care and support of children (including the supervision of children who have been before the courts and, in Scotland, Children,s Hearings),the handicapped and the elderly, and other groups in need of special(iii)private hospital facilitiesgeneral health matters, such as the prevention and notificationcare or support such as drup: addicts and alcoholics
(confidential)(ii) supervision of the standards of private provision in these fields,and grants to voluntary bodies(iii) training for social work.4.   EDUCATION - see paragraphs 122-126 (Scotland) and 236-238 (Wales)The main devolved matters will be:(i) schools, including organisation, attendance requirements and curricu(ii) further and higher education, except universities(iii) awards to students (subject to some exceptions)(iv) adult education(v) youth and community services(vi) national and local museums and libraries(vii) the Arts5.   HOUSING - see paragraphs 121 and 127 (Scotland) and 235 and 239 (Wales)The main devolved matters will be:(i) the provision, upkeep and improvement of housing accommodation by private owners and public authorities(ii) ; public-sector housing finance; subsidies to local authorities and     Ihousing associations; and control of rents in the public and private]sectors6.    PHYSICAL PLANNING AND THE ENVIRONMENT - see paragraphs &apos;128-130 (Scotland) jjand 240-243 and 249-250 (Wales)The main devolved matters will be:(i) land use and development, including protection of the countryside(ii) most executive aspects of the community land scheme(iii) environmental improvement, and rehabilitation of derelict land(including all the environmental functions of the Scottish and WelsjDevelopment Agencies)(iv) water, river management, arterial drainage and flooding, sewerage andsewage disposal and water recreation and amenity planning(v) new towns(vi) other environmental functions, including(a) allotments(b) ancient monuments and historic buildings(c) buildings: design and construction standards and buildingregulations(d) burial and cremation; and provision of mortuaries(confidential) I
(confidential)(e) byelaws affecting the devolved subjects(f) commons registration and management (Wales only)(g) markets and fairs(h) national parks (Wales only)(i) protection of the environment generally, including control of pollution of the atmosphere, control of noise (except noisefrom aircraft, motor vehicles and ships) and the preventionof nuisances(j)   provision and protection of public and civic amenities(k)   refuse collection and disposal(l)    sport and recreation, including the provision of parks and open spaces7.   ROADS AND TRANSPORT - see paragraphs 131-133 (Scotland) and 244 (Wales)The main devolved matters will be:(i) roads (including motorways) - planning, construction and standards(ii) the local application of rules for the management of road trafficexcept on motorx;ays and, in Wales, the authorisation of bilingualtraffic signs(iii) road safety publicity(iv) road service licensing, the appointment of Traffic Commissioners andappeals from Traffic Commissioners in cases involving services whollywithin Scotland or Wales(v) local transport planning (including, in Wales, powers for the Assembly,concurrent with those exercised by local authorities, to subsidisebus and rail passenger services(vi) bus and shipping services operated by the Scottish Transport Group(vii) payment of new bus grants(viii) payment of bus fuel duty rebate(ix) subsidies for Scottish internal air and shipping services(x) local authority airports (arrangements for devolving other publicly owned airports in Scotland will be discussed with the scottish administration)(xi) inland waterways8.   DEVELOPMENT - see paragraphs 134-137 (Scotland) and 245-247 (Wales)Factory building by the Scottish and Welsh Development Agencies and the highlands and Islands Development Board, new town corporations and local authorities(subject to Government control of the terms of disposal).All other functions, of the Highlands and Islands Development Board (subjectto retention of the Board and to Government control in certain fields).(confidential)
(confidentiaQ9.   NATURAL RESOURCES - see paragraphs 138-139 (Scotland) and 248 (Wales)(i) forestry, subject to retention of the Forestry Commission(ii) management of the agricultural estates nov.&apos; vested in agricultural ministers(iii) smallholdings(iv) crofting (Scotland only)(v) agricultural landlord/tenant relationships(vi) improvement of fisheries harbours (Scotland only)(vdi) freshwater fisheries10.    SCOTTISH LAW FUNCTIONS - see paragraphs 140-147The main devolved matters will be:(i)     as much of private law as proves, on further study, to be compatible with consistency in matters of wider United Kingdom interest,including the maintenance of a common framework for trade,    (ii)   the general criminal law (except for offences concerning the securityof the state, matters for which uniformity is important - eg explosrfirearms and dangerous drugs and poisons - and matters relating tosubject fields which will not be devolved, such as tax and motoringoffences)(iii) the treatment of offenders(iv) executive responsibility for the Scottish Law Commission,Responsibility for the supreme courts, the sheriff courts and the districtcourts needs further consideration.11. TOURISM - see paragraphs 148 (Scotland) and 251 (Wales)(subject to the retention of the British Tourist Authority for overselpromotion).12. OTHER MATTERS - see paragraphs 149-150 (Scotland) and 252-253 (Wales)including(i) fire services(ii) miscellaneous regulatory functions: taxis, liquor, music and dancinglicensing; shop hours(iii) the licensing of theatres and cinemas(iv) betting, gaming and lotteries(v) the fixing of public holidays and summertime(vi) registration of births, deaths and marriages(vii) records and archives(confidential)
APPENDIX ESCOTLAND: LIST OP NOMINATED BODIES IN DEVOLVED SUBJECTS(Paragraphs 151-155 of &quot;the White Paper refer.    Bodies coveredby special arrangements described elsewhere in the White Paper,such as the Forestry Commission, the Scottish Development agency and the Highlands and Islands Development Boardjare not listed.)The bodies listed here are those-which operate under Royal Charter or Warrant orunder statute.   The lists are not intended to be definitive.   Bodies formed by administrative arrangement, and statutory bodies to which no appointment has beenmade by ministers are excluded.A. Bodies operating on a United Kingdom or Great Britain basisArts Council of Great Britain&apos;Board of Trustees of the Central Bureau for Educational Visits and ExchangesBritish Library BoardCentral Council for Education and Training in Social WorkCouncil for Educational TechnologyCouncil for the Education and Training of Health VisitorsCouncil for National Academic AwardsCouncil for the Professions Supplementary to MedicineFire Service College BoardGaming Board for Great BritainGeneral Dental council general Medical council general Optical CoxvncilGeneral Practice Finance CorporationHorse Race Betting Levy BoardHorse Race Totalisator BoardHousing Association Registration Advisory CommitteeHousing CorporationNational Radiological Protection Board. Pharmaceutical Society of Great BritainRoyal Commission on Environmental PollutionB. Bodies operating only in ScotlandAdvisory Committee on Social WorkAncient Monuments Board for ScotlandArea Nurse Training CommitteesBoard of Commissioners of Queen Victoria School, DunblaneBoard of Management for Schemes of Pensions for Widows and other dependentsof Teachers in scotland board of Trustees of the Scottish National War MemorialBuilding Standards Advisory CommitteeCentral Midwives Board for ScotlandChildren&apos;s PanelsChildren&apos;s Panels Advisory CommitteesClean Air Council for ScotlandCommission for Local Authority Accounts in ScotlandCommon Services Agency for the Scottish Health ServiceCountryside Commission for ScotlandCrofters&apos; CommissionFire Services (Scotland) Examination Board
confidentialGeneral Nursing Council for ScotlandGeneral Teaching Council for ScotlandGoverning Bodies of Central InstitutionsHealth BoardsHistoric Buildings Council for Scotland^Legal Aid Central CommitteeLocal Government Boundary Commission for ScotlandLocal Review Committees (Prisons and Young Offenders&apos; Institutions)Mental Welfare Commission for ScotlandNational Health Service TribunalNational Optical Consultative CommitteeNational Panel of SpecialistsNew Town Development CorporationsNew Town Planning Licensing CommitteesPanel for the Independent Schools TribunalParole Board for ScotlandRent Assessment Panel for ScotlandRent TribunalsRoyal Commission on Ancient and Historical Monuments for ScotlandRoj^al Pine Art Commission for ScotlandScottish Arts council scottish Central Fire Brigades Advisory council scottish Certificate of Education Examination BoardScottish Dental Estimates BoardScottish Health Service Planning council scottish Housing Advisory CommitteeScottish Hospital Endowments Research TrustScottish Hospital TrustScottish Medical Practices CommitteeScottish National Camps association scottish Records Advisory CommitteeScottish River Purification BoardsScottish Special Housing association scottish Sports council scottish Teachers Salaries CommitteeScottish Tourist BoardScottish Transport GroupScottish Valuation Advisory council scottish Water Advisory CommitteeState Hospital Management CommitteeTrustees, National Galleries of ScotlandTrustees, National Library of ScotlandTrustees, National Museum of Antiquities of ScotlandVisiting Committees, HM Borstal Institutions, HM Detention Centre Glenochil,HM Young Offenders&apos; Institutions2
APPENDIX FWALES: LIST CF NOMINATED BODIES III DEVOLVED SUBJECTS(Paragraphs 254-260 of the White Paper refer.   Bodies covered by special arrangements described elsewhere in the White Paper,such as the Welsh Development Agency and the Forestry commission are not listed.)The bodies listed here are those which operate under Royal Charter or Warrant orunder statute.   The lists are not intended to be definitive.   Bodies formed by administrative arrangement, and statutory bodies to which no appointment hasbeen made by ministers, are excluded.A.     Bodies operating on a United Kingdom, Great Britain or Englandand Wales basisAdvisory Committee on Rebates and Rent AllowancesArts Council of Great BritainBritish Library BoardBuilding Regulations Advisory CommitteeBurnham CommitteesCentral Council for Education and Training in Social WorkCentral Council for the Education and Training of Health VisitorsCentral Fire Brigades Advisory Council for England and WalesCentral Health Services Council and committees thereofCentral Housing Advisory CommitteeCentral Midwives BoardClean Air CouncilCouncil for National Academic AwardsCouncil for the Professions Supplementary to MedicineCountryside CommissionDental Estimates BoardFire Service College BoardFire Services Central Examination BoardGaming Board for Great BritainGeneral Dental council general Medical council general Nursing Council for England and WalesGeneral Optical council general Practice Finance CorporationHorse Race Betting Levy BoardHorse Race Totalisator BoardHousing Association Registration Advisory CommitteeHousing CorporationMedical Practices CommitteeNational Health Service TribunalNational Radiological Protection board national Water CouncilPharmaceutical Society of Great BritainPublic Health Laboratory Services BoardRoyal Commission on Ancient MonumentsRoyal Commission on Environmental PollutionSevern-Trent Water AuthorityWelfare Panel of the Appeal TribunalWelsh National Water Development Authority(confidential)   1 -
B.     Bodies operating only in HalesAncient Monuments Board for WalesArea Health AuthoritiesCentral Advisory Council for Education (Kales)Community Health CouncilsCountryside Commission, Committee for WalesCourt and Council of the National Library of WalesCourt and Council of the National Museum, of WalesHistoric Buildings Council for WalesLibrary Advisory Council (Wales)National Parks CommitteesNew Town Development CorporationsRent Assessment Panel^for WalesRent TribunalsSports Council for WalesWales Tourist BoardWelsh Arts CouncilWelsh Health Technical Services OrganisationWelsh Medical Committee-Welsh Nurse Training CommitteeWelsh Nursing and Midwifery CommitteeWelsh Pricing committee


</content>
</cab>
