<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/35/28 images: 196-203</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet. August 1943.SECRET.Copy. Wo,118th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 118 (43),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, 23rd August, 1943, at 5-30 p.m.Present&quot;:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State&apos; for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce, Repre-sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Vice-Admiral Sir  NevilleVice-Chief of Naval Staff.Syfret,Viscount Wavell, Viceroy of India(Designate).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The   Right   Hon.   Sir   archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary of- State for Air.Captain the Right Hon. H. F. C.Crookshank, M.P., Postmaster-General (Items 5-6).The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs.Air Marshal Sir Douglas Evill, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff.Lieutenant-General A. E. Nye, Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat:Mr. Norman Brook.Brigadier Li C. Hollis.Lieutenant-Colonel C. R. Price.[25984]b
WAR CABINET 418 (43).Contents.minute no. Subject. . page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations ....      ....      ....      ....    241Air operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean&apos;.Pacific.Naval operations.Military operations:Sicily.Eussia.2     B.B.C. Russian Commentary ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    2423      South-East Asia Command   ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    2424     France    ....      ....   &apos; &apos;&apos;    ....      .... .....      -    242French Committee of National Liberation.5      Expeditionary Force Messages        ....      ....      ....      ....    2426      India      ....      .....      ....      ....      ........      ........    244Postal Communication..
Nasal, Militaryand Air &apos;^;S^:M,Operations,(previous reference:W.M., (43) 115thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Home Theatre.Mediterranean.Pacific.naval operations.Military,Operations.Sicily.Russia.1. The Vice-Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events ofthe previous week.Boihber -Command activity had been below average, theprincipal targetment at Peenemunde and the chemical factories at Leverkusen, asuburb of Cologne,  3,850 tons of bombs had been dropped for the&quot;loss of 51 aircraft (3-8 per cent.). Of these, 41 had been lost in thePeenemunde raid, when a specially large number of night-fighters had been encountered on a clear night.American heavy bombers had carried out a very successful attack on the Messerschmitt fighter assembly factory at Regensburg(65 miles north of Munich) and a fairly successful attack on theball-bearing factories at Schweinfurt (70 miles east of Frankfurt).Losses had been 64 bombers (17 per cent.). American claims for theweek by bombers were 134 enemy aircraft destroyed, 39 probably destroyed and 28 damaged.Coastal Command had had another disappointing week,resulting in only 2 sightings and no attacks. Eight aircraft hadbeen lost, of which 7 losses were believed due to enemy fighter actionover the Bay of Biscay.Fighter Command claimed 54 enemy aircraft destroyed,10 probably destroyed and 32 damaged,for 31 fighters lost.Allied aircraft had been active against enemy rail communica-tions and shipping. There had been some heavy air fighting,resulting in the loss of 64 bombers against our claim of 131 enemy aircraft destroyed.An attack had been carried out on the airfield in SouthernFrance on which were based the torpedo aircraft which, in theprevious week, had attacked our convoy near Gibraltar.In the two raids on Bizerta by a total of 135 enemy aircraft,17 had been destroyed (13 by A.A. fire).Enemy airfields at Wewak (New Guinea) had been successfully attacked, 175 aircraft being destroyed on the ground and 45 in air fighting for a loss of 6 of ours.Spitfires had succeeded in shooting down all of 4 Japanesereconnaissance aircraft which had ventured over Darwin.Shipping losses (confirmed) during the previous week amountedto 3 ships (16,800 tons).German fleet and U-boat dispositions remained unchanged, andthere had been few contacts in the North Atlantic. Losses on the19th August in the Halifax convoy had been due to collision in fog.Two promising attacks had been made against U-boats, one bya destroyer near the Faroe Islands on the 16th August, and the other by two Catalinas south of Madagascar on the 20th August.In the Mediterranean, Allied cruisers and destroyers hadbombarded bridges, railways and power stations on the Italianmainland. Submarines had attacked merchant vessels and tankersoff the east coast of Italy.A rough&quot; balance sheet &quot; of operations in Sicily showed thatAllied casualties worked out at 24,000 (14,000 British and 10,000American) against enemy losses of 32,000 killed, wounded andmissing (25,000 German and 7,000 Italian) and 130,000 prisoners ofWar, of which 7,000 were German/Of the original garrison of92,000 Germans and 216,000 Italians, it was estimated that 60,000Germans and 30,000 Italians had been evacuated and that some56,000 Italians had become absorbed into the civil population in sicily. -News from the Russian front continued to be satisfactory,particularly in the Kharkov area, -where the German southern flankwas now threatened.Russian claims of personnel and equipment destroyed and&apos;      captured, if converted into terms of Panzer and infantry divisions,worked out at something like 42 divisions of tanks destroyed,68 divisions of artillery,  18 Panzer divisions of mechanical transport and 23 divisions of infantry.[25984] * b 2
Took note of these statements and invited the Vice-Chiefof the Imperial General Staff to circulate a comparativestatement showing total German and Russian claims ofmen and material destroyed and captured oh the russian front since the beginning of hostilities.Commentary,2.. The attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to theRussian commentary by Alexander Worth&apos;, which had been broadcastby the B.B.C. on the 21st August. This had suggested that themilitary effort of the British and American forces was affordinginsufficient help to Russia. Was it reasonable that we should give facilities for the broadcasting in this country of statements,belittling our military achievements ?In discussion, it was pointed out that these commentariespurported to reflect current opinion in Russia; and there was noreason to believe that this particular broadcast misrepresentedcontemporary Russian opinion. ,The general view of the War Cabinet was that there was no sufficient ground for taking exception to this broadcast.South-East 3.   The War Cabinet considered a telegram from the PrimeAsia Command. Minister  regarding  the  appointment   of   a   Supreme   Allied(Previous Commander for the South-East Asia Command.Reference: A record of the discussion and of the conclusion reachedW.M. (43) H4th is. contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions, Conclusions.Minute 1.)France.french committee ofNationalLiberation. .(previous reference:W.M. (43) 110thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The War Cabinet were informed of the course of thediscussions at Quebec with representatives of the United states administration regarding the recognition of the French Committeeof National Liberation.The United States Government were not prepared to adopt anyformula involving the use of the word &quot; recognition &quot;; and it hadeventually been decided to abandon the attempt to find an identicalformula for use by the Governments of the United States, theUnited Kingdom and Canada. It had been agreed that separatestatements should be issued by each of the three Governments, aftercommunicating with the Soviet Government and other Governmentsconcerned.The War Cabinet-Took note of this statement.FoS^Sges. aQlr J- M tifr Meeting on the 16th August the War Cabinet h-    .       .    asked that the proposal, put forward in WP   (43^ 356  for--    .       yending th.e/-Peditionary Force Messages service over thew&apos;mS 115th  TSKS? Sh0mhe reConsidered and a further report madeMinutetT&apos;      k  ^hiWfr Cabi^et now,had before them a further MemorandumMinute. 5.).      by the Postmaster-General (W.P. (43) 375) indicating that, after examining various alternative proposals, he adhered to the view thattne best way of dealing with the position would be to suspend this service for three weeks over the Christmas period;The Postmaster-General said that it would be impracticable toadopt the suggestion, made by the Secretary of State for War at theprevious discussion, that the E.F.M. service should be used duringthis period for personal messages but not for Christmas greetings.Even if the group of greetings messages were deleted from the list
of standard texts, there Would still be many intermediary phraseswhich could be used to serve the purpose of a greeting message; andthe volume of the traffic would still he such as to involve substantialdelays. If all these intermediary phrases were to be removed, theclerks at telegraph counters would have to refer to the list inconnection with each&quot;individual message; and, in view of the largenumber Of standard groups, this would involve an amount ofadditional work which could not be undertaken during the christmas rush... .The Secretary of State for War said that he accepted this position, and was satisfied that in the circumstances the only practicable course was to suspend the service entirely over the christmas period. He thought, however, that this restriction wouldnot be well received, and it was important that all possible steps should be taken to disarm criticism. For example, he hoped thatthe General Post Office would find it possible to introduce theairgraph greetings card, which was now under consideration. Itwas also proposed that members of the Forces serving overseasshould be allowed, in the period before Christmas, five extra letter-cards, one of which would be free. It would be an advantage if allfive could be free. In addition, consideration might be given to thepossibility of increasing, Over the Christmas period, the existingration for the Concession Telegram service. He also hoped that theAir Ministry would undertake to provide any additional aircraftrequired to carry the heavier air-mail traffic which would follow the suspension of the E.F.M. service. Finally, he stressed theimportance of a proper presentation of this decision to the public;the reasons for the suspension should be carefully stated, and attention should be drawn to the alternative services available.It was suggested in W.P. (43) 375 that the suspension might belimited to messages addressed to troops in the nearer countries,which were best served by air-letter and airgraph. The WarCabinet were, however, informed that, on the basis of past experience, there were likely to be substantial delays in the delivery of E.F.M. messages to India, and there seemed to be little value indifferentiating between the nearer and the more distant countries.The War Cabinet&apos;s Conclusions were as follows : &apos;(1) The E.F.M. service should be suspended, for all countries,for three weeks over the Christmas period.(2) All practicable steps should be taken to provide compen-sating concessions on the lines suggested in thediscussion by the Secretary of State for War and toensure the speedy delivery of messages sent by thealternative services. In this connection the Secretaryof State for War would discuss with the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer and the Postmaster-General the sugges-tion that all the five extra letter-cards to be allowed to members of the Forces serving overseas during the christmas period should be carried free of charge. TheSecretary of State for Air would make every effort tot ensure that sufficient aircraft were available to carry &quot;theadditional air-mail traffic resulting from the suspension of the E.F.M. service.(3) The Postmaster-General should ensure that, when the time came to announce the suspension of this service, carewould be taken to present it to the public in such a way as to make clear the reasons for the restriction, and todraw attention to the alternative services available.
India. 6.   In the course ofthe discussion recorded m* the precedingPostal Minute,reference was made to delays in the transmission of air manCommunication, - to India.The War Cabinet were informed that for some time past theair mail, for which a charge of Is. 3d. was made, had had to becarried by sea for the greater part of the journey; and that air-mailletters often took as long to reach India as the ordinary mail. this situation was giving rise to increasing complaint in India.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary, of State for India and the Post-master-General to submit a report on the general conditionof postal communications to India.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1, -13rd August, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
