<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/48/14 images: 220-231</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0 c^U^jr.^^^JS^B^M^^^-. MAJEQTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)S E C R E T , /o21st Marcho  1 QhL.  COPY NO.^-*76/WAR CABINETTOWN AND COUNTRY PLANNING LEGISLATION(a)  Short Term,   (b) Long TermMemorandum by the Minister of Town and Country planning to the CabinetHeads of a Billin Appendix I,  annexedtoI submitthis paper,  the Heads of a Bill which&apos; requires to be passed into law this Session for the purpose of implementing our pledges with regard to the public acquisition of land.      In Appendix II I set out in briefthe principles which I suggest should guide us in drafting the further legislation which will be required to implement our pledges with regard to positive nationalplanningo2* I would draw particular attention to Item 5 of appendix I.      This provision does not deals nor can aprovision in a Bill so limited deal, with the question offloating value.     Furthermore, any Bill so limitedinescapably involves serious inequity as between theowner whose land is publicly acquired and the owner whois left free to dispose of his land in the open market.This inequity can only be smoothed out by reducing thevalue of all land to its value for existing use - i.e.by imposing a universal restriction upon any change of use without consent, by the payment of compensation forany loss, caused by such a restriction, of potential value for change of use which had accrued to the land at31st March,  1939s  an&amp; the levying of an appropriate feefor the grant of permission for change of use.      In other words,  this Bill cannot stand alone.      It is onlyacceptable if it is accompanied by a statement setting out in precise terms the further decisions relating to thecontrol of land use to which the Government intends togive effect as soon as possible - namely the impositionof a universal restriction upon change of use withoutconsent,  the payment of compensation and the levying ofa licence fee for the grant of permission for change of use (i.e.  the principles set out in Appendix II).    when such legislation has become law, not only will theinequities inherent in any Bill limited to public acquisition be removed, but it will be possible tocontrol and plan the use of land in England and wales in accordance with the undertakings on this subject whichwe have repeatedly given.3*   &apos;     It would no doubt be desirable that all thesematters should be dealt with at once in a single BilloThis is now, however, out of the question.      Even if theCommittee and the Cabinet were to approve forthwith, in specific detail,  the principles upon which such provisions are to be drafted,  there is no longer time to put suchprinciples into the form of clauses and to get them throughParliameiit as part of a Bill which must become law not later than this summer.,

!(..   &apos;      Despite,  therefore,   the disadvantages of a Billlimited to the matters dealt with in the annexed draftheads, we are, or so it seems to me, driven to theconclusion that we must content ourselves with such a Billduring the present Session.      It is, however, as I hopethe Cabinet will agree,  imperative that we should as soonas possible, and most certainly not later than theintroduction of a limited Bill, make a statement setting out, clearly and definitely,, what are our proposals as tothe control of land-use,  the payment of compensation, andthe levying of fees for the grant of permission forchange of use;    ano. undertaking to introduce as soon as( possible a Bill for carrying these proposals into effect,,v/o S o MoMinistry of Town and Country Planning,32, St, James&apos;s Square,S.W. 1...21st March, 19^+4.APPENDIX IHeads of a Bill for empowering the compulsory purchaseof land required for development or redevelopment, for regulating the disposal of such land when acquired,  andfor fixing the price at which land may be acquired for public purchase1, Extended powers of acquisition,,    Where the minister is satisfied that any area of land is required for thepurpose of development or redevelopment as a whole,whether by reason of war damage, or of obsolescence, orfor the purpose of providing housing or othex^ accommodation for those who may be compelled, to leave such areas, or forthe purpose of roads,  schools or other necessary development^he may authorise the Land Commission later referred to topurchase that land.2* Procedure for compulsory acquisition.    Provisions,/ ingeneral accordance with the recommendation of the ...HarrislonCommittee, for expediting and facilitating compulsorya*c-qtrisi tion.3. Appointment and powers of a Land Commission,,    A land commission, to be appointed by the Minister of Town and country -Planning.      The Commission to be responsible to,and subject to directions from, the Minister, and to beempowered -(a) to purchase compulsorily, and to hold and administer, any land acquired under the Bill.(b) subject to the general or -particular directions of the Minister, to lecyfe land held by them toany body or person for&apos;&quot;the purpose of carryingout on such land any approved development orrodev elopmen 10(c) with the consent of the Minister,  to sell anysuch land.,\

if. Development &quot;by Local Authorities,      The Minister tohave power to authorise local authorities to erectbuildings on land held or* acquired from the Land Commissionif he is satisfied -(a) that the erection of  the buildings proposed isnecessary in the public interest;    and(b) that they are not otherwise likely to be erected05* Basis of Purchaseo      The price at which the land isto be acquired by the Land Commission shall be the valueof the land as at 31st March,  1939^  to which shall beadded or from which shall be deducted any amount by whichthe value of the land for its use as at that date shallhave increased or diminished,      In assessing any such sumit shall be a direction to the arbitrator to disregard any temporary and abnormal increase or diminution in the valueof the land in question due solely to local circumstancesarising from the war,6. Ancillary Provisionsc      A certain number ofancillary provisions will be required, e,g* for thestopping-up of highways,  or the extinction of easementson land acquired under the Bill, and for the suspension of approved planning schemes in reconstruction and over-spill areas.      Special provisions will be requiredregarding the application of the provisions of the Bill to statutory undertakers (an interdepartmental committee under the Solicitor-General is studying this question).Provisions are also necessary in regard to licensed premises in reconstruction and-overspill areas and mayhave to be included in this BilloAPPENDIX IIPrinciples of the Lsglslatlon required to implement theGovernment&apos;s undertakings with regard to positivenational planning.Principle I. That the consent of the planning authority must be obtained before any change of use is effected in undeveloped land.Principle lie      That where loss of development value in undeveloped land is caused by the imposition of the requirement that planning permission must be obtained before any change of use can be effected, fair compensation should be paidoPrinciple &quot;III.      That where the Planning Authoritygrants a licence permitting a specified change of use ona specified area of undeveloped land,   it shall beempowered to make a charge for the grant of such a licence,equal to the value of the right conferred thereby0Principle IV.      That compensation in respect ofthe loss of &quot;land&quot;value arising from the requirement thatplanning permission must be obtained before any change of use of undeveloped land is effected should be payable toall owners, whether or not permission to develop issubsequently given,  in so fa??&apos; as their land possesseddevelopment value at the 31st March,  1939&quot;

Principle V. That the consent of the planning authority must be obtained before any change of use is effected in developed land.Principle VI.    That compensation, as under theexisiting law, in respect of loss of value arising fromthe requirement that planning permission must be obtained before any change of use of developed land is effectedshall be payable if (a)  that value had accrued at the31st March, 1939* and (b) an application for consent hasbeen made and refused.Principle VII,      That Where the Planning Authoritygrants a licence permitting a specified change of use-ona specified area of developed land,  it shall be empoweredto make a charge for the grant of such a licence, equalto the value of the right conferred thereby.Principle VIII.      That&apos; the price for the public acquisition of land for the purpose of reconstructionshall be its value as restricted to the use to which itwas being put at the 31st March, 1939? subject to thespecial considerations mentioned in paragraph 5 of appendix I.Principle IX.      That a Land Commission should beset up,    to be responsible to and subject to the - directionof the Minister of Town and Country Planning, for thepurpose of acquiring, holding and disposing of land to be publicly acquired and for performing the financialfunctions, not being functions relating to the formulation of the policy of town and country   planning, arisinghereunder.






</content>
</cab>
