<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/84/0 images: 359-383</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT),SECRET,COPY NNO.REVISE.CAB I N E T    44 ,(,5.6),.Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No, 10Downing Street. S.W.I., on THURSDAY, the25th JUNE, 1936, at 11, 0 a.m.AGENDUM.UNEMPLOYMENT ASSISTANCE: . THE NEW DRAFT REGULATIONS .(Reference Cabinet 51 (35) Conclusion 7),Report of Cabinet Committee,CP. 172 (36)    - already circulated.Memorandum by the Secretary of State forScotland.CP.    179  (36) - circulated herewith.(Signed).    M. P.A. 1IANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.June 23rd, 1936.
BENT IS THE. PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVEPJNTMENT)R E copy NO.C A B I N E T 44  (56).CONCLUSIONS of a&apos;Meeting of the cabinet held at N0. 10, Downing Street,S.W.1,on THURSDAY,  25th June, 1936, at11 a .m.PRESENT.The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.Prime Minister (In the Chair).[The Right Hon.J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.I   Lord President of the Council.:The Right Hon.I   The Viscount Hailsham,I   Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Neville C&amp;amberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.1.,K.C.V.0.. O.B.E., K.C., LLP.,    Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.[The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G.,G.&quot;CS.L, G.C.I.E.,    lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.I The Viscount Swinton, G.B.E.,j   LLC, Secretary of State for:The Right Kon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,C.I.LG., LLP.,    Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Bight Hon.Walter Runeiman, M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E.,K,C, LLP., Minister for theCo-Ordination of Defence.The Right K0n.Oliver Stanley, LLC, LLP.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Malcolm MaoDonald, LLP.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,  G.G.S.I.,G.C.I.E.,      Secretary of Statefor India.The Right Hon.W. Ormsby^Gore, LLP.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.,G.B.S., C.M.G., LLP . , FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, LLC, LLP.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right HonSir Kingsle;Minister of Health.Sir Kingsley Wood, LLP.,Sir R. B. HoworThe Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Labour.th,-   K.CM.G,, C.B.,..............Deputy Secretary.
jg DOCUMENT IS THE. PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVEPJIMENT).COPY NO.C A B I N E T 44  (56).CONCLUSIONS of a&apos;Meeting of the cabinet held at ND. 10, Downing Street,S.W.1,on THURSDAY,  25th June, 1936, at11 a.m.PRESENT.The Right Hon* Stanley Baldwin, M.P.Prime Minister (In the Chair).The Right Hon.J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G.,CCS.I., G.C.I.E.,    lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.The Viscount Swinton, G.B.E.E.C., Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Sir J0hn Simon, G.CS.I. ,K.CV.OO.B.E., K.C j LI.P. ,    Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Malcolm MaoDonald, is^- .,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Most Hon.The Marrmess of Zetland, G.C.S.I.,G.C.I.E.,      Secretary of Statefor India.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,C.M.G., L\P.,    Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Walten Runeiman, M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade,The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E.,K.C., M.P., Minister for theCo-Ordination of Defence.The Right H0n.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board ofi    Education,The Right Hon.W. OrmsbyKrore,Secretary of State for the Colonies-p. XT . j,The Right Hon. .Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.,G.B.E., C. M. G., I.I.P. ,    FirstLord of the Admiralty,M . P . ,The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, 1:1.C ,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Minister of Health,The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M,C, M.P.,Minister of Labour*Sir R. B. Howorth,-   K.CM.G,, CB.,..............Deputy Secretary.
PMPLOYMEWTSSI STANCE.jy New DraftLgulations.previous reference :Cabinet 51 (35)Conclusion 7) .With reference to the Conclusion mentioned inthe margin;, the Cabinet had before them the Report(paper CP.-172 (36))  of the Committee on theRegulations of the Unemployment Assistance Board.The Board&apos;s proposals for revised Regulations were described in detail in the Appendix to the Report(Paper U.A.R.  (34) 8),  and the proposals, which theCabinet Committee recommended for approval, were, with two exceptions,in accordance therewith.      As regardsthese exceptions, the Committee had ascertained thatthe Board were prepared to submit amendments to their original proposals for dealing with rent and earnings,which the Committee  had   accepted as satisfactory.The Report, after explaining the revisedRegulations, made suggestions for liquidating the standstill,  and in regard to the date on which the revised Regulations should come into operation.The Committee&apos;s recommendations to the cabinet were summarised as followss-(1) That the proposals of the unemployment assistance Board for revised Regulationsset out in the Appendix to this report should be approved, subject to the amendments suggested by the Board fordealing with rent and earnings explained in paragraphs 6 and 7 of this Report,which amendments the Committee have accepted as satisfactory.(2) That the method proposed by the Ministerof Labour for liquidating the Standstill&apos;(paragraphs 36-52 of Appendix)  should be approved.(3) That the date on which the revisedRegulations should come into operation should be 16th November,  1936, and not1st October,  1936,  as previouslycontemplated, and that the SecondAppointed Day should be. 1st April,  1937.The Cabinet also had before them a Memorandum(Paper CP.  179 (36)) by the Secretary of State forScotland stating that he had been unable to agree in
all respects with the views of the Committee.      Inhis Memorandum, the Secretary of State drew attentionto the serious political implications involved in theacceptance of the new Regulations, and in particular to the substantial &apos;cuts? which were in contemplationHe also informed the Cabinet as to the suggestions he had made to the Committee in regardto (i) the Rent Rule, (ii) the Earnings Rule, and(iii) the scale allowance of single men in lodgings.The Prime Minister invited the Chancellor of theExchequer, as Chairman of the Cabinet Committee&apos;, to open the discussion.The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed, theCabinet that the Committee had. held,, a - very largeexhaustively examined every aspect of the problem,which was full of technical detail and. difficultiesof every kind.    The Minister of Labour and. theUnemployment Assistance Board, had throughout done their best to find new proposals which would, be atonce defensible and in accordance with certainfundamental principles upon which there was generalagreement.    In addition, the Minister of Labour had.made for the Committee exhaustive inquiries into thepresent conditions of applicants for publie assist-ance throughout the country, and. also on the effect which the new proposals would, have on the various kinds of applicants.The Committee now submitted, to the cabinet proposals which the Board, were ready to accept, and.which were agreed, by all the members of the committee with the exception of the Secretary of State forScotland, who, while in agreement with a large partof the proposals, differed from the rest of the
Committee in certain important particulars.   He (&quot;theChancellor of the Exchequer) was sure that the cabinet would not wish to do over again the work which theCommittee had. done, and. he proposed, therefore, to confine himself to certain considerations of a general character.The Cabinet must recognise that the question ofthe new Unemployment Assistance Regulations was boundto give rise to very violent and bitter political criticism.    Every member of the Opposition wouldclaim to be an expert on the subject and to be ableto represent the viev;s of the persons who would fallunder the new Regulations, and. the opportunity would,no doubt be taken by the Opposition to endeavour tomake the maximum Party advantage out of the proposals.It could, not be too strongly emphasised that therewas nothing that could, be done in the way of new proposals which could conciliate the Opposition.If the new proposals had. resulted in only a singlecut, that cut would, have been seized upon for themost intensely hostile criticism.    The Cabinet must recognise that the Government was going to be mostbitterly and strenuously attacked, when the new proposals were published.    It was therefore necessaryto consider -(l) The immediate effect of theproposals:    and(S) Their ultimate effect.As regards the ultimate effect of the proposals he (the Chancellor of the Exchequer) was satisfiedthat they were, if anything, on too generous a scale.Public opinion took a much more humane view of thismatter than it had taken in the past, but the new proposals definitely involved raising the standard, of relief to a height very near the danger level.    no serious consequences would follow so long as tradeand industry continued, to expand, so long as the new
re-armament programme gave widespread employment,and so long as the country as a whole continued, to enjoy prosperity.    But at times like the present we were apt to forget that these conditions could, not last for ever, that the tendency would, soon he theother way, and that we might then find. ;it most difficult to maintain these high and generous stand-ards of public relief.In this connection it was very important to bearin mind, that the Unemployment Assistance Board, were now dealing with persons who had. exhausted, theirbenefit and. were now on transitional payment, but were not dealing with the large section of able-bodiedpersons who had never been insured, and for whom thePublic Assistance Committees remained responsible.These persons would, be handed over to the Board, onthe Second Appointed. Day, namely, April 1, 1937.Taken as a. whole, the treatment of these persons bythe local Assistance Committees was definitely belowthe standard of the new proposals .   Moreover, therewere still many persons who, for reasons such asself-respect, had. refused, to have recourse to publicassistance.    In future, reluctance to obtain aid ofthis kind would, tend to disappear, especially afterthe Boar&apos;&apos; had. assumed, responsibility for the admlnis-tration, and the more generous the benefits offered the greater would, be the inducement to many people to seek public relief.    It was quite impossible toestimate the extent o^ this drift, and it was forthis reason that it was so difficult to estimate thefuture cost of the proposals.    In any case he - theChancellor of the Exchequer) must again emphasise thefuture dangers, when trade declined, of the everincreasing difficulty of meeting the heavy cost of-4-
this service.   We might,  indeed, have to face anothercrisis like that of 1931, another Economy Committee,and the necessity for making cuts of a heavy and widespread character involving serious hardships onclasses and individuals .It must he recognised, that the only alternative to the new proposals would, he to make payments on thescale which had. been adopted, by the most extravagantAuthorities.   No doubt in this way cuts could be avoided, but the Opposition would, not be placated.The more carefully the proposals were examined,the more clearly it, would be seen that they were based,on humane and reasonable considerations.    Very greatpains had. been taken to meet the fair criticism whichhad. been directed, against the original proposals, and.to introduce a scale which, while enabling greateruniformity and. fairness to be secured, would benefit in particular deserving persons who were unemployedthrough no fault of their own.The liquidation of the &quot;Standstill&quot; presented, a difficult problem, and. it would, be necessary to havea transitional period    during which the arrangements would, be moved, from the Standstill on to a permanent and. long-term basis.    In the opinion of the Board,which he (the Chancellor of the Exchequer) shared,(though in this matter the Secretary of State forScotland held, a different view) the difficult time would, be daring the first few weeks.    The Board had accordingly devised plans to ease off the stand still and. only to bring about the necessary changes slowlyand gradually.It was very difficult to give a picture of how the scheme as a whole would work, hut it must beto beremembered that the actual persons/dealt with would not
the same individuals, but would constantly bechanging.    if the existing payments to persons nowunder the Standstill were taken and compared with thepayments to be made under the new arrangements to persons in the same position, the result would be wholly misleading, because, for one thing, thepersons would not be the same.   Apart, however, fromthis consideration, the new Regulations contained, anumber of provisions which would, cancel, reduce orgraduate the cuts, so that in actual practice itwould be found that, while theoretically there werenumbers of persons who 1.light, be adversely affectedby the new Regulations, many of these individualswould, for one reason or another, be unaffected, bythe change in actual practice.While it was not possible to give a. truepicture of what was going to happen, there were certain considerations which should be carefullynoted.    For example,  on page 9 of CP.-172 (36)  itwas stated  &quot;It is possible, however, to make anestimate of the results in the first three or four months where reductionsfrom existing payments will be confined to the two classes of grossly excessivepayments and. young men under 25&quot;.The class of &quot;grossly excessive payments&quot; referredto households with large resources where theAuthorities were illegally ignoring the Means Testand were giving relief in full.    It would, only benecessary to mention a number of typical examples ofwhat was going on to satisfy reasonable public opinionthat these abuses must at once be terminated.On page 5 of CP.-172 (36) the Committee, indealing with the proposed rate of lc/- for personsliving alone, stated, that the rate was to be subjectto adjustment, and that in a large number of casesmore than 15/- would in fact be paid,  &quot;In particular,
in the ease of older men who are receiving 16/- or17/- under the Standstill, there is no intention ofdisturbing these rates&quot;.    It should, therefore be observed that in the large number of cases of singlepersons over 55 no cut would be made, and. that,speaking generally, it would only be in the ease ofpersons under 25 that the cut would, be enforced atonce .It, would be seen from page 10 of CP.-172 (36)that the total number of reductions in the two classes to which he had. referred was roughlyestimated, at about 60,000.    On the other hand,increases on existing payments would, on the basisof the present, facts, be. about 2C&apos;0,000 spread, overthe country and. becoming effective during the first four or five weeks.THE RENT -he Chancellor of the Exchequer then drewRATE.   &apos;attention to the new rent rule, described, on pages5 and 6 of       CP.-172 (.36), and. recalled, that theold rent, rule had. given rise to serious criticismeighteen months ago.    In particular, it had. then been realised for the first time that very largenumbers of working men in Great Britain, andparticularly in Scotland, were paying rents much lower than had been thought, and were living undervery bad. conditions.    The rigid rent rule originally proposed would, have had the effect, in the case ofthese low-renteJ households, of making very severecuts in the amounts payable, and consequentially inlowering the standard of life.      In accordance withthe pledges given at the General Election, thisparticular difficulty was being met by invoking theassistance of the local Advisory Committees.    Thenew rent rule would, be exceedingly flexible.
Tt would be based on a quarter of the total of thescale of payments for the whole household, but thelocal Advisory Committees would be empowered to make recommendations with regard to reductions on accountof rent, as stated in (l), (2) and (-3) of paragraph of CP.-172 (35) .-   It should be noted that theseadjustments might be recommended for any classes ofcases either in the whole area or in part of it.In this, as in other ways, an attempt had beenmade to introduce a remarkable degree of flexibilityinto the arrangements.    Indeed, the Secretary ofState for Scotland had criticised, this particular proposal as giving too much discretion to the Boardand. the local Advisory Committees, and he would, have preferred, that the assurance to be given by the Board,to beand./embodied in the White Paper as to what re commend. -at ions the Board, would, regard as reasonable shouldbe inserted in the actual Regulations themselves.In regard, to this there were two alternative methodsof approach(l) To reduce to a minimum the discretion of the Board, and the Advisory Commit -tees and to put as much as possibleinto the Regulations&apos;    and(2) To give to the Board and the Committeesa wide discretion so as to keep thescheme flexible and elastic .The Committee had favoured, the second of these alter-natives for two reasons:    in the first plaoe itwould be much easier to get the new proposal throughthe T-Touse of Commons.    If figures were inserted, inthe Regulations, as they would, have to be, attemptswould, certainly be made in the House of Commons to substitute other figures for them.    Secondly, and.this was more important, we had. to deal with a state
of affairs in which no two cases were exactly alike,and in these circumstances the more we attempted to lay down hard, an^  fast rules the more certainwas it that ine;qualities and injustices would thereby he created .    Tn this connection it must henoted, that the attitude of public opinion towardsthe Unemployment Assistance Board and. the Board&apos;sofficers was now very different from what it had.been eighteen months ago.    So far as he (the Chancellorof the Exchequer) had. been able to ascertain by personal inquiry   and. his impressions had. been confirmed, by the Board, themselves   the Board&apos;sofficers had. succeeded in gaining the confidence and. respect of the people concerned, and it was generally recognised, that the administration wassympathetic and. humane .    The system was now workingsmoothly, and. this was a. most important factor.It might be taken for granted that the localAdvisory Committees would, not treat their own peopleharshly.   Their inclination would be to be generous.Indeed, in some cases where the administration took a political rather than .a social aspect, the localCommittees might make unreasonable recommendations which could not be entertained.   On the whole,however, the local Advisory Committees might beexpected, to work the new rent rule fairly and.properly.    The Board, were also prepared, to take a sympathetic view, and the Cabinet would be well advised, to place confidence in the Board in thismatter.
e Earnings The chancellor of the Exchequer then drew thele.attention of the Cabinet to the new earnings ruledescribed on pages 6 and 7 of CP. 172 (36).      Thenew proposals were &quot;that the wage-earning membersaged 21 and over should retain the first 14/- of their earnings plus half of the remainder, with a minimum of20/-, this to be inclusive of the wage earners mainten-ance;    between 18 and 21, 12/- plus half of the remaind-er with a minimum of 16/-, and under 18, 12/- plus halfof the remainder&quot;. It was important to note theminimum of 20/- in adult cases.    This provision was sub-stantially more generous than was being allowed atpresent.      It would be seen, however, from CP. 179 (36)that the Secretary of State for Scotland favoured the allowance of 17/- plus half the excess with a minimum of20/- in respect of cases of 18 years and over, and 12/-plus half the excess in respect of cases under 18.This latter proposal,  if adopted, would have to applyto the whole country and would mean increasing the allowances much above what was now in practice being given.      For the reasons given    at the beginning of his statement he hoped that the Cabinet would not endeavourto solve the Scottish problem by creating much greater difficulties in England and Wales.The views of the Secretary of State for scotland were contained in his Memorandum (CP. 179 (36)), inparagraph 3 of which it was stated :&quot;If it appears that the new regulations will involve substantial &quot;cuts&quot; in many different types of case and in many different parts of the country, and thatthe Election promises have not been ful-filled in the spirit and in the letterwe may be faced with a very unpleasantpolitical situation...&quot;
In his (the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s) view theGovernment would,  in any case, be faced with such a situation, end the Secretary of State had not explainedhow his own proposals would avoid the difficulty.      Inparagraph 4 of CP. 179 (36), the Secretary of State had set out twelve Scottish towns, together with the percentageof household cases liable to suffer cuts under the new regulations as compared with the &quot;standstill&quot;.      In orderto complete the picture he (the Chancellor of the Exchequer)had added;  in a second column, the percentages whichwould have resulted from the adoption of the Secretary ofState&apos;s proposals : -Percentage under   Percentage under EarningsEarnings and Rent Rule suggested to theRules proposed by Minister of Labour by theS/S for Scotland. Unemployment assistance board, allowing rentprotection of &quot;3/- plus&quot;in a few areas where itis known that rents arelow and families relat-ively large.Airdrie. 39 42Bathgate 334r 37-Blantyre 31-g-Cowdenbeath 38 40Dunfermline 43 45Falkirk 53 53Johnstone 54^   . goKilmarnock 52 ^3Dundee 37^ 43Edinburgh 20Glasgow 28 31Hamilton 21 2bIt was clear that the difference between the two columnswould not relieve the Government of the necessity offacing &quot;a very unpleasant political situation&quot;.In conclusion the Chancellor of the Exchequerrepeated that it was impossible to avoid a bitter con-trover sy in regard to the new proposals.    He hoped thatthe Cabinet would accept the Committee&apos;s recommendations and decide to maintain them, however severe the criticism and uproar might be.
The Secretary of State for Scotland agreed with theChancellor of the Exchequer that the Meetings of theCabinet Committee had been many and arduous,but in theresult proposals had emerged which were infinitely betterthan the proposals first submitted to the Committee.      he also agreed that no concessions would conciliate theOpposition.    He was anxious, however, to conciliatemoderate and reasonable opinion, and in particular theGovernmentfs own Left Wing,      His answer to the figures which the Chancellor had given in respect of the twelveScottish areas was briefly that if the earnings rule couldbe modified in the direction he desired, while the numberof the cuts would not be substantially affected, the size of those cuts would be nothing like so great.      TheChancellor of the Exchequer had also indicated that he (theSecretary of State) had disagreed as to the effect of theproposals in the immediate future.      The first obstacle to be surmounted was the House of Commons, and if the Regulationscould be got through the House he agreed that the board should deal first with the cases of grossly excessive pay-ments and the cases of the younger persons.      There were three possible courses :-(l) To take no action at all.      This was clearly out of the question.(2) To deal only with the grossly excessivecases.      This would leave the real problemunsolved.(3) To try and improve the Regulations so as tosecure the general support of reasonablepublic opinion.He was in favour of this third course, but the difficulty would be to persuade the House of Commons to accept the new proposals.    As he had pointed out, at present 56 per cent.
of the cases in Great Britain and 70 per cent,  of thecases in Scotland were governed, not by the Board&apos;sRegulations, but by the Transitional Payment practice.parliamentary criticism would be directednot so much   to   what will happen in the first few weeks of the operation of the new Regulations, but  to what their ultimate effect was going to be.      He was distrustful ofthe estimate which the Board had formed of the politicalatmosphere which the new Regulations would create,  and hethought that the new proposals would be judged by theGovernment&apos;s Election pledges, and particularly by theElection Speeches made in the constituencies.Public opinion in Scotland tended to favour the giving of more generous treatment to these persons.      the cuts themselves would operate mainly in the distressed areas, and the Opposition would be sure to make the point that when wages were rising and prosperity increasing, theGovernment were cutting the relief of the destitute.      he admitted that the concessions which had been made in thecourse of the Committee&apos;s discussions were substantial and important.      His particular difficulties were three in number;    two being of substance and one of form.The new rent rule was quite satisfactory to him, but would it not be much more satisfactory when the TransitionalPayment cases had been transferred to the Board,for theproposed definite relaxations of the rule to be embodied inthe Regulations, and not as proposed in a verbal pledge orin the White Paper?      The Chancellor of the Exchequer had pointed out that if 3/- was mentioned in the Regulations,amendments would be moved to substitute 4/- or 5/-, butthe answer could easily be given that we were safeguarding the worst cases.      Eighteen months ago the arrangements had
broken down because of the very high percentage pf cuts.He had always maintained that a percentage of 20, 25,  oreven 30 per cent,  of cuts was defensible.    He wished again to urge two matters of substance.    In the first place he hoped that the earnings rule would be amended as suggestedin paragraph 5(2)of G.P. 179 (36), his reason being the hard-ship which would otherwise be inflicted on a large percentageof household cases in Scotland.    In this connection it shouldbe remembered that the allowance of 26/- for a man and wifeis at present almost universal throughout Scotland, and thatthe proposed figure of 24/- which applies only to householdswithresources would therefore   in   itself operate as an intensification of the Means Test.    In England in a sub-stantial number of areas the 26/- rate was now being given.In the case of a man and wife with a son earning 40/-, the allowance was reduced by 13/-j    in other words, the state was saving 13/- because    a   son living at home was earning40/-.It was pointed out that under the present arrangements the son would now be regarded as contributing 18/4d.  to the household and that under the Secretary of State&apos;s proposalhe would still be regarded as contributing ll/6d., or only l/6d.less than under the new Regulations.   Moreover othermatters would have to be taken into account under the new regulations which might alter the position.The Secretary of State for Scotland agreed, butmaintained his view that 13/- was an excessive deduction.He then referred to the question of single men in lodgingsand pointed out that in England 69 Authorities were giving17/- and 78 Authorities were paying less than 17/-.      Hesuggested 17/- because if the cost of food and rent wastaken into account, little,if any,margin would remain.He was sure that if the concessions he suggested could be
made, the position would he greatly eased, particularly asregards the passage of the Regulations through the House ofCommons.      He much appreciated the Committee&apos;s efforts and theimprovement in the Regulations which had resulted therefrom,and whatever the Cabinet might decide would have his full support.The    Standstill   had, in his opinion, worked remarkablysuccessfully, and there had been very little public criticism.The modifications he was asking for would mean an increased cost as regards the earnings rule of  350,000 per annum, andtheas renards/single man of a figure (given later in the Meeting)of between    150,000 and  200,000 if the allowance was raised to 16/-, and of between  275,000 and  325,000 if the figure was raised to 17/-.The Minister of Labour did not agree that the    Stand-still   had been successful, though not unnaturally it hadquieted criticism.      Its effect was to give the best of bothworlds, and in the areas of the extravagant Authoritiesmaximum benefits had accrued to everyone.    It was very important to note that of the applicants 56 per cent, were on TransitionalPayment and 44 per cent, on the original Regulations, and thatthere had been practically no complaints.    He agreed that inthe first year the additional cost of the new Regulations wouldbe about  500,000 per annum.      Critics of the present system had failed to emphasise its essential unfairness.    The benefitswere,  in the main, going to the households with resources,whereas the necessitous cases were, as a rule, to be found inthe households without resources.      Speaking generally, thenew proposals would benefit the older persons and the personswithout resources.    So far from the    Standstill   workingsatisfactorily, we were getting month by month further and. : &apos; - .-.&apos;:&quot;.: V .;:      /\;:&apos;--hvm&apos;&apos;:further away from actual Transitional Payments, and more and more into the realm of notional Transitional Payments.    There was a
increase their scales so that Transitional Payments might also increase.The new rent rule had the great advantage of flex-lb iii ty and would enable the local Advisory Committees toadvise on classes of cases in the light of local circum-stances.    Any attempt to apply mathematically the various proposals to the &quot;standstill&quot; rates as they would be atpresent in all the cases was an unreal process which couldserve no useful purpose.      The Board proposed to deal in thefirst instance with the grossly excessive payment cases andwith the cases of single men under 25.      For the rest the?local Advisory Committees would advise.the Board ss to thetempo at which the change over should be made.    He (theMinister) thought that it might be possible to effect thein the majority of cases,change in six months/    In any case the shock, if any, wouldbe of an entirely different order from the shock of 18months ago.As he had said, any estimates based on purely mathe-matical calculations were unreal and misleading,  as theywere based on the assumption that the size and composition of the register,  and the circumstances of all the applicantsand all the households would remain unchanged during thewhole liquidation period.    Moreover, they ignored the partthat Advisory Committees would play in the adjustment of the&quot;standstill&quot; allowances to those of the new Regulations withinthe liquidation period.      They also ignored proposals ofthe Board,for example, in relation to men in lodgings.   -Some discussion took place on the question whetherthe new rent rule would apply to single men in lodgings, andit was subsequently ascertained that the rule would notapply and that the question of rent paid   by a single manliving in lodgings would be dealt with under the discretion-ary powers.    If he were necessarily paying a rent of morethen 5/-, the Board would increase the 15/-.    They would not,
however, reduce on account of a lower rent.The Minister of Labour referred to the observations of the Secretary of State for Scotland in regard to the earnings rule, and quoted examples to show that the newrule, as favoured by the Cabinet Committee, was verygenerous.The question was asked why it was thought necessaryto distinguish in the rule between the adult wage earningmembers and the younger wage earning members.      It wassuggested that there was no ground on merits for drawingthis distinction and that if a minimum of 20/- was allowed in the case of the aault wage earner,  it snould also beallowed in the case of the adolescent wage earner.      Whilethe general practice in England was to make this distinction,the practice was different in Scotland, and if the newregulation was maintained there would be an acute grievancein Scotland.The Minister of Labour explained that it was the almost universal practice in industry to pay higher wagesat 21.      In this respect Unemployment Insurance benefit and the scale rates under the new Regulations of theUnemployment Assistance Board distinguished between adultsover 21 and adolescents under 21.The Minister of Health stated that, in his view, andin that of his Department, the new Regulations weregenerous and fulfilled the pledges which had been given at the General Election.      As compared with the original proposals the position had been entirely transformed.He attached great importance to the i^proposed method ofliquidating the Standstill and to limiting, as wassuggested, the classes which were to be dealt with in thefirst few weeks.      He also attached great importance tothe provisions relating to the local Advisory Committees.
It was certain that there would he much criticism and trouble, but public opinion would recognise thatthe new proposals were reasonable,  and that it wasnecessary for the Government to take a firm stand upon them.The Cabinet Committee had been unanimous inhoping that the undertaking which the Board would give in the White Paper regarding the part to be played byAdvisory Committees under the rent rule would be carriedout by the Board in the spirit as well as in the letter.As Minister of Health he was most anxious toprotect those Local Authorities who had been doing their duty during the Standstill period.      If the government made the proposals too generous, these Authorities wouldhave a legitimate grievance.      He attached greatimportance to the Cabinet being united in support ofthe Committee&apos;s proposals which would be certain toevoke some organised opposition but would, he felt sure,appeal to moderate and sensible public opinion.
The Home Secretary agreed with the -views expressedby the Chancellor of the Exchequer and only wished, to add certain general observations.The passage of the new Regulations might have very important reactions so far as the Home Office was concerned.    In certain parts of the country there might be very serious trouble and. even rioting.He had. therefore at the outset been very anxious tosee that the proposals were humane, fair, and inconformity with the Government&apos;s election pledges .There could, be no doubt at all that the Governmentwere bound, to introduce new Regulations, and. thequestion whether the Standstill har* worked, well orbadly was really immaterial.    The reasons why theoriginal Regulations had failed were (l) the existenceof a number of &quot;hidden snags&quot; and (2) the fact that the criticism by Government supporters in the House of commons had met with the agreement of reasonable public opinionoutside in regard to certain or&apos;xne proposals.   As aresult of the examination by the Committee he hoped.that there were no more &quot;hidden snags&quot;.   A comparison of the new Regulations with the Election Manifestoshowed, that the latter had been fully met on every point.   He had. great sympathy with the Secretary oftheState for Scotland, where/customs and. practices weredifferent from those in England and Wales.    Thedifficulty was that if the Committee agreed to theSecretary of State&apos;s proposals great and unjustifiableover-spending in England and. Wales   must inevitablyfollow .On merits he did. not agree with the Secretary ofState in regard, to inserting into the Regulationsthemselves the important discretionary provisionsunder the rent rule, both for the reason which had.been ,given by the Chancellor of the Exchequer andalso because if figures were inserted, in the rule- 19 -
injustices and inequalities must be created in casesfalling just  outside the fixed figure.He therefore believed that it was very much better to include the assurance in the vVhite Paper and notto attempt to incorporate it in the Regulations .In conclusion, he trusted that the Committee&apos;srecommendations would receive the unanimous approvalof the Cabinet.The Lord President of the Council said that he felt some doubt whether the Committee had been supplied with all the necessary figures, but if theSecrfitary of State for Scotland was satisfied in this&apos;respect he (the Lord President) would not press thepoint further.   He personally was satisfied both inregard to the proposals for liquidating the stand still and for ensuring flexible administration by the Boardand the local Advisory Committees.   He was willing toaccept the decision of the Cabinet and. to support therecommendations of the Committee.    It was imperative,however, that the Government should present an abso-lutely united, front in the House of Commons .The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries saidthat he was not in agreement with many of the points which had been made.    In his view the danger lay inthe House of Commons, which would compare the new regulations not with the previous Regulations but withthe present practice throughout the coup-^rv.   Theproblem was very largely the problem of the distressed areas.     Under the scale an adolescent aged 18 to 21 would receive 8/-.     This compared with 10/- now being paidin Edinburgh and Glasgow, 11/- in Lanarkshire, and 12/-in Fife,     For adolescents under 18 the scale rates were also below those now paid in many Scottish areas.36 The Secretary of State for Scotland, said thatbroaclly speaking he was satisfied with the&apos;figures sup-pliecl.
It was going to be very difficult indeed, to persuade the House of Commons to agree to cutting thesea&amp;olescentsup to 3/- a week.    The effect would, be an enormous steepening of the Means Test.    This was shown by the fact that the Minister of Labour had.claimed, that the benefits of the new regulations would, mainly go to older persons and. to householdswithout resources.The basic scale for a man and wife was to be cutfrom 26/- to 24/-. It was true that, in many areasin England. 24/- was the normal figure:    but in theindustrial areas in Scotland  it was 2 6/-&quot;,    and. it&apos;must be remembered, that many o^ those now receiving26/-, who might be in work when the new Regulationscane into operation, would next year be applying for relief and would, only get 24/-.    Some of the scaleallowances were worse than the cuts in transitionalpayment made in the crisis of 1931.    For example,a single man in lodgings in 1931 received. 15/3 asagainst 15/- under the new Regulation.The -Tome Secretary had claimed, that the new proposals fulfilled, the Election pledges.   Had. he(the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries) stated,at the Election what was now proposed, he doubted,whether he would have been returned.    The Election,however, had. not been fought on this basis at all.It.was certain, of course, that the extremistswould offer violent opposition to the proposals.The question was, could, the Government persuadeordinary reasonable persons to accept  them?    when one looked at the internal position in France and.Belgium one would, hesitate perhaps to embark on acourse which might well lead to civil commotion and.possibly bloodshed, in parts of the country.   He quite
NOTE.        On the Prime minister&apos;s instructionsthe discussion has been fully recorded.ehali Gardens, S . 7.1,June 25, 193 6.agreed that some cuts were inevitable, but he thoughtthat the new Regulations went beyond, what publicopinion would, regard, as fair and. reasonable.    vVould.it be out of the question to have the problem re-examined from the point of vie13&apos; of distinguishing between the distressed areas and the rest of thecountry?The Cabinet agreed.  To adjourn consideration of thequestion at this point and. tomeet again at 6 pan. in the PrimeMinister&apos;s Room at the T-Touse ofCommons the same day for thecontinuance of the discussion.

</content>
</cab>
