<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/41 images: 448-459</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1945.// ___SECRET. x / Copy No.W.P. (45) 291.10th May, 1945.WAR CABINET.REPORT OF MISSION TO THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.Note ey the Minister of Production.I attach a Report prepared by the Minister of Food and myself on our recentMission in the United States of America on world food supplies. This report has been discussed by the A d Hoc Committee set up by the Prime Minister andit is now submitted for the consideration of the War Cabinet.O. L.Ministry of Production. S.W.1,10th May, 1945.REPORT OF MISSION TO THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.Memorandum by the Minister of Production and the Minister of Food.THE first part of the time spent by the Mission in the United States ofAmerica was in agreeing a world balance-sheet covering the more importantfood-stuffs meat, oils and fats, sugar, dairy produce, wheat and rice, and someothers of less importance. The result of these enquiries, which were conducted by the officials of the United States of America, Canada and the United Kingdom,showed serious deficiencies in all these commodities (with the exception of wheat),which could not be met for a long time after V.E. Day. The figures showed a deficiency of 2,528 million pounds (1,125 thousand tons) of meat, 545 thousand tons of oils and fats, 910 thousand tons of sugar, 691 million pounds (310 thousand tons) of milk products, and 1,185 million pounds (535 thousand tons) of rice.Supplies of wheat are ample and the problem as regards wheat is one of transport and clearance at European ports.2. The circumstances in which the Mission had to carry on their work were particularly difficult. Mr. Byrnes, who had promised to be the bridge betweenthe Crowley Committee and the President, resigned two or three days after ourarrival, Mr. Hopkins was in hospital, the late President, up to the time of his death, was only in Washington for one day, the new President obviously couldnot be approached at once, and the imminence of the San Francisco conference had an unsettling effect upon the State Department. Apart from all this, the senior officials of the Administration were almost continuously &quot; on the hill &quot;appearing before various Committees, some of them on food. Air. Claytoninformed us that he had spent much more than half his time on such committees in the last three or four weeks.The other difficulties were, of&apos;course, that every American home is affectedby food problems. The distribution at any rate of meat is inefficient, and thesystem incapable of producing a fair and equal share for ail. It must, however,be recognised that the American problem is not the same as our own, although itis clear that it could be tackled if the Administration had the courage. &quot;Forexample, in the United States no meat can cross a State Border unless it isFederally inspected, and the Federal authorities require a high standard ofsanitary conditions in the slaughterhouses before they will give a certificate.[29839] B
Only 65 per cent, of the meat is Federally inspected, and therefore the Govern-ment has no control of the remaining 35 per cent, which is privately slaughteredand does not cross any State line. It is this meat, the non-Feclerally inspected,which leads to very high per capita consumption in the agricultural districts, andno doubt feeds the Black Market, which is rampant. Federally-inspected meathas to nil all the needs of the Armed Forces, which is the largest single demand,and consequently the amount of meat which the Government controls for exportabroad and for equalisation of distribution at home is very small in relation to theproblem. &quot;Where the rationing system is tighter, as it is in sugar, since there arelarge imports of sugar into the country, the machine was so inefficiently managedas to have allowed consumption to exceed the allocations made by the combined food Board by over 500,000 tons in 1944, and in the first quarter of 1945 at therate of a little less than 400.000 tons per annum.&quot;Uneasiness over the whole question of food is very marked, and the american public is well aware that the problem ha? been badly handled. Lastly, the death of the President made the Administration much more sensitive to Congressionaland Senate pressure, and it is generally supposed that in this, as in all otheraffairs, both bodies will assume a greater control.3. Yve should refer first to our visit to Canada. We may claim perhaps thatwe were successful in altering the Canadian attitude about meat supplies, andthat our conversations in Ottawa led the Canadian Government to open the detailed negotiations in Washington with a very helpful statement helpful on two counts; first, it announced an increase in the supply of meat by about50,000 tons, and secondly, because it produced a marked psychological effect uponthe Americans. Before this statement there was great publicity about the lackof meat rationing in Canada, and pictures of American citizens carrying steaksbought in Canada across the border were appearing in the Press. The statement;that Canada was prepared to bring her rations clown to the scale of the UnitedStates, and to make further supplies available, took much of the wind out ofthe American sails.4. Verv soon after the detailed negotiations in Washington began it becameobvious that if we attempted to make a plan to deal with all requirements,including those of neutrals and liberated areas, in a comprehensive manner atthe same time, a sharp reduction in Britain rations would be entailed. Wetherefore pursued the line of saying that in the circumstances we wished theAdministration to give us supplies which would guarantee the British basicrations at their present scale. If then the Americans came down to approximatelyBritish rates of consumption a substantial part of the reduced needs of the liberated areas could be met in meat, oils and fats, sugar and dairy products.5. The success of the negotiations was due in the main to our having kept to this line, and we persuaded the Crowley Committee to accept as its policy the safeguarding of British rations.It is worth while referring to the sugar agreement, perhaps the most successful agreement which we reached. Owing to previous over-consumption, it involves a very sharp cut in the use of sugar by the American consumer, andthat at a time when the rate for the second quarter had already been fixedbefore we arrived. The Times of the 1st May states that the Office of PriceAdministration reduced the annual sugar allotment for home preserving for eachration book holder from 24 lb. to 15 lb. on the evening of the 30th April. Theagreement established the principle of equal per capita consumption in the three countries which was also applied to oils.and fats. In meat, alone of the majorfood-stuffs in critical supply, will the average per capita consumption of the1United States be markedly above that in the United Kingdom. The reasonshave already been explained.6. Throughout the discussions we received no satisfacion. and no figuresupon miltiary requirements or scales, and it was obvious quite early that onlythe President could discipline the military. The supplies of meat, for example,provided for the United States Army and Armed Forces are something over400 lbs. per head (the usual estimated figure is 430 lbs.) per annum and even after the recent cut in the American civil -ration it was quite obvious that the liberated Areas could get little or no meat unless the Army procurement was going to be cut clown. We left the discussion with the President to the lastpracticable moment because we felt that it was inadvisable to face him with theproblem during the first few days of his tenure of office.   When the Minister of
Production saw him on Thursday, 26th April, and pressed the point, thePresident said that he had the matter under investigation, that he would takea personal interest in it, and he expressed vigorous assent when the Minister ofProduction told him that he would regard cutting clown the procurement of meat for the Army, and making the savings available for the Liberated Areas,as almost the equivalent of another victory. The Minister of Production used the argument that during the progress of the war against Germany reservesmust exist against submarine sinkings, and against the wastage, spillage andpilfering which are unavoidable when great armies move forward with suchrapidity. Was it too much, lie said, to ask that these reserves should be madeavailable for the Liberated Areas when manifestly the reasons for their existencehad passed away? It is interesting to note that (as announced in the Daily Telegraph on the 3rd May) American troops on light duties in the EuropeanTheatre of operation are to have their rations cut by 10 per cent. There is reason to hope that this reduction will have fairly general application.7. The result of these negotiations on the United Kingdom consumer can best be shown commodity by commodity : (i) Sugar.If the supplies available come up to expectation the amount of sugar avail-able for civilians in the United Kingdom will be 70-8 lb. per head per annuminstead of 71-5 as in the year 1944. This would mean no reduction in the basicsugar ration of \ lb. per week as the deficit would be covered by not making the christmas bonus issue of -\ lb. per head and by certain other small savings.Moreover, any savings in the military ration, for which allowance has been madeat double the civilian rate, will acrue to the benefit of civilians. A later review,however, may show that the supplies available have been over-estimated by some300.000 tons; if this be so about 75,000 tons would have to be deducted from theUnited Kingdom share. By making certain other economies in allocations to manufacturers (the effect of which would be apparent to the public) this deficitcould also be met without affecting our domestic sugar ration.(ii) Oils and Fats.There will have to be a cut of approximately 12&apos;! per cent, in the amountof fat issued to confectioners and biscuit manufacturers. If supplies fallsubstantially short of the estimate made in Washington it will be necessarylater to cut either the domestic fat or the household soap ration. It may allsobe necessary to reduce linseed for paint and linoleum.(hi) Dairy Products.We shall have to draw heavily upon our stocks of skim milk powder. If we continue the scheme of distributing skim milk powder to domestic consumersduring the winter, supplies to trade users will to all intents and purposes haveto be abandoned. The effect of this last step on the public will be very noticeableai the reduced quality of ice-cream and chocolates.In evaporated milk it will certainly be necessary to reduce Service require-ments substantially and also the supplies given in the winter months to caterers.The effect of this latter step will be to increase the call on liquid milk. In thecase of Condensed Milk it is expected that no change will be necessary in thesmall releases of both SAveetened and skim-sweetenecl under the Points Scheme.In Cheese we may not be able to maintain the 2 oz. ration throughout therest of the year, but we are going to try both to obtain additional cheese from canada and also to manufacture more in this country.(iv) Bacon and Meat.The bacon ration must be reduced from 4 to 3 ozs. per week forthwith andthe amount of meat issued for manufactured products such as sausages will haveto be reduced.The basic meat ration of Is. 2d. per week can be maintained but only by requiring butchers, as has been done before, to accept as part of their rationedsupplies twopennyworth of canned corned beef to Is. Od. worth of carcase meatper week during five months of the year.Practically no meat will be available for the liberated areas until the fourthquarter of this year.[29839] &quot; B 2
(v) Wheat.The problem is not one of supply but of transport and there should be no reduction in the amount of wheat available for the. United Kingdom.If the necessary shipping can be provided very large amounts of wheat canbe made available for liberated areas.8. The table at Annex II shows the quantities of food required for liberated areas.9.   Annex I sets out the text of the Agreement reached with the Americans.10. We draw particular attention to the danger of countries outside the combined Food Board that have foreign balances trying to buy meat in theArgentine and elsewhere in South America.The Argentine Government is now showing little willingness quickly to conclude a long-term contract with this country. They may be waiting to see whether any other buyers are forthcoming. Both a French and a Belgian missionare proceeding shortly to that country. The President and the State Departmentboth promised to give support to our remaining the sole buyers of meat in theArgentine. If we are to maintain that position the Foreign Office must exertpressure upon the French Government.11. We trust that our colleagues will confirm these arrangements. In ouropinion they are the best that could possibly be obtained. The fact that equality of consumption is firmly established in oils and fats and sugar represents an advance upon any previous arrangement, which we think a considerable achieve-ment in face of the surrounding political and other difficulties.O. L.J. J. L.Ministry of Production, S.W.1,5th May, 1945.
I. ^Sugar.After allowance has been made for requirements of other countries, including938,000 tons for the liberated areas, it is estimated that the total quantity of sugar available for allocation to the United States. United Kingdom and Canadaduring the last nine months of 1945 will be 6,492,000 tons, making the total available to these countries for the whole year 8,684,000 tons. It is agreed thatthis balance shall be allocated to the civilian and military populations of thethree participating countries on a basis which would achieve equality of consump-tion levels for the nine months beginning the 1st April, 1945.It is assumed that the rate of per capita consumption by the Armed Forcesof the three participating countries would be double that of the per capitaconsumption of the civilian population. If this consumption were applied inpractice the average civilian per capita consumption level in each country during-the last nine months of 1945 would be at the annual rate of 70-8 pounds and theaverage military level at the annual per capita rate of 141-6 pounds. It would,however, be within the discretion of each of the three Governments to make anyadjustment between their military and civilian consumption within the alloca-tion agreed.Under this programme the allocation for the last nine months of 1945 to theUnited States will be 4,617 thousand short tons (raw value), .to the United[29839] b 3Intergovernmental Discussions on Eood Supplies.Memorandum of Understanding.Preamble.REPRESENTATIVES of Canada, the United Kingdom and the UnitedStates have together examined the supplies and requirements for 1945 of the major food-stuffs in short supply.With the notable exception of wheat and flour, supplies of most foods are inadequate to meet stated requirements, including those of liberated areas. Inview of the urgent need of food in the liberated areas the three countries areprepared to make every reasonable effort to make available essential food require-ments consistent with the effective prosecution of the war and the maintenance of productive capacity within each of the countries.There is set forth in this memorandum proposed programmes with respectto import commodities which represent the intentions of the three countries in1945. These programmes will be reviewed by the Combined Eood Boardmachinery prior to the 1st June and again prior to the 1st September, andfirm allocations will be made on a quarterly basis by the appropriate supplyagencies of the participating countries, after discussions with other countriesaffected by the recommendations. In the Combined Eood Board review therepresentatives of the three participating countries will be guided by theprinciples set out in the attached statements.The plans set forth herein are subject to approval by the Governments ofthe three countries.Any adjustment of supplies to the U.S.S.R. consequent upon the carryingout of the plans set forth herein are subject to consultation with the PresidentsSoviet Protocol Committee in the United States, the Allied Supplies executive in the United Kingdom, and the Canadian Mutual Aid Board in Canada.In so far as adjustments in supplies in Civil Affairs programme arenecessary in consequence of the carrying out of the plans herein set forth, theywill be subject to consultation with the Combined Civil Affairs Committee.The following commodities are covered :  I. Sugar.II. Oils and Fats.III. Meat.IV. Dairy Products (except butter).V. Wheat.VI. Rice.VII. Canned Fish.VIII. &apos; Beans and Peas.
Kingdom 1,532 thousand short tons (raw value) and to Canada 343 thousand tons (raw value). Taking into account the quantities estimated to have beenconsumed in the first quarter of the year, the total quantities receivable by thethree countries for the whole year will be : -United States   .........      6,274,000 short tons (raw value)United Kingdom        ......       1,962,000 short tons (raw value)Canada   ............ 448,000 short tons (raw value)8,684,000 short tons (raw value)A further review of the supply position will be made not later than the1st June. If this review indicates that the supply available for allocation tothe three countries will be greater than 8,684,000 tons, the increased quantitywill be divided in accordance with the formula set out above. If the figuresindicate that the quantity available for allocation will be less than8,684,000 tons :-*(a) The United Kingdom representatives undertake to use their influence with producing and consuming countries in the Middle East and inother territories covered by the London Food Council to makemaximum quantities available for meeting any deficit before anyuniform cut is made and in the event of a contribution of 50,000 tonsnot being available from this source the United Kingdom agrees tocontribute from its stocks the quantity necessary to make up the50,000 tons.(b)&apos; Account shall be taken of any alteration in the numbers of military personnel.Thereafter immediate cuts will be made to eliminate any deficit. Such cutsshould be borne equally by the participating countries, the liberated areas, theU.S.S.R. and the European neutrals in proportion to the amount of their presentallocations.The participating Governments will take immediate steps to prevent over-issues of sugar during the ensuing period so that if any reduction in allocationsbecomes necessary later in the year, it will avoid special hardship during the latermonths.II. Fats and Oils.A balance sheet of the 1945 world fats and oils situation reveals that require-ments exceed estimated supplies by approximately 500,000 long tons in termsof oil.The Combined Food Board Recommendation No. 170 embodies an inter-national allocation of fats and oils for the first six months of 1945.In order to meet the deficit in the calendar year of 1945 certain additionalsevere cuts in consumption in the United Kingdom, Canada and the UnitedStates must be made if substantial supplies are to be provided for liberated areas. Such action is agreed to by representatives of these three countries onthe basis of the following procedure : *1. As soon as practicable, but in no event later than the 1st June, 1945, theCommittee on Fats and Oils of the Combined Food Board shallrecommend to the member Governments an allocation programme forthe period the 1st July, 1945, through 30th June, 1946.&quot;2. This programme is predicated upon (a) the United Kingdom obligatesitself to reduce its stocks by 245,000 tons during the calendar year1945 and to a further reduction of 75,000 tons during the last halfof 1945, and 25,000 tons during the first half of 1946; and (b) &apos;an agreed reduction in consumption in each of the three countriesnecessary to balance the remaining deficit shall be shared by thesecountries in proportion to their stated total use of fats and oils,including butter, as shown in the table prepared as the balance sheetfor the 1945 calendar year.3. The principle of exclusive purchasing is reaffirmed, and buying arrange-ments shall conform to existing policy covering all exporting areas;subject, of course, to such minor modifications from time to time asmay be mutually acceptable to all parties adhering to the proposedCombined Food Board agreement.
4. Such 1945-46 allocations shall be subject to periodic review in the lightof changing conditions of supply and demand so as to make full use by agreement of any additional supplies or to share such furthersacrifices as may become necessary.The Committee on Fats and Oils of the Combined Food Board will begindiscussions immediately with the members of the Committee and other partici-pating claimants to implement this document as herein outlined.III.-Meat.Representatives of the United States, United Kingdom and Canada have considered the meat situation and based upon current estimates of forthcoming-supplies :  1. The United States undertakes to furnish 220 million lbs. carcass weightof canned meat to liberated areas out of fourth quarter productionexcept to the extent that such canned meat is required by the UnitedStates Army Forces for the successful prosecution of the war.2. The United States undertakes to make available 268 million lbs. of carcassmeat to the United Kingdom out of fourth quarter production, lessany quantity which the United Kingdom is able to obtain from SouthAmerica in excess of their current expectations of 1,479 million lbs.and on condition that the United States Army Forces are furnished with 433 million lbs. carcass weight of meat from the southern dominions.3. The United States undertakes to furnish the maximum possible quantitiesof canned meat for liberated areas from United States military stocks in Europe after VE day.4. Before the firm allocation for the fourth quarter the United Statesundertakes to consider whether it can provide additional quantitiesof carcass meat to the United Kingdom in consideration of any amount of canned (Points) meat which the United Kingdom is ableto offer to liberated areas at that time.5. The United Kingdom also undertakes to make available to the UnitedStates Armed Forces 41 - 5 per cent, of the canned meat obtained fromits purchases in South America.6. The Canadian Government undertakes to make available an additional quantity estimated at least 25 million ibs. of carcass meat to theUnited Kingdom and 90 million lbs. of canned meat for liberated areas.IV. Dairy Products.The supply and requirements position of certain dairy products for 1945has been examined. .1. Dry Skimmed Milk.There is a deficit between estimated requirements and supplies of134 million lbs. or approximately 15 per cent, of supplies. The United Statesundertakes to furnish liberated areas with 330 million lbs. of dry skimmed milkduring 1945, and undertakes to make available to the United Kingdom34-8 million lbs. and to United Kingdom Services overseas with 7-2 million lbs.To the extent, however, that consumer packets are required by the UnitedKingdom from United States supplies in excess of 34-8 million lbs., they willbe provided on the condition that offsetting quantities in bulk containers be&quot;madeavailable to liberated areas from United Kingdom stocks. Further, to the extent that shipments in bulk containers to the United Kingdom have been made in1945 in excess of 34-8 millions lbs., offsetting supplies will be expected for liberated areas from United Kingdom stocks.2. Condensed Milk.The deficit in sweetened condensed milk is estimated to be 152 million lbs.fhe requirements of liberated areas total 226 million lbs. The United Statesundertakes to furnish liberated areas with 58-3 million lbs. of condensed milk in1945, and will consider the balance of the requirements of the liberated areas for this product as part of the requirement for evaporated milk. It also under-takes to make available 6-7 million ibs. to meet the Service requirements of theUnited Kingdom.
3. Evaporated Milk.The total deficit in evaporated milk will be approximately 465 million lbs.,to which must be added a deficit of 92 million lbs. carried forward from condensed milk. The United States undertakes to furnish 300 million lbs. of evaporated milk to liberated areas and to make available 500 million lbs. to the British services overseas during 1945, to the extent that sufficient packaging materials can beobtained to meet this programme as well as that of the United States armed forces. The Governments of Canada and the United States will furnish such additional quantities of evaporated milk as possible to meet the requirements ofthe British Services overseas.As a result of these arrangements the requirements of the liberated areas willbe met in substantial measure provided the packaging difficulties in the UnitedStates can be overcome. The United States representatives undertake to make every effort to obtain the necessary packaging material.4. Cheese.The estimated deficit amounts to 146 million lbs. and the requirements of liberated areas for the balance of the year stand at 127 million lbs. The UnitedStates undertakes to furnish 100 million lbs. of cheese to liberated areas in 1945provided facilities are available in Europe to handle this cheese satisfactorily.If the liberated areas are found not to be in a position to handle substantial quantities of soft cheeses, the situation in the United States and in the UnitedKingdom will then be re-examined.The United States undertakes to make available 150 million lbs. of cheeseto the United Kino-dom and to British Services overseas. This wall involve areduction in the United Kingdom ration below the current rate of 2 ozs. a week.(3 ozs. during the winter months.)V. Wheat.Representatives of the United Kingdom, United States and Canada havejointly considered the wheat situation, particularly with respect to its relationship to the urgent needs of liberated areas. The problem is one of movement rather thansupply. They recognise that unless quantities of wheat substantially identical with the stated requirements of the liberated areas are furnished, the food situation in Europe toward the end of 194-5 will become most critical, particularlyin view of the difficulty which has been encountered in making a sufficient quantityof supplies of other food products available to meet liberated area demands.The United States representatives have undertaken to use every endeavour toensure that the necessary arrangements are made in the United States to enablethe maximum quantity of wheat and flour to be shipped from North atlantic and Gulf Ports.As a result of measures which they are taking, they expect to be in a positionto move 200 million bushels of United States wheat and approximately 85 million bushels of flour, wheat equivalent, in implementation of liberated area pro-grammes. The United States will also assist in the movement of Canadian wheat in transit from the lower lakes to the Atlantic seaboard so as to increase exports from Canada and maintain an active milling programme designed to supply asmuch flour as possible throughout the season.The Canadian Government is making every effort to move a maximum ofwheat and flour into export positions and undertakes to supply 312 million bushelsof wheat and 58 million bushels of flour over the North Atlantic route during thebalance of 1945.The three Governments recognise the importance which attaches to a rapidimprovement in port intake capacity and inland transportation in Europe, andwill take-such steps as lie.in their power to ensure that these factors do not standin the way of the implementation of the full programme. They will also take all practicable steps to ensure that shipping for the supply of wheat and flour for europe is given an adequate priority.VI. Rtce.1. The total rice deficit for 1945 is estimated at 1,185 million lbs., takingrequirements for Far East liberated areas at 746 million lbs.2. Omitting Far Eastern requirements, there is a deficit of 439 million lbs-m the remainder of the world.
3. Special measures are necessary to ensure that the requirements of thosecountries especially in need of rice are met Ceylon, Cuba and the West Indies.4. The Hinted States is prepared to make available the necessary quantitiesneeded for United States territories, Cuba and Canada, In addition, they under-fake to provide up to 125 million lbs. of rice for feeding programmes in the pacific Theatre of War.5.   The United Kingdom will use its best endeavours to obtain from other sources the rice needed to meet the requirements of Ceylon in view of the import--mice of that conn try&apos;s industries (rubber, tea, copra) to the war effort.6. In view of the world shortage of rice, it may not be possible to meet therice requirements of the liberated areas of North-Western Europe or to meet theneeds of European neutrals.7. The representatives of the United Kingdom, United States and Canadarecognise that the rice deficit in the Ear East cannot be met unless the rice-producing areas, namely Siam, Indo-China. Formosa and Burma, are rapidlyliberated and their rice industries rehabilitated.VII. Canned Fish.1. A balance-sheet for 1945-46 has been prepared showing a deficit of955 million lbs. between supplies and stated requirements. Stocks in the UnitedStates and United Kingdom are at their minimum operational figures and nofurther reductions can be considered.2. The requirements&apos; of the liberated areas have been stated as 547 million lbs.These are still incomplete. In that it is unlikely that any substantial quan-tities of canned meat will be available for liberated areas it is suggestedthat a substantial contribution should be made to their needs of canned fish.3. The United States, United Kingdom and Canada undertake to review their military and civilian requirements with the object of making the maximum possible contribution to liberated areas.4 It is recommended that any decision about the allocation of canned fishshould be deferred until the canned meat position is clearer and that, in cleter-mining what the liberated areas requirements should be, canned meat and cannedfish supplies should be considered together to ensure that reasonable provision ofthis form of foodstuff is made for the needs of the liberated countries.VIII. Beans and Peas.Full consideration has not been given to the world position in regard to beansand peas. It is agreed that this matter shall be further considered by the combined Food Board. The United States is prepared to provide a total of10 million bas;s, 100 wt., of pulses for liberated areas and about 2 million bagsfor other exports. *Washing ton. D.C.27th April, 1945.
ANNEX II.Liberated Areas.Commodity. (1)	Unit, (2)	Requirements of S.H.A.E.F.,S.A.C,M.E.D., Allied Governments and r.x.i;.i;..\. (3)	Requirements as screened by Working Party. (4) &quot;	Supplies Allocated or to be Allocated. (5)	Notes. (6)Sugar ... Oils and Fats...... Meat......... Dairy Products  Dry Skim Milk    ... Condensed Milk Evaporated Milk ... Cheese	&apos;000 tons &apos;000 tons Million lbs. Million lbs.	1,127 1,121 2,123 (nearly all canned)	1,011 805 1,687 (1,100 canned) 345. 166 \ 293 j 127	936 800 220    from    United States   in    fourth quarter 90 from Canada (all canned) 330 35S-3 100	Allocation subject to proportionate cuts if June review shows greater deficit than now estimated. It is hoped to meet the whole of the screened requirements, provided United Kingdom destocks as agreed, and remaining deficit is shared by reduced consumption in United States, United Kingdom, and Canada. The United States contribution is subject to United States Army demands.    In addition, United States will furnish maximum from United States military stocks in Europe after Y.E. Day, and  will consider additional carcase meat  for United Kingdom in consideration of any canned (points) meat United Kingdom can offer to liberated areas. Allocation depends on solution of United States packaging problem. Allocation depends on European  ability to handle &quot;soft&quot; cheese.



</content>
</cab>
