<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/86/0 images: 134-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
132OIL prices memorandum by the Minister of power at the outset of the Suez emergency the main oil distributivecompanies agreed to consult the Government before increasing theprices of their products.   Under this arrangement we consented tocertain increases in December last to meet the extra costs arisingout of the closure of the Suez Canal and the Syrian pipelines.   Thecompanies now seek consent to further increases.2.       To avoid anti-trust and restrictive practices complications thecompanies apply for consent separately and not collectively.    their proposals vary from company to company and from product to productbut all are of the order of Id. per gallon,3.     The justification for the increase lies in higher market pricesof oil products and of crude oil in the United States Gulf, and a rise intanker freights, above the level allowed for in current prices, partly offset by a fall in the costs of transit round the Cape due to the more efficient use of tankers.    The evidence on costs produced by thecompanies has been carefully considered by my Department and itappears that the price increases listed in the Appendix are warranted.These increases are below the highest levels proposed by the companies.4.     Although further increases in oil prices are unwelcome I donot think we can refuse our consent.    The companies are undoubtedly-involved in heavy extra costs and apart from this a refusal on our part to recognise the increased prices of American oil, after our endeavours to get American production stepped up for our benefit, would be most fortunate.5.     The timing of the increases, however, raises political issues which I should like to discuss with my colleagues.COPY NO.CABINETM.Ministry of Power, S. W.l.13th March, 1957.secret.(57) 6713th March, 1957
Present Price Proposed Price(per gallon) (per gallon)&quot;	Basic		Emergency-			Basic		Emergency			Net	Price		Surcharge	Total		Price		Surcharge	Total		Increa:	s.	d.		s.	d.	s.	d.		s.	d.	A. Wholesale Prices											Aviation Spirit	5	7	3d.	5	10	5	8 	2fd.	5		id.Motor Spirit (Premium)	5		3 Id.	5	6i	5	4i	2fd.	5	7	Gas/Diesel Oil	1	A	3d.	1	5a	1	41	2^d.	1	7l	lid.Kerosines	1		3d.	1	7f	1	61	2 d.	1	81	Id.Fuel Oil			3d.	1	2f	1	1*	2^d.	1	3i	\ d.B. Retail Prices											Motor Spirit (Premium)	5	7*	5d.	&amp;		5	9	4 id.	6	ii	Id.NOTE:   (a)  The basic prices of aviation and motor spiritinclude duty at the rate of 3s. 6d. per gallon(including the additional Is. imposed inDecember). -(b) All basic prices vary with alterations in themarket prices in the United States Gulf.

</content>
</cab>
