<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 65-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
5j Q R E T. 0.1/141/403.Copy No. 17........Secretary,:   If IIP &apos; ^&apos;War Cabinet.^HALLjy^   The attached memorandum (Uo.286 dated 17,12,17) fromGeneral Delme Radcliffe giving some details regarding thestrength and re-organisation of the Italian Armies Iscirculated for the information of the War Cabinet.The chief points to note are(1)    The total losses of the Italian Army during the retirement were 530,000 men made up as follows 30,000 dead 250,000 prisoners90,000 wounded 100,000 sick;    and 60,000 unaccounted for, who are presumably deserters In Italy, and are still at large.(2)    The total strength of the Italian Armies In the WarZone (excluding Albania and&apos;Macedonia) on 1st December 1917 was 1,747,400.(3)   The class called up this year is now incorporated in field units and Is reported to be doing very well.(4)    The 1900 class to be called up next year Is expected to produce 250,000 men.(5)    The position as regards rifles and machine-guns is satisfactory owing to French and British assistance,(6)   The re-armament of the Italian Armies with field artillery is proceeding; satisfactorily and It is expected that the 51 Infantry Divisions will each have 10 field batteries completed by the end of the year,(7)   It appears that the promises of howitzers and heavy guns made by the Italian Ministry of Munitions are .qualified by the fact that although the guns may be delivered to time, there may be delay in the supply of sights, fittings, spare-parts, etc.General Staff, War Office.28.12.17.
^-n^m . Italy   of 17th December 1917-)EC Kii-i... -;-NO.B..M..286..To The Director of Military Operations.,War Office.. London,      Sal..The following details concerning the strength on re-organisation of the Italian Army may be of interest :-The present strength of the Infantry is as follows : -92 Brigades of the Active Array (as per attached list) equal to .546 Battalions of which 30 are at Salonika and 12 in Albania,.    (a few Brigades have more and a few less than   battalions, but they are in process of equalisation),. FurtherBersaglieri,...........    48 Battalions of which 3 are in Albania,.Alpini .... *,.   68 Battalions.Skiatori 2 Battalions.3ersagliericyclists,.........,,.,..    12 Battalions.TOTAL...______.. c o,., 667 Battalions.(The above figures do not include troops in Tripoli, Cyrenaica, the Aegean, Erithrea and Somaliland) .Further there are 7 March Brigades  (assembled round CasteIfranco) with a total approximate strength of 60,000 men. There are&apos; now no other drafts available.The 1899 class  of recruits produced about 250,000 men, of which about 140,000 wont to the infantry and are doing very well on the front now.    It is expected that the 1900 class will produce also about 250,000 men and that it will be called up between January and. April 1918.The infantry units are organised, as follows  t-The Company ;    150 rifles ; 2,4 men with pistol cartridge machine-gun section (2 guns) and 30 men for supply, transport, stretcher bearers, etc.,       Total.......   204 rank and file.
Division.	Number.9 th.	16,80029th.	17,70052nd.	28,1942nd.	21,43612 th.	13,74827 th.	16,87737 th.	21,62418th.	25,57036 th.	26,7438 th.	18,60350 th.	25,00053rd.	20,90468th.	11,45048th,	18,28861st.	19,748	Total....    302,6852.The Battalion ;    3 Companies as above; 1 machine-gun company with 6 guns and 126 rank and file; 4 light trench mortars with 44 rank and file; 16 transport carts with 32 quadrupedsand 24 rank and file.     Total....... 806 rank and file.The Regiment : 3 Battalions as above; pack transport with 109 rank and file and 100 to 200 mules, according to circumstances;Total.......................... 2,527 rank and file.The Brigade : 2 regiments as above, 2 Companies of machine-guns with 12 guns and 252 rank and file, headquarters transport 1 cart, 2 quadrupeds and 11 rank and file.Total........................... 5,297 rank and file.Other details bring total strength up to 5,973, or say 6,000 in round numbers.The Division : 2 brigades as above, 2 machine-gun companies, 1 regiment field artillery, 1 battalion Engineers, Medical, Supply, Transport and Mechanical Transport units,-   ; - !.-.,-        .\  - .  ,     ...... .. &apos; ----- &apos;      -.   &apos;   - . -&apos; .... -    - , \ 1. -.-    -      -   -   &quot;i7-&apos;; &apos;/:-:.   .%:&apos;&apos;-   -   -W-V, v V - /    : v ; -  V ?-V : !: ..        :     - . - . &apos; .        ;   &quot; - &apos;   .      .       -. ^ - - -  - &apos;.i        .But the strength of the Division is very variable owing   , to losses, arrival of drafts, etc., etc.     The following table of the strengths, including absent sick (400 to 500 per Division) on 1st December 1917 of 15 Divisions taken indiscriminately from various Armies, enables an estimate to be made of the actual average strength in men of the Division
The total number of machine-guns vihich the Italian Army had left after the retreat was 5,000 in round numbers. But 2,000 Saint Etienne pattern. French machine-guns are expected very shortly and also 2,000 British Lewis guns; it is not known, however, ?/hen the latter will arrive. 150,000 French service rifles are to be supplied at once and 50,000 British service rifles are also expected.In addition to the above, about 100.000 new rifles, produced in Italy, are available,     Tho whole of the infantry of the Italian Fifth Army is to be armed with French rifles.The following artillery is expected from France im 300 Field guns 75 mm., calibre, French pattern for certain and shortly 75 h.eavy field guns of 120 mm, calibre and 75 guns of 155 mm. calibre are hoped for later.The Italian divisional field artillery will all be completed in a few days.     As to horses, it has been possible to find enough to make good requirements and about 4,000 left over will still be available.       There are at the present moment 3,000 artillery horses sick, but it is hoped to utilise most of these again.11 Regiments field artillery have been completely equipped with new materiel; 12 or 13 regiments have a part only of their batteries.      The remainder are being formed as rapidly as possible at Campe di Mirandola,     128 batteries have been re-formed as far as personnel and horses are concerned and some have already received their materiel. 60 of these batteriesallotted to the Fifth Army, are to be armed with French guns and are being formed into 6 regiments of 10 batteries each.It is intended that all the field artillery regiments of the army are to have ten batteries per regiment in future, instead of eight.     Sixteen batteries of the Second Army have already been supplied- with new Italian Deport materiel andthe
the total of one regiment frr each division will soon he complete.     The First Army is still deficient in Field Artillery, hut this is partly owing to its requirements in position artillery heing greater than in field artillery.The Third Army has had its field artillery completed with a total of 10 batteries per division, but the allotment has not yet been entirely equalised and some divisions may have more than others.A total of 57 regiments of field artillery will be completed by the end of December,  though, possibly, 3 cr 4 regiments may still require some guns to complete.    Of these regiments, 51 will be allotted to the 51 divisions of the Army and 6 will remain as a reserve at the disposal of the Comando, Supremo.The Ministry of Arms and Munitions has promised to supply the following artillery materiel by the end of the year :-Field guns, 75 mm.    Deport, 84 batteries or 536 guns.. Heavy field artillerv105 mm, guns................... 53 batteries, or 212 guns.149 mm. howitzers................ 60 batteries, or 24.0 howitzersOf the above, the Comando Supremo hopes that perhaps one-half may be delivered, as promised and the remainder in January and February.In addition to following heavy guns have been promised :-280 mm. Howitzers,  1 battery................... 2 howitzers.381 mm. Howitzers, 1 battery ............... 1 howitzer.210 mm. Howitzers, 4 batteries .16 howitzers.149 mm. Guns, 8 batteries .............32 guns.Although the above materiel may be delivered, it would appear that the accessories, such as sights, fittings, spare parts, etc., may be lacking and so delay the formation and employment of the batteries.
5th November. 1st December.Comando Supremo, IntendenzaGenerale, etc.Troops on the Northern (Swissfrontier)Intendenza. G.D.Naval Stations (Piazze Marittime)121,8004,200 7,600 50,000123,2004,200 7,700 51,200CavalryIllrd Army-Corps First Army. Second Army. Third Army. Fourth Army. Fifth Army.In re-forming Camps  (Campi di riordinamento)Employed on construction of works of defence.(These men belong to units broken up in the retirement and will shortly be passed to reform units)Albania and Macedonia,10,700 88,300 383,800 162,000 259,100 246,300 65,9 ^0200,000 60,00011,300 101,300 408,600 156,500 261,100 301,20055,300195,800 70,000110,CC0112,100TOTAL... 1,769,7001,859,500From the first column it would appear, therefore, that the total losses in men owing to the retirement were approximately 530,300,     Of.these it is estimated that about 30,000 are dead, 250,000 prisoners, 90,000 wounded,The following summarised estimate., of the losses during the recent retirement has been made :-The total strength, of the Army in the War Zone before October 24th was, in round numbers, about 2,300,000*   The total strength under various headings on the 5th November and 1st December, was as follow
100,000 sick and 60,000 still unaccounted for.The total strength of the men of the Milizia Territoriale (now including only men of the 1877 - f78 -and 179 classes) is about 80,000.     With these some 90 battalions of varying strength are formed.     24 of these battalions aro in Albania organised as regiments.     About 20,000 of the total number are regarded as combatants, the remainder as labour troops.As regards mechanical transport, the number of lorries lost was less than at first feared.     Since the retirement, as units have become re-organised, a number cf lorries have been found which had been commandeered by various units to supplement their own transport and which they detained.     Consequently it is estimated that less than. 1,000 lorries in all have been lost.The supply of transport lorries has now been made good and increased considerably beyond the formerscale in the case of many Army units,     There was alarge stock of lorries at the Piat works awaiting shipmentto Russia,     These have been partly drawn upon and the number required has been made good by means of the dailyoutput of 60 lorries per diem produced by the Fiat C om oanyof which about 30 are for Italy and the remainder for Francand other countries,     This is additional to those producedby the other manufacturing firms in Italy.The Fifth Army, further, has not yet receivedits allotment of mechanical transport, but this will becompleted by tho middle of next month.The principal anxiety as regards mechanicaltransport is the supply of petrol.     The Italian authoritie
Comando Supremo, Italy.have been forced to break into their general reserve of petrol and to mix the petrol with a certain proportion of petroleum in order to make it go further. The supply in this country is enough to last till the end of the month.   One steamer per month suffices to maintain the supply required, but if another steamer does not arrive before the end of December, the situation will be serious.   Two petrol transport ships were torpedoed just before the recent retirement began.(sd.)    C. Delme-Radcliffe, Brigadier-General *

</content>
</cab>
