<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 73-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel JonesThis Document is the Property of His Britannio Hajestyls Government.//SECRET.WAR CffilffBTComplaints of Hardship incurred whilst awaiting medical examination for the Army.One of the recommendations cf the Commission ofEnquiry into Industrial Unrest for the Wales and lion-mouthshire Division was as follows:-,;The immediate discontinuance of a too general practice on the part of modical hoards to keep numbers of man herded together long hours, in a nude state, and in comfortless placesj pending thoir medical examination&quot;,I confess that, having regard to assurances given onthe Occasions when complaints had been made, I had thoughtthere- was not much sdbstanoe in the complaint referred to bythe Commissioners;    but I have just had brought to my noticea concrete instance of a hardship which may be caused by thispractice, and I attach for the information of my colleagues,an extract from the letter referred to me.(SGD) GclJ,BARING.
&quot;A young friend of mine, wq will call A.B,, who returned from Canada 4 years ago, because he found the severity of the climate unbearable,   his father sent him to Largate for the benefit of the air of that placo with ad van at age.    Y/hen the war broke out in 1914, he entered the Royal Arsenal  vt \bolwich, where ho remained for 3 years.    In 1916, he was unwell for nearly 5 months and therefore frequently absent, and this painful con-ditiqn was repeated in 1917,-   las frequent absence from ill health, compelled him to take his discharge  mid his father sent him to Hastings for change,while there., the. authorities sent him three several sets of forms to fill up, and directed him to come to London for medical examination.    He replied at once, stating he was at Hastings and asked for a pass to London for the purpose.   The&apos; authorities then wrote saying they had arranged for him to be examined at Brighton and sent him a pass for that place.On Londay, the 17th; inst,, he went to Brighton, Upon arriving at the Town Hall, the place appointed, he was directed&apos;to attend at the Town Hall at Eovo, 2 miles away, - this he did.   Upon his arrival there, it being near the lunch hour., -the examination was deferred mntill the afternoon, when he again&apos;attended.   He and seven others were ushered into a large room, where was a fire, ancl directed by the 11,0,0. Orderly to strip, ready for ox-amiuation4    In this condition, naked except for their overcoats and waterproofs, they remained for about 2 hours before the examination took place,Ily friend when examined was classed C3, and granted exemption for 6 months.The circumstances against which I protest vehemently are that 3 menmsome of them worse crocks than A.B,, should be ordered to strip and compelled to remain for 2 Ion;&apos; hours with no other protection than a coat,   ,-If they had been criminals they could not have been treated in a worse manner.All the advantage derived by the 5 weeks residence at Hastings has been undone by this stupidity.This, I fear, is only one sample- out of thousands which illustrate the ineptitude of some of the authorities, and for which the Government is blamed,&quot;

</content>
</cab>
