<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 77-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i9 C?&quot; I[ THIS DOCUMENT IS THS PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANK10 MAJKa^Y1 .S, JKW^MMEKT)71SEC R E 3?,w A RC A 3 I 11 B--ToGaT, 3127PROPOSED APPOIiJTpijT^OF A BRITISH FIEAflCIAL-^r^ggil^iy^g.- Russia .: Copy. of. telegram from General Poole, Petro-grad, to the Secretary, Committee on ,;ussian Supplies. (Received 27th December 1917, 11040 a0m0)P. 764, December 26th,   Following for Colonel Byrne:-Have received your letter:of December 5thuI have started now evacuation of military officers only,   I consider that thero is much work in matters relating to prevention of eoods and stores falling into Gorman, hands to do from this mission.     Local events must control actions on these linos, but organisation is in hand already and Embassy are fully advised, Csbie at onco what stores are knoan to be needed, most in Germany.iiy advice here is rubber, metals, cotton, fats and oil and chemical products,    I consider that funds up to 10 million roubles should be provided by each of the allies- America. France and Great Britain     for purchasing outright or obtaining options on important stores against the German agents who now have free access to Russia;    Americans already have telegraphed for this amount of credit,I consider that British Government should at once send out an influential financial representative to consider the present and after peace Commercial intelligence Branch in Russia3   After a few months&apos;1&apos; time it will be too late to act,   Americans are becoming more active and German influence is increasing rapidlycRepresentative must be a real expert5   British business men here can give full particulars as to possibilities, and it will take some weeis to decide on policy to be-recommended to the British Government,,Do not allow the Impression to get about that all commercial interest in Russia Is at a standstill as that is quite inaccurate^ If properly managed Russia will ; elcome British capital etc-..Present organisation .of ,commercial Attache&apos; and Consulate for dealing with this question -Is totally inadequate from the informa--tion I have received and also out of date.,K&apos;or the present my policy a ill be to stay hero myself until conditions settle down with the non-military -side of my present staff.     It is conceivable that Germany v/il-1 send military force hero but I think It improbable-,

</content>
</cab>
