<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 97-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/ &apos;l --/This Document      the property j-iia.3ritannie kajeat/1 s Government.ff.T.,513%.,WAR CASIK3T&apos;-Record of meetings of the Committee appointed by War Cabinet 304, minute 2 held at 2, Whitehall Gardens, 21st, and 22nd. of December, 1917., Following upon War Cabinet 304, minute 2, deputing Lord Milner,.Mr. Barnes, Mr. Churchill, Mr, Roberts$ and Sir Auckland Geddes to deal with the difficulties arising out of the Ministry of Munitions Timeworkers Wages Orders, meetings were held at 2, Whitehall Gardens on 21st and 22nd, Dacamber, 1917.PresentRt. Hon. G.^&apos;,Barnes, M.P., Rt. Eon, Winston Churchill, M.P. )Minister of Munitions) , Rt. Hon. G.H,Roberts, M&apos;.P.., ^Minister of Labour), Sir Auckland Geddas, K..C.B. , M,P, ,,, Mini star of National Service).Sir George R. AskwithM.C.3., K.C,, .Sir Lynden Macassey, K.B.23, , K.C., Mr. Guy Calthrop, Mr. I. H. Mitchell and Mr, ,U0 Wolff (Members of War Cabinet Labour Committee), Sir Robert Chalmers, K.G.3, (Treasury), Mrc F0 G, Kail away. K.P, (parliamentary Secretary, Min-istry of Munitions), Sir Thomas Munro , K.B.i30 , Major Sills, M.P. , Mr, G, Campbell- and Mr. W. J. Larke, (Ministry of Munitions),Mr, Allan Smith and Mr. Fairholm, (Engineering Employers? Padaration).Mr. Duncan .(Shipbuilding Simpl oversr Federation) (Dec,22ndr only).Mr. G.&amp;,Hodgson (Private Secretary to Mr. Barnes), Mr. CS,Kuret (Acting Secretary, War Cabinet Labour Committee).1. D-5C embr*r 31bt.    4, 30a p,a,Mr. Churchill proposed that the 12-J-^ bonus should &quot;belimited, to tiem-workers as originally intended, mailing a public announcement that the earnings of piece-workers should be on a basis of 2bfj - 33;^ in excess of the time-wo rk e r s &apos; f 1 at r at e,The opinion was expressed that there would be dif-* ficulty in avoiding a wide extension of the bonus both to piece-workers, and also to all classes in many trades not cove-red by the existing Orders.    The cost was esti-mated at possibly  100.000,000 par annum, but the sug-gestion was mads that if such, an advance was to cone, it should be granted, at once, rather than be extracted piece-meal by damands and threats.
The meeting also considered the possibility of a frank withdrawal of the 12jt% Orders, relying upon a general pronouncement by the Government in regard to the whole position, including wages, man power, limitation cf food prices and of profits, to carry it through.    It was stated, however, that on political grounds the pos-sible results of such a course could not be risked.; Mr. Allan Smith suggested a grant of 7/- per week to piece-workers in all engineering and cognate trades,Mr, ^airholm was of opinion that an increase of 7/-on the piece-workers1 guaranteed time rate would satisfy the piece-workers in tho Sheffield Steel Trade,The meeting adjourned at 6.15. p,m,, till 10,30, a,m,on December 22nd.December 22nda 10,50.aBm,The liinistry of Munitions suggested that men employed on payment by results in the trades in which the bonus had &quot;been granted should be at once guaranteed that they should not receive less than they would if they were time-workers entitled to tho bonus, and that the question of any bettor terms to such men and of any extension of the bonus or an equivalent to other trades should be discussed between employers and workpeople concerned,Mra Duncan stated that the principle of guaranteeing a time-rate was more difficult in the Shipyards where many men have no recognised time-rate, but that if Sngin-eering piece-workers were given only an improved guarantee he did not anticipate any trouble in the shipyards.Mr, Allan Smith did not believe that the increased guarantee would satisfy the piece-workers, but stated that employers would loyally co-operate if they wore assured that the Govarnment intended not to give way later.&apos; The meeting adjourned at l,p,m, till 3ep.m,In roga,rd to the extension of the Order to other trades the mooting considered ths acuto position in the Sheffield Stool Trade.    It was thought that Sheffield should be in-cluded in a settlement for the Steel Trade generally,- and not dealt with separately,   The meeting considered the pos-sibility of extending the Order and the proposed piece-work conditions to all the Steel trade in so far as it is as-sociar,ed with engineering, and of drawing a line at or about that point beyond which tho Government would not be moved j any claims &quot;beyond that lino being referred to the Committee on Production for settlement on a cost-of-living basis,
A sub-Committee was appointad consisting of Mr. Hi tens 11, &quot;Mr. Wolff, Sir Thomas Munro, Mr. Duncan and Mr. Allan Smith, to examine the proposal with reference to the&quot;question whether it provided a defensible line within which the Government could confine the extension Of the 12%% Orders.The view of the meeting was that in order successfully to carry through such a proposition, it would be necessary for the Government to lift the whole question on to a higher plane by laying before the country the whole national po-sition. statin,-.; that no further wages advances would be given except on grounds of cost-of-living, but that the Government intended to secure a fair distribution of food and to limit tne cost of it, and also to&apos;..take for the State all excess profits.Mr, Allan Smith stated in r:-g.\rd to excess profits . that provided the bargain was not a one-sided one, the Government need not fear the attitude of the employers.The meeting was adjourned at 6,15,p.m,, till 11,a,m,December, 24th,

</content>
</cab>
