<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 247-252</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document ufCJ *.J,.**N t-v .*-v ?**7&apos;%P8  L s Ot)A/0.DEPARTMENT OF INFORMATION- INTELLIGENCE BUREAU,MEMOEABBUMonTHE   TENTH   GERMAN   VOTE   OS1   CBBDIT.9/a(Communicated by the Treasury.) (This is of value as showing up the weakness of German finances and the fallacies in the speech of the German Financial Secretary.)At the end of November the German Imperial Chancellor, Count von Hertling, laid the Tenth Voto of Credit for  750.000,000 before the Reichstag, and on December 1st the Financial Secretary, Count von Rodem, delivered the usual Vote of Credit speech. The total of the Votes of Credit to date amounts te  5,450,000,000 distributed as fellows:1914 August December1916 March August December260,000,000 850,000,000500,000,000 500,000,000 500,000,0001916 June October1917February JulyDecember600,000,000 600,000,000750,000,000 750,000,000 750,000,000The Financial Secretary made a provisional statement of the total yiold of the War Taa (War Profits Tax), which he estimated at  250,000,000 - a very considerably higher amount than it had been expected would be raised.    But as this tax was first imposed in 1916 and not oolleoted till the second half of 1917, it is probable that this total includes the yield of the tax as assessed on the extra inoomo for the greater part of
1916 and 1917, and so covers considerably more than one year. He then proceeded to. add to this sum the  5,000,000 yielded by the Property Tax and the whole of the proceeds of the  50,000,000 Defenoe Levy whieh was imposed early in 1913, and oolleoted during the three years 1913-15, thua arriving at a total of  300,000,000 direct Taxes raised by the Empire during the war.    Count von Rodern stated that the Defenoe levy was first assessed in the Summer of 1914 and its prooeeda were not received gill the first year of the war, hut this is directly contradicted by the Statistical Year Book of the German Umpire for 1914, whioh in-cludes In the Revenue of the Empire in the Budget Year 1913-14 the sum of  20,800*000 from the Defence levy.     On the expendi-ture side, the Army and Navy together cost  24,900,000 more in 1913-14 than in the preceding year.     It is clear then that Count von RBdern was not correct in including the whole of the Defence Levy in the direot taxation raised during the actual war peried.    He also added to the above mentioned sum of  300,000,000 a further  100,000,000 representing the additional direst taxes raised by tho Federal States and municipalities as a result of the war, making a total of  400,000,000 raised by direct taxes i,n the whole of Germany.     But the additional  100,000,000 raised by the Federal States and Municipalities during the three years 1914-17 must not, of course, be taken as equivalent t% their ehareof the war costs.     It represents largely interest on the very extensive debts incurred by them for war purposes, the aggregate of whioh Is very large Indeed. Berlin at the end of November 1917 had accumulated a floating debt of  40,000,000;   Hamburg&apos;s war debt amounts to  20,560,000, and in the Budget for 1918  1,450,000 is allowed for interest on this floating debt;   similar conditions obtain in the other German municipalities.    A certain proportion of some of this expenditure is repaid ultimately by the Empire, which will have
ss^mm^^^tl^w fetowsi. wtostaaAiJkg a* the end ofthe war.    The Financial Secretary went on to take great excep-tion to certain statements regarding German finance made by Mr. Bonar Lnw in his Tote of Credit speech of 30th October 1917. Count von Rodern maintained (i) that Germany^; war taxes had sufficed hitherto to cover the interest on her war debt; (2) that Gernany1s Vote of Credit expenditure is larger than the actual expenditure;   (3) that all advances to Allies in whatever form, and including guarantees, are included in the V-te of Credit expenditure.with regard to the first of these points Count von R5dern&apos;fi language was, no doubt intentionally, very ambiguous-He referred to the interest as having been covered to date by the war taxation granted by the Reichstag.    But the first additional war taxation was imposed in 1916 and was estimated       , to bring in  25,000,000 - the war Profits tax was also passed then but was originally intended to be collected after the war. in February 1917 additional taxation to bring in  60,000,000 was passed, which included a 20$ surcharge on all the rates of the **. x Pa -j fits Tf,x, the yield from which was estimated at  20,000,000. As the interest on the *;ar debt amounted in February 1917, accor-ding to Count von Rodern&apos;s own statement, to  170,000,000, it is clear that only a small part of this interest had been covered by war taxation.     The W?r Profits T     hrs been collected during the second half of 1917 and its yield (including the 20$ sur-charge) is stated to amount to  250*000,000 - a sum &quot;which probably covers the bulk of the two years 1916 and 1917.     But the W*-r Profits T*% is payable in v/- r Lo.    . s well as. in cash, and it was anticipated by Count von Rfl^ern in his Budget speech of February 1917 that a very large proportion of the whole would in fact be paid in Wer Locn      If  200,000,000 out of the total were paid in War Loan the interest burden (amounting at
the end of November 1917 to  240,000,000) would be diminished by Only  10,000,000 per annum and there would be not more than  50,000,000 regaining over in cash to meet the interest on the debt.    Even with the aid of the Vfcr Profits Tost it is impossible to maintain that the ever increasing interest charge on the Debt is being provided for out of additional War Taxation.     It must be remembered, moreover, that the W-r Profits Tax is universally regarded as war measure and could not be continued after the war at anything approaching its present level without very unenviable consequences for Germany1s economic recovery.    The whole of the normal revenue of the Empire has barely been sufficient to cover the interest on the war debt alone, for the total budgetary revenue for 1916-17 was only estimated at  187,900,000 - Bven so a very doubtful figure, as it included the whole of the customs revenue at its pre-war level of  36,000,000.    As the debt interest alone in February 1917 amounted to  170,000,000 it is evident that there was not much left over for normal permanent expenditure, which in 1913 amounted to  122,500,000 (excluding the &quot;einmalige Ausgaben&quot;). In actual fact much of the interest on the War Loans has had to be paid out of Vote of Credit expenditure.     Count von Rfldern admitted in July 1917 that one reason for the increase in monthly war costs between February and May of that year (to  150,000,000 monthly) was the necessity for paying part of the interest on the debt out of the Vote of Credit funds.     But he attributed this to the fact that the proceeds of the new taxes voted in February 1917 would not be collected till later in the year.     On the other hand, Dr. Kuczyusxi, Director of the Statistical Bureau of the City of Berlin-Schflneberg, in a recent article in the Europalsohe Staats- und l,Virtschafts-2eitun^ stated explicitly that wheras the loans raised during 1915 had been spent on the direct conduct of the war, the loans raised during 1916 had had to be used to a large extent to cover interest, pensions and war relief.     He
estimated that during 1917 nearly  650,000,000 wouJ.d be required for these purposes alone.Secondly, Count ron R6dern!s objection to the procedure of Mr. Bonar Law in comparing German, Votes of Credit with English actual expenditure cannot for a moment bjgr upheld.    The English figures contain very important items, e*g. for separation allow-ances, which enter to only a small extent into the German Votes of Credit.      The enormous expenditure of the German Federal States and municipalities for war purposes has already been pointed out above.    Further the official German statements of monthly expenditure, which have been given periodically in the Reichstag, show that the actual expenditure incurred by the Empire has certainly not fallen behind the amount of the Credits voted.    Mr. Bonar Law did not include in his figures of German expenditure the new Vote of Credit of December 1st 1917.Thirdly, Count von RBdera omits to mention in his statement conoern&amp;ig Germany^ advances to Allies, that the bulk of these have been carried out by German Banking Syndicates, which have advanced during the war  158,000,000 to Austria and Hungary and large sums to Bulgaria and Turkey.    The advances made by the German Government have taken the form mainly of Treasury Bonds which it has deposited with Turkish agents in Germany, and against which Turkey has then issued paper money. These Bonds do not constitute an immediate, but only an ultimate liability, as Germany is pledged to redeem in gold the Turkish paper issued against the Treasury 3onds, within a period ranging from 3 to 11 years after the conclusion of peace.    Despite Count von lifldern^ definite assertion, it is very difficult to believe that these guarantees are included in the Votes of Credit intended to cover current expenditure.     Certain other advances have been made by Germany to Turkey, e.g* for the purchase of munitions etc., but it is not certain hov? much of these had been
provided by Banks and how much bjr the Government.     In any oase the sums in question are not large.     It follows then that there is no substantial inaccuracy in the assumption that advances to Allies are not included, or are a negligible item in Germany*s Vote of Credit expenditure.Finally, Count von RBdem, after making Certain ill-founded criticism of English war finance, ended his speech by declaring that the Finance Administration was engaged, in coopera-tion with the Federal States, in working out the details of an organic and comprehensive reform of the finance system of the German Empire.    The new financial programme would not however be laid beforo the Reichstag till after the war.     It is clear from this that the Government is afraid to introduoe large mea-sures of taxation during the war and that very large loans will have to continue during at least the first year after the war. Further, the Reichstag, which has complete control of new taxa-tibn, will he in a position of enormous and unprecedented power as soon as the war is over.31.12.17.

</content>
</cab>
