<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 329-329</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government).

SECRET.

G.T.3197.

WAR CABINET.

DISSOLUTION OF AIR ORGANISATION COMMITTEE.

(Note by General Smuts).

The Air Organisation Committee, appointed by the Cabinet to undertake the preliminary work of the establishment of the Air Ministry and the formation of the Air Force, has ?alt with the following subjects:-

The legislation needed for the establishment of an Air Force and of an Air Council to administer it.

The constitution of the Air Council, its membership and the apportionment of duties between members.

The organisation of an air ministry and the rates of pay and duties of its offcials.

The mom?nlature of the Air Force.

The question of supply in all branches for the Air Force.

The rates of pay and allowances, conditions of service and pension rates of all ranks of the Air Force and the system of payment to be adopted.

The relations between the Air Ministry and Air Force and the War Office and Admiralty and Army and Navy.

The organisation of an administrative branch of the Air Force.

The district organisation of the Air Force in the United Kingdom.

The arrangements as to lands and buildings and works services for the Air Force

The question of a separate medical organisation for the Air Force.

The question of a peace establishment for the Air Force.

On most of these subjects the Committee has been able to arrive at an agreement with the departments concerned.  The consideration of the remaining questions has reached an advanced stage, and I consider that their final adjustment may now be left to the Air Council, which has now come into force. I recommend, therefore, that the Air Organisation Committee may be now dissolved, and I will be available if required to advise the Air Council, on behalf of the War Cabinet, should any unexpected difficulty arise.

(Initialled) J.C.S.

3rd January 1918.

</content>
</cab>
