<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/37/0 images: 361-374</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
wpu /-Victoria 8240. &quot;BOARD OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIESTelegrams:-Growmore, Sowest, Lokdox, &apos;29To avoid delay, address all communications to :-The Director General.FOOD PRODUCTION DEPARTMENT,72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. (1)2nd January, 1918.Sir,I beg to submit the following Report on the work of the Pood Production Department for the weeks ended 25th December 1917 and 1st January, 1918:-The Weather.The reports received indicate that the greater part of the country has been frost-bound during most of the past fortnight.   All outdoor work has been seriously interrupted and ploughing has been practically at a standstill.LOCAL ORGANISATION DIVISION. Agricultural Executive Committees. Birmingham - The Committee have been authorised to take possession of a farm of 60 acres at Northfield on the whole of which the grass keep has hitherto been sold.   The owners having been served with notices to cultivate, prefer that the Committee should take possession and let to a tenant.Gloucestershire - The Committee have been authorised to take possession of a farm of 42 acres at Aston Somerville which has been badly neglected and was in hand until Michaelmas 1916, when It was sold to a purchaser who is now negotiating for sale to a land speculator.Kent - The Committee have been authorised to take possession of 63 acres of derelict building land at various places in Thanet. Norfolk - The Committee have been authorised to take possession of 40 acres of land near Kennlnghall which require to be- 1 -
reclaimed and under ^-drained.   This work will be carried out by prisoners of w&amp;r.   The Committee have now taken possession of a piece of land of 478 acres in extent and forming parts of various holdings in Waxham and Horsey Marshes which is out of cultivation merely for want of drainage.   They propose to carry out the drainage work;   and when this has been done, they will probably be able to take additional adjoining land and treat it in the same way.Staffordshire - The Committee propose to cultivate a very badly neglected farm of 126 acres1 at Dunston, of which they have been authorised to take possession, and to use it as a depot for the Department1s horses,Suffolk, West *- The Committee have issued orders to cultivate portions of eight parks in the Melford district as a result of the enquiry referred to in the report for 19th December, as well as of a portion of Ickworth Park.Sussex, Hast - A farm of 625 acres near Eastbourne has been sold In separate plots to different purchasers;   and the tenant being Under notice to quit at Michaelmas .1918 cannot be expected to improve the cultivation which has been much neglected. Consequently the Committee have been authorised to take possession of two outlying portions aggregating 186 acres.. Sussex West - A farm belonging to the Village Charities of Cootham, 40 acres in extent, has been absolutely neglected and the Committee have been authorised to take possession of it.. The Committee have also been authorised to take possession of 137 acres of arable land on a neglected farm at Shipley. Worcestershire - The owner-occupier of a farm of 200 acres near Bishampton has failed to make any effort to improve his cult.ivat.ion., and the farm is in a seriously neglected state; the Committee have been authorised to take possession.
Drainage of Lands - The work done by the West Riding Committee upon the West Moor Drain has reclaimed 530 acres of water-logged land and has improved 650 acres in addition;    out of the530 acres reclaimed, it is hoped that 426\acres will grow cropsIf If, \limit /oar, having previously been derelictV   The work on theParks Drain has improved 2,000 acres;   a considerable amount ofarable land will be obtained out of this.     The whole work on thetwo drains has cost  1,300 and it.is hoped that the greater partof this expenditure will be recouped.   This Committee are nowdealing with the Austerfield Drain under the powers of a ParishAward.The Nottinghamshire Committee have obtained the clearance of the greater part of the Pairham Brook by the occupiers of adjoining lands.   In Westmorland notices have been issued to the occupiers to clear out the Hale Mosses, Hellington and Levens Drains. Golf Courses - In Essex the Committee have ordered the ploughing up of 25 acres of the Romford Golf Course;   in Kent 30 acres of the Herne Bay Course and 50 acres of the Mid-Kent Course at Gravesend are to be ploughed up.   In Lancashire the Bury Golf Club have offered to give up 20 acres for ploughing;     and in Leicestershire the Committee have ordered 60 acres to be broken on the Birstalf Courset and 63 acres on the Western Park Course. Prosecution - A farmer near Magor, in Monmouthshire, has been fined  10 for non-compliance with an order to plough 34 acres of grass land for 1918;     the Bench said they had taken a lenient view as this was the first prosecution in the county. Credit Scheme - Reports have been obtained from the Agricultural Executive Committees showing what action has been taken under the Credit Scheme.   The total number of applications received up to the end of November was 487, of which 303 were granted and 184 refused.   The total amount for which the grant of credit was
approved was  21,077, of which  13,225 was for the purchase of seeds and manures,  4,084 for implements and machinery,  1*480 for working horses and  2;288 for other livestock.   The largest number of applications is reported by the Essex Committeej namely 64* of which 44 were granted * comprising a total of  2,616.    In the case of 12 counties no applications were received.The comparative, smallness of the transactions is attributed to the fact that most farmers can obtain accommodation from their bankers without a guarantee;   while those to whom additional capital would be useful usually dislike the idea of disclosing their financial position to their neighbours.   At the same time there is general testimony to the soundness and usefulnes of the Scheme and it is expected that advantage of it will be taken to an increasing extent as it becomes better known. Determination of Tenancies - During the fortnight 12 Orders have been made authorising landlords to determine tenancies on account of bad farming in respect of 900 acres, and 4 Orders have been made by the Board determining the tenancies of 670 acres. Provision of ^and for Allotments - Reports received by the Department show that in 1,099 districts 205*346 applications have been made for plots under the Cultivation of Lands Order, and 186,372 plots have been provided containing a total area of 13,717 acres.The Board have authorised the Barnes Urban District Council to enter on small portions of Barnes Common and Sheen Common for the purpose of providing allotments under the Cultivation of Lands Order.
HORTICULTURAL DIVISION. Fruit and Vegetable Preserving,    The total number of demonstrations given during the year has been 300,000.     The number of demonstrators, exclusive of voluntary workers, has been reduced from 45 to 16 owing to the decreased demand for demonstrations during the winter. Demonstrations have also been giveh at Exhibitions at Button, Edgbaston, Coventry, Maidstone, Anerley, Blackpool and elsewhere. Demonstrators have also done useful work in instructing Domestic Science Teachers.     This instruction Is being continued and is likely to be productive of valuable results.    There can be no doubt that the work done by the demonstrators has resulted in the preservation of a very considerable quantity of fruit and vegetables which might otherwise have been wasted, and it appears desirable that the instruction should be continued during the coming year. Canning,   Arrangements have been made at Leomihster for a local firm to start a Canning Factory in connection with its proposed Pulping Station in the.coming year, and the firm in question has undertaken to give facilities for demonstration by the Department in the use of Home Canners.     Demonstrations in Canning have also been given in the Gas Showrooms of the British Commercial Gas Association at Winchester and at Preston.Spraying in 1918,,   Organisers have- been appointed and are now at work lecturing and making arrangements for Potato Spraying in 1918, Allotments Section.   As the result of visits by Mr. Sutton and members of the staff of the Allotments Section, additional land for 200 allotments has been provided In Lambeth and 150 plots at Godalming and Newbury.     Land has also been inspected at Jarrow, Chester-le-Street, Darlington, Durham, Seaham Harbour, Sunderlandj Clitheroe, Halifax, Hackney, Walthamstow, Leyton^ Penzance, Bodmin and Exeter.Several local Authorities have undertaken to acquire the areas recommended by the representatives of the Department.   At Exeter 300 additional allotments will be provided, and a letter subsequently received from the representatives of.the Hackney local Authority states that &quot;as a result of your Inspectors visit, we
are hoping to provide 500 more plots.&quot;   Upwards of 1,000 new allotments have been taken up during the period covered by this Report, as a result of the representations made to local Authorities.&apos;   TECHNICAL DIVISION. Inspection of Land.   * Kempsey, Stonehall and Defford Commons, in Worcestershire, were Inspected on the 21st ultimo, by an officer of this Division, in company with the Secretary of the Agricultural Executive Committee and the County Land Agent;     In the case of the two former, which are comparatively small (212 acres in all) and mostly covered with gorse, the labour involved in clearing and fencing the ground would be considerable, and it would be impossible to prepare the land for ploughing in time for a crop In 1918.The case of Defford Common is different,    It is about 400 acres in extent, level, free from gorse, fair stiffish clay soil, and is at present entirely devoted to grazing stock.     The scheme drawn up by the local Committee provides for taking over the whole Common and cultivating it in 1918, 1919 and 1920, but after careful consideration of the circumstances, the Inspector suggests that the Committee should not aim at cultivating more than half the area. The remainder is probably extremely heavy landj    it is low-lying, and cultivation would always- be difficult.    It could be comparatively easily fenced off from the drier areas, and if improved by cleaning out the ditches and application of slag, it would provide grazing for a considerable number of stock which would otherwise be grazed on drier land which ought to be broken up,Flant Diseases.   At the request of the Chairman of the Agricultural Executive Committee * the Department1s Entomologist has visited the Wadebridge District of Cornwall, to enquire into a complaint of serious losses to the young wheat crop in that area through disease. The cause of the disease is being investigated and a report will be submitted as soon as possible.&quot;LABOUR DIVISION. Soldier Labour. Since the last report, 184 additional ploughmen-6-
have arrived from overseas on two months1 agricultural furlough, bringing the total number of these men up to 1,286.     90 of these men are out in charge of Government horses, and 1,045 are with farmers on ploughing worfc;   the remaining men are being sent out immediately.The number of soldiers attached to Depots to date for the 1918 Programme, exclusive of the men above-mentioned, is -31,416, of whom 21,172 are so-called &quot;skilled&quot; men and 10,244 unskilled.   With the advent of bad weather and the conclusion of root pulling, many of the unskilled men sent out for harvest work have been returned to Depots by farmers, and steps are being taken with a view to getting these men out again as soon as possible.   Many of them are being sent to the Training Schools for training as Tractor Drivers c Plorse Ploughmen.An additional 205 men have been sent out for training as Tractor Drivers, making a total of 2,025 men to date. Horses. Orders for the issue of 215 additional horses have been sent out, making a total of 4,536 horses to date.In view of the expected arrival of additional ploughmen, steps are being taken to acquire at once 50 more horses in every county, and the Departments Purchasing Representatives have been instructed accordingly.Harness.   Contracts are being placed for the supply of 4,500 additional collars and 4,500 hames.Prisoners of War. One further batch of ^ri?oners, of War commenced work during last week, bringing the number of Agricultural Camps up to 32, and the total number of combatant Prisoners of War employed-up to 4,471.    In addition, 1,463 released aliens are being employed on farm work, making a total of 5,934 prisoners of War now engaged on work connected with food production.In view of the prisoner ploughmen expected to arrive from Prance for agricultural work in this country, enquiries are being made in the various counties for, premises suitable for their housing in districts where ploughing work is required to be done.   A number of such premises have already been selected and particulars sent to
the War Office in order that they may be inspected forthwith, and no avoidable delay arise when the prisoners arrive.Womenfs Branch. Good reports are still being received of those women in the various motor tractor Training Centres.   At Harper Adams Agricultural College where the trainees are learning to drive Moguls and Titans, two of the pupils have done so well that they are being kept on a3 Assistant Instructresses.     Fourteen girls are now in training there, and as soiwi as the Fords are received twenty-five can be trained.The Branch has received interesting accounts of the work of those girls who have volunteered for national Service from the Potteries,    The Organising Secretary states that the prejudice against women1s labour In that district has enormously decreased owing to the good work already done by the women.   There is still a steady supply of women volunteering from the toiros in Staffordshire, and the recruiting is done entirely by those who are already working on the land.   Two cases out of many have been reported where girls on leave have urged others to join the Land Army,   One girl stood in uniform on the monument in the middle of Stoke and urged others to come forward*Women are now being employed in a large number of occupations kindred to agriculture, the latest of which is   farriery A request for a woman to do this work has come from Hereford, where a farmer has asked for her help in shoeing farm horses and making and repairing farm implements.There are 7,065 women accpunted for as followsin Instruction Centres .............. .229On farm work........................ 5,758Employed by the Forage Dept. ........ 512Employed by the Timber Supply Dept. , 165 Waiting for references to beplaced in Training Centres ......... 69Waiting for employment in Depots .... 89Waiting in their own -homes.......... 245Tptsl......        &apos;
Women&apos;s Institutes.   There are now in existence 214 Women1s Institutes.     The year was started with 50 Institutes and as the movement had then been in existence for 15 months the rate of progress during the last year has been very gratifying.    Since the propaganda work&apos; of the Institutes was transferred from the Agricultural Organisation Society to the Women1s Branch of this Department, new Institutes have been.formed at the rate of 23 a week.     This Is largely due to the fact that the Women!.s Institute propaganda has been linked up with the Women1s Branch&apos;s organisation in the various counties, the Women!s War Agricultural Committees being an excellent means for presenting the Institute idea to the villages.     In those villages where Institutes have been established for some time, the members are beginning to realise the power of combined action.     Classes have been arranged in cheese-making, cooking, boot-mending, &amp;c, which would never have come within the scope of women living in remote places had not th  means been suggested whereby such instruction could be obtained.     Talks on gardening by a local expert - often the gardener of the &quot;big house&quot; - are given each month in many Institutes.     Reports of results of such instruction are encouraging.     Members do not hest:fc&amp;.te to ask advice freely when the ffbeaker is one of themselves.     At Witton-le-Wear such practical talks resulted in a marked improvement in the fruit produce from cottage gardens.     Co-operative buying of coal, vegetable seeds and fertilisers has been undertaken by most of the Institutes.
MECHANICAL CULTIVATION DIVISION. The position with regard to the Provision of Tractors and Horse-drawn implements remairis as set out in the Report for the week ended 18th December.A remarkable record in tractor ploughing has been accomplished in the Holland Division of Lincolnshire, where seven tractors started ploughing in the Spalding area -on October 12th for seven weeks with the following result:-Week ended. Acreage Ploughed.Total. Average per TractorOct. 19th 114j 16,r     26th 146 21Nov.    2nd 1534 -          22&quot;.      9th 1361 20&quot;     16th 153 2223rd &apos;                                      156 22,r     30th 124 18Average per week.     141 ...  20The work done by one of the tractors included above must be a record for consistency of any Government tractor in the United Kingdom.   Commencing on October 19th, the tractor ploughed in successive weeks up to November 30th as follows:     1st week (4. working days only) 15 acres.    2nd week 28 acres * 3rd week 23-J acres.) 4th week 23 acres, 5th week 35 acres, 6th week 35 acres, 7th week 22 acres, and this work included 3 days ploughing 12 inohes deep, the remainder not less than 6 inches..  Total 18lg-acres, being an average of 26 acres each week.&apos;  1 per acre was. the minimum charge to the farmer.The total fuel consumption was as under:-Paraffin 732 gallons, average 4.1/30 gallons. Petrol       25       &quot; &quot; 1/7 &quot;Grease      17 lbs. &quot;Oil 58 gallons,       &quot; 1/3 &quot;,      .-. : ?4i    .... * .&apos;-The above consumption includes fuel used in travelling-from farm to farm.   There were 10 moves and the distance
travelled by road was 64 miles.   For each move the spuds had to be taken off and replaced, this.operation taking about 2 hours on each.occasion.One tractor in the unit ploughed 45 acres in one week, 7 inches deep and during the 7 weeks 167 acres, an average per week of nearly 24 aores.The following statement sets out the cost to the Food Production Department of the working of the above tractors, and the receipts from the farmers concerned:-Receipts. 973 acres 0  1 per acre 6     &quot;     &quot; 30/- &quot;     &quot; 6     11     &quot; 25/- (* Total receipts Total expenditureNet Profit   -Expenditure. 973. 0. 09. 0. 07. 10. 0 989. 10. 0804. 14. 9 184. 15. 3Total expenses in connection with 7 tractors for 7 weeks 804.14.9.xx,This figure includes salaries of all officials, rentals, wages, travelling expenses, repairs, depreciation and general expenses.The above figures are interesting, in view of the frequency with which charges of extravagance are levelled at the Department^ Tractor Scheme, and show.that, where working conditions are good, the Government tractors are fully paying their way.The officers mainly responsible for this very creditable record are Mr. ,W,,R. Wintour, the County Machinery Officer, and Mr. F. Myers, the Tractor Representative.
SUPPLIES DIVISION. Basic Slag.   The prospects for further extension In the out-put of basic slag are good.     Additional plant has been put up at several places, and it is hoped that it will be at work early in the New Year.Potash.   The arrangements for the distribution of Blast Furnace Flue Dust are working satisfactorily, though the quantity actually being distributed does not at present exceed about 1,000 tons per month.    A Conference was held with the Cleveland Iron Masters1 Association with the result that they have appointed a large firm of Furnace Owners to collect the Flue Dust produced at furnaces in the Middlesborough District, and distribute It in accordance with arrangements made by this Department.     It is not improbable that other associations of Blast Furnace Owners may take similar action.     Agents appointed in this way under the direct auspices of the  last Furnace Owners will probably be able to secure a larger quantity of Flue Dust, and to sell it under more favourable conditions thari Agents not directly interested in the trade.     The policy of the Department, is however, to recommend the Controller of Potash Production to iicence a limited number of reputable firms to act as Yfriolesale Collecting Agents, provided they can show that they are in a position to do the work In an efficient manner.     The Wholasale Collecting Agents are required to test the Flue Dust for the presence of Cyanide, with a view to preventing the sale of any material which is likely to be injurious to plant life.     The charge for Flue Dust is based on its content of water-soluble Potash, and the Department is in correspondence with the Government Laboratory as to the terms of the test for estimating Potash content.The attention Of several large firms engaged in the fertiliser trade is being directed to the deposits of Potash in AbyslnAia with a view to providing for the representation of British interests in the Italian Company which holds the concession
and is now working the deposits.Stable Manure.-   Satisfactory progress is being made with the removal of stable manure from the Army dump at Eelmoor near Aldershot.     Five barges are new at work on the Canal and orders have been received for several thousand tons to be sent to different places in Surrey and Hampshire.     It is hoped that more barges will be secured at an early date.Lime.   The plant for grinding chalk whiOh has been put up at Croydon is complete., and Is now being run experimentally.     Output from this source during the winter, however, may not be very large, as when the chalk contains more than a certain percentage of water it becomes difficult to work.     A similar plant which is being put &apos; up at Stoneycombe, Devonshire, is also making progress, and may be completed in the course of a month or six weeks.Returns which have been received from 125 of the principal Lime Works in the country show that the deliveries of lime amounted to 23,000 tons in December as against 15,000 tons in the same month last year.     The main difficulty in a further increase of supply is the difficulty of obtaining suitable labour.     An arrangement has been made whereby men skilled in the Lime Trade now in the Army may be transferred to an Agricultural Company and employed In the manfacture of lime..     This arrangement applies, however, only to men whose medical category is below B.l. and it is probable that the number of skilled workmen below this grade is.very small. Seed Wheat.   A small reserve of seed wheat is available for the use of farmers and orders are still being received. Seed Oats.   The arrangements for the shipment of Manx oats have been completed, and the first cargo is likely to arrive in the course of the next week. .It is improbable that Irish supplies can reach an English port before the latter end of January and latest advice indicates that it will not.be possible to obtain as. much as 20,000 tons suitable for seed purposes,
The Department are making arrangements for StorageAgents and selected Approved Agents in the various counties tohave the option of distributing seed oats to farmers on termssuggested by the Cereal Seeds Advisory Committee.Seed Potatoes. Applications from the various counties andpublic authorities for potatoes under the Distribution Scheme arecoming in rapidly/ and the following are approximate figures upto the presentj-Immune varieties Other varieties7,000 tons. 4,500 tons.Final figures will not be available for anotherfortnight at least.I am,Sir,Your obedient Servant,Director-General.The Rt. Hon. Rowland E. Prothero, M.P.President of the Board of Agricultureand Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
