<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/44/8 images: 106-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1943.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. St Is issued for the personal us8 of........./Qf&amp;f&amp;^J.........................../!........MOST SECRET , \J       Copy NoW,P. (43) 558.Uh December, 1943.WAR CABINET.SUMMARY OF NAVAL AIR OPERATIONS-AIJGUST-SEPTEMBER-OCTOBER 1943.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.Section I. Aircraft Carriers Dispositions and Movements,(a) Fleet Carriers.H.M.S.  Victorious      On the 27th September H.M.S. Victorious returned from an extended tour of duty with the American PacificFleet, during which she operated with the United States.Aircraft Carrier, Saratoga, with Task Force 4, underthe command of Admiral Ramsey, U.S.N. As a preliminary to combined operations by the Naval,air forces of the Allies, the experience was most valuable.It. also developed still further the feelings of mutualrespect which already existed between the two Services.The interchange of ideas and technique was extended tothe interchange of aircraft, an American Fighter squad-ron operating from Victorious and a British Torpedo-Bomber squadron from Saratoga. A. high tribute to the. success of the experiment was paid by Admiral Ramsey,U.S.N., on the conclusion of the operations, which keptTask Force 4 continuously at sea for twenty-eight days.He said : &apos;&apos; The co-operation and collaboration between thetwo Commands have been so whole-hearted and intensethat I sincerely believe we have built a foundation of understanding and team work which all our Alliedships engaged in this work may well emulate . . . .the friendships alone will remain long after the lasttorpedo has been dropped,&quot;H.M.S. Illustrious      Sailed for Malta on the 23rd August, 1943, and pro-vided Fleet cover for Mediterranean operations by force &quot; H&quot; (see remarks under the section headed&quot;Escort Carriers&quot;). Sailed from Mediterranean for united Kingdom on the 18th October.H.M.S. Formidable      At Malta, Alexandria and subsequently with Force&quot; H &quot; in company with Illustrious during Mediterraneanoperations (see remarks under the section headed&quot; Escort Carriers &quot;). She sailed with Illustrious for theUnited Kingdom for operations with the Home fleet and then for a refit, due to begin in mid-November.[26553]B
H.M.S. IndomitableH.M.S. FuriousIn the United States for repairs after being damaged in a torpedo attack off Sicily during the combined operations in August; should be completed early in 1944.Working up, after refit, for service in the home fleet to relieve Formidable (q.v.) in November.(b) Escort Carriers.H.M.S. UnicornH.M.S. HunterH.M.S. AttackerH.M.S. StalkerH.M.S. Battler.H.M.S. BattlerH.M.S. TrackerH.M.S. BiterThe decision to land the Fifth Army near Salerno was founded on the availability of ship-borne air protection.The ensuing carrier operations, which took place off theItalian coast, were a most significant development ofNaval air power and went a long way towards answeringthe question whether ship-borne fighter aircraft could give effective cover to troops landing on defendedbeaches.The ship-borne fighters (sea fires) were flown from theaircraft carrier Unicorn (combined repair ship andcarrier) and the escort carriers Hunter, Stalker, A Hackerand Battler. These ships, with escorting cruisers and destroyers, worked under the Command of Rear-admiral sir Philip Vian, who controlled the force from a Cruiser.An entirely new tactical conception was needed for the simultaneous operation of 5 carriers together in a con-fined area, a problem which has never had to be facedbefore. Its unqualified success reflected great credit onall concerned and many valuable lessons were learnt.Our carrier force was not attacked and aii; controlover the area was maintained for the three vital-days onwhich the carriers were present.Enemy opposition was considerably less than was expected, and such enemy fighters as did appear seemeddisinclined for combat with our sea fires. Frequently thecry &quot; Achtung Spitfeuer &quot; was overheard whenlistening to the enemy&apos;s Radio-Telephony.Ten combats actually took place, one M.E. 109 beingshot down, one probably &quot;shot down and four damaged.None of our aircraft was lost in combat, but seven pilotswere lost from other causes.A total of 713 sorties was flown during 42 hours ofdaylight, while at the end of this period twenty-sixaircraft were flown to a Strip airfield ashore to continue their support of the Army.A flat cairn prevailed during practically the whole period of the carrier operations, making the take-off and landing of high-speed, heavily-loaded fighters ahazardous operation requiring the highest skill andcourage and inevitably leading to a number of minoraccidents. Repair work by the maintenance crews wasspeedy and efficient, and was an invaluable contributionat the height of the air activity. On one occasion thedamaged propeller of a Sean re was changed and theaircraft flown off the deck again on a fresh patrol withinthirty-five minutes of the accident occurring. , , ....During the operations more distant cover was providedby aircraft from the Fleet Carriers Illustrious and.Formidable, working with Force &quot; H &quot; under- the command of Vice-Admiral Sir Algernon Willis, K.C.B.,D.S.O. These ships also were unmolested, by day but had night air torpedo attacks. As a result of these,several enemy aircraft were shot down, three separateenemy crews being taken prisoner the following day.Is now employed on anti-U-Boat operations in theIndian Ocean.Two convoys were covered, by Tracker and a third byTracker and Biter in company.   All three convoys com-
H.M.S. FencerH.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.H.M.S.SearcherPursuerEmperorStrikerChaserActivitySlingerTrumpeter-Nairana(c) M.A.C. Ships.Empire Mac Andrew-Empire Mac alpineEmpire MacraeRapanapleted their voyage without loss. The Commodore ofHX. 258, the late Admiral Fitzmaurice. remarked . &apos;&apos; My convoy felt like a dog with two tails. one could sense the rise in morale. I have never had sucha splendid escort, surface or air. Fourteen surface ships, one aircraft-carrier and three Liberators all the daylight way across.&quot;Accompanied the force detailed for the occupation ofthe Azores. Her aircraft provided A/S protection forthe force, during passage from the United Kingdom andfor the ships and harbours during the disembarkationperiod. The force suffered no losses from U-boats.H.M.S.. Fencer continued to provide protection untilthe R.A..F. &quot; Hudsons,&quot; which were long delayed at gibraltar by adverse weather, were able to fly in and takeover. H.M.S. Fencer and her escorts then carried out some useful patrols in the vicinity before returning, to-the United Kingdom. .Three escort carriers now being fitted out , for operating high-performance fighters in support ofassault forces in &quot;the Far East.Three escort carriers preparing for anti-U-boat duty.Two escort carriers recently arrived from UnitedStates carrying the new Corsair Squadrons forequipping Illustrious.British-built escort carrier preparing for service in theFar East.In spite of limited opportunities for offensive actionin the Atlantic, these four M.A.C. ships have gainedvaluable experience in covering eleven convoys during-the period under review. An aircraft from EmpireMacalpine, which was covering ONS 18, sighted&apos; aU-boat on the surface and attacked with R.Ps. in the face of intense A/A gunfire, but the U-boat, bymanoeuvring at high speed, escaped damage. this incident emphasised the fact that, to ensure successagainst a U-boat prepared to remain on the surface andfight back, a diversionary attack should be made by asecond aircraft, preferably a fighter. Improved methodsof attack on these lines are being developed. Onemerchant ship of this convoy was torpedoed and abandoned in a blizzard.The opinion of Senior Officers about M.A.C. Ships inconvoys is interesting.   One of them reports : &quot;I  was  most  impressed  by   the  way  EmpireMacandrew was handled between the columns.....her all-round efficiency gave a feeling of confidencecomparable to having a proper escort carrier in company.&apos;&apos;The Commodore of a convoy remarks with reference tothem : &apos;&apos; The spirit of co-operation between the Royal and merchant Navies is splendid.&quot;Another. Commodore remarks : -&quot; The skill with which Empire &apos;Macandrew washandled inside the screen between the columns, thepunctuality With which she flew off her patrols, the:&apos;[26553]B&apos;9.
AmastraEmpire MackayAcavusAncylusA aircraft.excellence of the R/T and W/T communications which invariably existed with her aircraft, and theprecision with which her aircraft landed on and flewoff from a heaving deck all earned our unboundedadmiration.&quot;It is impossible to speak too highly of the work of theseconverted merchant ships with their small flight decks,and their necessarily limited accommodation and facilities for aircraft handling and maintenance.Thanks to the devotion and persistence of officers andmen, and to the flying characteristics of their Swordfishaircraft, they have flown in all weathers and have main-tained a high rate of serviceability of aircraft in themost difficult circumstances. It is bad luck that, despite their gallant efforts, the M.A.C. ships have not yetrecorded a U-boat &quot;kill.&quot;Both ships were due to sail on their first operationalvoyage with ONS 22 early in November.New M.A.C. ships preparing for service.M.A.C. ships have used Swordfish aircraft up todate. Landing trials with Martlet fighters carried outon Amastra have, however, proved completely successful in fine weather, and later these ships may carry one ortwo fighters to assist in attacks on U-boats. .  .The ftiture.It is estimated that a total of fifteen M.A.C. ships willbe in service by the end of the year, with two additionalships by the end of February 1944 and one more by theend of March.(d) Aircraft Transports.H.M.S. AtheneH.M.S. Engadine(e) Training Carriers.H.M.S. ArgusH.M.S. Ravager(f) Trials Carrier.H.M.S. PretoriaCastleReturned to the Atlantic late in August and have since been employed transporting first-line aircraft and storesfrom New York to the United Kingdom to meet opera-tional requirements.Deck-landing training in the Clyde.In this quarter 226 pilots completed their initial deck-landing training and 60 underwent refresher courses.Her present programme of trials includes many testsof new Radar equipment for ships and aircraft; thecollection of data on deck-landing; take-off andaccelerator launches of all new types of Naval aircraft;rocket-assisted take-off and development of night decklighting equipment.The first cordite-operated accelerator has been fittedin the ship. Special photographic rooms each side of the flight deck are being fitted for photographic recording.Representatives of all firms working for the Fleet air arm are invited to visit this ship. Their test pilots maycarry out deck-landings.Section II. Detached Naval Squadrons Operating from Shore Bases.Home.The night attacks upon E/R-boats and any other targets which offeredthemselves in the English Channel have been continued by 841 Squadron(Swordfish and Albacores) operating under the direction of the R.A.F. Fighter
Command. Opportunities have arisen for pressing home forty-nine attacks,,out of a total of 248 sorties made from four South Coast aerodromes. Theco-operation between Naval aircraft and RA.F. Radio Control Staff has led toa high degree of efficiency in interception, with the result that eleven enemy vessels have been sunk, ten seriously damaged and five slightly damaged at&apos; thecost of one casualty. Enemy night fighters have failed in their attempts to-prevent these activities.Abroad.The culmination of the Mediterranean Naval campaign led to the with-drawal of the remaining shore-based Naval aircraft, the last Squadron to leavebeing 701 (Walrus) Squadron which completed a period of long and invaluableA/S work in the Eastern Mediterranean in conditions which made replacementand maintenance of aircraft exceptionally difficult.In a signal to the O-in-O, Levant, Air Officer Commanding, 201 naval co-operation Group, R.A.F., said of 701 Squadron  -&quot; I would be grateful if you would convey to the Commanding Officermy appreciation of the most excellent work this Squadron has carried out.Their operational record has been magnificent, and I would like to inviteyour attention to the Squadron&apos;s record of serviceability in spite of theirancient aircraft. No calls have been unanswered, and the work of bothOfficers and maintenance personnel has been beyond praise.&quot;Commodore, Levant Area, says of this Squadron : &quot; 701 has contributed much to the war effort. . . . Ships on this coastwill miss the familiar sight of the Walrus, in whose protection we all placeso much reliance.&quot;Section III. Aircraft.American Aircraft.An increasing number of American aircraft are coming into service. EightTarpon squadrons are formed or forming and three will be ready for operations in the near future. A further eight Corsair squadrons are now working up,five in America and three in the United Kingdom. Two Hellcat Squadronshave formed and two more are in the process of forming.The general performance of these American aircraft is most satisfactory.The fighters particularly are a welcome addition to the FA.A. fighter strength which is now stretched to the limit, and beyond, by the need for the completeequipment of six escort-carriers with specially trained fighter squadrons (andthe necessary reserves) for the support of amphibious operations, outside the range of R.A.F. single-engine fighters in the Far East.Photographs of these aircraft are shown on the succeeding pages.British Aircraft.The Firefly was originally designed as a long range two-seater fighter, as areplacement for the Fulmar. With the introduction of modern high perform-ance single-seater fleet fighters, its daylight role will be mainly that of a fastfighter reconnaissance aircraft.The first squadron has been formed and is now in training.After delivery of the first 150, Firefly aircraft will be fitted to carry bombs,or R.P. projectors.A night fighter version will follow.[26553]
APPENDIX I.Wastage* May to July 1943.Losses of Naval A aircraft incurred during the period May, June and July 1943-Reports received up to and including 30th October, 1943.Type.	Operational Squadrons.			Squadrons working up.      i      Training and Ancillary.						Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.	Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.	Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average mon thly wantage as per-centage of strength.T.B.E.......... S.S.F........., 2 S .F A.B.E. and L.B.&apos; Total  Operational Types   ... Non-operational Types  ....... Tqtal ...        ...	66 57 2 8	251 201 20 59	Per cent. 8-8 9-5 3-3 4-5	10 6	66 45 2	Per cent. 5-1 4-4	34 7 12 13	397 44 80 85	Per cent. 2-9 5-3 5-0 5-1	,133	531	8-3	16	113	&apos;   4-7	66	606	3-6				...			72	669	3-6	133	531	8-3	16	113	4-7 .	138     !  1,275		3-6* Note: 5 Aircraft (A.B.IO employed on Air Sea &quot;Rescue duties were also written off during theperiod.
APPENDIX II.Wastage May to July 1943.Losses of Naval Aircraft incurred during the period May, June and July 1943.   Reports received up to and including 30th October, 1943.Aircraft.	First Line.					Training and Ancillary.					Total.	Operational Types.					Operational Types.				Non-Opera-tional Types.		T.B.R.	S.S.F.	2 S.F.	A.B.R./ L.R.	Total.	T.B.R.	S.S.F.	2 S.F.	A.B.R./ L.R.	Miscellaneous.	(a) Lost or missing in operational flying (6) Destroyed on the ground or in H.M. Ships by enemy action (c) Lost in ships whilst in transit (d) Written off charge owing to accident (e) Written off charge owing to age, reduction to spares, &amp;c.        ...      ... (/) Unclassified     ......      ...      ......	17 3 48 5 3	12 46 2 c w	2	5 3	29 8 . 96 10 6	22 7 5	7	4 7   . -1	7 6	35 34 3	75 54 9Total       ...      ...	76	63	2	8	149	34	7	12	13&apos;	72	138Note. Written reports have not yet been received in respect of 35 of the items included in the above table. These have been included in the appropriate groupwhere possible. Certain cases included in group (d) may belong to group (a) as some aircraft accidents are subsequently shown to be attributed to enemy action. Inaddition to the above 5 aircraft (A.B.R.) employed on Air/Sea Rescue duties were written off during the period.
APPENDIX III.Casualties to Naval Flying Personnel, 1st August-31st October, 1943&quot;.Operational:PrisonersKilled. Missing. of War.Officers     ... ... 3 6Ratings    ...      ...      .... -  -  Flying Accidents.Officers     .*......... 47: -    : -Ratings    ........: 24 1 -




Tarpon I.

Barracuda Formation.Tarpon Formation.

Corsair 1.(The Corsair II is similar with raised Pilot&apos;s Cockpit and Clipped Wing Tips.)

Hellcat I.

Firefly F   Mk. I.




</content>
</cab>
