<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/21/1 images: 10-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GQYERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1942.SECRET CoPyW.P. (42) 21.January 14, 1942WAR CABINET.CONSIDERATION FOR LEASE-LEND AID.\.:Note by the Minister without Portfolio. -IN accordance1 with the request made by the War Cabinet at their meetingheld on the 5th January, 1942 (W.M. (42) 2nd Conclusions, Minute 11), I submita memorandum on the subject of consideration for Lease-Lend aid. Thismemorandum summarises the arguments Which have been expressed at theCommittee on Economic Aspects of Reconstruction Problems for and againstthe acceptance of the United States draft of Article VII of the proposed Lease-Lend Agreement. The history of the recent discussions is given in the Annex!to the memorandum. .&quot; &apos; (Initialled) -    . A. G.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,January 14, 1942.. Memorandum by the Minister without Portfolio.1. The reasons which have been urged in favour of the immediate acceptanceof the United States second draft of Article VIP of the proposed Lease-Lend,Agreement are:-(i) The necessity of ensuring by all means the continued goodwill and support,of the United States Administration and people both during the war and forpost-war reconstruction. Our main objectives should be to promote unity inwar and a state of mind ensuring a better peace. A strong warning (not givenspecially in connexion with, the lease-lend issue) against assuming, now that thetwo countries are co-belligerents, American compliance with our &quot;views was senton the 22nd December, 1941, by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador (telegram No. 5962):&quot; It is essential that no grounds should be given to the Americans for feeling,now they are &apos; in the bag&apos; by their entry into the war, we feel less obligation totake account of their opinions and wishes.&quot; !(ii) United States support, both in the Administration and in Congress, isparticularly necessary now that the President is about to approach Congress fora third lease-lend appropriation. That the Administration^ view of the necessityof United Kingdom acceptance of their draft of Article VII remains unchangedby co-belligerency isclear from two telegrams&apos; recently communicated by thqUnited States Ambassador, one of which contains the words: &quot;Developmentsin the immediate future render it highly important that an agreement becompleted without delay between our two Governments. There should not evenbe the appearance of disagreement between the Governments.&quot;(iii) In certain circles the Ottawa preferences have been regarded notprincipally as a political question, but as an attempt to save primary producersfrom the effects of continuing deflation. A new economic system will have tobe established after the war and everything should be open for consideration. &apos;.* Eeproduced in j\nnex, page 4, paragraph 4.[233433 - B
- (i-v) The- second United States- draft, of Axticla VII,. to which we are nowasked to subscribe, does not state that Imperial Preference has to be abandonedin advance without any quid pro quo or balancing advantages. True, thetheoretical principle would be abandoned by subscribing to the Article, but fromthe practical point of view the Article has most definite provisions for &quot;agreedaction by the United States of America and the United Kingdom&quot; for the-&quot; reduction of tariffs and other trade barriers and the attainment of all theeconomic objectives &quot; set forth in the Atlantic Charter, whilst- the seeond partOf the Article refers to conversations with a view to determining, &quot; in the lightof governing economic conditions,&quot; the best means of attaining the above-statedobjectives &quot; by their own agreed action.&quot; The concession in principle is thereforehedged round with so many reservations, that for the practical abandonmentof Imperial Preference the members of. the British Commonwealth could exactalmost any price they liked. Is it suggested that no price is great enough tocompensate for the reljnquishment of Imperial Preference?(v) The decisive question must be what kind of economic arrangements willexist in the post-war world ? It would be deplorable if there were a stronglyprotective British Empire confronted by a high tariff United States. Mutualconcessions will have to be made; and. if opinion against us hardens now inthe United States as a result of a refusal to accept this draft of Article VII,post-war concessions, fromi the United States, are not likely. The. world willfchen drift back to its, pre-war positiom(vi) The question has, been discussed with Dominion-High Commissioners^and it would appear; that some Dominion. Prime Ministers are not opposed toa commitment: to work towards&apos; the ultimate, abolition of Imperial Preferenceso long as theabolition is gradual and so; long as. the quid pro.- quo is-satisf actory,It is admitted that; the position of Canada requires special&apos; consideration..2. The reasons which have been urged against the acceptance&apos;of&apos;the&apos;UnitedStates second draft of Article VII are: (i) The acceptance of the United States draft of Article VII would&apos; committhe Government of the United Kingdom in principle to working towards theelimination of Imperial Preference. In fact, however, the whole situation hascompletely changed in the last few weeks. An agreement which was appropriateto a situation1 in wlhich a non-belligerent was; helping a,; belligerent (and wasdrafted to meet that situation) is quite inappropriate to the relationship betweentwo co-belligerents. Article II (which refers to-the United&apos; Kingdom contributionto the defence of the United^ States of America see Appendix 1)) in* fact;, becomes:-a most important reality.(ii) It cannot, be seriously imagined thatr the United States Government,Congress or people, because-. this country, refuses,to; commit itself on. an issueq$ post-war economic policy (an issue which had already been, safeguarded by thePresident&apos;s, adherence to-the exception.made, in Article: IV of the. Atlantic;Charter for &quot; existing obligations&quot;), would damageus;, themselves, and the futureexistence of democracy by. withholding full support .in^ the.war..(iii).-. ImgeriaJi-^reference-. sh6uld--nofc.bi&amp;..ahaaaid6nedi- ewiLih.gKincflple,-.witiM)uta ,definite,.knowledge of the.n&amp;t\&amp;&amp;.of the: quid,pro quo.  This cannot be, got now.(iv) Imperial; Preference is; not, fundamentally an, economic issue,. but- anexperiment in a new technique of free co-operation in a commonwealth of nationsdesiring;the same mode of life, including economic life.. JMm.analogous to thetransference- by the States of the American:Union to the Federal Government.ofcontrol of economic policy. Its, abandonment, would destroy the, chances; of thisfree,co-operation, whilst,the economic effect.on exporters, in the Dominions, theUnited Kingdom, and, above all, the. Colonies, would,be disastrous. There.arelong-standing preferences, in the United ^Kingdom for. imports, ftorn., the- ColonialEmpire, whilst, the United * Kingdom itself has benefited for many years bypreferences in the Dominions. After the war the best, chance, of markets wiilbe in favoured ones.(v) There is, in fact; no strong Reeling in ther United States on the subject.Whilst,, no.doubt, this is. a, particular enthusiasm of Mr. Cordell Hull and,.hisassociates; who endeavoured to secure, without success,- revision, of Article IVof the Atlantic Charter even after its signature, and whilst postwar coroperatibubetween the United Kingdom and the United States is certainly essential, itshould be on the basis of the co-operation of equals.&apos;.
(vi) Dominion Governments have been kept informed of the proposals, andof: our difficulties in regard to them. But a suggestion to Dominion Governmentsat this particular time, following immediately on recent events which have causedprofound disturbance of mind in the Empire, that the long-standing arrange-ments between the United Kingdom and the rest of the Empire should, even inprinciple, be abandoned would cause a profound shock to the many persons, notonly in the United Kingdom but throughout the rest of the Empire, who considerImperial Preference a most important bond of union, Abandonment of ImperialPreference would leave a deep wound in the British Commonwealth and in theBritish economic union. It would arouse tremendous passions, and give rise toa clamour for liberation from &quot; American pluto-democracy.&quot;(vii) The words in the proposed Article VII &quot; open to participation to allother countries of like mind &quot; and &quot;the agreed action of other like-mindedcountries &apos;1 might give to countries such as China unrestricted entry into Empiremarkets. What would the position be if, e.g., China, established after the Waran autarkic system and then went in for a policy of export subsidies ? *(viii) The only possibility of the United Kingdom and pther EmpireGovernments subscribing to the draft Article VII would be if an interpretationcould be agreed between the United States Government, the United Kingdom,and other Empire Governments stating that the Article does not prejudice theissue of policy in regard to Imperial Preference. A draft of such an interpreta-tion might be : &apos;&quot; Representatives of the United Kingdom Government have stated thatthey do not understand the word &apos; discrimination&apos; to apply to specialarrangements between members of the same Commonwealth orsuch as the United States of America or its possessions or the British; Commonwealth, and that before agreeing to action involving modificationof the existing system of Imperial Preference, the Government of the UnitedKingdom would, of course, require to consult with the Dominions.&quot;(ix) There is a disparity between the principle which the United Kingdomand other Dominion Governments are asked to accept, namely, the complete&quot;elimination&quot; of Imperial Preference, and that which the United States andother countries are asked to accept, namely, the &quot; reduction of tariffs and othertrade barriers,&quot; whilst the latter principle will also affect the United Kingdomand Dominion tariffs and import restrictions. There is thus a fundamentalunfairness in the suggested bargain.Offices of the War dub met.4 Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,January 14, 1942.[23343!
ANNEX.History of the recent Discussions on Lease-Lend &quot; Consideration.&apos;&apos;&apos;1. As a result of discussions at Washington on the subject of the considera-tion to be paid by the United Kingdom for Lease-Lend aid, a draft (reproducedin Appendix I) of an agreement between the United Kingdom and the UnitedStates was handed,by Mr. Dean Acheson to Mr. Keynes on the 28th July, 1941.No substantial issues are raised by any of the draft Articles, except byArticle VII, though it may be observed that Article II has become even more ofa reality than it was last July.2. As it was thought that the word (&apos; discrimination &apos;&apos; in Article VII mightbe held to include Imperial Preference (an interpretation we now know from theAmbassador^ telegram No. 5954 of the 21st December, 1941, to have been placedon the word both by the State Department and the President), the followingredraft, aftef approval by the Prime Minister and acceptance by His Majesty&apos;sAmbassador, was submitted in October 1941 to the United States Government :-Article VII.(i) The terms and conditions upon which the Government of the UnitedKingdom receives defence aid from the Government of the United Statesof America and the benefits to be received by the United States of Americain return therefor, as finally determined, shall be such as not to burdencommerce between the two countries, but to promote mutually advantageouseconomic relations between them; they shall provide for joint and agreedr action by the United States and United Kingdom, each working within thelimits of their governing economic conditions, directed to securing as partof a general plan the progressive attainment of balanced internationaleconomies, the avoidance of harmful discriminations, and generally theeconomic objectives set forth in the joint Declaration made by the President- of the United States of America and the Prime Minister of the UnitedKingdom on the 12th August, 1941.(ii) And, furthermore, it is agreed that at an early convenient dateconversations should be begun between the two Governments with a view todiscussing the best means of attaining the above objects and generally thebetter ordering of economic intercourse between nations in future conditionsof settled peace.3. Very shortly after the receipt of the first American draft the AtlanticCharter had been signed.  Article IV reads as follows : &apos;&apos; They will endeavour, with due respect for their existing obligations,to further enjoyment by all States, great or small, victor or vanquished, ofaccess on equal terms to the trade and to the raw materials of the world whichare needed for their economic prosperity.&quot;4. On the 2nd December, 1941, the State Department submitted to HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador the following revised text of Article VII: Article VII.(Second United States Draft.)(i) In the final determination of the benefit to be provided to the UnitedStates of America by the Government of the United Kingdom in return foraid furnished under the Act of Congress of the 11th March, 1941, the termsand conditions thereof shall be such as not to burden commerce between thetwo countries, but to promote mutually advantageous economic relationsbetween them and the betterment of world-wide economic relations. To thatend, they shall include provision for agreed action by the United States ofAmerica and the United Kingdom, open to participation by all othercountries of like mind, directed to the expansion, by appropriate inter-national and domestic measures, of production, employment, and exchangeand-consumption of goods, which are the material foundation of. the liberty
and welfare of all peoples; to the elimination of all forms of discriminatorytreatment in international commerce, and to the reduction of tariffs and othertrade barriers; and, in general, to the attainment of all the economicobjectives set forth in the joint declaration made on the 12th August, 1941,by the President of the United States of America and the Prime Ministerof the United Kingdom.(ii) At an early convenient date conversations shall be begun between thetwo Governments with a view to&apos; determining, in the light of governingeconomic conditions, the best means of attaining the above-stated objectivesby their own agreed action and of seeking the agreed action of other like-minded Governments.5. This more lengthy draft, in addition to words which specifically allowof participation by other countries &apos;&apos; of like mind &quot; and also provide forexpansion of &quot; production^ employment, and exchange and consumption ofgoods,&quot; still contains words which would, on the United States interpretation,preclude Imperial Preference, viz., &quot; discriminatory treatment in internationalcommerce.&quot; The arguments with which Mr. Acheson and Mr. Feis supported thesecond United States draft were (Ambassadors telegram of the 4th December,No. 5589) as follows(i) As it is desired to avoid the impression that exclusive Anglo-American.    action is intended, &quot; agreed: - action &quot; replaces &quot;joint and agreed^action.&quot;(ii) Expansion of production, &amp;c. is put in the forefront in orderto emphasise that the United States must play a-substantial part inachieving this end and that the elimination of discrimination andreduction of tariffs, &amp;c. may be seen as part of a much bigger scheme,capable of achievement only as part of this broader statement of aimswhich the United States Government would help to promote.(iii) The qualification &quot; in the light of governing economic conditions &quot; hasbeen put in paragraph 2 instead of paragraph 1, because paragraph 2refers to what is actually to be done in contrast with the statement ofgeneral objectives in paragraph 1. Paragraph 2, in fact, refers to theaction to be taken, after discussions, to achieve the purposes stated inparagraph 1.(iv) The new draft as a whole deliberately uses general terms in an effortto meet our objections to the original draft, but at the same timethe United States Government- have avoided unduly cautiousphraseology which might arouse hostile criticism in the UnitedStates. ;(v) The United States Government are set on aiming at elimination of&quot;discrimination,&quot; though they realise clearly that this cannot beachieved at once. There is admittedly a disparity between&quot;elimination of all forms of discriminatory treatment&quot; and &quot;thereduction, of tariffs and other trade barriers,&quot; but the United StatesGovernment feel it would be impossible to get the countries of theworld to commit themselves to the aim of complete elimination oftariffs, but that complete elimination of discrimination, which isqualitatively different from tariffs, is a practicable aim. \.(vi) Very lengthy discussions had; been necessary to produce this agreeddraft, not only with the State Department but also with the EconomicDefence Board, the Office of the Lehd-Lease Administration, andwith the President himself. The proposal of verbal amendments toprovide a loophole, e.g., for Imperial Preference (in addition to theprovisional exception, which, in the United States view, exists underparagraph 2, because complete abolition of discrimination must taketime) would &quot; create a very bad impression with regard to our desireto co-operate in achieving these ends and make many of our friendsfeel like throwing up the sponge.&quot;(vii) There are already indications that other Departments wish to interfere,viz., the Army and Navy Departments, and delay might make itimpossible to keep them at bay. The consequence of such interferencewas unforeseeable, but might well be disastrous.
$(mix) Most important jof all was the urgency on political grou&amp;ds ,of reachingan agijeement, -Ths T3nti^*S$^Mwmmmb-.Mm[e&amp; ^b*;men.:in .January they asked Congress for a third Lease-Lend appropriationthey must have a provisional agreement behind them which ithej.coukidefend before Congress, if necessary. Publication would mostprobably be necessarv when the President goes before Congress inmid-January jot a little later, and it would take all the backing ofinfluential members of the Administration, such as Mr. Hull, to* makeit accept&quot; this statement of purpose as an adequate quid fro quo forLease-Lend and a satisfactory declaration of policy for the post-warperiod, particularly having regard to the suggestion for a reductionof tariffs.&quot; The United States Government feared that theAdministration might need to be armed with supporting evidence&quot; to convince Congress and the American public that the errors ofthe last post-war period will be avoided, perhaps in the form ofexchanges of letters which provide for discussions of such, specificthing? as joint defence measures, provision of capital assistance andnutrition schemes.&quot; 16. At the date of his telegram (the 4th December, 1941), the Ambassador&apos;sviews were that he was convinced of the good faith of the President and theUnited States Administration in their expression of desire to achieve the purposesstated in the new draft of Article VII: they fully appreciated that the UnitedStates would have to play a major part in achieving these ends and that theymust devise the means of helping the United Kingdom over its post-wardifficulties. They believed that the second paragraph of the new draft Article VIIrecognises that means must be devised to realise the purposes of paragraph 1,and that these means must depend on governing economic conditions, and thatwithout provision for assistance by the United States the statement of aimswould be nugatory and therefore would not bind any country independently ofthis assistance. The Ambassador was also convinced that the United StatesGovernment was gravely concerned about the formidable political difficulties withwhich they are now, and in future will be, confronted in striving for these ends.Perhaps they did not feel sure that international co-operation would be possiblealong the lines they desired, but they honestly believed that the only chance ofsuccess lay in striving now to get the respective countries to accept these articlesof faith. They feared that even during the war the political situation in theUnited States might so deteriorate in consequence of our achieving nothing new,, that the forces of economic and political isolationism might triumph and makelater success impossible. They urged that some risks must be taken for the sakeof the future. They were willing to take their risks with Congress, and theybegged us to take political risks on our side to win the large gains at stake. TheAmbassador therefore expressed the view that the second United States draft ofArticle VII should be accepted as it stood. In his view, it did not commit us toabolition of Exchange or other controls at the end of the war without regard toeconomic conditions then prevailing, or to United States assistance in changingthose conditions, nor did it commit us to dropping Imperial Preference withoutregard to the prevailing conditions. He appreciated, however, that a questionof paramount political importance was involved, since the draft &quot; commits us toa policy of ultimate abolition of Imperial Preference albeit for the sake of- widereconomic opportunity all round,&quot; In his view there was no chance of gettingthe Americans to except Imperial Preference explicitly nor of redrafting theArticle so as to except it by implication. Any attempt at verbal change on thisvital point would be bound to fail.7. The Ambassador&apos;s telegram; and the second American draft ofArticle VII were considered by the Committee on Economic Aspects of Recon-st;ruetion Problems o$ the 12jh December, 1941, and as a result the telegram(No. 6914) reproduced in. Appendix II of this memorandum wags despatched onthe 13th December. The Ambassador&apos;^ replies (telegrams Nos. 5953 and 5954)are reproduced as Appendix HI, It will fee seen, that the Ambassador, for thereasons given m his telegram No, 5953, did not convey to the United States thesuggestion made, in, the telegram tohimt oj the 13th December, that conversationsshould take place before; the terras of the toswtattioa Agreement, were finallysettled.  In his view the steps suggested in the telegram of the 13th Deecember
would have a most deplorable and perhaps long4asting effect upon relations withthe United States of America, and he summarised the point at issue as follows :  &quot; Ar&amp; we or are We^ not p^paa*ed&apos; tove5Sp*es  a^eatenbe-to&apos; the generalprinciples, subject to means being found by later discussion, to make suchprinciples effective ?&quot;8. These telegrams were considered by the Committee on Economic Aspectsof Reconstruction Problems on the 23rd December, and on the 24th December atelegMm (No. 7224, reproduced^ asf Appendix LV): was:&quot; despatched&apos; The repliestoithiS&apos;(Wos: Mm atod 6106) are reproduced itf AppehdM V. These; were! dfecussMby the Committee on Economic: Aspects of RedJns^ruction Problems 6b! tM31st December, 1941, and the Ambassador was informed that the War Cabinetto whom the matter had been reported, felt that the! return of the Prime Ministeri *
: .        Proposed Anglo-American Agreement under Lease-Lend Act.0 &apos; Preamble.[Not Copied.]Article I.THE United States of America will continue to supply the United Kingdomwith such defense articles, defense services and defense information as thePresident shall authorise to be transferred or provided.Article II.The United Kingdom will continue to contribute to the defense of the UnitedStates of America and the strengthening thereof and, should circumstances ariseih;which the United States of America in its own defense or the defense of theAmericas may require articles, services, or information, will provide such articles,services, or information as it may be in a position to supply.Article III.The Government of the United Kingdom will not without the consent ofthe President transfer title to, ox possession&apos; of, any defense article or defenseinformation transferred to it under the Act or permit the use thereof by anyonenot an officer, employee or agent of the Government of the United Kingdom.Article IV. &quot;If, as a result of the transfer to the Government of the United Kingdomof any defense article or defense information, it becomes necessary for thatGovernment to take any action or make any payment in order fully to protectany of the rights of a citizen of the United States of America who has patentrights in and to any such defense article or information, the Government of theUnited Kingdom will take such action or make such payment when requested todo so by the President.Article V.The Government of the United Kingdom will return to the United States ofAmerica at the end of the present emergency, as determined by the President,such defense articles transferred under this Agreement as shall be determinedby the President to be useful in the defense of the United States of America orof the Western Hemisphere or to be otherwise of use to the United States ofAmerica.Article VI.In the final determination of the benefits to be provided to the United Statesof America full cognizance shall be taken of all property, services, information,facilities, or other benefits or considerations provided by the Government of theUnited Kingdom subsequent to 11th March, 1941, and accepted or acknowledgedby the President on behalf of the United States of America.Article VII.The terms and conditions upon which the United Kingdom receives defenseaid from the United States of America and the benefits to be received by theUnited States of America in return therefor, as finally determined, shall besuch as not to burden commerce between the two countries but to promote mutuallyadvantageous economic relations between them and the betterment of world-wideeconomic relations; they shall provide against discrimination in either the UnitedStates of America or the United Kingdom against the importation of any produceoriginating in the other country; and they shall provide for the formulation ofmeasures for the achievement of these ends.Article VIII.This Agreement shall continue in force from the date on which it is signeduntil a date agreed upon by the two Governments. bSigned and sealed at Washington in duplicate this       day of , 194
Copy of Telegram No. 6914 from Foreign Office to Washington,, dated December 13, 1941.. YOUR telegrams Nos. 5589, 5590 and 5670.Your telegrams were sent before the outbreak of war with Japan. Positionis no doubt therefore greatly changed. We feel we cannot at this moment pressAustralia, for example, with the enemy at her gates, to discuss with us so-far-reaching a matter as an agreement looking to the eventual abolition ofImperial. Preference.2, If you share this view, could you take an opportunity when seeing himon other matters to suggest to the President that discussions on the terms ofArticle VII might be suspended for a while until all the Governments concernedcan give the matter the mature and careful consideration which it requires ?3. It is obvious that we could not come to a decision upon the issue ofImperial Preference without full discussion with Dominions. From the pointof view of Australia and Canada it would be extremely inopportune in presentcircumstances to embark upon consultations which, in any event, would be lengthy&apos;and difficult..4. As you know, we have all along been willing to embark upon theconversations contemplated in the drafts of Article VII. Our proposal now isthat, as soon as conditions admit, and before attempting to settle finally theterms of the Consideration Agreement, there should be conversations with theAdministration of a preliminary and general character. The necessaryconsultation with the Dominions would also be of a general character, requiringno final decision on Imperial Preference or any other large issue. Thisconsultation could therefore be much more easily taken up and could probablybe fairly quickly completed.5. Your Report, as a whole, makes us feel that it would be much betterfor conversations with the Administration to take place before the terms of theConsideration Agreement are finally settled. We believe that these conversationsmay clear up many questions, and, in particular, give the American repre-sentatives a better impression of our intentions and a clearer understanding ofour difficulties, thus creating a more favourable atmosphere for settling generalformulas. In suggesting this we think you will agree that recent events have-greatly reduced the force of your argument in paragraph 5 (3) of your telegramNo. 5589 for an immediate settlement.6. Apart from Imperial Preference, the reintroduction of the word&quot;discrimination&quot; without any qualifying adjective shows the importance whichthe Administration attach to it. Our comment, for your information, is thatthe word &quot;discrimination&quot; admits of various interpretations and it becomesessential that we should review very carefully to what extent we can at this&apos;stage whole-heartedly subscribe to it. Is it certain that the Administration wouldwish entirely to eliminate all possibilities of discrimination against States which:may still in the future exhibit aggressive tendencies? Have they in mind toeliminate the discriminatory export subsidies now in force in the United States!which distinguish between different destinations ? But what we have chiefly inmind are our own post-war difficulties, which wiill be very real; they certainlyare not understood in America at present. We need to review carefully howfar we can afford to undertake to divest ourselves of the power to use protectivemeasures unless and until better arrangements can be found.7. You will appreciate that the issue of Imperial Preference is one in whichParliament would take a very close interest. Presumably Congress, too, wouldwish to be consulted about the proposed abolition of existing United Statesdiscriminatory measures and the suggested permanent undertaking never toemploy them or any others.[23343]c
Copy of a Telegram No. 5953 from Washington to the Foreign Office; datedDecember 21, 1941.YOUR telegram No. 6914.1. I am most reluctant to convey the substance of your telegram under repljto the United States Government. Such action so shortly after America has comeinto the war must, in my judgment, have a most deplorable, and perhaps long-lasting, effect upon our relations.2. The first two sentences in your telegram under reply convince me that possibly through some faulty expression by myself I have failed to make clearto you the real point of the draft agreement. The position as I see it is asfollows : &apos;3. His Majesty&apos;s Government have been asked to subscribe to a jointdeclaration which, in accordance with their own expressed wish, is in the mostgeneral terms. American Administration have repeatedly told us that, in theirjudgment, adherence to draft declaration is an essential preliminary to thedetailed discussions which will follow. We in our turn have put them under the[ ? group undecypherable : impression] that our financial and other problems willbe very grave. They are just as well aware as ourselves that, with the best willin the world, we may all fail to find workable solutions politically acceptable toboth sides and to the others who must also be consulted later on. Nevertheless,they ask for the acceptance of the draft agreement as a definition of our commonobjective and as a demonstration of our goodwill.4. We undertake, if we sign the draft as it stands, to do no more than towork towards certain objectives, but only provided that, and only for so long as,the United States Government does the same thing. There is an overwhelmingobligation upon us at this critical juncture in the history of Anglo-Americanrelations to take no steps which will make the task of collaboration, in all&apos;conscience bound to be hard enough, more difficult still by what, I cannot but feel,,would be a political blunder at tlie outset. To attempt to ride them off by whatthey will certainly think evasive tactics will inevitably create an atmosphere ofdeep mistrust, of which the smallest of the possible evil results must beenormously to aggravate the difficulty of reaching agreement in discussions.Above all, we simply cannot afford to allow suspicion to arise in the mind of thePresident or of his advisers that we are organising [ ?] the entry of the UnitedStates into the war as a pretext for evading the commitments which we mightotherwise have been not unwilling to undertake, as appears to be suggested bythe reference in paragraph 1 of your telegram under reply to the changed position.5. The simple point surely is this : Are we or are we not prepared toexpress adherence to the general principles, subject to means being found bylater discussion to make such principles effective ? If we say that we are soprepared and I should suppose that most people would like the principles ifthey thought they could be made effective the obligation to implement suchgeneral profession of purpose will depend on whether or not discussions show themeans by which, and extent to which, this can in fact be done.If we say that we are not prepared to accept the general principles, in spiteof acceptance being safeguarded, we shall quite gratuitously, as it seemed to me,gravely prejudice the prospect of economic co-operation between the UnitedStates and the commonwealth which we all want and know we must have.6.   See my immediately following telegram.
-       . Copy of telegram No. 5954 from Washington to the Foreign Office,dated December 21, 1941.YOUR telegram No. 6914. ..My immediately preceding telegram. - &apos;o As I explained in my preceding telegram, President and his advisers desireHis Majesty&apos;s Government to agree to their revised draft, because they believe itis absolutely essential as a first step to developing healthier conditions for post-war world &quot;trade, but I am not sure that the true meaning of article 7 has been;,fully grasped, especially with regard to tying our hands or defining our policyafter the war.2. As regards Imperial preference, question having been put to the StateDepartment orally last July, they replied that in their view it was included indiscrimination, and the President indicated that this was his view in conversationwith me in August on his return from the Atlantic conference. But theAmericans neither ask nor expect us to give up Imperial preference now, andwhatever they may hope about ultimate abolition of it, they have throughouttheir discussions on several trade agreements never sought anything more thanmodification in exchange for important reductions of their own tariffs.. - 3. I cannot judge from here the attitude of the different Dominionsregarding the implication of possible ultimate effect on Imperial preference. Ishould certainly expect them to be most unwilling to contemplate abandonmentas an isolated proposition. But this is not the proposal that the United StatesGovernment are making. They want us to say we are willing to work with themfor a wider world system of trade. The kind of agreed action which administra-tion have in mind is indicated by negotiations of new trade agreements with theUnited Kingdom, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa. These agreementsif concluded, would provide for modification of certain alternative preferencesand a very substantial reduction of United States tariff. If a fair balance ofconcessions can be struck, result might be not disadvantageous to the Empire.If we press now our objections in principle to abolition of preferential systemit seems to me that a deadlock must be reached, whereas if we avoid discussionof principle and try to agree upon balance measures of adjustment, principlemay remain for an indefinitely long time. When the Dominions were consultedregarding our draft article 7 they raised no objections. I do not believe presentdraft materially changes the situation. If we raise now need to consult withDominions as an insuperable obstacle to a settlement, Americans may well wonderwhy the Dominions were not consulted earlier.4. As regards other Questions included in discrimination, I believe thatlast sentence of paragraph 6 of your telegram under reply misinterprets theextent to which we would be committed if we subscribed to article 7. As aresult of my discussions with Americans, I do not think article 7 divests us orother countries in the same position of power of use of necessary measures todeal with post-war difficulties. As part of a general plan, main features ofwhich Americans intend to be beneficial to the world, they ask us to join themin avoiding methods of discrimination which might cut across this general plan.This applies equally to methods of theirs to which we object. Our rights areretained until by agreed action we create conditions in which full use of themwill have become unnecessary. Besides providing for declaration of our intentionto strive jointly with United States for a certain kind of economic system,article 7 provides for discussions to start as soon as convenient with a view todevising means of attaining that system. Discussions must inevitably includemethods of dealing with post-war problems not specifically covered by theUnited States formula. It may be, of course, that Administration arc strivingfor a system more ideal than they or any future administration can finallypersuade Congress to approve, but I should say that this unescapable elementof doubt would not prevent us from accepting draft agreement with all itsadvantages to us.5.   No doubt conflicts of interest, and even misunderstandings, may arisein the course of these discussions, but I have no doubt whatever that theatmosphere will be far more favourable for amicable settlement of our difficulties[23343] c 2
if we now subscribe to the general declaration of intention as in article 7 than ifwe could get Americans to agree to this latter course. This view is strengthenedby the very fact that you regard &apos;&apos; discrimination &apos;&apos; as admitting of a variety ofinterpretations. Our negotiating position would be sure to be more favourableif we could have discussion of difficulties on basis of particular issues involvinginterpretation than if we began by discussing difficulties of principle in anattempt to define &quot;discrimination.&quot;6. This latter argument covers the question raised in paragraph 6 of yourtelegram under reply regarding possible discrimination against aggressive States.Acceptance of principle of avoiding discrimination would not prejudge questionof taking action against aggressors. But I should not in any case like to putseriously to the Americans, as a reason for not accepting article 7, that it wouldnot rule out economic sanctions in future. Frankly, I believe it to be a badargument. It would irritate the Americans because they would think itdisingenuous; and they would probably reply that economic sanctions constitutea large political question requiring treatment on its merits by measures outsideproposed agreement.7. Your paragraph 7. No doubt discussions would almost certainly giverise to proposals which would require Congress and Parliamentary [groupundecypherable : ? approval]. To what extent Australian Government wouldfeel it necessary to consult Parliament before assenting to assessment of generalprinciples in proposed consideration agreement is, of course, for them to decide.So far as United States Congress is concerned, it is a special advantage of thisform of procedure for dealing with questions of consideration under Lend-LeaseAct that Congress need not be consulted before agreement is signed. Americansare well aware of this, and their desire to get agreement settled now is part oftheir plan of campaign to get and keep Congress in right frame of mind.      1
Copy of Telegram, No. 7224 from the Foreign Of/ice to Washington, dated .December 24, 1941.YOUR telegrams Nos. 5953 and 5954 [of 20th December ; draft ConsiderationAgreement].   ,We fully appreciate the great importance of the considerations set out inyour telegrams under reference, but they do not remove the difficulties confrontingus here and with the&apos;Dominions if we accept Article VII as it now stands. Thecase might be different, however, if an interpretation embodying the views set outin your telegrams as regards both Imperial Preference and other forms ofdiscrimination (similar views have recently been expressed to us here by UnitedStates Ambassador) could be agreed by the two Governments with the under-standing that this agreed interpretation could, if occasion arose, be made public.After all, your telegram No. 5589 [of 4th December] states, in paragraph 8, thatArticle VII commits us to a policy of ultimate abolition of Imperial Preference.This view of Article VII, when the Agreement is published, will certainly beexpressed in Parliament here and in the Dominions, and also presumably inCongress. On the economic, as opposed to the political, side, proper reservationsin regard to other forms of discrimination are not less important than those inregard to Imperial Preference.2. Neither Government, we suggest, can risk the publication of a documentof which the interpretation is uncertain, and such a step would gravely prejudicefurther co-operation.3. As the Prime Minister is fully seized of the difficulties we feel, whichwere discussed with him before he left, we suggest that you should take theearliest opportunity of placing before him the views expressed in our previous,and your own telegrams and in particular ascertain his views as to thepracticability of securing an agreed interpretation of the nature suggested above.Of course, we could not in any case commit ourselves to a policy putting thefuture of Imperial Preference in the melting-pot without previous consultationwith the Dominions. If a satisfactory interpretation were agreed, however, itwould make it very much easier to carry out consultations with the Dominionsto finality, and we should hope to be able to reach early agreement with them asto the course to be pursued.
Copy of telegram No. 6105, dated December 29, 1941, from Washington to th&amp;Foreign Office.A&quot;   YOUR telegram No. 7224. &apos;     &apos; -I spoke to the Prime Minister as suggested in your paragraph 3, but,unfortunately he has so much vital business on hand that it is quite impossiblefor him to spare the time to deal with the matter.2. But the matter cannot be left in cold storage. I do not wish to restatethe argument of my earlier telegrams, but I should like the Chancellor, to whomthe Prime Minister said he was accustomed to look for advice on this subject,and the Cabinet to appreciate this.Unless my judgment, as that of all my principal advisers here, is at fault,there is not the smallest chance of the United States Government revising theirmain position on this contentious clause. Delay will not affect the attitude ongeneral declaration of intention to which they desire our adherence.When we get to discussions we can well argue on particular questions, ason detailed application, for example, of wheat agreement, that we cannot tie ourhands before we know more of the shape of the problem, as it will emerge. Butthis argument does not serve for ground of refusal to subscribe to a generaldeclaration of intention.3. The choice therefore before His Majesty&apos;s Government, if difficult, isclear, and remains as stated in paragraph 5 of my telegram No. 5953.&apos; 4. To this I would only add : (1) if our final choice must be that we cannotreject the way of economic co-operation with the United States, or (b) if they.will not, as I am convinced they will not, vary the broad basis of the declaredcommon purpose in which they invite us to join, then the only result of delaymust be to breed unnecessary and embarrassing suspicions at this end.5. I cannot gauge the probable reaction of the United States Governmentto your suggestion that we should have an agreed interpretative documentsupplementary to Article VII until I know the sort of document you have in mind.I have drafted statement of ^the kind that I imagine you are contemplating, andto save time I send it in my immediately following telegram for your comment.6. I do not think that it would be much good trying for agreed interpretativedocument if it was to involve delay of, say, more than a week or two.But I cannot myself feel, from such exchange of views as I have had withthe Dominions representatives here and in London, that they would feel greatdifficulty in assenting to general declaration, on the understanding that the degreeto which it can be implemented will depend on subsequent discussions and on thewhole scheme that emerged being satisfactory to them and to ourselves.I should hope, therefore, that you would approach them and invite them toconcur in the article, as drafted, with or without an interpretative agreeddocument if we could get one.6 [sic]. Since drafting the above, Hull asked me this morning whenwe might be in a position to reply, and said that they would be obliged to makea statement before Congress not later than mid-January. He hoped we mightbe able to settle before then.7 [sic&apos;].   See my immediately following telegram.Copy of Telegram&apos;No. 6106, dated December 29, 1941, from Washington to theForeign Office.MY immediately preceding telegram.I have the honour to refer to conversations between representatives of theGovernments of United States and United Kingdom in connexion with Article VIIof Lease-Lend provisional agreement signed this day.
2. During the course of these conversations representatives of United Stateshave indicated that their Government fully appreciate post-war problems whichwill confront the Governments of United States and United Kingdom, and ofother countries which may subsequently participate in the agreed action for theattainment of objectives stated in the said Article 7.3. Representatives of the United States Government have referred to specialposition of the United Kingdom by reason of its dependence on internationaltrade, and to the severity of the problem of balance of payments with which theGovernment of the United Kingdom will have to deal in post-war period, andthey have recognised the necessity of taking this problem into account informulating agreed action to attain the ends of Article 7.4. Representatives of United States Government have also referred to theobligation On the Government of the United Kingdom to consult with theDominions before consenting to the agreed action that may involve modificationof existing system of Imperial preference.5. Representatives of the Government of the United Kingdom have referredto the problem which will confront the United States Government in makingadjustments in productive system of the United States in order that the UnitedStates may take their appropriate place in the system of world trade that therespective Governments are striving to attain.6. Representatives of both Governments recognised that progress in theattainment of objects stated in Article 7 must be gradual, and that nothing inArticle 7 binds either Government to take action unilaterally without regard toaction by the other, as may be agreed after discussion for which the above-mentioned Article provides.




</content>
</cab>
