<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/2 images: 68-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Sis document is the property of his britannic majesty-s governmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1940..P. (R.) (40) 2.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND  KEY.Copy No. 9gIt is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.PUBLICITY IN ENEMY COUNTRIES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues, for their information, a further report,r the period the 20th November-the 21st December, by Sir Campbell Stuart on.work of the Department of Publicity in Enemy Countries.H.Foreign Office, January 1, 1940.Report by Sir Campbell Stuart.Weather.My last report was dated the 20th November. Since then the weather hassn exceptionally bad, even for late autumn, and consequently the Royal Airirce have informed me that it has only been possible for them to distributeiffie million leaflets by aircraft, and another million by balloon. This totalUmprised seven separate leaflets. The delays and uncertainty entailed by[favourable conditions have been even more disappointing than the shrinkageoutput, since they have made it almost impossible to count on the leaflet as aeans of swift rejoinder to the enemy&apos;s propaganda. We had, however, foreseene difficulties of the season, and had adjusted our plans to them. For some time;ast our leaflets have been so drafted that they do not rapidly become out of date.,y printing orders have, moreover, been reduced to accord with the smaller loadhich winter temperatures enforce, and I have relied increasingly upon our littleur-page paper, Wolkiger Beobachter, since it combines propaganda points withcts withheld by the German censorship, and thus effects an economy in theJDlume of our production.implement to the Wolkiger Beobachter.In regard to this useful broadsheet I may add that we now intend to encloseith it a supplement which will permit us to treat serious propaganda themesjore comprehensively and argumentatively than has hitherto been possible.   Iope that this new production will obtain a considerable circulation from handhand.  At the same time I am, of course, continuing to produce the one-pageTge-print leaflet, since, owing to Gestapo measures against picking up ourterature, it conveys its message to the maximum of potential readers.   For the10794   [20558] B
time being, however, I am, in view of restriction upon distribution, using it only for such important propaganda points as the Prime Minister&apos;s broadcast on the26th November, the invasion of Finland and the pooling of Anglo-Frenchresources.Special Raids.1 am also beginning to develop regional propaganda from the air. by arrangement with the Royal Air Force I have supplied them with leaflets fordissemination by special raids on Austria, Czecho-Slovakia and Hamburg.Climatic conditions, however, have not yet permitted these flights. The delayis unfortunate, since, in addition to their propaganda value, thef would have demonstrated to the German authorities our capacity directly to foster localdissensions.Joint Anglo-French Leaflet.In my last report I mentioned that my French colleagues had readily acceptedmy suggestion of a joint Anglo-French leaflet intended to counter the effort ofGerman propaganda to divide the Allies. This is in the hands of the RoyalAir Force, and a second has since been prepared. So warmly, indeed, havethey taken to the idea that recently the)&apos; have themselves suggested a co-operativeeffort to produce a six-page leaflet of a more ambitious type than either country has yet attempted. This, it has been agreed, will contain a joint statementsigned by the Prime Ministers of Great Britain and France. The other contentshave, at the suggestion of the French propaganda department, been, for themost part, drafted by us, and the whole is now being printed in Paris.Londoner Brief.Under leaflet production I may also record a new venture in the shape ofa fortnightly news-letter in German, which, with the ultimate aim of reachingGermany, we are now posting to German firms in neutral countries, and to neutral firms which are known to trade with the enemy. The distribution isabout five thousand, but, if our reports indicate that our efforts are successful,it will probably be increased. I need scarcely add that in regard to this publica-tion I am acting with the full knowledge and approval of the Ministry oiInformation. Neutral countries fall, naturally, within its sphere of activity,but i have from the first agreed with it that my Department is entitled to all necessary way-leaves through neutral countries to its own objective, the Germanpeople. A rough and ready definition of my claim is the right to conductpropaganda either by direct or indirect means among Germans in Germany itselfor outside it. My liaison with the Ministry of Information is very close, andarrangements exist in virtue of which each of us will know all activities of theother which concern neutral countries. Consequently, there is no fear of over-lapping or waste of effort.Broadcasting.Fortunately, indeed, the frosts and fogs of winter do not frustrate theB.B.C. Indeed, the limits they have imposed on our printed output have tosome extent, been compensated by additional time on the air, since the early morning news programme to Germany is in full swing. The B.B.C. now givefour German programmes a day, and so satisfied am I of their value that Ihave asked for three more. If my request is granted our output will stand ina more satisfactory proportion to the immense flood of wireless propaganda whichpours from the German stations. Inasmuch as we believe that the German publiclisten in chiefly for the sake of trustworthy news, the B.B.C. confine specialtalks in German to the later evening programme, which always includes one,and usually two, of these and only less regularly at other times. In these we seek to provide a wide variety both of topics and of speakers. Matters of enter-tainment value only is, however, avoided, since we believe that Germans whoare risking their personal liberty by tuning in seek information rather thanamusement. Instead, we strive to make in attractive form the strongest possibleappeal to German reason and sentiment. Every now and then a broadcast speciallyaddressed to Austrians is included, and we have been fortunate in securing(according to experts) excellent broadcasts and broadcasters for this particular
eature Czech, Polish and the recently introduced Slovak broadcasts alsontinue in these respective languages, and, as i recorded last month, are heardar over Central Europe. We have recently been challenged in the Press forailing to labour propaganda points which arise in the news. This, however,,s a deliberate policy. Germans are satiated with the over, emphasis of theirwn propagandists, and there is every reason to believe that they welcome the ore restrained presentations of our own wireless.esults Achieved.In the period under review further evidence of the effectiveness of Britishropa^anda has been received. One letter from Germany, reported from aefuo-ee source, states that, &quot; in spite of penalties, the leaflets are being passedround, even from one town to another .... the print is so legible that youon&apos;t have to pick the leaflet, but can read it lying on the ground.&quot; Manyources confirm that the circulation is considerable, and some also state thatctive measures are still being taken to counter their effect. The Chief Censoras heard from a known Dutch informant who visits Germany that &quot; the Germanopulation in any big town in general is, anxious for the news by pamphlets to behrown by British aeroplanes.&quot; He often heard such questions as &quot;Did youeceive a pamphlet, too? &quot; and &quot; May I read your pamphlet? &quot; Other informa-ion which I have received from an American source within Germany emphasisedhe value of a British leaflet, &quot; Der Fiihrer Spricht.&quot; Mr. Villard, the American,ournalist. has also paid a tribute in the Press to this particular piece ofropaganda. It is perhaps worth adding that steps are being taken to provideat, when leaflet raids on certain localities can be timed more accurately, a secretgent will be present on the spot and will report by devious channels oneir effect.roadcastincj Reports.Information received in regard to the effect of our broadcasts in Germanyrengthens the belief that listeners to them are increasing, and that they areore highly esteemed in Germany than any other foreign services.   The reasonually given is the trust placed in the accuracy of the B.B.C. news.  An instancea regular German listener who papered his windows and listened to a muchuced volume has been conveyed to me.   Another message states that, thoughidphones can only be obtained illicitly, they are often used; yet another, thatstyle of the German bulletin is made to suit the German mentality.  We have,ever, been told that families which employ servants and some with youngIdren are chary of listening.   As we had hoped, tidings of prisoners are aticular attraction.  Furthermore, we were interested to learn through a trust-rthy source in Hungary that, in spite of the fact that the B.B.C. provide abgramme in Magyar, Hungarians listen to a great extent to the British newstalks in German.It would appear that, as the result of years of censorship arid distortion, thelging of Germans for accurate news has become so great that numbers of the mill risk imprisonment to indulge it.  In these circumstances we are conscious ofgreat opportunities; but I submit that the inexorable condition of realising themthat we continue to uphold our standard of strict truthfulness.*$ential Intelligence.It is, of course, obvious that&apos; the efficiency of any organisation for propagandach as mine depends primarily upon its service of Intelligence.  For the purposesbroadcasting and in a lesser, though still important degree, of leaflet produc-.,n--the information at its.disposal must be fresh, accurate and complete.  Frome first we sought to create a first-class intelligence department, and soon found at we required from, it a daily summary of the Press and broadcasting both ofermany and of neutral countries.   To this we came later to add intelligenceleceived from sources of our own.   This summary is naturallv devised to meetIpat our Intelligence Department knows to be our special needs.    It hasowever attracted,the attention of the Service and other Government Depart-ents, which^at theiRown request,.have for some time been supplied with copiesit. -Recently,, moreover,.we have been asked to take over* the fortnightly reviewGerman propaganda for the War Cabinet, which was-formerly furnished by[20558] b2on
the Ministry of Information. It will thus be seen that we require an Intelligencestaff of some size, stronger indeed than our productive and translating staffscombined. Reading neutral newspapers naturally demands readers versed in a range of languages. I am glad to say, however, that, owing to their quality, Ihave not had to exceed the number of four senior and two junior experts, some ofwhom are also available for other work.A nglo-French Co-operation.I have already alluded to joint Anglo-French leaflets. They are, indeed, ,ipromising outcome of the excellent relations which exist between my own depart-ment and the French Propaganda authorities. Only last week I visited Paris inconnection with the work of the Joint Anglo-French Propaganda Council. on many sides, as well as from the specially informed. I heard of the influence ofGerman propaganda on both the French army and civilian population. british propaganda in France is not within my sphere, but I can think of few better ways of deterring enemy efforts to disintegrate the Entente than to show their authorsthat the direct result of this type of argument is to unite the propaganda, forcesof France and England. My French colleagues are alive to this fact, and I feelthat I can count on their assistance. I feel, also, that my co-operation with theFrench in propaganda against a common enemy may well tend to assimilate thewar policies of the two countries, and to promote both the spirit and fact of compromise.Co-operation with the Fighting Services.Since my last report I have held two meetings of my Services Committee,which have been attended by the Directors of the respective Service Intelligencesor their nominees. Each of them has led to useful conclusions, and to increasedco-ordination of propaganda with strategy.As a result of arrangements made at them, my service of military news for broadcasting has been valuably increased, and two specially effective broadcastson the sinking of the Graf von Spee have been delivered. In some respects these meetings have provided a common ground for discussion of propaganda aspectsof the war, which, I venture to believe, may have been scarcely less valuable tothe Services than they have been to my department. In view, moreover, of theinterest the Services take in the publicity and propaganda activities of theMinistry of Information in France and Neutral Countries, and of my ownrelationship with that department, I have invited the heads of its ForeignPublicity and News Departments to become members of the Committee. It maybe of interest to add that the whispering campaign, discussed by the Committeeand mentioned in my last report, is now in operation.Secret A ctiviti.es.Secret arrangements made by my Department in Neutral Countries have begun to bear fruit in the form of interesting reports. I have, of course,no intention of developing an extensive and redundant secret service of my own;but I have placed, or am arranging to place, a few well-chosen agents at pointsfrom which information of the kind my organisation particularly requires islikely to emerge from Germany.Refugees.During the last month I have continued my efforts to co-ordinate the refugeegroups in Great Britain so as to be able to take full advantage of such usefulinformation and advice as they have to give. I have also found certain individualrefugees of standing, both German and Austrian, who have helped me consider-ably. My method has been to put to a. carefully selected few a questionnaireembodying points of special difficulty, on which I believed that their views mightbe of value, and I have had useful replies. This, I believe, will probably be foundto be the most effective way of employing their knowledge of enemy conditions,which tends, in most cases, to rest on past knowledge rather than on recent news.I am, however, obtaining a certain amount of intelligence through emigrechannels, which has already proved valuable in providing matter for broad-casting, and will. I am convinced, increase in volume as time goes on.   The
establishment of the type of relationship I have sought has not been easy, and Ive certainly no reason to regret my cautious approaches to this particularoblem. .I ought, perhaps, to add that, in such relations as I have with refugees, I am&quot;thholding any encouragement to schemes for the establishment of a Germanvernment in Great Britain or to political intrigues of a sectional character ino-ard to the future of Germany.elntions with the Press.I have, since the meeting mentioned in my last report, kept in touch with theading newspaper proprietors of London and the Provinces, who are members ofv informal committee, and have had personal interviews with some of them. A11 meeting of the Committee has been arranged for the 3rd January, at whichintend to report upon the outstanding features of my Departments work.conclusion. -i find that I can look back on nearly four months of propaganda directedwards an enemy whose spirit has frequently been elated by victories claimed,t not yet depressed by any serious defeat.   Reviewing our efforts, I can findarcely a point of potential value which has not been employed.   Frequently, ase retorts of the enemy have shown, we have struck shrewdly.   Such reports,oreover, as are received from German sources indicate that we have only torsist along our present lines to secure ever-increasing results.   This is also theew of our French colleagues.   I am satisfied with my machine, which, I believe,capable of producing the propaganda the circumstances of the war require,am equally satisfied with a position in which I have the advantages of intimateitact with the Foreign Office and the Service Departments, and I am, indeed,ateful for the assistance they render me so willingly.   In one particular onlyve i reason for regret: It is that circumstances do not permit of a wider andpre copious dissemination of British propaganda by our aircraft.   I trust,wever, that increasing air resources and the coming of better weather willble this invaluable weapon to be employed on a larger scale.

</content>
</cab>
