<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/83/40 images: 416-423</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   &lt;0^ C4BINEI

   vaa. V CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street on

&lt;&apos;&apos;7THURSDAY 4 DECEMBER 1986

at 10.00 am X/sy&apos; PRESENT

^ The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP Prime Minister

The Rt Hon Viscount Whitelaw (fy) The Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St Marylebone Lord President of the Council Lord Chancellor

The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MThe Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP Secretary of State for Foreign and &lt;S/1 Chancellor of the Exchequer Commonwealth Affairs

/A The Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP /^VThe Rt Hon Peter Walker MP Secretary of State for the Home Departme^/Nsecretary of State for Energy

V    The Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MP ^V&apos;^^Rt Hon John Biffen MP Secretary of State for Wales Privy Seal

The Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP Tlrer^R^Hpn Norman Tebbit MP Secretary of State for Social Services Char  jrelJ^r of the Duchy of Lancaster

The Rt Hon Tom King MP The Rti^^^&apos;Nicholas Ridley MP Secretary of State for Northern Ireland Secreta  /d?r State for the Environment

The Rt Hon Lord Young of Graffham The Rt HorrKenneth Baker MP Secretary of State for Employment Secretary of State for Education and Science

The Rt Hon Kenneth Clarke QC MP The Rt Hon John/Macuregor MP Paymaster General Chief Secretary^x^rj&amp;eaury

The Rt Hon Malcolm Rifkind QC MP The Rt Hon Paul Cjygirri^gQMP Secretary of State for Scotland Secretary of State f^C^ffr^de and Industry

The Rt Hon John Moore MP Secretary of State for Transport

ALSO PRESENT

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury


   \4	SECRETARIAT v\		

&lt;	&apos;)/\ Mr D F Williamson siL/^ Mr C L G Mallaby		

	l//  \ Mr A J Langdon (Items 1 and &lt;s\^/s Mr M J Eland (Items 1 and ///\	2)	

		2)	

	CONTENTS		

tttem	Subject		Page

1.	PARLlAMEmi^RY AFFAIRS Debirce/&amp; the Need to Establish a Committee of Privy to Ov^K&gt;eg}Matters of National Security	Councillors	1

			1

	Debate on/pe  ence in the House of Lords		2

	Rate Support Grant 1987-88		2

|l	Stalker Case /^\ HOME AFFAIRS		2

	Flotation of Britis^Sas		3

	Teachers&apos; Pay, DutiesCdKw(^onditions of Service Acquired Immune Deficien^J^^  fcdrome		3

			3

3.	FOREIGN AFFAIRS		

	United States		4

	(s&apos; S\ North Atlantic Alliance s^SSS		4

	mm syri   		4

4.	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS &lt;(&lt;		

	V European Council		5

	Completing the Internal Market /s~^\		5

	%	i	5


   ARLIAMER^ii^ H The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House aFFAIRS^v/} of Commons in the following week and that, subject to the progress of /X^vbusiness, it was proposed that the House should rise for the Christmas vo^wdjournment on Friday 19 December until Monday 12 January.

m

Debate on	TH&amp;^E#ffl5TARY OF STATE FOR	THE HOME DEPARTMENT said that the debate the

the Need to	prev&lt;i^us/Jiay on the motion	tabled in the name of the leaders of	the

Establish a Liber^J/^*4) Social Democratic Parties to the effect that there was a Committee	need tS&apos;^j&amp;ablish a Committee of Privy Councillors to oversee matters of

of Privy	nationalC^^Srity, had passed off well and the motion had been defeated.

Councillors He had madfe it clear that in the debate the Government could not comment to Oversee on various&apos;^allegations made by members of the Opposition while the case Matters of	to prevent the publication	of the memoirs of a former member of	the

National	Security Service .^-Mr Peter	Wright, was still being heard by the

Security	Australian coureyC|^s far	as progress of that case itself was

concerned, the m4  $y  icus now was on proceedings in which the defence sought discovery o  ce)ntain British official documents. The Government had been granted	appeal to the Court of Appeal of New South

Wales against a rulitig/tfc^t the documents be discovered; and that hearing was expected	on 11 December 1986. If that court ruled

against the Crown then &lt;tt^jp*was the option of further appeal to the federal High Court of AustMm. If that option had to be invoked then a ruling from the High Courf^crauld not be expected until well into the Year.

THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up^r^sAort discussion, said that very careful consideration would hagiven to whether further statements should be made once tK^c^^e had been concluded. The principle which had been followed wy&quot;prtvious Governments of all political persuasions, that Ministex^[[  J     yld not comment on security matters was being gradually eroded aSd^^ich concession merely increaased the appetite for further disclosure, ^p^^principle in the Wright case was absolutely clear:	unauthorised disclosures by previous members of

the Security Service raised doubts about whether material entrusted to that service would remain secure, and this undermined the trust and confidence which was vital to its work. The mot*le of serving officers had been seriously damaged by the publicity giy^nV^o the various allegations of the past few years.

The Cabinet -

1. Took note, with approval, of the Prime Min4^^^s summing up of their discussion.


   THE LORD CHANCELLOR said that the debate on defence that had been held Deferin t^ie House of Lords on the previous day had included some excellent speeches, most notably by Lord Thorneycroft and by Lord Stewart of LordsyL^y^jA. Fulham. The latter had dissociated himself from his party&apos;s policy on defence and his speech was a striking illustration of the difference \\V&gt;^between the Labour Party of the present and that of the past.

%

Rate	Bf&amp;^a&amp;RETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that the distribution of

Support	bftJMiygrant dictated by the Local Government, Planning and Land Act

grant	198oC^^  ntinued to raise problems. The proposals for 1987-88 that he

1987-88	had o^Vginally put out to consultation had been received with hostility

by many shire county areas, and that situation was rendered even more difficult by th   availability of further data relevant to grant related expenditure th^t it would be legally unsafe for him to ignore. With the agreement of/vfieySub-Committee on Local Authority Expenditure (E(LA)) he had thereforVA. miMjjshed revised consultative proposals that moderated these effects se/f  nas was practicable under the present statutory machinery, thougn_JBu  ly.nghamshire, Berkshire, Northamptonshire and East Sussex would stiF^jrfieive less grant than in 1986-87 and then in his earlier consultativer/jjroposals. It was inevitable that there would be losers in such situa,M  l(s&gt;&apos;i\ and some authorities that had stood to do exceptionally well under^jidjfc earlier proposals would now have their gains very significantl^^d  ced. In particular, Birmingham, which would have got   60 milliw^njA^e grant than in 1986-87 under his earlier proposals, now stood to gefe^^Nmillion more than in 1986-87. He did not gainsay the difficulty	but decisions had to be taken on the

overall balance of the settl&amp;fcperat^ The very difficult distributional problems he had described wouTcl/p^radnue to face the Government until the present statutory machinerj^&apos;C/aa^nsp laced by the new structure outlined in the Green Paper &quot;Payi^i fp^ Local Government&quot;. Indeed, unless some very radical interim aooOTwere taken, the Rate Support Grant settlements in the years befo	new structure was in place

would get increasingly difficult as tner	effects of the moderating

devices that had been adopted fed throi^firti into the system.

Stalker Case THE PRIME MINISTER said that the question of crasts^Lncurred by those who were cleared under proceedings arising from theiSylJ  &amp;liessional life might require further study.	)J

The Cabinet -	6//)&apos;  S}

2. Took note.


   2. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR ENERGY said that the deadline for applications for shares in British Gas had expired the previous day.

Some 4-4i million applications had been received, the issue had been Flotdicoiyof	oversubscribed and it would be necessary to reduce the amounts available

BritisbS^i\ to overseas investors and the institutions to accommodate the smaller V-investor. There had been some suggestion that the number of \k^w/applications from small investors had been less than might have been C&apos;y/^wjected. Two possible explanations for this were that the general fall V&apos;jLjyAhare prices earlier that week might have put off some small

^ffvekfors and that the proximity of the share issue to Christmas had

the small investor had less money readily available. Even so :lear that an impressive number of small investors had come forvaunj^^hd in some parts of the country it appeared that as many as two family&apos;s in every five had applied for shares.

Teachers&apos;	THE SECRETARt/oF$TATE FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE said that the

Pay, Duties individual te^aSh^jSS^v unions were now establishing their members&apos; views, and	The Secondary Heads/Association and the Professional Association of

Conditions	Teachers had toIsZferaybhat they would be seeking variations in the

of Service	package developed JBurnham Committee and so there was a good

prospect that the u^^^^^ould not sustain a united front. The National Previous	Union of Teachers had^fS^ynj^d a campaign against the Teachers&apos; Pay	and

Reference:	Conditions Bill which th^^SJffenre presenting as an attack on union

CC(86) 39.1	negotiations rights. TR^^campaign would not have moved into full	gear

before the Bill left the&apos;Qgds^&apos;of Commons and therefore the main attack could be expected in the HculWO^ Lords. It was hoped that the Bill might start in the Lords on^2^J^uary 1987.

%

Acquired	THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL	said that there had been

Immune	discussions with the World Health OrgM^syAion about Acquired Immune

Deficiency Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS). WHO estirfiareathat there were about 100,000 Syndrome	cases of AIDS in the world at the presefcre time and that about five to

ten million people might have been infected. It was possible that there Previous	would be about three million deaths within five years, of which a

Reference:	substantial number would be in Afria. In the IMited States of America

CC(86) 38.2 there might be about 170,000 deaths over five	In Europe there

were about 4,000 cases so far and there might	000 deaths over

about three years. It was clear that public concdxrT&apos;about this serious issue would continue to increase.

The Cabinet -

Took note.


   IfOREIG^^X 3* THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the United States IaFFAIRSv^vs^ President had announced that there would be an investigation by

I ___ -/^^independent Counsel into the diversion to the Contra rebels in Nicaragua

lunited St  fie*)pf funds generated by United States arms sales to Iran. No less than

\^%4&gt;ght Congressional committees were competing to investigate the matter.     Previous	President had appointed Mr Frank Carlucci, a man of wide experience,

iReference:	&apos;^  /$is National Security Adviser in succession to Vice Admiral John

ICC(86) 39.2	v&lt;5yLpd&amp;xter. The United Kingdom should continue to reaffirm its policy

oiC&apos;tfo^tlages and terrorism, as well as arms sales - policies which should be ^  n^wi the light of recent developments in Washington to be the right^Hies- This should be done in a way which would not undermine the positrSo^i the United States President.

The LeadMl of the Opposition, Mr Neil Kinnock, was visiting the United States. Iks attempt to advocate the defence policies of the Labour Party appeared to be evoking little response. In discussion it was noted that Mr Kinnock appeared not to be observing the convention that politicians shojtQrdSkbandon party rivalry when they were outside this country, a poin&apos;^kjiftich had been noticed by the media. It appeared that no Congressman, ReiptTBljLcan or Democrat, in the United States had supported Mr Kinnoqk&apos;Jj^&apos;^iews on nuclear weapons.

%

I North	THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWE^TMS^CRETARY said that the Defence Policy

I Atlantic	Committee of the North Atrag^^NTreaty Organisation was meeting that day

I Alliance	and the North Atlantic Counod  b5wi  uld meet the following week. It would

be important to ensure that C^e^olnmuniqu^s on these meetings included the points made by the Prime fmuikir in her statement following her meeting with the United States Rres^Vnt at Camp David on 15 November. The chances of achieving this wou#rb^greater in the case of the North Atlantic Council, where France wouLd^foe^participating.

1

I Syria	THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that in a trial in Berlin

ending on 26 November, Mr Ahmed Hasi had been convicted of planting a I Previous	bomb in the premises of the German-Arab FrienjMfTM   Society in West

I Reference:	Berlin and had been sentences to 14 years&apos; imp^spwnent. His accomplice

I CC(86) 37.3	had received 13 years. Mr Hasi was a brother of^lfirSNezar Hindawi, who

had recently been convicted in the English courDq^&amp;f^Sattempting to place a bomb on a El Al flight from Heathrow. Tha^j^ejrnment of the Federal Republic of Germany had reacted effeetively^vJ^Knouncing on 27 November that there would be no early replacement^efi^cwe Federal German Ambassador to Syria, that three members of the SmalJ Embassy in Bonn must leave the country, that there would be striccviwSciprocity of staffing of military attaches&apos; offices, that bilateral aiit&gt;ierftld be banned and that the Federal Republic would recognise only ^  &quot;riah diplomatic and ordinary passports, not service ones. Other^Ejriiwean countries and the United States had made statements in supporfy^id^this Federal German reaction. The Western allies in Berlin had taweii^c^ion


        yy*\ to expel from Berlin members of the Syrian Embassy in East Berlin. These reactions amounted to useful additional pressure on Syria in the light ^X^\of its support for terrorism.

The Cabinet -

wt

COMMUNITY	4. THlf-NSi&amp;ME MINISTER said that the European Council on 5-6 December

AFFAIRS	would be^Ae^iing with	relatively uncontroversial issues in the field	of

__	business &apos;srod jobs and	of safeguarding the open society. It was

European	regrettable that some	press comment found the absence of controversy	a

Council	matter for criticism.	In discussion it was said that the initiative	on

employment was likely to be endorsed but not without opposition from some interests	the Community.

%&gt;

Completing THE SECRETARY OF STATBC^R^TRADE AND INDUSTRY said that the Internal the Internal	Market Council on 1 De^eiSt^xhad agreed on nine out of the thirteen

Market	measures on which the Prim^Kjnister had invited other Heads of

Government to withdraw therfar raserves. Two more measures were likely to go through quickly. The Tetuajprthz two might be achieved by the end of the year. In discussion it &lt;*k^p  inted out that the United Kingdom Presidency had already made f afcyM   /eater progress than its predecessors in reaching agreement on measur^y/^OAppen up the internal market.

m

Transport	THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TRANSPORT r^M^ied that the last Transport

Council had made good progress on two ex^ments - access and capacity -which were important for the progressive&apos;T.iberalisation of aviation.

The Council had also made progress but had finally been stalled on the conditions applicable to lower fares. His recep-fe^discussions with Ministers of other member states had confirmed&apos;/tha\ consumer pressures were beginning to be felt more widely but thar^soja^member states were not yet willing to change their basic position onf fanes. In these circumstances there was a fine balance to be drawn__a^the next Transport Council. If the aviation package were not raised, ^nj^Wvances already made would slip back but, on the other hand, it was	to avoid

any public and press reaction that the discussion had^oe^ni^ failure.

He proposed that the aviation package should be on the	i; that he

should seek to establish conclusions which held the posi^aon/on access and capacity; and that the discussion on fares should lead    conclusion that the issues must continue to be pursued. H^fi^i^in mind that he might thereafter call, if it seemed appropriate, a nwp^Wgof the Chairmen and chief executives of airlines concerned, whicnm  gwt draw attention to the consequences of action in the European Ccrfii^^  ^


   \ Justice if the aviation package were not settled. At the next Transport V Council he had good hopes that some useful measures on shipping, but not /^\the proposal on cabotage, would be agreed.

The Cabinet -

%

Cabinet Office

4 December 1986



</content>
</cab>
