<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/219/0 images: 215-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT  IS JTHtL   g^g^^0 QoJCOPY NO.         AGRICULTURAL LAND  (UTILISATION) BI1L.             POSITION OF AGRICULTURAL LABOURERS.   Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.     1.   In my memorandum to the Cabinet of the 9th December (C.P.415(30)) I drew attention to a position that was likely to arise during the Committee stage of the Land Bill with regard to a proposal discussed with me by the Liberals, the effect of which would have been to extend the same opportunities to agricultural labourers as to the unemployed as regards unemployed small holdings. The question was considered by the Cabinet on December .10th and it was agreed (Cab. 72.(30) Conclusion 2 -     &quot;That the Small-holdings part of their Agricujiuaral     Policy had been devised in the interests of the unemployed,     and that the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries, in     dealing with the matter in the Parliamentary Committee,     should adhere to this attitude and should emphasise the     fact  that unemployed agricultural workers are eligible     for small holdings&quot;. 2.   The Clause as put down by the Liberals was as follows :-        &quot;The Minister shall have power to provide     a small holding for an applicant who is an     agricultural worker on the same conditions as are     set out in section six of this Act and to extend to     such  applicant the same facilities as are authorised                      -     by that section;       -  Provided that the condition* set out in paragraph     (a) of subsection (i) of that section shall not apply     in respect of such applicant.&quot;             *  That the person is unemployed and unable to                    obtain suitable employment.Another clause to the same effect was put down by the Tories.
      3.  Knowing that a considerable number of our members were f Q.  very  uncomfortable about it I sent round a special private whip  the  day before the clause was taken on December 16th.   In the sequel, however, I found that with one exception the whole of our Party on the Committee, GO far as our Whips could ascertain, could not bring themselves to vote against the clause as it stood.   I took  the view of my colleagues on the Bench - the Secretary for Scotland, Under-Secfetary,  Chancellor of the Duchy, Attorney- General, and Lord Advocate - and they were unanimously of opinion  that I could not put our people, who included, I think, all ourmembers from agricultural constituencies, in the position of voting - if they did vote - directly against the agriculturalworker,   with its obvious consequences in the constituencies.There would have been these six official members and perhaps one other in a minority that would have advertised the position toall the country.     4.    In the circumstances  as they had developed, I had totake upon myself the  responsibility of doing the best I could andI consulted all my colleagues on the Bench,  who were.unanimouslyof opinion that I could not do  more than get the greatest possiblefreedom of action for myself and the Government.  I thereforedeliberately confined myself to an emphatic  statement of ourobjections to the clause and claimed complete freedom for safeguardsand limitations on Report.   I had to consider not merely theimmediate situation,  but the position which  we should have to faceon Report,  and to provide against either a defeat on the floor ofthe House or a humiliating  surrender.   Any  other attitude would merely have drawn attention to  our predicament without having anyeffect whatever on the result so far as the  Bill is concerned.  The  consequence v/as that what was really a most embarrassing Governmentdefeat passed practically unnoticed by the Press.  5.   In the statement I made to the Committee I made it abundantlyplain that  notwithstanding this amendment we could not   /                                -2-
 accept- the responsibility of dislocating the  whole  economy of the countryside  and that I must be  free  to act accordingly.      60  The  position which has resulted is most unsatisfactory5 for these reasons:-          In the  first place, the clause  will  make the employed agricultural  labourer a specially favoured  classs by giving him at State  expense, the exceptional privilege of working capital and temporary maintenance allowances,  which the Government Bill conceded to the unemployed alone, as an  exceptional concession because of their  great need.          In the  second place, the administrative consequences will be serious.    There might be almost an avalanche of applications  from employed labourers (of whom there are  some 800s000 in Great  Britain)  for &quot;unemployed&quot;  holdings, with advances of working capital  plus temporary maintenance allowances, with the result that  as  the total expenditure on this type of holding has, on financial grounds,  been definitely  limited  from  the start, by agreement  between  me and the Chancellor  of the Exchequer,  most of the  applicants will be  disappointed and  will find themselves on a long  waiting list for  years  to  come.   Meanwhile, the unemployed -  in whose  case  alone  the exceptional concession was granted by the Government   -  will be deprived of a considerable proportion of  the total  money  allotted for  &quot;unemployed&quot;  holdings. The  agreed provision for these  holdings  is  not  exceeding  950,000 in 1931, and  not  exceeding  2,600,000 in the following year  (covering about 2,500 holdings a year).    I  understand that&apos;, in view of the serious Budget position,  the Chancellor of  the Exchequer will be unable to  increase&apos; the allocation  in order  toprovide for employed labourers.         It is recognised however that  within the financial limits agreed there must be some elasticity as to the types of holdings to be provided for agricultural workers,  which should necessarilynot be made to conform to the very limited type contemplated fc-jp
unemployed persons, inasmuch as it would he uneconomic toprovide this type of holding for agricultural workers whoseexperience, especially in some districts, would point to the wisdom of providing a different type.     70    Notwithstanding the unsatisfactory position, after careful consideration and consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer, I have come to the conclusion that the only practicalcourse open to us is to leave the clause as it stands, as it is entirely permissive, and to refrain from putting down limitingamendments which would immediately &quot;be advertised as a handicap onthe agricultural labourer.   It is also very unlikely that wecould carry such amendments if they were moved;  nors a fortiori5could, we carry the rejection of the clause.          The only thing to do, therefore, In my opinion, is to announce, on the Third Reading of the Bill, that the government propose to accept the clause unaltered, but to add a statement asto the realities of the position, with regard to the physical andother difficulties in providing large numbers of small holdingsquickly, so as to avoid raising false hopes.   I am emphaticallyof opinion that it would be a mistake to mention any figurespublicly at the present tine.   The figures given above arestrictly confidential, and  should not be mentioned to anyone.(Intld.)    G.A.Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries   20th January, 1931c

</content>
</cab>
