<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/219/0 images: 258-262</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1931.SECRET.CP.  27 (31).                                  CABINET.GENERAL CONTROL OF BRITISH RELATIONS  WITH  TERRITORIES                         IN THE MIDDLE EAST.         MEMORANDUM  BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE  COLONIES.     AT the meeting of the Cabinet on the 20th January reference was made to theReport of the Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence on the general control of British  relations  with  territories in  the Middle East,  in which was discussed the possibility of focussing in the Foreign Office the general control of ourrelations with the  whole  of  the territories  in  the Middle East in which we are interested.  It was decided that the matter should be placed on the  Agenda of theCabinet after the return of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs  from Geneva.     On the 23rd July, 1930, the Cabinet considered the above-mentioned report and decided in favour of the  transfer  to  the Foreign Office of responsibility for HisMajesty&apos;s Governments relations with Iraq &quot; when Iraq is admitted to the Leagueof Nations  in  1932.&quot;   This decision left unchanged the position as  regardsresponsibility for affairs in other middle eastern territories.     The possibility  of the transfer, to the Foreign Office of the general control ofHis Majesty&apos;s Governments relations  with those parts of the Middle East which atpresent fall within the sphere of the Colonial Office is dealt with in Part II of theReport already1 referred to, and it may be noted that this part of the Report was notsigned by the representatives on the Sub-Committee of the Foreign  Office, the IndiaOffice or the Colonial Office.   The arguments in opposition to such a transfer werecontained in paragraph 5 of the Report, and these, it is understood, represented the considered views of the Foreign Office.    For convenience of reference they are quoted below :          &apos;r (a)  Administration  is not  the business of the Foreign Office, and its    attempts to  conduct it  in the past  have generally been attended by failure.  An    overiuhelming case  should be  established before the administration  of any    further territory should be entrusted to it.        (b)  The outlook, training and temperament of administrators  and diplomats    are essentially different.   The  Foreign Office does not produce administrators,    and when it requires them, has to borrow from other branches of Government    service.   On more  than  one  occasion in  recent years the qualifications of    Governors  thus  recruited  have been questionable.   Yet,  in these  Mandated    Territories,  though diplomatic abilities may be of importance, the quality of the    administration is the criterion  by which world opinion will judge the  success    or failure of the  Mandatory Power.        (c) The Sudan is  under Foreign Office  control solely  because the  Con-    dominium with  Egypt makes it impossible  to  place the territory under the    control of any other Department.  That it should have been administered uith    some success is  due  to  peculiar and exceptional circumstances.   Firstly, the    Sudan is practically  isolated in the middle  of the continent and removed from    external influences and distractions,  so that  all problems of government are    considerably simplified.   Secondly, it has been possible to endow the country    with an  efficient staff of numerous carefully selected Englishmen, and the    administration,  though good, is very expensive.   Finally, and resulting from    this, the  amount  of   administrative  control  exercised  from-  London  is   infinitesimally small.&quot;      [5003]34Copy No.
2   ; !   The arguments in favour of a transfer are  summarised as follows  in Part II  of the Report:                                           &amp;)U\v .&apos;!o&apos;i   .i;  \M!           &quot;(a)     iAe1  case of both Iraq and Trans Jordan, our position is that of       advisers  to  the local  Governments:  we are  not directly administering  the       territories.  In regard to Palestine, toe are,  it is true, directly responsible for       the government of the country.   The  burden of administration teas heavy at       first, as was natural in a country which had just emerged from conditions of       war, and in which an entirely new administrative machine had to be set vp. It       still remains heavy; but it might  have been relaxed in course of time, as the new       regime became more stabilised, had it not been for the unhappy events of August       last.   These events have undoubtedly caused a serious set-back, the permanent       effects of which can hardly be gauged at present.           (b)  The special business of the Colonial Office is undoubtedly administra-       tion.  But, in the first place, the  functions of  His Majesty&apos;s Government in       two out of the three countries under consideration are, as stated above, advisory       rather than administrative.  Secondly,  the Colonial Office, if their administra-       tion is to be effective,  should be permitted to administer by their own methods,       and along tried and proved lines.   This they are frequently precluded from       doing  by international complications arising  out of the mandatory status of the       countries in question.  Asa result, the advantages of Colonial Office control are       to some extent neutralised.&quot;       Taking these two arguments together, the following comments may be made :        So far as can be foreseen, the administrative work in connection with Palestine  is likely to increase in importance and complexity for some years to come.  Such  increase may be expected as a natural consequence not only of the general progress  of the country, which  is still at an early stage of development  on modern lines, but  especially in view of important reports which have recently been issued in connection  with Palestine, viz.,  the  Reports  of  the Shaw  Commission  on  the Palestine  disturbances of August 1929  and the steps necessary to avoid  a recurrence; of  Sir John Hope-Simpson on Immigration,  Land  Settlement and  Development; of  Mr.  C. F. Strickland on the economic position of the Fellahin  and  the organisation  of Co-operative Societies;  of Sir H. Dowbiggin on the  Palestine Police Force.  Another important report will be  that of the Commission, consisting of  Sir Samuel  0&apos;Donnell  and Mr. Brittain of the  Treasury, recently appointed to examine the  whole administration  of Palestine and Trans-Jordan from the point  of  view of  economy and efficiency.  All these enquiries are bound to result in a mass of detailed  work, almost entirely of  an administrative character, e.g., the setting up  of a  Development  Commission  and  the  working out,  in close consultation with  the  Treasury, of schemes of development to be financed from the  proposed  guaranteed  Loan.  Moreover, the  reimposition of strict Treasury control  of Palestine finances  will  considerably  add to  the body  of  administrative work  of the  Department  concerned,  and  will  further  eliminate  the possibility of  leaving  the  High  Commissioner a free hand on Sudan lines.       Another important problem which  is likely to add, at  any rate temporarily, to  the work of the Department responsible for Palestine, is the proposed creation of a  Legislative Council, a matter calling for delicate negotiation  and appreciation ofI local conditions in Palestine.    It is true that Palestine is differentiated from most of the territories for whichthe Colonial Office is responsible by being a mandated territory, but the responsibilityfor all territories administered under mandate by Plis Majesty&apos;s Government in theLnited Kingdom at  present rests with the Colonial Office.   There would be obviousinconveniences attaching to an arrangement  whereby some mandated territories wereadministered by the Foreign Office and the  remainder by the  Colonial Office, whereco-ordinating machinery already exists.&apos;    It may, moreover, be pointed out that Trans-Jordan is included within the scopeof the Palestine Mandate, and His Majesty&apos;s  Government  are as fully responsible to the Permanent Mandates Commission and the League Council for Trans-Jordanas for Palestine, the Arab Government set up in Trans-Jordan  being subject, asregards its independence, to the general limitations imposed by the Mandate.
 ) Ci .11/. / 3toi t-j i. &apos;   -While Palestine  is  differentiated  by the Mandate  system from  most other territories for which the  Colonial Office is responsible, yet it has been the policy of successive Secretaries of  State for the Colonies to bring it, for  practical purposes, within the Colonial framework.   This is a matter of considerable importance as regards the European personnel of the Administration.   New recruits are now appointed to the  Colonial  Service  as  a single unit.    This  tendency to  inter- changeability is in accordance with the views of the last Colonial Office Conference and with the recommendations of the Report of the Committee, presided over by Sir Warren Fisher, on the system of appointment in the Colonial Office  and the Colonial Service.   It would be unfortunate  if Palestine were withdrawn from the scope of the imifiecfXaloniaT Service^, This would seriously prejudice the- prospects of  promotiori&quot;by transfer of officers  now  serving.   It would also remove from the Service a territory which has special amenities and attractions for a number of officers serving elsewhere, and would thus weaken  the framework of the  Service. Further, the problem of recruitment would be made more difficult by the  withdrawal of the prospect of transfer to any part of the Colonial Empire, and  by the fact that recruits would not be drawn from so wide a field.    Under  the  present system,  Palestine  participates,  and would do so  to  an increasing extent in the future if it remained under the Colonial Office, in the benefits to be derived from various schemes  of  co-ordination,  especially in  the spheres of agricultural and other technical services; and the experience of the technical advisers to the Secretary of State on various subjects such as medicine, agriculture, veterinary science, finance,  engineering, education, is placed at the disposal  of the Palestine Administration.         &quot; (c) Under  present arrangements a  situation  has grown up in,  which    different Departments of State are apt to find themselves ranged on the side of    rival Arab chieftains:  the Colonial Office on the side of the Sharifian family,    King Feisal  and A mir A bdullah; the Foreign  Office  and India Office  on that    of Ion Saud.  Unification of control would enable the Department dealing with    the problem to take a more comprehensive vieto  of the whole matter, and  would    tend to promote a more consistent policy.&quot;    This can hardly be regarded as a serious consideration.    The rivalry  which undoubtedly  exists is that  between the Amir  Abdullah  and  Ibn  Saud, and not between the&quot; Foreign Office or India Office and the Colonial Office.  There is no reason to suppose that this rivalry would be lessened  as  a result  of a  transfer of responsibility from the Colonial Office to the Foreign Office.  Such  a transfer  might even lead to misunderstanding on the part of the Amir Abdullah,  as to the degreeof his independence vis-a-vis His Majesty&apos;s Government, with possible unfortunate results.  On  the other hand, the close personal touch which is maintained by  the Colonial Office with both the Foreign Office and the  India Office should  tend to eliminate any serious cause  of friction or inconsistency in action.    It may be noted that the Arab Press in Palestine has already  drawn attentionto the alleged hope of the Jews for a transfer of responsibility for Palestine from the Colonial Office to  the Foreign  Office.  It is by  no means unlikely that such a transfer, if it took place in the  near future, would be exploited by various Arab leaders who are on  the lookout for any means to gain their special ends.   There are two ways in which  such a transfer might be exploited :i -    (1) By inciting disaffection on the ground that it foreshadowed the  destruction           of the hopes  which have recently arisen among  the  Arabs that His           Majesty&apos;s Government recognise  and intend to do what is  possible- to           remedy their grievances.    (2) By claiming that it means an important change in the status of Palestine.    This might stimulate  agitation for wider powers of self-government than wouldbe compatible with the mandatory responsibility of His Majesty&apos;s Government.         &quot; (d) It  is understood that Iraq is likely to be admitted to the League of    Nations.in 1932, in lohich case  the responsibility for our relations with that    country will presumably have, ostensibly, in any case, to be transferred:from the    Colonial Office to  the Foreign Office.&quot;                  -        ;  ;i - : &apos;A\  &apos;  This point is disposed of by the decision of the Cabinet in regard to Iraq. -%
&apos;     While Palestine is differentiated by.the  Mandate system  from most other territories for which the Colonial Office is responsible, yet it has been the policy of successive Secretaries of State for the Colonies to bring it, for practical  purposes,within the Colonial framework.   This is a matter of  considerable  importance asregards the European  personnel  of the  Administration.   New  recruits are nowappointed to  the Colonial Service as a single  unit.   This tendency  to  inter-changeability is in accordance with the views of the last Colonial Office Conferenceand  with  the  recommendations of the Report of  the Committee, presided over bySir Warren Fisher, on the system of appointment in the Colonial  Office and theColonial Service.  It would be unfortunate if Palestine were  withdrawn  from thescope of the rnhfiecTColonial Service^  This would seriously prejudice the  prospectsoT promotion&quot;by  transter of officers now  serving.  It would also remove  from theService  a  territory which  has special amenities and attractions for a number ofofficers serving elsewhere,  and would  thus weaken  the  framework of  the Service.Further, the problem of recruitment would be made more difficult by the withdrawalof the prospect of transfer  to any part of  the Colonial Empire, and by the  fact thatrecruits would not be drawn from so wide  a field.    Under the present system,  Palestine  participates, and  would do  so  to  an increasing extent in the future if it remained under the Colonial Office, in the benefits to be derived  from various schemes of co-ordination, especially in the spheres ofagricultural and other technical services; and the experience of the technical advisers to the Secretary of State on various subjects such as medicine, agriculture, veterinaryscience,  finance, engineering, education, is placed at the disposal of the  PalestineAdministration.        &quot; (c)   Under present arrangements a  situation has  grown vu/p  in  which    different Departments  of State are apt to find themselves ranged on the side of    rival Arab chieftains: the Colonial Office on the side of the Sharifian family,    King  Feisal  and Amir Abdullah; the Foreign Office and  India  Office on that    of Ibn Saud.  Unification of control would enable the Department dealing with    the  problem to take a more comprehensive view of the whole matter, and would    tend to promote a  more consistent policy.&quot;    This can hardly be regarded as  a serious  consideration.   The  rivalry  wThichundoubtedly  exists  is  that between  the Amir  Abdullah  and Ibn Saud, andnot between the&quot; Foreign Office  or India Office and the Colonial Office.  There is noreason to suppose that  this rivalry would be lessened as a result of a transfer ofresponsibility from the Colonial Office  to the Foreign Office.  Such a transfer might even  lead to misunderstanding on the part of the Amir  Abdullah, as to the degreeof his independence vis-a-vis His Majesty&apos;s Government, with possible unfortunate results.  On the other  hand, the close personal touch which  is maintained by theColonial Office with both the  Foreign Office and the India  Office should tend to eliminate any serious cause of friction or  inconsistency in action.    It may be noted that the Arab Press in Palestine has already drawn  attentionto the alleged hope of the Jews for a transfer of responsibility for Palestine fromthe Colonial Office to the Foreign Office.   It is by  no means  unlikely that such a transfer, if it took place in the  near  future, would be  exploited by various Arableaders who are on the  lookout  for any means to gain their special ends.  There aretwo ways in which such a transfer might be exploited   -    (1) By inciting disaffection on the ground that it foreshadowed the destruction          of  the hopes which have  recently  arisen among  the Arabs  that His          Majesty&apos;s Government recognise  and intend to do what  is possible- to          remedy their grievances.    (2)  By claiming that it means an  important change in the status of  Palestine.    This might stimulate agitation for wider powers of self-government than wouldhe compatible with the mandatory responsibility of His  Majesty&apos;s Government.        &quot; (d)  It  is understood that Iraq  is likely to be  admitted to  the League of    Nations in 1932, in which case the  responsibility for our relations  with that    country will presumably have, ostensibly, in any case, to be transferred from the    Colonial Office to.the Foreign Office.&quot;                .      nvjiifuri iThis point is disposed of by the decision of the Cabinet in regard&apos;to Iraq.
    &quot; (e) With  regard   to  the  argument  that  Foreign  Office  attempts at administration have been unsuccessful in the past, we assume that reference is to such places as Uganda and other Protectorates.  In regard to this, we thinkit fair to point out that the Foreign Office had to discharge the  difficult role ofdealing with these areas in the pioneer stage; and that their successors have atleast had the advantage of building upon the foundations which they had laid.Moreover, the selection of personnel  for administering any such areas on  the spot is not in the least  confined to officers of the Foreign Office or diplomatic service; the field of choice alike for  Governors and their subordinates shouldnot be artificially limited, though  the natural expectation would to find men ofthe right experience largely from  the Overseas, Colonial. Indian, and SudaneseServices.&quot;    This argument is partly discounted  by  the comments made on Arguments (a)and (b) above.   Ft may, however, be added that the Personnel Department of theColonial Office  contains officers of long experience and special  training  in the selection of candidate^ for the Colonial Service.  Palestine, if it remains under theColonial Office, stands to benefit by their experience on  an equal footing with other colonial Office territories.    In conclusion,  it may be remarked that the  Middle  East  Department of theColonial Office was set up in March 1921 after a very full consideration of the wholequestion by a Committee appointed by the Cabinet, and the whole organisation ofthe Colonial Office is now based  on the inclusion of a Middle East  Department.  Inmy opinion, most of the difficulties of administering Palestine and Trans-Jordan are inherent, and will persist,  no matter what Minister or what Department bears theresponsibility.Colonial Office, January 31, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
