<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/182/0 images: 194-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ttis DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY gCF&apos; jftirflg felESTYfS GOVBRNMENT.ST SECRET 77394(26)^ AwnTRADE    UNION   LEGISLATION.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.1.     I feel some misgivings as to the position in whioh the Unionist party and the Government at present find themselves in relation to the Trade Union movement.    There is hardly a speech made by a member of the Government which touches on the subject, but contains professions of belief in the Importance, the value, the necessity, or at the lowest the inevitableness of trade unions in the industrial world. No doubt we confine these pavegyrics of their usefulness to the occasions when they confine, themselves to their proper sphere.     And we drop a tear over the frequency with which they exceed their real function.     But we pay the tribute to the principle all the same,2. The real point which we have to decide is this.Do we wish to attack Trade Unions as such or do we not? For example, the major part of the outcry against the political levy is not motived by a burning Indignation for the trade unionist^ who is forced to subscribe to the furtherance of political principles which he abhors.    It is based on a desire to hit the Socialist party through their pocket and it uses the comparatively small proportion Of cases of Injustice in respect of the political levy as a smokescreen under which to make the attack.     What I sxibmit is that at least we should not delude ourselves as to our intentions, as such self-delusion is a most fatal cause of bad judgment as to the action to be taken.
3.      There has been a marked trend of the Trade Union movement in recent years towards political action. The pernicious doctrine of class war, and the activities of the minority movement^ are helping to push it in that direction, and should he combated by all legitimate means.      I doubt whether the great bulk of the rank and file are yet seriously affected, but at the same time, it is a mistake to suppose that the average trade unionist regards his trade union as an instrument of oppression or his officials as arbitrary tyrants.      There is not in fact any substantial reason why he should He knows only too well that on balance, however hard the stu*e may pinch at times, he would now and in the future be far worse off with no or with weak trade unions than under the present regime.      Even if the grievances of individuals were in fact or were believed to be, much more serious than they are, the sentiment of trade union loyalty is a force of enormous strength.     iSven the minersr leaders have not yet impaired it.      The alleged persecution of individual members outside the mining districts is known by the rank and file, as well as by the officials, to be in substance so trifling, that they suspect the motives of Conservative or liberal champions of the oppressed trade unionist.4.     Under these circumstances, what should be our action?   I am quite convinced that, if in fact we sot out to attack Trade Unions, we may delude ourselves into the belief that we are really only acting for their good andt their best friends, but we shall not delude others.     The attempt v/ill without any doubt be seen through.     Trade Unionists, Conservative as well as literal or labour, are, with the exception of a small
small minority, primarily Trade Unionists and not politicians. They will believe and be right in believing that political speakers, who are so solicitous for the non-labour trade unionist who has to contract out of the political levy, are less concerned with the principle of freedom of thought than with the income which the Labour Party draws from the Unions. They will say and be right in saying that most of the members who take up the cause of the trade unionist victimized in the General Strike are grasping a plausible pretext for attacking the autonomy of the union.    If this be so, the alteration of the law concerning the political levy will be a boomerang that will Inflict more hurt on the attackers than the object of attack.   Further, by our action, we shall consolidate the Trade unions and the Labour Party and play directly into the hands of the Extremists.5. Trade Union organisation and administration is in need of reform.   Reform from within is the only proper course in some respects.    In others it is not and would also be a long business.    In ray view the policy of the Conservative party towards trade unionism should be in substance, and not merely in profession, constructive and not vindictive.    It should be made capable of being appreciated by the rank and file, not perhaps at first blush but at any rate on reflection, as designed to help the unions to build themselves up and to improve their internal administrationD    Some element of Coercion, or of apparent coercion, is inevitable in any-eg-LSlative proposals, but it ought to be as small as possible, and it ought to be presented with as much regard as possible to their deep-seated, if unreasonable,  susceptibilities.    If we
can adopt, and can shew convincingly that we have adoptedi a policy, which is neither hostile nor avoidably coercive, but is designed to help trade unions so to organise themselves that they can conduct a consistent and dignified policy compatible with the interests of other classes and the State, we may be able to avoid the danger of pushing the rank and file wholly into -fehe arms of the Socialist party.(Intd)    A.S.-M.Ministry of Labour. 22nd November, 1926.

</content>
</cab>
