<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/182/0 images: 358-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOOUMEHT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS, 3RITANNIQ MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET. . COPY NO.   SOCP. 412  (26)CABINET.GOVERNMENT COAL PURCHASES.Memora.nd.Tjia by the President of the Board of Trade.I think my colleagues will be interested to have a short account of the Government dealing in foreign coal during the strike.        I therefore circulate the attached Memorandum.I am sure the Cabinet will agree that we are greatly indebted to Sir John Hindley for his able handling of this business and for his untiring work through seven arduous months.(Intld.) P. QrL.   .Board of Trade,10th December,  1926.
-1-9th December, 1926.To provide fuel for essential services and,- in particular, for the smaller public utility undertakings and domestic consumers, who were not likely to import foreign coal, the Cabinet, after the strike had been in progress for two months, authorised the purchase by the Mines Department of coal from the United States of America and the Continent.   The first authorisation was given on 2nd June 1926, and further authorisations were given on various dates up to the 5feh October.    The sum of  3,000,000 was voted by Parliament for the purpose, to be used as a revolving credit.The total of the amounts authorised from time to time is 2,800,000 tons.      The total bought was about 2,500,000 tons (roughly 1,800,000 from the United States of America and 700,000 from the Continent, chiefly from Upper Silesia).   No useful purpose would have been served by buying the last 300,000 tons authorised, as the shortage of supplies both in the United States and on the Continent, was then so aoute that all available quantities were already being bought for Britain by private importers, and any at temp jj by the Government to buy would merely have increased the price without increasing the supply.The whole of the coal bought, with the exception of about 6,000 tons in store, has now been disposed of by distribution in detail, sale in bulk and cancellation.Buying and selling has been done under the direction.of a small Departmental Committee with Sir John Hindley in the Chair.     Three firms of factors actually bought the coal, operating in different fields and with different sellers, while a fourth firm did the whole of the chartering for conveyance of the American purchases.
These arrangements were very successful in keeping 284 down prices for coal and ships up to September, when the gradual exhaustion of stocks, combined with the approach of winter, led to a very large increase in freight rates and to some increase, though a surprisingly small one, in the price of coal.    In short, by September the surplus of world supply of coal that existed in April, 1926, had become a deficiency.    In October this deficiency became so marked that &quot;panic&quot; buying, especially by the Railways, forced up prices of ooal and of sea-freight to extravagant figures, and the end of the stoppage relieved a situation that was fast becoming desperate.The Government operations have required constant watch-fulness.   We were buying not for a known consumer who took the risk, but as an insurance against breakdown of the smaller essential services.    We had therefore, so far as we could, to seize the most favourable moments for buying coal and chartering ships but at the same time to have regard to the prospects of disposing of the coal when received, which, in the case of American ooal, was after an interval of two months or more from the date of ordering.The steady arrival and distribution of Government cargoes, at prices below the current prices of similar foreign . coal has not only been of great value in meeting urgent needs but has had also an effect in steadying prices.    The principle followed has been to sell the Government coal just below the market prices, so as to steady prices without discouraging the private importer by underselling him too heavily.The operations have involved two periods of liquidation of ooal on order or in transit in addition to the steady distribution of coal arriving.    The first of these was approved and carried out in July, in view of large private arrivals for August and falling-off in demand for Government coal.    The liquidation of about 400,000 tons was effected on
satisfactory terms.   The second was approved on the 12th November, in view of the prospect of an early end of the strike, and by the 2nd December some 600.000 tons had been sold or cancelled.    Loss was inevitably incurred in respect of the cargoes to arrive in December, but by proceeding with the liquidation before other large buyers grasped the position the loss has been minimised.    The course of prices in the last week and the efforts now being made to dispose of foreign purchases by other buyers afford a clear justification of the prompt disposal of the Government coal.The operation as a whole should show a profit, but it will not for some time be possible to give definite figures, as many claims affecting large quantities of coal have siill to be settled.    That the very heavy loss foretold at the beginning of the transaction has not been incurred is due to our leaving the market, for the reason already indicated, after the first week in October.    Had we continued buying for arrival at the rate of 200,000 tons a week the losses would have been very heavy, amounting to as much as  2 a ton on American ooal.Average f.o.b. prices of coal and freights and selling prices have been approximately as follows:--	i Purchase	Average price of coal.		1    Average cost of freight.		Average selling price.		American.	Oontl.	American.	Oontl:	American &apos; Gontl.1 1 )f. i. .1. &apos;t. ... &apos;-	1st &amp; 2nd 3rd. 4th 5th 6th 7th 8th 9th 10th	19/-20/-20/-20/6 20/6 20/6 21/-22/-30/-	28/-29/-32/6 33/3 34/-39/-42/-	14/-15/1 14/8 16/5 18/2 19/3 23/6 28/-32/-	4/6 5/10 6/2 9/3 7/5 8/9	38/-     !   40/-40/-     ;   44/3 38/-51/-     j   48/6 54/-54/5      j   54/7 50/-     j   44/-42/-     I   55/-34/-     &apos; Can- &apos; celled..; ^ ......   -....................    .....  - v;r. X    ...........................................................................*

</content>
</cab>
