<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/182/0 images: 362-369</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy No.  we.&quot;P. 413 (26).CAB IN B g.COMMITTEE ON PAY Off THE PISHTIHG SERYTCBS.ON CADET FISS.1.     At a Meeting of tho Cabinet on Maroh 18th, 1925, (Cabinet 16 (25), Conclusion 4) the Terms of Reference of the Committee were extended to include the question of fees payable by Cadets of the three Services.2o      The Committee have considered memoranda from the three Service Depertments and the Treasury, and have heard, in evidence, representatives of the Servioe Departments, the Treasury and tho Board of Education-3.      The question calls for considernation from three aspects(a)    Whether fees should be reduced or abolished in order to &quot;democratise&quot; the Servioes, in other words whether by this means the field of candidates should be widened so that no hoy is prevented from competing by lack of means.fb) Whether the present syetem of fees Is satisfactory in principle.fc) Whether any changes are necessary to attract increased numbers of suitable candidates.4.      The reduction of fees, as ajtneasure of democratisation, has been repeatedly urged In Parliament by certain Members, particularly under the late Government.    The late Prime   &quot; Minister promised that the matter should be oonsidered, &quot;-but little progress was made.    These representations continued to be made to tho present Government and led the Cabinet to refer the matter to this Committee.I0IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIMNIC MAJESTY1 S G0Y1HHMENT)
5.     In submitting their views to the Goasmittse the Departments? R 7have in the main considered the question from the third aspedt. Both the Wax Office and Air Ministry are experiencing difficulty in securing sufficient candidates for commissions and have submitted proposals designed to improve this position.       They do not, however,  suggest any general reduotion of fees or modification of the existing basis. The Admiralty, under the late Government,worked out a scheme,  the basis of which was that the Board should have     general discretion to remit fees, in whole or in part, for any suitable candidate who would otherwise have been prevented from entering by lack of means. This scheme has boon submitted to the Committee hut the Admiralty have stated that owing to the financial position they do not wish to press for any further remission of fees at the moment.6,     The present system of fees is as followsformal Pees.Royal Haval College, Eartmouth(3 years, 8 months course). 150 p.a.Royal Military Academy, Woolwich and Royal Military College, Sandhurst(18 months course).............Standard FeeSon of aGeneralAdmiral )Air Chief Marshal)It. or Major-General Vice or Rear Admiral Air Marshal or Vice-MarshalColonel or Lt.Colonel, Captain,R.II.or Cossnander, Air Commodore, Group-Cap-tain or Wing CommanderOfficers of lower rank(with at least 20 years service if they retired voluntarily)Soldiers, Ssi lors,Marines and Airmen    (With a similar condition)Son of a deceased officer whose widow is or would be, if alive,  eligible for wi d ow1s pens i on 200 p.a.1059580
Royal Air Force College. Granwell.    (2 year course)Standard Fee Son of a major or officer of )corresponding rank, 1officer of lower rank,    j75 por annum40soldier,  airman,  sailor In addition charges for uniform, hooks, etc., amount to  100 for the course.Special Fees (PrizoJJadets and oases of pecuniary need) Dartmouth.10$ of each entry et a:i00 pEQ,      ) . at the discretion of)    the First Lord, accord-&quot;       &quot;     &quot;       n      &quot;    70   p.a.      )    in$ to the financial)    circumstances of&quot; n       n &apos;      n       n     40    n  n )     parents,Woolwioh, andi -Sandhurst.Son of a deceased officer or man whose family is in pecuniary distressPrize Cadet KingTs Cadet 20 per annum. 105 p.a,) plus remis-) sion of ) charge for Nil-.    ) uniform,) books,etc.Cranwell.Son of a deceased officer etc. whos9 family is left in pecuniary distress.Prize CadetKing1 s Cadet, 20 per annum. 20 p.an) plus remis-) sion of) charges forNil.   ) uniform,) books,  etc.The  150 fee for&apos; Dartmouth and the  200 fee for Woolwich and Sandhurst were recommended by the Geddes Committee of 1921.    The Cranwsll Fee was not similarly increased  owing to shortage of candidates..Irize Cedotships are awarded by merit on the results of the results of the Entrance Examination. &apos; When an Army Prize Cadetship is won by the son of an officer (or. man) the finan-cial benefit is limited to the remission of the charge for uniform., books since the cadet is already eligible toentry at a fee equal to or less than that assigned to the prize cadetship.,In addition charges for uniform, hooks,   etc., are made amounting to  70 -  90 for the course.
7.     The proposals submitted to the Committee by the Departments are as followsTho Admiralty desire a greater measure of discretion in entering boys at reduced fees, where justified by parental, circumstances, subject to the condition that the numbers so entered do not exceed the existing limit of 20f0 of each entry.The War Office propose -fa) to double the number of prize cadetships (80 perannum instead of 40 per annum); (b) to admit prize cadets at half the fees they wouldhave to pay if not prize cadets (see 3 of Motesto paragraph 6); (o) to admit the sons of officers retired after 10 years service at a fee of  100 per annum.    (To be eligiblefor the present scale of preferential fees the parent must normally have given 20 years service before retirement!-The Air Ministry propose to increase the number of prize cadetships from 3 per annum to IS per annum,    (The Air Ministry have recently made savings on messing allowances and rates of pay of cadets which more than off-set the cost of the additional prize cadetships proposed),8o      The Committee have considered the present rates of fees and the above proposals in relation to them.      They agreo with the Departments that the present standard rates of fees should not be reduced. To reduce fees all round would only result in relieving many parents of charges which are well within their means and are not greater than they would pay in educating their sons for other careers.      On the other hand,  the inability of a parent to pay the full fees should not be an absolute bar to the admission of his
son to a Cadet Collage.      It is essential that a limited number of cadets from less well-to-do families, in all respects suitable for training as officers and of proved attainments,  should be eligible for entry at reduced fees.9.     The Committee consider that the present Admiralty system meets all requirements and they concur in the grant to the Admiralty of the greater discretionary power desired by them in order to facilitate its administration.       They understand that arrangements to this effect have now been agreed between the Admiralty and the Treasury.10.    In the case of the Army, however,  the Committee regard the present system as out of date and they are of opinion that it should be completely changed and a revised basis adopted before consideration is given to the necessity for further concessions.     Under the present arrangements a cadet who is the son of an officer (or man) in any of the three Services is entered at a reduced fee  (on a scale varying with the father1s rank), without any regard to financial circumstances.       While the son of a civilian is required to pay  200 per annum,  cadets from Service families normally pay from  55 per annum to  105 per annum only, although in many cases the parents must be in a position to pay a higher fee.        The same consideration arises in regard to the prize cadetships which are of the nature of entrance scholarships.    The benefits attaching to a prize cadetship are granted without enquiry whether the parents means are such as to merit financial assistance.
11.    The1 Committee agree that it is reasonable that a degree of preference should be granted to the cadet from a Service family, but they think that the preference now given gbes far beyond what can be justified. The money involved in the admission of the sons of officers of adequate means at unduly reduced foes could, in their opinion, be more advantageously applied to facilitating the admission of less well-to-do cadets.12.    The trend of sdicational policy since the War War in regard to the award of scholarships supports the view that the low fees should be reserved for cadets of limited means..   Educational Authorities have adopted very widely the policy of limiting the financial benefits of a scholarship to students of limited means.      The State Scholarships awarded by the Board of Education at the Universities and at the Imperial College and the Royal College of Art are all graduated according to this principle.      It is now also adopted by Colleges at Oxford and Cambridge in respect of the Scholarships and Exhibitions awarded by them.     Under the new statutes only  30 per annum (or tho equivalent in free rooms)&apos; is awarded to College Scholars without conditions, the balance of the scholarship benefit being dependent on proof of need satisfactory to the College.     Looal Education Authorities have m some cases adopted a scale of income limits in accordance with which the value of a scholarship is adjusted, and in all cases obtain information as to the financial circumstances of candidates before making awards.13.   Under the War Office proposals the son of a wealthy officer would be eligible for a prize
cadetship entitling hint to admission to Woolwich or       9 a o Sandhurst at a fee of  27. 10/-,   40,  47.10/-,  or  52,lo/- per annum according- to his father!s rank, and to free hooks, uniform,  otc.    On the other hand., the most favourable terms on which the son of a civilian could enter would be as a prise cadet paying x.100 per annum..14.    The Committee consider that both these examples are indefensible.    They agree that provision should be made for the entry of a limited number of cadets at reduoed fees,  but they are strongly of opinion that the War Office should adopt the principle according to whioh reductions in fees? should only be granted where justified by the pecuniary circum-stances of parents.    While, however,  this principle should be applied generally a Service parent might be charged on a somewhat lower scale in all cases than a civilian parent of corresponding means.    The Committee recommend that the War Offico should be instructed to prepare a scheme on this basis fur submission to them.15c.    As regards the Royal Air Force,   the  situation does not differ in essenoe from that of the Army,  and should the above recommendations be adopted,  the Committee world wish to explore fully the question of the introduction of the uame principles.    The present Royal Air Force fees are,, however, already on a very low scale, notwithstanding which the greatest difficulty is being experienced in recruiting suitable cadets.    Having regard to those difficulties,  the Committee recommend that the increas &apos;d number of prize cadetships proposed by the Air Ministry should be allowed,  provided that this increase can be made on the existing basis without pre-judice to tho possibility of revising the present system in accordance with the above principles-.
16*    The Committee recommend :-(1)    That the War Office and the Air Ministry should both adopt the principle according to which reductions in fees should only be granted where they are justified by the pecuniary circumstances of the parents of the entrant^subject to tho reservation that a limited preference may be given, whether as regards standard or reduced fees,  in the case of the sons of officers and other ranks of the three Services.(2)    The War Office should be directed to prepare a scheme on the above basis for consideration by the Committee.- (3)    The number of Prize Cadetships awarded by the Air Ministry may be increased from 3 per annum to 12 per annum forthwith,  on the existing basis, provided&apos;that this increase will not prejudice the possible revision of the system of fees on the basis of Recommendation (1).(Signed on behalf of the Committee)JOEH GILMOUR,(Chairman).2 Whitehall Gardens,  S*W.  1, 10th December,  192 6.

</content>
</cab>
