<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/203/0 images: 237-277</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;5: jpmffiNT,..IS .;THE,PROPERTY; OP^HIS. BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.RET- Copy No.     0  . 117 (S9)-   ^CABINET  .Trade JOut look.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate,  for the information of my colleagues, reports which I have received from members of my Advisory Council, regarding the trade position and prospects.The progress reported last month is on the whole maintained. The fall in exports during March this year as compared with a year ago is largely explained by weather conditions at the beginning of the month,  and by Easter falling at the end of the month.      For the first quarter of this year exports at  181.2 million were within  700,000 of the first quarter of 1928.Coal output in March was well maintained.      Export prices hardened slightly on long term contracts,  and much higher prices were quoted for the small amount of free coal on the market.I regret that I have to report an unfortunate setback in the process of rationalisation in the coal trade.    The Scottish scheme has come to an end, and the owners have not yet agreed upon a substituted scheme.Steel production in March was the highest since May,  1927. The immediate outlook appears to be satisfactory, but the industry is handicapped by a serious shortage of scrap.    Foreign steel makers are ready buyers at prices which the English makers oonsider very excessive.      There is a good demand for galvanised and corrugated sheets -In engineering the increased px-oduction is well maintained, but prices are severely cut.    In 1927 figures got out by the
industry show that although output was greater than in 1994 profits were only 70% of the level reached in that year.In shipbuilding and marine engineering there has been a slackening off of new orders, but employment on existing contracts should be good until the end of the summer; and there is an expectation of more orders in the autumn.In electrical engineering both home and exuort trade are well maintained.The motor trade reoort that business is rather better than this time last year. The industry is now unanimous in desiring a change from the horse power tax to the petrol tax.In the ootton trade Indian orders have fallen off again; and the fear is entertained that the United States will become a serious competitor in the export market.The woollen and worsted industry shows some improvement in certain sections.    It will be remembered that when the previous Safeguarding Committee was sitting, the home trade obtadned a similar benefit by merchants placing orders at home for fear a duty should be imposed before delivery could take place on orders placed abroad.      Seven firms in this industry have given notice of a 10% reduction in wages,  and it is feared that this may give rise to serious disnutes.Trade In boots and shoes and in hosiery are both better; and the chemical industry regains good,The trade in tyres is steady and the demand for ordinary bicycles is greater than ever.In retail trade reports from the North show an increased turnover, no doubt reflecting the increased purchasing power due to better employment there.My colleagues will be interested to see the satisfactory account given by Mr.Alexander Shaw of the  latest experiments with pulverised coal on board ship, and in an experimental
marine installation on land.    The first results of the latter appear to show a 4:0% economy over oil.    If these results are confirmed,  a real impetus should be given to the coal industry. Mr,Shaw has given this information confidentially and he is unwilling that the first results should be published at the present.P.O.L.SO/4/29.Board of Trade.
Date of Meeting .   ....   ...   ........  . 1Coal....................... 1Iron and Steel.................. non-Ferrous Metals................ engineering.  .   .    .........  ....... 5Electrical Industry ..........   ..... 10Motor Manufacture. u............... 11Cotton ......    ..........  ..... 12Wool...................... 14Hosiery, Boots and Shoes............. 16Chemicals................... 17Rubber .................... 17Finance.................... 18General Trade................. 18Distributing Trades.  .    .............. 20Shipping...................* 21Railway Traffic ..........  ...... 23Employment  .....    ......  ....... 25Australian Trade................ 27Indian Trade................. 27Russian Trade.................. 29South American Trade.............* 29Statistical Data ...    ............. Annex.CONFIDENTIAL. THE TRADE OUTLOOK.
DATE OF MEETING,The date of the next meeting of the Council was discussed, and it was decided hy vote that in future the meetings should be held regularly on the second Wednesday of the month instead of the first Wednesday.    The second Wednesday of the month was chosen because by that date statistical and other information bearing upon the conditions of industry in the previous month would be more complete.Accordingly, the next meeting would be held on Wednesday, May 8th.coal.ME.  V/AFdiAM gave the following figures as to the output of coal in the United Kingdom:-5,526,000 tons. 5,562,000    &quot; 5,632,000    &quot;The output for the week ended March 25rd was 107.5$ of the March,    1925, weekly average basis, whilst the number of persons employed for the week ended March 23rd was 82.7$fe,  calculated on the same average weekly basis,.      They were getting 7-g- per cent, more output than in 1925 with,  roughly speaking, four-fifths of the men employed.      This was very largely owing to the increase of machinery.    In some pits about 77 per cent, of our coal was now being got by machinery, with the result that the coal per man had increased very much indeed.      The hewer was being to a large extent displaced by machinery,   and was now becoming a filler.      The filler&apos;s job was an easier one.Unemployment in February had been 15.3%, as compared with 19.1% in January.    While these figures showed some improvement, it   was the general experience of collieries that they could not find enough skilled workmen.      As Mr. Warham had stat6d at the Council last month,  it might be that the official figures of - unemployment were swollen by the inclusion of unskilled and unsuitable men who had been employed as labourers in or about the mines at some period or another.    But it appeared-certain that the figures for February in no way represented the number of bona   fide, able-bodied miners out of employment.The quantity of coal exported in February, which of course had   been a short month, was 3,890,000 tons,  as compared with 4^ million tons in January.      The value in February had been 15/8 as compared with 15/7d.  in January and 15/Cd,  in December. Although the market price for export coal rose by 2/- or 3/- a ton the realised price in February was only Id- more.      There was,  in fact,  very little coal to sell,  largely owing to the epidemic of influenza which caused the output to be much below the expectation of tho exporting producer and had been the cause for the week ended March 9th, ii     .1       n i.     .i      i6th.it      h       i, ii     23rdi
COAL (OOHTD.).of a great deal of delay to shipping in the porta.    The home trade was now falling off owing to the warmer weather, but the exporting collieries were still busy making up arrears, It did not seem likely that the output of coal would long be maintained at the high rate of January and February, or that the five million ton mark would continue to be exceeded during the summer.   Nevertheless some very long forward contracts had been made in Wales,  although buyers generally seemed to think that,  for buying ahead, they were entitled to offer a low figure,  and the collieries did not seem disposed to take it.Our principal competitor, Poland, exported by sea in January 652,000 tons,  and only 262,000 tons in February,    By land she sent off 462,000 and 415,000 tons.    Unfortunately, v/e were hardly in a position to take advantage of the falling-by sea, for the frozen condition of the ports affected our importing power as well as their exporting power0    Reparations in kind,  especially in coal, would be    a question of the greatest importance as the winter demand slackened off,  and the coal trade was waiting with great anxiety to learn the result of the present negotiations in Paris.MR. MITCHELL considered that the coal trade in Scotland was in an unsatisfactory position.    Some collieries that were closed had been re-opened, with resulting excess of output and some idle time at the collieries.  &quot;Prices of coal were falling rapidly, and very little new business was being done for export.    The new coal organisation scheme for Scotland had not yet been formed,  and efforts were still being made to get coalowners to agree to join.    Meanwhile the old scheme had come to an end.ME. PHILLIPS referred to the classification of unemployed coal miners.      Every year in July a classification of all insured workers was undertaken.     Those who were thon in employment were, of course, classified according to the industry in which they   were engaged.      Those who were then unemployed were classified according to their last employment, whatever it may have been.      Accordingly, insured persons who were last employed in coal mining,  remained under the catergory of coal miners so long as they continued in unemployment.      On the other hand,   every year a clearance was effected; and every year   for the last four or five years the total numbers attributed to coal mining had gone down by substantial amounts.      Beaths on the one hand and the accession of new-comers on the other might go some way to balance each other, and the net reduction which had occurred under the heading of coal mining was, no doubt,  due to people formerly employed in that    trade going into other trades.
IRON AND STEEL.THE PRESIDENT observed that Mr. Mitchell had asked at the last Council meeting whether inquiry could be made on two points in connexion with steel scrap.    The first was whether Germany was buying sorap in this country and delivering i t to Poland on reparations account.    The Board of Trade had been in touch with the Reparation Commission and ascertained that there were no deliveries of scrap at all to Poland on reparations accountj indeed any such deliveries would be a breach of the Wallenberg regulations under the Dawes scheme.    The second point was about de-tinning.    The Board had comr^unicated with Cohens who were large scrap merchants and de-tinners, and that firm had said that very little tin plate scrap, if any, was being exported, that their existing de-tinning plants could deal with an additional 15,000 to 20,000 tons of scrap tin-plate a year, and that they would be glad to extend if further material were available.   The President had suggested to the Iron and Steel Federation that they might go into the question whether,, in view of the big output and possible shortage of scrap, they could not make some arrangements for collective buying.-MR. MITCHELL stated that specifications for steel were not very satisfactory in Scotland, and there was some difficulty in getting works going.    Basic pig iron from England, which was used, in the steel, works, was proving scarce.    Owing to the coke shortage in England, furnaces which were ready for starting could not be blown in.    Scrap was also still scarce,- and dear, and the cost of production of steel had gone up rather seriously, with no addition in price.    Imports of iron and steel into Scotland from the&quot; Continent were lower, but still considerable.MR. BOND wrote:&quot;Business during March has not quite fulfilled the promise of the two previous months but, without exhibiting pronounced signs of weakness, has been somewhat quieter.   -Much of this quietness was due to the exceptionally severe weather experienced in February and the first fortnight of March when outside ?irork of all kinds, such as building con-struction and operations in -Shipyards, was greatly interfered with.    Orders for&quot; materials could not therefore be placed at the same rate but once the arrears of work are overtaken an improvement in the volume of orders is confidently expected. In spite of the slight slackening in new business current production shows a further slight increase over February.&quot;increase in pig iron production has been handicapped by a shortage of coke which in one instance actually resulted in the blowing out of a furnace.    So far as at present reported there was a nett increase of four blast furnaces In operation during March, six furnaces having been blown in (2 on North East Coast,  2 in Scotland and 2 in South Wales) and two blown out (1 on North East Coast and 1 in the Midlands).    Steel production in March was the highest since May 1927.    Imports of iron and steel in February at 160,000 tons were lower than In any month since January, 1924, but
IRON AND STEEL  (GONTD.).it is felt that  the decline is mainly due to the difficulties --experienced in Continental ports during the extremely cold weather.    March imports may he low for the same reason but when the tremendous congestion in Continental ports is relieved imports will again rise, though, it may be hoped, not to the average level of 1923,    Export demand continues fairly satisfactory though it Is extremely difficult to sell to near Continental countries.    In the case of steel, prices are not competitive with the home prices of the Continent, but pig iron would be exported in large quantities to France and Germany but for the tariff operating against imports of pig iron.&quot;The belief that the quieter conditions of March were only temporary is expressed by a Scottish correspondent &quot;who states that the Clyde keeps active and order books are beginning to assume a healthier appearance.    Pig Iron in . Scotland continues somewhat dull although two blast furnaces have recently been blown in.&quot;Reports from the North East Coast indicate that works in that area have reaped the benefit of increased activities in the shipyards and that the slight increase in the tonnage on the order books at the end of March over February is almost entirely accounted for by shipbuilding requirements. There is also a renewed demand for galvanised and corrugated sheets and an increased volume of orders from re-rollers. Very little change has taken place in the ratio between home and export trade but there has been a slight falling off in the export trade.    The constructional trades have been less active than last month and makers report a falling off in the demand for heavy sections for wagon building and general constructional purposes,    The prices of saleable products remain steady but the tendency towards the rise in prices of raw materials has been accelerated by the Increasing demand. Summarising the position, it is stated that trade on the North East Coast appears to have attained what may be described as a fairly healthy standard, but is dependent on the continued activity in the  shipbuilding industry.On the North West Coast the increased demand for hematite iron is sustained and unless production is increased a state of scarcity may soon exist.    The position was rendered easier owing to the fact that, since pig iron is a continuous process, the production of pig iron continued throughout the Easter holidays while steel production ceased for a few days.&quot;in South Wales the demand for tinplates remains on about the  same level - 10% of  capacity.    Steel makers in South Wales who have of recent years been dependent upon liberal supplies of scrap at low prices are suffering severely from the continued export of this material in large quantities.    The price of scrap has gradually advanced from 65/- to 82/-, resulting in increased costs of steel which is handicapping tinplate manufacturers in competition with other countries.    Local works are finding a poor demand for galvanised and black sheets.&quot;
CONFIDENTIAL.NON-FERROUS METALS.CAPTAIN LYTTELTON wrote:&quot;Business with consumers in refined copper has been at a standstill owing to the wide fluctuations in price on the standard market, which is at present standing at a figure which bears no relation to the price quoted by the American interests for electro.      In this connection it is important to note that American manufacturers have been in a position to offer semi-manufactured goods, such as copper rods, In this country at below the official price for wire bars.     Business is being seriously affected with the brass makers owing to the high price of copper, and substitutes are making considerable headway.      High prices are also resulting in a scarcity of orders which cannot altogether be explained by holiday conditions.&quot;Both lead and spelter have fluctuated sharply in sympathy with copper, and consumers have been unwilling to cover more than their immediate needs, owing to fear fjf low prices.      The demand for refined spelter is affected by a falling off In the demand for brass, but there are signs that the cable trade is once more active.      Galvanisers complain of poor Indian orders, but the home demand Is fairly satisfactory.&quot;in the case of tin also there has been a sharp fall in price which has encouraged the -demand from consumers, and the South Sales tinplate trade is reported as satisfactory,&quot;engineering.SIR ERNEST PETTER stated that exports of machinery during January and February were 2.6,-c in excess of the same two months in 1928, and 87.4% of the 1913 rate.      Unemployment In engineer-ing had decreased from 10.5)3 in January to 10% in February, which was rather a greater decrease than was shown in trade generally.      He handed in a table  (reproduced below) which had been prepared by the British Engineers1 Association, based upon the statistics of the Board of Trade which, taking 1924 as the basis year, endeavoured to express the trend in all branches of general engineering in the subsequent years.      1924 had been chosen as the year of the last Census of Production, and as now generally accepted as the best for comparative purposes.      One very striking part of the table showed the extraordinarily bad results of 66 representative engineering concerns  in the matter of profit earned,  as compared with. 1924.      In 1927 It was only about 70?t, which confirmed what had. been said before at the Council as to engineering business generally being obtained at very competitive and often quite unprofitable prices, although output had increased.MR. RICHMOND reported that in Scotland locomotive builders had recently secured some fair orders;    tool makers reported an appreciable improvement, and prospects -were continuing to be favourable.MR. BROiVNLIE wrote:-      I have nothing very definite to report as to the present   Bt*iy* of the Engineering Industry, apart from the fact that a number of our unemployed members have recently found employment;:   there has bsen a reduction of over 1,000 in our unemployed figures during the recent month.
CONFIDENTIAL. -ENGINEERING: (CONTD.)Handed in by Sir E.  FetterSUMMARY OF PRINCIPAL TRADE AND OTHER STATISTICS OF RELATIVE IMPORTANCE TO BRITISH   ENGINEERING    INDUSTRY.1924 - 1928&apos;.Expressed as Index Numbers (1924 * 100).1924 ;   1925 .   19261927  !   1928lOALProductionPer cent, of 1924(million    J269.6 tons)   j   100Exports (incl.Foreign Bunkers)  &quot; j 79.3 per cent, of 1924 i   100Home Consumption                (      &quot; )   Il90.2 per cent, of 1924 \   100! 243.2 ;   90.2ij 67.2 !   84.7i! 175.9 :   92.5! 126.3 i   46.9j! 28.2 :   35.5;   118.1! 62.1 I254.4 !241.9 94.4 I   89.868.0 85.7188.9 99.366.8 84.217 5.1 92.iron and steel.. Production:    Pig Iron Per cent, of 1924!(thousand  7,307 tons)   !    1001 :    Steel Ingots&amp; Castings  ( Per cent, of 1924aImports:Per cent, of 1924 Exports:Per cent, of 1924(&quot; ) 18,201 I    100&quot; ) j2,429 i    100&quot; ) ;3,851 ! 100 -1-! 6,262 i   35.77 ,385 90.02,720 112.0 3,731 96.92,458 I 33.7 ;3.596 i 43.8 i3,7 38 I 153.9 i 2,988! 77.6!7,293 j6,611 99.8 I   90.59,297 !8,525 li.0.9 ; 163.94,406 I 2,896 181.5 j119.3 4,200 I 4,261 109.1 j110.7PGINBSROG AND ALLIED METAL PRODUCTSImports ( millions,(Corrected to 1924 Values) ! 85,8 i 103..per cent. Of 1924 j   100 j 120,3Exports1 1i! 105.4! I   122,9 1118.8 I 109.6 138.6 i127.8(Correc	ted to 1924 Values )    &quot;			1	181	.1	197 .	0 i	184,	3	210	.5	230.	3 per	cent, of	1924		1 j	100		lo3..	3 i	101.		116	.3	127.	2ACHINERY.				1		1		1		i				Imports			(thousand	i j	60	.1	74.	9 j	80.	4i	101	.9	98.	5Per	cent, of	1924	tons )	1	100 :		124,	0 1 0 1	133.		159	.8	164.	2	(aver	. - value	per ton	 ^17 5		.8	161.	0 j	159.	0!	156	.0	169.	8Per	cent, of	1924		j	1	00 1	91.	7 1	90.	4]	88	.7	96.	5Exports			(thousand	i	463	.4 1	517 .	1	47 6.	sj&apos;	512	.1	566-.	1Per	cent, of	1984	tons )	j	100 1		111.	5 i	102.	8!	110	.5	122.	1	(aver	&apos;. value	per ton	 )	96	.5 !	95.	0 j	95.	8I	97	.5	94.	9Per	cent, of	1924		1	100		GO.	5 !	S 9 *	3j 1	101	.1	98.	4(contd.)
coupidentIal.engineering (oontd.).1924IALYSIS op MAOHINi-ilY exportsextile Machinery (thousand   \ 103.6per cent,  of 1034 tons)     i      100&quot;iectrical Machinery         ( &quot;    )     !   51. per cent,  of 1034 100gricultural Machinery     ( &quot;    )     I    18.0per cent, of 1924 j      100oilers &amp; Boiler House Plant &quot;    )     I   55. per cent. of 1924 j      iooCranes, Hoists,  etc,          ( :     )     .19. per cent, of 1^24 j      ioo&quot;achine Tools                      ( &quot;    )     I    12.0Per cent. of 1924 100prime Movers (not elec.)  ( &quot;    )     j    50.per cent, of 1924 100Printing, etc. Machinery ( &quot;    )           4.3 per cent,  of 1924 100pumps                                  ( &quot;    )    j     6i4Per cent,  of 1924 100i3e-7ing Machines (inc. Parts) ( &quot;    )         21.per cent, of 1924 &apos;            100&quot;x port a to:-19251026i  ln271928T.123.1 I 119.9!33.2 105.723.1 128.855.8 100.723.4 120.714.3 119.256 .8 112.0111.7 Ij7.7 120.2  !I28.9 ! 133.2  !101.5 97.934.4 109.420 .3 113.057.7 104.121.7 111.813.6 113.448.2 94.94.1 95.36.1 95 .226 .8 123.6119.3 115.240 .9 130.0lo.3 107 .652 .2 94.325.7 132 .314.5 120.950 .0 98.64.7109.37.5I   117.3iI     26.6 122.6125.2 I 120.841.5 I 131.421.8 121.258.7 106 .030 .0 154.614.6 121.651.2 100 .95 .8 134.810.4162 .531.9 147 .british Countries	/      &quot;    )	230	249	229	356    !	(a)Per cent,  of 1924		100	108.2	99.5	110.3 j	-Foreign Countries	/      t*    \	233	267	346	256    j	(a)Per cent,  of 1924		100	114.6	105 .5	109.9    i	European Countries	(      &quot;    )	i 108	132	127	i 137    1	J    (a)Per cent,  of 1924		100	122 .2	177 .7	1   126.8    1	-EXPORTS OF OTHEIl engineering &quot;pivO DUCTSua.il Locomotives (inc.Parts) ( 000) Per cent, of 1924Hoad Locomotives (incl.Agricultural &apos; raotora) ( &quot; ) Per cent. of 1924uotor Vehicles &amp; Chassis      (    &quot;   ) Per cent.  of 1924Ne i Ships (not registeredan British) (    &quot;  )Per cent, of 19242,497 1005,522 1003,350 130 .2724  iioo !i i4,869 1007,412 152 .26,276 113.73,622 145 .2623 ! 756 86.0    i   104.47,158 147.04,630 83.12,890 115.7484 66.88,450 173.64,531 82.1(a)  Statistics not available. ..   -7-4,633 185 .6(a)7,149 146 .815,576 381.8
	1924.	1925. ; i	 --1 1926.	1927.	1928.PBU ILDIMG		......      i 1 i			&quot;  ---------&quot; Irld Output (thousands of gross	2,248 100	2,193 &apos; 97,6 i	1,675 74. 5	2,286 101.7	2,699 120,1	1,440 100	1,085 75,3 :	640 44.5	1,226 85.1	1,446 100.4[, Tonnage under construction (in OOCs)	1, 237 100	j 788 63.7 ! !	661 53,4	1,574 127.2	1,243 100. 5I. Marine Engines under construction-&quot; t end of year -.Steam                        (thousand h.p.)..	(a)	i 354 100	429 121.2	608 171.5	517 146,0,011                          (thousand h.p.)..	(a)	234 100 i	292 124.8	373 159.5	377 161,2K NUMBERS OF NATIONAL PRODUCTION.		1 1			5 compiled by Board of Trade)						.100	(a)	(a)	106.8	105,2	100	(a)	(a)	110,0	102,3	100	(a)	(a)	115.1	112,7li(KMEWT (% of total insured workpeople		i i			iverage for year).		*			For cent,  of 1924....................	w9 $ 5 100	88.6 98.9	-&quot;-82. 6 92.3	90.2 100.7	89,1 99,5Per cent, of 1924....................	85.3 100	87.4 102.5	84.0 98.5	89.7 105,2	9004 106.0Per cent. of 1924..................	84. 6 100	!     87.4 103.3	84. 2 99,5	89.5 105,8	90.1 10 6,5Per ce it. of 1924..................	94.7 100	94,5 j     99.8 ! -   79.0 95.1	92.3 97.4 72.7 87.4	94.8 101.2	95.1 100. 5j Per cent, of 1924..................	83.1 100			84.2 101.3	86, 5 104.1Bonstructional....................... I Per cent, of 1924..................	87.1 100	87.4 100.4	80. 6 92.6	90.1 103.4	89.4 102.6Jsr cent,  of 1924....................	94.3 100	84.2 89.3	t	81.8 86.7	77,8 82.4m\ and Steel........................ ir cent, of 1924....................	79.6 !     100	!     75.8 95.2	58. 2 73,1	82.0 103.2	79,0 99,3BPbuilding.............&apos;.....,,	!   70.2 i     100	65.7 95. 6	59. 6 84 .9	1    75,0 i  10S.9	73. 3 104 ..4(a)Statistics not available.(-&quot;-) Including estimate for all miners not at work. It) Coal Stoppage Kay to November inclusive.CONFIDENTIAL. ENGINEERING (CONTD.).
ENGINEERING (CONTD.)19241925192619271928Ilesaie prices WrbT^&quot;*Fn&amp;ex Nos .\ll Commodities [ron and Steel. Soal...........100100 10096.1 88.1 84.6I TAIL PRICES - Cost of Livint(M. of L. Index No.HANCIAL RESULTSof 66 representative engineer-ing and allied firmsAggregate Amounts of :-Paid-up Ord. &amp; Pref. Capital( 000s)Per cent, of 1924..........Earned Profits            ( 000s ) Per cent, of 1924..........Ord. &amp; Pref. Dividends ( 000s) Per cent, of 1924..........100100.5148,56089.2 86.4 (a)85.2 j 84.4 83.9 j 78.6 74.3     I    68.3!______   .. _j_______I98.795 .5(Financial years)141,407 j 140,867100	95 .2	94.9	94.4	-8,620	5,170	3,900	6,036	(a)100	60 . 0	45 .3	70 .0	-6,885	6,041	5 ,542	5 ,873	(a)100	87.8	80.6	85 .3	140,21195 .0(a)(a )    Statistics not available
MARINE 5i\L G-INEERI EG.MR. Richmond reported that March had been notable on the Clyde for the number of ships launched, - 22 vessels of 75,500 tons,  - which constituted a record for this month of the year.     The output for the first quarter of the year was the third highest recorded, being 147,936 tons as compared with 162,897 for the same period last year, whi ch itself had been a record.      The finishing of these vessels and the other work in hand should ensure no diminution In employment until well after midsummer.     New contracts were coming along rather sparsely, but there were expectations of a better demand for new tonnage In the late summer and the autumn.     Employment figures for the district were better, the wholly unemployed in marine engineering in March being 1,298, as compared with 1,479 in February.From the Mersey a good report was forthcoming, and the engine shops there were actively engaged.      On the North East coast a fair amount of tonnage had been placed, but the keen competition for work and the excess of facilities had prompted the public statement by a director of one of the leading yards that some form of co-operation or rationalisation seemed desirable.     The Tyne was fairly well placed for some time ahead, but at the moment there was a lull in the placing of fresh orders.      It was a satisfactory feature that much of this work was for foreign countries, - Canada, United States, France and Norway.      The Tyne had also been successful in obtaining four destroyers.     Altogether the prospects in this district during the remainder of the year were satisfactory, and output might exceed that of 1928. (See also the section on Shipping).ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.SIR HUGO HIRST stated that the heavy side of the electrical industry was well employed.      The programme of the Electricity Board had resulted in some three or four million pounds worth of contracts being placed.     The progress of the Electricity Board&apos;s schemes had also Inspired the public with the Idea that electricity supply was getting cheaper, and had had a corresponding effect on demand In the lighter side of the industry.      There had been a very large increase of business month by month in that side of the Industry up to about two months ago, and during the last two months it had remained steady.Export had on the whole been good, particularly to Australia.      The Indisnmarket had been satisfactory, and China seemed to be showing signs of improvement.
MOTOR MANUFACTURE.SIR KILLIAM MORRIS said that, on the whole, the motor trade was holding its own;    in fact it was probably busier than last year.    In ^be earlier part of the season the exceptional weather had caused a temporary set-back, but up to date he could say that, speaking of his own concerns, they had already passed last year&apos;s figures, even with the bad start which they had had owing to the severe weather.    The trade was lagging at the moment, waiting for the Budget proposals on the subject of the petrol versus the horse power tax.The most important matter to the industry was the fact that we were not exporting anything like the number of motor cars that we might do, simply owing to the horse power tax,    Oversea markets were asking, as everyone knew, for a big engine, and they w ere getting it  from America.    Owing to the horse power tax, we had never been able to  sell a big engine in this country, and it was obvious, for reasons of cost, that we could not split our production into two classes of cars.    He was hoping that in time the tax would be taken off horse power and put on to petrol.MR. HACKING observed that his chief concern was, of course, to increase the export trade, but up to the present,  at any rate, the whole industry had not been in agreement ,    Two firms did 80 per cent, of the export trado and the others had not been so favourable to the proposal to change the basis of tax.SIR GEORGE BEHARRELL stated that,  as President of the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders, he could say that there was now complete unanimity in the trade on that point.SIR W. MORRIS agreed that in the past the trade had not been unanimous, but when they met the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the last occasion it could be said that the whole trade were unanimous in the  case put to him.    Sir W. Morris would go so far as to say that the whole of the horse power tax should be taken off and a petrol tax substituted with perhaps a registration fee for each motor  car.    If the motor trade could design their products for overseas, he was convinced that it would not be very long before our exports equalled our home consumption.  There n,as, of cotirse, the additional point, which was not always realised..,,, that it would be much easier to collect a tax on petrol, because the tax would be paid a little at a time instead of in comparatively large suras all at once.SIR GILBERT VYLE mentioned that in the Midlands they had had the first labour disturbance for a long time - the strike in the Austin motor works, A point of interest was that the strike was an entirely unofficial one organised by a miner from Cardiff for whom work had been found in the motor factory In accordance with the appeal of the Government.
COTTON .SIR KENNETH STEWART reported that conditions in the cotton trade had tended to become  slacker during the month of ivarch, so far as the volume of fresh business was  concerned. Early in the month there had been a really good spurt in demand for India, which had subsequently fallen off.      China was now the brightest spot and continued to place fair orders for greys, whites and fancies.     Most of the markets were dull and below normal, except Australia, where some good business had been done in heavy drills.THE PRESIDENT recalled that Sir K. Stewart had spoken at the meeting of the Council on 6th parch of the custom of Indian merchants of holding up their orders for some time each year at about the beginning of February;   and this usually brought about a period of good enquiries at the  end of February and the beginning of March.SIR K. STEWART thought there was no doubt that the Indian houses had been very busy at the beginning of March.      Indian merchants placed heavy orders then which supplied their current wants, and business thereafter had become slack. Sales of yarn were beginning to fall off and mills in the coarse section of the trade might&apos; shortly be expected to reduce their output.Steady progress was being made by the Lancashire Cotton Corporation.      The first mill - appropriately named the &quot;Ace&quot;  -had decided to join the Corporation.      The debentures on that mill amounted to rather more than it would cost to build the mill new, and behind the debenture holders there were the unsecured creditors whose claims also exceeded the cost of a nevr mill.      Behind them again were  400,000 of shares, preference and ordinary, and it was a remarkable feature that in the preference shares one found the uncalled capital, while the ordinary shares were fully paid up.      That illustrated the extraordinary state of the spinning trade.      Of course, there were variations and eccentricities in the finances of nearly every mill, but the    Ace was a typical example.      The total of creditors and capital amounted to something over  1,000,000 and the Corporation were taking over the mill at about  250,000. The Lancashire Cotton Corporation had made definite offers for another 22 mills, amounting to about four million spindles, and the terms proposed were now being considered by directors, shareholders and creditors.      /-bout 120 other mills had requested tho Corporation to make them offers.      t-s many of these mills had over 1,000 shareholders and innumerable loan-holders and creditors, progress was necessarily slow.MR. LEE referred to the decision of the Bolton Master Cotton Spinners&apos; Association to run one-third short time in the tra.de using Egyptian cotton.      Two months had just been com-pleted under the scheme, and though stocks at the mills had been a little reduced,  it was not sufficient to warrant returning to
COTTON  (CONTD.hfull time.    There had been no decision for an organised continuation of short time, but another month had been suggested by the Association and their suggestion would probably be carried out.   They were avoiding ballots and publicity, and relying on the private recommendations of the association, in order that their position should not be known more than possible to their customers and to foreign nations.    The difficulties experienced by the fine cotton trade were not limited to the trade in England. There was the same trouble in Italy, Germany and Gzecho Slovakia,    France, however, continued very busy.In the export trade Brazil was raising the duty on fine goods and the United States were proposing a very severe increase on fine goods.    Canada had created a difficult situation by raising the percentage of British material and labour to qualify for the preferential tariff rates from 25^?&apos; to 50%&apos;.    The Canadian Customs representatives had visited Manchester and had been given information to show that it was impossible to bring the cheaper goods within the regualtions, owing to the raw cotton having to be obtained wholly outside the British Empire..   He hoped that some satisfactory arrangement might be arrived at.Mr. Lee drew attention to the competition that was likely to be experienced in the near future from some of the fine cotton spinning mills in the United States.   At the present moment, these mills were working 120 hours per week in two shifts, and their rates of wages were very little more than those in Lancashire.    Women and children were working on both shifts.   The Americans were intro-ducing great increases of duty on the finer yarns, with a view to making them themselves, and their exports were increasing every year.    The U.3.A.. exports of yarn only had increased in a few years from 13 million lbs. per annumto 28 million lbs. and this yarn was exported to Canada, Australia, South America, and even to England.    If they continued to&apos; work those two shifts up to the limit of production, it would be impossible to compete with them in England or on the Continent.MR. ARTHUR SHAtV said that Mr. Lee1 s statement as to these hours of labour In the United States ;as a serious one, though he was certain it had been made in good faith. He thought it should not be put on record without comment unless it was to be carefully examined.MR. LEE mentioned that the hours of labour were stated in a book published by the International Federation of Master Cotton Spinners1 Associations,    It was also mentioned in the report of the tariff enquiry in America.THE PRESIDENT thought that there would be some information on the question already in the Board of Trade,* and if necessary he would cause inquiries to be made of our Commercial Counsellor in Washington.    In any case the observations of members of the Gouncil were always treated as strictly confidential.-* The matter is being investigated in the Board of Trade.
i onWOOL.MR.   ARTHUR  HAW thought there had been a decided upward pendency in the industry in the past month, and his impression was borne out by the fact that quite a large number of applica-tions for temporary overtime had been made and granted.      The employers with whom he had discussed the situation seemed to think there was a general upward lift which could be considered to be more than merely seasonal.From the trade union records there had been a remarkable change since the end of February in all sections of the industry.     There had been a steady decrease, not only in total unemployment, but also in partial unemployment.      Taking the industry as a whole, he thought that in the period from the end of February to the end of March, the total number of people who had been signing the vacant books had been reduced by one half, although, generally Bpeaking, trade was not better at the end of March this year than at the end of March last year.      In the Bradford, Keighley and Shipley areas those signing the books had been reduced by one half since the end of February.      In the heavy woollen district there had been a marked improvement; in that case about 15/; were signing the register, as compared with 30;^ in January.      In the Yeadon and Guiseley area there was practically no unemployment, the figure being lower today than at any point since 1924.      The Huddersfield trade was fairly good, having recovered somewhat during the last month.A serious situation had arisen in the heavy woollen district, where firms employing about 12,000 people had posted notices for a 10/ reduction in wages to take effect that week. A ballot vote had been taken of the whole of the operatives concerned, and the steps to be taken by the unions ?/ere being carefully considered.      There was a great danger in any extension of the trouble, having regard to the possible real improvement in trade,- and before any action was taken the operatives would certainly endeavour, through the Industrial Council,- which unfortunately was failing to function on this occasion, to find some way out of a difficult situation.SIR FREDERIC AYKRQYD wrote:&quot;The position in the &apos;7est Riding as far as the textile trade is concerned does not alter much from the last report that was made..    Although we are now in the midst of arrivals of raw material from abroad,  the percentage of combing machinery which is running full capacity has changed very little from last month, representing 37.19/ total amount of machinery.      This represents a slight falling off in the merino combing but an increase in the carded and preparing crossbreds.&quot;The spinning, taking it all round, has exactly the same number of machines running as last month, namely 75:*,. but no-one seems to be able to plan for the running of their businesses very far ahead, as orders are very spasmodic and are coming to hanc
WOOL (CONTP.)in driblets.      Some spinning for seasonal goods, are temporarily busy whilst others are very poorly employed.      Trade as a whole in this section cannot be described as healthy, as in some of the crossbred sections yarn is accumulating,  and contracts are not being taken up as they should be.     The woollen and worsted manufacturers are not having a very good time as a whole . Buyers appear to be holding off, and not more than 50;i of machinery is running.&quot;There are exceptions,., however, for the coating trade Is better than a month ago and the outlook Is considered fairly good.     The goods are mainly from fine wools and business has been considerably assisted by very much lower prices than last season.     Engineering in the Keighley district is considerably better with more machinery running and a more optimistic outlook. In the Yeadon and Guiseley areas - who make the woollen goods -practically all the firms are busy and overtime is general, most of the mills running two shifts.     These good-s are wanted for immediate delivery and the outlook is considered, good.&quot;It is of interest to note the change in England&apos;s position regarding the exports of worsted yarn to Japan, and to see how the percentage from England is only a little more than half during 1928 than in 1927,  while from Germany the exports are 6% higher than 1927, and from Poland 10/2 higher than 1927.Below	are the figure	s indicating what has		been	done:-Imports of Woollen		and Torsted	Yarns into	Japan.		1927.	Per	1928.		Per	(12 months)	Cent.	(6 months)		Cent.England...	4,366,582	2 5,10	557,391		13.50Germany...	.    5, 6*3, 415	31.13	1,549,246		37.51France. . . :	.    3 , 749 $ 047	20,25	767,098		18.57Poland, c .-..	.    2,848,312	15.50	1,060,011		25.67Czecho-					Slovakia..	787,003	4,28	117,851		2,85Others....	682, 929 ..	3.74	73,280		1.9018, 082,289 lbs. 100. 00,0      4,129,877 kin. 100.00%&quot;The mills in the heavy woollen districts, which represent the Dewsbury and Batiey area,  are by no means working to capacity but they are probably better employed to-day than at any time so far this year.      There is reasonably good business from the home market in light-weight goods for spring and summer wear. The output was accelerated just before the holiday in order to effect every possible delivery before Easter, and, following the holiday, a fair amount of activity continues.      Overtime is being worked at some mills, but this is occasioned not so much by the aggregate bulk of the orders, as the short time within which delivery is required.      The home market is now buying for Whitsuntide trade,  and tweeds retain their popularity.&quot;The condition of overseas trade shows little change, though there are indications that the transatlantic demand is slackening. Continental trade is on the up-grade, however, and it is learnt that a little more direct trade is being done with Germany.
WOOL. (CONTD.)&quot;The topic of the week in trade circles concerns the wage reduction notices given by seven of the largest woollen firms in the district, and the subject is being discussed both from industrial and. trade aspects.      Buyers are already asking whether, if the reductions arc conceded, the full advantage will be passed on to them.      The point is one upon which enlightenment may be forthcoming before the matter Is ended, but, meantime, hesitancy will probably be shown in ordering.&quot;In the Leeds area firms continue to be active in order to satisfy the spring demand.     Factories have resumed work and the increased volume of business reported before Easter has been maintained.      Local firms are expected to be fully occupied for another month.&quot;The following table may be of interest shewing the increase in the worsted spindles and the decrease of woollen spindles between 1923 and 1927, and also the increase between these dates of power looms and the decrease of hand loomsYear Ended December 31. ^pollen        Worsted Total.oplndiee.     Spindles.       -&apos;1923  ................ 90,960 251,380 342,3401924................ 73 , 265 3 03 , 840 377,1051925  ................ 79,695 330,220 409,9151926  ................ 72,997 308,080 381,0771927  ----............ 76,769 311,3 70 388,139Power Looms. Hand Looms. Total.1923................ 14,158 6,873 21,0311924  ................ 19,447 -    5,979 25,4261925................ 16,532 5,802 22,1341925 ................ 16,288 3,239 19,5271927  ................ 27,005 2,420 29,425&quot;Summing up, there is considerable disappointment that business as a whole is not developing as it should for the time of the year&apos;f.HOSIERY, BOOTS AND SHOES.MR. TALKER thought the unemployment figures would give the truest guide to the state of trade in the Leicester district.    In March, 1929,  there was a total number of unemployed of 3,682,in February 4,543,  and In March, 1928, 2,225.      The percentage of unemployed was only about three per cent, but in the boot and shoe trade and hosiery trade it was not usual to put people on total unemployment and a great deal of systematic short time was worked.In the hosiery trade the fine weather before Easter benefited the fancy outerwear and the hosiery sections and they could now be described as fairly well employed.      The underwear sections in Leicester were still working below their normal capacity.    Export trade in hosiery was quiet.In the boot and shoe trade the position was better than a month ago, although not so good as at the same time last year. The general, hours of working were three quarter time.      Prospects for April seemed decidedly better, although the export trade was quiet.
CHEMICALS .MR. HILL said that the home trade during March was fairly good.      The industries consuming alkalis and bleaching powder had been fairly active, and there had been a further slight improvement in the demand for chemicals used in the artificial silk industry.      In the dyestuffs section in March, the dyeing of cotton piece goods had been extremely quiet, and the results of short-time working were being felt by the dye manufacturers.      The position in the coal tar products had not undergone any material change.The March export trade was up to normal and represented an improvement on February.      February, however,, had been lower than February 1928, and the drop during last February, though not very great as a whole, had been due to a falling off in exports of sodium compounds and coal tar products,  the loss  in both these being quite appreciable.In the pharmaceutical chemicals section,  the French and German suppliers had come together and brought about a sharp advance in the prices of the  salicylate group - a rather important group - which had been followed by the English manufacturers.      For a long time past these chemicals had been sold  at unremunenative prices and the higher levels should on the whole tend to healthier conditions in the trade.      The movement was expected to extend to other substances.RUBBER. -SIR GEORGE BEHARRELL, referring first to tyres, which represented probably 80% of the rubber consumption of the country,  said that there was a steady demand for these, but not equally applicable to all types.      The demand for pneumatic giant tyros was very heavy and seemed likely to continue;    for ordinary motor tyros it could be described as steady and no more, whilst in cycle tyres there was a considerable improvement,  corresponding to the steady increase in ordinary cycles in this country for the  last two or three years.      The ordinary bicycle was having now a greater vogue than ever in the history of cycles.     Motor cycles were not developing and that type of tyre was certainly on the downward grade.      The export trade  in tyros generally had probably not advanced, on the whole,In lines such as hose, foot wear and belting,  it was very difficult for some British manufacturers to hold their own against foreign competition.      Rubber sports goods appeared to be In a very satisfactory state,  so far as volume was concerned.      Prices wore not too favourable, but there had been a very heavy demand for these goods and the export trade was undoubtedly fairly good.      This had been an.extraordinary &quot;winter for hot water bottles    -   a trade line which was by no means to be scoffed at, and which was being maintained even now.      Waterproofs had had the most disastrous three months that any one in the industry could remember.     Nobody wished to buy a waterproof when the temperature was down to zero with no prospect of rain.
1 Q1X iJ JLCONFIBENTIAL.FINANCE.SIR GUY GRANET sent in the following:-&quot;Conditions in the money market were throughout March rather difficult although, being the last complete month in the Government financial year, money in the open market is usually scarce.      It was, however,  this year an unusually trying period, mainly owing to the abnormal state of the &quot;New York market, and the efforts of the Bank of England to counteract the effect of the high rates ruling in that centre. Consequently there was for some time a nervous interest in the London - New York Exchange which in the early part of the month was as low as 4,85 1/8, at which price it was almost possible for -American purchasers to outbid the Bank of england for gold in the open market.      Fortunately support for sterling was forthcoming, and by paying above the minimum price the Bank of England was able to secure a good proportion of the shipments which arrived.     Towards the end of the month the Federal Reserve authorities made serious efforts to regain control of the situation by making various arrangements with member banks to restrict their loans to the Stock Markets and also to adopt measures to discourage the influx of foreign funds.      Their efforts have to some extent been successful as repatriated sterling has appeared in this market and was extremely useful in easing the position at the end of the quarter.&quot;in the discount market it is expected that conditions will be more comfortable than during the past month.&quot;The institution of the 5^/t rate in London has undoubtedly aided the Federal Reserve authorities in their struggle to regain control, and the possibility of the Bank of England being able to. acquire some further gold In the near future justifies the hope that the corner has been turned and that there is no reason to fear a further increase in the official rate.&quot;Notwithstanding the firmer rates which have ruled since the raising of the bank rate,  there has been a good demand for London acceptance facilities and the volume of bills has been fully maintained,  in fact the market has not been so independent of Treasury Bills since 1913.&quot;GENERAL TRADE.SIR GILBERT VYLE said that his personal Impression of tne . general business conditions in the Midlands and other districts-was that the reasonable improvement in trade was being maintained, though there were not yet sufficient orders being booked to inspire confidence.    There was also a considerable hesitancy in face of the budget and the general election.&quot;
GENERAL TRADE  (OONTD.)LORD EB3ISHAM remarked that matters were very much as they had teen in the previous month.      One disturbing question was the financial uncertainty both here and in the United States.MR. MITCHELL gave the following reports from various districts In the country.      In the seed crushing trade at Hull there was a slow demand for cakes, and oil prices were low, indicating indifferent trade.     Freight markets eastward were weak   -   westward they were more holding their own.      The timber trade was not unpromising, with firm prices.In Liverpool the3&quot;e was very little change In the general timber situation:   demand was rather weak and supplies -were generally plentiful.     March had been a dull month in hide and leather, but the hide market had steadied a little, and English hides were firming up.      Boot and shoe manufacturing had experienced a dull time for the Easter trade, which was generally brisk, consequently the demand for leather had been slack.       Ship repairers had experienced depression in the volume of work carried out, as compared with the month of February.A distinct improvement had occurred in almost all sections of the Nottingham hosiery trade.      The season was opening out well,  in both men&apos;.s and women1 s underwear;    the better qualities of silk and artificial silk hose and fancy ha If-hose were in good demand, whilst outwear departments were busy. The cheaper qualities of laces were being bought in consider-able quantities, smart novelty lines  in silk and cotton mistures being especially in evidence.     As regards export trade, more orders were coming along from the Overseas Dominions, particularly Australia, but the position in other overseas markets could  only be described as quiet.LORE&apos; GA INF ORD wrote : -&quot;On the whole,  it Is probable that the customary seasonal expansion is proceeding normally.     Most of the staple trades  , record improvement and the fall in the unemployment figures in the middle of V-arch was impressive.      The outlook for the future, however, continues uncertain.     The monetary situation in the United States grows more rather than less disturbing. It seems difficult to see how the measures which are being taken to check Stock Exchange speculation over there can be prevented from reacting sooner or later on American trade and prices, and through them on international prices.      The picture cf abundant prosperity in the United States which Is at the moment being exhibited to the world is not without Its ominous features, notably the falling off in building contracts and increasing unemployment.     Moreover,  In our own country the adverse effect^ on industrial development of the increase in the Bank Rate to 5%% has still to be experienced, though the Bank of Ehgland appears to be doing all in its power to mitigate it.&quot;
GENERAL TRADE (OOftTP.).Co-operative Wholesale Society.MR. HAYHURST stated that the Society&apos;s sales In March were satisfactory;    while one or two sections had shown slight decreases, the aggregate trade had been well maintained.    In the banking department, the number of depositors had increased and the turnover indicated increased savings by working people Their bank&apos;s assets showed an increase of over  12,000,000 in the half year just closed as compared with the corresponding half year of 1926.In New Zealand the Society had made an arrangement with the producers under which it had put down a capital of  120,000 to extend the producers1 factories with a view to bringing their butter and cheese here, where there was a very large market for their produce.    In dried fruits there had been satisfactory sales.    The flour market had been somewhat quiet.    In bacon and hams, a firm tone had prevailed.    In the tea market,  of course, everybody was waiting for the budget statement.    The market at home had, however, shown renewed strength since the date of Mr. Hayhurst&apos;s last report, all descriptions of tea having made some advance in price.    The strongest demand had been for the cheap and medium blends which were -fd. a lb. dearer.    With regard to the rumoured changes of duty, if the duty was taken off Empire tea he was afraid the benefit would not be passed on.DISTRIBUTING TRADES.SIR WOODMAN BURBIDGE pointed out that last year Easter fell in April, while it fell at the end of March this year. March, 1929, had, therefore, the benefit of the pre-Easter trade, but owing to the holidays it had three working days les this year than March,  1928.    Moreover, the Easter trade appeared to have been somewhat slow in starting.    Retail business at the beginning of the month was not as good as had been anticipated, although of course conditions improved very considerably as the month wore on, with better weather and the approach of Easter.    In the case of the West End stores the comparison was, if anything, in favour of March 1928;. Within this area piece goods had been some 7 per cent down, women&apos;s wear about the same percentage up, men&apos;s wear about level, and boots and shoes down.    Furniture also did not appear to have sold very well, and only one increase had been reported.    The concerns in the outer area of London generally had a similar experience, although their figures made a slightly better showing.The reports from the North were, generally speaking, much more favourable,  and in Liverpool especially retail trade appeared to have done well.    In piece goods there was an average increase    in trade of some 12 per cent, while in women&apos;s wear the increase was much more marked.    Several store had reported improvement in sales by from 20 to 30 per cent, and the average was about 20 per cent.    From the South of England cheerful reports had also been received,although the stores which reported pointed out that in their view the
DISTRIBUTING TRADES  (CONTD.)improvement had been due almost wholly to the incidence of Easter trade this year In March, and would probably be counteracted by corresponding reductions next month.     Women&quot; s wear again provided the best showing,  increases of up to 20 per cent, being reported from several centres.SHIPPING.MR. ALEXANDER SHAW observed that taking 1920 as equal to 100, the index number of shipping freights for February, 1929, was 28.25 as against 28.54 for January of this year and 24.5 for February last year.     As compared with 1913 at 100 the figures for February, 1929, were 120.73, for January, 1929, 121.9., and for February, 1928, 104.70.      The tonnage laid up in the United Kingdom on.the 1st January, 1929, was 329,771 tons, whereas on October 1st of last year there were 415,399 tons laid up.      (These and other figures are given in the table at the end of this   section   ).The experiment with pulverised coal for certain boilers on the Hororata had been so successful that the ship was to be converted to use pulverised coal throughout.     Experiments were also being undertaken on shore, not for shore installations but for marine installations, with a new type of modified Scotch boiler both with oil and pulverised coal, and the data to hand so far pointed to the fact that, except in Atlantic trades where oil could be had very cheaply, there would be for modified Scotch boilers and pulverised coal with the latest type of turbines a monetary saving of upwards of 40 per cent, in fuel, as against oil burnt under Scotch boilers XV ITH reciprocating machinery which had been the more usual system before.,  THE PRESIDENT   observed that this matter was of grea^, importance to us as a ooal-producing country.      The publication of information would no doubt be&apos; considered as soon as the proper time came.MR. SHAW said that this was still In the experimental stage, though prospects were bright.     Difficulties which had occurred up to date had been successfully overcome, though some had seemed insurmountable at first.      Indeed, in the case of large passenger ships the difficulty of coaling still remained, and there the balance might be turned in favour of oil, but for cargo ships the prospects seemed favourable.MR. WARHAM pointed out that ships had, so far, been converted to the use of pulverised coal rather than designed for It, and that had always been a hindrance.;   but he understood that some steamers were now being designed from the first to use powdered fuel.MR. SHAW then referred to a proposal last autumn to raise outward freights to Australia roughly by 10 per cent, over all, which had been agreed with exporting interests in this country. A delegation headed by Sir Alan Anderson had gone to Australia and a conference had been arranged between them and a committee representing commercial interests In the Commonwealth.    Certified figures relating to the cargo trade for the last three years had been produced and had shown that trade with Australia had been carried on at a severe loss.      It was hoped that a number of matters^might be so arranged that there would, after all, be no necessity to make an Increase in freights.     Shipowners owed a
SHIPPING (CONTD. )great debt of gratitude to Mr. Bruce and the Australian commercial Interests for meeting them in the.most friendly way, and nothing but good seemed likely to result.- SIR FREDERICK YOUNG said that he was very much interested in the statement made by Mr. Shaw, and thought a e-reat deal of good could come from this mission that had gone to Australia from the shipping interests here.MR. RICHMOND referred to a paper by Mr. J. Johnson, of the Canadian Pacific, which should have considerable effect in restoring confidence in the economic possibilities of steam. Mr. Johnson was an advocate of high pressure,  - high temperature steam installations, - and in a series of comparisons which had been made not from- estimates but from actual working records, he showed that In the majority of cases which he cited the advantage lay with the steamship as against the motor propelled vessel.     His paper would certainly have an important influence on shipowners who had services and conditions of a similar type : to meet, and was probably the most convincing contributiou,.that had yet been made to the steam versus Diesel question.The Bauer Wach and similar systems were also making progress, and there appeared to be a recession in the tide of Diesel engine construction.     Pulverised fuel developments, for &apos;&quot; marine purposes were, as the Council had already been informed., proceeding on various lines, were being watched with Interest, and giving encouraging results. .MR. ALEXANDER SHAW asked whether Mr. Johnson had not confined himself rather to the larger vessels, and indicated &quot;that with the smaller cargo vessel of a few-thousand tons the Diesel might still be the best proposition from a financial point of view?MR. RICHMOND replied that he had certainly made the qual-Ification that for certain services there was an advantage In the Diesel engine.      It seemed indeed to be becoming more and more apparent &quot;that,  in some conditions of bunkering and facilities-at different ports for oil, the Diesel engine would probably be the more    economical, but for the larger Atlantic services, to which Mr. Johnson had referred, his results certainly showed that the high pressure water tube boiler installation&apos;was the more economical.TABLE HANDED IN BY MR. ALEXANDER SHAW.INDEX NUMBER OF SHIPPING FREIGHTS .and1920 - 100. 1913  - 100.February,  1929  ..........        28.25 120.73January,  1929 ...........        28.54 121.97February,  1928...........       24.50 104.70Tonnage laid up at the principal ports of Great Britain Ireland.British and Foreign.&apos; &quot;ki .o     k o x&quot;i s *January 1st,  1929........ ^2^57771&quot;October 1st,  1928........ 415,399January 1st, 1928........ 371,674
CONFIDENTIAL. SHIPPING  (CONTD.) TABLE HANDED IN BY MR.  ALEXANDI,R SKA&apos;( CONrfD. )TONNAGE UNDER CONSTRUCTION.Gross tons.December 31st, 1928.  In GreatBritain andIreland.Abroad1,242,794 1,575 ,207 2,618,001September 30th, 1928.In GreatBritain and . Ireland. Abroad1,089,760 1,431,5822,521,342December 31st, 1927. In GreatBritain andIreland.Abroad.1,579,7131,559,0083,118,721TONNAGE LAUNCHED.Quarter endedDecember 31st,1928. September 3Oth,1923. December 31st,1927.TONNAGE COMMENCED. Quarter endedDecember 51st,1928. September 30th, 1923. December 31st,1927.Gt,Britain &amp; Ireland.245,375 387,572 493,550Gt.Britain &amp; Ireland.431,758 244,591 377,492Gross tons.Abroad.252,000 443,927 337,073Gross tons.Abroad.248,969 252,989 258,595Total.507,875 831,499 835,623Total.630,727 497,580 636,188RAILWAY TRAFFIC.SIR JOSIAH STAMP wrote  :-&quot;A comparison of the railway traJTfic receipts of the four Groups for the first quarter of this year, i.e., 13 weeks ending 51st March, 1929, with the corresponding period of last year is disturbed by the fact that this year the period includes the Stood Friday week which fell later last year.&quot;Passenger Train Receipts.      The passenger revenue of the Great Western is the same as the corresponding period^in 1928,, and the Southern show an improvement of  59,000 or 1.73$.      The London Midland and Scottish and London and. North Eastern receipts are less by  45 , 000 ( 0.75,2)  and  65,000 (1.63$) respectively, and the total for the four Groups shows a decrease of  51,000 or 0.32$.
RAILWAY TRAFFIC (COITTD.)&quot;Merchandise , Other Minerals apd Live JStookL   Rec eipts shew a further decres.se,  the total for the f our &quot;Groups being  1,209,100 or 7.06$ below last year,  the individual companies figures being:-		 	%L. M. S.   * .. *    . * * *	o. a. *	618,100	8.07L . N . E *   * * *     . . .	a    f   *	16 ,000	7.45G.W.       ......	*   a   a	102,000	3.59Southern.....	m  * w	73,000	7.09Total	m   a   a	1,209,100	7.06&quot;Coal and Coke Traffic.    The improvement in this class of  traffic is more than maintained,  the total increase in receipts for the four Groups being  936,100 or 10.29$.    Each company has shared in this increase to the following extent:		 	/*		375,100	10,01-Li o - I * iit a       a   *   a            *   a, a	a. a  a	357,000	10.65G *.vJ: *                a   a   a            a   a   *	a. a  a	136,000	8.59Southern	a   a   a	67,000	15.83Total	a   a   a	936,100	10 .29&quot;Taking the receipts from all traffics, the Great Western and Southern Companies show increases of  34,000 (0.49$) and  53,000 (1.10$) while the London Midland and Scottish and London and North Eatern   Companies receipts are less by  287,000  (l.65;i)  and  124,000  (0.96$) respectively.    The total of the four Groups shows a decrease of  324,000 or 0.77$&quot;.SIR CYRIL HURCOMB sent the following statement:-&quot;During the five /reeks ended 31st March, 1929, the railway receipts,  compared with the corresponding period in 1928, show an increase of  332,000, made up as follows:- .Passenger Train Traffic. Increase.        430,000Freight Train Traffic.Merchandise and Minerals. Decrease. 547,300Goal,  Coke &amp; Patent Fuel. Increase. 449,300For the 13 weeks ended 51st March, 1929, the decrease was  324,000, arrived at as under:-Passenger Train Traffic. Decrease 51,000Freight Train TrafficMerchandise and Minerals. Decrease 1,209,100Coal,  Coke &amp; Patent Fuel. Increase. 936,100
RAILWAY TRAFFIC  (CONTD.)It is necessary to bear in mind that the figures for 1929 include a part of the Easter passenger train traffic, whereas in 1928, no portion of such traffic Is included.&quot;The latest detailed statistics available are for the month of January, 1929.      Compared with the corresponding period in 1928 passenger journeys (excluding the London Tubes and Metropolitan District Railway)  increased by over 800,000, due to the continued Increase in cheap ticket travel.     Freight traffic increased by about 2t million tons or 9-f per cent,  coal, coke and patent fuel accounting for l.,930,000 tons or three-fourths of the total increase.      Other commodities which show marked Increases are - Iron Ore, 12%,, Pig Iron, 15%., Iron and Steel, 11%,, Machinery, 6$., Bricks, 15%., Stone, 12%*, and Manure (packed) 25/*.     There was an additional working day in January this year&quot;.EMPLOYMENT.MR. PHILLIPS observed that the chief feature in the unemploy-ment returns during March was the sharp recovery as soon as the frost came to an end.      The highest figure during the frost was 1,458,000 on 18th February.      The figure on 25th March was 1,133,000, a reduction of 325,000.     Of this total reduction, some 140,000 cr 150,000 had to be discounted, because it represented persons thrown out by the frost.     But it left a balance of 180,000 in a period of five weeks, which was reasonably satisfactory.     The total, however, was still about 100,000 above last year.In accordance with the usual experience, there might be found to have been some slight increase - he hoped only a temporary one - round about Easter.     Last year the figures began to take a turn for the worse just after Easter, but this was unusual and there was no apparent reason why it should be repeated this year.      Tho average number unemployed during the four weeks ended 25th March was 1,242,890.Mr. Phillips handed in the following table of Insured persons in employment.     During March there had been an increase of about a quarter of a million.
EMPLOYMENT  (CONTD.)Monthly Stailst1cs of Insured persons aged 16 to 64 In employment.i Estimated! number of date! Insuredi persons.Number ofinsuredpersons (including tw i  months file i   of lodged i    books.)Difference be twooh columns 2 and o (to nearest hundred) .I) 8.mar. apr.May Jane(3)11,608,000 11,617,000 11,526,000 11,629^000July ! ll,636,000f(4)lug.Septoct.rev.see.19.11,643,proof ll,656,proof 11,658,proof 11,666,proof 11,674,00OfJan. j 11,682,000ti?eb. jll,690,000fif.Iar. ill,698,OOOfi I--1__.1,095,858 1,093,158 1,123,989 1,225,150- i1,322,560   ji1,324,311   Ii1,304,390   ! 1,356,037 1,407,800   I 1,290,4001,421,800 1,412,800 1,165,40010,512,100 10,523,800 10,502,000 10,403,900 10,513,400 10,318,700 10,545,600 10,302,000 10,258,200 10,383,60010,260,200 10,277,200 10,532,600Estimated number of insured persons in employment after deducting from col.4 3jg per cent, of numbers in column 2 to allow for sickness     and other unrecorded non-employment, exclusive of temporary holidays^__Includingpersons directly involved in trade disputes. 15)__10,105,800 10,117,200 10&quot;, 095,100 9,995,800 9,906,100 9,911,200 9,937,800 9,894,000 9,849,900 9,975,0009,851,300 9,868,000 10,123,200rExcludingpersons directly involved In tradedisputes. _______(6) _____10,100,800 10,116,200 10,092,100 9,975,800 9,905,100 9,910,200 9,934,800 9,892,000 9,846,900 9,974,0009,848,300 9,866,000 10,114,200The sickness rate has been taken at an estimated annual mean; it has not been possible to allow for seasonal variations.t Provisional figure.
AUSTRALIAN TRADE.SDR FREDERICK YOUNG reported that about 10% of the total wool clip had now been sold.      Throughout Japan had proved a very consistent buyer, with keen competition also from the home trade in Australia.     A firmer tons had generally been noted in the March sales.Shipments of flour during the present season amounted to 152,600 tons as compared with 96,500 tons for the corresponding period of last year.     Freights for flour had been somewhat lower lately.     Yfrieat shipments to date had been 41,487,000 bushels as against 16,694,000 for the corresponding period last year.     Large shipments of apples were made during March from Tasmania and Western Australia, a good proportion going to Hamburg.      Immediate, prospects as regards primary production for 1929 were very favourable owing to timely and bounteous rains.      In Queensland, for instance, splendid rains had occurred In nearly all districts, and if followed by further rain during April, there should be a substantial recovery from the severe drought which had been prevailing there for some years.      This satisfactory opening of the season should have an early influence on trade to the benefit of this country.      In finance, the bank clearances from 1st January to 25th February were 379 millions as compared to 368 millions during the same period last year.SIR HUGO HIRST said that he had proposed to say something about the mission to Australia, of which he had been a member, but in view of the lateness of the hour, he would defer It till the next meeting of the Council,      Their report dealt mainly with problems that the Australians would have to settle for themselves.      But they had come back with messages to the different industries, based on their experience, and he thought it would be appropriate to lay before the Council their suggestions for the improvement of our business with that Dominion.INDIAN TRADE.MR. GREEN mentioned that since the Council last met the Indian budget had been debated and approved.      No additional taxation had been imposed, apart from an increase of 2 annas per gallon in the customs and excise duties on petrol.      The additional tax, which was estimated to yield over  620,000 in the first year, would not go to general revenue, but 4o the newly constituted Road Fund.      Capital expenditure on railways during the ensuing year was estimated at  19 million, apart from some  5 million which would be required for the purchase of the Southern Punjab Railway.Imports during the 11 months ended February,  1929, had increased by 1%% in Value and exports by 3%.      The net Imports of gold and sliver had advanced by over  1-J million and totalled  22fj million for the 11 months.     The visible balance of trade for the period, taking into account both merchandise and gold and silver, was nearly  35 million in favour of India,
INDIAN TRADE (CONTD . )and  2-g- Tr-HHon higher than last year.      The total remittances made by the Government of India to the Secretary of State for the year ending 31st March, 1929, came to nearly  31 million, all obtained by purchase of sterling in India.      In the ensuing year it was anticipated that the Secretary of State&apos;s require-rnsnts would be rather higher.The chief feature of  the trade of India during the last few months had been the recovery In the export of raw cotton. Not only had Japan and China bought much more heavily than last season, but shipments to the Continent of Europe and to this country had improved remarkably.      Exports for the present season from 1st September last to 21st March were up by more than hQ% In quantity.      Nevertheless, the stock at Bombay was 1,156,000 bales,  or a quarter of a million bales higher than this time last year.The movements of wheat were also interesting.      Last year&apos;s crop was poor and India had to import, and is still importing, very considerable quantities.      The area under wheat this year was slightly less than last, but the output would probably be better,The final rice forecast issued recently estimated an increased production, the improvement over last year being put at 3I million tons.      In the past year the export trade in rice had been doing badly, but it was hoped that the size of the new crop and the fall in prices would stimulate exports.Developments in the import trade of India had not been very favourable to the United Kingdom.     During the past ten months India&apos;s  Imports of articles mainly or wholly manufactured had fallen in value by nearly  400,000.      Cotton yarns and manufactures alone had declined by  if million, and this was all the more remarkable because production in India had fallen off, largely owing to labour disputes in Bombay,      Under grey goods the United Kingdom had lost trade in the same period worth  IV3 million.      The chief reason for this decline was the question of prices.      In the slump which follo-wed the war boom, Indian merchants were badly hit and had not even yet any confidence In the stability of prices.      They would,  therefore, only buy from hand to mouth.Imports from this country of white and coloured goods and yarns were rather better, hut they did not make up for the losses in the grey trade.      Imports of machinery of all sorts had improved, with no small advantage  to this country, being  It  million higher.      Nevertheless,  the United Kingdom share in the import trade of India, which before the war was sixty per cent., was still declining;    in 1924 It was fifty-four per cent.,  in 1926 forty-nine and a half per cent., and In this last calendar year it was a little more than forty-six per cent. That, he thought, was also due to prices more than anything else .
? ft 9(d u fvINDIAN TRADE  (CONTD. )The new King George&apos;s Dock,  Calcutta, had teen opened; arid the Port Trust of Bombay had made a considerable reduction in their charges, - their surtax of fifty per cent, had been lowered to thirty-three and one-third per cent., which meant a reduction in charges of no less than eleven per cent.RUSSIAN TRADE.MR. HAYHURST mentioned that in view of the renewed interest In the subject of trade with Russia, following the visit of the trade delegation, he had got out some figures of the Co-operative /Tholesale Society&apos;s trade with Russia during the last five years.      In 1924 they had made bank advances amounting to about  -y  million.      In 1925 these advances  on transactions the terms of which were 20 per cent,  cash and 80 per cent, credit for six months, amounted to  3 if- millions and in 1927 to  8 millions.      The total of the whole transactions which the Society had had with Russia In the five years,  in advances and in commodities, was    about  29 millions, and  271? millions had be e n re pa id .SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE .MR. HOSE wrote to the following effect :-&quot;Mail advices indicate that in Argentine the maize crop has been rather severely affected by the&quot;&quot;dry weather, and it is possible that the yield may be 30 to 40 per cent, less than last year.     The lack of rain, however, has assisted the farmers with their threshing operations, and has facilitated the carting of wheat to the stations.      The economic situation remains intrinsically sound, and prospects for autumn trade activities are favourable.      Conditions in the markets for imported textile goods are unchanged, although it is to be noted that the collection of drafts Is taking place with increased facility. There appears a superabundance of agents and representatives  of Manchester, Bradford, and Nottingham firms, and competition has latterly been further increased by a southward movement of firms from Brazil, this having, been brought about by the increase in Customs duties in that country.      Some uncertainty is expressed in regard to the Argentine labour situation, and in certain directions the workmen show a disposition to bring forward demands for higher wages.&quot;in general, the volume of trade  in Chile during February was maintained, although retail sales in some directions showed signs of restriction.      Trading conditions, however, may be described as fundamentally sound, and the activity in the import markets would n pr-ear to indicate anticipations of an increased retail demand during the approaching autumn and winter seasons.      With the Improvement in weather conditions in Europe, the demand for Chilean nitrate of soda has become more active,
CONFIDENTIAL. ^OUTH AMERICAN TRADE  (CONTD.)next coffee crop is expected to be adversely affected by the intensely hot summer which has been experienced, the yield will probably be satisfactory.     Steps are being taken to organise a local Bolsa In Bogota, and the proposal has been well received, as it is hoped that it will encourage the formation of limited companies and that commerce will benefit thereby.&quot;At the present time, a revolutionary movement of a reputed serious character is taking place in Mexico. The Government Is   adopting energetic measures to suppress the revolt, and, apparently, in this connection, valuable support is being accorded by the supply of munitions by the United States.    These periodical upheavals, however, do not appear to affect in a widespread manner the ordinary everyday commercial and industrial life of the country, the general attitude being that of leaving the politicians and place-seekers to settle their own quarrels.    Nevertheless, these recurrent disputes must necessarily be  costly and impede considerably the economic progress of the Republic.&quot;There has recently been a steady demand for Guatemalan coffee, principally from Europe,  and producers apparently&quot;have had no difficulty in effecting sales.    Coffee has been moving freely to the ports,  and Increased steamer space has been available, so that there has not been the same congestion as in previous years .&quot;In Salvador,  the present Government has been.In office two years, and martial law, which was brought Into force on the occasion of the attempted political revolt in December, 1927, has now been withdrawn.    In regard to the trade situa-tion,the satisfactory conditions ruling during January con-tinued throughout the following month.    In particular, a rapid export movement of coffee was in evidence.&quot;Reports recently to hand indicate that the yield of coffee in Nicaragua this  season will be even less than had been anticipated&quot;, excessive rain, which has proved very destructive, having been experienced in the Metagalpa and Jinotega districts.
CONFIDENTIAL .-SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE  (CONTD.)and heavy deliveries are now taking place,  those for the second half of March having shown an increase of some 66,000 tons on the total for the corresponding period of last year.&quot;Trading conditions  in Brazil remain quiet, and it is significant that in Sao Paulo, the  chief centre of the national textile industry, stocks of imported goods are stated to he generally sufficient to meet requirements, and no considerable demand appears likely to arise for some time.      In view of the haste with which imports were made towards the end of 1928 and during the early part of the current year, so that shipment? should arrive before the application of the new Customs duties on cotton textiles, the position must be regarded as somewhat unsatisfactory;    in consequence, more than usual caution Is desirable at the present time on the part of exporters to the Brazilian markets.      The exceptionally heavy rains which have recently occurred in Brazil have fortunately not caused any considerable damage In the coffee plantations, which have,  in fact,  in some areas, benefited from the wet weather.      The Sao Paulo Railway, on which a large proportion of the coffee is moved, was flooded for a considerable distance, but the Company new has a full service running to Santos on a line constructed on a new level.      The old line is still out of use, and appears likely to remain so for some weeks.&quot;Business conditions in Peru are seasonally dull, and import orders are being restricted to those necessary to cover immediate requirements.      This state of affairs may continue into July, when the income derived from cotton exports normally increases the purchasing power of the agriculturists.    Drought has recently been experienced in the Republic, and It  is feared that this, combined with lack of sun, may reduce the yield of the cotton crop.      In the sugar plantations also, the  cane is suffering from lack of sun and water, although it is satisfactoi to observe that the latest advices received by mail state that the drought has broken.&quot;Trade conditions in Uruguay are generally satisfactory, although the maize and fruTE crops have suffered damage from drought.      The feature of Uruguayan conditions during the past few months has been a heavy influx of tourists,  largely from Argentina, which has stimulated sales of summer goods.      Import continue to take place steadily.&quot;it is reported that approximately 30 per cent, of the Venezuelan coffee crop has now been delivered in Caracas, but, owing to the poor interest shown by the European markets, and the reticent attitude of  the local sellers, who anticipate a higher level of prices, very few sales have been taking place. Apparently, however, exports are shortly expected to commence on a large scale.      Rumours have been current that the cocoa crop will not be as good as was  at first anticipated, but up to the present such reports have not been confirmed.&quot;in Colombia, progress is being made with an extensive programme of public works, but it is understood  that In some instances construction will have to be postponed, as negotiations by the Government for a foreign loan to provide the required additional funds have failed to fructify for the time being.     Dear- money in the New York market is obviously hindering the securing of loans at reasonable rates.      Basic commercial conditions, however, are sound, and, although the
LATEST STATISTICAL (Inform at ion r s c 3lved up to cir c i]Latest.a month ear11sr.Sew Canital Issues in Great ^Britain (midland Ban]-: statement) -United Kingdom purposes.. Overseas purposes........ March 24,774,000 &quot;        9,007,000Total......lank Clearings :Country Cheque and provincial week ended......percentages of Advances toDeposits  (London clearing banks)......................Money Market:Bank Rate...................Market Rate 3 months &apos;Bank Bills..................Discount  (3 months treasury bills).....................IFrices: Wholesale:  &quot;Boardof Trade&quot; Index Wo.   (1924* 100):Food.......................MateriaIs..................Total......................Railway receipts we^k ended -Goods&apos;Traffic  (Gross).......Passenger Traffic (Gross).. . ^External Trade:Net Imports.................I British Exports.............Net Imports of Raw Materials-I [Shipping - Entrances andClearances    with cargoes inthe Foreign TradeEntrances....... o.........Clearances................IShipbuilding: Vessels under construction&quot;1-World.....................United Kingdom............I Vessels commenced -World.....................United Kingdom............j^essels laid up in United I Kingdom Ports:British...................Foreign...................pmployment -Unemployed on Live Register (inc.persons on short time receiving benefit)........33,781,000Production; Coal output during weekended......................Pig Iron output in month....,&apos;    Average par day..........Crude Steel output in month.Apl.13 92,237, 000Mar chApl.1956.1Os/o3,5i - 5/L$  5.  2.1.07dMarch 11Apl.13March 112,Mar^h 11Mar.31 11Jan. - Mar. 11jan.1st 1190.3 81.2 84.3  .082,800 1,360,600&amp; *88,606,877 58,623,357 22,844,804Net tons. 4,575,256 5,510,460Gross ton:2,837,8121,357,375660,639 362,358Net tons. 311,657 18,114Apl.15Wholly unemployed Others849,783 303,752 .26,183,000 6,86-?:, 00033,047,00089,927,000.    54.2Dg/o55A6 - 5fg  5.   5.   1.71d.89.4 80.0 83.3  .2,163,000 lj251,00081,048,458 55,664,975 21, 03 0, 047Net tons.&apos; 3;913,36 2 4,619,285Gross  tons Dec. 31    2,618,001 jldaa1,242,794 IIOct.-Dec. 680,727 jjanj &quot; 431,758 I1,153,535Apl. 6MarchTons.3,702,100 590,500 19,000 859, 900Net tons. ! 1st  Oct.     412,365 i 1928. 3,036 I893,510 I 283,94i I1,182,454 ITons.5,526,300 519,600 18,600 774,900-::-Inclu&apos;i.tonnage on wh
:.&apos;VL DATA.[irculation of Minutes)At corresponding date inJ:               1928.	1927.	1924.1            18,652,000 23, 044, 000	 . 27,738,000 6,976,000	 . 6,589,000 6,735,00041,696,000	34,714,000	13,324,000if ? 81,772,000 la!	 . 79,325,000	88,619,000ii 1!                  55.3 b1	55. 5	*i8.8: i 1!                          ala/		4^16^ Ij	3i:L/l6 -	3-yi6/ &apos;!i        4.  1.  1.58d. I	 3.  12.11.86d.	 2.17.  8.3d.li       91,4 81. 1 f i               84.6 1                    . 1, 630, 100 1              1,615,900	08.4 82.8 84.7  . 1,863,100 2,041,300 n	97.3 100.8 99. 6  . 2,202,100 1,474,900 r*99,249,943 64,958,123 1            27,151,400	3j * 102,728,076 62,114,146 28,978,006	 . 90,995,056 61,102,767 24,150,6551 Net tons. 1             4,74-1,450 I             5,380,611 1	Net tons. 4,813,308 5,380,093	Net tons. 4,107, 031 5,102,470is . Gros s tons .Par. 31,1928  2,89c, 251 &quot; 1,440,012Gross tons [Mar. 31,1927 2,569,864 &quot; 1,216,932I Jan.-Mar605,423 Jan.-Mar.   946,865! Jan.-Mar.  431,606341,843Net tons. 359, 32.12,346760,519 325,255&apos;1,083,774Tons.4,345,500 592,600 19,100 793,300Gross tons. Mar. 31,1924 2,516,504 &quot; 1,473,629579,839;Net tons. 352,416 12,456701,338 405,1021,106,4-0Tons .5, 294,400 671,800 21,7C0 949,600227,786Net tons. 605,535 24,. 1781,039, 190 Tons.5,851,900 668,600 21,600 816,900Bwhich work was suspended.
TABLES ILLUSTRATING THE ECONOMIC POSITION IN THE UNITED KINGDOM.Table I. General-- - -			monthly averages.										items.		unit of measurement.	1924.	1927.	1928.	oct.-dec., 1927.	jan.-march, 1928.	april-june, 1928.	july-sept., 1928.	oct.-dec., 1928.	feb., 1928.	jan., 1929.	feb., 1929.At .													1. new Capital Issues.													(midland bank statements)-													(a) united kingdom purposes		million  &apos;s.	7-4	14-7	18-3	17-2	18-5	20-0	12-4	21-6	22-6	18-0	26-2((,) overseas purposes ...			11-2	11-0	11-9	20-4	16-0	12-5	9-8	9-5	5-3	29-4	7-1total-all purposes			18-6	28-3	80-2	37-0	34-5	33 1	22-2	31-1	27-9	47-4	33-3 per cent, of 1924 ...			100	141	162	202	1S5	177	119	167	150	255	1792. bank Clearings.													(country cheque and provincial)-													average amount daily ...		million  &apos;s.	15-5	15-8	15-4	15-7	15-6	15-6	14-6	15-5	15-5	15-9	15-aPer cent, of 1924 ..			100	08-3	98-9	101-4	100-6	100-5	94-3	100 1	99-8	102-4	100-23. Postal   Receipts   average amount daily   ......		thousand  &apos;s	115	126	131	139	120	125	125	146	122	125	120Per cent, of 1924 ..			100	110	114	121	no	109	109	128	107	109	1054 Wholesale Prices Board or Trade Index Number		-	100	85-2	84-4	84-9	84-6	86-1	83-8	83-1	84-3	83-2	83-35. Railways-Freight   Traffic (great britain).													(a) coal, coke and patent fuel Per cent, of 1924 ......		million net ton miles.	825 100	789 os-e	722 S7-B	774 93-8	782 04-8	000 80-0	098 84-5	743 90-7	73S 49-5	S45 102-5	(6) other minerals and general merchandise			763	7S1	-; 57	775	757	754	74S	708	740	747	- (1)Per cent, of 1924  ..			100	102-4	991	101-5	99-2	98-8	97-9	100-6	97-7	97-8	-6. Shipping - Entrances   and Clearances with cargoes iu the foreign trade 								-					(a) entrances ...		million net tons	4-61	505	5-03	5-03	4-50	5-14	5-32	5-20	4-17	4-67	3-91Per cent, of 1924 .			100	109-4	109-0	109-0	97-5	111-3	115-2	111-9	90-4	101-3	84-8(*) clearances ...		,,	5-44	5-29	5-87	5-17	6-04	5-35	5-64	5-46	4-77	5-41	4-62Per cent, of 1924 .			100	97-2	98-7	95-0	92-5	98-4	103-7	100-3	87-6	99-4	84-97. Shipping Freights-chamber of shipping index (2)													Per cent, of 1924  .			100	93-8	87-0	92-5	84-2	82-4	85-6	96-2	82-7	96-3	95-.38. External Trade-													(a) Net Imports value as de-clared		million  &apos;s.	94-8	91-3	89-7	95-4	92-2	87-1	85-6	94-0	87-2	106-3	81-0value at 1924 prices   ... Per cent, of 1924......		&apos;:&apos;r&apos;..	94-8 100	105-4 111-2	102-3 107-9	100-9 112-8	105-3 1111	101-6 107-2	94-8 100-0	107-81 113-7.	(3)	(3)	(8) t(6) British Exports   declared	value as	,,	66-7	59-1	60-3	68-5	60-6	57-8	59-9	02-8	57-2	66-9	55-7value at 1924 pricey   ... Per cent, of 1924 ......		-M	66-7 100	68-3 102-3	69-8 104-6	73-8 110-6	70-2 105-1	67-1 100-5	69 0 103-3	73-2&quot;) 109-6.	(3)	(3)	(3)(-o) Net Imports of Raw Mate-rials value as declared   ...		II	27-0	23-4	22 -4	23-3	25-3	21-3	19-3	23-6	23-8	33-9	21-0value at 1924 prices   ... Per cent, of 1924......			27-0 100	30-6 1130	27-8 101-3	28-9 107-3	29-9 110-7	26 O 98-7	22-3 82-7	80-51 113-2.	(3)	(3)	(3):9. Employment (great britain).													(a) estimated number of ln-sured workers (aged 10-04) in employment (4)		millions	9-51	10-00	9-97	10-03	10 01	10-05	9-91	9&apos;00&quot;			. Per cent, of 1924			100	105-1	104-8	105-4	195-2	105-6	104-2	104-0.			-  (6) numbers of insured workers (aged 16-64) unemployed ...		thousands	1,135	1,118	1,247	1,131	1,173	j   1.147	1,317	1,351	1,195	1,422	1,413per cent of 1924			100	9S-5	i   109-9	99-6	103-3	1   101-1	116-0	119-0	105-3	125-1	124-5									1				(1) information not yet available. (2) published by courtesy of the Chamber of Shipping of the United Kingdom and of the Statist company, limited.lhe calculation of the value of the imports and exports at 1924 prices is only made quarterly.   (4) allowance is made for sickness, eto., and for trade disputes.a:   (302)739(089)  \vt 275-3S53   250   4/29   easBeprinted from The board op Trade Journal, dated March 28, 1929.
TABLES ILLUSTRATING THE ECONOMIC POSITION IN THE UNITED kingdom table II. Paetictjlar Trades.		Monthly Averages.										Items.	Unit of Measurement.	1924.	1927.	1928.	Oct-Dec, 1927.	Jan.-March, 1928.	April-June, 1928.	July-Sept., 1928.	Oct-Dec, 1928.	Feb., 1928.	Jan., 1929.	Ecb.. 1929.1. Coal Mining  (ii) Quantity of saleable coal raised Per cent, of 1924.......	Mill, tons	22-3 100	20-9 94-1	19-8 89-0	20-9 93-7	21-4 96-3	18-9 85-1	18-4 82-9	20-4 91-8	20-7 92-8	22-4 100-8	21-1 94-e(5) Quantity of coal cxport-ed (1)............ Per cent, of 1924......	Mill, tons	5-14 100	4-26 83-0	4-17 81-2	4-05 78-9	4-01 78-0	4-18 81-5	4-14 80-7	4-35 84-6	4-01 78-0	4-47 87-0	3-89 75-1(c) Percentage     of    Insured Workers wholly unemployed Percentage    of    Insured &quot;Workers Temporarily stopped		M	10-9 7-5	14-5 7-7	11-5 6-6	12-3 5-6	14-0 7-6	16-1 10-0	15-7 7-5	12-4 6-1	15-3 3-8	13-3 j-52. Iron and Steel  (a) Crude Steel Output Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, tons	683 100	758 110-9	710 104-0	668 97-7	728 106-5	702 102-7	678 99-2	734 107-4	764 111-9	765 111-9	783 114-5(b) Pig Iron Output...... Per cent, of 1924  ...	Thou, tons	009 100	008 99-8	551 90-5	577 94-8	568 93-3	573 94-1	520 85-4	543 89-1	551 90-5	564 92-6	520 85-3(c) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		20-6	18-0	21-0	20-7	19-4	20-0	23-2	21-2	18-7	20-1	19-43. General Engineering  Percentage of Insured Workers Unemployed.........		15-9	10-5	9-8	0-7	9-7	9-6	10-0	9-9	9-8	10-9	10-34. Electrical Engineering  (a) BEAMA (2) Index of Pro-duction. Per cent, of 1924...		100	119 -6	89-8	109-0	92-5	84-4	84-1	98-1	91-5	104-1	106-2(6) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		5 0	51	4-9	4-3	4-7	4-8	5-1	50	4-8	6-3	5-45. Shipbuilding in the United Kingdom (3)  (a) Merchant vessels under con-struction at end of Quarter Per cent, of 1924  ...	Mill, gross tons	1-44(4) 100	1-43(4) 99-4	1-24 86-5	1-58 109-8	1-44 100-1	1-20 83-6	1-09 75-7	1-24 86-4	1		(b) Vessels commenced during Quarter      ...... Per cent, of 1924  ......	Thou, gross tons	203 100	441 168-0	324 123-5	377 143-8	342 130-2	279 106-2	245 931	432 164-4	f (3)	(3)	(3)(c) Percentage    of    Insured Workers   in   Shipbuilding, Ship repairing, and Marine Engineering Unemployed ...		27-4	231	23-6	190	18-3	21-5	25-5	28-9	19-0	27-6	23 06. Base Metals  (o) Copper available for con-sumption (5) and (6) Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, tons	9-39 100	11-7 124	11-7 125	121 129	12-4 132	12-3 131	10-6 113	11-7 124	8-6 91	12-0 127	8-3 88(6) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		12-3	10-1	10-0	90	9-5	9-5	10-4	10-7	9-6	10-6	10-77. Cotton  (a) Raw Cotton delivered to Mills............ Per cent, of 1924 ......	Mill. lbs.	118 100	135 115	125 106	125 106	13S 117	125 105	105 89	132 112	136 115	151 128	121 103b) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		13-8	9-1	12-0 -	11-1	9-2	10-9	15-4	12-3	8-7	11-3	11-98. Wool Textile Industry  (a) Index of Wages Paid.   Per cent of 1924 ......... (6) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed		100 7-0	94-7 8-8	92-7 11-2	96-7 6-9	96-2 7-4	95-0 8-9	88-0 14-9	91-6 13-6	96-4 7-6	SS-C 14-4	87-8 13-19. Artificial Silk-Production of Yarn and Waste Per cent, of 1924 ......	Mill. lbs.	2-11 100	3-35 159	4-52 214	3-94 187	4-43 210	4-59 218	4-64 220	4-42 210	4-31 204	4-co 21S	s-95 18710. Natural Silk-Deliveries for Home Consump-tion (7)       ......... Per cent, of 1924 ......	*   Thou. lbs.	180 100	212 118	261 145	253 140	274 152	256 142	227 126	287 160	2s5 158	234 158	261 1451. Crude Rubber, available for consumption (6)       ...... Per cent, of 1924 ......	Thou, tons	1-90 100	3-73 190	4-03 212	4-88 230	4-70 247	2-89 152	3-43 180	5-09 207	6-50 341	5-28	4-73 2482. Building  (a) Plans  approved  by  14G Local Authorities in Great Britain, estimated cost  (i) Dwelling Houses.   Per cent, of 1924   ...... (U) Other Buildings and additions and alterations to   existing  buildings. Per cent, of 1924 (6) Percentage    of    Insured Workers Unemployed : (i) Building    ...... (ii) Public Works Con-tracting, etc.		100 100 10-3 17-0	105-9 11S-9 9-7 17-2	106-5 133-1 12-3 20-S	102-9 118-6 13-4 19-0	103-0 121-8 14-5 21-1	108-3 136-1 9-7 17-8	108-4 134-2 10-0 19-2	100-S 140-4 14-2 23-2	123-7 125-3 15-0 21-ff	90-2 119-4 19-8 20-8	101-2 126-S 24-s 30-9(1) In addition the quantity of eoal shipped as bunkers in the Foreign Trade averaged 1,474,000 tons per month in 1924 and 1,394,000 tons per month 1928. (2) Published by courtesy of the British Electrical and Allied Manufacturers&apos; Association. (3) The figures relating to shipbuilding are acuaggregates for the quarterly periods; monthly figures aro not published.       (4) Including a quarterly average of 62,000 gross tons in 1924 and 11,000 kio&quot; &quot; in 1927 on which work was suspended.    (5) The figures given do not include in the available supply the metal produced from imported ores, matte, etc.    W Net Imports, less additions to warehouse stocks or plus reductions in warehouse stocks. (7) Tho approximate silk content of the cocoons and waste liasestimated at one-third of their full weight.
FLUCTUATIONS DURING THE PERIOD JANUARY 1928- MARCH 1929.
FLUCTUATIONS DURING THE PERIOD JANUARY 1928 - MARCH m%

</content>
</cab>
