<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/31/49 images: 536-541</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1942.SECRET.W.P. (42) 569.December 7, 1942.WAR CABINET.CONVERSATION   WITH   GENERAL   VON   THOMA   ON   JOURNEYBETWEEN CAIRO AND LONDON, NOVEMBER 18-19, 1942.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.I circulate for the information of the War Cabinet and Defence Committeethe annexed account of a conversation between Air Vice-Marshal Collier andGeneral von Thoma on a journey between Cairo and London on the18th/ 19th November, 1942.The conversation resulted from the discovery that General Hierthes, whocommanded a Bavarian Division in the last war and with whom Air Vice-MarshalCollier had studied German in 1932, was an intimate personal friend of.Von Thoma.A. H. M. S.December 7, 1942.General von Thoma spoke very readily on various military and politicalsubjects. After a few minutes&apos; conversation we discovered that we had a mutualfriend in Lieut.-General Hierthes, who commanded a Bavarian Division onthe British front in France in the last war. Von Thoma served in this division.His estate in Bavaria is administered in his absence by General Hierthes, with whom he maintains close contact. While studying German with General Hierthesin 1932, I got to know his political views, which were not favourable to Hitler,but receptive to Hitler&apos;s desire to reinstate Germany. Von Thoma assured meseveral times that his views were similar to those of Hierthes and that they repre-sented the views of the great majority of senior German officers.2. Von Thoma claims to have drawn up the plans for the invasion of theLow Countries and France. As such he came frequently into contact with Hitler,but declares that he always insisted on speaking frankly to him and not with-holding facts displeasing to him. He describes Hitler as greatly overworked andas sharing with most other dictators the tendency to rely on the advice of politicaladherents, who have learnt to tell him only the things he wishes to hear.Von Thoma described the attack on Russia as a great mistake made from politicalmotives. He admitted the similarity of Bolshevik, Nazi and Fascist creeds, butascribed the attack on Russia as due to Hitler&apos;s desire to destroy what he believed,to be the antithesis of the Nazi creed. He referred repeatedly to the enormousstrain which the German Army and the whole German people had had to bear forthe last nine years. The German people were beginning to realise that British and american war production, together with that of Russia, would quickly outstriptheir own output and would then place them in an impossible military position As-soon as the German workman was given time to pause and to realise the failure ofthe Nazi programme, his reaction would be most bitter and there would be acute-trouble in Germany. Von Thoma seemed to assume a victory of the Allies in a notdistant future, and referred to the difficulties of the peace. He repeatedarguments which we have heard ever since 1918 about the danger of holding-Germany down and the (to him) inevitable consequences in the shape of war inf247271Copy- No.
the future. He declared that America was already the only gainer from the war.Her new territories in Northern Africa were clear evidence of this. Whenreminded that the Americans had promised not to remain in these territoriesafter the war, he retorted that, in any case, they would take care to receivecommercial advantages and monopolies in return for their evacuation. It isdifficult to say whether von Thoma was deliberately trying to create mistrustbetween England and America, or whether he was merely speaking his thoughtsaloud.3. He considers Hess to be a rather foolish man, whose knowledge of theBritish from his childhood in Alexandria made him desire to put Anglo-german relations on a good footing. He asserted, but without too great conviction, thatHess did not come to England on the direct instructions of Hitler. He referredto Ribbentrop&apos;s delusion that England would not fight for Poland, and considersthat Pibbentrop&apos;s influence has been a catastrophe for Germany.4.   Von Thoma was in Rome some months ago, where he discovered that thearistocracy and military classes were against the war and were rapidly desertingMussolini.  He thinks that a possible development in Italy will be an anti-Fascistreorganisation under the leadership of the Crown Prince.   He gave credit toMussolini for his services to Italy at the beginning of his rule.  His vital mistakehad been when be became imbued with the desire to lead Italy to victory through a series of wars.   Mussolini had failed to appreciate that an unmilitary people could not produce victorious armies.   In order to maintain good relations with italy, Germany had constantly to make concessions to Italian pride or avarice.. The Southern Tyrol and Croatia were testimony to this.   Von Thoma had certain information that Italy was still pushing forward with all speed the constructionof fortifications on the Brenner.   Large numbers of men, working day and night,were there building a line of fortifications similar to the German defences in western Europe.    In spite of acute shortage of petrol in Germany, largequantities had to be released to Italy.   Consequently, although German doctorshad now to visit patients on foot, Italians could use taxis for pleasure at the cheapest of rates.5. Von Thoma was on the Russian front about a year ago. Before the warwith Russia he had been informed by General Kostring, German Military attache in Moscow, that a German military adventure in Russia would meet with two major difficulties, climate and space. The Red Army had fought magnificentlyagainst the Germans, and their strategic retreats had been carried out with greatprecision and skill of organisation. Russian concealment of their military pre-reparations for this war had been conspicuously successful. The Russian 50-tontank came as a complete surprise to the Germans. German medical preparationshad been carefully and skilfully organised and they had thus been able to keepdown the incidence of sickness. Von Thoma had known Marshal Timoshenko,when the latter had been one of the Russian officers under instruction in the secretRussian Staff College in Berlin in the early twenties. He referred to the enormous:zeal and capacity for work of the Red Army Staff Students.6. Von Thoma&apos;s first acquaintance with Libya occurred when he was sent out by the German General Staff to report on Graziani&apos;s Army. He was receivedvery coldly by Graziani and w^as only able to obtain full information of theposition in the desert because of a personal instruction from Mussolini that hewas to be afforded all facilities. His report after this visit was that the war in libya was a war of supply and communications (&quot; Nachschub &quot;). He held then,and ever since, that victory would go to the side which first organised its supplyadequately. The Germans failed to obtain unity of command. Because of Italiansusceptibilities, supply and 1. of c. remained an Italian responsibility. Theywere not equal to the task of organising proper 1. of c, and, if Italian divisionsfailed to get away from El Alamein, it was the fault of the Italians themselves.Italian equipment was ludicrously antiquated and deficient. The eight Italian-divisions were all quite unsuited to warfare in the desert against an Armyeauinned with modern British and American munitions.ill7. Von Thoma was constantly hampered by lack or shortage of fuel.Italian arrangements for the security of convoys failed repeatedly. The loadingand unloading of ships was done slowly and inefficiently. Recently 80 newItalian tanks had been left standing near the port of unloading for want of fuel.The tragedy was not as great as it seemed, inasmuch as the tanks were badly-designed and constructed and practically worthless for modern war. He had told the Italians that 80 tins of sardines would have suited him better.
8. Were it not for the fuel and supplies obtained in Tobruk, the position ofthe German and Italian armies in the desert would have become acute somemonths ago. The Germans found conditions in the desert most trying. Theywere not suited to warfare under these climatic and geographic conditions.Von Thoma seemed to have little conception of air operations. He referred toour success in capturing communications behind the front and in theMediterranean, but seemed to have no clear-cut views about German air operations and the reasons for their failure.9. The Battle of El Alamein was a battle of material. GeneralMontgomery&apos;s tactics had been similar to those of General Nivelle on the WestFront in 1917. A heavy and carefully planned artillery bombardment hadblasted holes in the Axis lines. An offensive of this nature could be worked outon mathematical lines provided that resources were sufficient (von Thoma seemsto like detailed military plans worked out with mathematical precision. Hisplan for the invasion of France was apparently a series of most detailed timetables for all units). General Montgomery&apos;s artillery bombardment was most effective. On one sector five out of a battery of six 88-mm. anti-tank guns hadbeen knocked out. This gun was the keystone of the German defences and losses on this scale were decisive.10. Von Thoma had told Rommel and Hitler that the advances and retreatsof the past year in Libya had only tactical and not strategical significance. Forthe Axis, strategical success could only be represented by the capture ofAlexandria. For the British the capture of Tripoli would be the prelude tostrategical success. Von Thoma considers that the Germans have no chance of holding Tunisia. The last-minute reinforcements now being dispatched wouldbe no match for the British and American forces landed in North Africa.Germany should admit failure on the North Coast of Africa and should nowbe employing all her resources in the Mediterranean for the defence of the innerline represented by Crete, Sicily, Corsica and Sardinia. If the Germans were sending their Mark 6 tanks to Tunisia it would be deplorable, as they wouldbe destroyed or captured by us. This tank is a very good one and has markedadvantages over the Mark 4.11. Von Thoma appears to be a man of very considerable militaryexperience and ability. He is prepared to speak frankly on military and politicalsubjects. On political matters he is not as intelligent as in the military sphere.His political arguments are the same as one would expect from any German-officer of similar rank and experience.(Signed) A. C. COLLIER,Air Vice-Marshal.Air Ministry,November 21, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
