<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/43/27 images: 250-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 527.22nd November, 1943.WAR CABINET.MORALE IN GERMANY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate to ray colleagues herewith a paper on morale in Germany, whichbrings up to date the information contained in W.P. (43) 396 of the 14th September.This paper represents the agreed views of the various Departments concernedwith this question, including the Service Departments.A. E.Foreign Office, 22nd November, 1943.Morale in Germany.Since the last report was circulated Germany&apos;s position has continued to deteriorate. Air raids on German cities by day and by night, though spells of bad weather have spared them something, have remained frequent and very heavy.The collapse of Fascism was followed by Italy&apos;s unconditional surrender. Thehopes of a new Dunkirk, which nourished for a day or two after the Salernolandings, were finally dissipated, and the Allies have firmly established themselves in Italy. The U-boats resumed activity on a considerable scale, butcan claim no substantial successes to counterbalance their continuing heavy losses.The promised retaliation for raids on Germany and the improved defences whichwere to reduce their intensity have so far not materialised. The retreat in theEast, which was expected to stop at the Dnieper, continues, and even at home the authorities hint at disasters possibly no less grave than Stalingrad. In thepolitical field the conclusions of the Moscow Conference must have extinguishedmany hopes. In the background, underlining the Germans&apos; difficulties andpromising to sharpen their sufferings, lies the fact that the fifth winter of thewar has begun.Against this can be set the rapid and not unsuccessful measures taken tohold the situation in Italy and the Balkans, including the spectacular rescue of mussolini and the reoccupation of Cos and Leros. The food situation has been maintained and harvests in occupied Europe have been generally goodThese few crumbs of comfort have, however, clone nothing to relieve Germananxieties. Since September it has become for the first time a commonplace inthe speeches of the German leaders to make the avoidance of defeat conditional upon the continued resistance of the home front. Even Hitler, in his speech of the 8th November, appeared to consider the possibility that the German peoplemight break under the strain. The regime is relying increasingly upon repressionto maintain the war effort and, since Himmler s appointment as Minister of theInterior, the number of executions for &quot; defeatism &quot; or at least the number which is announced has grown remarkably. Rumour multiplies the number,and this is in itself an effective instrument of terror.The process with which Himmler is trying to cope is the rapid transformation,mentioned in the last report, of the belief that Germany cannot win the war intothe belief that Germany must lose it. The belief that Germany must lose breedsthe hope that an end &quot;should come soon. A standard formulation of life inGermany seems to be &quot; Almost anything would be an improvement on the present state of affairs.&quot; Himmler is trying to prevent the word &quot; almost &quot; fromdropping out.of this formula.12202   [26452]Copy No.
Air raids are probably first in importance among the factors affectingmorale. In the areas directly affected they have had a shattering effect uponmorale. But their remoter repercussions have also been severe. Evacuation, lass and less orderl)- as the numbers involved grow, leads to a hopelessness which isaggravated by the cold welcome extended to evacuees in the reception areas. the approach of winter will add immensely to the already great problems ofinadequate housing and shortage of consumer goods.Bombing also appears to be giving rise for the first time tc anxiety lest thedestruction of German capital equipment should render impossible the task of post-war reconstruction. There is an increasing interest in the possibility of an anglo-American occupation, though, in this &quot;connexion, what the Germans seemmost to fear is not what the Allies might do, but what they might be unable toprevent. As the news from the East gets worse, heavy casualties, which werebearable as the price for victory, seem senseless as the accompaniment of defeat.The Moscow Conference, though it is still too early to estimate its full effect,must have clamped the considerable hopes which had been built up in Germany onthe basis of disunity between the Allies. Many reports over the last two monthsspeak of a widespread belief that a separate peace could be made either withRussia, or with Britain and the United States. Whatever efforts German propa-ganda may make to belittle the Conference, it must certainly have underminedany belief of this kind, although an immediate effect in informed circles may be temporarily to stiffen the will to resistance. It is also probable that the MoscowDeclaration on Austria, where discontent has been greatly increasing^for sometime, will add considerably to Hitler&apos;s anxieties.It is the educated and propertied classes those who still have something to lose, and are worried about their own and Germany&apos;s future who are mostsusceptible to defeatist thoughts. In these relatively restricted circles Himmler&apos;smethods have, however, succeeded so far in inhibiting action. The masses are more exclusively concerned with the strain and discomfort of day-to-day life.Among them and particularly among the women a sense of the hopelessness of thewar is increasing; but opposition is unco-orclinated and unorganised and has nomeans of finding expression. The German police are quite capable of preventingdisturbances or acts of open opposition. But in the long run widespread physical and nervous exhaustion, against which the machinery of repression is relativelyineffective, is likely to prove the most important factor in its effects upon theGerman ability to continue the war.For the present, however, fear of what the regime will do to those who defy itstill remains a source of strength. It now appears to be becoming a. moreimportant influence over the whole field of German opinion and behaviour, eventhan fear of wdiat her enemies will do to a defeated- Germany. An additionalfactor in sustaining morale to a considerable, though now decreasing, extentamong both civilians and the armed forces is the hope of averting defeat throughthe use of a &quot; secret weapon ;&apos; against Great Britain.The position may be summed up as &quot;follows. Though no doubt discussion ofsuch projects continues in military and conservative circles, there is no report ofany attempt yet on the part of the military leaders or industrialists to overthrowthe Nazi regime. There have, in fact, been no signs of active opposition in any quarter. Nevertheless awareness of impending defeat has grown and readiness to accept it. The prestige of Hitler has fallen yet further. Even party circlesshare these.feelings and over the whole field of administration the effective control exercised by the authorities is slackening. There is severe strain, apathy andindifference, which tends to cause bad work and lower production and. increases the tendency mentioned in the last report to give personal safety and privateinterest precedence over the needs of the war effort.Morale in the armed forces remains considerably higher than at home. Ifit were not, it is hard to see how the German army could continue to fight so well.But here, too, there have been signs of sagging and reports speak of a slackeningof discipline during the retreat in the Fast. There is evidence of considerabledepression among the forces of occupation, particularly in Norway, while thepossibility of the contagion of low morale at home spreading to the fightingservices appears to be causing anxiety to the authorities. The morale of crews of operational U-boats, particularly those based on French ports, has declinedconsiderably. As regards the German air force, evidence from the Russian frontis deficient but that from other theatres indicates that there has been some decline of morale and a slight weakening of fighting spirit.



</content>
</cab>
