<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 64-70</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANHIC MAJ2STY&apos;S GOVKRH^NT). SECRET,CP,2915. CAB I N h T.--- -ISURVKY OF THJ5 STATS OP IRELANDFoTT^Br:mirsniri?ay7&apos; tsst;(Circulated by the Chief Secretary for Ireland),I submit for the consideration of the Cabinet my eurvey for the week ended the 2nd instant,OBiirRAL STATE OF Tiff COUNTRY, S tat is tics of Outr^jgoa,Tho total number of outrages reported for tho weok ended the 30th ultimo is considerably lower than that for oach of tho two preceding weeks, but the reduction is mainly accounted for by tho decrease in the number of raids on mails Attacks on the Crown Forces have continued with undiminishod frequency, and the number of casualties sustained (28) is approximately the same as for the previous week (30).    There Is, however, a very welcome decrease in the number of&apos; fatal casualties, which fell from 11 to 1, the latter figure being the lowest recorded for any week since the beginning of tho present year, .  The one fatal casualty was that of a soldier of the East Lanes,heaiment who was murdered on the public road at Epnount, Co, Cork, cn the 30th ultimo. -Although 36 attacks upon parties or individual members of the Crown Forces were reported during the week there wa3 very little serious fighting.    In the majority of cases I the attackers withdrew on tho failure of their first effort and tho only instanco in which they appear to haVo obtained tho bettor of thm encounter was an ambush of a small party of military at Glenloigh-Railway Station, Co, Kerry, on the 26th ultimo, which resulted in the loss of a Lewis
gun, four rifles and a quantity of ammunition.    An ambushof a very deadly character which miscarried in its execution was made upon a train in which a party ofmilitary consisting of an officer and fifteen men of thoDovonshire Regiment were proceeding from Formoy to &apos; at or-ford on tho 29th ultimo.    The attack was made about.15 p.m. near Eallyhineh crossing, the gates of whichwere closed as the train approached.    On the, train being brought to a standstill before the gates wjrc reached firewas opened upon It by a concealed body of rebels, and twosoldiers were wounded, one severely.    The military atonce engaged their assailants who Viithdrew after a shortengagement, but ao all the roads leading to tho scene wereblocked and two bridges blown up, a party of reinforcementswereWhich loft Dungarvan/dolayod ond failed to arrive in time to cut off the,  rebel retreat.     Two other trains contain-ing military passengers wer   fired upon near Burrov Station, Dimr;arvan District?,;. Co. &apos;, &apos;a tor ford on the 28th and 29th ultimo, but in each case the train proceeded without stopping *and no casualties occurred,12 unsuccessful attacks on occupied police barracks were made during the week,     Tho majority of these attacks were little more than sniping operations but in to attempt on Port roe barrack, Nonagh District., Co, Tipporary a force of about 50 rebels wero engagod and the fight lasted and hour and a half, bombs and rifles being used on both sides.    Ho police casualties wore sustainod and it is not known whether the rebels, suffered any loss.3 additions wore mado to the list of Sinn Fein murders of civilians, the viatim3 in 2 cases being ex-soldiors.
Minor outrages Includod 42 raids on mails (a decrease of 49 on the previous week 1a figure) 1 raid on a Coastguard Station (in v/hich no injury was committed) and 4 raids for arms.Arrests for outrages and political offonocs numbered 47 for the week.Trials of Civilians by Court Kartlal,Fifty-six trials of civilians by Court Martial wero concluded during the week resulting in forty-four convict-ions and twelvo acquittals.    The following Is an analysis of the sentences imposed.-18 Sontcnces of Penal Servitude (3 years to 10 years).14      &quot; of Imprisonment with (Smonths to 2 years)2 hard labour2      &quot; of Imprisonomnt with-(6 months to 9 months)out hard labour 4 Finos        (10/- to  2).6 Sentences not confirmod by Confirming Officer.Total.The above scntonccs includod a sentence of throe ^oars penal servitude on a Constablo of the Royal Irish Constabul-ary for shooting with intont to murdor, and    sentonces of 9 and 3 months imprisonment respectively with hard labour on too Constables for theft.    Among the other convlotions were the cases of three men ,who were found guilty of taking part in an ambush at Ballymacelligott in November last. This was tho ambush which has been scoutod as fictitious by opposition politicians including the gentlemen comprising the Labour Commission which visited the South of Ireland in December of last year.    It will be interesting to see whether this attitude of sceptloism will be maintained in tho face of the testimony furnished by the conviction of
throe men for participating in the ambush. Internment Orders.125 Orders for internment were made during tho week bringing tho number of persons now intorncd to 2,093*    In addition there aro at present 90 orders analting completion and 7 in abeyanoo pending tho arrest of tho persons whoso internment has boon ordorod,    Tho number of persons who have been roleasod from internment is 135. STATE OF THE POLICE FORCES.The roofuiting figures for the Royal Irish Constabulary arc slightly better than those of tho previous week but the number of resignations has increased from 27 to 42 and the number of dismissals from 24 to 31*    Tho not increase in the strength of the Regular Force is 31.    Tho figures for tho Auxiliary Division again show a small net decrease.    The following aro the usual particulars of wastago and rccruit-ing for the week. Regular ForootStrongth on 24th April, 1921......................13,875Deaths during week.....................6Retirements...........................18Resignations..........................42Dismissals............................31Total wastage $ffRecruits,Ireland.... Gt, Britain.15112127Net IncreaseStrength on 1st May, 192115,006
Auxiliary Division.Strength on 24th April, 1921.........................1,474Recruits...................................10Re signatlona *.....................10Deaths.............................2Dismissed,........................ ,1Discharged (M;.dicr.lly unfit....... ,1Discharged (undo r a go ).............115No t increase............,......................._5^Strength on 1st May, 1921............................1,469The corresponding figures for the Dublin Metropolitan police arc as follows;Strength on 23rd April, 1921.........................1,126Deaths..........................resignations....................2Total wastage,      3Rocrui 13 (Ire land).....,........3Not increase or decrease........................, nilStrength on. 30th April, 1921.........................1,126.PggggHT POLITICAL SITUATION Iff IRjUjID,Tho now Lord Lieutenant, Viscount Fitzalan of Porwont, was sworn in beJdre a meeting of the Privy Council hold in the Council Chamber, Dublin Castle on the 2nd instant and has now been taken up   the duties of his office.    His Excellency1s first public act has been the issue of the Proclamation summoning the Southern and Northern Parliaments, the former to moot in Lublin on tho 28th Juno and tho lattor in Pclfast on the 7th Juno,    So far as present indications go there would appear to be little likelihood of Sinn Fein candidates mooting with serious opposition in tho Southern Irish constituencies, but a stern contest is expected in Ulster whore all parties appear to bo determined to put forth their full strength.     In a public proclamation addressed
t* the Irish People Mr Do Valero maintains the legitimacyof the so&apos; called Republican Government end states explicitlythat lthc   policy of Sinn ^oin remains unchanged&apos;.    Thegeneral to:., j of his manifesto, however, is decidedly lessbellicose and uncompromising than previous documents issuingfrom - tho same quarter and the following pasaa.ee anncars tomc tc mark the first definite advance mode by part of SinnFein towards a workable understanding with Ulsterj&quot;Sinn Fein stands for Ireland undivided end a unit wit&apos;.:, regard tc other dations and States, but in home affairs for such devolution of administration and authority as would make for the satisfaction and contentment of all sections of tho people and -eould not bo inconsistent with efficiency and economy&apos;1.Inasmuch as Sin,&apos;. Fein must now realise that any agreement with Ulster providing for Union in regard toexternal affairs can be arrived at only on the basis ofIreland remaining within the Smpiro, this overture, if it issincere, would appear to indicate that the Sinn Fein leaders have at last been driven by the logic of cvonts to recognise the impracticability of their full Republican demands.There is no doubt that the almost universal support whichis still given to their party amongst the greater part ofSouthern Ireland is not founded upon a popular faith inRepublican doctrines, and the fact that their doctrines, sofar as their application to Ireland is concerned, have beenemphatically repudiated by men of tho influence of CardinalLogue, Archbishop Gilmartin and Bishop Coholan may haveconvinced tho political loaders that the general sense ofthe people is in favour of moderate counsels and tho abandonment of claims which have   been shown to be unroalisablo.i(Initialled)   H.G.Secretaryrs Office, Dublin Castle,3rd May, 1921.
Stat eiaent   aiiowlrtgWeekfICATuRiS OF OITTRiiSS.owing Total number from 1st January,  1919,  to 26th llarch,  1921. ly Totals to v/eek ended the 30th April, 1921 and Totale- at that dateTotals from WE^a: X/1sd.Totals from        ^______ - ^     . . .   ..     - ...____1st Jan 1919 2nd April 9th April    16th April    23rd April Both April&quot;   Totals toto 26th 1921. 1921.              1921                1921 1921.          30th April&amp;arch 1921. 1921Courthouses destroyed.I.C. Vacated Barrccks destroyed Jl.j.C, Vacated Barracks damaged R*I*C. Occupied Barracics destrpyed^1120&amp;.I.C. 0ccupi ed Barracks daca^ed24 TITRaids on HailsBalds on Coastguard Stations andLighthouses4C43.211242itaids for Ams ^___,___Raids on Offj.ces of Rate Collectorsand Petty Sessions Clerks__Policemen killed__j_56910264 /&quot;4-5Pollceaen WoundedPolicemen Pired at etc. Soldiers Killed  _-406 g1416.X.10not recorded1212121010Soldiers Wounded206^-Soldiers laired at etc.not recoraedT4-..9. 4X Civilians KilledCivilians Wounded11 TTotArrests for Outrages and Political Offences&quot;6.636SIToB&quot;140ToT62JZ183.143X   These figures do not include casualties in Ulster Kiots during period June - September, 1920: 20 Civilian cieatias occurred in Londonderry riots and 62 in Belfast riots during that period.H.B. The above particulars do not include outrages of a -and wuldi are not norr be in 7 co^itced s*g* 119 raids on Revenue Offices which occurred during months of April and kay, 1920 and resulted in the destruction of many official documents and much other public property.    Minor for as of outrages (e.g.  intimidation, cattle-driving, etc) are also not included.j6    These figures in each case include t&quot;o Special Constables. .X. This figure includes 3 Special Constables.1201603,130101291 W102: 235:15FCT5

</content>
</cab>
