<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 128-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS POCUk^FT IS THI PROPERTY OF HIS BRITALIC IV J-v-TY1:: C-QV        :T&apos; C A B IN E T.CP. g.981,IRILAI1D AID AM RICA,(Memorandum by tho Secretary of State for ToveirnAffairs).The Cabinet will have read the three important telegrams from Sir A. Geddes about American Relief for Ireland.     Immediately upon their receipt, I communicated with the Lord Lieutenant, who is in England, and wrote at length to the Chief Secretary who is in Ireland, Indicating what I thought, subject to his Opinion, ou^h/i to be the nature of our reply.     I heard from him this morning, concurring strongly In the view that the American proposal is in the main political in characterj constitutes an unwarrantable Interfer-en.ee with the Government of a foreign State, would be indignant ly rejected had it been made in analogous circumstances to the American Government, and ought to be firmly though politely refused.On these lines I have drafted the following telegram, incorporating in it the main points of the Chief ?ecrotery&apos;s reply.   At the suggestion of the Prime Minister I circulate it to the Cabinet for discussion, to-morrow.Foreign Office,Mav 9th. 1921(intlld).   C. of K.
Your telegrams Nooa 303, 304, and 305 (of May 5th) have caused me considerable surprise as I had been led to hope and believe that the very full information to which such publicity has been given in the United States respecting the re a?, conditions in Ireland would have made it difficult, If not impossible, fcr tho present movement to have essumod tho proportions dosoribed in your telegrams.I hope, in a later telegram, to supplement the information already sent to you by more recent data, which will confirm what has already boon stated, namely that no part cf a belligerent country has emerged from the reoent war richer in men and wealth than Ireland?   that as a whole Ireland has never boon more prosperous, and that whatover thero may be of spora&amp;io distress, is the direct outcome of the rebellion, and if anywhere unrelieved, is so only because the assistaneo^tendered by the constituted authorities Is deliborately rejected.Thero is no truth whatever in the allegation that ICC,000 men, women and children in Ireland aro faoed with acute economic distress.     Nor is thore any shortage of food.    Where there is unemployment it is due to the same industrial depression that prevails in every part of the Unitei Kingdom and is met by the same methodsnamely
mmely u employment  rantse      There are a number of ox-Service men who arc out of work because they aro boydotted by thoir fellew-eouatrymen.   For those special provision is made by lulu. Gcvornmont,     Ample means are available for mooting c.onuj.no distress, \hioh exists in Ireland in an incomparably less decree than in other countriosi      The only funds which thero is apparently any substantial difficulty in keeping replenished, ere those needed for carrying on the campaign cf murder and terrorism.     The real difficulty which is bein^ faced is indeed not that of an impoverished poople but of a conspiracy to wrest Ireland from tho United Kingdom by tho armed rebellion of a small but desperate minority of its inhabitants.Further tho American Committee would appear to have been gravely misinformed as to the extent of damage caused by the rebellion.   Thoir report&apos; specifies creameries and factories.   Of 710 oroerneries in Ireland, 33 have been destroyed end  0 damaged, of whioh 7 are working a^ain. The average, number of employees is 10 per creamery.   Two oreamorios have had to be closed because they wore activo centres of rebellion,     as to factories two only have been destroyed, one emptying about 100 workers and the other about 7C of both sexes.In these circumstances there can be no scopo in Ireland for the work of foreign relief missions, and it would be neither honest nor becoming on the part of H*lvi. Government were they to avail themselves of pecuniary ?2nd other assistance offered by the generosity of contributors in foreign countries in order to relieve conditions, the e:.Uitence of vhich is denied.Indeed/
Inieed any organ!action set u.; for such a purpose a.; the American subscribers have in view would, if created, find itself without legitimate occupation.   The only use to which ita energies and resources could be put, wouK be to substitute itself for the general administration of the country.   The danger of this happening - ho.-ever little it may correspond to the original intentions of the pro-mot ers * wculcl bo in direct proportion to&quot; the number of agents employed, and the area over which they would operate.   From this point of View, the American scheme reveal- plans which do not err on the side of moderation. It is proposed to cover Ireland with a network of directorates, penetrating into every country ana every district, and embracing in their functions some of the essential attributes of local government, such as trans-port, commerce, warehousing, supplies, as well as building and engineering operations, under the super-vision of architect---, and other experts.To ask the British Government to authorise such an arrangement is to expect them to abdicate their proper function;;; of government on their own territory in favour of a foreign body deriving its authority from, and responsible to, a private association in another country,   iiuch a proposition, a country defeated in war, economically ruined, civ., politically demoralised, mi&apos;;:ht reluctantly accept if faced with the alternative of a complete national collapse; it is not one to which any British government would consider it compatible with its dignity to ajree.further it is clear to His Majesty&apos;n Government that the surfeited scheme while professedly humanitarian in intention, could in practice have little other resultthant
than to prclcn ; the state of rebellion an&apos;&quot; hinder that reconciliation ami peace which is devoutly desired by the gre majority of the Iris:? pecpie.It i? not f o&apos;-&quot; ur. to say v:hether the State De .! rt-ment should or should not corasunicate the scheme to you. Upon one point however we vrirh to be quite clear namely that if the proposal3 are such as yon have reported, it will be impossible for Kir; Majesty^ Government to accept the , for the reasonr; whioh I have explained.

</content>
</cab>
