<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 353-355</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMOT IS TEH PH0P3RTY OF HI3 BRITAIOTC M/L^STY?S GOV^aM^T) ,*S OR E t. *VC A 3 I IT B T, &quot;^3,Po 293li,03? 1ctq388it0us SCHOOL chii^i; . Jtooran^M by. the Preoiaento of the Board of fc&amp;uoation..,i circulate for the information of my colleagues a summary return up to 23rd April (Table &apos;A!) showing the increase during the present emergency in the number of meals provided by Local Education Authorities to school children under the Education (Prevision of Ideals) Acts,   Returns up to 30th April are not yet complete, but i am endeavouring to accelerate them..Prom the latest information (relating to the year ended31st March 1920) in the possession of the Board as to thecost of these meals, it appears that during that year thed * d *average cost per meal was 7*01 of which 4.15 represented the cost of the food and the remainder the cost of service.On this basis the total cost of the 1,090,000 meals provided in the week ended 23rd April would be approximately  32,000which, after deducting contributions from parents (which in -1919-20 amounted to about 13.8 per cehtf of the totalexpenditure) would fall to be met as to half by  rant fromthe Board and half from the local rates.Table ,B* shows the number of children fed in certainselected areas during the weeks ended 19th March, 16thApril and 30th April.   In the case of the Counties includedin the table it must be remembered that the areas are those for which the County Councils are Local Education Authori-ties for Elementary Education.(Sgd.)   H.A.L. 3PI8H3R.Board of Education, s.y/. 10th May, 1921.
*TABU    &apos;A&apos;J   &apos; BOAR I)   0 E   E E UCATIO N.jnmary of Weekly Returns of Meals provided by Local Education Authorities to School Children under the Education (Provision of Heals) Acts.i2i. ;March!123seklingNo, of Local Education AuthoritiesNumber of Meals Provided.Number of Children fed.Eeed lng.March	127 .	189 April	100	216April	124	: i 192! 1April	127	189April	133	183NotEreeing188EorPaymentTotalEree430,978 380,79481,452 59,939512,430 440,73373 ,416 74,406EorPayment16,639 15,208Total.90,055 89,614This being Easter week/, complete figures are notavailable..595,193 1,003 ,35046,593 /2,91306,703443,356 668,106r1!a3090i31374,327 98,878 157,74813,549 14,503 16,22987,876 113,381 ; 173,977*
TABLE 13&apos; .Illustrative Cases showing tho Number of School Children fed during the weeks endedkberland A.C. :ham A.C, lacs. A, C, , Helens C.B. rtnumberland A,C. tts. A.C.rks W. Riding A.C, ordare U.D. untain Ash U.D. ntypridd U.L. ondda U.D. (rthyr Tydvil C.B, nmouthshire A. C. bbw Vale U.D.19th March, 1921,   -l th April, 1921.   30th April, 1921i1,344 1144736891,520537 4831,4201093 24 371 5156,077 59166 2,490 2,188 2,8222,2421,74860,2667,607 6,6817,7501,519 10,0006,366 2,6463,55911,2977,9319,057 2,544

</content>
</cab>
