<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 383-390</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IJS BOOUMLIiiT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BKIVA11ITIO hAcE;,!FY&apos;&amp; (JOYEiJ!; uIJT.)ECfiET,0 a B I 1J I; T.SURVEY OF THE STATE OF IRELAUD FOR !week IHIDED 9th, HAY, 1921.f Circulated &quot;by the Chief Seorotary for Irelandz)I submit for the consideration of the Cabinet my survey forthe week ended the 9th instant.SEHURAL STATS OF THE COUNTRY.Statistics of Outrages,The number of outrages reported for the week ended the7th instant is approximately the same as for the previous week and indicates no change in the general situation.    The total casualties sustained by the Crown Forces reached the same figure (28) for eaoh week, but I regret to state that the number of fatal casualties has risen from 1 to 18.   Of the latter number 14 were deaths in armed conflicts with rebels forces and the remaining 4 were cold-blooded assassinations of policemen, the victims in two oases being unarmed.   The majority of the fatal casualties resulted from two ambushes, one of which took place at Tourmakeady, Oo. Mayo, on the 3rd instant,and the other at Rathmore, Co. Kerry on the 4th instant.     In the former case a party of Royal Irish Constabulary consisting of a Head Constable, a Sergeant and 11 Constables who were proceeding in two motor cars from Ballinrobe to Derrypark were attacked by a body of rebelsnumbering/200, armed with rifles and other firearms and in the engagement which followed the Sergeant and 3 Constables were killed and .2 Constables were wounded.   The casualties inflicted upon the ambushers are not known but at least six wore believed to have been killed.   On the arrival of military and police reinforcements the rebelsabout
withdrew from the encounter whioh had lasted about an hour. Tho ambush at Rathmore on the 4th instant was a cunningly oontrived massacre in which the police although armed were raniered practically helpless by tho oiroumstanoas of the attack.   According to tho police report the ambush was brought about by a message received at the Barrack to the offset that the dead body of a man was lying on the public road at Rathbeg, about half a milro from Rathmore Station. A party consisting of a Sergeant and 8 Constables at onoe proceeded to the scene and found tho body, to whioh was affixed a label with the now familiar inscription ^Convicted spy&quot;,   &quot;/hiie the police were examining the body, heavy rifle fire was opened upon them from a distance of about fifty yards, and eight of the party (including the Sergeant) were shot dead in thu space of a few minutes.   The single survivor succeeded in obtaining oover and in offeoting his return to the barrack uninjured.   It is suggested In the Police Report that the man whose body was found cn the road was deliberately murdered by the rebels and used as a decoy to attract the police to tho scene of the ambush.   If this explanation of his death proves to be correct the whole episode must be regarded as one of the most infamous in the long series of Sinn Fein orimes.An ambush which yielded very different results took plaoo on the 3rd instant at Lackelly, Bruff District, Co.. Limerick where a mixed patrol of military and polioe numbering 14 encountered a body of rebels estimated at about 1 0.   After fieroe fighting which lasted for over&apos; four hours the attackers were beaten off with the loss of at least 6 killed and many wounded, and a quantity of arms, explosives and ammunition were captured.   The casualties
to the Crown forces on this occasion were g Soldiers and 1 Constable wounded, none seriously.Five oooupied police barracks wore attached during the week, in every case unsuccessfully.In all 2d armed conflicts between the Crown ana&quot; rebel forces were reported during the week and although tho Grown casualties are regrettably heavy there are good grounds for believing that the rebols suffered more severely both in killed and wounded.   There would appear to be no doubt, however, that the rebel organisers Ere doing their utmost to increase their numerical fighting strength and in some districts they are known to have resorted to the conscription of youths of from sixteen years of ago upwards.   Three additional victims (including one ex-soldier) wero added to the list of Sinn Fein murders of civilians.Raids on mails numbered 58, an Increase of 10 on the previous wee^s total.Arrests for outrages -and political offences numbered 92 for the week.Trials of Civilians by Oourt Partial.Seventy-three trials by Court Martial were concluded during the week resulting in fifty-six convictions and seven-teen acquittals.   The following is an analysis of the sentences imposed in the oases of conviction:23 Sentences of penal servitude (3 years to 15 years)25       &quot;       of imprisonment with (14 days to 2 years) hard iabour5        w       of imprisonment with (1 month to 1 year) without hard labour.  Finesotal        55In the remaining case   the aeousod (a Constable of the VeteranDivision of the Royal Irish Constabulary) was bound over ini,his.....
his own recognisances to ^cep tho peace.    Sentences varying from 9 to 3 months Imprisonment with hard labour were imposed on four Constables of the Royal Irish Constabulary convicted of looting, and sontonccsof imprisonment for 14 days and 1 month respectively were imposed on two Constables convict-od of being drunk and threatening a civilian with firearms. An officer of tho Auxiliary Division and five constables of the Regular R.I.C. accusod of theft and one constablo accused of assault with vloloncc were acquitted.     Sentence of 15 year3 penal servitude was imposed in a case of convictionfor bomb-throwing in Bclfaot, and sentence of 10 years penal servitude in the case of a man convicted on his oT.?n admission, of having takon part in the burning of Strokcstown Courthouse, Co. Roscommon, on the 29th July, 1920* Internments.The following table shows tho present position as regards internmentsjTotal internment orders made......3.111Orders oancolled for reasons other than - releaso,.......................Ae,94Releases ordcrcdo........,..............141235Balance showing number of persons nowInterned 2,B76In addition 129 orders are at present awaiting completionthe persons concerned being already In custody.    Appealsagainst internment orders are awaiting hearing in 35 casos^STATE OF THE POLICE FORCES,,Tho wcek!s recruiting figures for tho Royal Irish Constabulary have fallen below the average of recent weeks but the decrease Is not such as to suggest that there will bo any difficulty in maintaining the standard necessary to meet requirements.    The following aro tho usual particulars for the week?f 4 *f
Regular Force.Strength on 1st Hay, 1921...........................13,906,Deaths during week......................18Retirements.............................15Resignations............................36Dlsnissala or discharges................19Recruits:Total wastage............. 88Ireland.................6Gt. Britain............8793Hot increase for week.............................   5Strength on 8th Hay, 1921...........................13,911Auxiliary Division.Strcgnth on 1st May, 1921........................... 1,469Recruits during week.................0..18Re signatlons............ *6Transferred to ulster Special Constabulary.-... .1Dismissed...............rl*****8Hot Increase...................................      10Strength on 8th I lay, 1921............................1,479The corresponding figures for the Dublin Metropolitan Police arc as follows:Strength on 30th April, 1921.........................1,126Resignations....................3Recruits.Ireland.............1Gt. Britain.........12Hot decrease....................................      1Strength on 7th Lay, 1921........................... 1,125Pr3Sg T POLITICAL SITUATION IK IRSLAIIP&apos;The mooting between Sir James Craig and Mr Dc Valora on the 5th In3tant mast be ragarded as an event of the first political importance.    YJith the doubtful exceptionof/
of the Convention of 1917-18, whioh wag held at a tiiuo when j ir. ;iedmon&amp;&apos;s authority to speak on behalf of tho majority of Southern Irishmen had already been scriously challenged, this is tho first occasion in modern history on which duly accredited representations of tho  orth and South of Ireland have met of thoir own initiative and without tho intervention of British Statesmen to discuss the differences that have so long divided the two sections of the Irish people, and although neither Sir Janes Craig nor Mr Do Valora appears to have emerged from tho Interview with his convictions in any degree shaken, tho fact of thoir having entered into direct negotiations has produced a deep impression in tho minds of men of all parties and has materially improved the prospects of peace.    Tho consensus of approval given to the mooting by the Press of the whole country is a further encouraging sign that the Influence of fanatics and extremists on both sides is gradually giving place to a growing disposition towards a settlement by conciliation and compromise.    The hope of permanent peace in Ireland depends upon those two loaders mooting again, as in my opinion, they will, and upon their agreeing on some plan acceptable to the two sections of the Irish people.    Tnclr importance in conferonco enhanced by the fact that thoy really represent their respective parties and can bind practically all Ireland by their decision.(Intd)   H .Cf Secretary^ Office, Dublin Castle, 10th May, 1921.
Statement shewing Total Number of  serious Outrages from 1st January. Ii*19 to 2nd April, 1-j 21. Weekly totals to week ended the 7th May, 1921, and Totals at that ante. - -Totsls from 1st        -        milt HHICT--To fair;K -iTURS OF OUTIUGES. Jan.1919 to 2nd 9tn April 16th April 23rd April 30th April 7th M*y 7tTT Ha^ _April,  1921._1921_1921__1^21_1921__1921___19210 ourthouses des troyed B.I.C Vacate5T&quot;3arraok8 Seatroyod E.I.C. Vacated&quot;&quot;iJtrrabks damajR.I*C* Qeeupled Iarracks destroyed.&apos; 25 R.I.Q.  coupled B&amp;rraelca damaged 120gaifts on ffiuls&quot; Raids on Coastguard i stations and-_       Lighthouses___ 56 ___ ......_____     __   ..______   ......___________ aids for^ros   &apos;&quot; 3, J05        ^ &quot;5   &quot; 10 6&quot; 6&quot; _4^ SZZ.     ^7133Raids on Offices of Hate &quot;Collectorsand Potty Sessions Clerics 96    _ -     _;        5 - 1 - 102g ojioemen gllXeo:--- 2T2 T&quot;-Ig &quot;g   &quot;&quot; 10-------r15&quot;^oTToemea wounded---&quot; &quot;glSnJT   &quot; Ig&quot;&quot;Tl* 1ST It 18^&quot; &quot;7&quot;Policemen fired aty etc. iot recorded 6 11 T&quot; 12    _IT&quot;f7. q&quot;3o9&quot; 491^pldiers killed-----------9B 1                                       1-       1.-3--------- &apos; T02&quot;&amp;oldler^wounded-&quot;                              210 5 4 T                 W---g-----.    ^SoIdlers &quot;fired at eto*                   not&apos; recorded 5 4        _     3    **&quot;4                 3            ......-jCLvllians-^illea        -------      102 - 7 &apos;      6 3 &apos;3----&quot;3&quot;&apos;   -------T 40lYiHans Wounded&quot;&quot;                                 13? 7 &quot;9 2&quot;                2                 5------&quot;-----159*fotala   &quot;&quot;-57779   ------------ log&quot;                                    I6&quot;2^-----ire--------&quot;US-- j&quot;7,356&quot;Arrests for Outrages and Political                                                                      ........ &quot; *_Offences______-____74_83_____143_______52 92^ *   These figures do not include casualties in Ulster Riots during period June - September 1920: 20 CiTilian deaths occurred in Londonderry riots and 62 in Belfast riots during that period:The above particulars do not Include outrages of a kind which are not now being committed e.g. 119 raids on Revenuo Offices which occurred during months of April and Uay, 1920 and resulted in the destruction of many official documents and mucl other public property.   Minor forms of outrages Oe.g. intimidation, oat tie-driving etc) are also not included.$     These figures in each case include two Special Constables. s*X-   This figure includes 3 Special Constables.
SECEEE.cabinet.J LAKEPOKT OH BEVOLlf IQIvABY OBGMIS/1TIOIS Iff THE&quot;UHI?BD JCIHGDOBpn^porOo^oB&apos;).(Paper Ho. CP. 2938).IT IS BEQ (JESTED THAT THIS DOCUMENT MAY BE REGABLED AS HIGHLY001\T?IDEHTIA1.2, Whitehall Gardens, Sv8.1. , 13th. May, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
