<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 419-420</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Tho following telegram, winch was issued with the concurrence of the Prime Minister, Lord Curzon, and Mr. Churchill, is circulated with reference to Cabinet 37(21), Conclusion 6 of 10th May.E. S. M.12th May 1921.From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department,nth May mi.Clear the line.Secret. Afghanistan. Mis Majesty&apos;s Government have now given the most careful consideration to your telegram of the 5th May. I understand that your view is that the best form of treaty would be one which would exclude the Russians from Afghanistan ; but that if such a treaty could not be concluded, rather than no treaty, you would suggest, in view of the considerations you have brought to our notice, a treaty which would not exclude the possibility of the Afghans getting arms and a subsidy from the Russians.2. His Majesty&apos;s Government entirely agree with you as to the first alternative. It is eminently desirable that we should administer a diplomatic defeat to the Russians at Kabul; that we should convince the Amir that he has nothing to gain from Bolsheviks and everything to gain by friendship with us, and that by taking our advice on his relations with foreign Powers he will avoid again getting into a dilemma like the present. We do not believe in the capacity of the Bolsheviks to continue payments of large sums of money. On the other hand, the Amir must know tliskjie can rely upon any undertaking we make. In order to get rid of both the Bolshevik treaty and the Bolsheviks themselves, we would agree, and indeed urge you, to go to the very limits of your financial capacity in this direction. We note that you &quot;mention 30 lakhs, and that Dobbs suggested 40 lakhs annual and one crore initial. Having regard to the present value of money and the comparable cost of tribal warfare, we would urge you not to put too low a limit upon the expenditure necessary to produce so desirable a result. Promise him the arms that he wants; give him every assurance of assistance short of direct military intervention against unprovoked aggression by the Russians, and real friendship if he will give up his treaty with Moscow and dismiss the Bolshevik Mission. We note that you think it impossible to&apos;demand the latter. It is, however, the logical conclusion of the policy which we wish Amir to pursue, and while Dobbs must determine by what means it can best be secured, he will naturally regulate his offer of money, &amp;c, according to the completeness of Bolshevik elimination.3. This then is the most desirable course, and no effort should be spared to get it; and so far as we can judge the situation here, we cannot help thinking that a persistent and firm attitude will achieve success if negotiations are not hurried.4. As regards the alternative, His Majesty&apos;s Government still hold the view expressed in my previous telegrams, the view that you are familiar with from your presence at the Cabinet at which this matter was last discussed before you left England. That India should be paying a subsidy to the Amir whilst-at the&apos;same time lie had formed a treaty under which he was receiving money from the Bolsheviks,, is a solution which we find difficult to justify, and to - which we could assent only . with the most extreme reluctance. It opens up unlimited possibilities for the Amir to play us off against the Russians, and the Russians&apos; off against us ; applying to each in turn for an increase in subsidy, and seeking every opportunity to, profit by any dissensions between Russia and ourselves. Whilst Russia is governed by a Bolshevik Government with its known hostility to the British Empire, with its known desire to wound what they describe as a capitalist Government through the East, the objections are obvious, and even if Russia were once again animated by a similar policy to that which animated it under the Czarist regime, the objections would be equally, if not more,, obvious. We should, therefore,-infinitely prefer that such an arrangement should npi be contemplated, but His Majesty^ Goyernm^rfc recognise that In are thorough f&quot;&quot; &quot;&apos;&apos; 1      dews and 1 -  ,a&apos;i have appreciated their force
in recommending such .a course for our approval. Therefore,. if in the event of Dobbs&apos; failure, you tell us that you still remain convinced that it is better to conclude such a treaty than to have no treaty at all, in tho last resort we should be willing to acquiesce, and we recognise that,it is .only right to inform you at this stage to that effect. You will, I presume, instruct Dobbs to do all in his power with force and firmness to get the exclusive treaty. How far you will take him into your confidence as to possibility of the pis alter, I must leave to your discretion.. On the one hand, it is obviously desirable that he should be in full possession of our aims and purpose. On the other, we are so reluctant to assent to the second alternative, and so anxious to secure the first, that we do not want to risk Aveakening his patience or endeavour by too early a recognition that failure does not necessarily mean rupture. There is also to be considered that at Kabul, wheie everything gets known, the Amir may learn of the possibility of an alternative which may lead him to new bargaining with the Russians.   However, I leave that with complete confidence to you.In all that I have said, I have assumed your intention to be that even the second alternative should be conditional upon disclosure of the Bolshevik treaty and cancellation of the Consulates on our frontier.In conclusion, we must take care that Amir does not give to Angora the facilities for threatening India which we shall be paying him heavily to refuse to Moscow, and li should be glad to know how you propose to deal with situation created by Turco-Afgiian Treaty.

</content>
</cab>
