<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 503-503</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
!9 DOOtMJSNT IS THE fSGNBHW of HIS... /i\A i M aJfilTAHBIC majesty S &amp;0V3RflSSIJT) ^ 0 ri.30 (e De1CS11 HeJDSBTIAI, 2951.CABINET.LEAGUE   OF   NATIONS.CAMPAIGN AGAINST TYPHUS IB EASTERN EUROPE.Copy of Letter from the Cabinet Officesto the Secretary-General, League of _____Nations v______2, Whitehall Gardens, 11th May, 1921.S.W.Sir,I am directed to refer to the circular appealing for funds to combat the spread of typhus in the 3ast of Europe, for-warded on January 24th last by a Committee nominated by the President of the Assembly of the League of Nations.    In the last sentence of this communication appeal is made for an immediate and ^enercus contribution (or if a contribution has already been made, for further assistance) towards the funds which are so urgently required to carry on an effective campaign against this scourge.In reply to this appeal I am to remind you that a sum of  50,000 has already been advanced by the-British Government for the purpose in question on their bein^ given to understand that there was good reason to hope that if this sum of  50,000 was offered without other conditions, provided the whole sum of  225,000, esti-mated as the amount neoessary to enable operations to be put in hand at once, was made immediately available, other nations concerned would also withdraw their conditions.His Majesty&apos;s Government have as yet received no information to show that the conditions imposed by other nations have so far been withdrawn, or that the sum of  225,000 above referred to has actually been made available.   In these circumstances you -will, no doubt, agree that His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot reasonably be expected, for the present, to consider the question of granting a further contribution to this fund, however deeply they may sympathise with its objects.I am,Sir,fiecrs tary-General, -ague of Nations.Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) G.3. 3PI03R.Assistant      rotary.

</content>
</cab>
