<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/123/0 images: 609-621</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2978 This ls the reply of the French Government  rSECRETThis Document Is the. ProgertjMjf His Britamiicj^^4713*to my memorandum of May 20th, on the subjectof Upper Silesia which has already been circulated.(Initialled) C. of K.
Translation,Ministry of Foreign Affairs PARIS. May 23rd, 1921.1.   The French Government is grateful to the British Government for replying in detail to its memorandum of the 14th May, and hastens in turn to furnish data and detailed explanations, following the paragraphing of the British Note of May 20th,   This preliminary exchange of information between the two Governments will be useful as clearing the ground, before the discussion at the Supreme Council, of what-ever is tendencious and inaccurate in the treatment which the press of the two countries has accorded to the Silesian question.2.  The views formed by the French Government are-based upon a very large number of reports, both official and semi-official, received from the French officials and officers, upon whose testimony the French Government places the same reliance as that which the British Government extends to its own officials.   The latter are, it may be observed, less numerous and less favourably situated than, the French for correctly estimating the various aspects of the situation in Upper Silesia.3. mat the sudden outbreak of the insurrection came as a surprise, is indisputable, although the language of the Polish press in the plebiscite area had left no doubt as to the feelings of the population.If
If the secret police did not discover anything, in spite of itsirepeated investigations,it must also be observed that the plebiscite police, though under the coaaRal cf a British major, was equally%in the dark.  Moreover the French Government had, in the month of October last, given the British Government every satisfaction in the matter of their equal representation on the police force.Reliable and corroborated Information proves that the in-surgents only received a very slight and mostantary support from polish territory-  this is a point to be noted to the credit of the Polish Government.Ihe insurrection broke out in the manner described in the British note.  But, if it be true that it was Korfanty&apos;8 news-paper which first published the new, it is none the less in-conteotable that the conclusions of the Aaglo*Italian report fere knetwn by the Germans in Upper Silesia from April 29th, and hat their tancur was public property.  It is enough to refer to he German newspaper in Upper Silesia, &quot;Ostdeutschemorgenpostw, hich so declares, categorically, in its number of the 2nd May.It can hardly be maintained that the insurgents proceeded ystematically to occupy the rural districts; for it was the inhabitants themselves of those districts that rose, Nor is it easy to see how the allied troops stationed in the towns could have effectively resisted either the occupation of the rural istricts or the attacks on the railways.Bie British memorandum cites a certain number.of places where engagements took place between the insurgents and the allied troops.  The French Government is in a position to supplement the information of the British Government under tile head.  French troops were engaged at Koenigshutte, atonierihutte, Slemenovitz. Grose-strchlitz, Pless and /bnik.   In all the towns where there were French troop3 order has been maintained, and the Commission has retainedlie upper hand, once the first surprise waa over.The
The Inability of 12,000 troops easily to suppress from 60,000 to 100,000 insurgents is merely what was to be expected, as any one will admit who has had experience of the almost insurmountable difficulty of suppressing a popular insurrection.  His Majesty1s Government will remember that, in accordance with the advice of Marshal Foch, the French Government has always declared that in the case of an insurrection at least 60,000 men would be required to Impose order.    The observations of the British note on,this point would have carried greater weight had circumstances permitted the British Government to assume its share of the responsibility and the burden, under conditions of groat delicacy.4.    The &quot;humiliating&quot; position, in which certain British and Italian officials felt themselves to be placed in the districts occupied by the Poles, was not under far more disagreeable conditions, for the French officials, controllers and officers in the districts where the majority of the population was German.   Thus the French controller of the district of Kreuzburg is. at present completely isolated in the midst of armed German bands, and deprived of all authority.   Similarly, in many cases, our officers have been hustled.threatened and even arrested.The charge of fraternisation and partiality, which His Majesty&apos;s Government go so far as to bring against them, is entirely unproven. - The French Government attributes the insignificance of their losses solely to their coolness, to their superior armament and to the respect inspired by their prestige.   This enabled them to rescue/
rescue the Italian troops at certain points, and to clear the towns.    Some of the facts mentioned in the British note are obviously inaccurate, or explain themselves.   Detailed information has been asked for on all the others.    There is, for instance, the refusal to disarm the insurgents in the district of Beuthen.    The garrison of the town could not leave the town and sweep the country to disarm insurgents.   If insurgent patrols were able to assemble in Beuthen itself, this lasted a very short time and the town was rapidly cleared.That difficulties were placed by the French head of the Military Department in the way of arming police volunteers is perfectly true.    It is to be regretted that he allowed himself to be ultimately over-ruled;  for the result was that many undesirables were armed.    The Mayor of Oppeln himself came to protesrt to the Commission, declaring that to his knowledge sixty criminals had been enrolled.    These strange police brokie into the house of a British officer at Oppeln on May 17th, in order to arrest his polish servant.    It is surprising that the British Government has not been informed of such facts.5.    The removal of a company in the district of Beuthen was not abnormal, garrisons being frequently removed without the Controller being immediately informed.Generally speaking, such indecision (flottement) as there may have been at certain points is explained by the small numbers of French troops available in proportion to the population, and by the initial element of surprise.6.    The/
6.    The refusal of General Le Rond to form, without the instructions of the French Government a mobile column to clean up the country by force, is entirely justified.    The measures proposed must have failed, in view of the impossibility of preventing the revolutionaries from disappearing in front of the column and re-forming behind it, or from profiting by their numbers to inflict upon lt a severe check. There was a risk of this action resulting in massacres. The proposal did not bear examination;    it might even be represented as having a tendenclous character. The British Government would most certainly have judged likewise, had it been British troops that bore the principal responsibility in Upper Silesia;   British common-sense would never have risked troops under such conditions.7.    In genera!, no importance can be attached to press reports in affairs of such moment as this.   From the nature of the case, newspaper correspondents rarely speak of facts of which they themselves have been eye-witnesses;    usually they quote reports which have been made to them, mostly at second hand, or by persons whose character and prejudices make them unfit to estimate facts impartially,It is certain that the Polish Government has made the most serious efforts to prevent volunteers, arms or munitions from crossing the frontier.    The information to the contrary which the British Government appears to have received Is in conflict with thefacts,/
facts, which our agents all agree in reporting.    The closing of the frontier, the disavowal of the insurgents, the recall of Korfanty, etc - these proofs are public and indisputable.    Finally, it should not be forgotten that the powers and the commission have on several occasions intervened with the polish authorities to induce them to remove their troops from the frontier, and that this measure has been one not calculated to facilitate its closure.      On the German side, the frontier has remained * open and unguarded, in spite of repeated representations.If British officers have been arrested by polish insurgents, and have even been fired upon, the same thing has happened to French officers at the hands of German Insurgents.    It is hardly necessary to recall , the arrest of General Gratier and of Captain De Blois, and the shots fired at the General commanding the troops.It is not accurate to say that work is practically at a standstill in an important part of the area.    it has been resumed in a proportion varying from 50 to 90 per cent.8.     The French Goveranent like the British Govern--ment has never ceased to press for the rigid application of the Treaty of Versailles, which lays down perfectly precise stipulations as to Upper Silesia and the functions of the Allied commission and the allied Governments respectively.Similarly/j!
*   7   MSimilarly, the polish insurrection has been disavowed in the most definite manner possible by the French Government, which has made continual and energetic demands, both at Oppeln and at Warsaw, tbrat everything possible should be done to enable the allied commission freely to resume the administration of Upper Silesia in accordance with the treaty.     The active participation of the British Commissioner in all measures designed to produce tliis result has been constantly demanded, and not always with success.    Nevertheless, the latest reports indicate that, thanks to the agreement prevailing between the three commissioners, the situation is rapidly improving, so far as the Poles are concerned.    Equally with the British Government, the French Government has never admitted that it is possible to accept a fail.,accompli.9.    The decision taken at Lympne, at the last moment, and without any record in the minutes, to instruct the three Commissioners to send in their report without delay was, as is proved by events, undoubtedly a mistake. For it was this that let loose the insurrection.    All that can be said is that it was a mistake to which both Governments were partiese10.   The French Government is glad to learn that the British Ambassador at Berlin has made representations to the German Government even though, Lord D&apos;Abernon being without instructions, this has not been done in concert with the French Ambassador.    The latter has brought daily and unremitting pressure upon the German Government point-ing out the grave responsibilities incurred by it by the despatch of armed volunteers to Upper Silesia from various parts of Germany, and by the facts that the frontier remained open and that arms and munitions, collected at Breslau for destruction under the orders of the military control,&apos;-&apos;
,controi cornmiBBion, had &quot;been stolen.    the french govern-ment is disposed to think that the relatively good behaviour of the german government up to the present is essentially attributable to the energetic pressure thus applied by the french j\mbassador at berlin..   on the other hand, it is t&amp;eyowi dispute that german public opinion has interpreted official british speeches u an encourage-meht rather than as a warning.the french government cannot share the view that the german military formations have on thd whole remained inactive.    many acts of brigandage, incendiarism, extor-tion of money, etc., have been recorded.    the influx of . volunteer bands into the western zone has assumed ^such proportions that the allied commission has officially drawn the attention of the conference of ambassadors to the dangers involved.   the french government are entirely unable to Bhare the opinion of the british government as to the accuracy, of reports from German sources.    as an example may be taken the accusation made ty the german delegation to the conference of Ambessadbr^s that a french general had Associated with the insurgents on a ceremonial occasion.  This allegation has been denied, and its falsity is admitted.    Similar instances might be ntultiplied.11,   cn receipt of the first news of the insurrection, even in london, and every day since, the french government has telegraphed to Oppeln and to Warsaw, while it was simultaneously telegraphing to berlin, inviting the polish government to disavow the insurgents, to cut off all assistance or participation from poland, and to use all its authority to secure the dispersal of the polish bands and the re-establishment  of the reign of law in upper silesia.    it is true that the French government had previously/
previously been opposed to the expulsion of Korfanty; but this was because the French Government considered that his expulsion would give rise to the most serious dis-turbances, and because it thought itself justified in hoping that Korfanty would continue to observe the propriety of behaviour expressed in his proclamations and his repeated declarations.   What has happened shows how necessary it was to act with great caution in this matter.12.   The mining area taken in its entirety (i.ev including the districts of Pless, Rybnik, Kattowitz town, Kattowitz rural, Kfinlgshutte, Beuthen town, Beuthen rural, Tarnowitz, Zabrze and Gleiwitz) represents 34^,485 Polish votes and 289,980 German votes: that is to say, an indisputable Polish majority,On the other hand, the Polish insurrection, deplorable though it be, and necessary though it be to put an end to it, has come from within the area.   The Polish Government has in no way intervened from outside, and has done in this respect everything that it could do and everything that it has been asked to do.The German Government on the other hand, has permitted volunteer bands to be formed, armed and trans-ported free of charge from various parts of Germany to the Upper Silesian frontier; it has allowed these bands to steal arms that should have been destroyed in accord-ance with the treaty; and, finally, it has kept the front-ier open without opposing any obstacle to its passage by these bands or to the concentration of their strength at&apos; two or three clearly defined points of attack.   If, there-fore, these bands had definitely come into conflict with the Poles in the plebiscite area, their action would havebeen/
been one exerted fiom outside, without hindrance from, and with complicity of, the German Government, which by the mere, fact of intervention from outside, would have made itself guilty of a violation of the Treaty of Versailles even more serious than that which, disavowed by and unassisted by the Polish Government has taken place in the plebiscite area.13.   The British suggestion to allow the Germans forthwith to occupy the left bank of the Oder (that is to say, the agricultural area where their majority is not in dispute), and to allow the Poles to occupy the part of the mining area where their majority is over-whelming, while keeping the remaining part of the mining area as a disputed district under the control of the allied troops, would, without a shadow of doubt, have prejudiced the final solution, and would not have put an end to the Polish insurrection.  On the contrary, it would have increased the difficulties of the situation, by creating a danger that the Polish Government itself would be drawn in.   The fact is that, to divide the minings area into two parts by separating the completely Polish part from the part where Polish and German votes more or less balance, would have given to the settlement of the problem a definite turn in the German sense.Moreover, the British suggestion raised the ques-tion of the safety of the troops.  On this point the allied military advisers were unanimous, the British representative on the Versailles Committee emphatically concurring in the view of his colleagues.   In these circumstances, the British proposal could not but be set aside.
14,  The memorandum given on May 13 by the British Ambassador to the French Ministry for Foreign Affairs states that &quot;the French Government is indicated by the French press to be absolutely determined to in-sist on the cession of the whole of the industrial area to Poland, and this is to be achieved, if necessary, by connivance in an act of unlawful and predatory violence&quot; The memorandum adds that, &quot;if thin be a correct definition-ition of the policy of the French Government, His Majesty&apos;s Government must only say that they cannot possibly acquiesce in any such development, and that, if this course be persisted in, they cannot continue to exert pressure on the German Government to refrain from counter-measures, for which they can already find ample excuses&quot;.   The British memorandum now under reply appears to have overlooked these passages.   They justify the comment on them by the French President of the Council,15.  The German press and the German Chancellor himself have made many allusions to the encouraging hints that have been given to them as to the possibilities-ity of Upper Silesia being retained, if Germany were to accept the ultimatum.In the opinion of the French Government, the obligation of Germany to pay reparations can in no respect be modified by the assignment of the Upper Silesian mining area to Germany or to Poland.   This opinion is based on article 90 of the Treaty o;f Versailles, which has this very point definitely in view, and which lays down the steps that are to be taken to safeguard the interests of Germany, in thee vent/
event of the Industrial area passing to Poland. It is with the same&apos;end in view (namely, to take into account, so far as possible, the reaction which a decision favourable to Poland would have oh German capacities) that the Polish Government has supplemented the primary guarantees given by the treaty ty an undertaking to assume a proportionate part of the reparation liability in respect of Upper Silesia, and to safeguard the industrial development of the area    putting it under allied control.  Consequently, the French point of view on this matter is logically impregnable.16.  The French Government agrees that the first condition for a determination of the fate of Upper Silesia is impartiality, and it will not, any more than the British Government allow its convictions to be deflected by considerations of sympathy or antipathy.  Any reproaches of this kind which may have been made to either of the two Governments are cn an equal footing and are equally unfounded.

</content>
</cab>
