<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/36/0 images: 122-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. ..- -Iatel-ligence -Bureau,Department *f Information.GDW/003WEEKLY   REPORT   ON   DENMARK. III.(DEC. Hth, 1917)In the early part pf November Dr. L.V. Birck. University professor of National Economy in Cooenhagen, recorded his experience and im-pression ef a recent visit to England.     The articles are quite interesting, but too long, except briefly to summarize here.    The &quot;insularity&quot; of a very large proportion of the English amazed him. Most of the middle class he says simply look upon Denmark as &quot;the butter country&quot;, they talk vaguely about the Schleswig-Holstein question, or are surprised to learn that Denmark Is tnly interested in the Danish pooulatian in North Schleswig.    With the exception of the &quot;Times&quot;, he considered the other English pacers both unfair to Denmark and badly informed.     In Government ciroles, however, this made no differenoe, as they had the official figures;   but the oublic imagined that by her exports Denmark was simply sup-porting that country.&apos;     ficofessor Birok states that the annual value of the coal which Denmark gets from England is not over  3.000.000, and the longer the U,Boot campaign goes on, the more England will, by virtue of her monopoly in bunker ooal and all, try to get the Neutral tonnage to work for her.    Prom England, he says, fair treatment may be expected, but the Danes consider that the neutral tonnage which sail3 between the Entente countries ought to be considered equivalent to an export of articles for which some-thing other than coal ought to be retu&amp;U&amp;i     In other i/tcr&amp;d it Is claimed that the freight earned by Denmark in the serfice of the Entente whould be paid back in goods, nofc in money.     In the Danish comment on Lord Robert Cecil&apos;s reply to Dr. Birck it is stated that in P&apos;rli ment he openly and energetically asserted DenmarkTs
* ,t &apos;1- 2 -loyalty to. Great Britain.     Hie words, therefore, were received with attention and good-will in Denmark,It is stated that several Danish vessels have recently been sunk by submarines, that an enormous quantity of mines have been washed up, and that tne exploded at Skagen in Jutland.The order prohibiting the export of agricultural products, in-oluding pork, butter, and eggs was issued on the 19th ultimo. Export will, however, not be stopped, the Government simply desiring to control the expert of provisions so as to obtain, by way of oom-pensation, the most needed commodities.     Export licenses will be granted on the recommendation of the Export Commissions,The Danish people apparently agree with the statement of the President of the Norwegian Storting, M.Mowinkel - namely, that if the choice lay between agreement with America and a breach ef Scandinavian ties, it were better to starve than to separate.The v-fcole economic position of the Scandinavian Countries has been revolutionized in the past few weeks by events in Russia.Conditions vary in each country, but the meaning of the meeting of the three Kings in Christiania was that so long as the three kingdoms held together they constituted a definite factor end would be better able to urge their claims for favourable treatment oiS the Belligerent Powers, and try to find a &quot;modus Vivendi&quot; for one another through the mutual exchange of commodities.The position of Denmark^ according to their Press, is different from that of Norway or Sweden, in that the latter want food, and have commodities, iron, minerals, etc required by the belligerents. Denmark has e certain surplus of food, w ich might for example be exchanged with Norway for fish, or the fish bought on behalf of the British Government and now rotting in Norway (see Reuort on Norway IV), might be released, to ba made into cattle food, or fish oil, etc.
But each country feels a soreness and feels that the screw has been applied harshly, whilst the best friends of the Allies deprecate their treatment, because in View of the altered conditions Scandinavian countries may be able to get all the food they require from Hussia and thus indirectly play into the hands of Germany. This would seem to be a condition of things difficult to combat, and one which requires serious consideration.     In this regard an article from the &quot;Finans Tidende&quot; of Copenhagen of Nov. 28th is very interesting, and accords with the views stated above.     The article says j-&quot;In spite of all hindrances and dangers, and in spite of the political pressure used against us from other quarters, the  Allied Powers were\allowed the greater part of the pro-duction of our agriculture as well as our shipping trade, and partly also the production of our industries.     Was it beeause the Allies offered the highest prices?   On the contrary, it was beoausw we wanted to carry on a policy with a view to the future.   To us it appears as though Greai Britain and America were doing exactly the opposite.     From the mo-ment they break off connection with us they are inflicting a permanent poss upon themselves, and are acknowledging that Germany is the natural support of the neutral European States\ The former connection between Europe *nd the United States h^s been to our mutual advantage.     America is wrong 1b believing that sh  can do without European immigration and the export of European goods after the war, and that she can find compensation for the European markets elsewhere. Even if th* cutting off of the supplies to Neutral Powers should at present serve their purpose, it would in the long rua cause irreparable damage to Great Britain and America.The two Western Powers are at present acting like an ostrich burying its head in the sand.     We should not think it possible for two such splendidly organised states to show such lack of foresight if we did not find examples of a similar nature in history.   In 1864 Great Britain allowed the Central powers to crush Denmark and build the Kiel $anal. Later on Great Britain&apos;sold Heligoland to Germany etc     Yet none of these examples seem to jzs as grave as the blockade polioy into which Great Britain is now forcing the neutral Powers.     She confronts them 7/ith a cri3is wjrich gives them the option between suffering complete economic ruin or seeking help where they can get it.....,. By their way of conducting the war the Allies have up to the present only cleared the&quot; way for the supremacy of Germany on the European Continent. The statesmen of America and Great Britain know how little this result accords with our policy of neutrality&quot;.
Meanwhile unemployment in Denmark increases.   This is caused by lack of supplies, and is considered serious, as it is feared many workmen will go abroad to find employment.The question of the Icelandic flag and the Iceland question, has been in a way for Denmark what the Irish question has been for Eng-land.     Prom the days of Queen 1&apos;argrret in the 14th century, when Norway was united zo Denmark, Iceland has been a Danish province, and was recognised as a part of Denmark by the peace of 1814.In 1871 and 1874 Iceland made claims of independence which resulted in her obtaining a Parliament, the Danish Governor appointed by the king of Denmark being the intermediary between the island and the mother country.     The Danish Minister of Justice had a special port-folio as Minister for Iceland but did not visit or reside in the country.   This, but more especially the fact that the Minister was not an Icelander, aroused great dissatisfaction.     In 1903 the post of Governor was abolished, and an Icelander, H.Haffstein, was aopoin-ted as first resident Minister.     It is the Minister&apos;s duty to come to Copenhagen as often as necessary in order to lay before the King in Council his prop sals for legislation.    Iceland&apos;s grievance has long been that Danish Ministers insist on being present at these Councils, even although they admittedly take no part in the discussions.   While retaining the advanfcH^es of Danish nav^l and financial protection, Iceland h^s hitherto c.i imed th t her crnnecti n with Denm rk sh uld be merely a personal union with the King.     The Icelanders demand that the flag granted them for loccl use shall become their N-tion.I Plug, but so fcr their request hf-s not been granted.Danish p pers (Dec 12) st;.-te   :-&quot;The- result of the import of coffee into Denmark, caused by the British-American blockade, has boen the introduction of a rigorous system of rationing cciee, so tfc*?t no one to-day can purchase coffee except on the presentation ofj
his ration- card.     Generally speaking the blockade has brought about a very critical situation in Denmark.   Al-most all foodstuffs are rationed - bread, sugar, coffee, bacon, and butter, for examples , are only obtainable in very small quantities, while to procure lard or margarine is an impossibility. -   But for a commercial agreement come to with Germany it would have been equally impossible to obtain so necessary an article as salt.     Moreover, the lack of coal and of a number of raw materials is producing a constantly increasing amount of unemployment.     Each week sees the addition of fresh batallions to the crowds of the unemployed.     Last week the number of these latter increased by 20 per cent.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
