<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/36/0 images: 129-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
From Sir P. Cox, 13th December 1911.        \.&apos;y       j(Addressed to Foreign, repeated to Secretary of State for Indiaand Teheran.) . -\* \\ (Received 11.15 a.m. 14th. December.)jy^9$3. Your telegram 1.151 S. I have recently been on tour in Jratplirates Valley and received above telegram just after interviewing among otliers the three leading Miijtahids of Mesopotamia, namely, Saiyid Muhammad Kazim Yezdi of Nejef, Sheikh Husain Mazanderari of Kerbela and Mirza Muhammad Taki of Samara. Relations with these luminaries have all along been most intimate and friendly and recent interviews were none the less so&apos;: Bat in coarse of interview all. the Ulemas made anxious inquiries as to what was to be our attitude towards Persia and what the prospect of Persian State after the war ; especially in view of collapse of Russia, of whose policy and. attitude towards Persia they all spoke most resentfully.Prima facie they would all be willing -to give co-operation; but from above conversations I am convinced that before committing themselves to write letters in the sense suggested, they would require from me an authoritative statement in writing as to extent to which Great Britain intended to assist.Persia in the future and as to our post-bellum position ois-d-via Russia in regard to her.Quite apart from above we seem to have arrived at a psychological moment in the course of our relations with Persia at which a reconsideration of our policy is highly desirable and may even be forced upon us. If His Majesty &apos;s Government are in a position to make any communique on the subject it is possible proposed letter to these Mujtahids might afford a convenient and potent means of doing so... Naturally the question which strikes .one as of fundamental importance and on which a decision is an&apos; essential preliminary to any reconstruction of policy is whether or not, having regard to treacherous conduct of Russia towards her allies, the Anglo-Russian Agreement, and&quot;other engagements between Russia and Great Britain any longer hold good.We know that if Russia makes separate peace, Germany will do her best to upset Persia and turn her against us, and even though no serious thrust into Persia on the enemy&apos;s part may be a practicable contingency, nevertheless, it would unquestionably be useful if we could reassure Persia at this stage by a fresh&apos;announcement of stipulation calculated to make her proof against collusion with Germany.. a As to details the Bakhtiari could no doubt be squared by a promise of Ispahan Government, and once free of Anglo-Russian agreement and spheres of influence we ought not to find it difficult to satisfy reasonable ambitions of the national party, though I realise that to do this would involve a good many changes in existing arrangements.I offer these observations with diffidence for such consideration as they may call for.

</content>
</cab>
