<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/36/0 images: 167-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.femployment of Japanese Troops in Mesopotamia.y^jM ith reference to Lord Curzon&apos;s memorandum of the 3rd October 1917 TO.T. 2206), and minute 8 of War Cabinet No. 250, of 16th October 1917, I circulate to the War Cabinet a memorandum by tbe Political Department of the India Office, on the question of tlie employment of Japanese troops in Mesopotamia, which has my entire concurrence. I have no reason to doubt that Mr. Montagu would be in agreement with the views expressed therein. The Government of India&apos;s views, as given in a telegram of the 21st November 191.7, are embodied in the memorandum. Mr. Montagu had personally raised the question with the Viceroy before the despatch of the Government of India&apos;s telegram.Islington.13th December 1917.Memorandum by Political Department, India Office.&apos;1. The Government of India were recently consulted by the India Office on the suggested employment of Japanese troops in Mesopotamia. Their reply /dated the 21st November 1917) is unfavourable. They consider that, so far as can be foreseen, Japanese assistance is not likely to be required by the military situation in Mesopotamia, and they regard the proposal as open to objection both on military and political grounds.2. The following is a summary of their objections :  (i) From the military point of view, the)7 consider that, owing to differences in equipment, armament, supplies, &amp;c, arrangements for the maintenance of the expeditionary force would be complicated by the intro-duction of a Japanese element, while the demands upon tonnage would be greater than in present circumstances in which reinforcements for Mesopotamia are mainly drawn from India.(ii) Their objections on political grounds, to which they attach still greater weight, are as follows :-(1) The proposal would involve the establishment of a military base in India itself ;(2) it would alienate Muhammadan, and especially Arab, sentiment ;(3) it would impair not only the immense prestige acquired by our single-handed success in Mesopotamia, but our prestige in the East generally, and would create throughout the East a belief in the depletion of our resources ; and(4) it would give Japan a voice in the post-bellum settlement of Meso-potamia, and a foothold in the Persian Gulf that would prejudice our prescriptive rights in that region and our strategical position, both naval and military.3. Dealing first with the military aspect of the question, it seems to be generally admitted that, whatever may be the case later on, Japanese assistance is not immediately required in Mesopotamia. Lord Curzon&apos;s Memorandum of the 3rd October 1917 proceeded on the assumption that &quot; a most desperate and determined effort&quot; was about to be made by Turco-German forces &quot;to turn the British out of the Turkish territories in Asia.&quot; There was every reason to believe, at the time his memorandum was written, that such an attempt was seriously contemplated by the enemy. But circumstances have somewhat changed since the beginning of October. General Allenby&apos;s advance into Palestine, coupled with our successful actions in the Euphrates valley and the Jebel Hamrin, have strengthened&apos; :     S373   60   12/17 A
the British, position in the East; and recent indications tend to show that, for the present - at all events, the German General Staff intend to concentrate their efforts in other directions, and are little inclined to embark upon dubious military adventures in the East. There are even grounds for inferring that German policy in Asia has undergone a &quot; re-orientation,&quot; and that there is a disposition to abandon the &quot; Berlin-Baghdad line,&quot; as a means of striking at the British Empire in India, in favour of the &quot; Pan-Turanian &quot; project which the collapse of Russia has brought within the range of - practical politics of uniting all the Turkish-speaking peoples, of course under German guidance and control, in one continuous chain from Constan-tinople to Samarkand and beyond. - How far this aim is really capable of accomplishment may be open to doubt; but, if achieved, it would place Germany across the northern flank of our position in India, the Persian Gulf and Mesopotamia, and would more than compensate her for any temporary disappointment at Baghdad.4. The inference seems to be that a serious enemy offensive in Mesopotamia is less likely to materialise, in the near future at all events, than was at one time supposed ; and it follows that the date at which need will arise&quot;for Japanese assistance in that quarter is likely to be correspond-i ugly postponed. In any case we have the assurance of the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, given to the War Cabinet on .the 16th October last, that such assistance is not, likely to be needed before the autumn of 1918. The question therefore arises supposing the Japanese Government agree to place troops at the disposal of the Allies how these troops are to he employed. The Secretary in the Military Department of the India Office (Lieutenant-General Sir Herbert Cox) considers that the right course would be to treat them as a strategic reserve of the Allied armies as a whole, and to concentrate them in a locality where they will be readily available for any theatre of war in which they can be most effectively employed in the general interests of the Allied cause. The locality best fulfilling this condition is, in his opinion, Egypt. To quote his own words: &quot;From a &quot; military point of view I consider that it must be greatly to the advantage &quot; of the Allies to employ the Japanese Army, and that the first step should &quot; be to place the part of it that can be transported there and kept supplied &quot; (from the East) in Egypt.&quot; The political complications to which the presence of Japanese troops in Egypt might give rise are, of course, beyond the scope of the India Office ; but it may, perhaps, be doubted whether the objections on this score are greater than those discussed in the succeeding paragraphs as applicable to Mesopotamia, [n any case, Mesopotamia clearly offers no advantages as a base for a general strategic reserve, and there can be no object in sending Japanese troops to that theatre unless and until they are needed for active military operations there.5. The political objections to accepting Japanese assistance in Mesopo-tamia nray be classified broadly under two heads, viz.: (1) the effect in India and upon Oriental opinion generally; and (2) the price to be paid, to Japan, now or hereafter, for her co-operation.As regards (1), Lord Curzon emphasised in his memorandum the unde-silability of employing Japanese troops in any theatre of war where their appearance &quot; would be construed as ah admission that we could not protect our own interests and were obliged to rely upon another Asiatic Power.&quot; He regarded these considerations as definitely ruling out such areas as Persia, Afghanistan, Arabia, &amp;c. ; but held that Mesopotamia need not necessarily be placed in the same category. Mr. Montagu, in his letter of the 28th. September 1917, gave a number of reasons for taking the opposite view. They were based, firstly, on the intimate connections commercial, religious, &amp;c. that have existed between India and Mesopotamia for generations past; and, secondly, on the prominent part played by India in the Mesopotamian campaign itself. On the first point it is perhaps relevant to quote the following extract from the Report of the Trade Commissioners who visited Mesopotamia in the early part of the present year : &quot; Great stress should here be laid upon the organic connection which already exists between India and Mesopotamia.    Bombay is felt,
throughout Iraq, to be the nearest important centre of commerce and civilisation, and before the war the inhabitants of Basra used to regard Bombay and Baghdad as equidistant. Indian interests are, however, chiefly engaged on account of the pilgrimage of British . subjects and protected persons to the Holy Places. Besides the well-known Shiah shrines of Kadhimein, Kerbela, and Nejef, there are. Sutini places of pilgrimage ...   .   .   at Baghdad, besides othersnear Basra, which exert a strong attraction.....The &apos; Pir &apos;of Baghdad used to pay periodic visits to Delhi; and, lastly, the administration of the well-known Oudh bequest has fostered the Indian attachment Before the Avar there were about 3,000 Indians resident in the Baghdad Vilayat alone   .   .   .   .&quot;The country has, in fact, long been regarded as falling within the sphere of India&apos;s external relations, a view which found , formal expression in the arrangement under which the post of Consul-General at Baghdad was normally filled before the war by an officer of the Indian Political Depart-ment, who reported direct to the Government of India as well as to the Ambassador at Constantinople, and who bore, in addition to his Consular designation, the Indian title of &quot; Resident &quot; in Turkish Arabia.As regards the second point, the Mesopotamian campaign has from the first been popularly regarded, to quote Mr. Montagirs words, as an &quot; Indian -show.&quot; in its early stages it was, conducted from Indian headquarters; India has furnished the majority of tbe fighting men, and has served throughout as the base of supply and reinforcement. It may be said with truth that the operations in Mesopotamia have excited more general interest in India and have been more generally regarded there in the light of a domestic concern than those in any of the other great threatres of war.(]. For these reasons the arguments advanced by Lord Curzon in regard to Persia and Arabia appear to the Department to apply with, no less force to Mesopotamia. If we invoke Japanese aid in fighting what the Asiatic regards as our &quot;Indian. &quot; battles, he will draw the conclusion that we are no longer strong enough to light them for ourselves. Our next step, he will probably argue, will, be to call in Japanese troops to help us to maintain order in ludia itself. Rumours crediting us with this intention have already found some currency, and any action tending to give.them colour might have a very adverse effect upon the internal tranquillity of India,As regards the second of the Government of India&apos;s &quot; political&quot; objections, Muhammad an opinion is &quot;known to be extremely sensitive as to the introduction of &quot; idolatry &quot;---or what Islam regards as such into the sacred soil of Iraq. The Government of India recently felt themselves compelled, in deference to these feelings, to abandon a project, for which money had been collected in India, of building a Gurudwara at Basra for the use of the Sikh troops ; and similar complications might easily arise in connection with, the Japanese. The Arab is resentful of all external intrusion, and would doubtless view the intervention of Japan with dislike and suspicion.7. The Government of India make one notable point which was not referred to in Mr, Montagirs letter, viz., that the employment of Japanese troops in Mesopotamia would involve the establishment of a Japanese military base in India itself. As to this, Sir II. Cox writes: &quot; There is little doubt that the employment of Japanese -&quot;troops in Mesopotamia must include a Japanese base in India. &quot;Even if their force was sufficiently Avell found to be independent of &quot; India in all matters of equipment, stores, &amp;c, it would be impossible to &quot; resist granting room at Indian ports and hill stations for their sick and &quot; Avounded.&quot; If this view is accepted as correct, as it apparently must be, it affords a further poAverful argument against the Avhole proposal. The establishment of a Japanese base in India Avould obviously give colour to the rumours mentioned in paragraph 6. But it might have still more unfortunate results in another direction.   There is a risk that the JapaneseS 373 A 2
military mission might be used as a cloak for the propagation of &quot; Pan-Asiatic &quot; doctrines, which are known to Hud favour in influential quarters in Japan, and for intrigue with the party of disaffection in India, It is submitted that this danger is by no means an imaginary one. We know that sympathy for the &quot;oppressed Indian&quot; has been widely exploited in Japan, and that there is a party in the country whose watchword is that &quot; Japan&apos;s mission in Asia&quot; is to liberate the subject Asiatic races from the European yoke. These doctrines may not represent any very strong or genuine current of opinion ; but they have powerful advocates, and, to judge by our experiences in the case of certain notorious Indian seditionists who have taken refuge in Japan, they meet with little active discouragement from the Japanese Government itself. It must be remembered that serupu-lousness is not a characteristic of the Japanese, while espionage and secret propaganda are arts in which they excel. We should have no voice in selecting the personnel bf the Japanese mission, and could exercise but little control over the movements of individual officers. The pretext of military business would always be ready to hand, and, in the guise of Staff Captains or Transport Officers, Pan-Asiatic propagandists would be able&apos; to tour about the country almost at will. The internal condition of India already gives &apos;cause for anxiety, and the prospect of any extraneous incitement to the malcontents must be regarded with serious apprehension. &apos;8. It is perhaps worth mentioning, as a point of subsidiary importance, that sgme 10,000 Nepalese State troops, lent for the period of the war, are at present employed on garrison duty in Tndia. Japanese attempts at &quot; peaceful &quot;penetration &quot; in the States adjoining the North-Eastern Frontier of India have occasioned uneasiness for some time past. Tibet seems to have been their main objective ; but Nepal also has not been neglected. As the Government of India reported not long ago, &quot; attempts have been made &quot;l.o obtain permission lor various Japanese to take up their residence in &quot; Nepal under the cloak of religious study, a course to which the Prime &apos;&apos; Minister of Nepal naturally objects.&quot; The undesirability of giving facilities for Japanese intrigue with the Ncpalese needs no demonstration.9. It remains to consider the second group of political objections to the employment of Japanese troops in Mesopotamia,, viz., those arising out of the claims likely to be advanced by Japan as the price of her co-operation. Lord Curzoii questions whether Japan would be in a position to demand any political quid pro quo as a preliminary condition. It is not as if she were entering the war for the first time. She has been a belligerent for over three years, and could not quote as a precedent &quot; any case in which an Ally, &quot; merely because, he has been asked to move his troops in this or that &quot; direction, has demanded blackmail before consenting to the operation.&quot; It may. be remarked, however, that from the Government of India&apos;s stand-point it seems to matter little whether the Japanese demands are made in advance or are deferred until the peace negotiations, if it is to be accepted as common ground that, when made, they could not be resisted. It is true that Japan, if she intervened in the Mesopotamian campaign at this stage, would be sending troops to a country already conquered by ourselves. But her intervention could bo adduced as evidence of our inability to maintain our conquests without her aid, and must surely give her stronger claims to privileges in the region affected than if no Japanese soldier had ever set foot in the country. It is too much to hope that Japan, would refrain from playing so valuable a card, or would neglect so good an opportunity of pushing her interests in a part of the world where she is known to entertain projects of commercial penetration.10. The following passage may be quoted from the report of the Mesopofamian Trade Commissioners (see paragraph h) in thib. connection :  &quot;British merchants will certainly experience severe competition from Japanese in many branches of trade after the war. The markets in Mesopotamia are already  flooded with cheap Japanese glassware.
matches, cutlery, copper, metal sheets, and some kinds of piece-goods, especially what is known as &apos; American &apos; sheeting.   There have been various indications that Japan has commercial designs upon the .    Persian Gulf and Mesopotamia, and, in particular, mention may be made of the fact that Japanese steamers, under charter to a Bombay &apos; firm, have entered the carrying trade between India and the Gulf &apos;   * ports.   As a military measure, restrictions have been placed upon the entrance of Japanese ships at the port of Basra, and it is highly desirable that these restrictions should be stringently worked in order that Japanese traders-may not appeal to the precedent created, and maintain that their right to trade in the Persian Gulf has been recognised by His Majesty&apos;s Government.   .   .   .   The Government of India have under consideration the desirability of the registration of alien firms and individuals, and the restriction of their trading and commercial activities by means of licences.   ...   The Mesopo-tamian Administration will   .   .   .   be in a much &quot;stronger position, and it should be possible, on the ground of racial and religious susceptibilities, to deny to foreigners, other than Persians, the right of residence in the country for a considerable time to come.   The Commissioners are not aware of the political bearing of this proposal, hut, from the trade point of view, they desire to emphasise as strongly as possible the essential importance of excluding Japanese nationals, without of course placing any embargo on the access of Japanese products to the market.   The Bombay representatives of the Mitsui Bussen  Kaisha, in  an interview with  the Commissioners, most earnestly represented their hope that they would be allowed to send an agent to Basra.   They stated that they handled 40 per cent, of the imports of Java sugar into Bombay, and they doubtless have it in mind to float their trade on foreign sugar imports into the Gulf, just as the Germans did.   They are also aiming at the supply of oil tins and wooden cases to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company.&quot;11. This is not the place to consider whether the restrictive measures recommended by the Commissioners could or, ought to he enforced in their entirety.   Much will depend on the general commercial policy followed by His Majesty&apos;s Government after the Avar.   It may be that anything in the shape of permanent discrimination against the foreigner will be found as impracticable in the future as in the past, and that in the long run (as Lord Curzon suggests) we should in any event be unable to&apos; withhold from Japan such privileges as she may be expected to claim as the price of her military co-operation in Mesopotamia.   But the Commissioners&apos; Report indicates that even a temporary check upon foreign competition may be of the utmost value in enabling British commerce to take full advantage of the new openings offered to it.   If we keep our hands free, we may be in a position to give our own nationals just the start they require to put them ahead in the race with their foreign rivals ; whereas, if we are compelled, immediately the war is over, to admit the Japanese into Mesopotamia on equal terms with our-selves, the handicap is likely to be all the other way.   Owing to financial exhaustion, we shall be in a disadvantageous position after the war in comparison with a rival whose resources will remain intact.   It may be taken as certain that Japan will exploit her advantage to the utmost in every possible direction; and it therefore seems most desirable that, in a region where our own efforts have placed certain weapons of self-defence in our hands, we should not deprive ourselves in advance of the right to use them. The facts cited by the Trade Commissioners leave little doubt as to the reality of Japanese ambitions in the Persian Gulf ; and the experience of the past affords ample proof that commercial influence in this part of the world leads inevitably, sooner or later, to political claims.   We shall have gained little by the elimination of Germany from Mesopotamia and the Gulf if Japan is to step promptly into her shoes.12. In the foregoing paragraphs an endeavour has been made to state the objections, mainly from the Indian point of view, to the employment of Japanese troops in Mesopotamia, now or in the future.   It is, of course, fully
recognised that the final decision must he based on wide considerations of military policy or necessity, to which, in the last resort, everything else will have to give way. To Lord Curzon&apos;s question &quot; Is it better, to lose Baghdad [during the war] or to ensure its retention by Japanese aid?&quot; there can clearly be only one answer. But until it is certain that the alternative of holding Baghdad without Japanese assistance has, for military reasons, ceased to be a practicable one, or that the presence of Japanese troops in the Mesopotamian theatre would exercise a really decisive influence upon the whole course of the war, there appear to be very strong arguments against a course involving so many political disadvantages.J. E. Shuckbtjrgh.Political Department, India Office, 13th December 1917.

</content>
</cab>
