<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/36/0 images: 182-189</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DEPARTMJT Oi1 INFORMATION INTELLIGENCE BUREAU.19th December, 1917. WEISKLY   RISPORS? . QJ   gMY.1. in Armistice for twenty-eight days between Russiaand the Central Powers was signed at Brest-Litovsk on Friday, December 15, and will take effect from Monday, December 17, ex-piring on January 14, 1918.     Notwithstanding the protestations of the Bolsheviks, their diplomacy is by no means public, and little has transpired with regard to the terms of the armistice. It is Baid that its conditions deal with:(1)     The question of the non-transference of German troops to other fronts - a matter which Germany has probably already settled to her own satisfaction by transferring a great portion of her best troops and heavy artillery to the West.(E)     The relations of the German and Russian fronts during the armistice(3)    The gueStion of the Oesel Islands, the Gulf of Finland and the Russian fleet - points on which Germany is reported to have made some concessions.Further, it is believed that the negotiations for a definitive peace will begin at once with the armistice.The belief of the Bolsheviks that they can hold a weapon over Germany in the form of political agitation among the German Socialist masses is quite puerile.     The German Socialist masses may be, and probably are, prepared to agitate on their own account in favour of peace and also against the attempt which is being made by the reactionary majority in the Prussian Chamber to burke the Prussian Pranohise Bill.     But they will hardly take a lead from the Bolsheviks, as their attitude towards Russian revolutionaries is. really one of condescending patronage,
I   -2-sinoe they regard them as being on a lower cultural level.The behaviour of the Bolshevik Government towards the Russian Constituent Assembly is not calculated to recommend them or their methods to the German Majority Socialists, who are now working on parliamentary and constitutional lines and have already, e.g. at their. Wtirzburg Congress, vaunted the superiority of their patriotic policy to that of the Russian revolutionaries.2. The German Press is very exultant both about themilitary position and prospeots, which it naturally exaggerates, and about the political advantages of the Russian armistice and the disclosures which are being made from the Petrograd archives regarding the history of the Allies&apos; war diplomacy.     It was mani-fest at the time of theAmerioan revelations ebout Germany^ treacherous dealings with the United States and Mexico and about Count Luxburg&apos;s submarine suggestions that they had a very dspres-sing effect upon the moral of the Reichstag majority and the classes it represents.    But all that is forgotten in the present satisfaction at the exposure of Russiars policy towards Rumania, of this Allies&apos; efforts to obtain Greece&apos;s participation, of the secret convention between Prance and Russia as to annexations in the East and in the West, and the plans as to Syria, Arabia and Asia Minor.     Who, it is asked, were the Powers that were greedy for annexations?    And how noble by comparison is the disinterest-ed attitude of the Central Powers as expounded in the Reichstag Resolution of July 19, the reply to the Pope and Count Czernin&apos;s speeches I     Por the moment the picture is arranged so as to leave out the repudiation of the Reichstag Resolution by many of its former supporters, though not by the Socialists, and the aggres-sive character of Count Czernin&apos;s speech to the Hungarian Eelega-tion on December B, in which, under the influence of the Austro-German victory, he practically warns Italy that if she now con-tinues to fight, she cannot hope to obtain even tho status quo
ante bellum.     And, as regards the past, Bethmann Kollweg&apos;s declara-tions to Mr. Gerard about Germany1s intentions with respect to Belgium are always brushed aside as apocryphal.   It is,, neverthc-less, clear that the Bolshevik disclosures are designed to influ-ence public opinion in the allied countries and that they are cal-culated to influence neutral opinion in Europe.    Tno German press also makes appeals to President V/il^oa on tho ground of these disclosures.3. It is ovident that in the negotiations for peacewith the Potrograd Government a groat aim of Ettnlmann and his associates will be to secure at the earliest possible moment the resumption of economic relations between Geric-ny and as much of Russia as can be brought into the peaoe.     So iv.i      the actual indebtedness of Rufc&amp;ia to Germany - Government t-nd Railway Stock industrial interests, etc. - is concerned, it is pointed out that it represents a comparatively small item as compared with the olaims of the Western Allies.     It is not much above one milliard marks -  50,000,000 - while French creditors alono hold some 20 to 30 milliard francs - about  1,000,000,000 of Russian scrip.     In the cases of Groat Britain, America and Jipci, it is believed in Eermany that Ru ?.ic &apos;v indebtedness is mostly for war material supplied or for advances to meet the cost of it.     The Allies1 olaimB upon Russia, according to some Gorman journals, do not represent any leverage in their hands, but rather an instrument which the present Petrograd Government can hold in terrorem over them.    Tho soeotre of &quot;repudiation&quot; is one that respectable Gor.v a financiers do not care to conjure up, because, as the Frankfurter Zoitunp; is ruick to perceive, Russia after the war will need the financial cooperation of the whole world and par-ticularly of Britain and America to put her on her feet again. Lenin and Trotsky are probably impervious to such sublunary con-
slderations, and there are plenty of Pan-Germans whose vision does not range beyond such nihilistio expedients as repudiation.    But it may safely be assumed that Hortling and Kt&amp;lmann, who are the men at the holm, are amenable to more rational considerations which will certainly be urged upon them by competent German.authorities. Meanwhile, they may net be above tho trick of frightening the millions of the French peasant and artisan creditors of Russia vith the prospect of tbe loss of their savings.4. Without exaggerating the significance of the reportswhich constantly reach us regarding the^internal state of Germany, there is every reason to believe that the necessity for an early peace daily becomes more urgent.    But tbe distress of the people and the decline of its moral are only one element in the problem. It is impossible to product how much a people, drilled and organ-JLsed like the Germans, will tear on this side of absolute starva-tion.    She military situation is manifestly an anxious one, notwithstanding the elimination of Russia - if, indeed, the ... jmilitary tasks of Germany in Russia be really at an end.    Any elaborate German offensive on tbe V/estern front will, at the best, mean fresh holocausts of the German slain, while the Italian oampaign also threatens to be very costly and, perhaps, even doadlys when Generals January and February bogin their operations in the Alpine Passes.      The German masses will be horror-stricken at such fresh sacrifices after they had been beguiled by pictures of a military and political situation in which Germany is represented as holding all the trumps in her hand.     (That she alasi holds many trumpB no one can help the Allies1 cause by denying).Yet attention must again be drawn to the internal political situation of Germany.    Prussia, it must be remembered, represents two-thirds of Germany in territory and population, and much more than two-thirds in military power, in wealth and in
political weight.     And Prussia is in a state of violent ferment over the Reform Bills.   The supporters of the Franchise Bill wanted to have that Bill dealt with separately in Committee - where all the real amending is done. - fhey wanted a separate Committee for that Bill, so that its fate should not be coupled with that of the Bill for &quot;reforming15 the Upper Rouse (Herrenhaus) and giving it more influence and the Bill curtailing the financial powers of the Chamber of Deputies (Landtag).    This they have failed to secure. A Committee of 35 iias been appointed to deal with all three bills, and, in acoordanoe with the composition of the Chamber, elected in 1913 on the existing threo-ol$ss franchise, there is in this Committee an overwhelming majority of.opponents of the democratisa-tion of Prussia.    This majority may be estimated as something like three to one.    The vice-President of the Prussian Ministry, Dr. Friedberg, and the Minister of the Interior, Rerr Drews, have, it is true, warned the Majority regarding the perilous consequences of a rejection of the Government&apos;s democratic franchise proposals at a moment like the present.    Dr. Priedborg said that &quot;if the proposals were rejected it was not the Crown that he was afraidtof but the Conservative and Moderate parties in the State&apos;.1      The Reichstag is elected by direct and equal suffrage, a&amp;d there is a general consensus of opinion that, if the Prussian franchise pro-posals are rejeoted, the electorate in the Empire would let the Conservatives and Moderates know that they would simply be swept away at the next General Election.     That is why the Moderates are so much more democratio in tho Reichstag than in the Prussian Chamber.    Dr. Priedberg invited the Chamber to pass the democratic franchise proposals unaltered, in order to save tho country from &quot;grave convulsions&quot; (sohwere  esohttttorungen).    The bad prospects of the Bill have at once thrown the Socialists - not only the Independent Socialists but the Majority - into a state of great agitation.    They have issued an appeal to the masses to meet for powerful demonstrations, and they have set up a programme which
goes far beyond that of tbejPrussian Upper House, reduction of theChamber.     ^Demonstrations&quot; in war-time are dangerous anyvfbere. In Germany they would be repressed witb bloodshed, and a state of things would arise which might be incompatible with the prosecution of the war.    There would certainly be sabotage and passive resis-tence i&amp; the Munition works,   on the railways, and p&amp;ssibly at the front.     Such are the dangers with which Germany is at present confronted.It ought to be added that the question of German finances after the war is causing grave concern.K    The Frankfurter Zeitungj itself an organ of tee capitalist classes, is advocating, the impounding of one-quarter to one-third of all capital by the Strte.     It is said that the capitalists themselves would prefer this radical and summary measure to the endless screw of an uncertain income-tax.    The difficulties in the way of such a measure are serious - in the case, for example, of real property, whether held by individuals or by land companies.     The State would have in some cases to take over land and administer it.    But as the advocates of the scheme urge, it would have to be carried out with considera-tion for certain important classes of capitalists and without in-quisittrial interference with interests which might suffer to the detriment of the national resources, if a mere policy of indiscrim-inate confiscation were adopted.franchise age to twenty and an extension of the rights of the
Appendix to Report A&amp;ti/Q&amp;S,   if Sov,, IfP?Tl&apos;o terms of the husso-Germjji armistice have been disclosed and published by the.P...ess since the above report was written.    The;.- go beyond all that had previously been reported. Article IV contemplates the establishment of carefully-regulated intercourse between the opposing lines at the front &quot;for the develop-ment and strengthening of friendly relations between the nations of the contracting parties&quot;.     Such relations having been estab-lished between the unsuspecting Russian peasant and carefully chosen German emissaries at the front, it will not be easy for any Russian Government to reject GermanyTs ultimate terms of peace, however onerous they may be.     In Article VII, it will be noted, one of the places where special commissions, presumably half-German, are to be established in order to give effect to the Agreement, is Odessa (for the Black Sea).   Thus, far behind the Russian lines and at the great centre of the grain-trade, Germans will be sitting together with unbusiness-like Bolsheviks and will doubtless arrange matters to the complete satisfaction of the German Government.     In connec-tion with this it is to be observed that by Clause 5 of Article V, commercial navigation is permitted throughout the whole of the Bl- ck Sea and the Eastern front of the Baltic;   the establishment of safe navigation for merchant ships is entrusted to the special commissions which will sit at Riga and Odessa.     This part of the Agreement has the momentous effect of practically providing for the immediate rc-establishment of complete commercial intercourse between Russia, Germany, Austria-Hungary and Turkey.Thus, even before the actual conclusion of peace, such reserve stores of.oorn as may be accumulated in South Russia will be at the disposal of Geriaany, Austria-Hungary and Turkey.   Germany has, by the conclusion of this Armistice, obtained practically all that she could desire to have embodied in a final peace.     She has on her side, avoided committing hersSlf on any of the highly
contentious problems, for instanoe, tbe future of Poland and tbe Ukraine, which must ultimately, come up for settlement.Article IX. regarding Persia is a direct interfer-enoo with existing treaty engagements between the Russian and tho British Governments.    It     c first step towards placing Russian foreign polioy in Gorman leading-strings and directing it against British interests.    The last sentence of the &quot;Supplement&quot; to the Agreement provides for a mixed commission consisting of repre-sentatives of all the contracting parties to meet in Petrograd for &quot;re-establishment of cultural and economic relations between the contracting parties&quot;,    Thiu again seems to be a first step towards the realisation of a Geivuin scheme for placing at the disposal of the Bolshevik or whatever other Government may be in power at Petrc-grad, the resources and organising talents of the German bureaucracy. These would doubtless be backed and supplemented by the old Baltic German elements which played so important a part under the old Russian regime.    Russia needs strong government in order to rocover from the anarchy of her present collapse and Germans are assuredly preparod to-  . organise it behind the scenes.     It is needless to dwell upon the significance for Europe, Asia and, indeed, the whole world, of the prospects which a virtual German control over the population and resources of Russia or any groat part of it would open out.    The Armistice terms boar every sign of being an eeson-tially Gorman production.

</content>
</cab>
