<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/36/0 images: 294-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
n,is wemsm is the property o? his britamic hajthsty&apos;s ooysrsmsht . I0.1/139/396.In reply to your letter of th.? 6th instant I forward for submission to th^ Tar Cabinet the following observations regarding the Final Report of the Dardanelles Commission :-1.     I think that tho roferencoson pages $6 and 57 to projects of landing in the neighbourhood of Alcxandrotta, specifying Ayas Bay, had better be omitted.2,,     On page 6 it is stated that in January 1915 the War Council were discussing future military policy basod on the possibility of a stalemate in tho Western theatre. This phrase, which is repeated on page 6, and in an even worse form on page 15, is in my judgment likely to have a bad   effect onpablic confidence, and I think the conclusion is inevitable that the military authorities and the War Council, nearly three years ago had formed the opinion that the Gorman lines in the West wore impenetrable.3.      On page 7 a memorandum cf the General Staff, prepared on December 19th, 1906, is mentioned, and further-references are made to the same document in some subsequent pages, e.g., twice on pa.ge 84,     The memorandum discusses the possibility of a combined attack, naval and military, upon the Dardanelles.      I think the date should not be given and the words &quot;at an earlier date&quot; should be substituted for it throughout.     While,  of course, every soldier knows that it is the &quot;business of a General Staff to prepare plans of offence, the man in the street does not understand that such memoranda are prepared as a matter of routine. .   -Capital will, I am sure, be made out of this memorandum. The Germans will use it in their propaganda to prove that we-always meant to attack Turkey, and there may be a great howl from all our pacifists,4.      On the same pa:^e, Lord Kitchener&apos;s words are quoted that the Army &quot;ought to Gee the business through&quot; and that &quot;the effect of a defeat in the Orient would be very serious&quot; and &quot;there could bo no going back&quot;.     The same idea occurs twice, on page 10,  on page 23 and with marked emphasis on page  4.      1 think it unadvisabie,  considering that the attaek failed^ to emphasise the deplorable effects that failure was likely to have upon our prestige in the East. It would seem to me to be as veil to let sleeping dogs lie. We have not yet by any means finished our ^ork&apos; in&quot;the Fast, and the passages quoted show to the enemy how very sensitive we are in regard to our Eastern position.S rp. C RUT.----.- ^ 0ABI3^T tG.T. - 3078 . &quot;THE DARIAHESLLliSS CQiHISSION.Observations by tho Chief of tho Imperial General Staff in the Final Report of the Dardanelles Commission.
.   5,     Muoh of Sir John de Robe elds report of-Match, 7th on pages 13 and 14 may give information to the enemy-, but I presume the Admiralty will deal with this^ ,6,     On page   73, there is a reference to the *Saturnia1 having brought wounded to Mudros from Heiles although partly laden with ammunition.     This is, of course, perfectly permissi-ble under International Law. but the Germans have made a good deal of capital,-out of a similar incident that was reported in the Mesopotamia^ despatch, claiming that it shows the Red Cross to have been abused.7-.     Paragraphs of the Report that deal with water, food and medical arrangements and the detailed tables in the appendices will, I think, be studied with great interest by the German General Staff&apos;,8.     On page 80, Surgeon-General Howse is stated to have said &quot;We were in the unfortunate position of having no history to guide us of a previous landing on such a large scale in modern times,  so that we could get no idea of what medical arrangements should have been made.&quot;     The Germans, having no great experience of overseas transportation, are in the same unfortunate position, and it is good policy to keep our experience to ourselves..    .9*     The Force Orders and Instructions found on pages 140 to lb6 might, I should have said, have been omitted without sacrificing any of the interest of the final reportc      They were not published with Sir Ian Hamilton&apos;s despatch.     They sre full of information of value to the enemy.which 1915,10.    I observe, on pages 98, to 100, that the passage was omitted from Sir Ian Hamilton&apos;s despatch of 20th May when published, has been reinstated in this edition.11.   On the whole. I submit that publication should be deferred to the conclusion of hostilities.     Public interest in the Dardanelles is quiescent and the publication of this report is certain to revive in an acute form a large number of dead controversies which had better remain buried.     The question-that will be raised;  if and when this report sees the linht, will divert the attention of men on whom there reste the very heaviest responsibilities, to matters which, whatever v of them is held; are beyond lepair*.ewFrom a military point of view, publication will undoubtedly be harmful, unless such drastic omissions are made as entirely to alter its form,      It gives much valuable information to the enemy, and there is much in the strategical discussions on pages 6 to 12 which it is very undesirable Should be published.;( Signed)   W, Rc ROBERTS03JGeneral,Chief of the Imperial General Stafx   7WAR OFFICE,17th December,  I917.

</content>
</cab>
