<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/36/0 images: 302-309</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ocument is the Property of Bis Britannic Majesty&apos;3 Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   December 1917.SECRET.NAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION No. 30. Week ended 15th December., NAVAL OPERATIONS.On december 12th, at noon, a convoy of 1 british and 5 neutral vessels, escorted by north the destroyers. &quot; Pellew&quot; and &quot;partridge&quot; and the armed trawlers &quot;livingstone,&quot; &quot; tokio,&quot; &quot; Commander fullerton &quot; and &quot; lord alverstone,&quot; which had left lerwick for Norway at 11 a.m. on december 11th, was attacked by 4 enemy destroyers about 34 miles to the westward of selbiorns fiord. &quot; pellew &quot; ordered the convoy to scatter and &quot; partridge &quot; took station astern of &quot; pellew,&quot; and they were engaged by 3 of the enemy destroyers at about 8,000 yards range, the fourth enemy destroyer attacking the convoy. the enemy gained rapidly, and &quot; partridge &quot; was hit and dropped astern under heavy fire from 2 destroyers, shortly after which a heavy explosion took place and she sank. about the same time &quot; pellew &quot; was holed on the water line, and her engine room became full of steam. the enemy broke off action and apparently turned to attack the convoy, but.by this time, owing to rain squall, visibility was low. as &quot; pellew&apos;s &quot; speed was decreasing, and two of-her engines were disabled, she made for territorial waters, and when off slottero had to stop owing to loss of water in her boilers. She was towed to anchorage by a norwegian torpedo boat. all the ships of the convoy and the armed trawlers are believed to have been sunk.the &quot; shannon &quot; and &quot; minotaur &quot; with 4 screening destroyers, who were acting as covering force for this convoy, were steering towards it at noon at 17 knots when an emergency signal from &quot; partridge &quot; was intercepted. , Speed was immediately increased to 20 knots and all the destroyers were detached at full speed to the assistance of &quot; partridge.&quot; these destroyers picked up 88 scandinavians, of whom 2 were women, and 10 british, 7 of the latter being from the armed trawler &quot; commander fullerton.&quot; the &quot; shannon&apos;s &quot; force, and also the third light cruiser squadron, which, with 4 destroyers, was making a sweep further south at the time, failed to get into touch wdth the enemy.the &quot; pellew &quot; had 1 officer and 5 men killed, and 21 men wounded, 2 seriously. the crew of 12 of the armed trawler&apos;&quot; lord alverstone &quot; landed on the Norwegian coast in their own boat on the 13th. the enemy are reported to have picked up 3 officers and 21 men from the &quot; partridge,&quot; 11 men from the armed trawler &quot; livingstone &quot; and 1 officer and 14 men from the armed trawler &quot; tokio.&quot;On december 12th, at about 1.30 a.m., a small number of enemy destroyers sank near the farn islands the danish s.s. &quot; peter willemoes,&quot; which had become separated from a southward-bound convoy of 5 merchant vessels, with an escort of 2 destroyers and 4 armed trawlers. at about 4 a.m. on the same day the swedish s.s. &quot; nike,&quot; which had become separated from the same convoy, was torpedoed, apparently by enemy destroyers, and at(C 832)   55   12/17   H&amp;S
about 4.45 a.m. a fishing trawler was sunk off the Tyne, presumably by the same enemy destroyers, and another was badly damaged by gunfire.Mines have been laid off the Belgian coast and in the Heligoland Bight.The laying of a deep minefield off the East Coast has been continued.Flanders area and N.E. France.on december 12th a dover destroyer patrol engaged 3 enemy destroyers at long range, the enemy withdrawing. the shore batteries on the belgian coast fired 11 rounds at our patrol, but did no damage.r.n.a.S. machines from dunkirk have bombed enemy aerodromes at varssenaere and oostacker and bruges docks. two direct hits were observed at varssenaere and a number of bombs were seen to drop close to and among the sheds. good shooting was also made at bruges and a fire started. the total weight of bombs dropped was about 9\ tons. one of our machines failed to return.machines from dunkirk have destroyed 3 of the enemy and numerous low patrols have also been carried out, in the course of which many rounds have been fired into enemy trenches and at an anti-aircraft battery.during the period 18th november-lst december r.n.a.S. squadron no. 8, attached to the r.f.c. in france, has carried out 8 offensive patrols and 45 special missions in pursuit of enemy aircraft and low reconnaissances; the squadron took part in the aerial operations in connection with the advance of the 3rd army, west of cambrai; low recon-naissance flights, obtaining valuable information, were carried out in very bad weather, and enemy troops and transports were engaged with machine guns from low altitudes. there were no decisive aerial combats.   one pilot was accidentally killed.during the night of december 9th-10th, italian motor boats torpedoed the austrian 3rd class battleships &quot; monarch &quot; and &quot; wien &quot; in trieste harbour. the &quot; wien &quot; was sunk and aerial reconnaissance showed the &quot; monarch &quot; lying with a heavy list.the british monitor &quot; sir thomas picton &quot; has fired 28 rounds of 12-in. shell at enemy encampments on the piave.the railway between adrianople and constantinople was attacked on december 12th near alapie station by 2 r.n.a.s. machines, direct hits being obtained on the permanent way, on a train, and on warehouses at the station.enemy machines dropped bombs on tenedos town also on the 12th but did no damage.on december 12th two enemy submarines shelled funchal (madeira) at daybreak for half an hour, using 4.7-in. and 5.9-in. shrapnel. three persons were killed and 17 wounded.Casualties,        the armed boarding steamer &quot; stephen furness &quot; was torpedoed and sunk on december 13th in the irish sea, only 12 survivors being picked up.the destroyer &quot; wolverine &quot; has sunk as the result of a collision, and 4 of the crew are missing.airship c 27 has been destroyed by a german seaplane in the hoofden, and c 26 made a forced landing in holland. the airship n.s.5 has been wrecked on shore near St. abbs head.two seaplanes have been lost on patrol.attack upon enemy submarines.Submarines during the week 15 to 18 large enemy submarines have been located, nearly all of operating, ,.wnicn have been working to the westward of the british islands. three of these are of the &quot; cruiser &quot; type, one of which bombarded funchal, madeira, on the 12th instant. for the first time for several weeks one &quot; u &quot; type boat has been operating in the open sea, 180 miles west of ushant. the chief areas of activity this week have been the irish sea, the western part of the english channel, and off the north-east coast of england.Mediter-ranean.Atlantic.
The following Table shows the number of actions with enemy submarines in Home Actions Waters during recent weeks, and the nature of the craft which have been engaged, and ^mariS also the. number of submarines -destroyed : Nature of Craft.Cruiser   ......     ...Special Service Ships T.B.D. andT.B.... A.P. VesselsAircraft  ...     ......Sloops and &quot; P &quot; Class VesselsMerchant Vessels......Destroyed by MineTotalWeek ended November 24th.Week ended December 1st.Week ended Depember 8th.Week ended December 15th.Actions.1 1 4 4i3Results.Actions142 3 1 1 1Results.Actions.1 1 1104Results.17Actions.2 1 6 112Results.&quot;Results&quot; indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.One enemy submarine was sunk during the week by French destroyers.MERCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION. The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all Merchant Nu*nberVessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action : 		British Vessels.			&quot;Allied and Neutral Vessels.					Total.										Week Ended	1,600 tons gross		Under	1,600 tons	1,600	tons gross	, Under 1,600 tons		All sizes.		and over.			;ross.	and over.			gross.			No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No. &apos;	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.November 3rd	8	28,731	3	3,669	8	22,404	6	3,106	25	57,910November 10th	3	11,325	4	3,033	5	13,362	5	5,166	17	32,886November 17th	11	41,627	-8	7,626	4	10,703	c-	4,761	30	64,717November 24th	13	49,594	7	2,709	10	29,651	6	4,044	36	85,998December 1st...	16	- 59,533	1	179	7*	25,946*	6*	3,641*	30*	89,299*December 8th	14	45,958	.    7	4,689	6	18,696	11*	5,465*	38*	74,808*December 15th	14	44,966	&apos;3	2,011	10	23,749	10	9,288	37	80,014and ton-nage of all vessels lost.* Adjusted. y;  - . -The. total British tonnage lost this week is less than in any week since that ended November 10th, but owing to an increase in the losses of Allied and Neutral vessels the total of all losses remains at about the same level as during the last few weeks.The table in Appendix I shows in detail the numbers and tonnage of sailings and of Losses of losses by submarine and mine, and the percentage of losses to sailings of British Merchant British steamships of over 500 tons gross register and the table in Appendix II shows by trades fteamslups as regards such ships the percentage of tonnage sunk by submarine and mine to tonnage in ra es&apos; sailing to and from:United Kingdom ports during the last four wcekg,.(i :The percentage&apos; of losses to sailings as regards Overseas trades;.is this week 2.53 as against .64 last-week, but there has been a reduction in the losses in the Coasting and(C 832) A 2
- ENEMY MINES. .&apos;.     .&apos;Minelaying. Enemy minelaying activity has this week been experienced in the Nore area, the Straits of Dover, off Falmouth and in the Minches. The policy of widely scattering mines is becoming more and more pronounced with consequent increasing difficulty in locating them. For example, in the Minches two vessels have been mined,, but after very extensive searches no further niines can be located. There is evidence to hand that some enemy submarines are now both laying mines and operating with torpedoes.Casualties. The following table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed and British Vessels sunk bv mine in Home Waters in recent weeks : Week Ended.	Number of Enemy Mines Destroyed.	Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.November 17th...      ...	71	1 , .     -	Nil24th.......	25	1	ADecember 1st ...    . ...	38	Nil	48th......	46	1  .	1&apos;   15th......	47	Nil	3In addition an unidentified fishing vessel has been sunk by mine off the Shetlands, and an oiler has been damaged by mine in the Little Minch.DEFENCE AGAINST SUBMARINE AND MINE.Convoy. During the week 711 ships have been convoyed as compared with 703 last week.   Ofthese 711 ships, 375 were engaged in the French Coal Trade, 118 on the Scandinavia-Lerwick-Humber route and the remaining 218 in Overseas trade, 87 inward and 131 outward. There have been 10 losses in convoy during the week, 1 in the outward convoy from Fal-mouth and 9 .on the Scandinavia-Lerwick-Humber route, 8 of these having been sunk by enemy destroyers.Defensive armament.During the week 32 merchant vessels have been fitted to take primary armament and 30 to take supplementary armament, the number of Merchant Vessels at present fitted with defensive armament being 3,706. . .The total number of Howitzers and Bomb Throwers delivered to date is 413^Mine pro-tectiongear.At present 996 Merchant Vessels are fitted with Otter Equipment.MOVEMENTS OF ENEMY SHIPS.Merchant-men.Three enemy merchant ships have this week arrived at and three have sailed from Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat, and nine have left Delfzyl for Swedish ports with inemyleb^/ One has left Ymuiden for :Germany on completion of repairs.Cross-Channel trades with the result that the percentage of losses to sailings as regards all trades is 1.08 as against .87 last week. V: ;,:*.:Areas in The table in Appendix III is a comparative statement of all British Merchant Vesselswhich sunk, damaged or molested, and of all Allied and Neutral Merchant Vessels sunk in the&quot; vessels lost, last two weeks by enemycraft and by mine classified according to areas.It will be noticed that there,are still comparatively few losses in the Atlantic and thatthe losses in Home Waters this week are largely in the North Sea, owing to the loss of theScandinavia convoy. -
There is no foundation for the reports that the defences of Venice are being dismantled with a view to. declaring it an open city. Some of tfie guns of the land defences were removed and mounted on lighters,-but these were subsequently replaced.\ Denmark.An agreement has been reached whereby Germany has promised to supply 22,000 tons of shipbuilding material to Denmark within the next few months, on condition that the ships built with this material shall trade only with Germany or Scandinavian countries.- Japan.It is credibly reported, that the Naval Arsenal at Kure is working at only about 30 per cent, of its peace capacity, and 10 per cent, of its war capacity. Shortage of material and labour are the alleged reasons, but the former shortage is hard to reconcile with information received, while the latter is said to be due to migration from Government to Private Yards where pay is better. x&apos; China.In the Yangtze Valley lawlessness and piracy are rife, the Chinese troops being out of hand, and 2 British merchant vessels, 1 American merchant vessel, and 1 American gunboat have been fired on,- and British, American and Japanese offices have been looted and robbed.   Rioting is also daily expected at Hankow.The Allied Naval Force immediately available consists of River Gunboats, 1 British, 1 U.S.A. and 1 Japanese, believed to be stationed on the Upper River, and 2 British, 4 TJ.S.A. and 2 Japanese on the Lower River.Additional Naval Force is being supplied by us, and can be supplied both by U.S.A. and Japan. The U.S.A. have available two more River Gunboats at present at Hong Kong or in the Canton Delta, and two larger gunboats, and Japan, has six light cruisers in addition to destroyers and torpedo boats which are not definitely employed -on war work, and which are suitable for the Lower River, excluding the Tung Ting Lake. &apos;.- Trouble is also reported at Swatow whither one British destroyer is proceeding, and where, according to the Press, a Japanese ship has arrived. The cable to Hong Kong having broken down no details are available. - :Apart from Press reports of doubtful reliability, nothing has been heard for some time of affairs at Canton. There are vague indications of movements of troops and of activity on the part of Lung Chi Kuang, the former Military Governor, exiled to Hainan. On December 14th 2 light cruisers, 2 destroyers and 3 transports of the Naval Force disaffected to the Peking Government, left Canton and proceeded Eastwards in the direction of Swatow. A force loyal to Peking is already based on Swatow.Ecuador.The Government has announced that Allied men of war will be permitted to remain indefinitely in Ecuador ports. Guayaquil thus becomes an alternative to Callao as a base for H.M. Ships, but the unhealthy season, which lasts from December to May, renders it less suitable than Callao.NAVAL STAFF,20th December, 1917.[Appendices.
&apos; &apos;      iI.   .     -f     &apos; Italy.  -  - - . -&apos; *.     * .  r.:There is no foundation for the reports that the defences of Venice are being dismantled with a view to declaring it an open city. Some/of the guns of the land defences were removed and mounted on lighters., but these were subsequently replaced.I Denmark.An agreement has been reached whereby Germany has promised to supply 22,000 tons of shipbuilding&apos; material to Denmark within the next few months, on condition that the ships built with this material shall trade only with Germany or Scandinavian countries.Japan.It is credibly reported that the Naval Arsenal at Kure is working at only about 30 per cent, of its peace capacity, and 10 per cent, of its war capacity. Shortage of material and labour are the alleged reasons, but the former shortage is hard to reconcile with information received, while the latter is said to be due to migration from Government to Private Yards where pay is better. x:* China.In the Yangtze Valley lawlessness and piracy are &quot;rife, the Chinese troops being out of hand, and 2 British merchant vessels, 1 American merchant vessel, and 1 American gunboat have been fired on, and British, American and Japanese offices have been looted and robbed.  Rioting is also daily expected at Hankow.The Allied Naval Force immediately available consists of River Gunboats, 1 British, 1 U.S.A. and 1 Japanese, believed to be stationed on the Upper River, and 2 British, 4 U.S.A. and 2 Japanese on the Lower River.Additional Naval Force is being supplied by us, and can be supplied both by U.S.A. and Japan. The U.S.A. have available two more River Gunboats at present at Hong Kong or in the Canton Delta, and two larger gunboats, and Japan has six light cruisers in addition to destroyers and torpedo boats which are not definitely employed -on war work, and which are suitable for the Lower River, excluding the Tung Ting Lake.Trouble is also reported at Swatow whither one British destroyer is proceeding, and where, according to the Press, a Japanese ship has arrived. The cable to Hong Kong having broken down no details are available. -Apart from Press reports of doubtful reliability, nothing has been heard for some time of affairs at Canton. There are vague indications of movements of troops and of activity on the part of Lung Chi Kuang, the former Military Governor, exiled to Hainan. On December 14th 2 light cruisers, 2 destroyers and 3 transports of the Naval Force disaffected to the Peking Government, left Canton and proceeded Eastwards in the direction of Swatow. A force loyal to Peking is already based on Swatow.Ecuador.The Government has announced that Allied men of war will be permitted to remain indefinitely in Ecuador ports. Guayaquil thus becomes an alternative to Callao as a base for H.M. Ships, but the unhealthy season, which lasts from December to May, renders it less suitable than Callao. ,. .NAVAL STAEF,20th December, 1917.[APPKNDIPES.
APPENDIX 1.Statement of Numbers and Tonnage of SAILINGS and LOSSES of British Merchant Steamships of over odd ions gross register forthe Week ended 15th December, 1917.Sailings.Losses.Percentage of Losses to Sailings.* Figures for previous week.Trade United Kingdom, to and from 	In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.	-----.....-.....-.....&apos;.....-.....-   &apos;        1  .           .&apos;	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	. No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons. *	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.North America Coast.........     -... Gulf and West Indies.......... Gibraltar....      ...      ......      ...     .... Dakar, St. Vincent, W. Africa and S. America Bay, Portugal and Spain, West of Gibraltar Scandinavia Holland ... Russia   ...............	36 8 19 15 22 23 4	200,037 55,111 77,466 74,293 - 56,525 50,991 4,025	31 3 42 15 10 11 8 1	187,181&quot; 17,226 171,874 102,015 23,594 17,816 10,808 3,933	67 IF 61 30 32 34 12 1	387,218 72,337 249,340 176,308 80,119 -68,807 14,833 3,933	2	9,263	1 2 2	5,690 7,278 4,383	3 2 2	14,953 7,278 4,383	5.55	4.63	3.22 4.76 1,8.18	3.04 &quot;4.23 24.60	.4.48 , 3.28 5.88	3.86 2.92 6.37Total Overseas Traffic to and from United Kingdom	127 132*	518,448 619,605*	121 167*	534,447 717,616*	248 -.299*	1,052,895 1,337,221*	2 1*	9,263 1,879*	5 2*	17,351 6,648*	7 3*	26,614 8,527*	1.58 .76*	1.79 .30*	4.13 1,20*	3.25 .93*	2.82 1,00*	2.53 .64*Coasting...      ...      ......	.  &apos;.&apos;	&apos;--	- (i		597	1,084,018	 	-   .	 	&apos; ,-	3	4,899	  r]	-:	- 	 	.50	.45Cross Channel  ....	262	560,616	267	587,484	529	1,148,100	 	-r	2	3,917	2	3,917	  .		.75	.67	.38	.34Total of Coasting and Cross Channel				 	1,126 1,156*	2,232,118 2,315,883*	 	-	 	-r	5 11*	8,816 23,226*	 				.44 .95*	.39 1.00*Grand Total of traffic to and from United Kingdom .					1,374 1,455*	. 3,285,013 3,653,104*			 		12 14*	35,430 31,753*		 	-		.87 .96*	1.08 .87*		Losses on otlier Trades			* * *	* * *            * &quot; *				- *	4 5*	11,455 18,607*					::: :			Total Losses fo		r Week ...	...	&apos;   ... .&apos;   ...	 	 	 	-	16 19*	-46,885 50,360*						
&apos; APPENDIX II.Statement showing by Trades as regards British Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross, the percentage of tonnage sunk by Submarine and Mine to tonnage sailing^ -in tt     - ,        t    ttt- t t. 1        * 1 1 &apos;Week	Week	Week	(Weekended	ended	ended s	ended24th. Nov.	1st Dec.	8th. Dec.	15th Dec.	-    *		4.632.11			3.04.98	 		3.86.14.14	4.08	&quot;   -	;   &apos;2.59	4.13	1.66	4.235.02	4.11	1.42	2.92- /  	12.18	 &apos;	i      &quot;:._	6.11	 	; _2.93	&quot;i  	2.22	7.31	13.66	6.42	! &apos; :4.28	6.88	3.66		z	_	24.60 - -	 	 	6.3719.27	- _	*_	\ -             -8.07	0	      v	1.39	2.48	.30	1.79- 2.34	2.06	.93	.3.251.83	2.26	.64	2.53.89	- .84	1.51	.452.42   &quot;	.87	.96	,671.23	.44	.47	.341.34	1.25	.87	1.08TradeUnited Kingdom, to and from-North America Coast     ......      ...Gulf and West In 1 as     ......^   ...Gibraltar............   ......Dakar, West Africa and South America Bay, Portugal and Spain, West of GibraltarScandinavia......Holland     ............, ...Russia       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...Total of above Trades        ......Coasting    ......      ...     ...     ....Cross Channel      .............Total of all United Kingdom Tradesfin   ..4 Out .. t Total fin   ..-j Out&quot;.. L Total fin   ..-i Out ... I Total fin   ...-i Out ... t Total fin   ...-i Out ... t Total fin   ...j Out ... [ Total fin   ...^ Out ... I Total fin   ....^ Out ... [ Totalfin  ...-i Out ... (j TotalTotal fin   ... -i Out ... I TotalAPPENDIX HI.Statement of the number of British Merchant Vessels sunk, damaged or molested, and Allied and Neutral vessels sunk during weeks ended 8th and 15th December,	British.								Allied and Neutral.				Sunk.				Damaged or Molested but not Sunk.				,   Sunk.			Area.	1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended														Dec. 8	Dec. 15	co 6 a P	Dec. 15	Dec. 8	Dec. 15	Dec. 8.	Dec. 15	Dec. 8	1-1 P	Dec. 8	iO h d 0) PArctic and White Sea Atlantic (North) Atlantic (South) Bay of Biscay Gibraltar   ...... North Sea...... English Channel Irish Sea and Bristol Channel...... Mediterranean	1 1 1 iSMf . :c5 2 5	2 1 5 1 k-2 3	1 5 1	2 1 1	1 3 s   2 3	1 4&apos; 1	1 1 1	4 1	1 i _     &apos; 5	4 1 -5   1 1	2 3 6	2 3 % % 1Totals       ...1	14	14	7	4	9	6	3	5	6   i	10	11	10

</content>
</cab>
