<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/42/3 images: 16-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted&apos; for the War Cabinet.   April 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (44)45th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 45 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, 5th April, 1944, at 6-30 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)(Items 3-4).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council (inthe Chair) (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production (Items3-4).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following wThe Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir ArchibaldSinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Items1-3).The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Items1-3).Major the Right Hon. G. LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Fuel andPower (Items 1-3).re also present:The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India andSecretary of State for Burma(Items 3-4).The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State forScotland (Item 4).The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Health (Item 4).The Right Hon. Lord Portal,Minister of Works (Item 2).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.[27256-2]-b
The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General (Items 3-4).Admiral of the Fleet Sir AndrewCunningham, First Sea Lord andChief of Naval Staff (Items 1-2).Mr. A. T. Lennox-Boyd, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofAircraft Production (Item 3).Air Marshal Sir Douglas Evill,Vice-Chief of the Air Staff (Items1-2).Lieutenant-General A. E. Nye, Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-2).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Lieutenant-General Sir Hastings L. Ismay.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. W. S. Murrie.WAR CABINET 45 (44).Contents.MinuteNo.                                     Subject. Page1      Oil        ................................    201Discussions with the United States:   Instructions to officialdelegation.2      Building...............      .............   .....     2023      Industrial Unrest..................      ....      ....     203Position in the coal industry.Question of additional powers to deal with persons who instigatestrikes.4      Man-Power      ............      ................     204Supply of doctors.
Oil.Discussionswith the UnitedStates:Instructions toOfficialDelegation.(PreviousEef erence:W\M.(44)37thConclusions,Minute 4.)1. Following the conclusions of the War Cabinet at theirmeeting on the 21st March, 1944, a Ministerial Oil Committee hadbeen appointed by the Prime Minister on the 28th March, underthe Chairmanship of the Minister of War Transport (the othermembers being the Minister of State, the Financial Secretary tothe Treasury, the Chairman of the Oil Control Board, and repre-sentatives of the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Secretary ofState for India), to consider, in the first place, the terms of theinstructions to the Official United Kingdom Delegation toWashington for the forthcoming discussions on oil.The War Cabinet now had before them : (i) a Report(W.P. (44) 179) by the Ministerial Oil Committee, setting out theirrecommendations as to the instructions to be given to the OfficialOil Delegation; (ii) a Report by the Chiefs of Staff on the strategicaspects of the forthcoming discussions (C.O.S. (44) 322 (O) ).*The Minister of War Transport said that the undertakingsthat had been received from the United States Government madeit unlikely that issues involving existing rights or properties in oil,or the transfer of oil products without payment, would be raised.It would be the business of the Delegation to see that thediscussion was not limited to the Middle East, but was directed toconsideration of the world position. The position as regardsService requirements was fully protected. While the authoritygiven to the Delegation was very limited in character, he believedthat there was an opportunity of an arrangement being arrived atwhich would be advantageous to this country, and that there wasgood reason for examining certain of the questions which theUnited States Government desired to raise.The First Sea Lord said that, from the strategic point of view,the Chiefs of Staff supported the draft Instructions, and hadreached the conclusion that, on balance, it. would be to ouradvantage that the United States should have an interest and hencea strategic commitment in the Middle East oilfields.In the discussion the following points were made : -(a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Treasurywould have preferred that Instruction (1) should have spoken of&quot; ascertaining the views of the United States Delegation &quot;as topossible bases&quot; rather than &quot;exploring possible bases.&quot; TheInstructions as at present drafted might suggest that the twoDelegations were to collaborate in finding bases of agreement.In reply, it was pointed out that the discretion given to theDelegation under.their Instructions was strictly limited and couldhardly well be further reduced. Moreover, we had agreed in thecorrespondence leading up to its despatch that these conversationsshould be exploratory. It seemed doubtful, therefore, whether anyamendment was really necessary.(b) The Lord President of the Council suggested thatInstruction (5) might be read as committing His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment to a general support of particular oil interests. It was urged.,on the other hand, that there was definite advantage in an arrange-ment on these lines, and in placing the onus, so far as practicable,on the Governments concerned of ensuring that the general conductof enterprises of this nature followed the right- lines. The recentconduct of the Mexican Government in oil matters had brought outthe possible advantage from our point of view of arrangements suchas those now suggested.(c) The point was raised that the United States Governmentmight refer to the provisions of the Atlantic Charter as regardsaccess to raw material. It was urged that the alternative to anarrangement such as that outlined in the Instructions was an inter-national scramble for oil which might well be more dangerous toworld peace than the measures of control which would result from[27256-^2].W.P. (44) 187.
close collaboration on oil questions between the United States andthe United Kingdom.The War Cabinet-(i) Took note of the Report of the Ministerial Oil Committeeand approved the Instructions to the Official Oil Delega-tion to Washington recommended by them,(ii) Took note of the Report by the Chiefs of Staff on thestrategic aspects of the forthcoming discussions.Building.(PreviousReference:W.M. (44) 14thConclusions,Minute 4.)2. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Production (W.P. (44) 182) proposing a temporaryembargo on new building projects in order to ease the burden oninland transport.The Memorandum explained that early in March Departmentshad been asked to plan for a reduction of 10 per cent, in theirdemands on transport for building materials and to review theirnew building projects in the light of the theory of maximum impactduring 1944. Since then the Ministry of Production, in conjunc-tion with the other Departments concerned, had explored thepossibility of making greater savings, and had come to theconclusion that the most effective step which could be taken wouldbe to place a temporary embargo on all new building projects whichhad not started by the end of the present week. The question ofcontinuing the embargo would be, reviewed at the end of April andit would not apply to maintenance work or to works of less than 5,000 value. Exceptions would also be granted for operationalworks which would be ready in time for forthcoming operationsand for certain other projects. The labour released by the embargowould be used for transport and other urgent operational needs andfor essential housing repairs. Decisions on claims for exemptionfrom the embargo would be made by the Minister of Productionthrough the machinery of the Ministry of Works.The Minister of War Transport said that he strongly supportedthe proposed embargo. Coupled with the zoning system alreadyintroduced for building materials, it would enable a very sub-stantial saving to be made in inland transport.The Secretary of State for War said that he assumed that theService Departments would be entitled to decide what works mustbe regarded as essential for forthcoming operations and that thequestion of what projects fell within this class would not be leftto the decision of the Ministry of Works.The Secretary of State for Air and the First Lord of theAdmiralty said that they accepted the scheme, subject to one or twoparticular points, on which they were in correspondence with theMinister of Production.The Minister of Works said that, subject to one or two pointsof detail, the proposals in W.P. (44) 182 had been agreed with theProduction Departments. In paragraph 8 of the Memorandum theMinister of Production offered to consult with his colleagues on anyspecial procedure that might prove to be required for the adjudica-tion of claims for exemption on grounds of operational importance.The embargo would not hold up work on the repair of war-damagedhouses, since only projects costing more than  5,000 were affectedby it.The War Cabinet-(1) Approved the proposals in W.P. (44) 182 for the impositionof a temporary embargo on new building projects,subject to the exemptions mentioned in the Memo-randum.(2) Agreed that the question of the continuance of the embargoshould be raised at the end of April.
IndustrialUnrest.Position in theCoal Industry.(PreviousReference:W.M.(44)43rdConclusions,Minute 7.)Question ofadditionalpowers to dealwith personswho instigatestrikes.3. The War Cabinet discussed the situation in the coalindustry.The Minister of Fuel and Power reported that there had beena considerable improvement in the position in Yorkshire and thatthere was reason to hope that the strike was breaking up. If workwas fully resumed next week, it would be possible to keep all themajor gas works going and the railways and electricity generatingstations would not be affected. There would, however, be a sub-stantial loss of production in the coke ovens.In view of the interest shown by Members in the situation andof the fact that the House would not meet again until after Easter,he proposed to make a statement after Questions on the followingday. It was not intended that there should be any debate on thisstatement.The Minister referred particularly to the tendency which hadshown itself in the Press to blame the Government for the recenttroubles in the coal industry. In fact, the Porter Tribunal was anindependent body and there was no alternative to accepting theiraward. The Minister of Information had explained this to Lobbycorrespondents.The Chancellor of the Exchequer endorsed what the Ministerof Fuel and Power had said about the responsibility for theunsettled state of the coal industry. There was no foundation forthe suggestion, which had been made to him by certain Members ofParliament, that the industry, if left alone, could have worked outthe application of the Porter Award satisfactorily. In fact, theGovernment had had to step in in order to prevent the two sides ofthe industry from throwing an unwarranted burden on the CoalCharges Account.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he haddiscussed the question of industrial stoppages with the T.U.C.earlier in the day and had obtained their support for a new DefenceRegulation, which had been approved in principle by the LordPresidents Committee, tO&apos; enable action to be taken againstinstigators of strikes. There was definite evidence that membersof a political organisation were fomenting trouble, especially in theSheffield area, and the question whether action could be takenagainst them, either under the Trade Disputes and Trades UnionAct, 1927, or by the use of Defence Regulation 18b, was beingexamined. He had considered whether it would be possible to callup young miners who were on strike for service in the Forces. Inview, however, of the man-power situation in the industry and of thefact that youths were being directed into mining instead of beingcalled up to the Forces, it was impossible to take this course.The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security said thathis information suggested that the organisation referred to by theMinister of Labour and National Service had from 1,500 to 2,000members. Certain documents which had come into the possession,of the Home Office were now being examined with a view todeciding whether action could be taken under existing powers.The War Cabinet-(1) Took note of the report made by the Minister of Fuel andPower on the situation in Yorkshire and of the actionwhich was being taken by the Minister of Labour andNational Service and the Home Secretary and Ministerof Home Security against instigators of strikes.(2) Agreed that on the following day the Minister of Fuel andPower should make a statement in the House on thesituation in Yorkshire. The statement should notinclude any reference to the proposed action againstinstigators of strikes.
Man-Power. 4.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSupply of Lord President of the Council (W.P. (44) 180) about the allocationDoctors. of doctors to the Services in 1944.. The requirements of the Services,including India, for doctors was now put at approximately 2,350.The total allocation was estimated at 1,250 on the assumption thatthe Services would accept 200 women and alien doctors. Thisrepresented the limit of what could be provided, as the medicalfacilities available to the civilian population had reached a pointbelow which it was not possible to go without serious danger of abreakdown.  Moreover, the Services needed fit men of military age.At a meeting of the Lord Presidents Committee the Secretaryof State for War had made it clear that failure to supply the fullnumber of doctors asked for by the Army (who would receive onlyjust over half their requirements) would, unless forthcomingoperations were more immediately successful than we had the rightto expect, involve a grave risk of a breakdown in the Army medicalservice later in the year. Accordingly, the Lord PresidentsCommittee, while approving the suggested allocation of 1,250available doctors between the Services, had asked the Service andHealth Ministers to make immediate arrangements for an examina-tion into the possibility of devising a scheme whereby medicalpersonnel in various establishments, Service and civilian alike,would be earmarked for immediate transfer in case of emergency toestablishments where a breakdown or loss of efficiency would havethe most serious consequences.Attention was also drawn to the fact that some months ago theUnited States War Department had undertaken to supply us withequipped and staffed field hospitals with 8,000 beds. It nowappeared that this undertaking would not be fulfilled, and it wassuggested in the Lord Presidents Memorandum that a furtherapproach should be made to the United States Government on a veryhigh level.Points raised in discussion : (a) The Minister of Health said that he had heard that therewere 80 Danish doctors now in Sweden who were ready to comeover here. He suggested that steps should be taken at once to getparticulars in order to find out which of them would be suitable foremployment in this country.   This was agreed to.(b) It was reported that there was some uncertainty as to theprecise scope and purpose of the examination which the LordPresidents Committee had suggested should be arranged by theService and Health Ministers, and that a direction from the WarCabinet would be helpful.(c) The Prime Minister emphasised that, if we were to sustainheavy casualties over a considerable period, the Services must beready to accept a dilution of fully trained personnel, and&quot; adeparture from the high standards which were appropriate in othercircumstances. Only in this way would the best use be made of theavailable personnel.The War Cabinets conclusions were as follows : -(1) The allocation of doctors to the Services approved by theLord Presidents Committee, as set out in paragraph 1&quot; of W.P. (44) 180, was endorsed.(2) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs undertook, inconsultation with the Minister of Health, to instructour Ambassador at Stockholm to obtain particularswhich would enable us to settle which of the Danishdoctors now in Sweden were suitable for employment inthis country, and to take the necessary steps to bringover those adjudged suitable as soon as possible.(3) The enquiry asked for by the Lord Presidents Committeeshould be carried out by the Chief Medical Officers ofthe Ministry of Health and the Department of Healthfor Scotland and the Medical Directors-General of thethree Services. The representative of the Minister ofHealth should preside.
(4) The purpose of this examination was to prepare a scheme,capable of application at short notice in an emergency,whereby medical personnel, Service and civilian, wouldbe earmarked for transfer to those establishments andServices where the results of a breakdown would be mostserious. The fact that officers were so earmarked fortransfer in an emergency did not imply that theirservices were not being fully and economically utilisedin their present appointments.(5) The Service Ministers should also consider what steps couldbe taken by way of further dilution of personnel, or alowering of standards, in the event of a threatenedbreakdown.(6) The Secretary of State for War undertook to provide thePrime Minister with material for a telegram to send tothe President, explaining our serious shortage ofmedical personnel, and asking for help from theUnited States, whether by way of the provision of fullyequipped and staffed field hospitals, or by the supply ofmedical man-power in other ways.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,5th April, 1944.




</content>
</cab>
