<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 34-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  document  is  the   property   of  his  britannic  majesty&apos;s   governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1951SECRET - Copy No.     3CP. (51) 8\0th January, 1951 &apos;*CABINETTHE FUTURE OF THE CONDITIONS OF EMPLOYMENT and national ARBITRATION order memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National. service the Conditions of Employment and National Arbitration Order commonlyreferred to as Order 1305 was made in July 1940 under powers conferred by theDefence Regulations. Its purpose was to provide that trade disputes should besettled by peaceful means negotiation, conciliation and, in the last resort, com-pulsory arbitration rather than by strikes or lock-outs and so to avoid the dis-location and loss of production involved in stoppages of work. Briefly, it providesthat, upon a trade dispute being reported to the Minister of Labour and NationalService by one of the parties to the dispute, the Minister must take the dispute intoconsideration. If suitable machinery already exists in the industry concerned, he must refer the dispute for settlement to that machinery and by doing so he make sit possible for the machinery to give a legally binding award. If, however, there isno machinery or if the machinery fails to bring about a settlement, the Minister hasto refer the matter to the National Arbitration Tribunal (which was speciallyestablished by the same Order) within twenty-one days of the dispute being reportedto him, unless for special reasons which appear good to him the Minister decidesto postpone doing so. Any award made by the Tribunal is binding upon the partiesto the dispute. In order to give time for the processes of conciliation and/ornegotiation to work, Part II of the Order prohibits strikes or lock-outs in connectionwith a trade dispute unless the Minister has failed to refer the dispute for settlementv/ithin twenty-one days of its being reported to him. Part III of the Order providesfor the observance by all establishments in a trade or industry in a district of terms and conditions of employment not less favourable than the &quot; recognised terms andconditions.&quot; Part IV of the Order relates to the recording of departures from trade practices and is of no special significance for the purposes of this memorandum.2. Order 1305 was a war-time measure. It was worked out by the joint consultative Committee under the present Foreign Secretary&apos;s Chairmanship, andwas made on the recommendation of both sides of industry as represented by theBritish Employers&apos; Confederation and the Trades Union Congress. Since the warthe Order has been continued with the concurrence of these two parties subject tothe undertaking that on the request of either party it will be at once rescinded.3. It would be difficult to overestimate the value and usefulness of the Orderboth during and since the end of the war as a complement to the normal negotiating machinery of industry. The existence of the National Arbitration Tribunal in the background has done much in a great number of cases to encourage the parties tocome to agreement by negotiation; in others it may have had the effect of makingone party or the other more intransigent: but it does give the assurance to both parties that in the last resort a settlement of a trade dispute can be obtained*com-pulsorily if need be. The provision prohibiting strikes and lock-outs (even thoughuntil recently no prosecution action had been taken since the end of the war)combined with the provisions for compulsory arbitration, have exercised con-siderable influence in restraining those who might otherwise have been tempted totake extreme measures. There have, of course, been stoppages of work throughoutthe existence of the Order; no system of sanctions or of compulsory arbitration will39926
entirely prevent them; but many stoppages have been avoided as the result of theexistence and operation of the Order. In fact Order 1305, used as it has been insupport of and not in replacement of, the normal negotiating machinery of industry,has without doubt been an important factor in our relative freedom from stoppagesof work due to industrial disputes.4. The time has come, however, to take stock. The- British EmployersConfederation and the Trades Union Congress have hitherto supported the con-tinuance of the Order, and I have no reason to believe that they do not still do so.In the period, from the beginning of 1946 to the end of June last, of the disputesreferred to the National Arbitration Tribunal 804 were reported by Trade Unionsas against 45 reported by employers. Moreover, of the Trade Unions using theOrder, those most vocal in their opposition to its continuance have been mostconsistent in their use of it. At the same time there is a good deal of restlessnessamong both individual trade unionists and indeed some trade union executives atthe restrictions which the Order imposes upon what they regard as their immemorialright to strike. This restlessness is increasing, and there was quite a sharp debateat the Trades Union Congress in September last, although in the end there was a fairly comfortable majority for the General CounciFs policy of continuing the Orderin force. The opposition to the Order will almost certainly have been strengthened by the sentences of imprisonment imposed by the Magistrate on certain menprosecuted in connection with the recent strike in the gas industry even though on appeal the sentences were reduced to fines. Indeed, the representatives of theGeneral Council in defending the Order during the debate in Congress last september laid most stress upon the fact that it gave the Trade Unions power totake intransigent employers to arbitration and slurred over or ignored the anti-strikeprovisions. It is probably not unfair to say that an increasing body of trade unionopinion is questioning the continued need for the Order and its value to trade unionists. Furthermore, in recent disputes involving some printing unions andthe Musicians&apos; Union, the unions were obviously manoeuvring, as they thoughtwithin the Order, in the hope that the employers would thereby be embarrassed indealing with their claims. This is an unhealthy development. Without at least the goodwill and friendly acquiescence of the great majority of the trade unions and employers, the Order in its present form will be impossible to administer.5. Coupled with the changes in trade union attitude towards the Order, inrecent months a number of difficulties have been disclosed both about the interpre-tation of certain of the provisions of the Order and its practical application.6.   Among the chief difficulties of interpretation are the following:  (i) I have referred above to the fact that the Minister may, for good cause,postpone the reference to the National Arbitration Tribunal beyond the twenty-one days provided for in the Order. The Order has been administered on the basis that in the case of postponement the prohibition-prohibition on strikes and lock-outs continues in force. It now appears thatif, within the twenty-one days, the Minister has not referred the disputefor settlement either to the machinery of the industry or to the national arbitration Tribunal, the prohibition may lapse even though the. Minister may have had good cause for the postponement of the reference. If that is a correct interpretation and if I wish to keep theprohibition alive, I have a maximum of twenty-one days in which to tryfor a settlement by conciliation or informal negotiation, and at the endof that time must refer the dispute to the National Arbitration Tribunaleven though I have good reason to believe that a few more days dis-cussion will result in a settlement by agreement. This was certainly notthe intention.?n: (ii) It has always been assumed that, in the case of failure to reach a settlement by other means, I must refer a dispute to the National arbitration tribunal. Some doubt has now arisen as to whether this provision isas mandatory as has been thought in the past. In general this is not a discretion which I should welcome,(iii) If reference to the Tribunal is mandatory, it appears that I must act even where the worker-party to the dispute is an individual workman or an unofficial committee of workers going behind the backs of their trade;   &apos;. union executives.   I need not point put to my colleagues howembarrassing this can be. ... .. .%
7. As regards the practical application of the Order the most difficult question arises in relation to the prosecution of workers for striking in defiance of the pro-visions of Part II of the Order in other words, in the enforcement of this part ofthe Order. Experience during the war showed that the penalties of the defence regulations did not deter workmen from striking if they felt strongly enough aboutthe matter in dispute, and the sanctions were impossible to enforce where thenumbers involved were large. Since the war only one prosecution has been under -taken-that of certain persons in connection with the recent strike in the gas industryin London. Prosecution action has been considered on a number of other occasionsduring, the post-war years, but has not been pursued because it was felt that it might prejudice the prospects of a negotiated settlement or because the number of workersinvolved was too large. So long as the initiative in proposing prosecution inpractice rested with me it was not too difficult to defend taking this kind of line,for after all my primary responsibility is to obtain a settlement of the dispute. Butas was explained by the Prime Minister in his reply to a Parliamentary Question on 7th November, 1950, responsibility for initiating prosecution action has now beenplaced upon the Attorney-General. His view is that, so long as the Order remains in force, it is his clear duty to see that it is not allowed to become a dead letter;and that he can no longer refrain from prosecuting in such cases as appear to himto be appropriate. He is of the opinion that, unless the Order is to be enforced, itshould be revoked.   With this view I have every sympathy.8.   In the circumstances described above, what are the alternatives before us?(1) We could retain the Order as it is. Apart from other disadvantages thiswould, on the Attorney-General&apos;s view, inevitably involve an increasing number of prosecutions; and as I have already pointed out it is the strike prohibition clause,with the threat of criminal proceedings in the background, which arouses mostantagonism to the Order in trade union circles. If there were, in peace time, a succession of criminal prosecutions involving sentences of imprisonment the T.U.C.would almost certainly be forced to demand the revocation of the Order.(2) We could revoke the Order completely. If we did this we should lose an instrument which, quite apart from the provisions relating to strikes and lock-outs,still possesses great values. Moreover, I cannot imagine a more inopportune timeto take this step a time when the international situation is full of danger, when our troops are fighting against heavy odds in Korea and when production of armamentshas again become a first priority. We should in any case probably wish to re-enactin some other form Part III of the Order relating to the observance of recognisedterms and conditions of employment. In my view we should contemplate revocationonly if it were requested by one side or the other of organised industry.(3) We could amend the Order in, inter alia, one or more of the followingrespects:  ia) By deleting the provisions relating to the prohibition of strikes and lock-outs. Although this would be welcomed by substantial numbers oftrade unionists, I have reason to believe that some of the more responsible leaders regard these provisions as strengthening the handsof the Executives of the Unions and as helpful to them in their efforts to restrain their more hot-headed members.(b) By providing that the penalty for an offence against the strike and lock-outprovisions should be a fine only and not imprisonment. (I am advised that this would require an amendment of the appropriate defence regulation.) This would remove much of the sting in the Order andwould I think be greatly welcomed by the Unions and probably facilitate the endorsement of the Order at next September^ Congress.(c) By providing that only established organisations habitually taking part incollective negotiations and acting through their Headquarters, and notindividuals or unofficial committees, may report disputes under theOrder.(d) By excluding from the scope of the Order, disputes relating to recognitionor non-unionism, neither of which are readily susceptible of settlement by compulsory arbitration. So far as recognition disputes are concerned,such exclusion would merely make clear what is already generallyunderstood to be the law.9. There may be other alternatives which will prove to be desirable, such aslimiting the period of strike prohibition to the first twenty-one days after the
Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,10th January, 1951.dispute has been reported. But the whole question requires the most carefulconsideration, particularly in view of the present critical international situation, and before making any specific proposals to my colleagues, I propose to seek the advice of both sides of organised industry whose interests are so vitally engaged in everyaspect of this matter. &apos; I have, therefore, arranged an early meeting of the joint consultative Committee of the National Joint Advisory Council, with a view toplacing before them the problems that have arisen in connection with Order 1305as outlined above. After this meeting I will report back to my colleagues as soonas possible.G. A. I.


</content>
</cab>
