<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 78-96</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TH1S document is the property of his britannic majestvs governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1951The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of .......r^^^O(cNrr?j^vr^w..(L*st-oA/i.:.............TOP SECRET Copy No.3CP. (51) 1612th January, 1951CABINETDEFENCE PROGRAMMES 1951-54Memorandum by the Chiefs of staff as a result of the conclusions of the Cabinet on 18th December (CM. (50)87th Meeting, Minute 1), a working party was appointed to consider in detail the acceleration of defence preparations. Their report is annexed. We agree withthis Report and would draw particular attention to the statement in the last paragraph.2. We recognise that the proposals in this Report can scarcely fail to have repercussions on the everyday life and habits of the majority of the community.Sacrifices, often unequal, by the civilian population will be necessary, but the enthusiasm and zeal with which each individual will answer the call to do his orher share in accelerating our defence preparedness, whether it be in the armed forces or industry, will depend entirely on every individual and every family being given a clear understanding of the present national situation and the reasons whythese sacrifices have to be made and why they must vary between individuals. Weconsider that the country as a whole has a latent appreciation of the dangers whichface us and we are confident that the nation will be receptive to the measures whichare necessary for the future safety and defence of the country. The degree of thisresponse will, however, depend entirely on every individual being imbued with the- knowledge that his or her services are really wanted and form an indispensablecontribution to our defence preparations.3. In transmitting this report to the Cabinet we would draw special attentionto the following further points:  (a) Paragraphs 53 and 59, which represent the necessary conditions for ensuring that the works and production programmes can be carried to com-pletion. Half measures will not meet the situation; the conditions laiddown must be considered as a whole and applied to the maximum practicable extent. If this is not done there is a danger that wholesectors of our preparations may be rendered useless by key deficiencies.
(b) It is impossible to stop short at measures designed to produce results in1951 and 1952. It is already too late to achieve in these two yearswhat the situation requires, and the most valuable part of the additionalequipment which the measures now described could produce will bethat to be produced in 1953-54.(c) In the short term the main measure we can take to improve our readiness to fight is to Call up reserve and auxiliary personnel as described inparagraphs 9 to 19 of the report. We accordingly attach the utmost importance to these recommendations.(Signed)        FRASER.W. J. SLIM,J. C.  SLESSOR.Ministry of Defence, S.W.1,12th January, 1951.
ANNEX[D.E./P (51) 69th January, 1951]DEFENCE PROGRAMMES 1951-54 WORKING PARTYReport to the Chiefs of StaffIntroductionAt their meeting on 18th December * the Cabinet (a) agreed that at the meeting of the North Atlantic Council on the following day the Foreign Secretary should say that the United KingdomGovernment had already decided to increase and accelerate their defence preparations still further;(b) invited the Chiefs of Staff to consider in detail in what directions defence preparations could most profitably be accelerated.2. The underlying assumption was not that a major war was inevitable withinthe next two or three years; the aim was to strengthen the active defences of thecountry for the purpose of preventing a major war. It was recognised that con-siderable additional expenditure would be required not only because of thedeteriorating international situation but also in order to encourage our continentalallies to greater efforts and to match the actions of the United States government so as to avoid embarrassing ^political pressure from them to do still more as acondition for receiving American military assistance.3. What will contribute most to improving the chances of preventing war isclearly a rapid improvement in the size, training, equipment and readiness of the armed forces. In C.O.S. (50) 534 the Chiefs of Staff accordingly directed thatcurrent plans for the expansion of the armed forces should be re-examined on thefollowing basis:  (a) First priority should go to the completion, as far as possible, by December1952, of the expansion programme (the  3,600 million programme)planned for completion by March 1954.(b) Within, and without prejudice to, this overriding priority all possible measures should be taken to increase the readiness of the armed forcesin 1951.ic) On completion of (a) and (b), an examination should be carried out of thepossibility of completing as soon as possible preparations not hithertoplanned under the 1954 programme but which are necessary to enable us to meet our full commitments, notably our share of filling the gap between the forces required under the Medium Term Plan and ourpresent national contribution.4. The Chiefs of Staff have also agreed with the Defence (Transition) Com-mittee the basis on which, in their view, the war planning of the civil departments should proceed.5. The existing programmes of the armed forces have been reviewed againstthe hypothesis given in (a) and (b) above. The present report is therefore concernedin the main with what can be done to improve the strength and preparedness of the armed forces over the next two years. Certain of the proposals in the productionfield, however, while greatly increasing preparedness in the war potentialsense, will have their main effect on the actual supply of weapons after 1952.6.  Before giving the results of this review certain general observations shouldbe made:  (a) The existing programme, involving an expenditure of  3,600 million overthe next three financial years, was planned as the maximum which couldbe achieved without the partial restoration of a war economy and theintroduction of such measures as direction of labour, requisitioning, &amp;c,* CM. (50) 87th Conclusions, Minute 1.39948 b 2
and on the assumption that substantial American aid would be forth-coming. This assumption will not materialise and it also seems probable,that some interference with the civil economy would have beenessential if the original programme was to be fulfilled by the datefixed. It is clear, therefore, that in order to achieve our new objectives,measures affecting both individuals and the civil economy in general will be necessary. Unless authority is given for the measures in para-graphs 53 and 59 of this report, we are advised that no substantialacceleration of the defence programme is possible.(b) Even with such measures it will not be possible, as explained below, tocomplete by December 1952 the production programme planned to becompleted by March 1954.(c) It will, however, be possible materially to improve our state of preparednessduring the next two years and even more thereafter. Not the leastimportant result of the measures proposed is the creation, by theend of 1952, or shortly thereafter, of a greatly increased productionpotential which, should war come, would materially reduce the normaltime lag involved in attaining full war production. The only alternative to creating this increased capacity would be to hold large war reserves in store, but it is impossible to build up such reserves in time.7.  Our proposals are set out below as follows:  Section  I. Man-power in 1951.Section II. Production.Section III. Work Services.Section IV. Research and Development.Section V. Miscellaneous.Section VI. Summary.Section I. Man-Power in 19518. The following proposals on man-power refer to the year 1951. The actionto be taken in 1952 can only be settled nearer the time.(a) Navy9.  It is proposed-(i) to extend, to 18 months, the period for which officers and men whoseengagements have expired or will expire in future are to be retained in the Service and similarly the period of call-up of reservists now in service;(ii) to call up about 600 officers.   It is hoped that a number of air crewofficers will rejoin voluntarily under a scheme about to be launched.The remainder of the 600 will be drawn as far as possible from theEmergency List; but for certain categories and seniorities it will almostundoubtedly be necessary to call for volunteers from the R.N.V.R. andR.N.V.S.R.; if volunteers are not forthcoming it will be necessary tocall up officers from these reserves, the period of call-up to be18 months;(iii) to call up a maximum of 6,000 Royal Fleet Reservists for a period of18 months;Certain categories of officers and ratings are not available in sufficient numbers inthe organised reserves and the Admiralty may be forced to seek powers to recalla small number of &quot;Z &quot; reservists to meet commitments in 1952.(b) Army10. The Service Ministers&apos; Committee have already, subject to submission to the Defence Committee, provisionally endorsed a proposal by the Secretary ofState for War to recall for 15 days&apos; training with their units during 1951-(i) 80,000 reservists, mainly Class &quot;Z,&quot; for the First Contingent TerritorialArmy, and(ii) 35,000 reservists, mainly Class &quot;Z,&quot; for A.A. Command.
56411.  It is also now proposed -(iii) to recall some 62,000 reservists who will be posted to operational unitsof the Active Army for 3 months&apos; training. For the period for whichreservists are so posted this will bring the units concerned to higherestablishment;(iv) to call up 105,000 reservists for Reserve Army units required to supportthe forces in B.A.O.R. and M.E.L.F. and to support the strategic reserve in the United Kingdom for periods of training of either two weeks (about 90,000) or 3 months (15,000);(v) to call up 5,000 specialists for not exceeding 3 months&apos; training in A.A.Command;(vi) to retain time-expired regulars for approximately 12 months and to con-tinue this policy throughout 1951-52. The numbers involved will beat peak about 25,000 men.(vii) in order to provide reinforcements for Korea, to reduce the minimumembarkation age to 18 years 9 months with a minimum of 5 months&apos;training.12. The total number of reservists it is proposed to recall, whether for 15 days&apos;training or for 3 months, is 287,000. Most of these will be from Class &quot; Z.&quot; Ofthose required for 3 months (82,000) not more than about 40,000 will be in theservice at any one time.(c) Air Force13.   Similarly, a proposal (i) to recall the Control and Reporting units of the Royal Auxiliary AirForce and a number of reservists for 15 days&apos; continuous training;(ii) to take similar action in respect of the auxiliary units and the reservistsrequired for the light A.A. defence of airfields;which together involve about 2,500 Royal Auxiliary Air Force personnel and be-tween 20,000 and 30,000 reservists, mainly Class &quot; G,&quot;* has already, again subjectto submission to the Defence Committee, been provisionally endorsed by theService Ministers&apos; Committee.14.   In addition it is now proposed (iii) to recall, as may be required, 3,000-5,000 reservists (R.A.F.V.R. and regular) for service with the regular force. This includes aircrew and flying instructors;(iv) to embody the fighter squadrons of the Royal Auxiliary Air Force for about 3 months&apos; continuous training (about 2,200 men);(v) to retain time-expired regulars for 12 mo ths subject to an arrangement under which those men not required foi so long will be released after a shorter period. The total number of regulars affected would beabout 11,000 men.id) General15. The essence of the above proposals, so far as they effect Class &quot;Z&quot;reservists, is that the men concerned should be selected according to the rank,trade, or arm of the Service where the need exists. The difference in the treatmentof individuals arises from the varying needs of the Services.16. Legislation covering the recall of Class &quot; Z &quot; reservists, though techni-cally not required, will we think be necessary.ie) National Service Intake17.  The following national service intakes are desired for 1951-52:  Navy     ..................      ... 2,500Army.....................      149,000Air Force       ..................       53,000tTotal..................     204,500* The Air Force Class &quot; G &quot; is the equivalent of the Army Class &quot; Z &quot;.t If regular recruiting falls away an additional 2,000-3,000 may be needed.
18. On the basis of present policy the call-up will fail to produce these numbers, and by April 1952 the accumulated deficiency will be about 55,000. Tohelp bridge this gap it will be necessary:  -id) to discontinue the policy of deferring agriculturists (yielding possibly15,000);ib) for the Services to make greater use of Grade III and Grade IV medicalcategories (yielding possibly another 15,000);[id) and (b) have already been proposed by the Minister of Labour inD.O. (51) 1.]19. These two measures will not produce the full numbers required and we feel it necessary in addition ic) while not abandoning altogether the existing policy of deferring apprentices and students, to recommend reducing the numbers to whom temporarydeferments are granted by a change of policy designed to withholddeferment from the least important categories.20. Even if this measure is adopted the situation will have to be watchedclosely. For the present, however, we do not recommend id) dropping the age of registration again to 18.Resultant Strength of the Forces in April .195221. If the Service Departments obtain the full national service entry they desire they hope that the strength of the armed forces on 1st April, 1952 (ignoringreservists recalled for three months or less), will be:  Navy......................      149,000Army    .....................      470,000Air Force............      ...   260,000-270,000So far as the national service entry can be forecast, however, and making no allowance for the effect of restricting deferments which cannot accurately be esti-mated at present, the Army and Air Force combined may be 20,000-25,000 short of the above figures.22.   The effect of the above proposals will be:  id) Navy(i) To bring forward for service the following additional ships:  1 Light Fleet Carrier.2 Fast Minelayers.3 Destroyers.2 A/S Frigates.24 Minesweepers.4 Submarines.Additional small craft.(ii) To improve the state of readiness of the reserve fleet.(hi) To bring the ships&apos; companies of the Home and Mediterraneanfleets up to standard peace complements.(iv) To increase the front line strength of naval aviation.(v) To improve mobilisation arrangements.ib) Army(i) To increase the Active Army strength to 470,000 by 1st April, 1952;(ii) To raise the strength of the Army for part of the year to a levelnearer to its higher establishment by the introduction of reservists;(iii) To train reservists in up-to-date equipment;(iv) To allow units to get to know reservists and to decide how to employ them to best advantage;(v) To improve mobilisation arrangements.ic) Air Forceii) To enable the expansion of the front line to be accelerated (as described in paragraph 44.
(ii) To provide for the additional training requirements both of thefront line and of reserve personnel.(iii) To improve the readiness for war of the auxiliary fighter squadrons,of the Control and Reporting System and of the A.A. defencesof airfields.Section II. Production23. Under the plan set forth in D.O. (50) 81 for the size and shape of theforces during the years 1951-52 to 1953-54, which has been endorsed by the Cabinetsome  1,560 million was included for production as follows:   m.1951-52   ...............      ...      4361952-53   .........      .........      5171953-54   ..................      61.1Total   ............    1,56424. These figures make no allowance for short-fall and the actual provision in service estimates would be somewhat less. Thus the provision for productionin service estimates 1951-52 amounts to  387-5 million. This compares with 198-2 million for the current year.25. To complete by December 1952 the programme planned for the threeyears ending March 1954, it would be necessary to spend over  700 million more on equipment during the next two financial years. So large and so rapid anincrease in expenditure would in our view not be possible in any circumstances short of actual war.26. We estimate, however, that, provided all the conditions set out in para-graph 53 below are fulfilled without delay, expenditure by the Services on production in 1951-52 and 1952-53 can be increased to the extent shown below:  1951-52 1952-53 m.  m.Admiralty        ...............      17 50War Office      .........      ...      ...      32 85Air Ministry     ...............      20 67Total............      69 20227. Current prices with allowance for such increase in cost as are alreadyknown have been used in preparing these estimates. No attempt has been made toestimate probable trends of costs and prices in 1952 and after.28. The following paragraphs summarise the results expected from the accelerated programme for each of the three Services:  Royal Navy29. The completion of the 1954 plan by 1952 is not physically possible asfrigates and larger ships necessarily take more than 2 years from the date ofordering to the date they are ready for operational service. In this respect theprovision of propelling machinery and certain specialised equipment is generally the limiting factor, rather than the construction of the hull.30. The increased programme has only been made possible by a considerablerelaxation of staff requirements which accepts ships and equipment of lowerperformance which can be made available in place of higher performance equipmentavailable by 1954.3L  The major items in the accelerated programme are:  (a) The number of coastal and inshore minesweepers to be completed by theend of 1952 will, be increased by 50 per cent. (i.e., from 41 to 60) and 12fast patrol boats and 16 seaward defence craft which would not other-wise have been completed by that date will be provided.
(b) The number of ex-fleet destroyers converted to A/S frigate by the end of1952 will be 22 instead of 10 and a proportion of our existing fleetdestroyers and frigates will be fitted with more modern equipmentthan at present planned.(c) The front line strength of Naval aviation will be increased from the present150 to 230 aircraft by the end of 1952 instead of to 180 under existingplans. In 1951-52 and 1952-53 a total of 972 naval aircraft are expectedto be produced instead of 802 under existing plans. In 1953-54 it ishoped that a further 608 aircraft will be produced making a total of1,580 in the three years.(d) Deficiencies in mobilisation and reserve stores and equipment, other thanarmament stores, will be made good by the end of 1952 instead of 1954.Army32. In the first year of the accelerated programme improved deliveries will beof those types of equipment not affected by problems of design and not involvingheavy manufacturing processes. In weapons, armoured vehicles and ammunition,the increase will be small. The important point is, however, that preparations willbe made which will result in substantial increases in subsequent years. Theseequipments are therefore considered under the year 1952-53. The steps proposedwill not enable the number of divisions, &amp;c, in the Army to be increased, butexisting units will be better equipped and more battleworthy.33.   The main improvements in 1951-52 are: :(a) Vehicles. It will be possible to complete the planned purchase of some4,000 commercial vehicles for military use in 1951-52.(b) Clothing. An additional  15 million can be spent on clothing.   this increase will enable deliveries under the three-year plan to be completed in two years.(c) General Stores. It will be possible to spend an additional  10 million on general stores.id) Signals Equipment. A small increase in the delivery of wireless sets andother communication equipment will be possible.34. In 1952-53 the effects of acceleration would begin to be felt in the heavyarmaments fields.   The most important increases will be as follows:  35.   Anti-Aircraft(a) Repair and Conversion of H.A .A. Guns. There will be a small increase in1951-52 and a substantial increase in 1952-53. The greater part of the planned programme for repair and conversion of last war guns will becompleted in two years instead of extending into the fourth year as atpresent planned.(b) Radar. Production of fire control radar will be increased from 400 to 500,and of predictors from 150 to 200 in 1952-53.(c) L.A.A. The production of the new L70 BOFORS gun will be brought forward by one year, and 100 will be produced in this country in1952-53.36.   Tanks(a) Centurion production will be raised from 410 to 540 in 1951-52 and from500 to 755 in 1952-53, giving a total of 385 extra tanks in the two years.This would be partly achieved by accelerating the conversion of theR.O.F. factory at Dalmuir.(b) The conversion of Centurion tanks from Mark II (17 pdr. gun) to Mark III(20 pdr. gun) will be expedited to complete 250 tanks.(c) There will be an increase in the upgunning of Cromwell tanks.37.   Anti-Tank Weapons(a) The introduction of the new battalion Anti-tank gun will be advanced byone year and production in the two years will be raised from 100 to 500.(b) The programme for the production of the Platoon Anti-tank weapon (3-5inch Rocket Launcher) will be increased.38. Vehicles. The production of front line vehicles of good cross-countryperformance will be speeded up. Requirements in this range under the three-year
programme should be completed in 1912-53. This represents a 400 per cent,increase of deliveries in the two years.39. Ammunition.-Broadly speaking the production of ammunition willmatch the increased production of weapons, and, in the case of A.A. Command,it will be possible to improve reserve holdings. The increase is best shown interms of cost:  (a) A.A. Ammunition. Increased from  8-6 million to  14-8 million in1952-53.(b) Field Ammunition. Increased from  10-76 million to  15-1 million in1952-53.40. Signals. An additional  7 million worth of signals equipment will beproduced in 1952-53.41. Clothing and General Stores. The programme, originally planned tocover three years for remedying deficiencies in reserve holdings of clothing andgeneral stores will be completed in 1952-53.R.A.F.42. The Ministry of Supply estimate that, provided all the necessary machine tools, plant and factory spaces are forthcoming, the accelerated programme might produce the following numbers of aircraft compared with deliveries forecast underthe existing plan:  
		1951-52		1952-53			1953-54			1951-54			Present			Present			Present			Present			plan	Increase	Total	plan	Increase	Total	plan	Increase	Total	plan	Increase	TotalFighters 												Vampire       ......	179	240	419	75	270	345	 		_	254	510	764Meteor 8      ......	378	50	428	371	250	621	250		250	999	300	1,299Venom FBI  ......	37	 	37	239	20	259	565	170	735	841	190	1,031Swift   .........	 	-	-	4	 	4	68	110	178	72	110	182F.3/48.........	 	 	-  	9	 	9	242	58	300	251	58	309Venom N.F.......	 	 	 	32	 -	32	85	150	235	117	150	267Vampire (dh 113)   ...	50	 	50	 	 	 &apos;	 		-	50	-	50Total        ......	644	290	934	730	540	1,270	1,210	488	1,698	2,584	1,318.	3,902Short-range P.R. 												Meteor p.r. 10	20	-  	20	20	10	30	-	40	40	40	50	90Light Bombers 												Canberra B 2......	74	 	74	138	120	258	566	480	1,046	778	600	1,378Trainers 												Chipmunk    ......	164	90	254	100	190	290	52	140	192	316	420	736Varsity        ......	43	 	43	130	30	160	41	205	246	214	235	449T.16   ...     ......	 	 	 	60	100	160	60	170	230	120	270	390Total        ......	207	90	297	290	320	610	153	515	668	650	925	1,575Grand Total	945	3S0	1,325	1,178	990	2,168	1,929	1,523	3,452	4,052	2,893	6,945
43. These figures assume that no aircraft are allotted to other countries exceptan arbitrary allowance of 200 Vampires for N.A.T.O. and Commonwealth air forces,against existing and expected requirements, and a few other deliveries to those forces against outstanding commitments. They also assume that exports of airframes and engines will be interfered with to the extent necessary to complete the planned R.A.F. expansion programme.Effect of increased production on strength of R.A.F. by December 195244. Assuming that in addition we receive from North America, during thenext two years about 400 F.86, 50 P.2.V.5 (Medium Range Reconnaissance) and30C.119 (Transport) aircraft besides the remaining Washingtons already promised to us, it is estimated that the operational strength of the R.A.F. by December, 1952,might be built up to 2,539 (instead of 1,775 on present plans). Details are given below.Strength by Strength byDec. 1952        Dec. 1952under under present Plan  Revised PlanBombers LincolnWashingtonCanberra ...Mosquito ...BrigandDay Fighter /Ground AttackMeteorVampireVenomF.86HornetNight Fighter/All WeatherMeteor N.F. 11   ...Vampire D.H.113Venom N.F.Maritime ShackletonSunderlandLancasterP.2.V.5     ...Transport HastingsValettaC.119    -P.R.-Canberra / LancasterMeteorMosquitoRemarksMet-Brigand ...Hastings  ...32641202416256520392112321,05615232Total1846425892474984024872416201,7751206413616834471848016264481,5261603211230464252432145406416120404088848122,539Difference4- 884- 16- 8- 84-1984- 88- 96* *venom N.F.4--&apos;,- substituted-I- if&apos; (see below)4- 8+ 112(Instead of day FighterVenom)4- 244- 324- 16- 104- 164- 164-764
45. If aircraft are allocated to other air forces, beyond those mentioned inparagraph 43 above, the expansion of the R.A.F. front line will be correspondinglyless.Inclusion of Second Line Squadrons46. The accelerated expansion shown above is based not only on increased production but on allowing some squadrons to remain equipped with obsolescenttypes of aircraft and on making no provision for stored reserves of new types. Inorder to build up a front-line of this strength, nearly all aircraft coming off produc-tion would have to go into squadrons, and there would be little except obsoletetypes of aircraft in reserve. Should war break out before an adequate reserve hasbeen built up to replace fighting wastage, it would be necessary to roll up a propor-tion of the squadrons in order to keep the remainder going.47. This situation is anticipated by the Air Ministry&apos;s proposal to regard30 per cent, to 40 per cent, of the squadrons as &quot; second line.&quot; We should, in effect,be keeping our reserves of aircraft in squadrons instead of in store and using themfor training our reserve of aircrews so that we should have a trained reserve on mobilisation. In war these squadrons could be used, in a crisis, as operationalreserves to reinforce the front line, but normally their function would be to providereplacements for losses. After 1952 these second line squadrons can progressivelybe transferred to the front line as reserves behind them become available.Other R.A.F. Equipment 48. (a) United Kingdom Radar Chain. It is impossible to exaggerate theimportance of the United Kingdom Radar Chain, on which our fighters and A.A. defences are wholly dependent. It is vital to accelerate theproduction of equipment for it, by diverting resources from civilian purposes.(b) Ancillary Equipment, Ammunition, &amp;c. Accelerating the production of aircraft is useless unless the full range of ancillary equipment is pro-duced in phase with it. It is also essential to ensure that stocks ofammunition and other consumable equipment are built up to match.Production in 1953-5449. As a result of accelerating the production programme in the way nowproposed we shall have created production capacity which would deliver an output in 1953-54 substantially greater than that achieved in 1952-53 unless deliberatesteps were taken to curtail production. On the assumption that no such steps are taken, the money value of the output in 1953-54 is estimated at 50. In compiling the accelerated programme regard has had to be paid to theneeds of the Services in 1953-54 in so far as they can at present be foreseen.Deliveries in the earlier part of the accelerated programme will be those which canbe more easily, and therefore more quickly, produced, and for this reason theprogramme will initially be out of balance. This should be remedied in 1953-54,when the flow of most items of equipment will begin fully to match formation needsboth in quantity and quality. On the air side, indeed, deliveries in 1951-52 and1952-53 are limited by the fact that many of the types most urgently needed bythe R.A.F., particularly certain versions of the Canberra, the Venom and theF.3/48, are still in the development stage and substantial increases in the produc-tion of these types cannot be obtained under any conditions before 1953. In order,however, to achieve the maximum degree of preparedness on the air side it isessential to accelerate to the maximum possible extent the building up of productionof the new jet types and particularly the Canberra, F.3/48 and Venom. In orderto obtain the greatest possible output of these types in 1952-53 onwards, it isnecessary to set up at least three new production lines for Avon and Ghost enginesin addition to the four new lines already planned under the current programme.This will raise the peak ouput of these engines from about 420 to over 700 engines m.admiralty war office air Ministry184-00300-00375-00859-00
a month. It will also be necessary to expand the capacity for the production ofaccessories and equipment. These measures will create very heavy additional demands for machine tools, plant and factory space. They will result in an eventuallevel of capacity which would not require to be fully employed for more than a brief period in any conditions short of war.51. In addition to the acceleration of production programmes in 1951-52to 1953-54, there are certain further steps which should be taken, as generalmeasures for the improvement of preparedness, to increase capacity in certain important lines. Apart from the expansion of aircraft capacity mentioned in thepreceding paragraph, the most important of these steps are the creation of two newtank production units, for which proposals have already been submitted in D.O.(50) 106; the reopening of one or two of the filling factories used in the last warand the creation of additional capacity for the production of R.D.X. explosive.Labour Requirements52. The increase in the labour force engaged on production for the services required for the fulfilment of present plans has been estimated to be approximately375,000, of which 170,000 would be required in 1951-52, 125,000 in 1952-53, and80,000 in 1953-54. Under our new proposals, the increase required by the endof 1953-54 would be 650,000 spread over the three years as follows: 1951-52 220,000: 1952-53-280,000: 1953-54-150,000. This would bring the total labour force engaged in defence production to 1*,110,000 as compared with 460,000 atpresent. As examples of increases required in particular fields, we estimate thatthe present labour force employed on the production of aircraft, amounting toabout 190,000, will have to be doubled by the end of 1952-53. The labour at&apos; present employed in the Royal Ordnance Factories, amounting to some 36,000 willhave to be doubled during the next 12 months, and the labour force will continueto be built up thereafter as fast as additional labour can be absorbed.Conditions to be Satisfied9 53. If the increased programmes are to be achieved, the following conditions must be fulfilled without delay:  (a) Raw materials for the defence production programmes must be madeavailable to industry when they are needed. To ensure this, it will benecessary to prohibit or curtail inessential end uses of all scarcematerials and to devise means of securing preferential allocations to firms employed on defence contracts. The importance of this is notmerely to provide materials but to free capacity and labour from other work.(b) Authority must be given for requisitioning of factory premises if requiredfor the rearmament programme.ic) The additional labour required must be forthcoming when and where it is needed. There will have to be a considerable switch of capacity andlabour from civilian to defence production but much of this will not involve any physical transfer of labour. The Ministry of Labour is notable to forecast in advance of detailed working out of orders whethercompulsory measures may have to be applied. A change in publicopinion would bring about a greatly increased possibility of achievingtransfers of labour by voluntary means. Labour controls exist but thereare obvious political and practical objections to their use if the same result can be achieved without them. It will, however, be necessary tomake clear that if the need should arise the powers would be used.id) Production departments must when necessary be able to instruct firms thatcivilian orders, including dollar exports, must be deferred in order tomake way for defence orders.ie) The additional machine tools necessary to carry out the full acceleratedprogramme must be secured. A first estimate puts the cost of this at about  65 million in addition to an expenditure under the present pro-gramme of  50 million. Such a condition, which is vital to the achievement of the target, involves (i) the virtual abandonment of exports of United Kingdom machine tools, coupled with re-orientation of production. This is neces-sary to meet defence needs and as a condition of obtainingAmerican supplies;
(ii) the placing of substantial additional demands abroad, mainly on theUnited States.(/) Some 2,000 additional technical and scientific staff must be provided for theProduction departments. This is a labour problem already under examination as a result of Defence Committee instructions and will be dependant on the priority generally accorded to the defence programme and the willingness of industry and the professions to co-operate inmaking staff available. If work on the development of an atomic weaponcould be slowed down, some of the staff engaged thereon could betransferred to other more immediate design work, completion of whichwould improve our state of readiness during the next two years or so.We recommend that the Chiefs of Staff should consider the desirabilityof taking this step.(g) Defence production must not be seriously affected by power cuts.(h) Certain risks must be accepted as regards development, proof and trials,in. order to produce improved equipment more rapidly.54. As a means of accelerating the provision of equipment for the forces, thesupply departments will make the fullest possible use of production in other Euro-pean countries. It is not likely that this will contribute very much in the way ofwarlike stores by the end of 1952-53. There are, however, good prospects of obtain-ing substantial quantities of semi-finished goods, machine tools, and non-warlike stores.Section III.-Works ServicesRequirements:55. To match the measures proposed above in the fields of production and manpower and to advance the date of completion of certain active (e.g., Anti-Aircraft) defences, the following works programmes (almost entirely in the UnitedKingdom) must be carried out by the end of 1952, in addition to the large programme already approved.(a) Admiralty. Additional  airfields,  improvements  to  existing   airfields,extension of seaward defences, provision of two minesweeper bases,additional storage.(b) War Office. Completion of A.A. defences, additional storage including anew central ammunition depot, provision of Monsell Forts in variousestuaries, re-alignment of continental L. of C.(c) Air Ministry. Reoccupation and rehabilitation to modern standards of anumber of disused airfields; extension and improvement of existing air-fields; provision of additional accommodation and technical facilities.(d) Ministry of Supply. Provision of additional factory space for the accelerated production programme.Cost:56.   The following additional expenditure on works programmes will arise inthe next two financial years:  195112 195213 m.  m.Admiralty       ............       13 3-0War Office     ............       7-0 7-air Ministry    ............      10-0 20-0Ministry of Supply   .........       4-5 5-0Total       ............      22-8 35 057. It is not possible to project the programme accurately beyond 1952/3;the subsequent level of expenditure will depend largely on the situation at the time.Action Necessary to Ensure that Existing and Additional Programmes are achieved:58. Service Works Programmes are at present subject to severe limitationsarising both from shortages of staff and from administrative factors. If the accelerated programmes are to be achieved the following steps will be necessary.Most of them would, in any event, be necessary if even the works programmes
contemplated within the  3,600 million plan were to be completed. These pro-grammes already included for completion within the next two years services of thehighest urgency such as the works services required for the Control and ReportingSystem and for the preparation of airfields and other facilities for the reception ofUnited States Air Force reinforcements. It is of the highest importance that such services should not be delayed by such factors as those mentioned in the next para-graph.59. (a) Technical and Professional Staff. The Service Departments arealready very short of works staffs for existing programmes. Critical shortageshave already developed for the works sector of the  3,600 million programme. Theproposed acceleration will greatly magnify these. This problem, which is funda-mental, was brought to the notice of the Defence Committee in October last (D.O.(50) 87) and the Minister of Labour was invited to examine it and to make pro-posals. Inter-departmental discussions have since been proceeding It seems clearthat drastic action will be necessary if the requirements of the defence programme are to be met.(b) Materials. Priority for materials in particular steel, cement, timber andpossibly bricks will be required.(c) Labour. Priority for labour will be required and since a good deal of theproposed works will be sited in remote areas where there is an absolute shortage some direction of labour seems inevitable.(d) Powers of Requisitioning. At present the Service Departments have avail-able Defence Regulations:  87 authorising entry on to land for purpose of survey;50 authorising work to be done;51 authorising taking possession of land;52 authorising use of land for training.But Ministerial undertakings have been given that D.R. 52 will no longer be used and the other powers are only rarely used. The alternative of obtaining possessionarid subsequently acquiring land under the Defence Acts can be an extremelycumbersome business involving, in present circumstances, a quite unacceptableexpenditure both of time and of technical and administrative staff. A much more general use of all these defence regulations will be necessary. A Ministerialannouncement will be needed.(e) Consultation with Local Authorities.-At present the acquisition of landby the Defence Departments (whether under Defence Regulations or otherwise)must be preceded by consultation not only with other Government Departmentsaffected but with local authorities. The latter often leads to very long delays and again occupies staff who are urgently required for other work. The defence departments must ask in cases of real urgency, for authority to proceed without consultation with local authorities (although they would, of course, be informed)or where necessary to over-ride their objections to the use of particular sites.Consultation, as at present, with the Government Departments affected would continue.(/) Storage. The powers of requisitioning referred to would extend to storage.The existing inter-departmental machinery for allocating available storage spacewill have to be strengthened and directed to give priority to defence needs. It willbe necessary for the Air Ministry to regain possession of airfields now used for storage, and incidentally for farming. The Service Departments will need to regainpossession of accommodation now occupied by squatters and other civilians; thedifficulties of dispossession must be faced.(g) Closing of Roads. Both the Admiralty and Air Ministry programme will involve some closing of roads in the neighbourhood of airfields. Under existingprocedure (under the Highways Act or the Town and Country Planning Act) the closing of a road takes as a minimum nearly six months. The war-time powers ofthe Service Departments under D.R. 16 to close roads quickly have lapsed.Legislation will be necessary to revive these, or similar, powers. The agreement ofthe Ministry of Transport and the Treasury to the form of this legislation hasalready been obtained.
Section IV.-Research and Development60. No acceleration in the research and development programme at present planned is proposed, although additional effort in the field of land warfare, notablytanks and anti-tank weapons, is urgently required. The facts must be faced,however, not only that the present programme was planned to absorb all availablescientific staff but also that the availability of this staff may well be adversely affected by the proposed acceleration in production and the consequent diversion of staff to more immediate design work.61. The situation is being examined by the Defence Research Policy Com-mittee who will make recommendations to the Chiefs of Staff as necessary regardingchanges in research and development priorities. It is clear, however, that it is nowof vital importance that industry should be convinced of the necessity for givingpriority to defence research and development work. At present there is a feeling of uncertainty and a tendency for industrial facilities to be directed to more profitablecivilian and export projects. A positive pronouncement from the Government isnecessary if industry is to be persuaded for the future to co-operate wholeheartedlyin the defence research and development programme.Section V. Miscellaneous62. Higher Grade Civilian Staff&apos;. -Reference has already been made to theneed for diverting professional and technical staffs from other Government employ-ment to assist with the accelerated production and works programmes. It will alsobe necessary for the civilian departments to release other professional and admini-strative staffs to reinforce the Service and Supply Departments.63. Subordinate Civilian Staffs. A large increase in the number of industrial and the non-industrial staffs employed by the Service Departments, both at head-quarters and outstations, should be provided both for the additional clerical,technical (maintenance) and barrack housekeeping work which will arise from thenew expansion programme and also to replace uniformed personnel who will berequired for the formation and training of additional units.64. The additional numbers required, very roughly, over the next two years are: -Admiralty (excluding production)      ......       8,000 to 10,000War Office ...............      14,000Air Ministry       ...............      14,00065. In view of the isolated location of many service units and of the absenceof facilities (e.g., housing) in many of the areas concerned, it is highly unlikely thatthese requirements can be met without recourse to direction of labour.66. Oil. The building up of reserves of petrol, oil and lubricants for theservices should be accelerated in order to achieve the earliest possible accumulation of a stockpile appropriate to the larger forces now proposed, with special priority to the provision of an adequate reserve of aviation kerosene.67. Food. The Service Departments should increase their holdings of foodreserves. The Admiralty propose to increase stocks where practicable from five to twelve months&apos; consumption. The War Office (who also cover Air Ministry require-ments) plan to increase their holdings of composite and tinned reserves by 27,000,000rations.68. Transport. -The Ministry of Transport should examine the steps requiredto keep the availability and preparedness of sea transport in step with the increasedsize and readiness of the forces.69. Communication Zones. Approval should be given at once to open negotiations with Belgium and Italy for switching the Communication Zone inB.A.O.R. (which at present runs through Hamburg) to Antwerp and to establishlines of communication for B.T.A./BETFOR through Leghorn without waiting for financial agreement on the incidence of cost. The total cost in Belgium for 1951-2may be about  6 million; the cost in Italy will be considerably less.70. Infrastructure. The present infrastructure programme (costing  33million in all, including a United Kingdom contribution of  9 million, of which theMinistry of Defence vote will provide  7-15 million) will be completed in 1951-52.
7flIt is certain that further substantial expenditure will be necessary but no details areat present available. A United Kingdom contribution of  5 million in each of theyears 1952-53 and 1953-54 is tentatively assumed.Section VI. Summary(i) Manpower71.   It is proposed:  (a) To call up for a period of about 18 months&apos; service with the regular forces(i) a maximum 6,000 men from the Royal Fleet Reserve;(ii) the balance of 600 officers who do not volunteer (from theEmergency List, R.N.V.R. or R.N.S.V.R.);(iii) 3,000 to 5,000, as may be required, from the R.A.F. volunteer reserve and the Regular R.A.F. Reserve;(b) To call up for 3 months&quot; training(i) 62,000 Army Reservists, mainly Class &quot; Z &quot; for training with theregular forces;(ii) 15,000 Army Reservists, mainly Class &quot; Z,&quot; for training with theReserve Army;(iii) 5,000 specialist Army Reservists for training with A.A. Command;(iv) The fighter squadrons of the Royal Auxiliary Air Force (about,200 men);ic) To call up for 15 days&apos; training(i) 90,000 Army Reservists, mainly Class &quot; Z,&quot; for the Reserve Army;(ii) 80,000 Army Reservists, mainly Class &quot; Z,&quot; for the TerritorialArmy;(iii) 35,000 Army Reservists, mainly Class &quot; Z &quot; for A.A. Command;(iv) 2,500 members of the Royal Auxiliary Air Force and between20,000 and 30,000 mainly Class &quot; G &quot; (equivalent to Army Class: &quot; Z &quot;) R.A.F. reservists.id) To continue to retain time-expired regulars for the following periods:--(i) Navy 18 months;(ii) Army approximately 12 months;(iii) R.A.F. 12 months (some to be released earlier).(e) In order to provide reinforcements for Korea, to reduce the minimumembarkation age to 18 years 9 months with a minimum of five months&apos;training.if) That the Navy should retain for 18 months reservists already called up. Theperiod of retention of Army reservists now in Korea will be separatelyconsidered.(ii) Production72.   It is proposed that id) additional expenditure on production should be incurred amounting to 69 million in 1951-52 and  202 million in 1952-53;ib) approval should be given for increases of capacity for production of jetengines, tanks, filling factories and explosives as recommended in thereport;ic) approval should also be given to the special measures set out in para-graph 53 which are essential conditions to the fulfilment of the aboveprogramme.(iii) Works Services73.   It is proposed that (i) approval should be given to the additional works programmes described inSection III estimated to cost an additional  58 million by April 1953;(ii) approval should be given to the special measures described in paragraph 59,which are essential if the desired acceleration of the works programme is to be realised.(iv) Miscellaneous74. It is proposed that approval should be given to the additional recom-mendations in Section V.
(v) Finance75. The foregoing proposals, if adopted, will bring the total defence pro-gramme over the period 1951-54 to about  4,475 million (see Appendix).76. We recommend that approval should be given to the amended defence budget of  1,250 million for 1951-52 compared with  1,112 million already approved by the Defence Committee.(vi) General77. We repeat that, as stated in the report, the first essential for the fulfilment of this additional programme is the creation throughout industry and the country as a whole of the conviction that by making a success of this additional programme,and thereby improving our defence preparedness, we shall be taking the courseof action most likely to prevent war, and that accordingly any sacrifices which theprogramme involves are well worth while.(Signed) H. PARKER.Ministry of Defence, SWA,10th January, 1951.Appendix to AnnexCost of the Proposed New Defence Plan	1951-52 draft estimate		Accelerated	programme			1951-52	1952-53	1953-54	Total 1951-54Admiralty  Works     ......... Production         ...... R. and D.         ...... All other          ......	15-38 118-86 13-55 130-71	 m. 19 134 13 139	 m. 20 188 13 139	 m. 21 184 14 141	 m. 60 506 40 419Total.........	278-50	305	360	360	1,025War Office-Works      ......... Production......... All other.........	33-37 134-81 250-62	39 169 275	39 259 278	32 300 280	110 728 833Total.........	418-80	483	576	612	1,671Air Ministry  Works      ......... Production......... All other           ......	39-62 133-80 155-33	* 48 153 168	60 245 192	42 375 207	150&apos; 773 567Total.........	328-75	369	497	624	1,490Service Departments  Works     ......... Production......... R. and D.         ...... All other           ......	88-37 387-47 13-55 536-66	106 456 13 582	119 692 13 609	95 859 14 628	320 2,007 40 1,819Total.........	1,026-05	1,157	1,433	1,596	4,186Ministry of Supply...... Ministry of Defence	81-50 4-42	86 7	91 7	91 7	268 .   21Grand Total	1,111-97	1,250	1,531	1,694	4,475Note. Air Ministry Works&apos; figures have been reduced by  2 million in both 1951-52 and in 1952-53to allow for appropriations in aid from the United States. The full effect of American worksrequirements cannot, however, be fully assessed until detailed programmes are available.


</content>
</cab>
