<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 1-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT JPrinted for the Cabinet. January 1951The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issuedI for the personal use ofI TOP SECRET Copy No. 32I (51) V^t18r/i January, 1951CABINETDEFENCE PREPARATIONS BY CIVIL DEPARTMENTSI Report by the Depencb (Transition) CommitteeThe war planning of Departments generally has hitherto been related to theassumption, put forward by the Chiefs of Stan and approved by Ministers, thatthere will be no major war before 19S7. Some Departments have, however, recentlyadjusted some of their preparations to take account of the earlier date of 1954 towhich the Medium-Term Defence Plan of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisationis related. And the acceleration of defence preparations in the United States isnow being related to the possibility that major war may occur in 1952 or even 1951. J^^HAt the Cabinet&apos;s meeting on 18th December last (CM. (50) 87th Conclusions,Minute 1) the Prime Minister drew attention to the confusion which might arisefrom these different planning dates, and suggested that the position should now be ^^^brationalised. He expressed the view that a satisfactory new hypothesis could beframed on the basis that the Government&apos;s aim was to strengthen the activedefences of this country for the purposes of preventing a major war.II 2. At the same meeting the Cabinet agreed in principle to increase andaccelerate defence preparations; and the Chiefs of Staff have since framed a newplanning hypothesis to which that acceleration should be related. This assumesthat the defence measures most urgently required are those which are likely to makea substantial contribution towards the Government&apos;s policy of preventing theII outbreak of a major war. So far as concerns the Armed Forces and their supply,the new hypothesis sets the aim of completing, so far as practicable by31st December, 1952, the expansion programme at present planned for completion^^fl by 31st March, 1954.  To conform with this, the Chiefs of Staff have proposedthat the defence preparations of civil Departments generally should now be j^^Hgoverned by the following principles: -I. All preparations by civil Departments which contribute directly to the j^^Hpreparedness of the Armed Forces should be related to the programmelaid: down for the Armed Forces, viz., the aim should be to complete ^^^1^^fl &apos; these preparations, so far as practicable, by 31st December, 1952. ^^^HII. Certain measures of insurance against the possibility of an early war(e.g., stockpiling) should also be related to the possibility of war atthe end of 1952.in. All other relevant plans and preparations should be brought as rapidly as |^^H[I possible to a point of completion at which they would be ready to be put ^^^Hinto execution as soon as the physical resources which they require can ^^^Hbe made available. ^^^B3. The Defence (Transition) Committee have reviewed, in the light of these?       principles, the current state of the defence preparations and plans of the civil . ^^^HDepartments. They note that these principles would not provide for any accelera- ^^^HI .      t&apos;on  ^     defence preparations, other than those which contribute directly to the j^^^Hpreparedness of the Armed Forces and certain stockpiling measures. This omission ^^^H39987
?fl II bbb!is, presumably, to be justified by the fact that the Government are aiming to I^^Bprevent war, and are not at this stage putting in hand the preparations which would Ml BBM?VH                have to be undertaken if war were regarded as inevitable within the next two or BaBJthree years. It is understood that the Home Secretary will, in a separatememorandum, invite the Cabinet to consider whether it is right that civil defence Ml Bflpreparations should be allowed oh this account to fall so far behind the programmesproposed for the Armed Forces and their supply. I Bfl?YAW                      4.  Subject to this point about civil defence, the Defence (Transition) Com- QB ^?fafJmittee agree that the principles stated in paragraph 2 above provide a satisfactory HJbasis for the acceleration of the defence preparations of civil Departments generally.BayB                 The following paragraphs of this report set out the measures which should be pat BJ BBHin hand if these principles are accepted as a basis for the war planning of the civil ] BBS?VH                 Departments and, where practicable, include the best estimate that can at present ?y^BPAV                be made of their probable cost. These measures are divided into three groups to BJJ BBHcorrespond with the three principles set out in paragraph 2 above.Group I.-Measures in Direct Support of the Armed Forces Ml BBS?Sfl                      5.  The measures which we consider should be completed by 19S2 as contribut- BB^B?VJ                ing directly to the preparedness of the armed forces aire set out in paragraphs 6 and ftB^BBByfl                7 below. In the main these are all Category I projects in the programme for civil If BayJdefence expenditures over the next four years (D.O. (50) 57) and when this wasconsidered by the Cabinet, approval was given in principle to the expenditure of theBByfl  137 million estimated as the cost of Category I projects (CM. (50) 50th Conclusions, 11 BBJBHJ                Minute 2). We understand that the Official Committee on Civil Defence are seekingB^Bfl                Ministerial approval for this sum to be increased to approximately   180 million, but B^BJBayM                this is not on account of any acceleration of our defence preparations and is solely 11 BBHdue to certain adjustments to the programme which were under considerationbefore the question of acceleration arose. The measures proposed below, thoughB^^H                they entail an acceleration of some of the Category I projects in the &quot;four-year B^BJ?y^Hj              programme,&quot; do not involve, except in respect of blackout, any substantial increase ByHin the total expenditure over the four-year period.BB^BJ              Civil Defence BBH6. The Chiefs of Staff recommend that the following civil defence measures LyAVJB^BH               should be completed by 1952:-^^H[ (a) Full development of the Air Raid Warning System.^^^B (b) All practicable measures to secure an effective blackout as soon as possible^^^B                             after&apos;the outbreak of war. ^^fl^^^B (c) Provision and protection of War Rooms and essential communications.B^BBI                   {d) Experimental Civil Defence Mobile Columns. B^BJB^BH                    .(e) Personnel shelters and fire fighting equipment at civil airfields to be used B^BjBB^bj for air defence purposes.^^^M (/) Measures to provide storage and protection of petroleum supplies.^^^H (g) Civil defence measures at certain selected factories.BB^BB                   (h) Civil Defence Tactical Training School. BBH?B^^B              The cost of these measures is estimated at about  45 million. BJHBB^BB               Communications for the Armed Forces BBH^^^H 7.  It is difficult, within the programme for providing and protecting com-^^^H               mumcations, to segregate measures which contribute directly to the preparedness of B^BJBB^BBJ               the Armed Forces from those necessary for the protection of other essential tele-^^^H               communication services, e.g., for war industry and transport. The defence work on^^^H               telecommunications must proceed as a complete plan. Of this plan the most urgentBB^BBJ              sections contributing to the preparedness of the Armed !Forces &apos;have &apos;been &apos;selected BBH^^^H               (cost  12 million) for completion by the end of 1952, and we recommend that they?B^BBJ               proceed according to that time-table. -They include communications for proposed B^BJBB^BBJ              headquarters, gun-defended areas, seaward defence &apos;headquarters at defended BBH^^^H               ports and, in particular, the modernisation of the control and reporting system^^^H               for air defence.   They also include the most urgent parts ctf the protectiveBB^BBJ               schemes, consisting of deep-level cable tunnels, ring cables encircling London and BBBbI^^^H               other target towns, and mobile equipment to enable essential communication BBSH              services to be provided if normal circuits are damaged.                                       | j B^BJBB^BH                    The balance of the 1950-54 programme for the provision and protection of fflffflBl^^^H             communications (cost  18 million) will be completed as rapidly as possible within ^^^H
Ill&apos; 76 IGroup II.-Measures of Insurance. 8. The following measures of insurance against the risk of an early war might^Hl be taken. They should be related to the possibility of war at the end of 1952.9. The stockpiling programme already authorised by Ministers is based on^Hl              the accumulation of the strategic reserve over a period of three years up to October1953 at an estimated cost of  350 million. It would be consistent with the newplanning hypothesis if this programme were accelerated so that it could be completed^Hl by the end of 1952; and we recommend that this should be accepted as the newtarget. Acute world shortages of raw materials have, however, developed since that^Hl programme was authorised; and many of the materials of which a strategic reserveis desirable are now so scarce that it is unlikely even that requirements tor currentconsumption can be met. Thus, except by drastic cutting of home supplies,accelerated stockpiling will, at best, be possible to only a minor degree if presentcircumstances continue.10. The figures for the present programme have, however, been recalculatedon the basis of completion by December 19S2, and the following points have beenI taken into account:-(a) Prices generally have risen since the figures were originally prepared.(b) Departments&apos; proposals have varied from those originally drawn up.H (c) Estimated costs of freight, internal transport, handling and storage havenow been included.11. Row Materials and Food.-In the light of the above the estimated costof building up by December 1952 the desired strategic reserves of raw materialsand food (including the provision of new storage) is as follows:-  millionRaw materials ............... 223^?j Food      p^fsK ......... 118 ^L^mThere seems no prospect that anything like these amounts can in practice be acquiredduring the next two years.12. Oil.-The Admiralty are examining the possibility of accelerating their^?j               oil stockpiling programme, but as far as the acceleration or increase of other oilII programmes is concerned, it is (with the exception of reserves of aviation fuels), ^^^|^^fl likely to be the availability of storage, rather than supplies, which will be the ^^^|limiting factor. As regards aviation fuels, while storage might be made available, ^^^1the full requirements cannot be met from British controlled sources and we should ^^^|have to look for assistance from United States sources of supply, where our ^^^|demands might conflict with American requirements. ^^^|In all the circumstances it is estimated that the maximum practicable expendi- ^^^|ture (subject to an increase in the Admiralty programme) by the end of 1952 is ^^^|^^?1                25 million, of which  15 million would be for oil and  10 million for storage. I^^lli 13.   Tobacco.--This is of primary importance to a war economy.  Although ^^^|a tobacco stock does not involve expenditure out of public funds, it is included in ^^^H^^Ka this programme because it involves a claim on our currency resources. The stock ^^^HI        increases aimed at in 1951 and 1952 under the present programme would cost about 16 million. It is proposed that this programme should be accelerated with the aimof securing a total stock of  33 million worth of tobacco by the end of 1952. ^^^H14.  Civil Defence Equipment and Materials.-We consider that the pro- ^^^H^^fl gramme should include the stockpiling of certain key items as a first contributionto the needs of the civil defence services. While no detailed examination of produc-B tion prospects has been possible in the time available, our proposals can be regardedas a reasonable target, if priorities are accorded similar to those needed by active ^^^Hj  %      defence measures.  We have included items such as equipment for the warning&apos;  W      system and the fire and rescue services, blackout material, uniform cloth and39987 b 2
respirators.  Also included are the stock requirements which the Health Depart* V^H- ments regard as essential. A summary of the cost of our proposals is as follows: -Home Departments ............ 50 IlltitH?y^H Health Departments ..... ...     36 ?y^|?y^H Further details of the equipment and materials to be accumulated under this ?y^Jprogramme is given in the Annex. ?klPort Facilities15.  The country&apos;s military resources would be of little use without adequateport capacity, and a detailed survey has been made of the facilities which could Ly^Mbe provided at anchorages and minor ports to relieve the situation which would B^H?^Hl              arise if major ports were put out of action by air attack. Tentative estimates of V^Hthe expenditure involved on the basis of a target of providing extra facilities for200 ocean-going cargo ships in addition to 30 tankers show that it would amountB^^H              to some  7-25 million. We are advised that, if such expenditure was authorised          I EayJ^^^fl              in the near future, it is likely that much of the work could be done by the end ofKayAj                    16.  It might be argued that the provision of these port facilities with the V^H^^H| exception of equipment such as cranes, would only be of value in war and must B^H..&apos; * therefore be regarded as a wasting asset should war not break out. Nevertheless^^^B in our view they constitute an important measure of insurance which should be^^^B undertaken. The knowledge that such alternative measures exist might have some?y^BB deterrent effect against any contemplated mass attack on our major ports. BBH^^^H Group III.-Acceleration of Other Plans and Preparations^^^H 17.  We have considered the steps which should be taken to accelerate the BBHwar planning work of civil departments so that plans may be brought as rapidlyBB^BB as possible to a point of completion at which they would be ready to be put intoB^BBB execution as soon as the physical resources which some of them require can be ^^fl^^^H made available. We are taking steps to expedite some of this work-in particular, BBHthe preparation of the legislation required in war, the planning for the evacuation^^^H of Government staffs in war and the measures required to ensure the due function-^^^H ing of essential industry and services in war. Further examination of some of theBB^BH matters in this group, in particular the due functioning of industry, may reveal I BBH?y^^Bj a need for early action involving the use of physical resources and thus involving By^B?fAjAW further expenditure additional to that estimated for projects in Groups I and II ?y^J^^^H above.  For example, an examination now being carried out by the Ministry ofBB^BBj Fuel and Power on internal oil distribution in war has shown that oil distribution^^^H facilities will be inadequate and that such deficiencies will have to be met by^^^H Government reserves of road and rail tank-wagons and, possibly, additional pipe-^^^H lines. ?yJBJ?y^^H Redeployment of Administrative Resources I B^H^^^H 18. The acceleration of defence preparations must involve some redeploy-^^^H ment of administrative resources, both national and local.^^^H The measures proposed in this report-even those for the acceleration of plansBB^BBJ involving no early use of physical resources-cannot be carried through by the BBHBB^BBA dates envisaged unless additional staff is assigned to defence work.  The same By^B?y^^H condition undoubtedly governs the proposals in CP. (51) 16 affecting the ServiceB^^^BJ and Supply Departments. In the subordinate grades this need might perhaps be B^BJBB^BBJ met to some extent by the recruitment of additional staff from ouside Government        I iBBBJ^^^^B service.  But the bulk of this planning work must be undertaken by experienced^^^^B staff; and these can only be found by transferring existing civil servants to defence^^^^fl work from work of less urgency and importance. Some of these transfers will be^^^^M needed within Departments: others will involve transfers from one Department to B^^^^B another.  The Service and Supply Departments, in particular, will need to be^^^^M strengthened by the transfer of staff from other Departments.  These should^^^^M include, not only staff required for administrative measures, but also professional.^^^H technical and drawing office grades. B ^^B^^^H 19. This redeployment of administrative resources for defence purposes w^^^^H cannot be carried through unless Departments are free to discontinue or retard
Ill 77 Isome of the less important peace-time work on which they are now engaged. WeII        recommend that the Cabinet should-(i) Agree in principle that in Departments generally the administrativeresources devoted to defence work must be strengthened;(ii) invite all Departmental Ministers to consider to what extent they candiscontinue or retard peace-time activities of their Departments, andI *\ what balance of staff-can be made available, after meeting the increased^^?11 needs of their own defence work, for transfer to defence work in otherII Departments;(hi) invite the Treasury to consider, in the light of returns to be made mpursuance of (ii) above, whether the staffs which can be made availabletor transfer are likely to be adequate to meet the requirements of the j^^Hexpanding Departments.(iv) Agree that at the appropriate stage a public announcement should bemade regarding the peace-time activities which are being suspended orreduced in order to allow of this diversion of staff to defence work.20. We also believe that it will -shortly become necessary to call upon localauthorities to devote a large proportion of their effort to defence planning, in civildefence and other spheres. This will presumably involve a similar transfer of stafffrom current work to defence work. We therefore recommend that the Ministerof Local Government and Planning and the Secretary of State for Scotland shouldbe invited to consider, in the light of the results of the enquiry contemplated inparagraph 19 (ii) above, what guidance can be given to local authorities on thispoint.Summary of Proposed Expenditure in 1951 and 195221. The following table attempts only to give Ministers a broad indication j^^Jof the order of the financial commitment over the next two years:-^Hl A.-Support of Armed Forces l^^l  million ^^^MThe measures proposed in this report amount to ...j&apos;^},. ,. 57 ^^^hNote.-A considerable proportion of the itemscomprising this total are included in the^Hl expenditure proposed in the memorandum bythe Home Secretary (CP. (51) 19).^Hl B.-Stockpiling ^^^MOil stockpiling is estimated at  25 million. Thefigure for raw materials and food is  341 million; butthis figure represents requirements and, as the supplies^Hl &apos; are not expected to be .available, the amounts actually^^?j spent are bound to be less. A &amp;rm estimate is^^?1 impossible but it may not be unreasonable to takethe estimated provision for 1951 ( 130 million) and ^^^Hassume that this represents the rate .of expenditure over |^^^|I the next two years. On this basis the provision for this. item might be put at &apos;i-M* &quot;\ ^0The proposal to stockpile tobacco does not involve ^^^Hexpenditure from public funds: the commitment onI our currency reserves is  33 million. |^^^|^?1 Stockpiling  of Civil  Defence  equipment and^Hl materials is estimated at...... ........ 86 ^^^H^^?j C.-Port FacilitiesThe provision of alternative port facilities is ^^^1^H] estimated at ............. 7-25 if^^H^Hj Subject, therefore, to the uncertainty regarding the stockpiling programme the prob-able expenditure over the next two years, on the measures recommended in this ^^^Hreport, may be estimated at  400 million. ^^^H^?1 (Signed)        NORMAN BROOK,mf On behalf of the Defence (Transition) Committee. ^^^H^?1 Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,18r/j January, 1951.
ANNEXSTOCKPILING FOR CIVIL DEFENCEThe following is a list of the various items which it is proposed should beincluded in the stockpiling programme as a first contribution to the needs of thecivil defence services: -Home Departments   millionWarning System.................. 1&apos;8Blackout Materials ............ 10-0Fire Service-present programme ......... 2-455,000 self-propelled pumps with equipment     ... 14 010 million feet of hose ............ 2-52 million gallons of Foam Compound ...... 1*4Rescue Service--2,000 vehicles with equipment .........&apos; f 2-5Equipment for impressed vehicles ...... 1*0Radiation Devices ............... IIUniform Cloth .................. 2 01 million Steel Helmets............... &apos;75100,000 Anderson Shelters ............ 2050 million Sandbags ............... 2-5Respirators .................. 3 0Storage ..................... 3-25Total&quot;&apos;&quot;&apos;.................. 49-65Health DepartmentsDrugs-Raw Materials ............... 10Manufactured ............... 10-0Casualty Services-Blankets ............... 2JTentage .................. j&apos;JOther equipment (beds, &amp;c.) ......... 13 0Blood Transfusion-Equipment .................. &apos;4 ^^flAmbulances-Stretchers and fittings ............ &apos;6Evacuation-Blankets .................. 4-0Camp beds and mattresses............ 2-0Total .................-

</content>
</cab>
