<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 132-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;V    99SECRETNOTECP. (51) 24A meeting of the Cabinet has been provisionally arranged for TUESDAY,23RD JANUARY, at 11. 0 a.m. , at no. 10 Downing Street, S. W. 1.    If thismeeting takes place the attached paper will be considered at it.Cabinet Office, S. W; 1. ,22ND JANUARY, 1951.
00ItHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)100SECRETG.P. (51) 24 COPY NO.     3 222ND JANUARY, 1951CABINETARGENTINE NEGOTIATIONS AND THE MEAT RATION  .Memorandum by the Minister of food the latest talks with the Argentine have ended without result,as my colleagues will have seen from the press reports initiated by theArgentine Ambassador.    We must therefore now consider our position afreshand decide what policy is best in the long run.   As I warned the Cabinet inDecember (CP. (50) 282) our stock position is grave and we now have to face the further cut in the carcase meat ration, which I then foreshadowed.I am therefore setting out in this memorandum a full summary of the position,and begin by giving an outline of the latest negotiations.2, My officers held a number of meetings last week with Argentinerepresentatives;    The Argentine proposals were as follows:-(a) that we should pay an average price for all meat sent to this country by Argentina of  120 per ton;   or alternatively,(b) that shipments of meat should be resumed immediately, invoicedprovisionally at the old prices^ provided that a firm andretro-active price should be agreed within 45 days.As a condition attached to both alternatives we were to agree to include acertain proportion of chilled beef in our imports.3. During the discussions it became clear that the Argentinerepresentatives had no discretion to take anything less than an average of 120 per ton.   They said they expected to be able to work up a rate of shipment of chilled beef equal to 7 5 per cent of all beef shipments by the end of June 1952;from now until the end of June, 1952, about 50 per cent of the beef or one-thirdof all meat they would send would be in the form of chilled beef.    They suggestedthat if we must keep the prices of the remainder of the meat at the old levelsthis could be done either(a) by free ing   the import of chilled beef and removing it from price control and rationing, in which case they were prepared to takea chance on what it would fetch, or(b) that we should pay them the same price for chilled beef as we pay to United Kingdom farmers for fresh beef, which they tookto be about  155 per ton.4. We replied that we could not afford the increased expenditure involved in paying an average price of  120 per ton, that to free the import of chilled beef and to permit it to be distributed outside the ration was entirelyagainst our present policy, and that their proposed price for chilled beefwas completely out of relation to what we were paying the Southern Dominionsfor other types of meat.
5. The Argentine representatives would not reduce their demands,and are returning to Argentina.   Although the position has been left open for further negotiation, there has, for all practical purposes, been anotherbreakdown.6. So much for the negotiations.   We must consider what theArgentine demands entailed.    Under the existing long term agreement with argentina any increase in the price of frozen meat involves a proportionate increase in the price of canned meat.   Moreover, they are still claiming aretrospective payment to the 18th January, 1950 (in respect of their claim for price revision on devaluation) of any increase in the price of frozen andcanned meats which may now be agreed.   The effect of an agreement to payArgentina  120 per ton if, for the moment, we assume that we took nochilled beef, that we had to meet the contingent claims referred to above infull, and that we had to give a corresponding increase to Uruguay, &apos;would be an additional cost of approximately  20 millions over the period tothe 30th June, 1952.    If, on the other hand, we agreed to pay an average priceof  120 per ton but applied the whole of the increase to chilled beef in the hopeof evading these contingent claims, the price for chilled beef would have to bethe full  155 per ton and the additional cost over the period mentioned above would be approximately  9^ millions.    Thus the potential increase in the costof meat from Argentina and Uruguay over this period would lie between 9i millions and  20 millions, depending upon the apportionment of theincrease in the price between chilled beef and frozen meat, and the extent towhich we meet the claim for a retrospective payment.7. The price of  155 demanded by the Argentine is four times theprice we paid for their chilled beef before the war.    In any case, there is nodoubt that payments of the order demanded would create serious repercussionsupon Southern Dominion producers and would result in immediate demands for substantial price increases from both Australia and New Zealand.    Thepresent price of Southern Dominion frozen beef is less than  70 per toncompared with the price of  93 per ton we have been paying South America.Any increase we agreed in the price of frozen beef from Argentina would increase the disparity in the prices of beef from the two sources of supply;and if the whole of the price increase were applied to chilled beef we should bepaying Argentina  155 per ton compared with  113 per ton for first qualityNew Zealand lamb which, before the war, realised a very substantialpremium over South American chilled beef.    We should be very fortunateto avoid making additional payments of about  4 millions to   6 millions toAustralia and New Zealand over the period in question.8. To agree to the present Argentine minimum demand would therefore probably involve an increase in our procurement costs of meatof something between  13 millions and  26 millions up to the end of June, 1952.The consequences of such an increase are:-(a) if we put up retail meat prices to recover the whole increase, 13 millions would mean an increase of l^d. per lb. on the retail price of all imported meat or jd. per lb. on the retail price of all meat, including home-produced.   An increaseof  26 millions would mean an increase of 3d. a lb.on the retail price of all imported meat, or ljrd. per lb. on the retail price of all meat, including home-produced.(b) if we did not put up retail meat prices the increase would be anadditional burden of that amount on our food subsidies.(This would, of course, be over and above the increase in1951/52 of  60 millions in the procurement cost of subsidisedfoods which I have foreshadowed in E. P. C. (51) 4).
9. In my view we eould not contemplate for one moment adoptingtheir proposal that chilled meat should be imported by the private trade andsold off the ration without price control.    Chilled meat before the war couldnot be sent very far away from the port of entry because it must be eatenwithin a few days of arrival.    We are satisfied that we could handle it onthe ration, although we should distribute it in the big cities which at presenteat a higher proportion of frozen meat and less home-killed meat than theaverage,    If the trade brought chilled meat in they also would have to keep itin the big cities where it would be sold for what it would fetch, largely tocaterers able to charge relatively high prices for meals.    I could not recommend that we should abandon the principle of fair shares to this extent.10. What is our stock position?   As my colleagues will realisefrom my previous submission, the continued absence of supplies from SouthAmerica creates acute supply and rationing problems.   Stocks of carcase meatsuitable for issue on the ration as at 3rd February are now estimated at only19,400 tons, and this figure represents about the minimum stock necessaryto maintain distribution.   In the absence of supplies from Argentina andUruguay, supplies from all sources during the four weeks of February willbe inadequate to maintain the present carcase meat ration of lOd. per head.In no circumstances could supplies from South America or Uruguay now arrive in the United Kingdom before the end of February, and a reduction in thecarcase meat ration to 8d. per head as from 4th February is thereforeinevitable.   Even so, we shall do no more than maintain the minimumworking stock.    Our supplies in stock and in transit, of canned corned meat areonly 29,400 tons, of which not less than 10,000 tons must be kept back against any unforeseen emergency and to meet any sudden demand by the Armed Forcesetc.    Only 19,400 tons of canned corned meat is therefore available for distribution;   this is equivalent to a 2d.  ration of canned corned meat for 8weeks.    It should be possible to maintain the carcase meat ration at 8d.until about the end of March, even without supplies from South America.After that, we should expect to be able to raise the carcase meat ration to lOd.provided, firstly that supplies from the Southern Dominions, which would thennormally be arriving in quantity, are not delayed as they have been in recent months by difficulties of loading at the ports;   and provided secondly that homekilled supplies come forward according to the normal pattern at this time ofthe year.   It is always dangerous to speculate about future ration levels far ahead, but subject to the above considerations, we ought to be able to keep up to lOd. until the autumn, when our home killed meat should give us a much higher ration.11. There are similar difficulties in respect of manufacturing meat.Here again we have no choice but to reduce the off take without delay, and i must cut the issue of manufacturing meat by about one-third on the4th February.12. In the light of all these factors it seems to me that three courses are open to us:-(a) to give in now to the Argentine demand for an average price of 120 per ton;(b) to consider making a new approach to the Argentine;(c) to stand firm and not to make any approach to them.
f 0313,     To give inThe carcase meat ration must in any case come down to 8d.on the 4th February.   If meat were actually on the water from South Americaby then, we could safely add 4d. worth of canned corned meat, making l/-ration in all, and we could expect to keep the ration at l/- (all carcase meat)from March onwards with some improvement after a month or so.    Moreover,to give in would mean pressure for higher prices by our suppliers of other commodities besides meat, the possible cost of which we cannot estimate.14.     A new approachWe could only safely maintain a l/- ration (8d.  of carcase,plus 4d.  canned corned meat from 4th February) if there were a prospect of reaching agreement with Argentina within a week or two.    I do not think thereis any such prospect at a price of less than  120 per ton.   During the negotiationslast week we made an offer of  111 per ton for chilled beef, or 20 per cent morethan the same beef realised when it came frozen prior to the stoppage of meat shipments, in the hope that there would be some response from the other side, and our negotiators had Treasury authority to go further than this to the extent of an overall increase in prices of about  5 millions.   But therewas no sign whatever that either the officials on the other side, or theArgentine Ambassador, had any discretion to come diwn below  120 per ton.It is clear to me that any immediate new approach to Argentina would be taken as a sign of weakness and that we should be in grave danger of ending by payingtheir price.   Even if we make a new a.pproach eventually (which officials ofall Departments concerned are at present considering) we must decide on the ration level as if we were standing firm - there is no alternative, because ofour depleted stocks.15.     To stand firmThere are two possible ration courses:-(i) To reduce the carcase meat ration to 8d. on 4th February, withthe addition of 2d.  canned corned meat for 8 weeks.    There is good hope ofbeing able to provide a lOd.  carcase meat ratior/f although our canned cornedmeat would be exhausted. Al(ii) To reduce the carcase meat ration to 8d.  on 4th February,and to supplement it with 4d. canned corned meat.    This would exhaustour canned corned meat after 4 weeks and we should therefore face a periodof probably 4 weeks with a bare 8d.  carcase meat ration.16. My colleagues will naturally expect me to give my personalrecommendations in the light of all these considerations.    I wish I couldconscientiously say we could take an easy way out.    But no such way is opento us, I fear, in the situation we face.    I therefore recommend that we should adopt the ration reduction set. out in paragraph 15(i), namely, to reducethe carcase meat ration to 8d.  on 4th February, with the addition of 2d. canned corned meat;   that I should present the whole facts as clearly as I can this week to Parliament;   and that we should consider later, in the light of theArgentine reaction to our statement of policy, on what basis and at whattime we re-open negotiations.M. W.Ministry of Food, S. W. 1. ,22ND JANUARY, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
