<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 150-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
113     /THIS  DOCUMENT  IS THE   PROPERTY   OF HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENT     $Printed for the Cabinet  January 1951.confidential cp. (51) 2722nd January, 1951.MIGRATION POLICY: ASSISTED PASSAGE AGREEMENT WITHAUSTRALIAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations at the Meeting of the Cabinet of 18th December, 1950, (CM. (50) 87th Con-elusions, Minute 3) the Cabinet invited me to discuss with the Prime Minister ofAustralia, when he came to London in January, the question of renewing the assisted Passage Agreement and to report the result of the discussion to theCabinet.I annex a record of a conversation which I had with Mr. Menzies on thismatter on 15th January.It will be seen that Mr. Menzies, though he would like us to keep up our contributions, recognised our budgetary position and undertook not to make diffi-culties; and that it was left that he would send over Mr. Holt, the AustralianMinister for Immigration, for talks in March, when I shall have returned from my visit to South Africa.I will report again to the Cabinet after my talks with Mr. Holt.P.C.G.W.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,22nd January, 1951.ANNEXRecord of Conversation between the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and the Right Hon. Mr. Menzies, 15th January, 1951I had lunch to-day with Mr. Menzies.I told him that, although we had reached no decision, we might find it neces-sary to consider cutting out the million odd pounds that we were contributing toassisted passages to Australia. We had to find much money for rearmament andwould have to make many economies. If we did decide to do this, it would not mean that we were against migration to Australia. On the contrary we would do everything else to assist and stimulate it.2. Mr. Menzies said that he fully understood our budgetary position. Hethought that too much was contributed to passages. It looked to the immigrantthat he was being courted and that everything would be done for him; in fact hehad rather a tough time ahead of him in Australia. He would like us to keep up our contributions and find some way by which Australia could pay us back an equivalent amount.3. I pointed out the budgetary and accounting difficulties of this. (I didnot say that Australia might merely write a million less into a gift against sterling balances which would mean that we really gained nothing.)4. Mr. Menzies said he had already decided to send Mr. Holt, Minister of migration, over for talks. I welcomed this and suggested early March (when Ishall be back from South Africa).5. Mr. Menzies repeated that he fully appreciated our budget position andwould not make difficulties.Copy No.32CABINET40008


</content>
</cab>
