<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 152-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
11 H  /THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE   PROPERTY   OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTYS   GOVERNMENT *   v printed for the Cabinet.   January 1951SECRETCP. (51) 2822nd January, 1951Copy No,    6CABINETPERSIAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsRecent developments in Persia have been causing me some concern, and in viewof the widespread interest in Persia as a possible victim of Russian aggression, I wish to give my colleagues an account of the present situation there.2. In the spring of 1950 the internal situation in Persia was showing signs ofdeterioration. A succession of weak and ineffective Prime Ministers had loweredthe never high standard of administration, and the policy of deflation pursued bythe State Bank had produced trade stagnation. Public confidence in the regimehad therefore been seriously sapped, and the influence of the Communist-controlledTudeh Party was increasing correspondingly.3. In June 1950 the Shah decided to entrust the Premiership to Razmara, theChief of General Staff, who had a good reputation for intelligence and energy, but was unversed in politics. Razmara formed a Government, obtained a formal vote of confidence, and has remained in power since with only minor Cabinet changes.His appointment reassured public opinion, and for the time being the danger ofan expansion of Communist influence receded.4. Razmara&apos;s achievements so far are difficult to assess. He has failed tocontrol the Majlis (Parliament), which has proved itself more than usually ineffectiveand obstructive and in which undue influence is exerted by a handful of extremenationalists, the so-called National Front. Consequently many potentially bene-ficial measures which Razmara has introduced, including a long-overdue BankingLaw and a scheme of administrative decentralisation designed to reduce absenteelandlordism in the provinces, have been blocked in the Majlis, which is now saidto be holding up 110 Bills. He has also displayed irresolution in confronting theMajlis on important issues. On the other hand, he has concluded trade agreements with Russia (see paragraph 7 below), France and Western Germany, which shouldmaterially assist Persia&apos;s economy, and is negotiating a similar agreement with italy; and by tightening up the formerly lax exchange control regulations he issaid to have brought $4 million into the State Bank in the last two months.5. The Americans, who last summer had viewed the Persian situation evenmore seriously than ourselves, in July appointed Mr. Grady, former ambassador in Greece, to be their Ambassador in Tehran and sent out with him technicians to review Persia&apos;s economic needs. As a result, an Export-Import Bank line of credit to Persia of $25 million was proposed, and negotiations for it have recently been concluded in Washington, though it still awaits Majlis ratification. The Persiansseem to have regarded this line of credit as a disappointing result of Mr. Grady&apos;smuch heralded arrival, and to have consequently lost faith in American ability toassist them.6. In September 1950 His Majesty&apos;s Government, after discussing the questionof aid to Persia with the Americans, decided to offer Razmara a sterling loan of between  2 and  3 million as cover for an additional note issue, as it appeared thatshortage of local currency rather than of foreign exchange was holding up the40007
prosecution of the Seven-Year Plan of economic development. Razmara, whilegrateful for the offer, declined to accept it on the grounds that if, as he hoped, hesecured ratification of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company&apos;s Supplemental Agreement(see paragraph 9 below), his Government would receive sufficient funds. As willbe seen, this hope has not been fulfilled, but Razmara has not since reverted to thequestion.7. One of Razmara&apos;s first acts was to negotiate a trade agreement with Russia,eventually signed in November 1950, which by providing opportunities for both countries to dispose of exportable surpluses of their products seems to have been of genuine mutual benefit. In doing so he successfully maintained the principlethat the resulting trade should be conducted between the Russians and fiveGovernment-controlled Persian Companies set up for the purpose, thus avoidingdirect Russian contacts with the population. Shortly after the signature of thetrade agreement with Russia, the Persian Government banned the relaying of.B.C. and Voice of America broadcasts in Persia, undoubtedly as a sop to theRussians; and it seems clear that, while the Shah and Razmara continue to beapprehensive and suspicious of the Russians and to have no desire to collaborate with them, public opinion in Persia now favours a reversion to Persia&apos;s traditionalpolicy of balancing between Russia and the Western Powers.8. In their relations with the United Kingdom, both the Shah and Razmarahave continued to display a spirit of co-operation and have constantly taken HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador into their confidence, especially in regard to defence matters.Our relations with them have, however, been overshadowed by the problem of theAnglo-Iranian Oil Company&apos;s Supplemental Agreement.9. This agreement, signed between the Company and the Persian Governmentin July 1949, provides for a retroactive increase in royalty rates, and for anadditional element of Persian participation in the Company&apos;s profits. No PrimeMinister before Razmara was, however, prepared even to submit it to the Majlisfor ratification because of the opposition it was expected to arouse. Razmarafinally presented it in October 1950, but a Majlis Commission subsequently reportedthat the agreement, which in our view is fair and even generous, &quot; did not corres-pond to Persia&apos;s interests,&quot; and considerable political feeling has been aroused,including an unrealistic suggestion by the National Front minority that the persian oil industry should be &quot; nationalised.&quot; The Agreement, after various politicalmanoeuvres, is still before the Majlis Commission, which is unlikely to report forsome two months. Meanwhile the signature by the Arabian-American Oil Com-pany of an agreement with Saudi Arabia on terms involving a 50:50 division of profits, which for technical reasons would be extremely difficult to apply to Persia,has introduced a further complicating factor; and it seems now unlikely that aregularisation of the Company&apos;s operations in Persia can be expected for, at best,many months to come, or on any terms comparable with those of the SupplementalAgreement.10. Had the Supplemental Agreement been ratified, the Persian Governmentwould have received an immediate payment of about  38 million in respect of itsretroactive element, in addition to higher royalty payments for the future. TheCompany&apos;s payments to the Persian Government are in theory devoted to the seven-Year Plan (though this principle is frequently not adhered to), and theirresolution of successive Persian Governments, combined with the obstruction and lack of realism of the Majlis, have consequently deprived Persia of a sum whichwould not only have enabled the Persian Government to get ahead with much needed measures of economic development, without which the menace of com-communism is difficult to contain, but would probably also have restored their financesto health. As it is, the indications are that Razmara is finding himself seriouslyshort of money. It has been announced that the contracts of Overseas ConsultantsInc. technicians, who were responsible for advising on the Seven-Year Plan project,have not been renewed as from 1st January, 1951, for financial reasons, and it haseven been suggested that official and army pay may shortly fall into arrear.11. On the basis of the information available, it would appear that no betterPrime Minister than Razmara is in view, and that he should therefore be supported;and that he must be given some financial assistance, if the Seven-Year Plan is tobe re-started and the danger of another resurgence of communism averted.   His
Majesty&apos;s Ambassador considers that the Majlis, in its present mood, would be unlikely to ratify any foreign loan; and the only obvious source of financial aidis therefore the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. The Company are so far unwilling to pay money to Persia except on the basis of a regularly ratified agreement, but might be prepared to make advances to the Persian Government on account of future royalties. The whole question is being actively pursued between the interested Departments of His Majesty&apos;s Government and with the Company;and the conclusions reached will be submitted to my colleagues in a subsequentpaper.E. B.Foreign Office, S.WA,22nd January, 1951.



</content>
</cab>
