<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 218-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE   PROPERTY   OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MA.IESTY&apos;S   government memorandum by the Minister of Local Government and Planning andthe President of the Board of TradeAn interim report from the Committee on Distribution and Marketing on the marketing of fruit and vegetables (CP. (50) 262) was recently submitted to theCabinet and the Committee have now asked us, in this second interim report, to put before the Cabinet their proposals for dealing with resale price maintenance.2. Resale price maintenance is the practice by which minimum or fixedwholesale and retail prices, or margins for the resale of goods, are prescribed and enforced by manufacturers. This means that, although different kinds of shopshave widely different levels of cost, they all have to take the same mark-up, and price competition between shops is eliminated. Before the war it was estimated that about 30 per cent, of the private expenditure of domestic consumers oncommodities was on goods of which the final prices were thus fixed or recommendedby suppliers. The practice is widespread and seems to be growing. We need asnorter and more emotive name for it. The best we can think of, so far, is &quot; retail price rigging.&quot; But we shall welcome other suggestions.3. The effect of this practice is to keep many prices and distributors&apos; marginshigher than they ought to be, or need be; and we are satisfied that, in a time of rising prices which may inflict great hardship on many sections of the community, no single step will do more to slow down the increase of prices in the shops, and indeed,in some cases, actually to reduce them.4. A departmental committee under the chairmanship of Mr. G. H. LloydJacob, K.C. (now Mr. Justice Lloyd Jacob) reported on the subject in June 1949(Cmd. 7696). They recommended that an individual manufacturer should not be deprived of the power to enforce resale prices (e.g., by refusing supplies of goodsbearing his brand to any trader who sells below the prescribed price), but thatcollective resale price maintenance, by which a number of manufacturers agree to cut off an &quot; offender &quot; from a wide range of price-controlled goods, should be prohibited.5. Enquiries by the Board of Trade have shown that there is no prospect of a voluntary acceptance by industrialists and traders even of the modest proposals ofthe Lloyd Jacob Committee. Legislation will, therefore, be required to deal withthis objectionable restrictive practice. A debate on this subject on a private members&apos; motion on 16th June last showed very strong support for such legislationamong Government supporters. The Opposition were uncomfortably and signifi-cantly divided.6. Following a preliminary discussion on the subject by the Distribution and marketing Committee, the President of the Board of Trade set up an inter-departmental Working Party of officials on resale price maintenance. Their report is attached to this memorandum.-Collective Resale Price Maintenance7. We recommend, as proposed by the Lloyd Jacob Committee and endorsed by the Working Party, that collective measures operated by joint associations ofdistributors and suppliers to secure the maintenance of resale prices should be prohibited.Printed for the Cabinet. February 1951SECRETCopy No. d hiCP. (51) 371st February, 1951CABINETRESALE PRICE MAINTENANCE40072B
Individual Resale Price Maintenance8. The Lloyd Jacob Committee did not recommend prohibition of resale price maintenance by an individual supplier, because they felt that temporary price cuttingof a particular brand by a retailer to attract custom (the so-called &quot; loss-leader &quot;)in the long run benefited neither manufacturers nor consumers. The President ofthe Board of Trade proposed to the Distribution and Marketing Committee, andthe Committee agreed, that we should go beyond the Lloyd Jacob Report in thisconnection. The Working Party subsequently expressed doubts whether theeconomic effects of the loss-leader were as detrimental as the Lloyd Jacob Committeehad assumed: and we recommend, as proposed by the Working Party, that itshould be made an offence for individual suppliers to give any indication of resale prices, other than maximum resale prices.9. Resale price maintenance imposed by individual suppliers has exactly thesame results as collective price maintenance, so long as the suppliers can effectivelyenforce their wishes. There is no fundamental distinction between the two versionsof the practice. The distinction between the &quot; loss-leader &quot; type of price-cut and price-fedtictibns over a rafige of goods is more iriipoftaht, but we are satisfied both that the Working Party were fight to discbunt it for econoihic reasons and alsothat it would be quite impracticable administratively to incorporate it in legislation.10. In theory a provision which made it illegal to fix any retail price (otherthan a maximum price) should be enough to kill the practice. But, as the Presidentof the Board of Trade pointed out to the Committee, to rely on this alone wouldenable the supporters of resale price maintenance to base their case on the popularityof fixed-price branded goods and, quite apart from the practical reasons given bythe Working Party for banning the various sinister measures by which fixed prices are maintained such as collective boycotts, &amp;c. our attack will have much greateremotional appeal, if we draw particular attention to these practices in our presehta-tion of the Bill, and make them, as well as retail price fixation, illegal.Enforcement11. The enforcement of legislative provisions banning the indication bysuppliers Of resale prices, and collective measures or sanctions aimed at maintainingresale prices, would not, we are satisfied, present great difficulty. Traders who wishto reduce prices will naturally complain if they are impeded from doing so bysome infringement of these provisions. In many cases they will be able to under-take their own prosecutions of offences which harm them. The Working Partysuggested that some Governmental check might be needed on the institution of prosecutions, both to prevent frivolous actions and, still more important, to enable a prosecuting authority to take over cases where small traders might be unable toact effectively. This suggestion raises some questions about the refationship in thisrespect between the complainant, the Government Department concerned (normallythe Board of Trade) and the Director of Public Prosecutions, but we think these points can safely be left to be settled by the lawyers in the further stages of preparinglegislation. We did consider the idea that some new tribunal, rather than theordinary Courts, might be set up to deal with contraventions of the law, but we ourselves rejected it and the Attorney-General, whom we consulted, warmly supportsour view.12. These two prohibitions (of resale price indications and of collectivemeasures for price maintenance), given effective enforcement, should, as theWorking Party say in paragraph 19 of their report, &quot; make unlawful much thegreater part of resale price maintenance as now operated&quot; and we strongly recommend that they should be enacted. There are, however, two further issues which we think our colleagues will wish to consider.Discrimination13. A clear statement of the problem will be found at paragraphs 19 to 21of the Working Party report. Briefly, the point is that the two provisions alreadyrecommended would not prevent an individual supplier from refusing to trade witha particular distributor if he disapproved of the prices at which the latter sold hisgoods. Without committting the offence Of indicating any particular resale priceor of taking part in collective sanctions, he might still withhold supplies from atrader who severely cut the &quot; normal&quot; prices of his own branded goods or whomerely was known to be unpopular with other traders as a notorious price-cutter.
14. A particular example of this mischief is, of course, the discriminationwhich some manufacturers already exercise against Co-operative Societies andother traders who give discounts or pay dividends on purchases made by customers.We are not, however, in favour of a provision making it an offence for a supplierto discriminate against Co-operative Societies as such, nor does the Co-operativeUnion wish for special privileges in law to compel manufacturers to supplyCo-operative Societies. Most of the difficulties with which the Societies have beenfaced would be met by the general prohibition of resale price maintenance,particularly if reinforced by a general prohibition of unreasonable discrimination.15. Prima facie any legislation which prohibits resale price maintenance oughtalso to prohibit any unjustifiable stoppage of supplies of this kind. The working party tried to find a suitable form of prohibition for this purpose- Since, however,there are many legitimate grounds on which a supplier is unwilling to do business with a retailer, it is necessary to relate the offence to the motive of the supplier,i.e., discrimination or refusal to supply is an offence only when it is done becauseof the victim&apos;s price policy. Offences in which motive is an essential ingredientare notoriously difficult to establish in a court of law, and the Working Party, ona balance of argument, advised against attempting to ban discrimination as such.(A full statement of this conclusion is at paragraph 27 of the Working Party&apos;s report.)16. The Distribution and Marketing Committee were reluctant to accept thisrecommendation of the Working Party without consulting the Attorney-General.His advice is that he too can find no satisfactory and enforceable form of pro-hibition to make discrimination a criminal offence, and he sees little chance of framing a provision on which successful prosecutions could be based. But he suggests that the possibility of declaring discrimination unlawful in the statute andthen leaving it to be enforced by civil litigation (which might include proceedings at the suit of the Board of Trade for a mandatory injunction) might be further examined. He thinks that this course would give the victim of discrimination abetter chance of getting a remedy, though he admits that there would be complica-tions, delays and expense involved in the process.17. The case for banning discrimination, with civil proceedings as the sanction,* is that it would in effect be a declaration by Parliament that discrimination isunlawful. This should have a good moral influence on manufacturers and often be enough to prevent them from trying to find a way round the other provisionsof the proposed legislation. The case against this course is that the remedy by civil proceedings would normally be available only to large organisations theCo-troops., Sainsbury and so on who could afford expensive and protracted litigation.No small trader unaided could pursue a case against, say, Nuffield or Cadbury.This is an inequity which could only be overcome if the Board of Trade were willingto institute proceedings for an injunction on behalf of any trader who complained that his supplies were being cut. But this in turn would impose on the Board a burden of work and expense which would certainly be greater than anything wehave contemplated in the rest of this legislation. And the Attorney-General thinks that the Courts might be expected on the whole to uphold the traditional concept of &quot; freedom of contract,&quot; so that even the big people might fail to get a remedy.Further, if the procedure of seeking a mandatory injunction were used, the Courtswould have great difficulty in framing their orders so as to get for the tradersconcerned an equitable volume of supplies over a period on reasonable terms.18.   Two courses are open to us on this issue: either (a) to decide in principle now that the legislation should contain some provisiondeclaring discrimination unlawful and providing for remedies to besought by civil litigation, subject to the proviso that satisfactory pro-posals can be worked out on the basis of the Attorney-GeneraFssuggestion; or(b) to decide now that discrimination should not (at any rate initially) be covered in the legislation. The case for this rests partly on the argumentof the Working Party (paragraph 27 of their report) that the gap left in the legislation would not necessarily be disastrous. Also it would soon become clear whether any substantial amount of evasion of thelegislation^ was developing by means of discrimination; and, if therewere evidence of such evasion, the Government would then be in astrong position to introduce an amending Bill, to stop it.40072 ^ B 2
Retailers&apos; Price Rings19. Up to now we have been considering Retail Price Rigging at the instanceof suppliers. The Working Party further proposed to ban price fixing by associa-tion of retailers. On the Distribution of Marketing Committee, some ministers agreed with this proposal, but the majority felt that it would serve no good purpose to extend the ban in this way. We recommend that this matter, which raises somecomplicated issues, should be further examined by the Committee.Public Reactions20. A Bill to prohibit resale price maintenance will encounter bitter and well-organised opposition. This opposition will be directed by the joint associations of manufacturers and distributors who operate collective resale price maintenance and the initiative will be taken by the distributors who will fear that present margins of profit will be cut under a more competitive system. The Union of Shop, Distri-butive and Allied Workers may align themselves to some extent with this opposi-tion, though in present conditions of full employment and strong Trade Unionbargaining power, we do not consider that their members&apos; standards of life would been dangered by such legislation. On the other hand, we believe that legislation onthe lines which we have outlined, can be presented in a way which will commendit very strongly to the great body of citizens who are seriously concerned aboutthe rising cost of living and will warmly welcome action to enable individual readersto reduce prices against their competitors. More broadly, our purpose is to makeprivate trade more competitive and private &quot; enterprise &quot; more enterprising.Timing of Proposals21. It may be said by our opponents that, before we introduce general legis-lation against resale price maintenance, we should refer more particular cases for investigation by the Monopolies Commission. This argument will not carry muchconviction and, as we have said, the Lloyd Jacob Committee was set up beforethe Act of 1948 was passed. Moreover, the first report of the Commission canvasseswithin the field of dental goods some of the issues with which we are concerned.It strengthens our hand by saying that &quot; .... it must be for Parliament to consider in the light of the findings made, for example, by the Lloyd Jacob Committee(which clearly indicate that similar practices are operative over a wide range ofindustry), whether legislation confined to this particular industry should or shouldnot be enacted.&quot; Public reaction to the Commission^ report has shown that amonginformed opinion there is much support for early action over the wider field. Wethink, however, that no public announcement of the Governments intentions shouldbe made until the Commission^ second report, on builders&apos; castings, is published(provided this is not unduly delayed). The President of the Board of Trade wishesthen to issue a White Paper setting forth the Governments policy and thusencouraging public discussion on the whole question. This, of course, does not mean holding up action to prohibit exclusive dealing and the collective boycott inthe dental goods trade, as recommended by the Monopolies Commission. ThePresident of the Board of Trade and the Minister of Health are already in consul-tation on this step. These restrictive practices are used not only to support resale price maintenance, but to prevent new entries to the trade.Summary of Conclusions22.   We, therefore, ask our colleagues:  (a) To agree to prohibit collective measures to enforce resale price mainten-ance and the indication of resale prices by individual suppliers (para-_ graphs 7, 8 and 9).(b) To decide whether the possibility of a provision declaring discrimination in the matter of supplies unlawful and providing for remedies to besought by civil litigation should be further pursued or whether thelegislation should be introduced without any such provision (para-graphs 13 to 18).(c) To approve the issue at an early date by the President of the Board ofTrade of a White Paper explaining the Governments policy(paragraph 21).H. D.H. W.1st February, 1951.
APPENDIXFinal Report of the Official Working Party on Resale Price MaintenanceA. introductory. At their meeting on 11th May the Committee on Distribution and Market-ing &quot; invited the President of the Board of Trade to arrange for a Working party of officers of the Board of Trade, Treasury and Ministries of Health, Agriculture,Supply and Food, to make early recommendations within the general policy outlined by the President &quot;* (i.e., in his paper D.M. (50) 4). The Economic Section of theCabinet Office and the Ministry of Works have been represented at our discussions in addition to the Departments named.2. The main points of the Presidents paper D.M. (50) 4 which was ourstarting point were briefly as follows:  (a) Efforts to get a voluntary response from industry and trade on the basisof the Lloyd Jacob Committee&apos;s report had failed. Legislation would,therefore, be needed to deal with the problem.(b) The distinction between collective and individual resale price maintenancewas over-stressed in the Lloyd Jacob report. In some trades individualproducers could effectively enforce their retail prices and, for example,discriminate against Co-operative Societies. Legislation should not leave the matter open to the discretion of individual producers.(c) Legislation might have to include special provisions enabling some remedyto be invoked against &quot; loss-leading.&quot;&apos;. 3. We were asked as a first step to examine the validity of this &quot; loss-leader &quot;argument and we did this in our report headed &quot; The &apos; Loss-leader &apos; Issue &quot; (circu-lated to the D.M. Committee with D.M. (50) 20). We found that the &quot; loss-leader &quot;argument, considered purely as an eoonomic argument alleging that the &quot; loss-pleader &quot; practice raises manufacturing costs and impedes mass-production ofstandardised goods, was not convincing enough to justify the serious additionalcomplications which special provisions to meet it would involve in any legislation which might be adopted.4. We have now proceeded to consider what legislative provisions would beneed to effect the complete abolition of resale price maintenance. We have examined various possible provisions and set out below a series which, we believe,would in sum have this effect. To achieve complete abolition, a number of differentaspects of the practice have to be dealt with. We have, therefore, divided the pro-visions we propose into separate blocks, each block covering a particular facet ofthe problem. This enables us, at the end of the report, to suggest various ways inwhich the separate blocks might be combined to form a workable measure, if it were finally decided that some solution short of complete abolition should be sought.5. We are, of course, mainly concerned with the question how various objec-tives might be achieved in legislation, though we try to set out fully and fairly the implications of the means suggested. We do not tackle the question which of thepossible objectives whether complete abolition or some more modest aim shouldbe pursued, since this is primarily a matter for politioal judgment.B. Possible Legislative ProvisionsI. Provisions to stop suppliers laying down resale prices6. Resale price maintenance is a two-stage process. First the supplier sayswhat he wants the resale price to be. Secondly he may take steps (either alone orin association) to see that his wish is respected. Since, as will appear below, someof the means (particularly withholding of supplies) by which resale prices areenforced may prove difficult to stop, we consider that, if the practice is to be com-pletely abolished, it should be made an offence in the first place for the supplier ofgoods to lay down resale prices.
7.   A number of important points have to be met in defining this prohibitionmore closely:  (a) It would be no good to prohibit only the prescription of resale prices in contracts, because the maintenance of resale prices is not always (oreven usually) enforced contractually. It can be effectively enforced (e.g.,by withholding supplies) where the &quot; laying down &quot; is in form merelya &quot; recommendation.&quot;(b) On the other hand it would be too drastic to ban any indication whateverby a supplier of a resale price. Manufacturers may legitimately wish to prescribe maximum retail prices for their goods (e.g., to prevent themarket being spoiled by excessive prices in a temporary shortage or in rural areas where there is little competition among distributors). Withsome commodities, e.g., cigarettes or motor cars, resale pripe, mainten^ance has acted as a convenient form of price-control and manufacturers,even in conditions of extreme shortage, have not allowed their prescribedprices to be exceeded. Moreover, the Government in its trading servicesoften lays down maximum resale prices in the public interest.(c) It would not be enough in our view for the prohibition to bite only on the manufacturer of goods. It should clearly be imposed on any supplier,so as to prevent resale price prescriptions at the wholesale stage.Furthermore, it should operate against associations of suppliers because in some industries. (e.g., electric lamps) where there are price rings, thethe resale prices are issued by the association and not by the individual.Finally it would have to be so worded as to prevent the manufacturerfrom finding an easy loophole by getting some other party to indicateresale prices on his behalf.(d) It should clearly be framed to bite on imported goods, even though enforce-ment against foreign suppliers might sometimes be impracticable,because, if there is any advantage to manufacturers in resale price main-tenance, it would be wrong for foreign manufacturers to monopolise it.On the other hand, exports should in our view be exempted (by makingthe prohibition relate only to supplies in United Kingdom) because itwould be undesirable to enact something which might cause our ,exporters to fall foul of their customers in countries where resale price maintenance remains legal (e.g., United States) and because the inten-tion, after all, is to protect the consumer at home.8.   Main Provision. Taking these points into account, this first main provi-sion, therefore, will look somewhat as follows:  &quot; No person selling goods in the United Kingdom shall indicate or causeto be indicated in any manner any price for the resale of any goods sold by him and no trade association shall indicate any price for the resale of goods sold bymembers of that association unless any such indication is accompanied by a clear statement that the price indicated is a maximum resale price.&quot;9. The effect of a provision on these lines would be to establish the freedomof the distributor to sell at prices below those indicated by the supplier. If aretailer found his freedom of action in this respect circumscribed, he would normallyhave been given some indication of the prices at which he was expected to sell andthat would be evidence of an offence.10. There might be considerable opposition from manufacturers in manytrades where it is normal practice for them to express their selling prices as &quot; listprices &quot; less a discount (usually equivalent to the conventional distributors&apos; marginin the trade concerned). A frequent reason for this practice is to assist the operationof resale price maintenance itself but it is also done to reassure the retailer thatthe manufacturer will not undercut him in direct ex-works sales to the finalcustomers. The effect of the suggested provision would be to compel the manufacturer who uses this form of price-quotation to show the &quot; list-price &quot; asa maximum resale price. This would mean that the manufacturer would in effectbe undertaking not merely to refrain from under-selling the retailer, but to chargea higher price in his direct sales than the price charged by any retailer who reducedprices below those listed. In these circumstances many manufacturers would nodoubt abandon the practice. This might cause trouble for them with retailers whofeared an extension of direct sales by manufacturers. Moreover, since a good deal
of invoicing and bookkeeping is nOW done on the basis of list-prices* some tiresomerevision of office methods Would be needed. There are Usually strong forces ofinertia to overcome in making such changes in established customs and there would no doubt be protests.1L   Subsidiary Provisions. Various subsidiary provisions will be needed tocomplete this block:  (a) Existing Contracts. It will be necessary to provide that any terms in existing agreements imposing obligations inconsistent with the mainprovision above should be of no effect, without prejudice to the otherterms of those agreements.(b) Exemptions(i) It might, we think, be necessary to provide some machinery for exemptionin cases, for example, where manufacturers here are producing goods bylicence under patents, where the master-patent is held abroad and where&apos; the royalty-agreement with the foreigner contains terms governing resale prices. It might not be in the public interest that the benefits of these agreements should be lost. This question will require detailed examina-tion in the further stages of preparing legislation.(ii) In some State trading at present \e.g., sales of bacon by the Ministry ofFood) fixed resale prices are prescribed as a matter of administrative convenience. (In each case, so far as we know, only wholesalers&apos; resale prices are laid down, not those of retailers). It would clearly be undesirable to make an exemption on this account and thus discriminate between the public and private sectors in legislation which will be suffiently controversial in any event. A detailed check will have tobe made of all the existing cases, but we are hopeful that satisfactory alternative arrangements can be made and an exempting provisionavoided. This will, however, require further consideration.(c) Enforcement. We have considered how offences under the main provisionabove should be prosecuted. Although some of the stronger retailorganisations might be in a position to carry through their own prose-cutions , we think that enforcement would primarily be a matter for theBoard of Trade. Unless the Board had some control-in this respect,there might be frivolous prosecutions (e.g., by retailers who &quot; had it in &quot;for some manufacturer) and there wouid probably be a large numberof unsuccessful ones, if they were undertaken by people without thespecial experience which would be gained by the Board&apos;s solicitors in this field. This would tend to discredit the law as a whole. The board would need a small investigating staff to secure any evidence that mightbe needed over and above that provided by complainants. (A fullerassessment of the administrative resources and man-power likely to berequired as a result of the legislation appears at paragraph 41 below.)Further provisions, therefore, would be needed (i) To provide that prosecutions shall not be instituted except by or with theconsent of the Board of Trade.(ii) To lay down appropriate penalties.II. Prohibition of Collective Resale Price Maintenance12. The main provision suggested at 8 above would bite on suppliers ofgoods for resale and on trade associations having such sellers as members. Itwould not prevent distributors&apos; associations from issuing lists of minimum retail prices (this might be done without reference to the suppliers) and taking steps toenforce them. Indeed, if resale price prescriptions by suppliers were prohibited, weshould expect this to happen, since it is generally accepted that the main impulsetowards resale price maintenance comes from distributors. The stronger retailassociations might well be able to persuade manufacturers to cut off supplies frompeople infringing their price-fixing arrangements just as they do now in the case of collective resale price maintenance schemes. We consider, therefore, that a furtherprohibition would be needed to stop such arrangements. Moreover, it would, inour view, be necessary in any case to reinforce the prohibition of resale priceindications by a provision directed against the various collective means of enforcing
resale prices, as recommended by the Lloyd Jacob Committee.   The next mainprovision, therefore, is intended to meet both these points.13.   Main Provision. This prohibition might be roughly on the following lines (see also paragraph 18 (a) below):  &quot; No person shall enter into new arrangements or continue to operateexisting arrangements with other persons with the object of ensuring that goodsshall be sold by any parties to the arrangements at or above specified retail prices or with the addition of specified minimum margins to cost prices.&quot;&apos;14. The need to frame this provision so as to prohibit collective price-fixingby retailers may not have been foreseen. It will certainly be pointed out byopponents of the measure that this provision is out of line with the policy behind the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices (Inquiry and Control) Act, 1948, underwhich remedial measures can only be applied after reports from the monopolies commission have indicated the necessity for them. They will say that this type of provision could only be justified after appropriate references had been made tothe Commission and that to single out retail price-rings as against manufacturers&apos;or wholesalers&apos; price-rings for special treatment (outside the Monopolies Actprocedure) is discriminatory.15. The inconsistency between the suggested provision and the MonopoliesAct has to be faced. In a sense, of course, any legislation on the subject will be out of line with the policy behind the Act, because resale price maintenance is a restrictive practice about which there are as yet no reports from the monopolies commission. We take it that Ministers are ready to deal with this general point,as did the President of the Board of Trade in his statement in the House on 2nd June, 1949, by pointing to the fact that the Lloyd Jacob inquiry was started inadvance of the monopolies legislation and arguing that resale price maintenanceis a problem which can be examined by itself. It might be held, however, that this argument could not justify the prohibition of retail price-fixing, which, in form, goesbeyond the scope of resale price maintenance. Having considered this carefully,we find it impossible in practice to draw any useful line between resale price maintenance and retail price-fixing. So long as there are distributors&apos; associationsstrong enough to put effective pressure on suppliers, the effects of the two practicesare the same.   .&apos;16. It is true that the individual trader would be free to join or refuse to joina retail price-fixing association and that to refuse might be less immediatelyinconvenient to him than to refuse to comply with a manufacturer^ resale price and in consequence go without that manufacturer^ goods. But there may be allsorts of ways in which a refusal to play in with a powerful association may be disadvantageous. Moreover, it is difficult to believe that a powerful body say,the National Pharmaceutical Union would be unable to persuade some manu-.facturers to withhold supplies from a retailer who broke the Association^ price-fixing rules. They might even be able to arrange in some cases that manufacturersshould only supply members of the Association.17. We conclude, therefore, that if complete abolition is the aim, some provision on these lines will be necessary and the inevitable protests will have tobe faced.18. Subsidiary Provisions. (a) Stop-lists, &amp;c. We have considered whether there should be separate provisions dealing with the specific measures whichcollective bodies can take to enforce resale price maintenance or their own price-fixing arrangements. The most obvious example is the &quot; stop-list,&quot; which might,of: course, be used, even when there had been no offence against the &quot; no indications &quot; provision in Block I, to get manufacturers to withhold supplies fromretailers who became known as particularly vigorous price-cutters. We are advised,however, that the best way to deal with this matter would probably be by carefuldrafting of the provision in 13 above, so as to bring these collective sanctionswithin its scope. This would in due course be a matter for parliamentary counsel. We mention it here to show that this aspect has not been neglected.(b) Trades Union Amendment Act, 1876. Under this Act, any associationwhich has among its objects the imposing of restrictive conditions on the conductof any trade or business is a trade union, whether or not it is registered with the registrar of Friendly Societies or has obtained from him a certificate to the effectthat it is a trade union. As a trade union it cannot be sued for any act alleged to
resale prices, as recommended by the Lloyd Jacob Committee.   The next mainprovision, therefore, is intended to meet both these points.13. Main Provision. This prohibition might be roughly on the following lines (see also paragraph 18 (a) below):  &quot; No person shall enter into new arrangements or continue to operateexisting arrangements with other persons with the object of ensuring that goodsshall be sold by any parties to the arrangements at or above specified retail prices or with the addition of specified minimum margins to cost prices.&quot;14. The need to frame this provision so as to prohibit collective price-fixingby retailers may not have been foreseen. It will certainly be pointed out byopponents of the measure that this provision is out of line with the policy behind the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices (Inquiry and Control) Act, 1948, underwhich remedial measures can only be applied after reports from the monopolies commission have indicated the necessity for them. They will say that this type of provision could only be justified after appropriate references had been made tothe Commission and that to single out retail price-rings as against manufacturers&apos;or wholesalers&apos; price-rings for special treatment (outside the Monopolies Actprocedure) is discriminatory.15. The inconsistency between the suggested provision and the MonopoliesAct has to be faced. In a sense, of course, any legislation on the subject will be out of line with the policy behind the Act, because resale price maintenance is a restrictive practice about which there are as yet no reports from the monopolies commission. We take it that Ministers are ready to deal with this general point,as did the President of the Board of Trade in his statement in the House on 2nd June, 1949, by pointing to the fact that the Lloyd Jacob inquiry was started inadvance of the monopolies legislation and arguing that resale price maintenanceis a problem which can be examined by itself. It might be held, however, that this argument could not justify the prohibition of retail price-fixing, which, in form, goesbeyond the scope of resale price maintenance. Having considered this carefully,we find it impossible in practice to draw any useful line between resale price maintenance and retail price-fixing. So long as there are distributors&apos; associationsstrong enough to put effective pressure on suppliers, the effects of the two practicesare the same.   .16. It is true that the individual trader would be free to join or refuse to joina retail price-fixing association and that to refuse might be less immediatelyinconvenient to him than to refuse to comply with a manufacturer^ resale price and in consequence go without that manufacturer^ goods. But there may be allsorts of ways in which a refusal to play in with a powerful association may be disadvantageous. Moreover, it is difficult to believe that a powerful body say,the National Pharmaceutical Union would be unable to persuade some manu-facturers to withhold supplies from a retailer who broke the Association^ price-fixing rules. They might even be able to arrange in some cases that manufacturersshould only supply members of the Association.17. We conclude, therefore, that if complete abolition is the aim, some provision on these lines will be necessary and the inevitable protests will have tobe faced.18. Subsidiary Provisions. (a) Stop-lists, &amp;c. We have considered whether there should be separate provisions dealing with the specific measures whichcollective bodies can take to enforce resale price maintenance or their own price-fixing arrangements. The most obvious example is the &quot; stop-list,&quot; which might,of course, be used, even when there had been no offence against the &quot; no indications &quot; provision in Block I, to get manufacturers to withhold supplies fromretailers who became known as particularly vigorous price-cutters. We are advised,however, that the best way to deal with this matter would probably be by carefuldrafting of the provision in 13 above, so as to bring these collective sanctionswithin its scope. This would in due course be a matter for parliamentary counsel. We mention it here to show that this aspect has not been neglected.(b) Trades Union Amendment Act, 1876. Under this Act, any associationwhich has among its objects the imposing of restrictive conditions on the conductof any trade or business is a trade union, whether or not it is registered with the registrar of Friendly Societies or has obtained from him a certificate to the effectthat it is. a trade union. As a trade union it cannot be sued for any act alleged to
9-    173be in restraint of trade. The legislative provisions already outlined would, if carried into effect, override the protection given to price maintenance associations undertrades union legislation. We are advised, however, that in order to clarify theposition, it may be desirable to add a specific provision establishing that a tradeunion can be prosecuted for offences under the new resale price maintenancelegislation.(c) Enforcement. As with the provisions outlined in Block I above and for similar reasons, we think that prosecutions should be undertaken only by or withthe consent of the Board of Trade. Provisions to establish this and to lay downappropriate penalties would be needed.///. Provisions to prevent withholding of supplies19. Preamble. The provisions in Blocks I and II above would make unlawfulmuch the greater part of resale price maintenance as now operated. There would,we think, be comparatively few cases in which retailers found their freedom to reduceprices impaired, where there would not also be evidence of an offence against oneor other of the provisions already outlined. On the evidence of the price-maintenance associations themselves, the practice cannot be worked in many tradeswithout collective action. It is also important to note that a manufacturer cannotusually afford to have the resale prices of his own branded goods maintained, ifprice-cutting is going on with competing brands.20. It is still possible, however, to envisage circumstances in which suppliesmight be withheld from unpopular distributors and some resale price maintenancecarried on (though perhaps in a limited sphere), without bringing the peopleconcerned up against the provisions already outlined.  For example (a) First and foremost, there might continue to be discrimination againstCo-operative Societies.(b) Individual manufacturers in a monopoly or near-monopoly position might,while still keeping on the right side of the provisions in Block I above,discriminate in the matter of supplies against traders whose price policiesthey disliked. For example, they might not indicate explicitly that their&quot; list prices &quot; were to be regarded as minima as well as maxima, butthey might happen, all the same, to give preference to those of their customers who treated them as such. They might also cut off supplies from traders who laid information of offences against the provisions in Block I above.(c) Similar action might be taken by manufacturers in a close ring, either on their own initiative or under pressure from a strong distributors&apos;organisation.21. In general, the weapon of withholding supplies has always been the chiefmeans of making resale price maintenance effective and it is open to doubt whether legislation to abolish the practice could be completely successful, if it ignored thisweapon. We have, therefore, tried to find suitable provisions to cover this aspect of the problem.22. The difficulty about any direct prohibition of a refusal to supply goods for a particular reason (e.g., that the buyer is a notorious &quot; price-cutter &quot;) is that it makes an offence out of a motive and the prosecutor has the hopeless job ofestablishing that this particular motive rather than many other possible motivesfor the same action is the valid one. It is true that the onus of proof might be laid on the defence. This would mean prohibiting any refusal whatever on the partof a supplier to supply goods, but making it a defence to prove that his refusalwas not connected with the buyer&apos;s resale prices. This, however, exposes everysupplier to the risk of prosecution, whenever, for any reason, however justifiable,he is unwilling or unable to supply a customer. We mention this very bald formof prohibition in order to show clearly the implications which will be in some degreeinherent in any provision that will do the job effectively.23. As a matter of presentation, however, we have found that a prohibitioncan be more acceptably stated in terms of &quot; discrimination &quot; rather than &quot; refusal to supply.&quot; An Order under Defence Regulations was, in fact, drafted in 1946 to prohibit discrimination against Co-operative Societies and we have taken this asa model for the main provisions in this block. ** The Order was approved by the Law Officers and accepted by the Lord presidents committee but was not enacted, partly because it was considered that further thought shouldbe given to enforcement difficulties but mainly because the Parliamentary Committee of theCo-operative Union decided in the end for tactical reasons not to press the matter.40072 c
24.   Main Provision. This provision would be on the following lines:  &quot; No person supplying goods for resale shall in relation to the acceptanceor refusal of orders for the supply of goods or in/relation to the terms andconditions upon which he offers or agrees to supply goods discriminate against any person [because of the prices, other than excessive prices at which that person sells goods] [on the ground that that person is a Co-operative Society][on the ground that that person is a trader who regularly gives discounts orpays dividends on the purchases made by his customers].&quot;25. It will be noted that three possible versions of this provision have beengiven in square brackets. This is because there are arguments in favour of adoptingeach of these versions rather than the others and equally the objections are different in each case. We therefore deal separately with each possible form below. Someobjections, however, which are implicit in the balder statement of the prohibitionin paragraph 22 above, are common to all the versions, namely:-(a) Any such provision infringes the supplier^ normal &quot; freedom of contract &quot;by which he may choose whether or not to do business with any par-ticular buyer. Opponents of the measure would no doubt seize on thispoint. (It is worth noting, however, that resale price maintenance itselfinfringes the converse freedom of the buyer of goods to dispose of his property on whatever terms he chooses.)(b) It still exposes the supplier to the risk of prosecution whenever he isunwilling or unable to supply a customer, even for good reasons.(c) It is bound to raise formidable enforcement problems.26. Discrimination against any person because of the prices at which he sells. The most general form of the provision would make it an offence for suppliers to discriminate agaihst any trader whose resale prices they disliked. In this form theprovision raises acute problems of enforcement and prosecution.(a) Prosecutions. On one hand the arguments for allowing prosecutions to be instituted only &quot; by or with the consent of the Board of Trade &quot; seemeven stronger than in the case of the previous main provisions (see para-graph 11 (c) above). Any retailer with a grouse about his supplies (e.g.,in a time of shortage) could bring a manufacturer to court for the costof a summons. There might be many irresponsible actions and therewould certainly be many failures, which would discredit the law.On the other hand this provision differs fundamentally from the others. The prohibition of resale price indications or of retail price-fixing would be something enacted by Parliament to protect the public generally and it would be reasonable for the Board of Trade, as theappropriate authority, to decide which cases were suitable for prose-cution. This prohibition of discrimination, however, would be intendedessentially to provide individual traders with a remedy in cases of dis-crimination against them by other private parties. If the Board ofTrade were to pick and choose among the possible cases for prosecution,,they would in effect be deciding who should have the protection of thelaw in disputes inter partes, and they would certainly be open tocomplaints and charges of discrimination from traders whose cases theydeclined to take up.A possible answer might be to provide that remedies against dis-crimination in supplies should be obtainable by civil litigation. Thedifficulty about this, however, is that, even if Parliament created a&quot; tort&quot; in this way on which civil actions could be based, the com-plainant would have to show damage and the Court would have to assess the amount of supplies which he ought to get. In any case theusual snags of civil litigation expense, delay and so forth would render this solution useless in the majority of cases to the small traderof limited means. -(b) Enforcement. Whoever undertook prosecutions would come up againstthe difficulty of proving that a particular motive caused the discrimina-tion. The defendant might advance a hundred reasons not connectedwith prices for his failure to supply a particular trader-e.g., bad credit(which might be suspected precisely because of the trader?s price-cutting),
insufficient supplies to go round, a decision to reduce the number ofoutlets handling the goods in a particular area and so on. It would bevery difficult for the prosecutor to disprove such claims. There would no doubt be some cases sufficiently flagrant for successful prosecution,e.g., where supplies had been regularly provided over a long period but were suddenly cut off when the trader adopted a price-cutting policy.If the Board of Trade were responsible for prosecutions, one main difficulty would be sifting these promising cases out of, a mass of com-plaints. This screening job might require a substantial investigatingstaff or even some system of local committees (such as we have had for price control enforcement) which could hear the defence story and recommend the Board to institute proceedings only in promising cases.(If it were decided to proceed with the provision in this form, this possibility would require further study.)27. The question for decision is whether the object of this provision is so important as to outweigh these difficulties. On this the following points are worthmaking:  (a) The provisions of Block I would prevent individual manufacturers fromprescribing resale prices, other than maximum resale prices.(b) All this further provision aims at is to prevent individual manufacturersfrom cutting off supplies from traders on the general ground that theyare &quot; price-cutters &quot; (i.e., quite apart from any infringement of particularprice prescriptions).(c) To withhold supplies in this way would clearly be contrary to the spirit ofthe legislation and it might be expected that reputable firms would notwilfully evade the intention of Parliament.(d) If there were a general breakdown of resale price maintenance as a resultof the other provisions and price-cutting became widespread, the attemptto withhold supplies would in many cases become pointless. Moreover,manufacturers would have less reason to be concerned at pressure fromdistributors, since the existence of the law as a whole would help themresist it.Thus, a provision in this form would probably have effect only on a comparativelynarrow range of individual price maintenance. (This would usually be where the manufacturer had a monopoly position and where the problem could if necessary be dealt with by the Monopolies Commission.) To achieve this effect, the suggestedprovision is open to the serious objections set out in paragraph 25 above andinvolves fundamental enforcement and prosecution difficulties (paragraph 26) towhich we have found no satisfactory answer. Our conclusion, therefore, is that inthis form the provision would not be worth while and we cannot recommend it.28. Provision to prohibit discrimination against Co-operative Societies. Inits narrowest form the suggested provision would make it an offence for a supplierto discriminate against Co-operative Societies as such. We have considered this possibility because we realise that Ministers might wish to deal with discrimination against Co-operative Societies in this legislation. It is true, of course, that manyexamples of discrimination against Co-operative Societies have little or no con-nexion with resale price maintenance but are either political in origin or may springfrom resentment at the way in which the Societies &quot; push &quot; the sales of C.W.S.products as against those of competing manufacturers. In so far as the problemgoes beyond that of resale price maintenance, it may perhaps be outside our remit.In fact, however, the two problems have long been tied together and we appreciate that if Ministers were to agree that the general form of this provision, discussed inparagraphs 26 and 27 above, is undesirable, they might still wish to deal with theCo-operative Society issue specifically.29. As compared with the general form of the provision, this course wouldhave some practical advantages:  (a) The difficulty over prosecutions (see paragraph 26 above) would not arise.The Co-operative Movement have the resources and the sense of respon-sibility required to undertake their own legal actions.(b) Enforcement might also be easier, since the problem of establishing aparticular motive for discrimination might be less acute if the provision40072 d
made it an offence to discriminate against Co-operative Societies as such.(Nobody can say in advance, of course, how effective the provision would be and whether the Societies would in fact get supplies after a successful action, since this would depend on the attitude of the Courts.In particular the Societies might still have difficulty with goods whichare customarily sold through a restricted number of &quot; authoriseddealers&quot; e.g., motor cars since it would be hard for them to estab-lish that they, any more than other retailers who were not on the&quot; approved list,&quot; were discriminated against).30. There is, however, a fundamental objection to this form of the provision,namely, that it would provide a remedy against discrimination for one class oftrader which would be denied to all other traders. It would, in fact, be legislation in favour of a particular sectional interest, flatly discriminating in favour ofCo-operative trading, and as such would clearly be difficult to defend politically.Indeed, so far as we have been able to discover by informal consultation theCo-operative movement itself would not expect such a measure and might even benervous of its possible repercussions.31. Provision prohibiting discrimination against traders giving discounts. The third form of the provision would make it an offence to discriminate not merelyagainst Co-operative Societies but against any traders adopting discount or dividendsystems. It is an attempt to find a satisfactory middle course. The advantages which make it attractive at first sight are:  (a) It avoids the charge of discriminating openly in favour of Co-operative societies.(b) The Lloyd Jacob Committee might indeed be quoted in its support since they said (paragraph 102) that discount schemes &quot; offer a means by whichthe dangers of distributive rigidity may be mitigated and retail priceslowered and in our opinion it is in the public interest that they shouldbe encouraged.&quot;32. There are also, however, serious disadvantages in this version of theprovision:  (a) It is still discriminatory in effect, even though the class of traders favouredis broadened. Opponents of the measure might claim that the widerform of words was no more than a &quot; cover plan &quot; to disguise legislation in favour of Co-operative trading.(b) The effect of the provision in this form would probably to be protect theCo-operative Societies only against discrimination arising out of theirdividend system. It is doubtful whether it would cover discriminationfrom political or other motives. (This, of course, would be true also of the most general form of the provision.)(c) It would probably reintroduce the prosecution and enforcement difficulties.Whereas the Co-operative Societies could be left to undertake their ownprosecutions, it is doubtful whether it would be sound for all tradersrunning discount schemes to be entitled to prosecute. - It is true that many genuine discount schemes are run by substantial firms but there could be no objective test of &quot; genuineness &quot; in this respect and, if thisprovision were enacted, a large number of discount schemes might springup. Then the problem of frivolous and unsuccessful actions wouldreappear.Conclusion on the prevention of the withholding of supplies (Block III)33. The upshot of this discussion is briefly that, leaving aside the special issueof discrimination against Co-operative Societies, the need for an anti-discriminationprovision cannot be put very high. In its most general form, therefore, the suggestedprovision involves too many difficulties to be worth while. On the other hand, touse the provision to deal specifically with the Co-operative Societies&apos; problem wouldbe discriminatory. A middle course might be to frame the provision so as to pro-hibit discrimination against discount and dividend traders generally but this wouldhave many of the difficulties of the first course without completely meeting theCooperative Societies&apos; problem and without avoiding altogether the danger of discriminatory legislation. In point of fact we cannot recommend with any confi-dence any form of this provision.
34. Possible alternative provisions involving a tribunal. We have consideredbriefly whether the problem of withholding supplies might be overcome more easily,if the provision at paragraph 24 above were re-cast so as to give the victims of this type of discrimination the right of access to some form of tribunal which mightorder or recommend the Board of Trade to direct manufacturers to supply goods.35. The provision would be framed much as before but with an additional provision setting up a special tribunal to adjudicate in such cases and defining its powers of ordering remedies; possibly, also, empowering the Board of Trade tomake directions on the tribunal&apos;s recommendation. At first sight, this solution may appear to offer the possibility of a more flexible type of procedure.36.   We think, however, it is objectionable on the following grounds:  (a) The evidence would be no different from that heard in the normal courts and there is no reason to suppose that a quasi-judicial body would reach any better conclusions than the courts. It might well do worse.(b) There could be no preliminary screening process and the tribunals mightbe flooded with frivolous applications, arising, for example, out of local shortages. Unless a very large machinery were provided, there wouldprobably be long delays in dealing with cases.37. Minor considerations on the legislation. For completeness we think weshould mention one way in which the whole of this suggested legislation might in theory be circumvented, if manufacturers were determined to continue resale price maintenance. If, instead of selling their goods to distributors for resale, they wereto appoint the distributors as agents on a commission basis, they would legally beselling direct to the final purchaser and could determine the prices as they liked.This was in fact done in the United States and successfully defended in the courtsthere by the General Electric Company when resale price maintenance was stillillegal under the Sherman Act.Although it might conceivably be done here, particularly perhaps with thosetechnical goods e.g., cars, television that are already sold through selectedretailers, we think it would probably present too many accounting and administra-tive problems to manufacturers to be widely adopted. We do not think it is anygood anticipating such a development. If it were to occur on a large scale, how-ever, further legislation might have to be considered later.38. Coverage. We have not been able to make a full study of the applicabilityof the provisions we have suggested to particular commodities. We think there might prove to be special considerations in some trades which might justify exemp-tions. We have been told, for example, that in the Ministry of Works field thecomplete abolition of resale price maintenance would make illegal the MultipleBasing Point system of cement pricing and might involve extensive changes in exist-ing methods of tendering for building contracts. When the time comes to consultindustry and trade generally about the proposals, other examples may crop up, wherecogent reasons can be given for special treatment. These questions will have to begone into fully in the further stages of preparing the legislation. If necessary, a schedule could be included in the Bill to limit its coverage.C. Summary of Provisions39.   The following in brief are the provisions outlined:  Block IMain provision: (paragraph 8)No individual seller (nor his trade association) shall indicate resale prices, other than maxima.Subsidiary provisions: (paragraph 11)(a) Terms in existing agreements, inconsistent with the above provi-sion, shall be void.(b) Possible exemption for international agreements.(c) Prosecutions by or with the consent of the Board of Trade:appropriate penalties.
Block IIMain provision: (paragraph 13)N&apos;o collective arrangements shall be operated to ensure that retail orresale prices are maintained.Subsidiary provisions: (paragraph 18)(a) Trade unions can be prosecuted for offences under this legislation.(b) Prosecutions by or with the consent of the Board of Trade:appropriate penalties.Block IIIMain provision : (paragraph 24)In relation to accepting or refusing orders to supply, (or to the terms and conditions of supply) no supplier shall discriminate against any person [because of the prices at which that person sellsgoods] or [on the ground that that person is a Co-operative society] or [on the ground that that person runs a dividend ordiscount scheme].40. A Bill could be drafted in any one of the following ways according to the objectives it is intended to achieve:(a) It might contain the provisions of Blocks I and II only. This would makeunlawful much the greater part of resale price maintenance as nowoperated but would not deal with discrimination against Co-operative societies.(b) One or other form of the Block III provision might be added to these provisions. If this were the most general version and it proved work-able, resale price maintenance would be abolished as completely aswe think is possible. But we do not think that the need for this additionis great enough to justify the difficulties involved. If it were the versionconfined to dealing with the Co-operative Societies issue, enforcementwould be easier but the legislation would be openly discriminatory. Theversion prohibiting discrimination against discount and dividendtraders would be a middle course but has some of the objections to boththe others.(c) It might be confined to Block II only. This would make collective sanctionsillegal but would do next to nothing to stop individual resale price maintenance. This solution would be in line with the main recom-mendation of the Lloyd Jacob Committee.41.   Manpower Requirements(a) So far as we can see, subject to further study, the administration and enforcement of the provisions in Blocks I and II, if passed into law,would not require more than a quite small additional staff at the Boardof Trade, probably not more than 20 to 25 officers in all.(b) The addition of Block III if confined to discrimination against Co-operative societies would not require any further manpower, if it were left to theCo-operative Movement to undertake its own prosecution.(c) The addition of the full provision in Block III would probably require amuch larger investigating body to go into complaints and the screeningof possible cases would either be a big job for the legal department or would have to be delegated to a system of local committees. This is afurther important objection to the adoption of this provision.42. The&quot; Loss-Leader.&quot; In view of our conclusion on the &quot; loss-leader &quot; issue(see paragraph 3) we have not examined at length, for the purpose of this report,the provisions which might be required if some remedy against &quot; loss-leading &quot; wereto be incorporated in the legislation. We appreciate that despite our conclusion onthe economic aspect of the argument, there might still be cogent political reasonsfor making such provision. We feel, however, that if this were required, the wholeplan of the legislation would have to be radically different and that we should haveto tackle the problem as a separate exercise.Board of Trade,September, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
