<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 377-381</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE   PROPERTY   OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.&apos; February 1951SECRETCP. (51) 5928th February, 1951Copy No61CABINETOVERSEAS INFORMATION expenditure memorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerOverseas Ministers have proposed in CP. (51) 53 that provision for overseas information expenditure in 1951-52 should be approximately  1.1 million as against 10-5 million* in 1950-51 and  10 15 million which I informed the information services Committee on 12th February (I.S. (51) 1st meeting) I proposed to provide in the 1951-52 Estimates shortly to be presented to Parliament. The cut of  900,000suggested by CP. (51) 53 is no cut at all compared with the present level of expendi-ture, but an increase.  The following figures show the position in broad terms:  A. B.B.C. Overseas ServicesB. British council. Departmental Information Ser-vices (including Board ofTrade and allied Services ofC.O.I. and H.M.S.O.)Total   ......1950-51Provision &apos;0004,6852,9922,8231951-52Provision&quot;offered&quot; byOverseasMinisters &apos;0005,0803,0322,88710,500*10,999195i-52Myproposals toInformationServicesCommittee &apos;0004,6502,6502,85010,1502. I at first asked for a reduction of 20 per cent, in both home and overseas information services as compared with the 1950-51 provision. On the home side,thanks to the co-operation of my colleagues, this saving has been substantiallyachieved and the provision has been reduced from  4-2 million in 1950-51 to  3-4 million in 1951-52. On the overseas side a 20 per cent, cut would have meant areduction from  10 5 million to  8-5 million as compared with  11-9 million(including items totalling  275,000 not previously included in the Informationbudget) for which overseas departments had asked. The Overseas Ministers repre-sented that this would cause very serious damage to their services and, whilereserving my position, I agreed to a suggestion of the Foreign Secretary that officials should examine the effect of a reduction to  9 8 million. After officials had reported, we discussed the matter at the Ministerial Information Services Com-mittee on 12th February and Overseas Ministers took the view that even a cut to 9-8 million which had been worked out in detail would have very damagingeffects. They offered a reduction of  900,000 on the Estimates they had prepared.This would have produced a total of  11 million, which, as already stated, is nota cut at all but an increase of  500,000 on the 1950-51 provision of  10-5 million.I said I was prepared to agree to a total provision of  10-15 million for 1951-52and would insert that provision in Estimates. My colleagues, other than the overseas Minister:,, seemed to regard this as a reasonable compromise and some* Provision in the 1950-51 Estimates totalled  10,820,000, but reductions were agreed whichwould restrict actual expenditure to  10-5 millions. :    C&quot;. ; &apos;40217
took the view that we should not have gone further than  9-8 million.  10-15million represents a ieduction-pf;qnly: 3i.per cent, on the provision for 1950-51,instead of the 20 per cent, reduction for which I originally asked.3. Departmental information Services. The figure which I proposed to theInformation Services Committee for the various departmental overseas informationSefviceS&apos;(including those of the Board of Trade and the Allied Services rendered by the Central Office of Information and His Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office) ,was sub-stantially the same (see C. in paragraph 1) as that proposed by the Overseas ministers in connection with their offer to reduce the Estimates as originally prbposed by themselves by  900,000. I have therefore accepted these proposals for the purposesof the Estimates and I do not think that we need discuss the matter further.I appreciate that this offer was made with reluctance. It will mean the postpone-ment of certain proposed new developments and, largely as a result of increased costs, will necessitate some reduction in the scale of departmental information workin certain countries and in certain media, such as films. But if the economies are carefully planned I do not think they will seriously affect our capacity to fight the&quot; cold war &quot; or damage our general prestige overseas.4. B.B.C. Overseas Services. The following figures show the broadposition:- B.B.C. Grant in Aid- 000s1947-48    .......      ............ 4,4001948-49       ................... 4,5001949-50       ............      ...... 4,4501950-51.................. 4,6851951-52-Provision originally proposed by OverseasMinisters............... 5,330*Reduced provision now offered by OverseasMinisters   ...      ............. 5,080*Reduced provision at present included in theEstimates................ 4,650*Whereas the other overseas information services have been reduced in scale andexpenditure since the war, theB.B.C. has been spared almost all such cuts and has proposed a level of expenditure in 1951-52 higher than in any year since a separateGrant in Aid for Overseas Services was provided. (Until 31st December, 1946, thewar-time arrangement of a combined Grant in Aid for Home and Overseas Serviceswas still in force.)5. There are probably three ways in which economies could be secured inthe B.B.C.&apos;s expenditure:  \a) I have little doubt that fairly substantial reductions could be achieved bygeneral economies of administration and operation (e.g., in programmecosts) without involving any major reduction of services.(b) It should be borne in mind that the B.B.C. Grant in Aid covers capitalas well as recurring expenditure and that during the current year a verylarge capital sum (probably more than  300,000) will have been spenton the new station at Singapore. The Estimates for 1951-52, as sub-mitted to the Treasury, showed that provision of only  50,000 on this account would be required for completion. This reduction of capitalexpenditure at Singapore should in itself secure an appreciable economynext year.(c) I also believe that some overseas services could be reduced or even abolishedwithout serious loss to the national interest. I do not say that any ofthe services are without value, but I suggest that the value of many ofthem is extremely problematical in relation to their cost and that thereis very little evidence that the heavy expenditure and effort involved is concentrated to the extent that it clearly ought to be on those countries and audiences that matter most. For example, we at present spen4.. something like  750,000 a year on broadcasting to Western european countries (excluding Germany), which in peace-time are easily accessible* Includes  100,000 for Civil Defence measures hot included in previous years.
by other less expensive and probably more effective channels of com-munication and whose listening audiences, it is generally agreed, wouldin any case be swiftly recaptured in the event of war. We are spendingalmost  400,000 a year on services to Latin America (the British Counciland Foreign Office spending approximately as much there again). I donot suggest that the whole of these sums would be saved even if these services were abolished entirely, but I cannot believe that there is noroom for fairly substantial economies here, or that these particular ser-vices contribute very much to the prosecution of the cold war. I do not know whether the proposals in paragraph 13 (i) of CP. (51) 53 are thebest that could be devised. They are certainly not the only possibilities.For example, the B.B.C. have stated in earlier discussions that  50,000a year could be saved by closing down the General Overseas Service (in english) during those six hours of the day when it is least used. a variety of other possible economies have also been considered and Iam not convinced, therefore, that the economies for which I am askingwould necessarily involve such steps as abandoning measures to counteract Russian jamming as is suggested.6. Even allowing for the provision of  100,000 for necessary Civil defence measures, my proposal represents a reduction of the B.B.C.&apos;s Grant in Aid by only about 3 per cent, as against 1950-51. This seems to me to be a modest demand in the circumstances and I have.no hesitation in asking my colleagues to accept it.7. British Council. I agree with the Overseas Ministers that the british council has now discontinued a large proportion of its most &quot; rarefied &quot; work andconcentrates, possibly to a greater extent than some of our colleagues appreciate,primarily on educational work (using that term in a very broad sense). But I donot think that it necessarily follows that all the present expenditure, still less theincreased provision which was proposed for 1951-52, is justified in present cir-cumstances or that a reduction of approximately 11 per cent, as against the 1950-51level of expenditure (which is my proposal) would damage the CounciFs work asseriously as is suggested, particularly bearing in mind that the Council is unfor-unfortunately no longer able to work in Russia or in most of the Eastern european countries and may not be able to continue in China very much longer.8. As with the B.B.C., I am not convinced that the CounciPs effort is con-centrated sufficiently on the countries and the people who matter most. Forexample, it at present spends more money in Egypt than on any other single country(about  114,000 net in 1950-51 Estimates). The next highest expenditure is in Italy(about  87,000 net). For South America net provision of  202,000 was made inthe 1950-51 Estimates. Important though all these countries undoubtedly arefrom a political point of view, I doubt whether expenditure on this scale, considered in conjunction with that of the Departmental information services and of theB.B.C., can be regarded as really essential against the present background of worldpolitics. I am certain that there are many parts of the world where the Council&apos;expenditure could be substantially cut without doing serious damage to the objectives set out by the Overseas Ministers in paragraph 2 of their Memorandum,and I do not think that a reduction of 11 per cent., as proposed, is excessive. Theresult would be to reduce very considerably the CounciFs cultural activities, to restrict the number of countries in which it operates from 63 to 48 and to limit its activities at home to 15 towns instead of the present 23. I consider that these reductions represent a reasonable measure of concentration on those countries and activities which are of most value to our national interests.conclusion. I suggest, therefore, that the economies which I proposed to the Infbrma-tion Services Committee, involving an overall reduction of less than 4 per cent, onthe 1950-51 overseas information &quot;ceiling&quot;&apos; of  10-5 million are, in our presentbudgetary circumstances, a small demand to make. Any lesser reduction in this expenditure would, I think, be very difficult to justify when compared with the many other unpalatable economies to which I have had to ask my colleagues toagree.1           - ! , : ;;l; :r       :%;,:7  .7 ,;v    HG:Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1. .28th February, 1951. -



</content>
</cab>
