<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/44/0 images: 473-478</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC M AJESTVS GOVERNMENT *&quot;      jPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1951 .-The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited,   lit is issued:for the personal use of .     .Svr   *JarVy^M^ ..............TOP SECRETCP. (51) 7113th March, 1951CABINETPOST OFFICE TARIFFSMemorandum by the Postmaster-GeneralThe certainty of a rapid change in Post Office finances because of increased costs, including the effect of wages&apos; negotiations, has caused me to re-examinepresent Post Office tariffs.I have considered what increases could be justified to the House of commons on grounds related to the needs of the Post Office, and my proposals are set outin the following paragraphs. They have been discussed with the Treasury, whofully agree with the line I propose to take.Inland Postal services . Inland Printed Papers. The present postage is Id. up to 2 oz. and \d. foreach additional 2 oz. (The rate was increased from \d. to Id. on 1st May, .1940.)This is a specially cheap rate for certain classes of correspondence, which are liableto deferred treatment in favour of fully paid matter. (Deferment does not alwaysoperate in practice.) The service is used for Christmas and other greetings&apos; cards,football pool coupons, business and educational material and books.The present annual loss on the &quot; printed paper &quot; service is about  5 million.My proposal is to increase the rate to l\d. for the first 4 oz. This would yieldabout  5,250,000 in a full year; the earliest date on which a change could be madeis 1st June, 1951, and the yield in 1951-52 would be about  4,550,000.Overseas Postal services . Outward Parcel Post-This service (to Commonwealth and foreigndestinations) is at present operated at an annual loss of about  650,000.* In 1940,when other increases were made, this service was exempted in the interests of UnitedKingdom exports. Large increases in some cases double would now benecessary to make the rates economic; the matter is under discussion with theBoard of Trade.4. Inward parcel post. On this service there is a loss of about  250,000 ayear. We are entitled to charge overseas administrations for our costs of deliverywithin the United Kingdom but have not done so to the full extent, mainly becauseof the political aspect of the large &quot; gift &quot; parcel traffic. (This traffic, in fact, carriesin addition a special reduction of 20 per cent, in delivery charges for parcels from* The postage rates vary widely for different countries of destination. Some present rates are: 	2 lb.	3 lb.	7 lb.	11 lb.	22 lb.	s. d.	s. d.	s.d.	s. d.	s. d.France    ......	2   0	 	3   0	4  0	6   united States    ...	 	2  0	3   9	5  9	9   9Brazil     ......	3   3	 	5   3	6  3	9   9Malaya   ...		2   3	4  0	6  0	9   940282 b
certain Commonwealth,countries.) Any changes in our &quot;inward charges &quot; wouldhave to be negotiated with the overseas administrations concerned.5. If the rates were adjusted to the economic level,* the yield in 1951-52would be about  500,000 on the outward service and  100,000 on the inwardservice. In a full year, the total yield would be  700,000.Inland Money Orders and C.O.D.6. Inland money orders. The money order service is at present run at a lossof about  400,000 a year, and an increase of the poundage rates is desirable inorder to discourage the use of this uneconomic service, especially for small sums.I accordingly propose to increase the present poundage t by 2d. at each step, witha minimum charge of Sd. for amounts up to  10. The proposed increases would yield  120,000 in 1951-52 and  160,000 in a full year, but the service would stillbe run at a loss.7. C.O.D. The inland cash on delivery (CCD.) service incurs a loss of 90,000 a year, and I propose to increase the present fees 2 by Ad. at each step,with a minimum fee of \0d. for trade charges up to  1. This would yield  50,000in 1951-52 and  80,000 in a full year, but the service would continue to incur a loss.Telephone Service8. Rentals. Telephone exchange line rentals were increased by 15 per cent,over pre-war rates in 1940. My colleagues will recall that in the Budget of 1949it was proposed to increase the 15 per cent, to 33J per cent., but the proposal wassubsquently dropped. These rentals, viewed in isolation, are heavily subsidised bythe rest of the telephone service, and an increase in rental charges might be justified on that ground alone. There is, however, another and more compelling argument for such an increase, viz., that rising costs will reduce the telephone surplus to about 4-2 million in 1951-52 and, with a loss of about  5-3 million On telegraphs, the telecommunications services as a whole will show a deficit of about  1 million thatyear. To meet this situation I propose to increase exchange line rentals to 50 percent, above pre-war rates,? equivalent to about 30 per cent, over present rates;* Approximate economic rates for countries referred to above are: 	2 lb.	3 lb.	7lb\	11 lb.	22 lb.	s. d.	s. d.	s. d.	1 s. d.	s. d.France    ......	3  6	 	4   6	6  3	9   united States   .....	 	3   3	6   0	9   9	17  GBrazil	6 0	  .	8   3	12  0	18   3Malaya   ......	 	3   6	5   9	8   3	13   3		Present Rates			f Inland money orders% C.O.D.Amount PoundageUp to  3......... 4d. 3- 10         ......      ... 6d.Each additional  10 up to  50 2d.jrade Charge FeeUp to \0s. Od.       ...... 4d.10s. Od. to  1        ...... 6d. 1 to  2      ......... Sd. 2 to  5      ......... lOd.Each additional  5 up to  40 2d.5 The effect of the proposed increase on the main exchange line quarterly rentals is shown below: PresentLondon  ...Birmingham,LiverpoolChester ...Other placesGlasgow,and   Man-Business*  s. d.2    0   10Residential   s.    d.1    9   111 17 5 16 51   13   11       13    0*Rebate of 2s. I0id. forsubscriber sharing a line.ProposedBusiness^      Residential^s.132 82    4* Rebate93of5s:s.191410Od.d.060forsubscriber sharing a line.
(the fates for subscribers&apos; calls, trunk, arid local, are already 50 per cent, above pre-war-war rates). At the sarne time, I propose to extend the rebate on shared linesfrom the present 1.1 s.6d.,a year to  .1. These changes would yield about  7  million in a full year. I also propose to increase the present rates for specially rentedcircuits (telephone and telegraph),\ now 25 per cent, over the pre-war rates, to50 per cent, over the pre-war rates, in conformity with telephone exchange linerentals. This increase would yield about  520,000 in a full year.9. There is a very difficult problem involved in increasing these rentals, whichrest on agreements between each subscriber and the Post Office, specifying the items of plant provided and the appropriate rental for each item. There are about million of these agreements, which would have to be terminated by due notice and replaced by agreements at the new tariff. The practical and legal difficulties involvedin undertaking this task were so formidable in 1949 that my predecessor proposed legislation in order to obviate them, and the plan to legislate was announced in theBudget statement. When the Bill came before the Legislation Committee doubts were expressed as to the expediency of varying individual contracts by legislation and the Cabinet subsequently ruled that, if the increase of rental was proceeded with, the normal process of varying individual contracts should be followed.(Doubts were also expressed about the expediency of the increases and they werelater abandoned.)10. The difficulties involved in terminating and replacing agreements are evenmore formidable now than in 1949. A closer investigation of the problem showsthat the staff costs as estimated in 1949 (namely  200,000) were much too low;they are now estimated at  800,000. This figure is based on the immediate recruit-ment of some 2,000 additional clerical staff and the provision of accommodation for them; and the work would take substantially more than a year to complete.I am satisfied that under present conditions this programme could not, in fact, be implemented and that, in view of the increasing demands on the national man-power, legislation is essential if any additional revenue from increased rentals isto be secured at any early date.11. In 1949 the plan was to increase the then rentals by Act instead of by new agreements. To do no more than this is to leave the same problem to be dealtwith every time there is a further alteration of rental tariff. I feel that this is a problem which should be solved now, in a way which would make changes inrentals practicable without a quite unjustified call on man-power and delay inoperation. One course would be to legislate to provide that, while existing agree-ments would continue, charges could be varied by reference to a tariff to bepublished in the London Gazette (with an appropriate period of notice), i.e., without going through the procedure of determining agreements and negotiating new ones.This course has considerable administrative advantages but may be felt to be opento much criticism in the House in the light of the history of the 1949 proposals.An alternative, though much more radical, course is to make the new approach ofterminating the existing system of individual agreements, save in special cases inwhich the arrangements are subject to exceptional conditions or specially assessedrentals. The plan in this case would be to send out to each individual subscriberconcerned due notice of termination of his agreement and to introduce legislation to provide that, save in the special cases, all service would rest (in the case of an existing agreement, after it had been duly terminated) entirely on the basis of statu-tory regulations, in which the rental tariff and provisions for applying it would be incorporated. In brief, we should go over to a system for rentals which has beenin operation for many years for local and trunk call charges. In this way, therewould be no legislative interference with agreements, though this might be by nomeans apparent to a public faced with a flood of notices of termination, however,tactful the accompanying explanation might be. Under both alternatives, thelegislation would doubtless be somewhat involved; either course would solve thefuture problem, but the second suggestion would be an entirely fresh approach which might escape the main criticisms of the 1949 proposal; it would also havethe political advantage of bringing the question of rental tariff changes directly under the scrutiny of the House. On these grounds I would favour it. If mycolleagues agree, I will have a Bill drafted for consideration by the legislation committee: if my colleagues feel that further exploration of the alternatives isrequired I will submit a paper to the Lord President^ Committee.12.  There is a substantial staffing problem involved even in the preparation and despatch of termination notices in the simple form I contemplate. On present40282 B 2
information I should hope, that it can be compassed to make the new chargeseffective from 1st October, but there are problems of printing, supply of envelopes,and so on. The time-table is very tight. To comply with the contract conditions, asubstantial proportion of the notices must reach subscribers before 24th June. Theycannot go out until the legislation has received Royal Assent and the Bill must bepushed through rapidly if this time-table is to operate. Work must go forward onall the remaining notices while the Bill is going through and their wording, Oncesettled, cannot be altered. If we failed to get the Bill by, say, the middle of June,this work would be wasted and we should still be faced with a very serious problem to print and despatch within the appropriate time new notices substituting1st January, 1952, as the operative date. I am having urgent examination given tothe staffing, printing, and supply difficulties. It may be that the risks of working to 1st October will be too great and I shall be glad to have the authority of theCabinet to announce the operative date for rentals as 1st January, 1952 if I cometo the conclusion that this course is unavoidable.13. If the operative date is 1st October, the yield for 1951-52 would be 2,550,000 for exchange line rentals and  450,000 for specially rented circuits: ifit has to be deferred until 1st January, 1952, the yield in 1951-52 would be  850,000and  300,000 respectively.14. Call office charges. Local call charges from subscribers&apos; premises were increased in 1949 to 50 per cent, above the pre-war level. No increase was madeat that time ki the basic charge (2d) for local calls from call offices and it has, infact, remained unchanged since 1923. I propose to increase the basic charge to 3d.;this increase would yield about  700,000 in 1951-52 and  1,550,000 in a full year.Inland Telegraph Service15. The present loss on this service is of the order of  5 million. The scope for increasing the tariff without at the same time adding to the loss is limited; butI propose to increase the present charge of Is. for 9 words with Id. for each addi-tionai word to Is. 6d. for 12 words with \%d. for each additional word. The greetingstelegram minimum tariff of 2s. for 12 words would remain, but additional wordswould be charged at \\.d. each. This would, it is estimated, yield  300,000 in1951-52 and  450,000 in a full year. These increases would involve legislation, sincethe new figures would be higher than the ceiling prescribed in the Telegraph Act of1943.Summary.  16.  Following is a summary of the proposed increases in tariffs:  Yield in Yield in1951-52 full year   Inland printed papers             (paragraph 2)  4,550,000 5,250.000Overseas parcels               (paragraphs 3-5)     600,000 700,000Inland money orders              (paragraph 6)     120.000 160,000Inland C.O.D.                       (paragraph 7)      50,000 80,000Telephone exchange rentals (paragraphs 8-13)  2,550,000 7,250,000Specially rented circuits     (paragraphs 8-13)     450,000 520,000Call office charges                (paragraph 14)     700,000 1,550,000Inland telegraphs                 (paragraph 15)     300,000 450,000Total   ......* 9,320,000      15,960,000The above figures refer to the cash yield; each total would be increased byabout  2 million if the revenue from services afforded to other Government Depart-ments were included.17. The Commercial Account forecast to be published with the Post OfficeEstimates for 1951-52 shows an overall surplus of  8-4 million, on the basis ofexisting wage rates and other costs. The actual figure may well be below  .1&apos;million, in view of the certainty of general increased costs and in particular of* This figure will be reduced to  7,470,000 if the new telephone rentals are introduced from 1st January, 1952, instead of from 1st October, 1951 (see paragraph 13).
Post Office Headquarters, E.C. 1,Uth March, 1951.further increases in the wages of Post Office staff, following on the recent changeof attitude towards staff claims generally. On a conservative estimate, it is thoughtthat wage revisions alone may involve the Post Office in increased costs of about 8 million a year and if, as seems likely, these revisions are back-dated to 1st April,1951, the full impact will be felt in 1951-52. On these figures I consider that I couldjustify, on general Post Office grounds, the inpreas^s proposed, above, which would yield  9,320,000 (or  7,470,000) in 1951-52 and  15,960,000 uTa full year. Thefigure on which the House will concentrate, however, will be the published forecast of a Commercial Account surplus of  8-4 million in 1951-52, and I shall be in some difficulty to express publicly the expectation that it is going to be so rapidly anddrastically reduced, mainly by new pay awards which have still to be negotiated.There may also be serious political difficulty in justifying adoption in one stage-of all the increases suggested, which make it appear that I am budgeting for a surplus of about  24 million in a full year. Subject to the views of my colleagues,especially on this latter political point, I would propose to announce the aboveincreases to the House as Post Office proposals, based on its prospective financialposition, and to couple with it a statement regarding the introduction of thenecessary legislation in due course. The announcement would of course precedethe Chancellors Budget.N. E.


</content>
</cab>
