<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/263/0 images: 105-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1936.SECRET.Copy No.CP. 176  (36).CABINET.ANGLO-EGYPTIAN TREATY  NEGOTIATIONS.THE SUDAN.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    I CIRCULATE to my colleagues the annexed memorandum containing thedraft clauses about the Sudan,  together with comments thereon.  I think the document  is self-explanatory.    In my opinion, it is  desirable that  this subject  should be considered andForeign Office, June 19, 1936.     THE provisions to be adopted as the basis of conversations with the Egyptian delegation on this subject were discussed on the 17th June with Sir M: Lampson and the  Governor-General, and a draft article, agreed upon as a result of the meeting, is annexed (Annex A).     This article is based on the primary consideration that the Sudan conventions of 1899 have led to the establishment of an autonomous Government exercising conjoint  sovereignty in the form of a trustee (mandatory) administration for the welfare of the  Sudanese people,  and that  this trusteeship must  continue to, be exercised by the present (predominantly British) regime under the authority of the Governor-General.  The same considerations have underlain the draft articles drawn up in 1930 and 1933, but these articles failed  to secure  acceptance by Egypt owing to Egyptian insistence on a clearer statement of what they claim to be their rights in the  Sudan, particularly as regards sovereignty, participation in the administration and immigration.  These alleged rights flow in part from a claim that the condominium agreements are not being  justly applied, but more particularly from the Egyptian thesis of a residual Egyptian sovereignty  over the Sudan, i.e..,. a sovereignty deriving from the original Egyptian conquest and undivided (if disastrous) administration up to the time of the Mahdist rebellion. The 1930 and 1933 articles are annexed for convenience of reference (Annex B).     Paragraph 1 of the present article  states, for the first time, the theory  of a trusteeship in the interests of the  Sudanese,  It is desirable to  establish  this principle, since Sudanese nationalism, if still embryonic, is, and  will continue to be, a factor which cannot be ignored.  And it provides an argument against any excessive Egyptian i sat ion.           ? -  -     Paragraph 2 is almost identical with the Sudan draft prepared in  1933.  Itwill be seen- that it differs from the final  British 1930 draft in  omitting thewords  &quot;without prejudice to- Egypt&apos;s rights and interests &quot; which were included in that draft under Egyptian pressure and in a last hope of reaching agreement.In  pressing for these words- the Egyptians  were no doubt  thinking of their; [13386]B
 &quot; residual  sovereignty &quot;. and with this1 consideration;in- their minds they will doubtless press -for them again. ,x But the phrase is ih&apos;-the;;opihion of the-legal adviser to the Foreign Office definitely dangerous to our position, implying as&apos; it does that .Egy.pt. h% rights and interests (unspecified)pother5!-than  those flowing from  the terihs iof&apos; the condominium oi;; the articles of the treaty, or that the condominium is ih some way inimical to those rights and interests.  It is suggested therefore that if as anticipated the Egyptian delegation  raise the point; it be proposed first that the word  &quot; statu?;&apos;-&apos; ih line      be changed to&quot; admihistra- tion.&quot;  If this  proves insufficient the following modification of the  first sentence would be put forward :  &apos;&apos; While reserving liberty to conclude new conventions in future modifying the status  of the Sudan,  the High Contracting Parties agree that the administration of the Sudan shall continue to be that resulting from the agreements of the 19th January  and 10th July, 1899.&quot;  If even this were not enough to.secure agreement,  a third possibility would be to insert the following sentence :  &quot; Nothing  in this article prejudices the question of  the ultimate sovereignty of the Sudan.&quot;   These concessions (the result of  suggestions put forward for the first time)  are of  form rather than substance.    They do  not prejudice the existing position, nor alter it,  but they are calculated  to enable the Egyptian delegation to represent  to their public that they  have in fact reserved Egypt&apos;.s &quot; residual sovereignty &quot; and given nothing away.  One of the accusations which nO Egyptian statesman dare incur is that he  has &quot; signed away Egypt&apos;s rights hi the Sudan.&quot;     Paragraph 3.-This paragraph, which is a new one, represents the limit of concession to which the Governor-General can safely go.  He is perfectly prepared to consider the appointment of Egyptians to high technical posts; but he cannot contemplate  any Egyptian  &apos;&apos; quota &apos;&apos; of officials, nor a mixed  political service, and he is ready to explain to the Egyptian delegation, in person, why, if efficient administration is to be possible, he  cannot agree to this  dilution of the political service.  It  will  be observed that  this article is  to  be accompanied by an explanatory minute designed  to empower the Governor-General to appoint other non-Sudanese (e.g., Greeks) if necessary to minor technical posts.     Paragraph 4 provides a means of securing the return of Egyptian troops to the Sudan in such-a way that the  Governor-General can  prescribe where they shall be stationed and in what numbers.  Sir S. Symes has no objection  to the presence at Port Sudan of  one Egyptian battalion,  or even two, as part of the general Sudan defence plan, more particularly as it is understood that it has now been  definitely  decided that two  battalions shall  be  the minimum British garrison,     Paragraph 5, as now drafted, represents, in form at any rate,  a concession to Egypt.   It has  been possible to  make it  owing to the enquiries which haverecently been1 carried out as to the possibility of mass Egyptian immigration.   The Governor-General is satisfied that any such movement is out of the  question for at least a  generation, as for that period, at any  rate,  there  will  be sufficient available land in Egypt. Moreover, Egyptians en masse  do  not wish to go to the Sudan for, amongst others, climatic reasons.  It is  pointed out, moreover, thatthe  immigration of Egyptians  is  unrestricted at  present, save  by existing regulations, and that the system is perfectly satisfactory. -  , Paragraph  6. was accepted in 1930, and is accordingly ^reproduced in the present draft for use,, if necessary.  It calls for no special observations.  -Paragraph  7 is:in  the  form  drawn up in  1933, and  is acceptable to the Governor-General.   The Financial  Adviser to the  Egyptian Government  has suggested that  it might be possible to induce the Egyptian  Government to write off the Sudan&apos;s debt to Egypt as part of a settlement, and has indicated a possible line of argument to persuade them  to do so.  In any event, the question of the debtwill not be raised  spontaneously  by the British delegation, but it is thought probable, that the Egyptians will raise it, as it was mentioned in the-1930 drafts.    Paragraph 8 deals with a purely technical question which should produce no difficulty as the principle embodied in the annex was accepted by the Egyptians in 1930, and the present^,) draft annex contains only technical improvements. t.-!  :I must, however, draw-my colleagues&apos; attention  to the following important point.; ; The provisions, which I am proposing with regard to the Sudan are at present headed Article 11, i.e., as one. of the articles of  the Treaty  of Alliance. This is the manner in which the Sudan was dealt with in the draft treaty of 1930. This means,  however, that the Sudan article becomes subject.to the provisions                               (l) Not submitted.                     .-.
[13386] of the revision article (Article 14).  At the  end of twenty years the Egyptians may ask for the Sudan, article, to be revised,, and if the United ,Kingdom and Egypt cannot agree as to the terms of the revision the Council of the. League, acting unanimously (or some other tribunal if the parties cannot agree upon one), decides in what manner the  Sudan  article might  be.revised.   Theoretically, this means that the arbitrator could decide in favour of such a radical change&apos; in the existing arrangements that Egypt became the active and the United Kingdom the sleeping partner of the Condominium.  At first sight this seems an alarming possibility. From the practical point of  view, however, I do riot think there is any great risk in accepting it.   The  League of Nations would be bound in considering the manner in which the government  of  the Sudan was.to be allocated as between the Condo- minium Powers to put in the forefront, the mandatory principle, i.e,., the interests of the Sudanese.  It  is  inconceivable that a Council  of the  League  acting unanimously could decide that the interests of the  Sudanese would  be favoured by the government of the territory being put into Egyptian hands.   This would seem to be even less possible in twenty years&apos; time, when the process already begun of teaching the Sudanese to  administer  themselves and  the  introduction of Sudanese into the administration  will have developed a long  way.  Moreover, Sudanese  nationalism  which  already  exists  is  likely  at the  end  of  twenty years greatly to have increased in strength.   Further, it  must be  remembered that,  if  we refuse  the  Egyptians  the satisfaction  which  they,  may  get on theoretical grounds and grounds of amour-propre from the fact of the Sudan provisions being subject to revision in this  way, we are refusing something which we offered in 1930 in  a Sudan article which the  Egyptians rejected as insufficient and the  Egyptians will contend that, in addition to requiring them to agree to substantial advances  in our  favour in the  military articles  (advances which can be justified on the changed  military situation), we  are also being more  exigent in regard to the Sudan than we were  in  1930 although no such excuse can be put forward.  In 1930, when the breakdown came over the Sudan, the disputed question was whether there should be a revision of  the Sudan provisions in One year or in the immediate future; no difficulty was made on His Majesty&apos;s&apos;.government - menfs side to the application to the Sudan  of the general provisions of Article 14. I  am informed by Sir M.  Lampson that it is more than likely that the Egyptian negotiators would feel bound to sacrifice the treaty rather  than to give way on this particular  point.  I  strongly  advise  my  colleagues  not to endanger the conclusion of any treaty,by. refusing on this point to agree to what  was agreed in 1930.   In twenty years&apos; time, owing to  the development  of the Sudanese, the whole  situation with regard to the government of the Sudan will necessarily have changed.   The risk,  which I do not consider serious for the reasons which I have given, is in any case  problematical and  distant.  The risks of no treaty are immediate.    If, however, my colleagues feel unable to concur in my view, I propose the following course as the best alternative, though I am not- optimistic about its going through.   It would  be impossible I think for the  Egyptians  to agree to delete Article 14 from the treaty even though,  in view of the fact that certain articles are made permanent and  the Suez Canal  article-has  its own  special provisions, there are  few  other articles of  the treaty to which it  can  apply. Further,  it would be  equally impossible, I  am convinced, for-them to accept an express exception in Article  14 removing the Sudan  article&apos;from.  its application. Therefore,  I would propose to remove the  Sudan provisions from the Treaty of Alliance  altogether, and to put them into a separate agreement to be concluded simultaneously  with  the  Treaty of Alliance.  The paragraphs&apos; bf &apos; the  draft Article  11 here  proposed  would then  become  separate articles in  a  separate agreement.   The separate agreement would contain nothing corresponding to article. 14,  but  would  contain a  provision under  which disputes  as  to  its interpretation, and application (as opposed  to its revision)  might*be submitted toan outside  body..  In this way&apos;,; the fact that the  Sudan&apos; a &amp;ja2a?removed&apos;fromthe effect of &apos; the revision  clause,  though  it  can.  hardly-escape the  Egyptian delegation, might be made less&quot; obvious to the genera! public&apos;  in:Egyptv; 7 &apos;-&apos;hi. fish;    I feel bound, however, to; repeat that  I can hold  out&apos; little prospect1 :bfitheEgyptians accepting this solution.  : If, therefore, Sir M. Lampsoii were to.be instructed&apos;to; propose  it, I think&apos; it essential that he should be  authorised to-fallback upon the Original proposal! -if it&apos; should be necessary-td^do so&apos;in orderi to avoid a breakdown of  negotiations.                : -u;:.-.;.:^    June 19:, 1936.      &apos;-    - &apos;  ^   &apos;   .
ANNEX A-                 ,    , -         Draft - Article 11.     1.  The High  Contracting Parties agree  that  the  primary  aim  of the administration, in the Sudan must be the interests of the Sudanese.     2.  While reserving liberty to conclude new conventions in future, modifying the  agreements  of  the 19th  January  and the 10th  July,  1899, the High Contracting Parties agree that the status of the Sudan shall continue to  be that resulting from the said agreements.(2)  Accordingly, the Governor-General shall continue to exercise  on the  joint behalf of the  High Contracting  Parties the powers conferred upon him by the said agreements.     3.  Selections, appointments and promotions of officials in the Sudan will in consequence remain vested in the Governor-General, who, in making new appoint- ments to posts for which qualified Sudanese are not available,  will  select suitable candidates of British and Egyptian nationality.(3)     4.  In addition to Sudanese troops,  both British  and Egyptian  troops shall be placed at the disposal of the Governor-General for  the defence  of the  Sudan.     5.   Egyptian immigration into the  Sudan shall be unrestricted except for reasons of public order and health.     6.   There shall be no discrimination in the Sudan between British subjects and  Egyptian nationals in matters of  commerce,  immigration or the possession of property.     7.   The  question  of  the  indebtedness  of the  Sudan to Egypt  shall  be examined with a view to settlement on  fair and equitable  lines so  soon  as the general economic situation permits.     8.  The High Contracting Parties are agreed on the  provisions set  out inthe  Annex  to  this   article  as regards  the method  by  which  international conventions are to be made applicable to the Sudan.                              ANNEX B.1.  1930 Draft Proposals originally handed to the Egyptian Delegation.    Article  11. While reserving liberty to conclude new conventions in  futuremodifying the conventions of  1899,  the High  Contracting  Parties  agree  that without prejudice to Egypfs rights and material interests the status of the Sudanshall  be  that resulting from  the said conventions.  Accordingly, the Governor-General  shall continue to exercise  on the joint  behalf of the High ContractingParties the powers conferred upon him by the  said conventions.    (2) If the Egyptians make difficulties about this text because of the omission of the phrase&quot; without  prejudice to Egypt&apos;s rights  and material interests,&quot; which appeared in an  article whichHis Majesty&apos;s Government accepted in  1930 and which  as at present advised  we think  itdangerous to accept now, the following suggestions are made for the negotiations.  It is supposedthat the Egyptian  objection will be. based  principally on  questions of  sovereignty.  The  firstsuggestion is to change the word &quot; status &quot; in line 3 to  &quot; administration.&quot;  The second suggestion,assuming  that this is not enough, is to recast the first  sentence to read as follows: &quot;Whilereserving liberty to conclude new conventions in future modifying the status of the Sudan, theHigh Contracting Parties agree that  the administration of the Sudan shall continue to  be  thatresulting from the agreements of the 19th January and the 10th July, 1899.&quot; Thirdly, if even this is  not enough  to obtain  an agreement, it is suggested that we might offer to  insert thefollowing sentence:  &quot; Nothing in this article prejudices the question of the ultimate sovereignty of the Sudan.&quot;    (3) It is intended that there should be  an - agreed initialled minute to this provision to theeffect that this provision does not prevent  the Governor-General occasionally appointing to minortechnical posts persons who are neither British subjects nor Egyptians nor Sudanese.
2.  Final  Offer of His Majesty&apos;s Government in 1930.     While reserving liberty to conclude new conventions in future modifying the conventions of 1899  and  settling  the Sudan question,  the  High  ContractingParties agree that, without prejudice to Egypt&apos;s rights  and  material interests,the status of the  Sudan shall be that resulting from the said conventions.  TheGovernor-General shall,  as one of the consequences of  the  1899 Conventions,continue to exercise, on the joint behalf of  the  High  Contracting  Parties, thepowers conferred  upon him by  the said conventions.                                3. 1933 Draft.    While reserving liberty to conclude new conventions in future, modifying the conventions of 1899, the High Contracting Parties agree that the status of theSudan shall continue to be that resulting from the said conventions. accordingly the Governor-General shall continue to exercise on the joint behalf of the HighContracting Parties the powers conferred upon him  by  the said Conventions.

</content>
</cab>
