<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/263/0 images: 219-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.                                                         Copy No.C.P. 196  (36).CABINET.THE MONTREUX CONFERENCE.  Memorandum by the Ijord Privy Seal, acting for the Secretary of State for                              Foreign Affairs.     THE Montreux Conference is developing  in a way to raise issues of widerscope than  could be foreseen when the  Cabinet approved the memorandum which the Secretary of State for Foreign  Affairs circulated  to them  on the15th June-4.e., just before  the opening  of  the conference (see  CP.  168 (36)),and which constituted  the instructions to the United Kingdom Delegation atMontreux.     2.  The Turkish desire to remilitarise the Straits has met with no opposition,but on the subsidiary question of the passage of warships through the Straits intime of war, Turkey being neutral, a  deadlock is threatened on an  important question of  principle.   The issue raised affects  not  merely our policy  in theEastern Mediterranean and therefore the Near East in general, but threatens to involve  the  Anglo-German Naval Agreement and thus our whole ship-building programme and our general European policy  in relation to Germany and France.     3.  The 1923 Convention provided that, in time  of war when Turkey wasneutral, the  restrictions imposed by it should not apply to any belligerent  Powerto the prejudice of its belligerent rights in&apos;the Black  Sea.  In other words, the1923 Convention allowed all belligerent non-Black  Sea Powers to send unlimitedforces into the  Black Sea..     4.  The Conference began its work on the basis of a Turkish draft, but thepresent basis is a revised version  of the Turkish draft prepared by the UnitedKingdom  Delegation and submitted to the Conference on the 4th July.   Thisquestion of the right of belligerent warships to pass the Straits,  in time of war when Turkey is neutral, is dealt with in Article 16  of the United Kingdom draft,of which a copy is attached  as Annex  A.  The general effect of this Article which was agreed upon with the Turks before it was submitted to the Conference-is that in  the event of a war, when at least one of the belligerents was a black sea Power, a non-Black Sea belligerent would be able to send through the Straitsunlimited naval forces unless Turkey considered her security menaced, in  which case she would have the right to close the Straits to all belligerent  fleets, providedthat she applied this measure impartially.    5.  This Article must be read in conjunction with Article 23 of the British draft (see Annex B), which is a general overriding clause reserving the  rightsand obligations of all the Signatories, including Turkey, under the Covenant ofthe League.   The effect of the two Articles read together would give Turkey theright to discriminate between belligerent fleets only if Article 16 of the Covenantwere being applied, or possibly in  the event of a war under Article 15  (7)  of theCovenant:8718  [13512]B                   Printed for the  Cabinet.  July  1936.
     6.  The Soviet  Delegation, in combination with  the  French and strongly supported by the  Roumanian Delegation, have now put  forward amendments(copies  in Annexes  C  and D)  to Articles 16 and 23  of the British draft,  theeffect of which would be that Turkey would be obliged to close  the Straits to allbelligerent warships, except those acting in virtue, not only of the Covenant,  but of any regional pact which  may now exist or be concluded in the, future  withinthe frameivork of tlie  Covenant, whether Turkey is  a  party thereto or not,- andirrespective of any pronouncement by the League.     7.  These  amendments, which the French, Russians and Roumanians havestrongly pressed, are designed  to  facilitate the operation  of the Franco-SovietPact and the Franco-Roumanian alliance and to a lesser degree the Balkan Pactby obliging  Turkey to discriminate in favour of the parties to such pacts.  Since,under the United Kingdom draft, Turkey would be entitled so to discriminatein cases where the  Covenant bound  or  authorised her to do  so, the object ofthese amendments is presumably to oblige Turkejr to discriminate in cases where(a) the Covenant is not applicable, or (b)  the question whether  it was applicablewas  uncertain because there had  been no pronouncement on the point  by  theLeague.     8.  The Turks much dislike this proposal, which they realise would impose upon them  the obligation to implement pacts to  which they themselves mightnot be parties to the extent of embroiling  themselves with the  Power against which the pact was  being operated.   They are, however, obviously  much afraid of the Russians and it  seems  doubtful  whether Turkish  resistance alone  will succeed in preventing  the French  and Russians from  getting  their amendmentgenerally accepted.     9.  The attitude which the United Kingdom Delegation has hitherto taken up is that His Majesty&apos;s Government will accept  a  provision (article 23 of  theUnited  Kingdom draft) enabling Turkey to discriminate between belligerents in virtue of the Covenant, that they might even agree to such a proviso in the caseof Treaties  to which Turkey herself is a party,  but that  they cannot agree toa provision which would oblige Turkey to discriminate  (in  cases  where  tho,&apos;Covenant was not applicable) in favour  of the signatories of mutual assistancepacts to which she is  not a party, more  particularly  when this  discriminationwould apply not only in the case of pacts already concluded, but in the case ofany  future  pacts,  the  scope and effect of which cannot at present be  foreseen.Opposition by His Majesty&apos;s Government, however, to the Russian amendmentsmay easily  lend itself to misrepresentation  of their attitude  towards regionalpacts in general, and thus to serious  misunderstanding with France.   HisMajesty&apos;s Government may find themselves accused in fact, M. Titulescu hasalready made the accusation of going back upon their previous  support of  theidea of regional pacts within the framework of the Covenant.  A special difficultyarises in the case of the Franco-Soviet Pact, since His Majesty&apos;s  Government havehitherto supported the French  view that  this pact is in entire conformity withthe Covenant.  But  the  answer is,  of course, that the question now at issue isnot  whether the  Franco-Soviet Pact is  in  accordance with the Covenant, but whether it  is right  that  the  new Straits Convention, and.  His Majesty&apos;sGovernment as a  signatory of  that Convention,  should place  upon Turkey an obligation to assist in the implementing of that pact, to which she is not a party,in circumstances  where there would be no obligation upon her  to act under  theCovenant, and thereby to commit an unneutral act.     10.  The matter has a very practical side, since, if the Russian amendmentsare ; accepted,  serious  trouble with  Germany will  almost   certainly follow.Germany, though not a party to the Straits Convention of 1923,  and never having taken advantage of the accession clause which would have allowed her to become a party, has always acquiesced in  that  Convention, which at  present  is not at variance with any principle of international law, and does  not&apos; involve Turkey inthe  necessity of taking what might  be regarded&apos; as unneutral action.   Notwith-stahding her; claim  to equality, of treatment, she^ may judge  it convenient toacquiesce1 in any new Convention which gives her reasonable facilities;!of general application to all  Powers, even though these may involve the diminution of thefacilities which she, again in common with all other Powers, has enjoyed underthe  existing Convention.   On the other hand, it seems clear  that the Russian
3178 amendments  are specifically  designed  by Russia,  France  and Roumania to discriminate against Germany. Further evidence of a similar design is provided by another Russian amendment, which proposes that the right of passage of war- ships through the Straits should be confined to &quot; light surface vessels,&quot; as defined in the London Treaty of the 25th March, 1936.  This amendment would exclude the German pocket battleships from the Black Sea in peace time.    11.   It seems clear that Germany will not accept without protest a conven- tion which can thus be interpreted  as involving  discrimination  against  her. Moreover, if the amendment  to  Article  23  which  the  French, Russians  and Roumanians desire, is inserted in the new convention,  Germany will regard it as a proof that the Franco-Soviet  Pact was simply in the nature of a  military alliance directed against her, and the  consequences may be extremely serious. Germany is already paying a good  deal of attention to the Montreux Conference. Misapprehensions (which steps have been taken to remove) on the question  of the passage of warships through  the  Straits,  as affecting Russia, recently led the German Minister for Foreign Affairs to warn His Majesty&apos;s Government that in certain  circumstances the  German Government  might have  to  invoke  the &quot; escalator &quot; clause of the Anglo-German Naval Agreement.   It seems doubtful whether anything which is being proposed at  Montreux  could  give  Germany a legally valid reason for taking such action, but the question is a psychologicalone, and the possibility  of a German reaction which might seriously afreet theAnglo-German Naval Agreement- cannot be ruled out.  At all events, should there be any discrimination against Germany, however much concealed,  in the  new Straits Convention, especially if His Majesty&apos;s Government subscribe to  that discrimination,  Germany will  interpret the negotiation of the convention as a further  step  in  the  policy of  &quot;encirclement&quot; and will take  an even  moreuncompromising and difficult line than she has already taken in European affairs in general.  The repercussions on European politics may thus be very wide.   . .12.   In such circumstances the question naturally arises whether steps should not &quot;be taken to  ensure that Germany is invited to join the Montreux Conference. It is clearly invidious that His  Majesty&apos;s  Government should be placed in theposition at Montreux of defending, as  against  Russia, France and Roumania,what is in the  main a German interest.   It is true  also that by sponsoring an invitation to  Germany His Majesty&apos;s Government may be advancing the causeof closer  German co-operation  in European  politics generally.   There  are,however, serious drawbacks.   There  is every reason to believe  that the other Powers represented at Montreux would refuse to agree to an invitation being sent to Germany, especially as, if Germany were invited, there is no reason why othermaritime Powers, who had nothing to do with the original Straits  Convention, should not also be invited.   It is also by no means certain that Germany  would accept.  If she  accepted, some of the advantages of inviting her to  the Conference would disappear if the Conference were to end in failure, and it is unfortunatelyto be feared that, if  Germany were to attend,  the Conference  would be only too likely to fail, since the probable result would be a Russo-German deadlock.    13.  The consequences of a failure of the Conference would in themselves be serious, apart from the German aspect of the  matter.  The effect of failure to reach agreement on  the first  occasion when  the revision of part of the peace settlement by negotiation has  been attempted would be deplorable,  and there is little doubt that it would be followed by unilateral action on the part of Turkey in the direction not only of re-militarising the  Straits but of fixing new rules of passage, not only for warships but for commercial vessels, entirely at her  own discretion and probably in a sense A*ery unfavourable to our naval and commercial interests.  &apos; It is thus important that  the  Conference shall if possible result in some agreement.    14.  If then the  French, Russians and Roumanians maintain their present attitude of trying to insert in  the Straits Convention provisions clearly designed to discriminate against Germany, Plis Majesty&apos;s Government may shortly be faced with a choice of  evils either  to break off the Montreux  Conference or to acquiesce in  the Russian proposals at the  risk of far-reaching  reactions on Germany, and on Anglo-German relations.       [13512]       &quot;                                              B 2
    15.  It is  clearly desirable to make every effort to  avoid so unpleasant adilemma and the  United Kingdom Delegation are at present endeavouring  tosecure the acceptance of a compromise.  Desirous as they are of facilitating theoperation of the Franco-Soviet Pact, both the French and Russians have shown some  signs of realising the objections to trying to bind  Turkey  by the  presentconvention to give effect to pacts to which she is not herself a party.   On thebasis  of this argument the United Kingdom Delegation have proposed  an amend-ment  in article  16 of the draft convention by which, in time of war, Turkey, being-neutral, would  only be obliged to discriminate between belligerents if her ownobligations, under the League Covenant or under a treaty commitment to which she herself was a party, were involved.   It remains to be seen whether  the Frenchand Russians can  be induced so far to retreat from the position they  have taken up  as to accept this reasonable  compromise.  If not, I  propose, before  askingmy colleagues to choose between the alternatives set out in paragraph 14 above,to take action in Paris, with a view to impressing upon M.  Blum  the grave risks involved in the  attitude which the French Government have taken up at Montreux,and of persuading him, if possible, to adopt  a policy which  will allow theMontreux Conference to be brought to a successful conclusion, thus avoiding, onthe one hand,  a set-back to the principle of  treaty negotiation by revision, and,on the other, some unfortunate action on the part of a resentful Germany.                                                                        H.    July 13, 1936.                                ANNEX  A.       Article 16 of netv Draft Convention (United Kingdom Draft).    EN temps de guerre, la Turquie restant neutre,  les navires de guerre et lesbailments auxiliaires jouiront d&apos;une complete liberte de transit et de navigationdans les Detroits dans des conditions identiques a celles qui sont  stipulees auxarticles 9 a 15.    Ces  conditions  ne   seront  toutefois  pas  applicables  a  une  Puissancebelligerante au detriment de ses droits de belligerant.    La Turquie aura toutefois le droit, si elle considere a un moment donne quesa securite pourrait etre menacee par le passage  par les Detroits d&apos;une  flottebelligerante,  dhiiterdire  le passage  de navires appartenant a une  Puissancebelligerante,   a  condition  que  ladite  interdiction  soit   appliquee  a   touteflotte belligerante sans discrimination.    En temps de guerre, aucune  des Puissances riveraines de la mer  Noiren&apos;etant belligerante,  le passage des  Detroits sera interdit  a tout  batiment de guerre appartenant a une Puissance belligerante.    Dans le cas ou rinterdiction de passage, prevue aux deux alineas  precedentsdu present article, aurait ete mise en vigueur, il sera permis a tout batiment de guerre appartenant a une Puissance belligerante non riveraine de la mer Noire,et qui se  trouverait  eventuellement  dans ladite  mer,  de  se rendre  dans laMediterranee.    Dans les conditions sus-mentionnees, il sera egalement permis a tout batimentde guerre appartenant a une Puissance riveraine de la mer Noire de rentrer danscette mer.    Les navires de guerre des belligerants  ne procederont a  aucune capture, ilsn&apos;exerceront pas le droit de visite et de fouille. et ne se livreront a aucun actehostile dans les Detroits.    En ce qui concerne le ravitaillement et les reparations, les navires de guerreseront sounds aux dispositions de la Convention XIII de  La Ffaye  de  1907relative a la neutralite maritime.    Les droits et devoirs de la Turquie, comme Puissance neutre, ne sauraientTautoriser a prendre aucune mesure susceptible  d&apos;entraver le transit et lanavigation dans  les Detroits, dont les eaux doivent rester entierement libres entemps de guerre, la Turquie etant neutre, aussi bien qu&apos;en temps de paix.
                                ANNEX  B.                     Article 23 (United Kingdom Draft).    Aucune disposition de  la presente convention ne porte atteinte  aux droitset obligations decoul ant du  Pacte deTa Societe des Nations pour la Turquie oupour toute autre haute partie contractante.                            ANNEX  C.                  Article 16 (Russian  Amendment).Remplacer les 2&quot;uo, 3&quot;1&quot;3 et 4*n,e alineas par  le texte suivant:    &quot; Toutefois il sera interdit de passer  a travers les Detroits aux batimentsde guerre et navires auxiliaires de tout  Etat belligerant, sauf dans les casvises a Particle 23.&quot;                                ANNEX  D.                      Article 23 (Russian  Amendment).    Les dispositions de la presente convention ne pouvant porter atteinte auxdroits et obligations decoulant du Pacte de la Societe des Nations pour les hautesparties contractantes membres de la Societe ou restreindre d&apos;une f agon quelconquela mission  de celle-ci de sauvegarder efficacement la securite des nations,  il estentendu que 1&apos;effet desdites dispositions et notamment de celles des articles 5 et 9a 16 ne sera pas de limiter en quoi que ce  soit la mise en ceuvre  eventuelle  des mesures prevues  par  le Pacte k l&apos;egard d&apos;un Etat agresseur ni d&apos;entraver lepassage par  les Detroits  des batiments de  guerre  en  execution d&apos;engagementsd&apos;assistance assumes ou pouvant etre assumes a 1&apos;avenir par tels Etats signatairesde la presente convention aux termes des accords supplementaires au Pacte, ainsique le passage des batiments  de 1&apos;Etat auquel cette assistance serait due.

</content>
</cab>
