<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/263/0 images: 375-377</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOGIJMSST IS TEE PROPERTY CP HIS BRITANNIC              MAJESTY&apos;S GOVJEEHMERT) .COPY HO.SECRET. CP.  215/36.                      C A B I M E T                         INDIA       Appreciation of the Political Situation,  by the Government  of  India,  dated 16th August,  1936 .       Circulated for  the  information of the  Cabinet by the  Secretary of State for India.
Confidential appreciation of the PoliticalSituation in India,  dated the loth August,1936,  issued on the authority of theSecretary of State for India.     The month of July has been uneventful and therehas been little or no change in the political situation.The news of the attempt on the life of His Majesty theKing-Emperor evoked indignation from all sections of thepublic,  and relief was expressed at His Majesty&apos;s escape.His Excellency the Viceroy, during his monsoon tour,visited Ranch!, the summer headquarters of the province oBihar,  where he was received with great enthusiasm.   HisExcellency&apos;s visits to villages and the great interest which he displayed in village life evidently made a deepimpression.  His Excellency the Viceroy also visited theStates of Benares and Rampur and made an importantreference to the subject of the All-India Federation,stating that all the omens, at present,  encouraged him to hope that no difficulty would be experienced in the next stage,  namely,  bringing into operation the federal aspect of the scheme,  and pointing out that the interval between the inauguration of provincial autonomy and theestablishment of the federation cannot,  in the nature ofthings,  be a long one.     An interesting incident is also reported from BengalHis Excellency the Governor visited the district ofTripura to attend the opening ceremony of the &quot;AndersonKhal&quot; (drainage channel) which has been excavatedentirely by voluntary labour,  and the Government of Bengalin reporting the incident,  observe that the impression
                                                    2.created by His Excellency&apos;s visit end the object lessonin self-help afforded by this enterprise, will be widespread and lasting.  In this connection it may benoted that, in distributing to the provinces the money available for village uplift,the Government of india have emphasised the necessity of getting the villagersthemselves to contribute, either by labour or money,to any work undertaken for their benefit.     Political leaders continue to be busy over the preparations for the forthcoming elections, but there areno developments of importance.   Certain Moslem agitatorspossibly inspired mainly by the desire of capturing votesat the forthcoming elections, have been endeavouring to enlist sympathy for the Arabs in Palestine.   At ameeting in Allahabad, resolutions were passed advocatinginter alia the boycott of British goods, but so far noattempts have been made to carry these resolutions intoeffect, nor have they met with much support.   There are some signs, though as yet not very definite, that theCongress party are endeavouring to make capital out of th.agitation end hope to enlist some Moslems on their side in an agitation against the Government, as they did at thtime of the Khilafat agitation of 1920-1921.   At presenthowever the orthodox Moslem is rather antagonistic toagitation ana the danger is potential rather than real.

</content>
</cab>
