<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/52/0 images: 241-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
grtJMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S G^)VTSRNMENT . )CABINET   14 (26),Copy No.Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at 10 downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, Maroh 31st, 1926,at 11,30 A.M,a 0 0 o o eAGENDA.LUXURY TAX.(Referenoe Cabinet 6l [2$), Conclusion l)Report of Cabinet Committee(CP. 39 (26)   -   already circulated)Memorandum by the Home Secretary(CP. 73 (26)   -   already circulated)Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, covering memorandum by Board of Customs and Excise.(CP. 98 (26)   -   already circulated).PUBLIC ORDER.(Reference Cabinet 48 (2J?), Conclusion 2).Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP. 136 (26)   -   already circulated).FORTHCOMING IMPERIAL CONFERENCE.(Reference Cabinet 8 (26), Conclusion 18).-Report of Imperial Conference (Agenda) Committee,(CP, 124 (26)   -   already circulated).EAST AFRICAN AND PALESTINE LOANS.(Reference Cabinet 7 (26), Conclusion 6).Note by the Secretary of State for the colonies on the Palestine Loan Guarantee Bill,(CP. 71 (26)   -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.(CP. 129 (26)   -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(CP. 130 (26)   -   already circulated)..Memorandum by the Seoretary of State for the Colonies.(CP. 138 (26)    -   already circulated).
J i    i !l  j,l  ill! &apos;: ! i, I21SEDUCATION GRANTS..Note by the Secretary, covering a letter addressedto the Prime Minister by the President of theBoard of Education,(CP. 134 (26)    -   already circulated).6.   THE UNIVERSITY OP LONDON,Memorandum by the president of the Board of Education.(CP. 133. (26)    -   already circulated).7-    INTERNATIONAL REGULATION OP HOURS OP WORK.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP. 137 (26)    -   already circulated).8.    IMPERIAL WAR GRAVES ENDOWMENT FUND BILL.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.(CP. 132 (26)    -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(CP. 14-0 (26)    -   already circulated).9.   HOME affairs COMMITTEE.Consideration of recommendations on the following subjects(i)   She Indian, and Colonial Divorce Jurisdiction Bill(ii)    The Post Office Sites Bill,(H.A.O. (26) 6th Cons.    -    Circulated herewith).TO TAKE NOTE OF10.    THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE (ANNUAL) BILL.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for: War,covering Draft Bill&apos;.   .      i      -(CP; 135 (26)   -&quot;&quot;&quot;already&quot; oiroulated).(Signed):   M; P. A. hankey,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens,. S.W.I.,30th March, 1926.
joCTjy;mXJIj3,.THB PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITAITNIG MAJESTY&apos; S GQVSPJMEIHT. )c_.AJLi.JL3 .-.5L-.14....(261*CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10,-Downing Street, S.W.I., on Y/EDHESDAY,March 31st, 1926, at 11.30 A.M,Copy No.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. StanleyPrime Minister.Ilhe Right Hon,Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P,, Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Ilhe Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G,,G.C.V.O. ,C , B , ,Lord Privy Seal.Ilhe Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt,,M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.JThe Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthingtoh-Evans,Bt.,G.B.E. ,M.D., Secretary ofState for War,Ilhe Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C.K.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Ilhe Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.[The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt,,D.S.O.,M.P., Secretary for Scotland.[The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland, Bt.,M.P., Minister of Labour.[The Right Hon.Vi3count Cecil of Chelvrood,E,G,., Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.Baldwin, M.P.(In the Chair)The Right Hon,Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W, S. Churchill, CH.,M.P.,- Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L. S, Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies,The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for India,The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C,,M.P,, Presidentof the Board of Trade,The Right Hon.,W. Guinness, D.S.O.-.M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries,The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E,, first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.- Sir Douglas Hogg, K,C.,M.P.,Attorney General.[Sir M,p.A.Hankey, G.C.B................................ Secretary.X Present for Conclusions 1 and 2 only.
1... The Cabinet had before them the Report ofthe Cabinet Committee on Public Order foPaperCP.-136 (26)), covering the draft of a&quot;Preservation of Public Order Bill&quot;.The Cabinet were informed that theCommittee did not propose that any legislation should be introduced at the present time.    TheirReport should be regarded rather in the samelight as Defence of the Realm Regulations, -to be brought forward if and when an emergencyarises and offers a favourable opportunity for legislation.On this understanding the Cabinet,took note of the Report of theCommittee on Public Order (paper cp.-136 (26)) .-1
IlliflB INDIAN-, COLONIAL.TION2.    The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for India (paper.A.. (26) 1)., stating that, as the result ofdiscussion, it was proposed to introduce thedraft Indian and Colonial Divorce JurisdictionBill, with certain alterations in the text setforth in the Memorandum, together with therecommendation of the Committee of Home affairs thereon (H.A.C. 6th Conclusions (26), Para.1).The Cabinet agreed  To authorise the Introduction inthe House of Lords of the indian and Colonial Divorce JurisdictionBill in the form of the draft annexed to CP ,-82 (26), subjectto certain modifications recom-mended by the  Committee of HomeAffairs.-2-
(Paper CP.-117 (26)) by the -Postmaster-Generalcovering the draft Post Office&apos;Sites Bill,&apos; theobject of which is to give the Postmaster-Generalcompulsory powers to acquire land and propertyadjoining the Head Post Offices at Blackpool,Done aster and Swansea, for the purpose of extending those buildings;    together with therecommendation of the  Committee of Home affairs thereon (.H.A.C. 6th Conclusions (26), Para.2).The Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction inthe House of Commons of the PostOffj.ce Sites Bill in the form ofthe draft annexed to CP.-117 (26),subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that may be foundnecessary or desirable.
a-.  The Cabinet had before them draft instructions-tions to the British Ambassador at Constanti-nople regarding negotiations with Turkey., circu-lated by direction of the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Paper CP.-142 (26)).The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that he had not included inthe draft instructions any reference to our intention, if a Treaty is signed, to &quot;reduce theImperial garrison in Iraq., as set  forth in cp.-120 (26), Para.5, but he had discussed thematter fully with Sir Ronald Lindsay, who under-stood the Cabinet&apos;s decision.    If any mattersof decisive importance should arise in thecourse of the negotiations which were not covered by his instructions, the Ambassadorwould ask for &quot;further Instructions.The Cabinet approved the draft instructions to the british ambassador at Constantinopleregarding negotiations with turkey as set forth in CP.-142 (26).
9&apos;ir:h)     eJC The Cabinet had before them the following documents relating to Luxury Taxation:-.&apos;The Report of a Cabinet Committee(Paper CP.-39 (26) ) :A Memorandum by the Home Secretary(Paper CP.-73 (26)) :A Note by the  Chare el lor of theExchequer covering a Memorandumby the Board of Customs and Excise(Paper CP.-98 (26)) :A Note of a Meeting of the TaxationCommittee (26) held on February 16,1926 (Paper T.X.-(g6) Is t Cone lus ions .)In the course of a full discussion :in regardto the particular form of Luxury Tax which Isthe subject of the Cabinet Committee^s Report(Paper CP.-39 (26)), the Prime Minister readletters from the Lord&apos; President of the Counciland the First Lord of the Admiralty.The Home Secretary asked the Cabinet not to approve the tax on the supposition that he wouldbe able to exercise his powers of stopping letters and telegrams directed to persons abroad forpurposes of evading the tax, since such procedure in this matter was open to very strong objection.After a full discussion the Cabinet agreed(by a majority)  That, if he feels that the finane ialsituation renders it desirable to go forward with this tax, the Chancellorof the Exchequer should have atithorityto do so on the lines recommended bythe Cabinet Committee (Paper CP.-39(26)), and that he would receive thefull support of the Cabinet.
6. The Cabinet had before them the Report ofan Inter-Departmental Committee in regard to theAgenda and organisation of the forthcoming imperial Conference, covering the draft of atelegram which It was proposed should form thebasis of a communication to the Dominions andIndia (Paper CP.-124 (26)).The question of British representation atthe Imperial Conference was reserved for later consideration.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancasterinformed the Cabinet that, at a meeting of theSub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial defence on Limitation and Reduction of Armaments on theprevious day, the High Commissioner of New zealand had asked that consideration might be given atthe Imperial Conference to  the question of whether,for purposes of Limitation and Reduction ofArmaments, the British Empire was to be considered as a single unit or as a number of separate units.The Secretary informed the Cabinet that thismatter had already been raised at the preparatorySub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defencereferred to in Para.9 (a)  of CP.-124 (26), andwas to be further considered.The Cabinet approved generally the Reportof the Inter-Departmental Committee (Paper C.P.-124- (36),  and  the despatch, by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and the Secretary ofState for India, to the Dominion and indian governments respectively, of a telegram on thelines of the drafts contained in the Appendix
to CP,.--1S4 (26), subject to thefoil owing: -(a); The omission from Paragraph 7 in telegram &quot;&apos;A&quot;, of the words -&quot;(4) diplomatic representation in.foreign  gn co unt rie s v   (5) thestatus of foreign Consuls inthe Dominions&quot;-.The Secretaries of State forDominion Affairs and India were asked to consider the advisability of sounding th3 representativesof the Dominions.and Indiainformally at an early stage ofthe Conference proceedings as towhether it was desirable to raisethese questions.(b) The addition to the Inter-Departmental. Committee concernedwith Economic questions, referredto in Para.9 (c) of CP.-124 (.26),of representatives of the Ministryof Labour and the Scottish Office.-7-
7.-  The Cabinet had before them the following documents in regard to East African and PalestineLoansA Note by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies on the PalestineLoan Guarantee Bill (Paper CP.-71(36)):A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Colonies (paper cp.-129 (26)):A Memorandum by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer (Paper CP.-130 (26)):A further Memorandum, by the Secretaryof State for the Colonies:, coveringan Opinion by the Law Officers ofthe Grown -on the question of whetherthe condition that- a &apos; guarantee wouldbe subject to all the money raisedbeing spent either in the UnitedKingdom or the mandated territory concerned would be consistent withthe Mandate (Paper CP .-138 (26)),The main point outstanding was as to whether these Loans should be raised through the CrownAgents for the Colonies, in which case thecommission would be received by the Grown Agentsto the advantage of the Colonies or mandated territories concerned;    or, insomuch as theywere guaranteed loans, through the Treasury andthe Bank of England, as in the case of Governmentissues.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That, as a matter of principle,stocks for which the BritishGovernment is responsible,byguarantee or otherwise, shouldnot be issued in any other waythan the ordinary way to whichthe money market are accustomed:(b) To take note of the Opinion ofthe Law Officers of the Crownthat the attachment to the Britishguarantee of the proposed loansof a formal condition that non-local expenditure should be inthe United Kingdom would not be inconsistent with the terms ofthe Palestine and East AfricanMandate s:
(c) Subject to the above, to approve, the proposed guaranteedloans .
B. The Cabinet had before them a letter fromthe President of the Board of Education to thePrime Minister,, asking that the Cabinet Committeeon Rating Valuation and Poor Law Reform might begiven an opportunity of cons idsring certain problems&quot;in connection with the method of substituting block- grants for expenditure grants on Education (paper cp. -134 (s6) ) .The Cabi.net agreed  That the- question of the substitution.for percentage grants of grantsindependent of expenditure for education, Health and all, othergrant services should first be explored by an Inter-DepartmentalCommittee to be set. up by theTreasury, which should be asked toreport not later than the end of Maywith a view to further considerationof the question by the Cabinet.
LONDONDiversity,JhjG&apos;S college,0 theimperialinstitute.(previousUeferenc 8:Cabinet 12(26), Con-elusion 5.)9. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the President of the Board of. Educationcovering a summary of the main recommendationsof the Departmental Committee on University ofLondon Reform (Paper 0.P.-133 (.26)) .The Cabinet agreed  That the President of the Boardof Education should be authorisedto state that the Government arein general agreement with theCommittee&apos;s recommendations and propose to introduce legis-lation to set up a statutory commission on the lines of theOxford and Cambridge Commissions .-11-
by the Minister of Labour reporting the Conclu-sions arrived at by the recent Conference ofMinisters of Labour on the International Regula-tion of Hours of Work in Industry (Paper C.P.-137 (26)).The Cabinet agreed  That this- question should be postponed to the first Meetingafter the Easter Recess .
11.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairsreporting representations from several of theDominion Governments with regard to the imperial war Graves Endowment Fund Bill now beforeParliament (Paper CP.-132 (.26)), and a Mote bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer expressing theview that the Secretary of State&apos;s memorandum is based upon misapprehension as to the natureof the Bill, which is shared by the Dominionsalso (Paper C.P.-140 (26)). &apos;.   The Cabinet were informed that in Englishlaw, in order to enable the accumulation of funds beyond a certain time, legislation was required, and, in order to provide an endowmentfund In perpetuity for the Imperial War graves commission, such legislation had been introduced and was contained in Clause 2(l) of the imperial war Graves Endowment Fund Bill.    On this therewas no dispute.The Bill, however, also made provision in clause (l.) for the appointment by the imperial war Graves Commission of Trustees of the Endow-ment Fund; in Clause 2(2) for the investment ofthe funds, and in Clause 2 (3) for the Audit ofthe Fund by the Comptroller and Auditor-General.The Cabinet were reminded that the Tmp9.ri.alWar Graves Commission was essentially an inter-Imperial body, and were informed that the repre-sentatives thereon of some of the Dominions hadprotested that, if one State were to insist onunilateral legislation, it would provoke other participating States to undertake similar
97.&apos;hi *3 ounilateral legislation, with results detrimentalboth to efficient ad^inis t rat ion and to the spiritof the Commission as an inter-Imperial body.It was urged that the Bill should be limitedto Clause 2 (1) , and that the other requirementsof the Treasury incorporated in other clauses ofthe Bill should be provided for by an additionalCharter, *-so far as they were not already coveredby the existing Charter.In the course of the discussion it transpired that, -if any difficulty was raised&quot; in regard tothe audit, the Treasury would be entitled, underthe terms of the existing Charter, as a conditionof each payment,  to insist on proper arrangements being made.The Cabinet agreed&apos; -(a) That Clause 1 and Clause 2 (l)  ofthe Imperial War Craves EndowmentBill are essential and must been acted:(b) That, in order to meet the wishes of the Dominions, the remainder of &apos;Clause 2 of the Bill should be dropped and that.,&apos; if further pro--vision is found necessary to meetthe. requirements of the Treasury,: it should be. made by SupplerrsentaryRoyal Chax^ter and not by legislation.
12.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of, State for War, covering the Army and Air Force Annual Bill (Paper C.P.-135 (26)), and approved the proposal of theSecretary of State to circulate it to parliament in due course.
13. The Prime Minister instructed theSecretary to record that the next Meeting ofthe Cabinet would he held on WEDNESDAY, APRIL14th.  1926.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,March 31st, 1926 .

</content>
</cab>
