<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/52/0 images: 292-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IMSITT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S government cabinet   IB (264.Copy No,Meeting of the Cabinet to be- held at 10 downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, 21st April, 1926,at 11,30 A.M.AGENDA.1.   THE REORGANISATION OP THE COUNCIL OP THE LEAGUE OP NATIONS.(Reference Cabinet 15 (26) Conclusion 2 (b)).Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.(CP. 146 (26)   -   already circulated.)1,    ASSISTANCE;TO NECESSITOUS AREAS.(Reference Cabinet J? (26) Conclusion 2).Memorandum by the Minister of Health covering Report ofthe Goechen Committee,(CP. 1^8 (26)    -   circulated herewith.)3.    THE TRAINING OP TOWNSPEOPLE FOR LAND WORK.Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.(CP, 1^2 (26)    -   already circulated.)4.    THE INTERNATIONAL REGULATION OF HOURS OF WORK,(Reference Cabinet 14 (26) Conclusion 10).Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP, 137 (26)   -   already circulated.)5.    THE LANE PICTURES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,(CP. 1J?4 (26)    -   already circulated.)6.    CONSinSRATION OF RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE COMMITTEE OF HOMEAFPAIRS ON THE FOLLOWING SUBJECTS;*1) Tho Secretaries of State Bill.2] The Wild Birds Protection Bill.[3, The Rating (Scotland) Bill.,4) The Unemployment Insurahoe Bill.(H.A.C. 7tn Conclusions (26)   -   61roulaie&amp; hGfrsrffiUh.)7.    PRIVATE MEMBERS1 BILLS POR FRIDAY, APRIL 23rd,  1926.The Moneylenders Bill.(Maj or Glyn,)The Workmen! s Compensation Bill.(Mr, Lunn.)fliitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,20th April, 1926.(Signed)   M. P. A. I3ANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.
touaaNT is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s goMmi,CABINET    18 (26)-.Copy Ho,CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,April 21st, 1926, at 11.30 A.M.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister, (In the Chair).Sight Hon.Ir Austen Chamberlain, K,(?,secretary of StateJr Foreign Affairs.(Post Hon.iie Marquess of Salisbury,,G,,G.C.V.Oe ,C.B.,ord Privy Seal,Sight Hon.iir William Joynson-Hicks,Ijt,,M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs,I;Sight Hon.[Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,l5i,,G.B.E. ,M,P., Secretary ofState for War,-Sight Hon.Sir Samuel Ho are., Bt.,C.H.G. ,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air,iEight Hon.loir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,ill.E, ,M.C,.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade,fcRight Hon.IIi Guinness , D.S,0. ,M,P,,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries,Right Hon.lord Eustace Percy, M.P,,President of the Board ofEducation, &apos;&apos; Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E., first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon,viscount Cave, G.CM.C,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon,W,; S, Churchill, C.H. ,M..P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L. S. Amery, M,P,, secretary of State for Dominion affairs and Seoretary of State forthe. Colonies,The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for India,The Right Hon.W. C, Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Sir John G-gilmour, Bt.,D,S.O.,M,P,, Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P., Minister ofLabour,The Right Hon,Viscount Cecil of Chelwood,K.C,, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster,The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.P.,Attorney General.m, p, A, Hankey, g.c.secretary
COUNCIL 1. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by%B LEAGUERATIONS. the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster containing proposals in regard to the re-organisation of thegviOllSfsvenae: Council of the League of Nations (Paper CP.-146 (26)).J.    1 cabinet lo25)  Oon- In the course of the discussion the Secretarylusion 2.)of State for Foreign Affairs informed the Cabinetthat he had told the Spanish Ambassador that inthe view of His Majesty&apos;s Government a new situation had been created by recent events at Geneva andthat the British Government would enter the Leagueof Nations Inquiry free of engagements to supportthe claims of any Power other than Germany to apermanent seat on the Council.The suggestion was made that, in the event ofany increase in the non-permanent seats on theCouncil of the League, the situation should be carefully watched from the point of view of thepossibility of a desire fo*r election to such seatby any British ^Dominion or by India, since this might lead to the question being raised at theImperial conference e .After considerable discussion, the cabinet agreed  (a) That the British delegate at theforthcoming meeting of the Leagueof Nations Commission on the Re-organisation of the Council of theLeague should base his attitude onthe following principles:-(l)  That the main object of our policy is  to ensure theelection of Germany as apermanent member of theCouncil:(ii) That, in present circumstances,the British Government do not favour any addition to thepermanent seats on the Councilother than a seat to Germany:-1-
(iii)  That the British delegateshould be at liberty tosuggest that the non-permanent members of theCouncil should be enlargedfrom 6 to 9;    of this number3 to be regarded as semi-permanent seats?   Statesoccupying them would retain their seats for three or fiveyears and be re-eligible atthe end of their term of office,The remaining 6 non-permanentseats would be tenable for only one year, or at any rateone term, and holders wouldnot be re-eligible for fiveyears after that;(iv)  That the British delegateshould have full discretion as to the precise stage ofthe proc eedings at which tobring forward the above scheme:(v) That any enlargement of theCouncil beyond 16 as an outside limit would be pre-judicial to the effectiveness of the Council, especially inview of the importance of retaining the principle ofunanimity:(vi)  That if any proposal is madefor abolishing the permanentseats on the Council, theBritish delegate should not take the lead in opposing it.If the proposal is opposed byother nations, it would besuf fic ient for him to pointout that the opposition of asingle member of the council or of the Assembly was sufficientto rule it out:(vii)  That any alterations in theCouncil should, if possible,be carried out without requir-ing the amendment of the Covenant,which experience has shown to be almost impossible to- secure inany point of consequence:(b) That in the Debate in the House of lords the same afternoon the Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster, without statingthat any precise Instructions had been drawn, should intimate in general terms that his attitude would be based on thelines of the instructions given to theForeign Secretary for the recent Sessionof the Council at Geneva (Cabinet 9 (26),Conclusion 2 (a).)    Lord Cecil shouldalso be authorised to state that His-S-
Majesty&apos;s Government consider that recent events at Geneva have created a new situation and. that they approachthis Inquiry free from any priorengagements to support the claims of any nation other than Germanyto a permanent seat on the Council;$nd to make clear that, apart fromthe Council&apos;s rule of unanimity, itwould be highly inconvenient if theBritish delegate were fettered by parliamentary ins true tions:(c)  That the entry of Germany to theLeague of Nations is a matter of .prime consequence to the peace ofthe world, and more especially soIn view of the Treaty being negotiatedbetween Germany and Russia, which,even though innocuous in itself, might lead to further developments if germany were humiliated by the rejection ofher application.    In these circum-stanoes the Cabinet welcomed the assurance of the Foreign secretary that he would consider whetherdiplomatic action in South american states or elsewhere could be used tobring pressure to bear on Brazil towithdraw her opposition, and took note of the fact that Sir Cecil Hurst hadalready been instructed to consider what steps could be taken, in the eventof Brazil remaining obdurate, to secureher immediate removal from the Councilin September, so that Germany&apos;s entryshould not be further delayed.
-4-the Minister of Health covering a Report of theGoschen Committee on Schemes of Assistance toNecessitous Areas (Paper C.P.-15S (26)).After hearing a statement by the Ministerof Health, the Cabinet agreed  That no specific Exchequer ass is t-ance should be given to LocalAuthorities of necessitous areastowards expenditure on Poor Relief,and that the Minister of health should be authorised, when thematter is raised in Parliament, tomake an announcement to this effect.
3. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries asking the authority of the Cabinet to the appointment ofan Inter-Departmental Committee to consider and advise as to schemes and methods of training.whichcotild advantageously be adopted in Great britain with a view to fitting (a)  adults and (b)  juvenilesin urban areas for employment in agriculture, either in this country or within the Empire overseas(Paper C .P.-152 (.26)) .-The Cabinet weire reminded of the risks in announcing the formation of a Committee, whichmight prove a first step leading irresistibly toan eventual heavy expenditure;    but the importanceof some kind of Inter-Departmental Inquiry Into aquestion which might have an important bearing onthe employment of displaced miners was not contested.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That a Committee should be set. up,under the Committee of Civil Research,to advise as to schemes and methodsof training which could advantageouslybe adopted in Great Britain with aview to fitting (1) adults, and (2)juveniles, from the urban areas, for employment in agriculture either inthis country or within the EmpireOverseas:(b) That the Minister cf Agriculture andFisheries, in consultation with other ministers concerned, should advise the Prime Minister as to the compo-sition of the Committee.
the Minister of Labour, submitting for the consideratioh of&apos;his colleagues the Conclusions arrived at by the recent Conference of Ministers of Labour onthe International Regulation of Hours of Work in industry  (Paper CP.-137  (.26)).The question was postponed pendingthe circulation of the proceedings at a Deputation received by thePrime Minister on the previous day from the National Federation ofEmployers&apos;  Organisations.
the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs inregard to the late Sir Hugh Lane&apos;s bequest of thirty-nine pictures to the National Gallery,London (Paper C.P.-154 (S6)).The Cabinet agreed - -That a Committee, composed asfollows -The Lord Chancellor,The Charcellor of the Exchequer,The Secretary of State for DominionAffairs,The Secretary of State for India,The First Commissioner of Works,The Attorney-General  should examine the question andreport to the Cabinet.
the Financial Secretary to the Treasury (H.A.-3 (26))covering the draft - Secretaries of State Bill,together with the recommendation of the Committeeof Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 7th. Conclusions (26),Para .1).The Cabinet agreed -To&apos;authorise the introduction forthwith in the House ofCommons of the Secretaries ofState Bill in the form of thedra-ft annexed to H.A.-3 (.26),,with a view to the passage of theBill into law during the presentParliamentary Session.
^T iNSURANOllit.-gviousabinet So25), Oon-7.   The Cabinet had &quot;before them a Memorandum(E.A.-5 (26))  by the Minister of Labour covering the draft&apos; Unemployment Insurance Bill, the objectof which is to extend until the 31st December, 1927,the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance acts of 1924 and 1925 dealing with the following ques-tions(1). The right to receive benefits, atpresent only, operative until 30thJune, 1926 (Unemployment Insurance(No.2) Act,  1924, Section l(l)).(2) The power of the Minister of labour to waive the condition that toreceive benefit at least 30 con-tribut ions must have been paidwithin a comparatively short periodprior to the claim. (UnemploymentInsurance Act,  1925, Section 2,extended this power of waiver until30th June, 1927.)(3) The maintenance, in connection with thearrangements under which Trade unions and other Associations of workpeopleare authorised under certain condi-tions  to pay out State benefit totheir members, of the existingcondition as to the scale of theminimum, benefits which the associa-tions are required to provide out oftheir own funds.    In the absence oflegislation the existing conditionwill terminate on the 30th June, 1926.(Unemployment Insurance Act, 1925,Section 5( 1) .):together with the recommendation of the Committeeof Pome Affairs thereon (F.A.C. 7th Conclusions (26),Para.2).The Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction in theHouse of Commons of the UnemploymentInsurance Bill, 1926, on the linesof the draft annexed to H,A.-5 (26),with a vl^w to the passage of theBill into law before the &quot;30th June,  1926.
8-. The Cabinet had under consideration a Memo-randum (.H.A.-4 (26)) by the Secretary for Scotlandcovering the draft Rating (Scotland) Bill, the main object of which is to simplify and unify the rating system in Scotland:    together with the recommenda-tion of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon(H.A.C., 7th Conclusions (26), Para.3) .The Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction inthe House of Commons of the Rating(^Scotland) Bill in the form of thedraft annexed to Paper H.A.-4 (26),subject to any minor or drafting alterations which may be foundnecessary or desirable, with aview to its being passed into law before the end of the year.
the ^ome Secretary (Paper H.A..-2 (26)) in regardto the Wild Birds (Protection)  Bill, together withthe recommendation of the Committee of Home affairs thereon (H.A.C. 7th. Conclusions (26), Para.4).The Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction inthe House of Lords of the WildBirds (Protection) Bill in the\form of the draft annexed to cp.-45 (26) as a Government Bill,on the understanding that the concessions outlined in the HomeSecretary&apos;s Memorandum (.H.A.-2 (26))might be offered, if necessary, toassist the passage of the Eill.
10. The  Cabinet agreed  That the Moneylenders Bill,  to beintroduced by a Private Member onFriday., April 23,  1926, should be supported, but that no promiseshould be given of parliamentary time in respect thereto.2, Whitehall Gardens, S .&quot;.*-&apos;. 1,April 21, 1926.
10. The Cabinet agreed  That the Moneylenders Bill, to beintroduced by a Private Member onFriday, April 85, 1926, should be supported, but that no promiseshould be given of Parliamentary  .time in respect thereto.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,April 21, 1926,
The envelope with its contents formerly placed atthis point in the volume was removed for examination by the Cabinet Office in August 1967, and is nowto be iound under the following reference :Cab. 23/90B

</content>
</cab>
