<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/52/0 images: 340-347</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C A B I N E T    21 (56).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10,Downing Street, S.1/7.1., on SUNDAY, Key 2nd,1926, at 12 Noon.PRESENTThe Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister (In the Chair).Right Hon.discount Gave,&apos; G.C.M.G.,rd Chancellor.Host Hon.e Marquess of Salisbury,3., G.C .V.O., C.B. ,pd Privy Seal,ftght Hon.ft. Joynson-Hicks, Bt.,Secretary of State forae Affairs.tight Hon.i Earl of Birkenhead,sretary of State for India.light Hon.!. Bridgeman, M.P., First&apos;d of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.The Earl of Balfour, K.G., O.M\Lord President of the Council.-The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, G.H., M.P.,Chancellor, of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart., C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary of State for air the Right Hon.Sir P. Cunliffe-Lister, K.B.E.,M.C., M.P., President of the -Board of Trade.light Hon.illegitimate Chamberlain, M.P.,lister of Health.light Hon.&apos; John Gilmour, Bart., D.S.O.,&apos;., Secretary for Scotland.tight Hon. * - :&apos;A. Steel-Maitland, Bart., ii.p.,lister of Labour.The Right Hon.V/, Guir.neas,  D.S.O., M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisher ies.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Cecil of Chelwood,K.C., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C, M.P.,Attorney-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT  \-The Right Hon. Sir W. Mitchell-&apos;   Thomson, Bart., K.B.E., M.P.,Postmaster-General.      (For Con.2),P&apos;A. Hankey, G.C.B.,Secretary,
5TT0ATION. 1.     The Prime Minister gave the cabinet particulars as to the latest developments injo the Coal Dispute, beginning at the point onelusionFriday evening when the negotiations betweenthe Government on one side, and the representativesof the. Trades. Union Congress and the Miners onthe other side, had broken down owing to the refusal of the Miners&apos; leaders (notwithstanding the efforts of the Trades Union Congressrepresentatives to find a formula) to commit themselves to agreement in the Report of the goal Commission on the Coal Industry .On the next day (Saturday, May 1st.) theGovernment had received two letters from theTrades Unioa Congress General Council.     Thefirst stated that the Executive Committees of theTrades Unions affiliated to the Trades UnionCongress, including the Miners&apos; federation ofGreat Britain, had decided to hand over to theGeneral Council of the Trades Union congress the conduct of the dispute, and added that theGeneral Council held themselves available ifthe Government wished to dlscuBs the matterfurthers     (Appendix I).The second letter offered, In the eventof a general strike in support of the Miners,to enter Into arrangements for the distributionof essential     foodstuffs.    (-Appendix n,)After some discussions between theGovernment representatives and the general council of the-Trades: union.Qpngress, it hadbeen agreed that conversations of an informalcharacter and of which no stenographic note
,,as to be taken, should take place between three representatives &apos;of either side.     The object of these conversations was to explore the possibility of finding some basis for negotiation, but theresults were to be entirely non-committal.     These conversationshad continued until the early hours of this morning.     shortly before the end, during k-an adjournment, Sir Horace Wilson had had a conversation with the Trades Union representatives, asa result of which, the latter had stated that their positionwould be correctly indicated by a statement on the following lines:- 1*15 a.m.2nd May, 1926.The Prime Minister haB satisfied himself, as a resultof the conversations he- has had with the representatives ofthe T.U.G. that, If negotiations are continued (It being understood that the notices cease to be operative) therepresentatives of the T.U.C. are confident that a settlementcan be reached on the lines of the Report within a fortnight.10, Downing Street, S.W.1.The words &quot;Prime Minister&quot; in the above formula of courseinclude his colleagues, the Secretary of State for India and theMinister of Labour, who acquiesced.Sir Horace Wilson had received an assurance that-this formula was intended to mean that, if negotiations were continued, In the view of the T.U.C. representatives the Miners1representatives would agree to negotiate on the basis of theReport of the Royal-Commission, recognising that this meantaccepting a reduction of wages.When the Prime Minister gave them a copy of the statementMr. Thomas said that he and his colleagues would not give thePrime Minister and his colleagues a reply until they had consulted with the T.U.C. full Committee and with the miners and if they came .back accepting $he statement they would comeauthorised by the Miners to -say on their behalf that the Minersaccepted the Report recognising that this meant accepting areduction of wages..
! jtaste/yeThe representatives of the Government thenagreed that the representatives of the TradesUnion Council should consult their ExecutiveCommittee, including the Miners, in regard tothis formula, and should return the reply inthe course of the day.    The proposal was thatif the formula should eventually result in a resumption of negotiations, these should beentrusted to a small Committee, composed, so faras the Government were concerned, of the Secretaryof State for &quot;India, the Minister of Labour andthe Minister of Mines, who would confer withrepresentatives of the Trades Union Council, both sidesaccompanied by experts. This would free thePrime Minister to deal with the situation as awhole including his Parliamentary responsibilities.After a statement by the Secretary of Statefor India, in support of the Prime Minister^remarks, a general discussion took place.   ^Theigeneral view of the Cabinet was that the aboveformula was too vague and indefinite, and gaveJno assurance that the proposed negotiations were co/by\ His, Majesty,\ l* he     hikely bo lead bo a successful issuej   and-thattaken in conjunction with the menace of a general strike, it would be regarded by public opinon as a yielding by the Government to threats.   &apos;It was felt that negotiations Involving thepayment of a subsidy ought not to be resumedwithout a definite answer from the Miners inregard to their acceptance of the Report of theRoyal Commission, which, of course, would commit
the Miners to mal.ce some sacrifice as indicatedin that Report.It was assumed that in any event thecoinplete withdrawal of the threat of a general strike was sine qua non to any resumptionof negotiations involving a subsidy.As regards the letter In Appendix II, thegeneral opinion of the Cabinet was that itshould either not be answer/ered at all, or elsea very stiff reply should be sent.     suggestions were made.that in the event of a general strike, legislation should at once be introduced,either to make a secret ballot necessary,and/or that in the event of a sympatheticgeneral strike, as now contemplated, legislation should be introduced to remove the Immunityof strike funds,/and to make picketing illegalThe subject was adjourned, pending thereceipt of the reply from the Trades union council, and the Prime Minister asked theCabinet to meet again at 4 p.m. (subsequentlyadjourned to 5 p.m. owing to the receipt ofa communication that the Trades Union council could not reply until after 4 p.m.)in such cases
0 TKANSPORTIIIOllS120conslusion2.     The Cabinet had a short discussion in regard to the present position of the Supplyand Transport organisation.     The PostmasterGeneral informed the Cabinet that no localdif Acuities had, as yet, arisen.     Therepresentatives .of the Trades Union council had Informed the Prime Minister1 and his colleagues on the previous day that they had as yet passedno formal resolution in favour of a general strike, but the Postmaster General stated thathe had information that telegrams calling forthe cessation of work had been sent to therailway men, the transport workers, therailway clerks and the iron and steel workers.The general feeling of the Cabinet wasthat the dispatch of these telegrams constituted a new factor, which had an important bearing onthe discussion referred to in Conclusion 1.The Cabinet agreed:-(a) That the Postmaster General, as ChiefCivil Commissioner, should communicate to the Prime Minister copies of the telegrams which had been sent by theTrades Unions in connection with theorder for a general strike?(b) That the Chief Civil Commissioner should consult the Cabinet again later In theday as to any further instructions he required.2* Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.2nd May,  1926.
SKiTTBAlffiE. UNION OOUG2BSS GBNiKEAX COUNOIX32, i^aclastoa Square,LONDON, S*V-. 1.1st May, 1926.3be Bt. Hon&apos;Stanley Baldwin, M*P.,10. Downing Street,Whit shall, S,W. 1.Daer Sir,Mining Lopk-out.I have to advise you that the Executive Qomaitteesof the Trade . Unions affiliated to the Trades Union Congress,including the Miners1 Federation, of Great Britain, havedecided to hand over to the General Council of the TradesUnion Congress the coduct&amp;at of the dispute; and the negotiations in connection therewith will be undertaken by tha general council *s I am direoted to say that tha General Councilaill hold themselves available at any moment should theGovernment desire to dlacuss the matter further.^ours faithfully,(SIGNjjJD-)      V/ADTUB M* CITBXNiJ.Aating Seo rotary s
THliJ TRADES UNION CONGRESS G&amp;MtfRAl. COUNCIL,32, JSocleston Square,3*W.    la1st May, 1926.8Kt. Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P..) Downing Street,itahall, 3.W. 1.r Sir,Mining Look-out - iiaaenti&amp;l ffooa-atuffs.I am directed to inform you that in the event the strike of Unions affiliated to the Trades Union Congressing place In support of the Minors, who have teen lookedt, the General Council Is prepared to enter into arrangemontarthe distribution of essential food-stuffs.Should the Government desire to diaouss the matter ,th the General Council they are available for that purpose.The General Council will bo glad to learn your wishesthis respact.Yours faithfully,WALTBH M. CITHINE.Aoting Secretary.

</content>
</cab>
