<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/52/0 images: 359-367</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS THIS PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAillJIO MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERHMEIIT)COPY NO.CAB IIEI   24 (26).Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at No. 10, Downing. Street,S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, May 5th, 1926, at 11 a.m.A G E N D U M.-1.     THE INDUSTRIAL CRISIS.fa) Proposed Circular to Boards of Guardiansrespecting scales of relief during the &quot;Strike.Memorandum by the Minister of HealthCP. 184f26)   -     Already circulated.fb) Provision of meals to children by LocalBaucation authorities memorandum by the president of the Board of EducationCP. 181(26)   -   Already circulated.(c) The Coal Crisis and re-organ is at ionMemorandum by the President of the Board of EducationCP. 183(26)   -   Already circulated.(Signed)    M.P.A. Hankey,Secretary-y,    Cabinet.foitehall Gardens, S.Y/.1.5rd 1% , 1926.
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS: BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)Copy No,CABIN E ^Z^JZ&amp;X.MEETING of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, 3.W.1,on Wednesday, May 5th, 1926, at 1-1.0 a.m.&quot;PRESENT:-The Rf. Hon.. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister   . (In the Chair).fbe Rt. Hon.. The Earl&apos;of Balfour,K.G., O.M., Lord Presidentof the Council.IteRt. Hon. W.S. Churchill, C.H.H.I., Chancellor of thekchequer.Ibe -Bt. Hon. L.S. Amery, M.P. ,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and theColoni es.The St. Hon. The Earl ofBirkenhead,  Secretary ofState for India.fhe Rt. Eon. &quot;W.C. 3ridgeman,M..p. ^Tirst Lord of the Admiralty.Ice Rt. Hon. Neville Chamberlain,M.P., Minister of Health.Iha Rt. Hon. Sir John Gilmour,Bt. ,13. 3.0. ,m. P.,  Secretaryfor Scotland. ...?fee Rt. Hon. Sir Arthur Steel-Haitians, Bt., ML.P.,Minister of Labour.le Rt. Hon. Viscount Cecil of-Chelwood, K.C., Chancellor ofthe Luchy of Lancaster.The Most Hon.  The Marquess of&quot;Salisbury, K.G. jG.C&apos;V.0. ,C.B. ,Lord Privy Seal.The Rt. Hon. Sir William Joynson-Hicks, Bt. , M.P. ,  Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Rt. Hon. Sir Laming Viforthing-ton-Evans, Bt. ,G.B.E.&quot;,M.P. %Secretary of State for War.   .The Rt. Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, BJfc-C.M.G., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Rt. Hon. Sir P. Cunliffe-Lister, K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P.,President of the Board, of trade the Rt. Hon. Walter 3. Guinness,D.S.O. ,M.P. , Minister of.Agriculture and Fisheries.The Rt. Hon. Lord Eustace Percy,M.P.,  President of the Boardof Education.The Rt. Hon. Viscount Peel,G.B.S., First Commissioner of Works.The Rt. Hon. Sir Douglas Hogg,K.C.,M.P., Attorney-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:The Rt. Hon. Sir W. Mitchell-Thomson, Bt. ,K.B.E., M.P., Postmaster-General.(For Conclusion 5).It.-Col.  Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B................ Secretary-
ipilATION 1. The Prime Minister informed his colleaguesHIS MAJESTYfjNG. that, in view of the failure&apos; of the Press,  theKing wished during the present industrial unrestto see one of His Majesty&apos;s Ministers daily.Colonel Sir Ronald Waterhouse, the PrimeMinister&apos;s Private Secretary, has undertaken tomake the necessary arrangements.-1-
ij,ES OP RFLIBP 2. The Cabinet bad before them a MemorandumTMG THEtlicE. by the Minister of Health in regard to a circularcular to which he proposed to issue in order to give some,rds ofjrdians . guidance to Eoards of Guardians respecting scales of relief during the strike (Paper CP.-184 (36)).vious&apos;jrence: The Minister of Health&apos;s proposal was that theinet 27). Con- best solution on the present occasion would be tosion 3 .)direct the attention of Guardians to the rates ofUnemployment Benefit as being appropriate to theordinary case where the award of relief covers -the man as well as the wife, and the children and where no conditions of exceptional need arepresent.   Where, however, the man is debarred from relief by reason of the Merthyr TydfilJudgment, the ordinary Unemployment Benefit of5/-s per week to the woman and 2/-s a week foreach child would be inadequate.    In these caseshe proposed that where no conditions of excep-tional need exist       the woman and each child may receive a maximum of 12/-s and 4/-s per weekrespectively, and to defend those figures  (l) by reference to the allowance of 12/-s per weekordinarily paid to an. insured woman, and (2) as representing a rather more liberal payment than was found reasonable in 1921, when allowance ismade for the fall.in the cost-of-living figuress inc e the n.The discussion showed that the main diffi- .culty in this matter was to adjust the rates of relief In such a way that the families of men on strike should not receive more than those of menin receipt of Unemployment Benefit.
The general view was that the precedent o1921 was very valuable, and the Cabinet agreedTo approve the proposals of theMinister of Health in C.P.-184 (26).
PROVISION OFKBAliS to children BYL0CAL EDUCA-TION AUTHOR!-TIBS.3. The Cahinet had before them a Memorandum bythe President of the Board of Education in rega3?to  the pro vi si on of meals to children by LocalEducation Authorities during the present industrial unrest (Paper CP.-181 (26)).The proposal of the President of the Boardof Education was that administrative action directed to individual Local Authorities, and concentrated upon those Authorities who appeared to be exceedingor abusing their powers, was preferable.to theissue of any general circular, and that wheneversuch action was necessary the following conditionof grant should be strictly insisted upon:-(a) The proper selection of children,with a view to the elimination ofthose who are not in fact necessi-tous:(b) Adequate co-operation with theGuardians and other reliefagencies, including arrangementsfor the recovery of the cost whichshould properly be borne by suchagencies:(e) .The elimination of any excessiveexpenditure.The Cabinet approved the proposals of the.President of the Board of Education as summarised above and set forth fully in CP.-181 (26) .
4. The attention of the Cabinet was drawn, as amatter of urgency, to an article which had appeared in a newspaper on the previous  day which was tanta-mount to an invitation or an incitement to sympathetic-thisers with the general strike to cause &quot;oscilla-tion&quot; and so to interfere with the circulation ofGovernment information and notices by means of wireless broadcasting, which was contrary to the regulation issued on Vay 3rd. under the authorityof the Emergency Proclamation.There was no difference of opinion in theCabinet that, provided the Attorney-General was satisfied that the law had been violated, the HomeSecretary should have authority to take appropriate action in regard to the said newspaper.   there appeared to be some doubt, however, as to whetherthe newspaper in question had not ceased pub lie a-tion.The Cabinet gave the Home secretary and the Attorney-General, in con-sultation with the Prime Minister,full authority to take appropriate action against any newspaper that had transgressed the law.
INDUSTRIAL 5. The Cabinet discussed generally the emergency[SIS.measures taken to deal with the situation createdSupply and       by the general strike.j,igport . The Cabinet were Informed that racing had,anisationalready been stopped.    There was general agreementivdous that cricket should not  be stopped.-   The particu-&apos;jrenc e:inet 22 lars of the latest information did not differ), Con-3gion 2.) materially from the latest Strike Bulletin.   Asregards food prices the Cabinet were informed that satisfactory arrangements had been made by thePresident of the Board of Trade rfith the heads ofthe principal sections of the food trade in london in regard to prices, the only difficulty outstandingbeing with certain American interests who controlledthe chilled beef trade.. The Prime Minister informed his colleagues that the letter of May 1st. from the Trades UnionCongress General Council, offering to enter intoarrangements forthe distribution of essential foodstuffs (Cabinet 21 (26), Appendix II), had notbeen and would not be answered, but had been referred to by the Chancellor Of the Exchequer inhis speech in the House of Commons on Monday, May3rd.    Reports were mentioned of the interruption of motor traffic in Fast London, and the mostimportant question at the moment was felt to beto  increase the number of Special Constables, andit was suggested that special efforts should be concentrated on the recruiting of young and vigorousmen for this purpose.The Secretary of State for Warundertook to co-operate with theHome Secretary in stimulating the recruiting of Special Constables.The suggestion was made that if the Governmentwould make it abundantly clear that loyal Trade
Whitehall Gardens, S.W,1,May 5, 1926.-7Unionists would be guaranteed against victiroisa-tion by their Trades Unions it would have a valuable effect.The above matters were left tothe Supply and Transport Oom-nilttea, which was about to meet.

</content>
</cab>
