<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/52/0 images: 415-416</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY-0? HIS BRITANNIC .f.iAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).Copy No.CABINET.__10  (26).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held inthe Prime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons,6&apos;n WEDNESDAY, May 12th,  1926, at 2.30 p.m.PRESENT :-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.Prime Minister. (in the Chair).3 Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,IvloP., Secretary of State \for Foreign Affairs.e Right Hon.The&quot;Earl of Balfour, K.G.,P.M., Lord President of theCouncil.ie Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.H., M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.5 Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.3 Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for India.i Kight Hon.W.C.  Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.; Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt., D,&apos;S.O.,M.P.,  Secretary for Scotland.I Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt., M.P., Minister ofLabour.The Right Hon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord chancellor.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G., G.O.V.O.,  C.B.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.., M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bt., G.B.E., M.P.,  Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt,, C.M.G.M.P., Secretary of Statefor Air.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-LIster,K.B.E., M.C., Mo P., Presi-dent of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.W. Guinness, D.S.O., M.P., .Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K?Q*.r !W.P. .Attorney-General.
THE INDUSTRIAL The Prime Minister gave the Cabinet an account situation.of a meeting he and some of his colleagues had hadThe decision of the same morning with the Committeo of the Trades,the T.U.C. tocall off the      Union Congress Counoil in the oourse of which thegeneral strike.latter had announced the unconditional and immediate[previous reference withdrawal of the General Strike Notices,     TheCabinet 29(26)Conclusion 2)    T.U.C. Committee had asked him to assist by askingemployers to make the position as easy and smoothas possible and he had replied to the effect thatthe point was one which he must consider (forparticulars see CP. 1$5 (26)).In the course of a short meeting the cabinet agreed:-(a) That the recruiting of Special Constablesand Volunteers should cease;(b) That in other respects the emergency arrangements should be retained for themoment pending the results of the orders to call off the General Strike;(c) To approve of the general lines of thestatement whioh the Prime Minister wasabout to make in the House of Commonsannouncing the unconditional withdrawalof the strike;    stating that he was immediately taking into consideration the question of how to resume negotiations in regard to the coaldispute;    and adding that it was a victory for the common sense of a united British people, that now it wasnecessary to look not behind, but ahead,in no spirit of malice or vindiotiveness;(d) That the Prime Minister and those Membersof the Cabinet who had assisted him inregard to the coal dispute, should atonco consider the question of further negotiations with the miners;(e) That the Cabinet should meet to considerthe coal negotiations and other questions on Thursday, Kay 13th, at 11,0 a*meat 10 Downing Street.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.12th May, 1926.

</content>
</cab>
