<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/46/0 images: 2-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 \ I- -    .air-11!.-(This Document is the Property of Hjg jfritannjo    bvMajesty&apos;3 Government.)&apos; 0 &amp;-&quot;5 E C R E T - COPY No.  rj^-i^cabinet 89 (33) .Meeting of the Cabinet to &quot;be held at 10,Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY, May 30,1985,- at 11-30 a.m.A G E N D A.11.SO a.m.......1. RENT AND MORTGAGE RESTRICTIONS BILLReference: Cabinet 28T23), Concl. 4Memo, by the Minister of Health covering draft Bill-(CP, 243- already circulated)Reference: H.A,C 11(23) 3,2. PARLIAMENTARY CANDIDATURE OP STATE SERVANTS.Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP. 234(23) - already circulated)3. VALUATION AND RATING REFORMSecond Interim Report of Committee.(C,P..230(23) - already circulated)4.  TO TAKE NOTE OF AMD AffPROVE(a) Conclusions of Meetinp of ministers held on Thursday, 24th May, 1923.(b) AGRICULTURAL RASES IH SCOTLANDHsiao, by the Secretary of State for   &apos;Home Affairs.(CP.252(23) - already circulated)- (Sgd.) Me p e A,H ASK3Y,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W./1 Secretary, Cabinet,28th May. 1923
SHIS DOCUMENT.IS THE PROPERTY 0? HIS Brownie MAJESTY&apos;o CQVERHHSMT)secret cabinet      9( 3)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10,Downing Street, S.&quot;./l onWednesday, 30th May, 1923 at 11.30 a.m.COPY HO.PRE3ENT:-The Prime Minister   fin the Chair)5he Most Hon.the wiarquese of Salisbury, It. G. *G.C.V.O., 0,3., Lord Presidentof the Council.the Rt.Hon.W.C.Briaxeman, M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.His grace the Duke of Devonshire, K.G.,G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.the Rt.Hon.Lord Robert Cecil, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.&apos;3Ehe Most Hon.the Marquess Curzon of Kedleston,IC. Go , G.C.S.I.,  G. C. I oEo secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.She Rt0Hon.the Earl of Derby, K.G., G.C.B.,G.C.V.O., Secretary of Statefor %r,She Rt.Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.E., Secretaryof State for India,The Rt,Hon.L. S.Ame ry, M.P., Fi rs t Lo rdof the Admiralty..&apos;2he Rt.Hon.Seville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.She Rt.Hon.Sir Robert Sanders, Bt., M,P,,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Rt.Hon,Vi discount Novar, G. C     G,,Secretary for Scotland,She Rt.Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., C.M.G,,M.P., Secretary of State forAir.The Rt.Hon,Sir Philip Lloyd-Greame, K.B.E.,M.C, M,j?,f President of theBoard of Trade.The Rt.Hon.E.Fi.L. Wood, M.P.    Presidentof the Board of Education.The Rt.Hon.Sir Monta ue Bar 1 owing , IC.B.E. ,M.P., Minister of 1st) our.Ihe Rt.Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bt., G.B.E. , II. P.,&quot; Postmaster-General.The Rt .Hon.Sir W. Joynson-Kiclcs, Bt. , M.P.,Financial Secretary to the Treasury.Sir M,P.A.Hankey, G.C.B...................................... Secretary,
(This Document is the Property of His BritannicMajesty&apos;s Government.)- SECRET -CABINET 29 (23)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,held at 10, Downing Strest, S.W.1, onWEDNESDAY, MAY 30, 1923, at 11-30 a.m.MESSAGE TO 1. After the Prime Minister, on behalf of the Cabinet,Mr BONAR LAW.had welcomed their new colleagues, the Cabinet agreed  -That the Prime Minister should send ontheir behalf a message of condolence andaffection to Mr Bonar Law.
2. The Secretary of State for&apos; Foreign ^Affairs oorarru-&quot;communicated to the Cabinet particulars in regard to thefollowing(a) A conversation ha had had on the previous day with the German Ambassador, as theresult of which Lord Ourzon had declined to hear from the Ambassador the GermanGovernment&apos;s idea3 in regard to a furtheroffer on the subject of Reparations.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs stated that he wotild circulate an accountof this conversation.(b) A conversation between the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs and M. Krassin,on which Lord Curzon stated that he wasabout to circulate a Memorandum.(c) An appreciation of the present and improved situation in regard to theprospects of peace with Turkey.
RENT ANDMORTGAGERESTRIG-wWfSS BILL.previous reference&apos;Cabinet 2B(23), Oon-clusion 4.)3. After considering a Memorandum by the Minister ofHealth, covering a draft Rent and Mortgage RestrictionsBill (Paper C.P.-243(23)), and the Conclusion of theOomrdttee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 11 (23), Con-elusion 3), as well as a later draft of the Bill embodying the recommendations of the Committee of Home Affairs(Paper C.P.-254(23)), and after hearing from the Ministerof Health an explanation of the more important Sectionsof the Bill, the Cabinet decided (a) (By a majority) That Section 12, Sub-Section (4) should be amended by the omission in the sixth line, after theword &quot;report&quot;, of the words &quot;or fordetermination&quot;, so that the Sub-Sectionshould read as follows&quot;In order to assist the court in the determination of questions arising under this part of this Act in rela-tion to the rent, character or condi-tion of dwelling-houses, the Ministerof Health may establish referencecommittees to who&quot;&apos; such, questions maybe referred by the court for consider-ation and report&quot;(omitting the words &quot;or for determination,as the court thinks proper&quot;).(b) To approve the introduction of the rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions Billin the form of the draft annexed to PaperIf A) CP ,-64 5 (ftg.) . subject to the modificationJ      indicated in (a) above.
PARLIAMENTARY      4. Consideration of the Report of the Cabinet CommitteeCANDIDATUREOP STATE on the Parliamentary Candidature of State Servants (PaperSERVANTS.C.F.-234(23)) was postponed in the absence of the LordChancellor, who had been Chairman of the Committee.(previous reference:Cabinet 28(23), Con-conclusion 7.)-4-
5. After consideration of the Second Interim Reportof the Cabinet Committee on Rating Reform (Paper CP.-230(23)), the Cabinet agreed  -(i) On the understanding that the Governmentwas not committed in any way to theprovisions in the draft Bill, to approve the following recommendations of theCabinet Committee:-(a) The revision of the draft Bill annexed to C.P.-27(23) by incorporating thereinthe modifications indicated in theAppendix to the Report of the CabinetCommittee (Paper C.P.-230(S3)).(b) The circulation of the revised draftBill to the local and other authori-ties concerned, with a view to obtaining their observations thereon.(c) A statement to be made in parliament by the Minister of Health to the effectthat the Government propose to adoptthe course indicated in (b) above, witha view to the introduction of a valuation and Rating Reform Bill next Session in lieu of the introduction of a Bill inthe present Session.(ii) To approve the recommendation 6&quot;f the CabinetCommittee that the Minister of Health shouldbe authorised, in consultation with theSecretary for Scotland and the parliamentary secretary to the Ministry of Transport, toappoint a small expert Committee to examinethe question of the valuation of railwaysand report to the Minister of Health.(iii) To approve the recommendation of the CabinetCommittee that the Minister of Health should appoint a Departmental Committee, including representatives of the Local Authorities,of the manufacturers, and rating experts,to obtain the necessary information andto prepare a definite scheme giving effectto such a limitation of the rating ofmachinery as they ray find to be practicable.
fe?&apos;&apos;RATINGip TITHES.previous reference:cabinet 1520), Con-elusion 9.)6. Arising out of the discussion in regard to theReport of the Cabinet Committee on Rating Reform, theMinister of Agriculture undertook to circulate to theCabinet at an early date a Memorandum dealing with thewhole question of the rating of tithes.
THE HONOURS 7. The Cabinet were informed that, in consequenceMBILL.O of the absence, through indisposition,, of the LordChancellor, the Second Reading discussion of the Honours(previous reference:       Bill in the. House of Lords, arranged for the previous cabinet 25(23), Con-       day, had been postponed,elusion 8.)fitter a short discussion in regard to government business, the Cabinet agreedThat the Honours Bill should be proceeded with in the House ofLords, but that no undertakingshould be given to pass it throughthe House of Commons in the present session.
THE carriage of GOODS by sea BILL.(previous reference: .Cabinet 16(S3),t Con-;clusion 7.)8.   The Cabinet were informed that the Carriage ofGoods by Sea Bill had passed its Second Reading in theHouse of Lords, and that it had been decided, with the&amp; hB sdt of the Lord Chancellor, to send the Bill to a select Committee of both Houses.The Cabinet agreed  That the President of the Board of trade should discuss the composition fflf theSelect Committee with Sir Claud   Schuster,the Permanent Secretary of the LordChancellor&apos;s Office, and that the question should be proceeded with as rapidly aspossible. x
9. The Cabinet took note that the President of theBoard of Trade had every hope that the Private Bill tomake compulsory on cotton spinners the levy of contribu-tions towards th-3 funds of the Empire Cotton-Growingwhich had already, got through its Committee stage would complete the Report and Third Reading by f ^June 8th, and that if any obstmiction arose which prevented this forecast bein,?. realised, Sir PhilipLloyd-Greame was arranging with the Government Whip3that the Bill should be starred as a government measure to ensure its passage.
9. The Cabinet took note that the President of theBoard of Trade had every hope that the Private Bill tomake compulsory on cotton spinners the levy of contribu-tions towards the funds of the Empire Cotton-GrowingAssociation/vould shorting et thrcmgh the Committee stage and complete the j2e*port Stage by JbaffCT^h^*and (thatPhilip Lloyd^Greavoe wajs^ajMiijps^hat theBilL^hould either be passed or else be &apos;;arred as a^overnment maaaur^jpM^^m4%AJL,    Iff)nging with the Governmen\^/
AGRICULTURAL        10. The Cabinet took note of and approved theLATES INSCOTLAND.        recommendation of the Home Secretary in his MemorandumPreviousReference:Cabinet 28 .23), Con-jluslon 3.)C.F.-252 (23) that the grant for agricultural rates to-be awarded in Scotland be calculated on the following basis proposed by the Scottish Office:-&quot;To provide as regards agriculturalhereditaments (i.e. including agri-cultural buildings), that rates should in future be levied equally on occupiersand owners on the basis of half the full amount and that the occupier should beentitled to deduct one-half of his ratesfrom his rent,   This amounts very nearlyin practice to the owner paying the squiv-alent of 75 per cent, of full owner&apos;rates instead of 100 per cent, as atpresent, and to the occupier paying25 per cent, of occupier&apos;s ratesinstead of 37% per cent, as at present.&quot;
11. The Cabinet took note of the Conclusions of aMeeting of Ministers, held on Thursday, May 1923,on the following subjects.-(l) CONGRATULATIONS TO TH1-7 PRIME MINISTER.^2) RUSSIA:    BRITISH RELATIONS WITH.(3) SITUATION AT CONSTANTINOPLE.(4)  THE TURKISH PEACE CONFERENCE *(5) IRISH DEPORTEES.     RESTORATION OPORDER IN IRELAND INDEMNITY BILL,1923.(APPENDIX. )Whitehall Gardens, S.-.1,May 30, 1923.
CABINET.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of ministers held at 10, Downing Street, S.W./1, onThursday, 24th May, 1923, at 12.0 Noon.PRESENT:--The Prime Minister (in the Chair).fhe Moat Hon.the Marquess of Salisbury, K.G.,G.C.V.O., C.B., Lord Presidentof the Council.The Rt. Hon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord schatcht*noellor.Dhe Rt. Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P., Secretaryof State for Homo Affairs.Us grace the Duke of Devonshire, K.G.,G.C.V.O., G.C.M.G., Secretary ofState for the Colonies.?he Rt, Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., First Lord ofthe Admiralty,Jhe Rt. Hon,Viscount Novar, G.C.M.G..Secretary for Scotland.The Most. Hon.tho Marquess curzon of Kedleston,K.G., G,C,S,I.f G.C.I.E,,Secretary of State for foreign affaire,The Rt, Hon,the Earl of Derby, K.G.,G.C.B., G.C.V.O., Secretary ofState for War.The Rt. Hon.Sir Montague Barlow, K.B.E., M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Rt. Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., C.M.G., M.P.,Secretary of State for Air.Ijr M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B,..,,...............................Secretary.m
CONCLUSIONS of &amp; Meeting of Ministers,held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.I., onTHURSDAY, MAY 24,  1923, at 12 Noon.This Meeting of Ministers was held before theCabinet was fully constituted or the Prime minister had &quot;kissed hands&quot; on appointment, primarily forthe purpose of dealing with a matter of immediateurgency, namely, the British Relations with Russia.All Cabinet Ministers in London were asked to attend.1.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, asthe Minister present who had longest held office, tookadvantage of the opportunity to offer to the PrimeMinister, on behalf of his colleagues and himself,their congratulations on his appointment and theirassurance of loyal and unfaltering support.
RUSSIA.BritishRelationswith.(previous reference:Cabinet 27(23), Con-clusion 1.)2. After consideration of the following documents -Note of a Meeting held at the ForeignOffice on Thursday, May 17, 1923, betweenthe Secretary of State for Foreign affairs and M. Krassin (F.0, Paper N/4501/3198/38),Letter from M. Krassin to the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, dated May 23,1923 (Paper CP.-250(23)  it was agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State for foreign.f fairs, in a further interview withM. Krassin, should set forth the british point of view on the various points inthe Russian reply, and should make itperfectly clear that the Russian trade agreement could only be renewed providedthat hi3 conditions, as set forth below,were met on each point:(b) That in regard to the question of fishingin northern waters, the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs should be authorisedto accept the offer of the Russian SovietGovernment to conclude an agreement withthe British Government conceding the rightof British citizens to fish outside thethree mile limit pending the settling ofthe larger question at an international conference:    and to pay compensation forthe particular cases cited in the british note.   Lord Curzon undertook, however,to make clear to M. Krassin that theBritish Government, though ready itselfto attend an International Conference onthe subject provided other Powers were equally willing, could give no guarantee&quot;as regards the attitude of other Powers:(c) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should be authorised, while-&quot;.;&apos;accepting the offer of the Russian SovietGovernment to pay compensation for theexecution of Mr Davison and for the arrest of Mrs Stan Harding, to repudiate the reservation that this willingness in no way signified that the Russian SovietGovernment recognised any irregularityin the repressive measures it- took against these persons:(d) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should be authorised to take note of the fact that the Russian SovietGovernment was ready to take back the twoletters signed by Mr Weinstein:(e) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should, as regards propaganda,insist on a general acceptance of ourdemands on the grounds that cessation of propaganda was a part of the original russian trade Agreement, that the demand was repeatedby Lord Ourzon in his Interview with
Krassin, and that it was a pivotalissue between Great Britain and Soviet   &apos;&apos;Russia.    In this respect Lord Curzonwas authorised to inform M. Krassin -that he was obliged for M.&apos; Chicherin&apos;soffer to discuss &quot;the matter with repre-sentatives of the British Government,but that he saw no need for the People&apos;3Commissary for Foreign Affairs to oometo London, since M, Krassin had madequite clear-that he was himself equipped with full powers to settle with theBritish Government.    If the evidence ofRussian Soviet propaganda contained inthe British Note should be disputed byM. Era3si.n, Lord Cur20n should beauthorised to show him the text of theintercepted wireless communications and to make it clear that in view ofthis definite and indisputable evidencethe question could not be allowed toremain where it was.   Lord Curzon should,however, be authorised, in accordancewith diplomatic practice, to make mattersslightly easier for the Russian SovietGovernment by consenting to the recallwithin a definite period of time of theiragents in Kabul and Teheran, instead ofinsisting on their dismissal:That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should require a reiteration bythe Russian Soviet Government of the undertakings given in the Anglo-russian trade Agreement in regard to propaganda,and their confirmation in a special declara-tion, but he should endeavour to embodythe renewed declaration in a more specificand definite formula:That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should consider the desirability,as part of the terms of continuing theRussian Trade Agreement, of requiring theRussian Soviet Government to allow thereturn to Russia of certain Russians whom,it was desired, to expel from this country.The Home Secretary undertook to let theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairshave a list of these persons,  and all necessary particulars: .That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should be authorised to give M.Krassin a few days within which to com-municate with his Government, but shouldmake it quite clear that his conditionsware final:That any further statement in the House ofCommons on the subject should be- made on theForeign Office Vote, which had been kept open and which could be taken on any Supply day.
situation at OONSTAN-TIHOPLB.o(previous reference cabinet 2?(23) Con-oluaion 2.)3.     The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed his .colleagues that the information from Lausannepointed in the cLiredbion of an early agreement betweenthe Turks and Greeks on the question of Reparations andthat assurances had &quot;been received &quot;both from M.VeniseIos at lausanne and from the Government at Athens that no forwardmovement would he taken by the Greek army without a previous denunciation of the Mudania Armistice and notice to the Allies.     In these circumstances no instructionsto General Harington as to his action, in the event of   aGreek advance appeared necessary.The Seoretary of State for foreign affaire undertook to prepare atelegram reviewing the whole situation to be sent to Sir HoraceRumbold at Lausanne which would be repeated to the Acting HighCommissioner at Constantinople forthe information of General Harington.-4-
SHE TURKISHL3&apos;CE CON-PERENCE.(previous reference:Cabinet 19(23), Con-elusion 4).4*   After making a statement on the present positionof the negotiations at Lausanne for a Turkish Peace,the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was authorisedto proceed on the following lines(a) To ascertain from Sir Horace Rumboldhis views in regard to the outstanding questions, the most important of whichwere the Judicial Regime to take theplace of the Capitulations, and Repara-tIons?(b) After obtaining Sir Horace RumboldfsViews, to make proposals to the Frenchand Italian Governments:(c) After reaching agreement with the Frenchand Italian Governments, to authorisethe 3ritish Delegation, at Lausanne tomake definite proposals to the Turks.
IRISH DEPORTEES.    5. It was agreed -RESTORATIONOF ORDER INIRELANDBl.      1923.I Previous^Reference :$Cabinet 28(23), Con-elusion He).)(a) That the Terms of Reference to the proposedTribunal should be:-To consider the Regulations madeunder the Restoration of OrderIn Ireland Act (1920) and to ,advise as to the amendment orcancellation of any such Regulations.(b) That the Tribunal might with advantage be composed of the following, if willingto serve:-The Right Hon. Lord Dunedin, K.C.V.O.,The Right Hon. Sir Donald Maclean, K.B.E.,M.P.,Mr, George Talbot, K.C(o) That no legal claim should be admittedin regard to compensation to the Irishdeportees, but that an ex gratia paymentshould be made in regard to any actualdirect loss suffered by individuals, andthat the assessment of such loss shouldbe referred to some suitable person, suchas a County Court Judge:(d) That the Home Secretary should make astatement as soon as possible afterthe Restoration of Order in IrelandIndemnity Bill, 1923, was moved InParliament, and should then withdraw.The Prime Minister should arrange as towhich Minister should be associated withthe Attorney-General in charge of theBill.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1., May 24th, 1923.

</content>
</cab>
