<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/175/0 images: 168-170</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY,. [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;8 Government.&quot;Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1925.SECRET.Copy No.    30CP. 428 (25).CABINET.SPECIAL REPORT  ON   UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 120.     September 1925.AS explained in the last monthly report on this subject CP. 408 (25) it is proposed to publish quarterly the detailed information and figures which have been included in previous reports. The collection of the necessary returns covering the period up to the end of September has, however, not yet been completed, and I think it may be desirable to issue in advance of the full report a sbort statement on the same lines as that issued last month, summarising the results of the recently published monthly return of unemployment in the various industries.(A.) Numbers of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges inGreat Britain.-	1923.	1924.	1925.						Sept. 24.	Sept. 29.	Aug. 31.	Sept. 7.	Sept. 14.	Sept. 21.	Sept. 28.	Increase (-\-) or Decrease (- ) since August 31.Men .. Boys .. Women Girls .. Total..	942,605 45,312 245,260 42,593	903,944 37,850 223,935 33,587	1,058,384 44,370 217,105 34,443	1,054,141 1,049,168 41,956 !    40,391 215,488 1  205,012 33,870 1    33,066		1,043,558 38,801 198,236 31,363	1,068,948 40,358 195,867 30,982	4-   10,564 - 4,012 - 21,238 - 3,461	1,275,770	1,199,316	1,354,302	1,345,455	1,327,637	1,311,958	1,336,155	-   18,147Note. The above figures represent the number of persons recorded as not at work on the dates given, whether they were totally, unemployed, suspended or stood off, &amp;c, or working systematic short time and claiming unemployment benefit.Percentage of unemployment (Great Britain) in the insured industries at the end of September 1923 1924 192511-6 10-6 12-1The figures in the table above show that substantial decreases in the numbers of persons unemployed were recorded in each of the first three weeks of September and that a sharp increase occurred in the last week of the month. Over the whole four weeks there was a net decrease of a little more than 18,000. It will be noted that throughout the period the number of women on the registers decreased progressively and the figure at the end of September was substantially less than at the corresponding dates of last year or 1923. A gradual reduction m the number of juveniles was the consequence of their absorption into industry following increased registrations after the end of the last school term. As [13714]
regards the figures for men, the total increase was caused by a rise, amounting to some 34,000, in the registers in Wales during the last week of the month. This swallowed up a consistent decrease, totalling more than 20,000, which would otherwise have been shown. Compared with a year ago, the number of persons unemployed at the end of September is greater by 136,839, but it may be mentioned that the excess of this year&apos;s figures over the corresponding figures for 1924 was gradually reduced during September. In fact, the net decrease of 18,147 during the month in the number of persons on the registers may be Contrasted with the increase of 36,436 which occurred in the corresponding weeks of September 1924, although the effect of administrative and legislative changes in the Unemployment Insurance Scheme should not be overlooked. Comparing the position during the past three months with that for the third quarter of 1924, it is found that the increases in the numbers unemployed were 31,912 and 189,872 respectively.(B.) Unemployment in Insured Industries.The latest date for which unemployment figures by industries are available is the 21st September, at which date the percentage unemployed in Great Britain and Northern Ireland was 12&apos;4, as compared with 12&apos;5 at the 24th August, with 10&apos;8 at the 22nd September, 1924, and with 11*7 at the 24th September, 1923.The figures of unemployment in respect of a number of the chief industries for the 21st September and the 24th August and for the corresponding date in September 1924 are given in the table below, together with the respective increases or decreases in unemployment during the two periods: -Industry.iUnemployment Books Lodged at Septeniber21,l August 24, 1925.      I      1925.September 22, 1924.Increase (4- )or Decrease( - ) as compared with August 24, 1925.September22, 1924.Coal Mining-Iron and Steel Mills and Forges Pig Iron Manufacture Tin Plate Manufacture Shipbuilding and Ship-Repairing Construction and Repair of motor vehicles, &amp;c. Engineering, &amp;c.. . Metal Trades CottonWoollen and Worsted Hosiery Lace SilkLinen    . ..JuteCarpet Manufacture Textile Bleaching, Printing, Dyeing,&amp;c.  i. Building-Tailoring .. ...Dressmaking, &amp;c. . : &apos;Hat and Cap Manufacture Boot anil Shoe   .. .....Pottery, Earthenware, &amp;c. Pood, Drink and Tobacco Trades Printing and Paper Trades Furniture Making, Upholstering, &amp;c. Road Transport (excluding Railway,Tramway and Omnibus Services) .. Shipping- ServiceCanal, River and Dock and Harbour ServiceTotal for Insured Industries ..292,723 53.278 0,448 3,600 86,37316,423 98,967 48,641 57,454 33,946 9,002 4,115 3,376 26,930 5,593 3,54518,208 64,074 25,994 7,188 2,616 18.710 11,360 41,275 17,409 5,81720,964 23,64958,7671,423,566279,781 53,774 6,24 L 4,629 85,55316,476 100,348 50,641 76,382 47,150 10,162 3,861 3,543 26,524 5,916 3,63718,634 58,591 25,174 8,377 3,027 17,833 14,503 38.749 18,375 6,29520,317 24,57057,8051,440,628103,076 53,327 4,734 i,082 77,79021,661 112,075 58,790 80,602 20,053 7,064 3,601 2,288 8,873 4,119 1,85915,286 70,412 21,9088,436 . 3,643 12.2908,440 44,021 20,6550,79923,047 22,10754,2591,240,0454- 12,942 -      496207 1,0298204444 4453 1,381 2,000 18,928 13,204 1,160 254 167 406 323 92426 5,483 820 1,189 413 877 3,143 2,526 966 478647 921962-   17,0624 4 44 4 4, 4 4 4 44 4444 4+   183,521
During the period between the 24th August and the 21st September the principal changes occurred in the Cotton and Woollen Textile Industries and in Coal Mining. A further depression in the latter industry added nearly 13,000 to the figure of insured unemployment, but the Cotton and Woollen Trades showed decreases of 19,000 and 13,000 respectively. Increased unemployment reported in the Building Trade may be attributed to the usual seasonal fluctuations, and seasonal causes are also mainly responsible for increases in other industries amounting in all to some 6,000. In addition to the Cotton and Woollen Trades, improved employment is recorded in the Pottery, Tin Plate, Hosiery and Dress-making Trades. The Metal Trades and Engineering (except Marine Engineering) also show slightly decreased unemployment. The position in the Iron and Steel and Shipbuilding Industries and in other sections of the Textile Industry showed little change during the month.Comparing the present position in the various industries with that of a year ago, it will at once be noticed that the difference in the two figures for the Coal Mining Industry is more than sufficient to account for the total increase during the year; in fact, its magnitude is such that the effect of the movements in other industries upon the total register figures has been practically obscured. Among these movements are the further decline in the Shipbuilding Industry, a similar decline in Marine Engineering and increased unemployment in the Pig Iron Manufacturing Trade. The Iron and Steel Industry shows no improve-ment during the year. The Pottery and Tin Plate Industries, though worse than a year ago, have recently recorded improvement, and the same is true of certain branches of the Textile Industry, including the Woollen and Worsted, Hosiery and Silk Trades. Among the industries whose position is better than a year ago are the Cotton Trade, Engineering (except Marine Engineering), Construction and Repair of Motor Vehicles, the Metal Trades and the Building Industry.(C.) Latest Figures.The latest figures of unemployment published are those for the 12th October, and give the total numbers on the registers as 1,258,825. This shows a decrease on the previous weeks figures of 38,803, hut is 48,624 more than a year ago. In the previous week a drop of 38,527 was recorded, and the decrease since the 28th September therefore amounts to 77,330. The distribution of this decrease by industry is not yet available, and it is therefore impossible to say definitely in which industries, the decreases in the last fortnight have taken place. A geographical analysis shows that reduced unemployment is reported from Wales (19,000), the Midlands (17,000), the North-Eastern and North-Western Divisions (25,000 and 15,000 respectively) and Scotland (4,000). Slight increases occurred in London and the Southern Counties. This distribution makes it highly probable that the fortnight&apos;s decrease is mainly due to an improvement in the Coal Mining Industry.A. STEELi-MAITLAND.Ministry of Labour,October 21, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
