<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/175/0 images: 173-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&amp; 3HP\DENT!AH Lit&apos;     v[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]   ^ ^ 2 Printed for the Committee of Civil Research.   October 1925.SECRET. Gopy No.   aoO.P. 430 (25).CABINET.BRITISH DYE INDUSTRY.Report by the Chairman of the Committee of Civil Research.THE question of the suggested- sale of the Government holding in the British Dye-stuffs Corporation was referred to the Committee of Civil Research by the Cabinet at their meeting on the 7th August, 1925- (Reference Cabinet 44 (25), Conclusion 10). The Committee have considered this question at two meeting-is&apos; held respectively on the&apos; 29th1 September and the 13th October, 1925. At the first of. these meetings the Committee heard a full statement on tbje question from Lord Ashfield, the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the British Dye-stuffs Corporation. Lord Ashfield was accompanied by Sir Alfred Mbnd and Sir Henry Birehenough, the Government Directors, and by Lord Colwyn, another member of the Board.Lord Ashfield summarised the history of the Corporation, and referred to the&quot; heavy tosses which had been made on its trading account since 1921. These losses had only been covered by using the interest from tie large reserve fund accumulated prior to 1921. The reconstituted Board, of which he was Chair many, were unanimous in the opinion that it was essential that the Government should renounce the extensive powers of control that it at present possessed. The Articles of Association provided that the Company should not make anything but dyes without the consent of the Government, and also gave to the Government a strict power of veto against any agreement with foreign&apos; dye-making concerns. It- was impossible, in the opinion of the Board, to achieve commercial success in the face of such restrictions, particularly in view of the fact that their British rivals labour under no such disabilities and were&apos; perfectly free both to manufacture valuable by-products and make any arrangements with foreign dye interests that appeared to them com-; mercially desirable. The Board proposed, therefore, that the Government should sell to them their holding, on the basis of the present market value. This would give the Company complete freedom to remove those restrictions by amending their Articles of Association.If the Government agreed to this proposal, the Board were prepared to recommend to the shareholders a large scheme for writing down their capital and utilising their reserves for productive purposes, and they believed that if these steps were taken commercial success was possible. If, on the other hand;, the Government were not prepared to accept this course, the Board were agreed that the only course they could recommend to the shareholders would be the liquidation of the Corporation.The Committee have &quot;carefully considered the question in the light of Lord Ashfiekhs statement, and have also considered the representations on this subject which they have received from the Principal Suppfy Officers&apos; Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence.At their meeting on the&apos; 13th October the Committee&apos; unanimously&apos; reached the following conclusions,, and decided to recommend to the Cabinet -1. That the Government should hot attempt to continue the particular relations which have hitherto existed between them and&apos; the British Dye-stuffs Corporation, and should1 withdraw their representatives from the Board and terminate their existing rights Of veto add control. [13679]
2. That the Treasury should therefore be authorised to dispose of the Govem-ment&apos;s holding to the Corporation on the best terms obtainable. 3. That as a condition of the foregoing the Corporation should be required (a.) To give an undertaking under seal that they would not alter Article 38 (1) of their Articles of Association, which provides that not more than 25 per cent, of their shares should be held by foreigners.(b.) To give an assurance that in all matters of technical information and research they would keep in touch with the Government in such manner as the President of the Board of Trade for the time being,&apos; might direct.4. That these changes, if adopted, increased rather than diminished the necessity of maintaining the policy embodied in the provisions of the Dye-stuffs (Import Regulation) Act, 1920, and the protection afforded to the fine chemical industry by Part I of the Safeguarding of Industries Act, 1920.The Committee further agreed That, as an integral part of the arrangement now recommended, the Treasury should undertake to regard with favour the use of a sum, approximately equivalent to the interest on the sum realised from the sale of the Government shares in developing, through the Department of Scientific and Industrial Research, facilities for pursuing chemical investigations, not necessarily ancillary to the making of dyes, but of value to the Fighting Services and to the chemical industry generally.Lord Haldane, who is a member of the Committee, has been prevented by illness from attending its meetings, but has sent me a memorandum, which I attach, giving his views on this question.A. J. B.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, October 16, 1925.Annex.Memorandum by Lord Haldane.TO my great regret I have been prevented by illness from attending the meetings of the Committee. I have, however, read all the papers. During past years I have given a good deal of attention to the questions they raise.I was Chairman of the original Committee, to which these questions in their then form were referred by the Board of Trade in 1914. We found that the Dyestuffs industry in this country was wholly inadequate for the supply of the public demand. In order to furnish what was necessary in the form of new chemical products, even for war purposes, a special organisation was set up by the Government under Lord Moulton. This organisation was successful, mainly for the reason that it made a full use of British Science, drawing on the Universities for technical knowledge and assistance.I think that the situation to-day is analogous. I have investigated, as far as I could, the dyestuffs organisation in Germany. There, before the war, the great dyestuff companies were earning large dividends, amounting at times to between 20 and 30 per cent. But the organisation was different from ours. The companies had as their directors a small number of men of business and a large proportion of skilled dyestuff chemists. The highly practical Boards devoted a great deal of whole time work to managing their businesses. They laid great stress on a full supply, by the Universities and technical schools, some of which I saw at work, of carefully trained students of the proper forms of chemistry. From these the various Boards picked the men they preferred, and offered them interesting posts, with the prospect of improving them.In the case of the British Dyes Corporation the procedure is very different. No doubt certain of the directors are very able business men.   But they do not give
i &apos;amore than a fraction of their time to the business of the Corporation, nor have they the technical knowledge which is desirable. They cannot engage in that close study of markets and of new processes which appears essential if there is to be success. There is no lack of students, actual and potential. I went into this question with professors of chemistry, both at Cambridge and at Birmingham. I was informed that there were students, not only in sufficient numbers, but highly trained, available. But the Dyes Corporation gave them but little encouragement. The students (the number employed by the Corporation is being extensively decreased, as appears by the, papers circulated) were put into routine work, and they had small prospects held out to them. I knew that the method in Germany had been different from this, and I set myself to ascertain whether no producing Company had been set up in Great Britain which had sought success by adopting or improving on the methods followed not only in Germany but in Switzerland. I found that the Scottish Dyes Company, a wholly independent organisation, had made a success of its business. I interviewed its head, a practical man of ability, whose whole time was given to producing the dyes required by the industrial public and to dyeing certain textiles which he himself produced.He told me that the secret of the success of his company, the chemical head-quarters of which are at Grangemouth, was that he presided over a small, but picked, body of directors, all of whom were trained experts. They had no difficulty in producing all the colours that were usually asked for, and if something new was required they did not fail to produce it. They had a body of selected student assistants. These were divided into the laboratory staff and the producing supervisors. When a new colour was asked for or suggested the question was turned over, under the supervision of a suitable member of the Board, first to the laboratory staff, who made the requisite researches, and, when these were complete, to the producing branch. When these stages had been gone through the Company proceeded to manufacture and supply. I hear high accounts of the efficiency of this Company. It aims at concentrating on its staff and encouraging and promoting the members, and it is said to be commercially successful as a consequence.It seems to me that the British Dyes Corporation, even if it has the largest liberty given to it, is almost bound to fail for want of really scientific organisation of this kind. Even if it can make, money for a time by what is tantamount to permeation by the Germans, it will not in this fashion fulfil the purpose for which the Government, after 1914, advanced large sums to it. That purpose was to develop a school of chemical colour experts who could supply and assist the nation from within in time of war as well as of peace. We want an independent and independently-manned organisation in this country. We have a huge market for its products, if they are what is required by the textile industry. That industry is ready to pay, if it can secure them, for the cost of dyes is only a comparatively small item in the cost of textile production. The success of the Scottish Dyes Company shows what can be done.I cannot but think that to let loose a body of directors with little but commercial . aims is a dangerous procedure. Almost inevitably the Germans will capture them. JSTo matter how able men of business are Lord Ashfield and his colleagues, they cannot conquer new ground unless they give to the task whole time and a devotion to the ideal for the accomplishment of which public monev was originally advanced lavishly.I regret that I am unable to see much room for hope in the conclusions reached by the majority of the Committee at the meeting on the 13th October. I do not believe any more than does the majority in the utility of a couple of part-time Government Directors. I should much prefer to tell the Corporation that the Government is willing to go out, if, but only if, the Board of the Corporation is reconstituted on the lines I have suggested above. A large Board is not required. But its Chairman should give practically his whole time to his work, and he should have the assistance of a first-rate Manager. I have not met Mr. Armstrong, and for all I know he may be such a man. The other directors should be experts who can give plenty of time to the work, rather than men engaged with the business of half a dozen boards of quite a different character.It may be that it is only the shareholders, as I gather at present a somewhat unhappy body, who can make the requisite changes. But the Government still wields a powerful lever, and I cannot but think that the public, when it comes to know more, will desire that this lever should be used.(Signed) HALDANE.Cloan, Perthshire, October 15, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
