<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/175/0 images: 507-513</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
j 1C*CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY.      r        :(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PfiOPEKTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 3 G0VJ3RMSB-T) OSITION OB&apos; THE DOMINIONS  IN RELATION TO THE LOO ARN 0&quot;-THEATY.Note by the Seoretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I circulate a memorandum on the subject of the position of the Dominions in relation to the Locarno Treaty,  together- with the draft of a telegram which, if my colleagues approve,  I suggest should be sent to the Dominionso    It will be seen that I further suggest that this telegram should be followed by a second stating the general lines (as indicated in the Memorandum) on which the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs will refer to this matter in his speech in the House of Commons on the 18th November,,I understand that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs concurs generally in the proposals put forward In the momorandum0I propose to take up later the question of the most suitable time for the next Imperial Conference to which reference is made at the end of the draft telegramoCOPY NO.14th November, 19 5,
ftraft Memprandurn. fQg,..Cirqulatlpg., to..the ^Gahlnet.A decision is necessary on the question whether any communication should be made to the Dominions as regards the possibility of their participation in the Treaty of Mutual Guarantee initialled at Locarno on the 16th October,  article 9 of which provides that &quot;the present Treaty shall impose no obligation upon any of the British Dominions or upon India unless the Government of such Dominion or of India signifies its acceptance thereof&quot;.Questions have frequently been ashed in Parliament and will undoubtedly continue to he askec   as to whether His Majesty&apos;s Government hove any information regarding the intentions and views of the Dominions in connection with the Security Pact.    Hitherto it has been possible to reply to the effect that the Dominions have been kept informed of the progress of negotiations but it seems doubtful whether,  in present circumstances,  this would be accepted as a sufficient answer^In any case,  it would  seem necessary to inform the Dominions that His Majesty&apos;s Government propose to advise His Majesty to ratify the Pact,  assuming that Parliament gives its approval and that the other signatories are also prepared to ratify, and the question which requires consideration is whether in ouch a communication anything- should be added in the nature of an enquiry es to the attitude of the Dominions under Articlo 9aCertain indications have already been given either in offioial communications or in the speeches of Dominion political leaders,  as to the probable attitude of some of the Dominions;    The Union
Government in a telegram of&apos; the 6th July with regard to the proposed publication of correspondence relating to the Security Pact,   stated that,  as they were not a party to the negotiations,  they had no suggestions to offer as to the method of publication,  and the . Governor-General explained that he understood confidentially that the wording of this telegram was intended to.indicate that the Union Government were unlikely to assume any responsibility in connection with the Pact.     The New Zealand Government,   on the other hand,  judging by their general attitude in the course- of the negotiations, may wish to accept the obligations of the Treaty.     As regards Canada, the Press of the 27th October quoted a statement by Mr. Mackenzie King in the course of which he said &quot;Parliament will rise to the occasion when it is necessary to take action but it is a mistake to raise any controvers?/ on this issue at present since no request has come to us&quot;, and. according to the same message Mr. Meighen had stated that &quot;the  question of ratifying the Pact is not at present opportune pending a settlement of domestic problems in the present election and without an opportunity as yet properly to study the terms of the Treaty&quot;.     As regards Australia, Mr. Bruce has stated, according to the Press, that the Commonwealth Government can only welcome the conclusion of any practical&apos; agreement in Surope having the effect of eliminating fears, of -war and securing political stabilisation there, though they have not decided whether Australia will accept the  commitments of the Pact and in any case would not assume any commitments without the sanction of the new Parliament.
The question of Dominion participation raises a number of important issues which will require careful examination no less here than in the Dominions.     The matter seems essentially one for discussion at an Imperial Conference and I submit that it would be wise to send a telegram to the Dominions at once suggesting that the question of the Locarno Treaty should be brought into a general discussion of the whole field of defence and foreign policy at such a Conference.The draft of such a telegram which in accordance with the usual procedure would take the form of a message from, the Prime Minister to the Dominion Prime Ministers, is annexed.If the terms of this message are approved by the Cabinet,  no doubt the Secretary of State for India will wish to send an appropriate communication on similar lines to the Government of India.Should the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs wish,  in his speech in the House of Commons on the 13th November, to make a reference to the question of the participation of the Dominions in the-Treaty,  I suggest that the statement should take the following forms-As was Indicated in answers to questions In the House of Commons during the summer,  the Dominions were kept fully informed of the opening stages of the negotiations and this process vas continued up to the date of initialling of the Treatv.The Treaty makes express provision as to the position of the Dominions and India in Article 9 ?. rich reads &quot;The present Treaty shall impose no obligation upon any of the British Dominions or upon India unless the Government of such Dominion or of India signifies
its acceptance thereof&quot;.      It is noticed that in some quarters comment has been made on the fact that this Article refers to Dominion Governments andAot to Dominion Parliaments, and it may be desirable therefore to exolain the reason for this wording.      It may well be that,  in accordance with general constitutional principles, no obligation in a matter of this importance would be undertaken by any Dominion Government without Parliamentary approval (in other words that they would feel themselves to be in the same position as His Majesty&apos;s Government in this matter).      But it is also an established principle that it is for each &apos;Government to decide whether such Parliamentary approval should be sought.      This principle was recognised at the discussion at the Imperial Conference of 1923 on the Negotiation, Signature and Ratification of Treaties, and reference may be invited to&apos;the explanatory statement which appears on page 15 of the Summary of the proceedings of that Conference (Cmd.198*7 )a As Hon. Members are aware, there have been recently General Elections in three of the Dominions and in. the majority of them Parliament is not how in Session. Apart from this, they will appreciate that, on issues of such importance end complexity His Majesty&apos;s Government would hesitate to ask the Governments of the Dominions and India to define their position under Article 9 until there had been an opportunity of discussing, in greater detail    than the limits of written or telegraphic communications permit, what may be termed the background of the Pact,.its implications, and its responsibilities, in other words the whole European and International situation.14th November,  19 25.
Eovomber, Com.idontial.f   Following from Prime Minister ,;or your Prime Minister hogins.\  As you are aware Article 9 of the Treaty of Mutual Guartntee which was initialled at Locarno and which it is hopod will he signed on 1st -December provides that the Treaty shell impose no obligation upon any of the British Dominions or upon India unless t,he Government of such Dominion or of India signifies its acceptance thereof0So far as this country is concerned, Parliament is being given an immediate opportunity of discussing the Treaty and, assuming that Parliament gives its approve! and that the other signatories also are prepared to ratify the Treaty, we propose to advise His Majesty to ratify,,As regards tho Dominions,  we have been proceeding on assumption that no obligation under Article 9 of the Treaty would, in any event be undertaken by airy Dominion Government unless the whole position had been laid before its Parliament and tho approval of Parliament obtained.    It has also seemed to us that, before arriving at any final judgment, Dominion Governments would desire the fullest possible informa-tion as to the situation croatod by the Treaty in relation to the whole field of foreign policy and defence,It would appear to follow that  there should be a general examination of the whole situation, and we suggest that ouch ax&amp;minat or: could b -st be deferred until there has boon an opportunity of personal discussion between Ministers here and representatives of tho Dominions and India such as would be afforded by tho r,curb Imperial Conference as to tho date of which wo hope to be able to make proposals in theDRA^T TELBGRAli   to Go^ernoxe-G&apos;-.ner&amp;l of Cant da, Common wealthof Australia,. Ii e&amp; Zealand, Union of South Africa and tho Irish Free State and to the Governor of Bewf oundland0
- av 4near future.Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in speech which he is reeking in House of Commons to-day will make statement on lines   indicated in separrte message which follows,,Similar message sent to other Prime Ministers. Baldwin.    Ends.Amery,

</content>
</cab>
