<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/175/0 images: 537-552</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] f a -------^Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1925. &quot;CONFIDENTIAL UBRM&amp;Y,SECRET. Copy No.    OUCP. 482 (25).(Also C.R. (H) 41.)CABINET.IRON AND STEEL INDUSTRY.Summary of Evidence and of Memoranda submitted to the Committeeof Civil Research.(Circulated by direction of the Prime Minister.)PageI. Introductory                         ..           ......           .. .. 1II. The present position of the industry      ..          . .          .. . . 2III. The attitude of labour            ..          ..          ..          .. .. iv. Commercial organisation of the British iron and steel industry (A.) Internal organisation   .          ..          ..          .. .. 4(B.) External marketing organisation      ...          .. .. 5(U.) Attitude towards international agreements          .. .. 5V. Foreign competition (A.) Wages am 1 hours       ..           ..           . .          .. . . 6(B.) Depreciation of foreign exchanges         ...          .. .. 6(0.) Supply of raw materials           ..          ..          .. .. 6(I).) Protection of foreign manufacturers      ..          .. .. 7(B.) Advantages derived from superior equipment       .. . . 7(F.) Advantages derived from superior organisation    .. .. 7(a.) Belgium         ..          ..                      .. .. 8(fi.) France            ..           ..          ..          .. .. 8(e.) Germany        ..          ..          ..          .. .. 8VI. Application of improved scientific methods to British industry .. 9VII.-Possible methods of assisting the industry                      ,. .. 10VIII. Protection by tariff- -(A.) Total prohibition of imports     ..          ..          .. .. 10(B.) Moderate tariff          ..          ..         .&apos;.          .. .. 12IX. Subsidies     ..          ..          ..          ..         ..          .. .. 13X.  Possibility of increasing&apos; efficiency by closer internal concentration .. 13(A) Suggested general merging of interests ..          .. ... 14(B.) Regional amalgamations           ..          ..          .. .. 14XL Attitude of the industry to concentration           ..          .. .. 15Appendix. List of witnesses ..          ..          ..          .. .. 16L-Introductory.1. AT their meeting held on the 26th June, 1925 (Cabinet 31 (25). Conclusion 2), the Cabinet had under consideration an application from the Iron and Steel Industry for an Enquiry under the Safeguarding of Industries Act. Having regard to the present distress in this industry, to the consequent desirability of avoiding undue delay, to the time which would be required to complete a Safe-guarding Enquiry, and to the political difficulties which would be involved by a recommendation, if made, in favour of the application put forward by the industry, the Cabinet considered that, before coming to a decision on the question of holding [13829] b
such an Enquiry-, the Government should themselves undertake a wider survey of the problem, and agreed (a:) That the Committee of Civil Research should undertake an Enquiry as lo what form of help, if any, would best enable the Iron and Steel industry to regain the export trade and maintain its position.No precise Terms of Reference were formulated, but it was generally agreed that the Committee should consider, inter alia, the following forms of possible assistance : Subsidy on specific contracts or orders for export. An Export Bounty.Assistance  to  local  rates  where  they  bear specially heavily on industry.Assistance to rates of carriage for goods on the railways. Some form of international cartel or arrangement of the kind.(b.) That in the meantime the question of an Enquiry into the Iron and steel Industry under the Safeguarding of Industries Acts should remain, in suspense.2. The Committee of Civil Research have held twelve meetings, at whicti various aspects of this question have been laid before them, and have consulted twenty-four witnesses, enumerated in the Appendix.II. The Present Position of the Industry.3. In 1913, the last completed year before the war, the output of pig-iron in Great Britain amounted to 10-26 million tons. British capacity for production amounted then to about 12 million tons per annum, which represented 14 per cent, of the world output, compared with 40 per cent, produced by the United States and 21 per cent, by Germany. In the same year the figures for steel ingots and castings amounted to 7-66 million tons, compared with an annual productive capacity of about 8 million tons. Exports of Iron and Steel and manufactures thereof at that time amounted to 4-97 million tons, while imports stood at 2-23 million tons.4. The immense demands for munitions led naturally to great extensions of plant in the industry during the war. In that period steel productive capacity rose from 8 to 12 million tons per annum, and even in the pig-iron industry, where there were great physical obstacles to expansion, capacity rose from 11 to 12 million tons per annum. The war-time deficiency in pig-iron was made good by the importation of pig-iron, by the restriction of exports, by the increased use of scrap, which, owing to the manufacture of munitions, was available in large quantities, and by the pro-duction of steel-making pig-iron in preference to foundry and forge pig-iron.5. The year 1920 was one of exceptional prosperity, but the five years since their have been marked by great depression in the industry.6. The production of pig-iron in 1924 fell to 7-3 million tons, being 29 per cent less than in 1913 and representing only 60 per cent, of existing effective capacity. It is true that the figure for steel production in 1924 (8-2 million tons) is greater by U per cent, than the production in 1913, but owing to the expansion of the industry during the war it only represents about 70 per cent, of present effective capacity. Imports during 1924 amounted to 2-43 million tons, representing an excess of 200,000 tons over the figure for 1913. This slight increase of imports has, however, been accompanied by a marked fall in exports. The effect of war-time restrictions was naturally reflected in the reduced volume of exports, which even in the boom year 1920 only amounted to 3-25 million tons; but in 1924 exports had only risen to 3-85 million tons, which is 1-12 millions less than the corresponding figure for 1913.7. The annual British production of steel in its crude form is slightly greater than it was before the war, but in weighing the figures on which this conclusion is based it would be illogical to rely on averages in which were included the whole pro-duction of 1923, which, by reason of the French occupation of the Ruhr, was peculiarly favourable for British steel manufacturers. The conditions created by the Ruhr Occupation have passed away.8. Apart from any question of the basis adopted in the preparation of statistics, there are two considerations which call for caution in drawing conclusions regarding the amount of British steel production at the present time : 
It3(a.) It is clear from the evidence that many steel works are accepting contraets-at rates that in ordinary conditions they would certainly refuse. If it is true that the margin is usually just sufficient to prevent an actual loss being incurred, it is equally true that under these conditions no profits a,re possible. Such contracts are accepted as a less objectionable alternative to the closing of the mills. That this process cannot be continued indefinitely without imposing an intolerable strain on the financial strength of the Companies is sufficiently shown by the immense indebtedness that the steel industry is known to have incurred with their Bankers and by the fact that some of the best-equipped mills have been closed by their owners, who have preferred to cut their losses rather than still further to cripple their resources by keeping their mills working in such unprofitable conditions.(&amp;.) The position of the British steel trade&apos; is, naturally, of great concern to the steel-using industries, whose prospects are ultimately conditioned by the existence of a vigorous steel-making industry in this country. Some concerns, realising this fact, have endeavoured to help the steel trade by using as large a proportion of British steel as they can, even at some sacrifice of immediate gain.9. Again, the Railway Companies have assisted the industry by anticipating the date at which they would normally give orders for Rails. Thus some of those now being rolled will not actually be laid until 1927.10. The fact that many of the orders now being executed in British steel works are being done at the price of increased exhaustion, if not at an actual loss, coupled with the artificial anticipation of British orders which can only be made up by a corresponding falling off in the future, has enabled British steel production to maintain its annual tonnage and, indeed, slightly to increase it, but the conditions by which this has been made possible are such as to temper the degree: of satisfaction that might otherwise have been drawn from the achievement,11. Having regard therefore to the complications with which the problem is beset, the most that can be drawn from a comparison between the pre-war position, and that which obtains to-day is that home production is. approximately the same,, imports are slightly higher, exports considerably less and the relation of actual production to productive capacity greatly reduced.12. In view of the fact that the present production both of pig-iron and of steel in this country is so far below the full productive capacity of existing plant (55 per cent, in the former and 60 per cent, in the latter), some witnesses have concluded that there should be a substantial contraction of the industry. If this were effected the less efficient works would be closed, the work that they are doing being distributed among the more efficient plants by which it could be more economically carried out. On the other hand, other witnesses have taken the view that though existing plant is largely in excess of immediate requirements, it is not more, judging by the past history of the industry, than this country can reasonably claim to maintain, if it were not for the exceptional conditions of world under-consumption, resulting from the war.13. During each decade of the 19th century world production of pig-iron, which as a basic material forms a good index to world steel requirements, increased on an average by 60 per cent. The increase in the last complete decade^ (1901-10) before the war amounted to 62 per cent. If the same rate of progress had been maintained, total world production should now have been 127,000,000 tons a year, whereas it is believed- not to exceed 105,000,000 tons. On this basis it is fair to claim that there is no substance in the contention that existing world capacity is in excess of what would be the world demand if it was not for the economic disorganisation resulting from the war.14. Whichever is the correct view, there is, however, no doubt that a number of steel works in this country are not sufficiently up to date to justify their existence. If means could be found to relieve the industry of the burden involved by the existence of such works, increased efficiency would result. If in the future it was-shown that British capacity had in this way been reduced to too low a figure, the remedy would quickly be found by the setting up of new plants of the latest and most efficient pattern.&quot;[13829]b 21
- III.- The Attitude of Laboue.15. The industry, if working at full pressure, affords employment for 267,000 men. Of this total, 64,000, representing 24 per cent, of the whole, were registered as unemployed on the 21st September, 1925. It is estimated that the production of a million tons of steel billets gives employment to approximately 33,000 workers per annum.* In the heavy iron and steel trades (smelting, puddling, rolling, forging, &amp;c), in which wages fluctuate in correspondence with the selling price of the finished products, the increases over pre-war rates vary widely, being in some cases (e.g., with certain blast furnace labourers) equivalent to nearly 70 per cent, over the pre-war weekly rates, while at the other extreme the rates for iron and steel workers in South Wales show increases of only about 20 per cent, on pre-war weekly wages. In the tinplate and steel sheet trade in South Wales the increase over pre-war rates amounts to about 34^ per cent.16. Mr. Arthur Pugh, the General Secretary of the Iron and Steel Trades Confederation, in giving evidence before the Committee, did not disguise his view that the position was so serious as to demand Government intervention. He considered thiat in this Industry they were subject to unfair competition from countries in which the standard of living of the workers was lower than in this country. British steel-workers would not accept any further reduction in their standard of living; their wages in this industry being governed by a sliding-scale had already fallen greatly owing to successive reductions in the price of steel; and, in his view, it was the duty of the Government to devise means for the assistance of the industry that would not at the same time involve further attacks on the wages of the workers. The relations between employers and Labour were good and there had been no serious stoppage for many years; but the men felt that there was room for improvement in the management of the Steel Trade. They were willing to co-operate with the employers in their effort to reduce costs by modifying Trade Union regulations that could be shown to stand in the way of efficient production, but they considered that for their part the employers ought to take steps to put their own house in order. Labour was strongly opposed to wasteful competition, and pointed to the successful, results achieved by the &quot; Tinplate Pool &quot; in South Wales, which so long as it lasted was of great advantage both to the employers and to the men. Mr. Pugh was doubtful whether a complete merger of the whole Industry would tend to increased efficiency; but without going so far as that great improve-ments could be effected by the establishment of closer co-operation between the employers in regard to marketing. Co-operative selling would have the effect of largely eliminating middlemen, whom Labour did not regard with favour, and would thus tend to reduce costs, while at the same time affording fresh outlets for British steel.IV. Organisation of British Iron and Steel Industry.(A.) Internal Organisation.17. The Iron and Steel industry in this country is divided very unevenly between about 250 firms, the capital of which amounts in the aggregate to approxi-mately  200,000,000. A large number of these firms, though maintaining for trade purposes their separate existence, are, in fact, owned or controlled by larger companies. In some instances holding companies have been formed for this purpose, and in these cases virtually complete control of methods of manufacture, distribution of orders and marketing at home and abroad is exercised by the holding company over its associated and subsidiary companies. Large concerns of this kind frequently own and control companies from which they obtain their raw materials in the form of ore and coal, as well as those that work up crude steel into finished products. As a rule, combinations in this industry in Great Britain have not, however, been carried out to the full extent outlined above, and the more usual method by which control has been effected has been through the nomination by the* Note. This figure only includes workers on the pay rolls of collieries, quarries and iron and steel works. It does not include the considerable number of men employed on the making and erection of mining and excavating plant, blast furnace and steel furnace plant, ingot moulds and rolls, and in the transport and delivery of nearly six million tons of materials and of the finished steel billets, and in tho manufacture and repair of waggon, &amp;c. These numbers cannot be precisely estimated, but they are certainly very large.
controlling company of Directors of the subsidiary companies; the management of these companies is thus brought into line with the interests of the group by which they are controlled. In addition, many firms, though retaining complete iridepen-dence, have entered into working arrangements with one another, which give many of the advantages that would be obtained by amalgamation. The tinplate pool in South Wales may be cited as a good example of this class of working arrangement. Tor two years under this agreement only British material was put into tinplates, and notwithstanding the increase of cost compared with the use of foreign steel the export trade was well maintained. It is true that owing to internal difficulties the Pool arrangements broke down in the early part of this year, but quite recently the tinplate trade have succeeded in reviving it.18. The effect of these arrangements is to obscure the extent to which concentration has already been carried in this country. That it is considerable cannot be doubted. Thus six companies directly or indirectly control upwards of  62,000,000, which represents 30 per cent, of the whole capital invested in the British steel industry. The production of these six companies in 1924 amounted to 2,700,000 tons, i.e., 33 per cent, of the total production.19. The great majority of the steelmakers are members of the National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers, but this body exists solely for consultative purposes, for the preparation of statistics and for the dissemination of information in regard to scientific improvements and foreign markets likely to be of use to British manufacturers. It does not in any sense control the Industry or exercise any functions in the nature of price fixing.(B.)   External Marketing Organisation.20. The question whether the industry would be strengthened by such a measure of unification as would enable it to co-ordinate to greater advantage the distribution of orders under conditions most favourable for production is discussed in paragraphs 70-74 of this Report. It is, however, intimately bound up with the corresponding problem of the development of methods of marketing abroad of the steel products manufactured in this country.21. Individual firms have spent large sums in developing an efficient overseas organisation for marketing their production; but such cases are exceptional and, in the majority of cases, firms have been content to continue on old-fashioned lines, maintaining their relations with their existing customers, merely endeavouring to find new ones as occasion may offer. There is a complete absence of anything resembling unified selling in the export market. The natural result is wasteful expenditure, unwise and unnecessary competition at home and lack of effectiveness abroad.22. It is, however, the case that the leaders of the Industry are fully aware of the disadvantages attaching to the present system; and their efforts to improve the state of the Industry have been particularly directed in recent years to the creation of some unified selling organisation. There are, however, great difficulties in the way of creating machinery for this purpose, especially in times of depression, when firms which, through their own efforts, have some advantage over their rivals in this matter cannot be expected to sacrifice their own immediate interests for the sake of a measure, the benefits to be expected from which are comparatively remote.(C.)   Attitude towards International Agreements.23. The absence of an organisation by means of which the Industry can work as a unit in relation to its foreign customers has a further grave disadvantage. In its present amorphous condition there is no way by which responsible representatives can be appointed to negotiate on behalf of the whole body of British steelmakers with foreign producers. The Belgian, French and German manufacturers are organised in such a way that their representatives can reach agreements which would be accepted as binding by those whom they represent; and it is common knowledge that the German steel industry is prepared and is indeed anxious to enter into relations with British manufacturers, but is faced with the difficulty that there is no responsible organisation in this country with which to negotiate.24. It cannot be doubted that in the sphere of international trade, as in that of the home industry, much wasteful competition and unneccessary expenditure could be eliminated by agreements for the division of markets between the chief producing
countries. The present lack of organisation makes it almost impossible for the British Steel industry to enter into such agreements and it is debarred, therefore, from the advantages that in this way it might hope to obtain.25. Almost the only serious negotiations for International agreement which have taken place since the war, in which British manufacturers have been represented have been those for the re-constitution of the pre-war &quot; Rail &quot; pool, and this was only made possible by reason of the fact that the number of British manufacturers heavily interested in rails were sufficiently small to enable them to reach informal agreement with one another in regard to the basis of negotiation with their foreign rivals.V. Foreign Competition.(A.) Wages and Hours.26. A great deal of evidence was submitted to the Committee on the subject of foreign competition, and many causes were suggested as contributing to the present situation, where foreign manufacturers are able to offer steel at from 25s. to 30s. a ton less than the lowest figures possible for British steelmakers.27. The most serious foreign competitors in this industry are Belgium and Luxemburg, France, and, to a lesser degree, Germany. Owing to the fluctuations in exchange and the difference in working conditions, it is exceptionally difficult to make an accurate international comparison. In Great Britain the average wages in the steel industry for a week of 48 hours amount to 63s. 7d., while a 60-hour week gives a German 42s. Qd. On the basis of an 8-hour shift and a 6-shift week, a Frenchman gets 33s. Id. and a Belgian 38s. a week. The hourly rates of wages are, therefore, Q^d. in Belgium and 8%a. in France and Germany, compared with Wd. in this country. These figures lend some colour to the assertion by Labour that British steel-workers are being prejudiced by the unfair competition of countries with  a lower standard of living, but no doubt the real wages received by the workers abroad is substantially higher than the foregoing figures would suggest, owing to the fact that the internal purchasing value of the franc has not fallen as rapidly or as low as the foreign exchange value. When due allowance is made for this fact, it is still clear that wages in all three competing countries are substantially lower than in Great Britain and that their hours of work are longer. On the latter point, it is fair to add that several witnesses, including the representatives of Labour, held the view that the longer hours worked are partly discounted by the lower output per man per hour abroad as compared with this country.(B.) Depreciation of Foreign Exchanges.28. It has been seen, in considering the question of rates of wages abroad, that the depreciation of the exchange acts as a subsidy to the employers, who avail them-selves fully of the advantages offered by the constant fall in the external value of the franc, with which rises of wages, though taking place from time to time, are unable to keep pace. Depreciation gives them artificial assistance of the same kind in so far as they buy their raw material in their own country. The only occasion on which it constitutes a handicap rather than an advantage is when the foreign manufacturer is forced by circumstances to buy his raw material abroad. In that case he experiences the full disadvantage of the depreciation of his currency, but in all other cases it acts directly to his advantage, giving a substantial stimulus to the export trade.(C.) Supply of Raw Materials.29. France, since the acquisition of Lorraine, has peculiar advantages in the matter of the supply of raw materials. She has all the iron ore necessary within her own borders in fact, more ore is produced than can be used locally. Coal is also being produced at the rate of 50 million tons a year, and, so far as can be foreseen, this rate of production will increase in the near future. She still, however, has to import considerable quantities of coking coal.30. Germany is able to supply from home sources all the coal and coke required for industry, but the home supplies of iron ore are not sufficient to meet the demand, and it is necessary for Germany to import considerable quantities from abroad.31. In Belgium, steel manufacturers have no natural advantages to help them and are dependent on foreign countries for the bulk both of their coking coal and ore.
(D.) Protection of Foreign Manufacturers.32. In France steel makers enjoy, special facilities in the matter of railway freights for steel products intended for export and this gives a factitious stimulus to this branch of their business. Several witnesses suggested that their foreign competitors were in receipt of some form of concealed subsidy from their Govern-ments, but they were unable to bring forward any evidence in support of this contention, and the Board of Trade have been unable to ascertain anything that would lend colour to this view. It should, however, be remembered that where works were damaged or destroyed in the war the French Government have provided fund? that have enabled the companies not only to make good, what they had lost but to instal machinery and plant of the latest and most up-to-date pattern.33. In dealing with this question, the representatives of the steel industry argued that foreign steel makers received substantial benefits from the tariffs of their respective countries which gave them complete command of their home markets and thus enabled them to concentrate all their energies on the development of their export trade.(E.) Advantages derived from superior Equipment.34. The criticism has been levelled against the British steel industry that in the practical application of research towards the improvement of methods of production it has failed to keep pace with the most progressive of its foreign competitors. While, no doubt to a certain extent, this is the case, it would be misleading to attribute it wholly to lack of initiative on the part of British manufacturers. Before the war the British steel industry proceeded on the assumption that there was available an indefinite supply of cheap fuel. This was never the case with foreign steel-making countries, who were always faced with paying much higher prices for their coal. The result of this distinction led naturally to a difference in the line along which the British and Foreign industries developed. Foreign steel works were at. a much earlier stage equipped, at considerable capital cost, with a view to securing the maximum economy obtainable in the utilisation of fuel. In the British industry less progress wTas made in the application of devices for fuel economy because, owing to the cheap and abundant supplies of coal in this country, the capital cost of installing fuel economy devices in the works would have amounted to a sum greater than that incurred by the use of the additional quantity of fuel necessitated by the absence of such devices. At this stage, therefore, of the progress of the industry it was actually cheaper in this country to use more coal than it would have been to instal the plant necessary to secure the maximum economy of fuel.35. The British iron and steel industry is, however, to-day passing through a rapid transition from a cheap fuel to a dear fuel basis. This is particularly true in the case of the higher qualities of coal used in the finishing processes. This transition is somewhat obscured at the moment owing to the fact that coking coal is to-day only a little more expensive than it was in 1913, but the cause of this is to be found in the coal subsidy rather than in economic considerations, and there is no reason to suppose that the process of transition which has already begun will not be worked out completely when the present artificial conditions have ceased to operate.36. It is true, therefore, that in the question of fuel economy, the best foreign practice is superior to the general standard in this country, but there is no reason to suppose that this is anything but a temporary condition. The steps which are being taken by the industry to deal with the situation are set out in paragraphs 48-52.(F.) Advantages derived from Superior Organisation of Industry.37. The nature of the organisation of the British steel industry has been outlined in paragraphs 17-25 and various suggestions that nave been put forward for its improvement will be dealt with later (paragraphs 70-74) and on this question interesting light is thrown by a comparison of the steps taken by rival nations to increase their competitive efficiency by perfecting arrangements for joint action m the spheres of production and of marketing.
(a.) Belgium.38. The great Belgium iron and steel establishments are of long standing and are the result of the development and fusion of smaller concerns. Nearly afl the Belgian works were demolished by the Germans during the war, some to the foundations; but in the years that have elapsed since the Armistice they have been reconstructed and are now equipped with plant of the most up-to-date and efficient pattern. Not only has the immense leeway caused by the devastation of the war been made good but there has been an actual increase of production. Thus the production of pig iron in 1924 exceeded that in 1913 by 340,000 tons and that of steel ingots in the same period by 400,000 tons. The steel industry has, moreover, since the war received a great accession of strength by the union in 1922 of the Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg with Belgium.39. The Belgian industry consists now of eight large groups owning blast furnaces, steel works and rolling mills. Many of these groups also own collieries and cokeries within the country, and iron mines and factories abroad, especially in France and Luxemburg. In addition to the groups of steel-producers there are a large number of nourishing re-rollers.40. The whole of the blast furnace firms are grouped in a single organisation which watches the general interests of the industry, but which does not, so far as is known, exercise control over its members in regard to the fixing of prices or internal organisation.(b.) France.41. In France one of the chief characteristics of the industry since the war has been the marked tendency towards consolidation. Mutual interests have, moreover, been established between many of the important groups controlling the production of Iron and Steel.42. Smaller companies have been acquired by their larger rivals, into whose system they have been absorbed. The great bulk of French steel production is now in the hands of six or seven great Combinations.Thus the Etablissement Schneider, whose capital amounts to 100 million francs, employs 18,000 men at Le Creusot, 3,000 men at Chalon and in addition has factories and works in a number of other towns. The de Wendel Company, which has a predominating position in Lorraine, has a capital of 117 million francs and employs no less than 35,000 men in its various works in the Department of the Moselle.43. The French industrialists have not, however, remained content with achieving the virtual concentration of the steel industry in the hands of a relatively small number of larger combines, but they have developed this policy still further by the establishment of mutual understandings and close working accord between the Combines so created. As the result of this policy France possesses a highly organised steel industry which through concentration is able to use its plant for production in the most economic conditions and which can present a firm and united front in the export market, where it is able to take immediate advantage of favourable opportunities, when they arise, for the extension of French interests.(c.) Germany.44. The German steel industry had, before the war, reached a high point of efficiency in the matter of concentration. The German manufacturers were combined for common action in a powerful steel syndicate, but in the chaotic conditions following the Armistice this was dissolved, as were many other rolled product syndicates and price cartels. The pig-iron syndicate was the only organisation of this kind which was able to maintain itself in that period. The break-up of the steel syndicate led to the formation of a number of large groups, but the tendency in favour of combined action was much weaker than it had been before the war. Recently, however, the concentration movement has taken a new turn in Germany and looks as though it will form as important a feature of German industry in the future as it has been in the past. Opinion has moved definitely away from the conception of immense heterogeneous combinations such as those of Stinnes and Stumm and the efforts now being made are in the direction of scientific concentration which will enable a. reduction in existing costs of production. These efforts are taking the form of a vertical association in Upper Silesia, while in the Rhineland d horizontal direction is being taken.45. In the case of Upper Silesia factories which have lost their basis of raw material on account of changes in the frontier will acquire under the new vertical
association fresh resources and will thus be enabled to replace the loss occasioned to their finishing industries. This process is being accompanied by the amalgamation of undertakings of the same character, the less profitable ones being closed.46. In the Rhineland, production after the war had been broken up between a number of concerns of relatively small productive capacity. The result of this process had naturally been a rise in costs. An end had also been put to any improvement in the direction of mass production. In this area the present efforts are being directed towards the amalgamation of the most important mining and steel concerns. One or two groups have elected to remain outside, but Krupps, who are unwilling to sink their identity by joining the combination, have agreed to adopt towards it an attitude of benevolent neutrality.47. These contemplated changes, when carried into effect, will be a great source of additional strength to the German industry, and while they may not go so far in the direction of concentration as the pre-war syndicate they will enable Germany to reduce its costs of production, and in the export market will give it an authoritative basis on which to negotiate with their foreign competitors.VI. Application of Improved Scientific Methods to the Industry.48. Allusion has already been made to the contrast in technical equipment before the war between the British and foreign steel industries. These differences have been largely modified as a result of the war, and in consequence the foreign steel industries, the most enterprising members of which had developed research for the purpose of affecting every possible economy of fuel, are to-day more favourably placed than their British competitors. The fact that in this respect the practice of British steel makers is inferior to that of the best foreign manufacturers has lent colour to the criticism that the industry has not taken adequate steps to keep abreast of the times in the application of research to metallurgy, and that it lies in their own hands further to reduce their production costs. So sweeping an assertion would, however, present a misleading picture of the situation. The critics are perhaps inclined to under-estimate the value of the research actually being carried on in ail the principal works in the country. At an early date steel works of any importance realised the necessity of having at their disposal the services of trained chemists to deal with the technical problems constantly arising in the actual processes of manufacture. From these modest beginnings have been evolved the considerable research departments now maintained by the larger firms. In these departments attention is not confined to the solution of day-to-day problems arising in the works but extensive research has been carried out involving the expenditure of many thousands of pounds. The fruits of such research are to be seen in the special processes devised at Sheffield, for example, for the manufacture of stainless steel. Another instance that could be quoted is the introduction of manganese steel, which was only possible as the result of a most costly investigation undertaken by a single firm.49. The advocates of the establishment of a comprehensive Research Association in the industry are apt to overlook the fact that it would be impossible for firms who had sunk so much capital in the research necessary for the discovery of new processes of this kind to put their results into a common pool. If they were to do so they would lose all the advantage gained by their work, full use of which would be taken by their competitors. There are, however, questions of fundamental research where co-ordination of effort on the part of the whole industry is possible without detriment to the interests of particular firms. This fact has been fully realised by the industry which, through the National Federation has, during the last two years, made special efforts in two directions.50. In the first place, the Federation has established a Fuel Economy Committee which have secured the services of Professor Bone, F.R.S., of the Imperial College of Science and Technology. The object of the Committee is to investigate questions of fuel economy as applied to metallurgical processes and collate and distribute information regarding the subject and to co-operate with other bodies engaged in similar work in other industries. Local Committees composed of Directors and General Managers engaged in practical production have been set up in six principal steel-making areas of the country. In addition a Fuel Officer has been appointed to co-ordinate the work of the Federation and to establish connection with other authorities throughout the world engaged on similar enquiries, the results of which are communicated to the industry from time to time in special reports. Close touch [13829] c
has also been established with the Fuel Research Board and with the technical departments of Universities engaged on similar work. Arrangements have also been made for the interchange of information with the directors of research in. other institutions in this country and with the French Coal Research Committee and the leading fuel technologists in this and other countries.51. A general survey has been made of fuel consumption in British practice in connection with the production of pig-iron, the production of steel by the open hearth process and the manufacture of finished steel. Blast furnace practice has been examined in considerable detail, while substantial progress has been made in the investigation of open hearth practice. A general survey of rolling mill practice has also been made. As regards blast furnace practice, the results obtained show that while British practice at first sight compares unfavourably with that of the United States and the Continent, this may be accounted for by reason of the lower proportion of iron in the ores and the better quality of iron produced, which involves increased fuel consumption. In the open hearth practice the best works in this country are at least as good, and in some cases better, than those abroad, though on the average fuel consumption is higher in Great Britain owing to the better quality of British as compared with continental steel. In the rolling mills British practice is, however, inferior to that of the Continent for the reasons which have been dealt with in paragraphs        of this report.52. New processes and equipment are constantly being investigated by the Fuel Committee, and where desirable particulars are circulated to the industry. Research has also been inaugurated in connection with coke properties in collaboration with the Fuel Research Board, and investigations have been undertaken by Professor Bone in collaboration with the Imperial College of Science and Technology in connection with blast furnace reactions.VII. Possible Methods of Assisting the Industry.53. From the evidence laid before them it is clear that there are only three main lines that Government assistance could follow, though each form could, no doubt, be subject to many possible variations : (a.) It would be possible, after a favourable report from a Safeguarding Committee, for the Government to introduce some form of tariff protection for the industry under the Safeguarding of Industries Act.(6.) The Government might decide that some form of subsidy would be preferable to the imposition of a tariff.(c.) The Government might consider that the objections to either of the above courses. were so great as to render them impracticable, and might endeavour to ease the present difficulties by assisting the industry to secure greater internal efficiency by closer concentration and by more effective co-ordination, both of production and of marketing.54. Both the grant of tariff protection and of a subsidy involve mainly political considerations, and it is not proposed therefore to do more than outline very briefly the arguments submitted to the Committee in regard to these proposals. The third alternative, however, does not raise any acute political question.VIII. Protection by Tariff.(a.) total prohibition of imports.55. Protection under the Safeguarding of Industries procedure has been demanded by the four principal sections of the industry, namely : (1.) The Pig-iron Industry.(2.) The Wrought Iron Industry.(3.) The Heavy Steel Trade.(4.) The Wire Trade.56. The substance of the arguments put before the Committee by the Industry amounts to this : At the present time British steel production is approximately 8,000,000 tons per annum, while crude foreign steel imports amount to 2,400,000 tons per annum.   British plants are at present working at 60 per cent, of their full
effective capacity, with the result that their overhead charges are proportionately increased. On the other hand, existing plant in this country could without difficulty make the whole of the 2,400,000 tons of foreign steel now imported. If British steel makers were put in a position to manufacture this additional, amount they would be able to run their plants at much nearer their full effective capacity ; this would enable them to reduce their overhead charges and, consequently, to reduce the cost of pro-duction of British steel. The industry argue that the economies that would follow from this increased production would enable them to reduce the cost of production bv, say, 10s. a ton. They do not claim that the whole of this reduction would be passed on in the shape of reduced prices to the users of higher forms of steel products, but they argue that a proportion say, 5s. would be passed on in this way,&quot;the remainder being retained by the industry as remuneration of the capital invested, on which for a number of years no dividends have been paid.57. In order that these economies may be realised, the Industry ask the Government to impose a tariff on imported iron and steel at a rate which in effect would amount to prohibition.58. The steel which is now imported and which would be excluded under pro-hibition comes mainly from Belgium and France, and to a certain extent from Germany. On the question of the probable course of action that foreign manufaturers-turers faced with prohibition would adopt, the industry are by no means unanimous. The advocates of protection agree that foreign manufacturers would undoubtedly attempt to increase their present sales in neutral markets by further price-cutting, hut they argue that very little success would result from these efforts, as prices are already cut to the lowest possible figure and markets extended to their utmost capacity. The result, in their opinion, would be that the foreign manufacturers would have to reduce their output, absorbing any existing surplus stocks by going on short time. It would follow from this that the foreign steel works affected would, on the introduction of prohibition, be forced to run at a lower percentage of their full capacity, with the result that their costs of production would rapidly rise, at a time when, ex hypothesi, the corresponding costs in British works would be going down. There would, therefore, be&apos; two forces at work tending to bring British and foreign steel prices into closer correspondence.59. The opponents of any form of protection for crude iron and steel that have given evidence argue that it is more than doubtful whether such protection would correspondingly increase home product: - thus benefiting producers to the extent anticipated. Protection of this kind woui^, in their view, intensify the competition in foreign markets and, so far as higher grade manufacturers are concerned, in the British market also, since the bulk of the excluded imports would necessarily find a market elsewhere. Further, owing to the difference, at present amounting to, say, 30s., between the cost of British and foreign steel, the anticipated reduction of 5s. in the cost of British steel would mean that manufacturers who had been in the habit of using foreign steel would be faced with an increase of 25s. per ton (i.e., the difference between 30s. and 5s.) in the cost of their raw material. The only way that such manufacturers could be compensated would be by bounty or subsidy at substantial cost to the Exchequer. This consideration would be of greater importance to the export than to the import trade. A policy of bounty on exports, if adopted, might give rise to retaliatory action in the United States and other countries. Finally, the opponents of the application -put forward by the industry argue that it would be impossible to single out one raw material, such as steel, for protection, as if once such protection was given it would inevitably lead to the imposition of import duties on higher-grade manufactures of iron and steel. In view of the enormous number and variety of such articles, duties embracing the whole field would constitute a substantial advance towards a general tariff.60. It should be observed that on the following important points the industry have either no definite view or else speak with a divided voice : 61. (a) It is common ground that a substantial proportion of the foreign steel at present imported is used in the manufacture of articles subsequently exported. If the precedent of previous safeguarding duties were followed the tariff would include provisions for drawback on such exports When questioned regarding their attitude to such a proposal the representatives of the industry admitted that they had reached no conclusion on this matter. Their evidence as a whole tended against the imposition of a drawback, as, if granted, it would let in a substantial amount of the foreign steel now imported which under their argument ought to be excluded so that by expanding their production they could reduce their cost of production. [13829] L c 2
It is probable, therefore, that the bulk of the steel makers represented by the National Federation would be opposed to a drawback. If this view were adopted it is difficult to see how the Government could resist the claim of the users of foreign steel, themselves the subject of keen foreign competition, for corresponding compensation in the tariff.Opinion among re-rollers is sharply divided. This is from 80, to 90 per cent, an export trade, and a large amount of foreign steel is used. The members of the Re-Rollers&apos; Association would undoubtedly oppose any measure of protection, and if it were granted wrould press for a drawback or for a bounty on export. Other re-rollers, including some of the largest firms, use a smaller proportion of foreign steel and are prepared to support a moderate tariff on steel.62. .(&amp;.) Another question on which the industry have been unable to give the Committee a definite reply is whether, in the event of a tariff being put on the import of crude steel, a demand would at once be made by the British manufacturers of higher-grade steel products to receive similar protection against competing foreign imports. The experience of the Silk duty, when the most insistent demands were made that the tariff should be pressed to its utmost logical conclusion, suggests that irresistible pressure would be exerted by the higher branches of the steel industry to secure that the tariff on steel embraced everything up to the highest grades and included within its scope even the smallest quantities of steel imported in whatever way into this country. Not only is the industry, therefore, without any agreed opinion on these important questions which would require decision in the event of a tariff, but up to the present they have not reached any definite terms of agreement with the interests that would be affected if protection were given to crude steel. Many of the re-rollers would object uncompromisingly to any such proposal, and no means have been suggested by which this opposition could be satisfied. The steel makers are averse from a drawback, while the re-rollers are staunch in their claim for the grant of compensation in some form if the price of their raw material is to be increased.63. The shipbuilding industry as one of the chief home-customers of the steel trade are keenly interested in any measure that would have the effect of raising their costs of production. No definite agreement has been reached between the two industries on this important question, though the steel makers claim that the shipbuilding industry will not oppose their application if they were to agree to a drawback on foreign steel used for ship plates. If this were granted the shipbuilders are said to be willing not to press for similar compensation in the case of angles and shapes.64. The attitude of the ship-owning industry as represented to the Committee appears to be opposed to the grant of protection to iron and steel. A considerable amount of foreign steel is at present being used by British shipbuilders, and if such steel were subject to a duty or if lyy prohibition shipbuilders were forced to use British steel, the increase of price that would follow would only increase the difficulties with which shipowners are faced in giving orders to British shipbuilders. For these reasons, shipowners hold that the grant of protection would tend to set a premium on the building of ships abroad rather than in this country. They are prepared to admit that protection should be given to steel if it could be proved that this course was essential for the national interest, but at present they are quite unconvinced that this is the case.65. As regards the engineering industry the evidence received appears to indicate that the majority of the industry would probably not oppose protection for the steel trade if that protection was fixed at a moderate figure. In the first place, the great bulk of the steel used in engineering is said to be British steel and to this extent the exclusion of foreign steel would have no adverse effect on the industry. In so far as foreign steel is used a moderate duty of, say, 15 per cent., would only raise the price of engineering products by approximately 2^ per cent., in view of the fact that the steel only represents some 15 per cent, of the total selling value.(b.) moderate tariff.66. Some of the advocates of protection who have given evidence do not go so far as to urge total prohibition of steel imports, but consider that the needs of the situation would be adequately met if a tariff of, say, 10 or 15 per&apos;cent, were imposed. Their argument is that it would be undesirable to impose a prohibitive duty, at any rate at the outset, but they admit that if any duty , amounting to less than
prohibition were imposed it would be. necessary also to create a general tariff scale of increased duties on the imports *of more highly finished steel manufactures.67. This proposal is. open to the same, or even greater, objections than a draw back, from the point of view of the advocates of prohibition. If a duty of only moderate amount were imposed, clearly the anticipated additional production of 2,400,000 tons at present imported into this country would not be secured and in consequence, the economies in production, on which the advocates of prohibition base their argument, to that extent would not materialise.IX. Subsidies.68. It would, no doubt, be possible to assist the Iron and Steel industry by the grant of some form of subsidy. Such a subsidy could take the form of direct assistance on the whole of the output of the industry. From the administrative point of view no doubt this would be the simplest form of bounty, but it has the obvious defect of being extremely costly in comparison with the results produced, as it would be payable not only on the increased output which it would be hoped to obtain, but also upon the whole of the output which would, in any case, have been produced whether there was a subsidy or not.Assistance could again take the form of indirect subsidies on output, such as bounties on coal, freight charges, or local rates. There are, however, great administrative objections to any such form of subsidy quite apart from the substantial cost to the Exchequer that would be involved and to the political issues which would necessarily be raised. In any case it is extremely difficult to see how it would be possible to resist similar claims on behalf, for example, of Agriculture, if the principle of giving a subsidy had been admitted in the case of Iron and Steel.69. Another form of assistance that has been suggested in this connection is that of subsidies for specific contracts. Under such a scheme an attempt would have to be made to limit the subsidy to orders which, in its absence, would not be placed at all, or, at any rate, would not be placed in this country. The obvious objection to such a scheme lies in the difficulty which would be experienced in confining it to genuine cases, as the tendency no doubt would be to represent that all orders were of this character and were, therefore, deserving of subsidy.X. Possibility of increasing Efficiency by closer Internal Concentration.70. The witnesses that appeared before the Committee on behalf of the Steel Manufacturers and the representatives of the Banks who were consulted, took the view that without external assistance the Industry would inevitably be faced with a number of financial failures of considerable magnitude within the next 6 or 9 months. Such failures would not, in their opinion, necessarily be confined to the less efficient firms, but would probably include some of the most efficient and best equipped works in the country, which for this very reason were less able to bear the financial losses resulting from large plants working far below their full pro-ductive capacity. An effort had been made without success in recent years by the Joint Stock Banks, to whom almost all the large concerns are deeply indebted, to secure an amalgamation which they had hoped would reduce the cost of production and increase working efficiency. In that event orders could have been executed at the works where the article in question could be most economically produced, instead of it being manufactured, very often under less economic conditions, at the works of whatever company might secure the contract, as is the case to-day in circumstances of unrestricted competition. Plants below a certain level of efficiency would have been closed.71. There are, however, great difficulties that would have to be overcome if amalgamations on a large scale were to be brought about. There are, for example, a number of works, the technical equipment of which is far from being efficient or up-to-date, but which, in the present depression, are able to maintain themselves and in some cases to make profits. That this is possible is due, in some instances, to the existence of local markets, in others to local protection afforded for example by railway rates. These works, though relatively inefficient, are able to execute small orders, which could not be undertaken at a profit by the large and efficient works running, as they are to-day, at little more than half their full productive capacity. It is doubtless in the interests of the industry that relatively inefficient works which,
though, having little power to do good, have great power to do harm by mistaken competition, should be eliminated, but naturally their management would only consent to such a course if offered very substantial compensation. Neither the industry itself nor the Banks have sufficient funds at their disposal to-day to enable them to carry out transactions of this kind, which resemble amalgamations less than an actual destruction of works by competitors who are financially strong enough to buy them out. A further difficulty lies in the fact that there is no unanimity of opinion regarding the lines on which combination should be effected.(A.) Suggested General Merger of Interests.72. The scheme attempted by the Bankers was of the most comprehensive pattern and contemplated the creation of a single huge holding company in which existing firms would be given shares, the amount of which would be dependent upon agreed valuations by Accountants. The principal difficulty of this method lies in determining the basis on which the valuation is to be carried out. This problem is complicated by the extraordinary variety in the circumstances of almost every concern. These differences relate not only to the condition and efficiency of their plants, but to their varying control of raw materials, to the situation of their plants in relation to iron, coal and coke, to the position of their works in relation to transport both for the home market and for export, the development of overseas selling organisations, the extent to which research has been developed, the classes and quality of the steel produced, as well as the financial strength of the companies and the efficiency of their general management. These natural difficulties, combined in a certain degree with personal jealousies within the industry, were the causes of the failure of the efforts of the Bankers. At one time the prospect of success seemed bright, but in the end one of the largest steel companies, the concurrence of which was essential to the scheme, withdrew their approval and the whole project therefore fell to the ground. The Bankers still hold the view that general amalgamation on these lines is not only desirable but possible, and, if agreement were secured, could be quickly carried into effect. They state, however, that as Bankers, they feel bound to govern their actions solely in the light of banking considerations. They agree that they could probably force an amalgamation, but they could only do so by refusing loans to firms which, on banking grounds, are entitled to such accommodation. This in their view would be treating old customers brutally and they are not prepared to act in this way. They believe that combined action by the Banks on such lines could not fail to have far-reaching results on public policy, and would constitute a precedent which they are unwilling to set. They are equally averse and largely on the same grounds to direct intervention by the Government, but they hold that much might be done to; the desired end by the use by Ministers of their personal influence with the leaders of the industry.73. If the Government were in a position to offer assistance through an adjustment of the Trade Facilities procedure or otherwise for the provision of working capital, it might prove a very useful argument with the Industry in favour of amalgamation. The Banks would offer no objection to such an arrangement provided that the whole transaction was carried out by the Government on a strictly business footing and that it did not involve any. direct gift of public money to the Industry.(B.) Regional A malgamations.74. A less ambitious method of amalgamation would be to secure unification of the industry in the various clearly defined areas in which it is situated. If a scheme of regional amalgamation were adopted it would probably be necessary, from the point of. view of efficiency of production, to utilise in each area plants for the manufacture of (a) rails, (6) plates, and (c) joints, angles, sections, bars, rods, &amp;c. If amalgamation of the chief firms making these classes of product could be effected in each area, it would probably follow that the amalgamated areas, when formed, would enter into working arrangements with one another. In this way something approximating to unified management of the whole industry would be achieved, though it would necessarily be less complete than if a single combination were secured. In such a scheme it is probable that about seven amalgamated concerns, each based on a given area, would take the place of the large number of existing independent firms.
XI. Attitude of the Industry towards Concentration.75. The leading members of the industry appear to share the view that its future development lies along the path of concentration, but in considering their present troubles they do not believe that it offers an immediate source of relief. Opinion among them is clearly hostile to the grant of any &quot;form of subsidy, the results of which would be difficult to forecast. It might, no doubt, give temporary assistance, but the industry fear that it would have the effect of stereotyping the underlying con-ditions which make it impossible in present circumstances for British manufacturers to compete on equal terms with their foreign rivals. Having, therefore, dismissed the possibility of a subsidy, the industry are directing all their efforts to securing protection under the Safeguarding of Industries Act.76. These efforts have not, however, had the effect of wholly diverting their attention from the question of concentration. Informal conversations on the lines of regional amalgamation are &quot;believed to be still in progress, but the bulk of opinion appears to favour the establishment, as a first step, towards concentration, of a joint selling organisation. Those who hold this view do not underestimate the difficulty of creating such an organisation, but they argue that, if it were created, many of the advantages of amalgamation would be achieved, though the actual merger of interests, which forms such a formidable stumbling-block, would be avoided. An overseas selling organisation working in the interests of the whole industry, and not of those of any particular firm, could hardly fail in practice to tend to give work to firms whose superior equipment or special facilities gave them peculiar advantages for economic production. This would, in fact, secure rationing of orders, and the consequent reduction in the costs of production. In this way much of the advantage hoped for from combination might be achieved without the sacrifice of the identity of individual firms.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, November 16, 1925.
List of Witnesses.Date of Meeting.		Name.		Description of Witness.July	1925. 10	Sir Arthur Balfour, K.B.E. Sir William Larke, K.B.E.	...	Chairman, Committee  on  Industry and Trade. Director, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers.July	14	Sir Glynn West Mr. Arthur Pugh		Chairman, Sir W. G. Armstrong, Whit-worth and Company. General Secretary, Iron and Steel Trades Confederation and the British Iron, Steel and Kindred Trades Association.July	17	The Bt. Hon. E. McKenna Sir Harry Goschen, K.B.E.	...	Chairman, Midland Bank. Director, National Provincial Bank.July	21	Sir James Lithgow, Bart., M.C.   ... Sir Andrew Duncan Sir William Peat, C.V.O.		President, National Confederation of Em-ployers&apos; Organisations. Yice-President,   Shipbuilding  Employers&apos; Federation. Chartered Accountant.July	29	Mr. Cyril Lloyd, O.B.E., M.P. Mr. Arthur Dorman Mr. J. Craig, C.B.E.     ... Sir William Larke, K.B.E.		President, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers. Past President, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers. Past President, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers. Director, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers.October	12	Mr. J. Craig, C.B.E. Mr. A. Peech ... Mr. Arthur Dorman Sir William Larke, K.B.E.	...	Past President, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers. Past President, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers. Past President, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers. Director, National Federation of Iron and Steel Manufacturers.October	20	Mr. F. Scarf  ... Mr. L. D. Whitehead   ...	...	President, Steel Be-Bollers&apos; Association. President, Whitehead Iron and Steel Com-pany (Limited).October	30	Mr.    D.   A.    Bremner,    O.B.E., M.I.Meo.E., M.I.E.E., M.I.M.M.		Director, British Engineers&apos;&apos; Association.November 10		Mr. Harold Judd Mr. F. W. Eawson		Messrs.  Mann,  Judd,  Gordon and Co., Chartered Accountants. Messrs. Bolckow, Vaughan and Co.November 12		Mr. Clarence  Dalrymple O.B.E. Sir Frederick Lewis, Bart.	Smith,	Chairman, Consett Iron Company. Chairman, Messrs. Furness, Withy and Co..APPENDIX.

</content>
</cab>
