<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/175/0 images: 559-604</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.CRET.TT485 (25).CAB I N E T.WRAPPING AND PACKING PAPER(Safeguarding; of Industries/.Note by the President of the Board of TradeI circulate herewith the report of the Committee appointed to consider the application concerning Wrapping and Packing Paper under the safeguarding of industries procedure, in order that ray colleagues may read It at the earliest opportunity.    I have not yet received the signed copy, but I understand that It will he in this form and will be submitted to me at the beginning of the week.I propose to circulate my comments and suggestions later(Intld.) P.C*L.Board of Trade,21st November, 1925.
CONFIDENTIAL.437    e3 /BOARD OF TRADE.SAFEGUARDING OF INDUSTRIESREPORTof the Committee onPACKING AND WRAPPING PAPER.
MINUTE OF APPOINTMENT. BOARD     OF      TRADE. This 7th day of September, 1926.The Board of Trade are hereby pleased to appoint the following gentlemen to be a Committee to enquire into and report upon the application made by theUnion of Wrapping Paper Makers, in accordance withthe terms of the Memorandum relating to Procedure and enquiries in connection with tho Safeguarding ofIndustries, presented to Parliament on 3rd February,1925, for the imposition of a duty upon packing andwrapping paperSir J.B. Brunyate, K.C.S.I.,C.I.E.  (Chairman), Mr. Douglas Wenham. Mr. J. Rowan, J.P.The Board are further pleased to appoint Mr. H.W, Acres to be Secretary to the Committee.(Signed) P.  cunliffe-LISTER.
f     &apos; - - ; :,SAFEGUARDING OP INDUSTRIES. PACKING AND WRAPPING PAPER COMMITTEE. REPORT.the Right Honourable Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.O.,M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.Sir,The Committee were appointed by you in the terms of a Minute of the 7th September, 1925, to enquire into and to report upon the application made by the Union of Wrapping Paper Makers for the imposition of a duty upon packing and wrapping paper.2. The Committee have held eleven public meetings andhave heard thirty-one witnesses.     The Statistical Department of the Board of\Trade, and the Statistics Division of the Ministry of Labour have also furnished them with valuable memoranda and statements dealing with matters on which they desired information.S. The Union of Wrapping Paper Makers were supportedby the British Paper Bag Federation on the assumption that any duty imposed on wrapping paper would extend to the wrapping paper in manufactured articles wholly   or mainly composed of such paper.    Failing such an arrangement they were opposed to a duty and technically thein status should be regarded as that of opponents under head (7) of the Instructions to Committees in Section II of the White Paper.4. The application was opposed by a group of membersof the London Chamber of Commerce (incorporated) which was formed for the purpose, and included merchants, &quot;importers, agents and industrial users of paper.       It was ascertained at tho opening of the enquiry that the
group based its claim to appear as a party on the ground that it mainly represented British industries which considered themselves likely to be affected if the application should suoceedj and its opposition was conducted in that sense.In speaking of &quot;the opponents&quot; throughout this report we refer to this group.5. There also appeared as opponents to the application(a) The Employers * Federation of Envelope Makers and Manufacturing Stationers, and (b.) The Manufacturing Confectioners&apos; Alliance.6. AH parties ware represented by Counsel:Mr. Kenneth R. Swan appearing for the Union of WrappingPaper Makersj   Viscount Erleigh for the British PaperBag Federation;   Mr. O.F. Entwistle for the grouporganised by the London Chamber of Commerce and forthe Manufacturing Confectioners&apos; Allianoe; andMr. F. Kingsley Griffith for the Employers&apos; Federationof Envelope Makers and Manufacturing Stationers.Mr. W. Oulross watched the proceedings on behalf of theBritish Paper Box Makers&apos; Federation.7. A descriptive list of the witnesses Is appended(Appendix IV).     We wish to express here our obligations to Professor Bowley for appearing to advise the Committee on questions connected with the comparison of wages In different countries.8. We propose before dealing directly with the eightheads of the Instructions to Committees to summarise the main facts elicited by our enquiry and to record our conclusions upon such preliminary points as arise in the course of this survey.
Description of the^rapping Paper Industry.9. The applicant Union now comprises 36 firms owning42 mills equipped with 94 machines, the number of &quot;machines&quot; worked being a very rough index to the outturn of a mill.   It claims to represent 56 per cent, of the productive strength of the wrapping paper industry, the number of non-member wrapping paper firms being estimated at 47 owning 50 mills with 75 machines. With a few exceptions the whole industry is in the hands    of private companies.   The bulk of the mills are situated in Lancashire, Yorkshire and the Midlands. The capital locked up In machines alone is put at over  5,000,000.    The number of machines in operation in 1920 is said to have been 178 as compared with the present figure of 167, and even this reduced number includes 10 machines belonging to firms in liquidation, and 23 not now in operation.   Thus about one-quarter of the industry is said to have gone out of production in the last five years. 10, The Opponents have urged that the wrapping paperindustry is not self-contained, and that many of the firms claimed as wrapping paper firms are using their machines for other purposes .   There is indeed no rigid line of demarcation and the Applicants only claim for their enumeration that It Includes those machines which are both &quot;adapted&quot; for the manufacture of wrapping paper and are in fact &quot;mostly and mainly engaged in the production of wrapping paper&quot;. While, however, we accept the bona fides of the list, there is evidence that it somer/hat overstates the true dimensions of the industry; indeed the Applicants
themselves have materially altered their estimate since the time of their original application to the Board of Trade in April last when they claimed that their Union embraced, as much as 75 per cent, of the wrapping paper manufacture. The effect of the diversity of production, greater probably among non-members than members, is to introduce a special element of uncertainty into the attempts which have been made to estimate aggregate wrapping paper production.    But the point is not other-wise material.     We are satisfied that wrapping paper manufacture is not normally so interwoven with other business in the paper trade as to make an enquiry limited to wrapping paper incomplete or misleading. 11. The descriptions of paper to be considered fall into   two main groupstFirst, those made of imported wood pulp, which the Applicants describe as including:    (1) Kraft, unglazed, machine-glazed and glazed, (2) Gaps and Sulphites, machine glazed, and (3) Glazed Casings, Including Manillas. Secondly, papers made of old paper, sacking and other waste of home production, namely, (1) Brown wrappings,  (2) Royal Bands, Tubes and Sugar papers, (3) Common Caps. There seems to be no generally accepted trade classifica-tion, but that suggested by the Applicants will suffice to illustrate certain points bearing on our enquiry. 12. At a very early stage of the Industry tho Britishmills made only the papers of home produced material, but for a long period the manufacture of wrapping paper from imported wood pulp has been a well-established
branch of the home production.   Kraft is a foreign product which was introduced about the beginning of the century.    Though a few British manufacturers were early in recognising its coming importance, it has never been manufactured in the United Kingdom on a large scale.The imported papers are. produced from wood pulp, imports of other kinds being generally regarded as negligible, though they do take place. 13. The various papers available are so largely inter-changeable that it is apt to be misleading to ascribe particular uses to particular descriptions, but it may be convenient to look upon Royal Hands, etc., as mainly used as Grocery papers and Glazed Casings as specially appropriate to the wrapping of textiles.    The significance of Manillas to the present enquiry is their use in the manufacture of envelopes.   Kraft is used for general wrapping purposes and is competing keenly with the British Brown Wrappings .    It is also indispensible in various industries using wrapping paper as a raw material.    It is peculiarly strong for its weight, and also pliable.   There is perhaps too an element of fashion in Its rapidly growing popularity.    The sulphites again are extensively used for general wrapping purposes, e.g. for wrapping drapery and cutlery, and as a raw material.There is a growing preference for glazed   or machine-glazed papers, which probably constitute nearly 60 per cent, of the present imports as compared with only 42 per cent, as recently as 192 0.Applicants&apos; definition of proposed duty. 14. Recognising the foregoing classification would notbe suitable for fiscal purposes, the Applicants
substituted at an early stage the following definition of1their application, namely, that a duty of 33grd. per cent.ad valorem be imposed on all papers of above 10 lbs.substanoe* classified by the Customs Department as Packingand Wrapping papers or Tissue, with the exception of &quot;GlazedTransparent&quot;.     The classification referred to is:-Paeking and Wrapping -TJnglazed (other than Kraft). Glazed and Machine Glazed (otherthan Kraft). Oiled, waxed and other waterproofwrappings. Kraft (unglazed, glazed, and machineglazed).Tissue.To remove doubts, they added that a duty was not desiredon Vegetable Parchment and Greaseproof papers, which do notin fact come under the heads of Wrapping Paper or Tissue.Tissue over 10 lbs. is included to prevent the admission ofthe thinner kinds of wrapping papers under that head.     Thesuggestion that the limit be placed at 10 lbs. recognises that the British manufacturers could not cope with thethinnest substances.     The limit is also related to therequirements of the Bag Nanufacturers,  who do not use papersof substances below that limit.      There was evidence that from certain points of view some higher limit such as 13, 14or 15 lbs. would have been more suitable, but the Bag Manu-facturera&apos; Federation, claiming to represent 70 per cent, ofthat industry, decided on cogent grounds in favour of thelower limit and we think that this view should be adopted ifa tax is to be imposed at all.^rapping papers of any given description are glineraTly sold by weight the price remaining constant within ordinary ranges of thickness.    The thickness of the paper is defined by reference to its &quot;substance&quot;; thus, a paper of &quot;10 lbs. sub-stance&quot; represents one of which a ream of 480 sheets double crown weighs 10 lbs.
15. The connotation of the term &quot;Packing and WrappingPaper&quot; is generally -understood In the trade and presumably also by the Board of Trade and H.M. Customs and Excise Department aa they have adopted It for statistical purposes and in our terms of reference.     But difficult questions may arise if the imposition of a duty should offer importers inducements to make Incorrect declarations.     This was brought out by a number of questions addressed to the leading fitness for the applicants in cross-examination but the point was not pursued subsequently as a ground of objection to the application and neither side offered technical evidence on the question of definition.     It is possible that a definition which shall be comprehensively inclusive as regards wrapping papers and absolutely exclusive as regards other papers and yet precise and convenient in actual working will not be attainable.     If so, we think the stress should be laid primarily on precision and convenience In working.Course of Home Production. 16* The Statistical data for determining the aggregateproduction in successive years are unsatisfactory and we have not found it possible to supplement or amend them.     A starting point is supplied by the results of the Census of Production In 1907 from which it may be inferred that the standard of wrapping paper production was then about 200,000 tons a year.     But for the bssic year 1915, the year preceding the war, the applicants are dependent on a limited response to a special call for Information made 12 years later for the purposes of this enquiry. Prom 1920 to 1925 returns have been r egularly obtained
by the Union (see Appendix I), but only from member mills and not from all of them.      Owing to the uncertainty referred to in paragraph 10 above and other complications which need not be elaborated there is no trustworthy means of deducing the total production of all the Wrapping Paper Mills.     We think, however, that the following conclusions as to aggregate production may be drawn with reasonable probability from the available evidence, general as well as statistical:-(1) In the prosperous quinquennium 1908-1913 there was a substantial increase of production, though not at the very rapid rate of the simultaneous growth of imports.(2) In the boom year 1920, when it is admitted that the mills generally were working at their maximum capacity, a further large Increase of output was obtained.(3) By 1924, when several mills had disappeared, many machines had been closed down,  and short time was generally prevalent, and owners were in some cases turning to other branches of production, the outturn of wrapping paper must have fallen by more than one-third below the maximum standard.The figures shown below may serve    to summarise these conclusions and to give some idea of the probable order of the.quantitIes involved, but with the exception of the first they have no assured statistical basis,Conjectural outturn in tons.The applicants&apos; estimates are somewhat higher but present very much the same general picture.1908 1913 1920 1924200,000 260,000 300,000 180,000
17.We may add that production   in 1923 and again in thecurrent year is believed to have been on practically the same scale as in 1924.    The other notable features of the period since 1908 are the reduction of imports in the last two years of the war to 20 per cent, of their former standard, which threw practically the whole burden of supply on the British industry;    and the slump in 1921 affecting home production and imports alike, and reducing them to less than half the 1920 figures. 18. It is also necessary for some purposes to form anidea of the proportions in which the aggregate production is distributed between the principal descriptions of wrapping paper, and the applicants have supplied the following table from returns submitted to them by member -mills -Here again it is Impossible to deduce trustworthy figures for the industry as a whole.    The non-member Mills for example do not ordinarily make the last two descriptions of papers at all.    In any case the proportions probably vary appreciably between different periods.     But the figures are sufficient to establish certain broad Inferences.    They show, for example, that the Applicants do not claim a present output of more than 8,000 tons of kraft a year, whereas the annual imports are about 70,000 tons.19. There is a small but developing export of Britishmade wrapping paper which reached 35,000 tons in 1924. This year&apos;s returns, however, show an extraordinary fall.Kraft, glazed and unglazed ........M.G.  Caps and Sulphites...........Glazed casings ............,.......Brown wrapping papers ...........Royal Hands, tubes and sugar papers Common caps .......................4% 22% 12% 37% 23%2%
No comparison 1b possible with 1913 when large quantities of papers other than, wrapping papers were included. It is difficult to form any opinion of the prospoots and Bignifioanoe of this trade, regariing which the applicants offered no evidence.COURSE OF IMPORTS.20.        In the import figures, which are shown in Appendix II, some difficulties arise from ohanges of classifica-tion and the exclusion since 1923 of the transactions of the Irish Free State.    The effect of these complioa-tions is very slightly to disguise the rate at which imports are growing.    The figures are summarised for oonvenienoe below.Net Imports. Tons.1908................ 119,0001913................ 201,0001920................ 194,0001924................ 210,0001925  (Est.)......... 216,000It would appear that between 1908 and 1913 Imports inoreased by about 70 per oent. and, since the full resumption of trade after the war have regained, and, Indeed, advanced beyond the pre-war standard.   The totals for the three years ending with 1925 also definitely indicate progressive Increase.   This Is not the result of a uniform upward movement in the individual exporting countries, but on a consideration of each oase we see no reason to anticipate that the progressive tendency will not be maintained. The latest figures available point to the following as being In round numbers the gross imports to be expected In the current year from the countries named *-
J!  ATons.Sweden. Borway. Finland Germany82,000 44,000 19p000 45,000 27,000Other countriesSweden consigns about half of her total exports of wrapping paper to the United Kingdom; Norway a little more; and Germany a little less.The new classification of wrapping paper imports, which has been in force slnoe the 1st January, 1925, only, shows the following percentage distribution during the current year:-The important   distinction between kraft and other wood pulp papers was not drawn   in earlier classifications.HOME PRODUCTION AND IMPORTS COMPARED.Combining the results of our examination of home production and foreign imports we may state the following conclusions(l) Before the war the home industry was already subjected to severe and rapidly increasing competition, the full threat of which was concealed by the circumstance that in a prosperous period the home proluct was still able to secure a valuable, though not a fully proportionate, share in the new demand.(2) In the period of depression succeeding the war there has been a serious decrease In the aggregate demand and the whole burden of the consequent loss of business has fallen on theKraft.......................Unglazed other than Kraft... Glazed and Machine Glazedother than Kraft...........Oiled, waxed and otherwaterproof wrappings.......52.2$ 28.8$38.9$0.1$
home producer, (3) Although the displacement of the home producedcommodity is&apos; for the moment proceeding moregradually there is no ground for the hope thatit is permanently checked. (4) This process of displacement originated in theintroduction by the foreign manufacturer of abetter type of wrapping paper and itsproduction on a large scale,COMPARATIVE POSTS AND PRICES. The Applicants claim that the cost of producing their papers, plus 5 per cent, for profit, exceeds the prices of the corresponding foreign papers by amounts ranging from, roughly  5.10s, to  Q.,10s. a ton.   The prices of imported papers which they quote for this purpose, viz., from  21 to  22,, 10s. are not seriously disputed though there is perhaps some tendency for prices to rise.There can, we think, be no real doubt that at this low level not one country only, but several, are able to compete without actual loss.   Sweden has increased her exports to the United Kingdom by about 33 per cent, since 1923 and Finland by about 20 per cent. German exports in 1923 were assisted by currency depreciation and now, with rising wages and a stabilised currency, show some falling off from the peak figure of that year.   But the absolute amount is still large and may, we think, at any time expand again,   Norway is temporarily hampered by an abnormal currency situation and it may be the case,  as suggested to us in evidence, that she is fulfilling some of her contracts at a loss.   But in her case too the
exports to the United Kingdom are now 33 per cent, higher than in 1923 .Turning to the British side of the costs question we find it difficxilt to feel sure that costs or prices quoted for a few selected British papers are fully representative,   The number of varieties is enormous and the price range a very wide ono.    tfe have found less evidence than might have been expected that the wrapping paper manufacturers have been willing,  as the engineering industry has been willing, to sell at bed rook prices in order to keep their mills at work, but one clear instance was brought out by the opponents in which a firm was regularly obtaining large supplies of a paper containing mechanical pulp from British makers at only  2 above the importers&apos; price.   An important witness for the Applicants put the typical difference in his own case at  5 a ton and a buyer for a large confectionery firm cited by the opponents similarly gave  4,15s, as an illustrative figure in the case of kraft.   The Applicants are in fact selling their products and the production of the member mills has now for several years remained fairly uniform. The Applicants claim that the tendency is for the British mills to receive only the small, special and emergency orders - the &quot;crumbs&quot; of the trade - and there is doubtles much truth in this picture; but even so a margin of  9 is far too wide for the maintenance of continuous business.    On the whole we may perhaps assume that the distance to be bridged does not in normal cases exceed  5 or  6 a ton.     If the disparity Is higher for some grades the fact may be taken to imply either that the British maker cannot manufacture them with reasonable economy or that they represent special descriptions of
paper made to particular orders and are not really subject to the competition of the large  scale Scandinavian production, 25. It should be noticed that in whatever disparityexists the circumstances that the British mills are generally working short time is an important factor accounting for as much as  2 a ton in British costs and pr ic e s ..26. As the papers made from home produced materials arenot generally imported, no direct comparison between home and importers&apos; prices was offered in respect of them, nor did the parties go closely into the question of the terms on which the alternative wrappings like krafts or sulphites can compete with the brown wrappings which they are tending to displace.   One or two typical illustrations however were sufficient to show that sheet for sheet, and on the basis of equal strength, kraft has a decided price advantage though its price per ton is much higher.Other Factors affecting Competition. 27, The opponents1 case rests mainly upon two contentions(a) that the foreign competition is based upon intrinsic superiority in methods of production and in the commodity produced and will not be overcome by the rectification of any unfairness In labour conditions which may be found to existj and (b) that a duty would exercise a seriously adverse effect on other industries using wrapping paper as a raw material.     We propose in the succeeding paragraphs to present the material required for dealing with these two questions.
On the question of quality various witnesses using wrapping paper as a raw material have testified that foreign paper is essential to their requirements and that they have been unable to obtain the quality required from British manufacturers.   In some instances these witnesses appear to us not to distinguish carefully between the advantage which the foreign paper possesses in price and any superiority which it may claim in respect of quality.   Not all, however, of the evidence offered could be so dismissed.   We think it may be taken as established that there is a general belief in the superiority of the foreign papers, whether that belief be well founded or not, and that in the case of Kraft in particular, though a high quality can undoubtedly be made in this country, its production has been so little developed that it would be unfair to consumers to take steps which might lead to the exclusion of the foreign product.   This, however, is not a possible result of any such duty as we could justify under Head (5) of the Instructions to Committees.   The facts that the bag makers and the envelope makers use between them some 40,000 tons of British wapping papers as well as 70,000 tons.of foroign, and that the former support the applica-tlon while the envelope makers in opposing it expressly state that they do not do so on the point of quality, show that the significance of this question of relative quality may be easily overstated.   Looking to the future, though there is no reason to expect that the British Wood Pulp Papers will reach a higher standard of quality than the Scandinavian,  we think that they would be produced In all the qualities in most common demand,
if the trade and fiscal conditions were sufficiently favourable to encourage development.   During the last few years of heavy foreign under-selling such development has been impossible.29. Another point which has been pressed is that ifforeign papers were excluded the British mills with their present machines could not meet the full demand. This is true but, the question of exclusion does noi arise. In essence the applicants case, as we understand it, is not that foreign papers should be excluded, but that by the rectification of unfair conditions their entry 3hould be so far limited as to give the British Industry a reasonable chance of using the producing power which it already has.    It could fairly soon perhaps, deal with an additional 100,000 or even 120,000 tons, if It could secure the orders;   more than this would probably require time and new machinery.30. The principal question however, is whether there isa reasonable probability that with the aid of a duty limited by the conditions of Head (5) of the Isstructions to Committees the industry will be able to secure any considerable additional business at all. On this point the opponents&apos;  case Is in substance that Scandinavia has a natural advantage in the fact that it manufactures the Wood Pulp frcm which all these-papers are made, the operations of pulp making and of papsr making being frequently carried on by the same enterprise;    that in many cases water power is available;    and that the Scandinavian Mills have the further advantage of priority and long experience and specialisation, and have also larger machines suited for rapid large scale production.-IS-
They have too an established hold on the market from whioh it will be difficult to dislodge them and this, as hag been stated, secures for them the bulk of the larger orders, so that they can work   with continuity and economy.31. A leading witness for the opponents belonging to a firm of agents for foreign mills gave us what purported to be exact details regarding establishment, machines and quantity of output per man and per machine In a number of typical Scandinavian Mills. No exactly oomparable data were offered by the applicants and it would be unfair to attempt precise comparisons, in respect of economy of working, between a flourishing industry in full time work in one country and a distressed Industry in another which for the moment Is barely able to keep going.   Apart from this, the particulars given did not admit of check either by this Committee or by the witness himself;   and they were ultimately, of course, supplied by foreign manufacturers deeply interested in the result of this enquiry.   On the whole   we do not think   that we can attach importance to this contribution   to the evidence except   in so far as it is confirmatory of the more general statements summarised in the preceding     paragraph.32. Looking now to the organisation of production on theBritish side, we must note that if a duty be imposed, the British Industry will still find itself burdened by two definite handicaps.   (1) Its present production of Kraft is on a small scale and confined to a few makers, whereas in Scandinavia the manufacture of Kraft on a large scale has been carried to a high degree of
A E K *i *Jefficiency,     (2) It seems likely that the use of Brown Wrapping Papers, which are estimated still to amount to as much as 37 per cent, of the total British Production, will continue to yield ground before the Increasingly popular wood pulp papers.   Thus as regards this branch of the Industry the question is not one of Safeguarding it in its present form, but of enabling, by means of a duty, British rather than foreign mills to take its place.33. Some evidence was also given In regard to methods of marketing.   These seem to be defective on the British side.   The same merchants, In many cases, handle both foreign and British papers and it seems doubtful whether the purchaser of foreign paper is always aware that he is not buying British.   We feel, too, that the industry requires greater concentration and provision for specialisation.w&quot;e shall defer further comment on the general Issue &apos; developed in the preceding paragraphs until we come to consider our.final conclusions.Use of Wrapping Paper in other Industries.34. fife now turn to the second question mentioned inparagraph 27 above.   Wrapping paper is used by:-(a) The distributing trades generally.(b) Industries generally for ordinary wrapping purposes.(c) Certain industries in which, though the articlesold is not made of paper, the character of the wrapping or container is an important factor in its saleability.(d) Certain Industries for which wrapping paper isthe principal raw material.We shall confine our remarks to the last two classes, on which the effects of a duty would be more important.
The third has special reference to the oase of the Confectionery Manufacturers who are one of the separate oppositions to this Application.   The principal Industrie included In the Fourth Class are the Bag Manufacturers, who stand alone in supporting the application, and the Envelope Makers who have organised a separate opposition against it, but the number of minor industries using paper as raw material is considerable, and it may be taken that they are In every case strongly opposed to a duty on any terms.   A list handed in by the opponents is attached as Appendix III.   From the facts brought out in evidence it would appear that the industries in the Third and Fourth Classes in paragraph 34 utilise as much as 90,000 tons of foreign paper and 50,000 tons of British paper in their products.   The figures may, indeed be higher.   A precise estimate of the total amount exported in the form of manufactured products Is impossible to make, but the amount Is probably over 10,000 tons.These industries are all united on one point, namely that a duty Imposed oh wrapping paper 3hould extend to the wrapping paper contained In articles made wholly or mainly therefrom, otherwise a duty meant to safeguard British industry would in the case of the manufactured article operate as a bounty on imports, and as the evidence shows and as might in any case have been anticipated would be disastrous in its effects. This is so obvious in such cases, for example, as bags and envelopes, that we have felt It right to assume that we should not have been called upon to make this enquiry at all without implicit authority to recommend the
4s /extension of any proposed duty on paper to the paper contained in paper made goods, and we so ruled at an early stage of the enquiry. The evidence heard in pursuance of that ruling would in any case have been relevant, and for the most part necessary,under head (7) of the Instructions to Committees.36. The question, however,  is not so straightforwardin the case of articles in which the cost of the paper used Is a less important element.   &apos;Are may perhaps offer the suggestion that no manufactured article should be taxed on import in respect of dutiable paper contained in it if the value of such paper,  as raw material, is less than 15 per cent, of the cost of the completed article. Our idea would be that this should be laid down in the Bill and that a power should also be taken In the Bill to specify from time to time by rule or order the classes of articles which contain wrapping paper to the extent indicated. The alternative of specifying these articles in the Bill in the first instance, and finally, would probably involve omissions and lead to some industries being heavily penalised in their own home markets.    This we think should not be allowed even in the case of quite minor industries.We take, it, that in the case of imported goods not themselves dutiable in respect of wrapping paper, no duty would be levied in respect of the wrappings or containers in which they were packed.37. It is doubtless also anticipated by the industriesaffected that there would be a drawback on exported articles manufactured from dutiable paper.  It appears, however,  that a right of this kind has not hitherto been  conceded by law and it is doubtful whether it could
&quot;be satisfactorily worked In practice. The precedent on this point is Section 12(1) of the Safeguarding of Industries Act, 1921, which does not appear to cover articles which have changed their state after the importation of the raw material. In any case, the task of identifying the constitutent material as of foreign and not of home origin would seem insuperable in practice unless elaborate machinery were devised. While, therefore, a system of drawback is much to be desired, if practicable, we think it safer to base our conclusions on the assumption that this will not be found possible. We proceed, then, to examine the effect of an import duty on paper in relation to manufactured goods on the basis (i) that the duty would extend to the paper included in imported goods, subject to some provision such as that stated in paragraph 36 and (ii) that there would In practice be no drawback. 38. The Manufacturing Confectioners are a large industryemploying 84,000 workers and paying over  10,000,000 a year in wages. Their export trade is an Important, and at present somewhat depressed, section of their business, the exports having fallen from about 30,000 tons in 1913 to 18,000, tons in 19 24. This is due to foreign competition, heavy tariffs and increasing local manufacture, to meet which British firms are already beginning to establish factories in the markets which they formerly served from Great Britain. The whole case was very fully put before us. In some lines the cost of the wrapping paper used is no doubt an important factor, but, taking their products generally, we should doubt if the cost of wrapping paper purchased forms a higher proportion than, say 1 per cent, of the aggregate
*? *Jturnover.    It Is clear, at any rate, that a duty representing only a fraction of the cost of the wrapping paper itself would bear an exceedingly small proportion to the price of &quot;the article sold and we have formed the opinion that even in the case of the export trade the adverse effect of the duty would not be serious, whileIin the case of the home market it might well be regarded1as negllgible.i59. The bag making industry uses 60,000 tons of foreign and 50,000 tons of British paper.    It is subject to insignificant foreign competition at home and   compared to the size of the trade its exports (about 3 , 000 tons) are1trifling.   This industry supports the application on the grounds, first, of its sympathy with the difficulties of the wrapping paper industry and, second, of its apprehen-sion that if the latter industry is extinguished by foreign    1 competition the bag making Industry must sooner or laterIffollow.   Some bag makers it is true, have appeared to oppose the application in their individual capacity, but we do not find in their evidence anything to outweigh the concensus of opinion Indicated by the decision of the Paper Bag Federation as a whole to support the application. It has been urged by way of discounting the significance of this decision that a number of bag makers are also Paper Manufacturers.   But this is very rarely the case and we do not attach importance to this objection.   Thus, the position here is that the industry concerned, is in the .1main satisfied that the duty will tend to increase its security and is prepared to accept any disadvantages that may accrue from higher prices and slightly diminished demand in the home market and from the possibly greater Injury which may be done to its relatively unimportant export&apos;trade.40. The envelope makers are interested in the cheap
Machine Glazed Manilla envelope.      It is calculated that this Section Of the entire envelope making Industry utilizes 10,000 tons of imported and 10,000 tons of British wrapping paper annually and employs 2,400 people.     The exports of envelopes of all kinds, which are rapidly growing, amount to about 2,500 tons in quantity and  200,000 in value but we are unable to state what portion of these amounts represents envelopes made from wrapping paper.    The home trade is not subject to serious foreign&apos;competition but is said to be largely dependent upon the envelopes being obtainable at a low enough price to permit of their use for many minor packing purposes where otherwise plain paper would be employed and also for cheap advertising purposes and so forth.    The export trade was pronounced by the industrial Court in October, 1923, to be carried on under conditions of intense competition from Scandinavia, Holland and Germany.     The case of the envelope maker, so far as   it rests upon the plea that an increase in the cost of paper would mean a diminished home consumption is not we think very strong.    But a duty would materially prejudice the export trade or at any rate that portion of it which relies on foreign paper.     The British paper used in envelope manufacture appears to be largely used for meeting the re-quirements of the Home and Colonial Governments and for the purpose of qualifying for the Colonial Preference wh-ere that is given.The minor industries can only be very briefly discussed. They are, no doubt, of small significance from the general employment point of view, but sometimes represent marked individual effort and initiative, especially in the building up of struggling export business against keen competition. We believe that that business, such as it is, would be gravely prejudiced by a duty.   The effect on the home market of these industries would not we think be serious.
42. We now proceed to deal seriatim with the eight headsof Instructions to Committees.Conclusions.(1) Whether the applicant industry is, by reason of the volume of employment engaged in -the production of the goods to whichthe application relates, or by reason of the nature of the&apos; goods produce a&quot;7 an Industry of substantial importance.43. The Applicants state that member mills returned thenumber of workers employed as, roundly, 5,000 for 1913,6,200 in 1920, and 4,350 in 1924, about four-fifths ofthese being male.   For non-member mills another 60$should perhaps be added, but it is not really possible tomake an estimate.    The industry also gave employment(not included in the foregoing figures) to other workers engaged in collecting and transporting the raw material.The goods produced are an article of the most widelyspread necessity, and the continued existence of the home industry might prove a valuable safeguard againstcombinations abroad to raise prices.    On the other hand the industry must always be dependent on foreign producersas regards the price at which it can get its importedwood pulp.We reply to both heads of this question in the affirmative, though with less emphasis as regards the second part.(2) Whether foreign goods of the class or description to which the application relates are being &quot;Imported&quot; into and retained for consumption in the united Kingdom in abnormal quantities.44. The retained foreign imports are now about 5$ higherthan those of 1913, a change of volume which considered by itself is not abnormal.    They constitute about 54$ ofthe combined net imports and home production,  as we estimate it, as against 44$ In 1913 and 37$ in 1908.On the same estimates the decrease since 1913 is about
4p s% &amp;&amp;70,000 tons, a figure which represents a loss by thehome industry of 80,000 tons counterbalanced to theextent of 10,000 tons by additional Imports.   No doubt,as -we have already stated, the precise figures of thehome out-turn are very uncertain, but the general tendencyis beyond question.   There can be no reasonable doubtthat imports are still increasing while home production has fallen very heavily indeed.    We think that in thesecircumstances the quantity of the foreign goods now beingimported may correctly be described as abnormal.    Thenormal course in a time of depression would be for imports and home production to fall together, indifferent proportions perhaps, but not with such disparityas to threaten the existence of the home trade.(3) Whether the foreign goods so Imported are being sold or &quot;offered for&quot;sale in the United Kingdom at prices which are below the prices at which similarfoods can be profitably manufactured or produced in he&apos;United Kingdom.45. The facts under this head have been examined inparagraphs 23-26 above.    It is not disputed that the imported foreign goods are sold at prices below theprices at which similar goods can be profitably manufac-tured in the United Kingdom.(4) Whether, by reason of the severity and extent of such, competition, employment in&quot;the manufacture or production of such goods&apos; in the United kingdom m is oeingjj &apos;6r &quot;is likely to&apos; be seriously affected.&apos;46. We have to record an affirmative finding underthis head.     The cumulative evidence that the foreigncompetition has already seriously affected employmentin the home industry and is likely to affect it stillmore seriously in future is very strong.     We havealready referred under Head (1) to the reduction ofemployment since 1913 and 1920 shown by the returns of
the member mills.    The figures would have been more striking but for the retention of men to the utmost extent practicable to prevent the loss of trained craftsmen and the practice of working short time or of alternating working and closing so that any work done may be put through as economically as possible.    In brief, the em-ploy ment shown for 1924 is not whole time employment. Returns received by the Wrapping Paper Union from 34 mills indicate that in the past two years these have been closed for an aggregate period representing 15^ weeks a year per mill.   We may also refer to the figures of mills in re-ceivership and mills and machines closed down, some permanently and some temporarily, which were given in paragraph 9 above.    It is a significant comment on the whole situation that out of 223 men on the books of one Trades Union who were discharged on the final closure of certain mills, only 13 have secured re-employment in the trade.47. The returns of unemployment published in the&quot;Ministry of Labour Gazette&quot; do not deal with the wrapping paper industry separately.    For the Paper and Paper Board making industry as a whole, numbering over 54,000 insured persons, the percentage of unemployment has ranged for some considerable time past round 1% (6.7$   on 21st September, 1925,) and throughout 1924 and 1925 the bad conditions in the Wrapping Section have been almost invariably cited as the main factor in the unemployment of the whole group, a fact which points to a high level of unemployment in that section taken by itself.48. We also had before us two Trades UnionSecretaries in the paper trade, who gave fully confirmatory evidence on this and other points.    They
put unemployment at over 15/ , excluding workers stillunemployed who had exhausted employment benefit and apart from some 50% of the workers estimated to be on short time.   They described to us also how, at a meeting with the Employers at which books were produced and thefinancial position of the mills frankly discussed, theTrades Union representatives had agreed to recommend areduction of wages in a number of mills.   This was not accepted by the men, whose wages were already reduced ineffect by the general prevalence of short time, but it is significant that the matter proceeded so far.    In theopinion of these Trades Union representatives the tradeis heading for &quot;extinction&quot;,   The position Is at anyrate one of suspense, and it seems clear that, withcontinued intense competition, the efforts already longmaintained to avoid further dispersion of working   &quot;establishments must weaken and considerable furtherunemployment ensue.(5) Whether such exceptional competition comes largely from countries where the conditions are so different from those in this&quot; country as to render the competition unfair.Competition for.the purpose of such enquiry is not^ to be deemed to be unfair unless it arises from one or more of the, following causes -Ca) Depreciation of .currency operating so as to create an export bounty.(b) Subsidies, bounties,, or other artificialadvantages.(c) Inferior conditions of employment of labourwhether as respects remuneration or hours of employment, or&quot;otherwise, obtaining amongst * the, persons employed in the production of the Imported goods in question as compared with those obtaining amongst persons employed fn the production of similar goods in the United Kingdom.In making their report upon the alleged unfairness of the competition, the Committee may call attention to any special circumstances by.reason of which, in their opinion, the&apos;&quot;industry in the United Kingdom is placed at a serious relative disadvantage&apos;&apos;.
s .fi F-*_ 4 to d^ &quot; Depreciation of Currency, etc.49. It Is not a part of the applicants&apos; case thatdepreciation of currency operates in the case of any competing country so as to create an export &quot;bounty.(5) (b) - Subsidies, bounties, etc.. and final paragraph of head (.5)  (Special circumstances50. No evidence for the grant of subsidies or bountiesin any competing country was produced before us, but we may refer to the following matters as coming under the description of &quot;artificial advantages&quot; or possibly more appropriately under that of &quot;special circumstances&quot; referred to In the closing paragraph of head (5).51. It was stated by an opposing witness that theGerman Government makes seme concession on its State-owned railways in favour Of consignments sent by rail to German ports of shipment, but that many mills nevertheless prefer to send by water.   The concession is apparently not a matter of significance.52. The applicants have put in a copy of a letterfrom the Department of Overseas Trade (Development and Intelligence) No. 3.1718 dated the 7th April, 1925, enclosing a report from the Commercial Secretary at Berlin concerning the position of the German Cellulose and Paper Industry.   The general effect of the report, so far as it bears on this enquiry , was that the domestic prices of certain classes of paper, including packing paper, had recently been raised by 5:A and that the groups which considered the increase necessary had &quot;at the same time Introduced export premiums&quot;. The writer then went on to say:-&quot;These premiums are paid to those firms who export &quot;the paper which they have purchased from the groups
&quot;in the form of paper goods, and amount to from 5 to n%% of the Inland price.   This premium only represents &quot;a partial compensation for the difference between the 11 prices charged by the paper users and those of the &quot;paper factories who export direct, as the latter have &quot;already for a long time had export prices which were &quot;lower than the inland prices.   This policy gives rise &quot;to the Impression that the inland prices are fixed &quot;somewhat arbitrarily by the manufacturers who rely &quot;upon the protection of duties, import prohibitions &quot;and cartels, and that only when they have to compete &quot;on the world&apos;s market, do they calculate carefully in &quot;order to meet competition&quot;. 53. A claim in respect of bounties cr artificialadvantages formed no part of the applicants&apos;  original case and no attempt was made in the course of the enquiry further to elucidate the system briefly described in the Report.   We do not know precisely to what papers it applies and under what conditions, and there is room for doubt as to its real significance. In the circumstances the applicants&apos; suggestion, made through their counsel at the close of his concluding speech, that these export premiums should be definitely recognised in fixing any duty to be recommended appears to us to be in the nature of an afterthought.   There is also no indication that it has yet affected German exports to the United Kingdom, which show some decline in the current year.    In our view the importance of the report lies more in the general remarks with reference to the existence of domestic prices in Germany higher than those at which the paper is exported. Some other evidence placed before us tended in the same direction, but was of too uncertain a character to
be made a basis for action.    Indications are not so much that the German exporter has so far actually-received assistance in a manner unfair to his British competitor as that a system exists in Germany which might at any time be used unfairly to the latter!s disadvantage .54. It was also briefly stated in evidence that theprice of Canadian papers on the London market is far below the price at which they are sold in Canada.   As,, however, Canadian imports, though increasing, are still insignificant, any duty to be imposed would evidently have to be fixed with reference to German conditions and competition,55. For the reasons stated we abstain from recordingany affirmative finding under head (5)  (b) or calling attention to any &quot;special circumstance&quot; under the last paragraph of this head.(5)  (c) Inferior conditions of employment of labour,_etc.56, As already stated, in dealing with the questionof relative wages we have had the advantage of Professor Bowley&quot;s advice.   It is not possible, however, with the materials available to institute wholly satisfactory comparisons.    In particular such data are wanting as the distribution of the various classes of labour between skilled and unskilled in the foreign paper making countries; their distribution by geographical groups where this determines the wage paid; and the extent to which work is arranged on the piece basis. The pre-war data are also slender.57. In the United Kingdom, the minimum hourly ratefor skilled workers is now lsc6d. compared with 91.t owing ..-    -
before the war. For other classes of workers the minimum hourly rates are now -compared with 6d. for semi-skilled and 4d. for unskilled workers before the war when the 60 hour week was in force. A Trades Union witness stated that in the case of the skilled men actual earnings are almost always In excess of the minimum rate and that a few of the semi-skilled mon also earn more than the minimum, but that the unskilled men are practically invariably paid on the minimum basis,   It is also In evidence that payment on the piece work basis is frequently arranged.The Applicants did not furnish wage statistics for Finland though this does not, we understand, imply that wage conditions thero are accepted as equal to tho British standard.   They eventually withdrew the claim that an inferiority of wage conditions now exists in Norway,   It was found that real wages in the paper industry there are probably somewhat in excess of wages in the United Kingdom. Indeed, the recent   rapid appreciation of Norwegian exchang has far outstripped the recovery of internal purchasing power and accordingly acts as a penalty on export.In the case of Sweden, the available statistics suggest that real (hourly) wages in the paper industry are from 20 - to 25a below those of the United Kingdom, but the factors of uncertainty mentioned above are specially operative in this case where the wage is based on an elaborate classification both by categories of workers and by geographical groups.   Fiece work, again, on rates calculated to yield 20% more than the hourly rates, is obligatory under the wage agreement whenever such anFor semi-skilled shift workers &quot; &quot; &quot; day workers.. &quot; unskilled shift workers ... &quot; &quot;        day workers.....Is .3d.llTsrd,
arrangement&apos;is possible.   Moreover, it would appear that British and Swedish real wages have increased to a practically identical extent since the war so that whatever disparity exists is apparently a continuation only of a disparity already present before the war.   We should hesitate to describe Swedish wage conditions, so far as we can ascertain them, as &quot;unfair&quot;, but we are not entitled, on the evidence given, to treat Swedish wages as equal to British and neglect thern altogether as a factor in the present depression of the British industry,60, German wages in the paper trade, like German wagesgenerally, have been steadily rising during the current year.   Even so, as far as we can estimate, they are still from 35)&apos;* to 40% below the British standard.     We have not been able to obtain satisfactory data by which to compare pre-war   and post-war wages, but there is no doubt that the low wages in the paper trade and the low wages generally prevailing constitute a definite Inferiority and unfairness which materially affect the cost of paper production.61. With reference to our allusion to the effect of ageneral low level of wages we may quote the latest index numbers for a group of selected industries in certain cities from the Ministry of Labour Gazette (September 1925 p.332).   These are based on the British food standard. They state the position as on the 1st April last and will at least serve to indicate general conditions in the recent past.u,K.(London)Norway,TosioTSweden. (Stockholm)Germany. TBerlin)1007672In the matter of hours the 48 hour week for theindividual worker is in force in Norway, Sweden and
Belgium and also in Germany except in 300 mills where a 60 hour week is permitted though not necessarily generally adopted.     The period for whioh mills may remain at work during the week is 144 hours.     In Finland the corresponding figures are 48 and 152 *     In all these cases it is perhaps hardly possible to feel assured that the limits are always rigidly observed.   In the United Kingdom the hours are 48 for the day worker, 44 for the shift rroricer and 132 for the mill.     Assuming only a 144 hour week abroad there is a definite disparity which must, we think, be regarded as &quot;unfairness&quot; within the meaning of this head.     Manufacturers generally attach the utmost importanoe to running their machinery at full stretch as a means of reducing the incidenoe of overhead charges *(6) Whether the applicant industry is being parried on In &apos; the United&apos; Kingdom with reasonable effiolenoy and economy.For the last eleven years conditions in the WrappingPaper Industry have been continuously abnormal;    first theperiod of War and control;    then a boom year In 1920 andre-action in 1921;   and thereafter foreign competitionfully re-established and decisively under-cutting theBritish producer.     An opinion on the present state ofthe industry must be qualified by due regard to thesecircumstances.     On the whole we think it may bepronounced reasonably efficient and economical in theordinary sense of those terms.     It has a good War record.There is no suggestion that its finances have beenderanged by inflation and.speculation in the ensuing boom.It was able, as we have shown in paragraph 48 to satisfyits own employees that its difficulties were not of itsown making.     Its best products are of high quality,
cases efforts have beon mado, in conditions of greatdiscouragement, to improve machinery and bring it up todate.   And generally, it has shown tenacity in carryingon through a period of general trade depression and against competition which has boen partly unfair.   Thequestion whether the industry is so far efficient in thebroadest sense that it may reasonably hopo to hold itsown when unfair conditions of competition are removed, isreserved for discussion in paragraphs 65-68 below.(7) Whether the imposition of a duty on goods of tlie class or description in question would exert a seriously adverse effect on employment in any other industry, being an industry using&quot; goods of that class or description in production.A duty on such an article as wrapping paper, used by every trade and industry, must necessarily imply a wide area of disturbance.    It is an added objection thatthe subject matter of the tax will not bo quite easy to define (paragraph 15).   A duty will also operate somewhatharshly in thoso export businesses which deal incommodities made of wrapping paper, and may in some degreeaffect the home demand for such goods (paragraphs 34-41).In brief, the effeotB of a duty cannot, in this particularoase, be localised, or be regarded as exhausted whenaccount has boen taken of those effects which are direct and more or less measurable.   We are clearly of opinionhowever, that any possible unemployment in other industries which could result from Imposing a duty on wrapping paper and on the wrapping paper included in articles manufacturedtherofrom would be very small compared with the additional employment which might be secured, or additionalunemployment *which might be avoided, in the wrapping paper
it i industry proper.     We must therefore return a negativeanswer on this issue.(8) Whether, having regard to the above conditions, ffiie applicant industry has, in the opinion of The Committee&quot;^&quot;&quot;established a claim to a duty; and if so, what rate or rates&apos;of duty,&apos; in the opinion of the Committee,&apos; would be reasonably sufficient to countervail the unfair competition.65.        We have thus found for the applicant industry under all the heads set forth in the Instructions to Committees. We feel, however,  considerable difficulty in dealing with the further question whether a mere reotifloation of unfair oonditions will suffice to restore the Industry, or a substantial section of it, which has been stated at the end of paragraph 65 above and examined in various aspects in paragraphs 27-33.     This question,  though not expressly posed in the Instructions to Committees,  is we take it, implicit In the whole safeguarding scheme.66.        We have no doubt   that several of the foreign competing countries are, apart from labour conditions, better situated at this moment for supplying the papers most in demand than the British mills generally.     We think it probable that, even with a duty, a number of the British mills will not be able to bring themselves up to a oompetitive standard of efficiency (see paragraph 32),     It may be (see paragraph 33) that in some directions the need for better organisation is general. But, while accepting much of the opponents&apos; criticism, we have not felt justified in rejecting a case for a duty,  otherwise established,  on the somewhat speculative hypothesis that a duty wovild not do any substantial good,     A duty, if imposed, should perhaps be regarded as in some degree experimental and its effects should be watched.   But we have decided that it ought on the whole, under the scheme laid down for our guidance,  to be tried,
4 / 367. We take it that much of the present competitivestrength of the Scandinavian mills has been gained during the war and in the long period of abnormal conditions which has followed the war (of. paragraph 63).   No fair opportunity has yet beon given to the British industry for putting itself into better order.   Unequal labour conditions may at least be credited with making any disparity of prices which might otherwise have arisen a decisive disparity and with maintaining thiB wide margin to-day.    Such inequality is general so far as the weekly hours limit is concerned and as regards remuneration has been proved with reasonable completeness in the oase of countries producing well ovor half the present imports. We do not see how we can. legitimately set this consideration aBide.68. Though some of the weaker mills have succumbed andmany machines elsewhere are idle, the industry, as we have already noted, has shown considerable staying power, and most of all, we believe, in these mills which produce the foreign types of paper.   We have been surprised to learn the amount of British paper taken by large industrial consumers notwithstanding the handicap of a higher price.   The home producer too has some natural advantages, at any rate in his home market,  such as the ability to give quick deliveries and generally to render better personal service.   We think a duty calculated to reotify unfairness  &quot;of labour conditions would turn the scale in many cases, especially if accompanied by efforts at improvement which will thus be made possible, and that it will suffice to keep the industry in being in an effective sense.69. The effect of a higher general level of wages andshorter hours in this country runs through all the
operating charges, and is not confined to the wages bill alone.   We think.that this must be taken into account.    We recommend a duty of V?i% ad valorem on packing and wrapping paper, subject to the limit and exceptions stated in paragraph 14 above,  and to the observations made in paragraph 15, and on the understanding that the duty will extend also to the wrapping paper in manufactured articles whenever the cost of such paper, as raw material, exceeds some named proportion, perhaps 15$ of the value of the manufactured article of which it Is a component. 70. We desire to express our obligations to our Secretary,Mr. H.W.Acres, for the great help which he has given us at all times throughout a complicated and protracted enquiry.We have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servants,
1 :cj fUnion of Wrapping Paper Makers - Statistics of Membership, Output and Persons employed in each of the Years1920 to 1924.I(Details furnished by the Applicants).	Membership of the Union.		Output.		Persons employed.	lars.	No. of Mills.	........ No. of machines.	No. of Machines in Mills for which Returns were received.	Output of Wrapping Paper.	&apos;    No. of&quot; Machines In Mills for which Returns were received.	Persons Employed.				Tons.		10... 1... 3... !4i t *	56 52 49 44 42	117 112 106 98 93	97 94 91 84 79	153,448 71,544 94,970 97,598 95,910	92 89 88 84 79	6,181 5,049 5,045 4,570 4,352Note (l)        The foregoing figures of output are based on weeklyreturns submitted at the time. The applicants state that on a special call for information for the purposes of this Enquiry the production and employment of 1913 were returned as135,ST^ tons and 4,946 persons respectively (No. of machines !)jlipnot stated). (iI 11Note (g)       The figures of output given in the above Table exclude ithe British production of Royal hands, Tubes, Sugar Papers -I&apos;)and Common oaps, the manufacture of which Is stated to be exclusively carried out by firms within the Union.   During the years 1913 and 1920 - 1924 the output of such wrapping papers waB stated by the Applicants to bo for 1913, 39,447 tons? 1930, 35,804 tons; 1921, 20,577 tons; 1922, 27,234 tone; 1923, 28,851 tons and for 1924, 28,055 tons;I!j: appendix I. --
isHmAPPENDIX II.Statement showing the Imports. Re-exports and net Imports df Packing and Wrapping Paper(including Tissue) in each of the undermentioned years..    ....   1     ,.......-                      -   ,................    .,               1         1          .1........... i i -                    1   1908. I i		1913.	1920.	1921.	1922.	1923.	1924.	Jfine mths. January-September, &quot;1925.	Estimated totals for year 1925 (based on figures In previous column).Total Imports (Countries whence consigned)....	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	T0H3.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.Finland (Russia for	14,000	13,000	21,000	10,000	14,000	16,000	20,000	14,000	19,000	36,000	68,000	94,000	32,000	53,000	62,000	81,000	61,000	82,000	36.000	53,000	46,000	13,000	32,000	33,000	34,000	33,000	44,000i-1	17,000	45,000	11,000	8,000	19,000	59,000	50,000	34,000	45,000	10,000	14,000	5,000	4,000	5,000	4,000	4,000	4,000	5,000		(50 tons) 12,000	6,000 12,000	1,000 9,000	6,000 12,000	5,000 13,000	6,000 16,000	5,000 12,000	6,000 16,000Other Countries.......	8,000									-121,000	205,000	195,000	77,000	141,000	192,000	211,000	.; 163,000	, 217,Q00	2,000	4,000	1,000	1,000	(500 tons)	1,000	1,000	1,000	1,000	119,000	201,000	194,000	76,000	141,000	191,000	210,000	162,000	216,000									GTS
\ APPENDIX III.OPPONENTSV ENUMERATION OF INDUSTRIES USING PAPER AS A RAW MATERIAL.Paper Bag Makers. Tube Makers. Envelope Manufacturers. Pitched Paper Manufacturers. Label Manufacturers. Gummed Tape and Stay Paper Makers. Paper Shaving Manufacturers. Orepod Paper Makers. Toilet Roll Manufacturers. Waxed Paper Manufacturers. Insulated Gable Manufacturers, Wall Paper Manufacturers, Paper Blind Manufacturers. Match Box Manufacturers. Christmas Cracker Manufacturers. Firework Manufacturers. Paper Twine and Textile Manufacturers. Emery Paper Makers,Paper D&apos;0yley and Laos Paper Makers. Cardboard Box Makers. Bookbinders. Card Index Makers, Music-Roll (Player Pianos) Makers.
APPENDIX IV. Descriptive List of Witnesses. (1) Witnesses called by the Applicants.Mr. Harry 0. Bradly, G.B.E.-Director of Messrs. Lepard and Smith, Limited, Paper Merchants of 81, Sari Street, W.C., President of the National Association of Wholesale Stationers and Paper Merchants.Mr. Archibald Pugiley Burt,-Connected with the firm of Messrs. E.S,and A, Robinson Ltd., Paper Agents and Merchants, importers and Exporters, Bag Makers, etc., with businesses iit Bristol, Glasgow, Edinburgh and other places,Mr, William Clough,-Managing Director of the -*Ramsbottom Paper Mill Company, Limited, Ramsbottom,Mr, Arthur Fowler.-General Secretary of the Amalgamated Society of Paper Makers, Stockport.Mr. G,R,Hall Caine, C.B.E., M.P.-Direotor of Carrongrove Paper Company, Limited, Denny, Stirlingshire and of Messrs. Henry Bruce and Sons, Ltd., Printing Paper Manufacturers, Currie, Midlothian. During the war was Chief Technical Adviser on Paper to the Ministry of Munitions and afterwards to the War Office and Admiralty,Mr, Harold Jackson. -tPaper Maker and Paper Bag Manufacturer, Chairman of the Wholesale Manufacturing Section of the British Paper Bag Feueration,Mr. James McClelland,-Managlng Director of the *Ulverston Paper Company Limited, Ulverston, Lancashire,Mr. John Lewis MerchantChartered Accountant, Secretary of the Employers&apos; Federation of Papermakers of the United Kingdom.Captain William Ewart Nuttall,-Director of *Me3ara, Cooke and Nuttall, Limited, Vale Mills, Horwich, Lanes, President of the Union of Wrapping Paper Makers which is a section of the Paper Makers&apos; Association of Great Britain and Ireland (1912) (Incorporated). Chairman of the Northern Section of the Employers &apos; Federation of Papermakers of the United Kingdom.* Member of the Union of $rapping Paper Makers.t   Non-member of the Union, of Wrapping Paper makers.
- ^ 479Mr. George E. Oswick. -Director of the fWansbrough Paper Company * Limited,,. Watchet.    Also connected with ^Messrs. F.&apos;Tremlett and Company; Stoke Canon.Mr. William Ross.-General Secretary of the Paper Mill Section of the National Union of Printing, Bookbinding,-. Machine Ruling and Paper Workers.Mr. Thomas Parker Smith.-Director of  -Messrs, Smith, Stone and Knight, Limited, makers of wrapping papers,Mr. Henry Gage Spicer,-Chairman and a Managing Director of Messrs. Spicers, Ltd., Wholesale Stationers, Bag and Envelope Makers, ets, - .Mr. Henry Wood.-Secretary of the Union of Wrapping Paper Makers.(2) Witnesses called by the Opponents.(a) Witnesses called by^the Group Committee of the LondonChamber of Ccmmerce.Mr. Walter James Alcock.-Proprietor of the British Patent Perforated Paper Company of Berkshire Road, Hackney Wick,Mr.  Joseph Chadwick.-Director of Messrs. Joseph Chadwick and Sons, Ltd., Warrington, Lancashire, Paper Bag Manufacturers.Mr. G,Ernest Clark.-Director of Messrs. Pisher, Clark and Co.  Ltd., of Boston, Lincolnshire, Manufacturers of Tags, Labels and Tickets.Mr. William Hooper Davey.-Paper Buyer in the employ of Messrs.Cadbury Bros., Ltd., Bournville, Birmingham.    Also acts as buyer for Messrs. Fry of Bristol.Mr. Daniel Freeder.-Partner in the firm of Messrs. D.Freeder and Company, Manufacturers of Crepe Paper goods, Lea Bridge Road, Leyton,Mr. Bertram George Goddard.-Paper Buyer in the employ of Messrs.  J.Lyons and Company, Limited, of Cadby Hall, London, W.- -Member of the Union of trapping Paper Makers. fNon-member of -the Union of Wrapping Paper Makers.
Mr. h. Hans on.-Managing Director of Messrs, W.S. Cowell and Co., Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Paper Merchants and Bag Makers, Market Lane, Ipswich.Mr. Arthur Haynes.-General Manager of the English Text ilose Manufacturing Company, Limited, Trafford Park, Manchester.Mr . Edward S. Jones.-Managing Director of Messrs. Samuel Jones and Co., Ltd., Gummed and Coated Paper Makers. Bridewell Place, E.C.4.Mr. James Ross Linton.-Manager of Messrs. Higham Brothers, Ltd., Cone Works, Parnworth, Lancashire, Paper Bag Manufacturers.Mr. Gilbert W. Morris on.-Joint Managing Director of Messrs. Clark, Nickolls and Coombs, Limited, Manufacturing Confectioners.. Chairman of Messrs. Thomas Smith and Company, Limited, Manufacturers of Christmas Crackers, President of the British Manufacturing Confectioners Export Union.Mr. John Mutimer.-Managing Director of Messrs. Davies and Royle, Ltd., 7, Old Swan Lane, E.C.4.   Agents for various Foreign Paper Mills.Mr. Sydney 7/. Pas call.-Chairman of Messrs. James Pascall, Limited. Ex-President of the Manufacturing Confectioners&apos; Alliance, Inc.Mr . A. TaylorSecretary of the Federation of Paper Tube Manufacturers.(b) Witnesses called by the Employers&apos; Federation of Envelope Makers and Manufacturing Stationers.Major Richard Spencer Dove.-General Manager of Messrs. Millington and 3ons, Ltd., Envelope Makers and Manufacturing Stationers of Crown Works, Tottenham and elsewhere.   Also associated with Messrs. John Dickinson and Company, Ltd., Paper and&apos; Board Makers, Envelope Makers, etc.Mr. T. Owen Jacobson.-Chairman of Messrs. Jacobson, Welch and Co., Ltd., Manufacturing Stationers, 7,. Paternoster Square, President of the Employers1 Federation of Envelope Makers and Manufacturing Stationers.(3) Advisory Witness. Professor A .L. Bowley, Sc. D., F.B.A.   F.S.S., P.E.S.,Professor of statistics in the University of London.

</content>
</cab>
