<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 8-8</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 34(50)							2nd June 1950



		Integration of French and German Coal and Steel Industries.



H.M.	Have seen E.B. with K.Y. – this am.



K.Y.	Many interchanges with French.  Starts fr. 25/5 message from E.B. to Schuman suggest. Franco-G. conversns with U.K. associated. (Started on Franco-G. basis – tho’ gone away from it now.)  That crossed Fr. askg. agreemt. to communiqué (agreed with G.) involvg. prior commitment.  They had sent same note to other Europ. Govts.  We said we cdn’t come in on this basis.  Fr. said we cdn’t participate on diff. terms.  Schuman said we wd. accept addl. sentence puttg. terms in wh. we wd. participate.



	Tel. 176 to Brussels of 25/5.  2nd para. sting. Fr. intend negotns to start with a Treaty – before details of plan discussed.

	Other Govts. have accepted – tho’ some have added reservns which show tht. their posn is v. like our own.



	Tel. 491. of 31/5 was our intended addn to the communiqué.

	Does not commit us to more than “a scheme”.

	Fr. Ministers decided to reject this.  Stressed common commitmt to common aims.  Hence proposal in Annex I. to C.P. 120. – askg. for reply by 8 pm. tonight: if we can’t accept, they will go ahead with the others.



	C.P. 120.  Proposed tht. we shd. issue our own communiqué.

	Alternative: might we propose mtg. of Ministers in Paris etc., ….



H.M.	We welcomed Schuman’s initiative – but implied we shd. want to know more about it.  Fr. want acceptance of principle before details are worked out.  Typical of diffce betwn. Continental and British approach – nothing sinister in this.



	“???? to themselves as immed. aim” – same concn : Fr. prob. thinkg. it gives room to manoeuvre.  But Br. publ. opinion wd. think it commd us to pooling.

	“High authy binding Govts”  may mean, in practice, binding Parlts.

	Also means possibility of closing mines or steel works: v. awkward politically.

	On other hand: if you start, and then w’draw, we shall be accused of breach of faith.

	Fr. are trying to commit us to scheme, details of wh,. neither we nor they know.

	Maybe much in this – on merits.  Don’t want reject it hastily.

	Saw E.B. – with K.Y. this am.  His view (a) we can’t commit their gt. indies until we know implicns of scheme.  Affectg. large nos. of people and much capital.   (b) didn’t like ultimatum of reply by 8 pm.  (c) procedure was unhelpful. 

	Exchange of notes giving rise to misunderstandings.  Mtg. of Ministers in Paris preferred.

	Not much between E.B.’s mind and officials’ recommns.

	If French decide to go ahead w’out us, we must make our attitude clear in communiqué.



E.Sh.	For sake of Anglo-Fr. relns we shd. do all we can to compose diffy. Support E.B. therefore.  But if Fr. go ahead, we must present our case in best poss. light.



	Dutch method – wd. exacerbate Anglo-Fr. relns if we went in and w’drew.



	Pleven told me reason was their concern at developmt. of G. steel prodn wh. might drive out French.  But my hunch is: they are worried v. defence and its cost are lookg. for a way out.

	A strong peace posn  wd. enable them to avoid defence prepns.

	V. dangerous.



	C.O.S. welcomed Schuman plan.  If, as result, you cd. get assurance tht. G. and French wd. join in resistg. aggression, wd. be worth much: but far fetched.  I reject F.O.S. pressure therefore.

	Public reaction won’t be bad.  Press is good.

	Don’t buy this pig while it’s still in the poke.

	Fr. draft involves commitmt.  We can’t accept w’out knowg. what’s involved. No. Br. Govt. cd. do this.



	x/. in para. 3 of draft communiqué is good horse sense.

	Support E.B.’s proposn.



H.McN.	Serious.  Will be trouble in U.K. if we part from French on this.

	The united Europe faction will complain – we have woo-ed them.

	Unusual for us to be faced by French with threat:             [Enter A.V.A.

	agree by 8 pm. or we go on w’out you.  There may be sinister motion. May be Fr. think they can evade defence obligns by this.  But may be U.S. are encouraging them: if so, v. serious.

	Can’t buy a pig in a poke.  But pol. consequences may be v. dangerous.

	Support E.B.’s plan.

	Look for supportg. arguments. Eg. how can Fr. negotiate with G. Govt., except with consent of High Commn.



G.A.I.	Domestic consequences.  If we pool, less for us: may mean unemplt. in our indies.  Prices.  Effects on engineering: exports.

	Must know what it means.



G.W.	Comm. contacts makes our posn difft. from that of other Europ.

	We shd. be slow to go into this w’out full consultn with them – esp. if there is ques. of surrendering sovereignty.	                        [Exit E.Sh.



K.Y.	On McN’s point: Schuman assumed H. Commn consent wd. be needed.

W.S.	3 High Commrs authy Monnet to see G. alone.  Permission wd. be requd for any G. action.



A.V.A.	Nervous of public reaction.  Dragging our feet.

	Contract with steel Feby?



E.Pl.	Preliminary views obtd from them y’day.  They don’t think there wd. be any danger to them if merger w’out them.  a) Fr. iron ore fr. N. Africa: some danger.  b) Slump: if union fought trade war with us, they wd. be strong posn.  But don’t fear its competn.

	N.C.B. fear they might lose some continental markets – no more.

	Full integrn: some advantage to our steel if it were good basis.



D.J.	Support offl. rept. and E.B.’s view.

	Worst of Fr. communiqué is binding us to High Authy.



	Endorse E.B.’s plan.



H.McN.	If we allow G. to negotiate as equal partners with Fr. etc. on this ques. occupn is at an end.  Restores sovereignty.



E.E.B.	Unthinkable to link this with our scruples.  We shd. be accused of trying to sabotage the whole project – in order to screen our own diffies.



K.Y.	And P.M. welcomed G-Fr. Conversns

	At stage of decision, we might take that point.  But not as obstacle to discns betwn. Fr. and Germans.



H.M.	Watch this in wording of communiqué.



K.Y.	What is Paris mtg. of Ministers to discuss?



H.M.	“How are we to handle this ques.”



A.	procedure …. and [the nature of the proposals] wd. be examd.



K.Y.	That means the conference itself.



H.M.	Say “procedure of terms of reference”.



H.M.	Communiqué.  Shd. we issue w’out P.M.’s seeing it.  Cd. we not hedge until full Cab. next week.  And give background guidance to Press tonight.



W.S.	1571. fr. W’ton.  Stories are slanted in Fr. favour because of absence of any offl. statement of our view.  Our case may go by default.



D.J.	Favour issuing our communiqué at once if Fr. announce decn to go on alone.         A. and H.McN. agreed.



G.W.	Shd. press Fr. not to announce tonight.



	Draft communiqué. H.M. and K.Y. to settle text.



K.Y.	Final phrase: intended as red light to U.S. re 3rd Force.  Do we want to do this, if statement is to be friendly.  We can tell U.S. privately.



W.S.	Agree – omit.



</content>
</cab>
