<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 14-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 40(50)							29th June 1950



		1.	Iron and Steel Act.



		Secretariat not present.





		2.	Parliament.					[Enter W.W.



P.M.	Congrats to Ch. Whip on whipping in Schuman debate.



H.M.	Business for next week.

	Korea: if pressure for debate, Opposn will give Wed. Supply Day.  The Opposn don’t want it but Silverman was murmuring.



J.	V. undesirable to have debate.  Room for argument on legal points under charter.



P.M.	Strongly deprecate debate, say so – H/C is solid.



H.M.	6th July.  Debate on P.O. Unions.  * P.M. shd. see P.M.G. re line of his speech.*

	7th July. Kitchen Cttee Rpt.  Ministers are mtg. this p.m.



H.D.	Iron Ore.  Agreemt. reached.  L.P. Cttee will endorse Fri.  Announce Tuesday.

								[Exit W.W.



		3.	Whaling Base on Deception Island.		[Enter K.Y.



R.S.C.	Ty. can be consulted: we can settle outside Cabinet.



J.G.	M/F. said they needed Cab. decn.



R.S.C.	No ques. of principle.  Put it to Ty.





		4.	Electors’ Lists.



C.E.	Diff. to explain to electors how to verify they are on list.

	Up to ’20 draft Register was available for inspn.

	Tried 3 times in b’cast to explain present method, of 3 lists, and can’t get it over simply.  Tried therefore to get back to pre ‘20 system – one list.

	Astonished at estimate of high addl cost.  Told it’s double handling of forms.

	After G. Election series of P.Q.s alleging register was faulty.  Easier to meet this criticism on basis of one list.



H.McN.	Sc. agents are emphatic for change.  Simplest we cd. devise.

R.S.C.	No diffy. for skilled person like an agent.

	2d. per name on register is too heavy a price to pay.

	We can spend £200.000 to better purpose on other things.



G.A.I.	Estimate must be excessive.  Must be a big margin in this.



R.S.C.	We have questioned that already.  And can’t sweat it down.

 

C.E.	It’s double handling of the big list.



A.B.	What is £200.000 to the “Fulcrum of democracy”.  Nothing is more important thn. accurate register.  Was wrong to reduce Register to once a year via two in the autumn.



C.E.	Stationery Office have bn. into it twice.  They got a bit off the total. May be as low as £170.000.



H.M.	This change won’t mean tht. everyone can vote.  Won’t cure all complaints.

	Worst case is when they miss a whole street.

	Advisory Cttee is getting perfectionist.  Postal ballot, poll-card – were “perfect” solutions wh. have brought us trouble.



	Support R.S.C. on balance.



C.E.	By makg. it simpler, we may attract a few more people to look at Register and we deprive them of excuse tht. it’s too complicated.



R.S.C.	Is it so complicated?  If they try at all, they won’t fail.



G.T.	New system (or pre-war) has only just bn. introduced.  Don’t fiddle with it.  Real improvemt. wd. rest on house to house calls beforehand.

	Spend more money on compiln of first register.



P.M.  	Too much money for a v. small improvement.



							[Enter Att.G. &amp; M.W.

		5.	London Meat Strike.



C.E.	Read typed statement.

	If we adopt recommns 1-3 on p. 2. we cd. assure Ldn’s meat supply for next week and thereafter.  But it means employg. these troops if cold-store men and dockers come out on strike.  Post workers’ Cttee is body wh. has conducted unoffl. strikes before – and Govt. can’t afford to bow to their will and deprive Ldn. of meat.



P.M.	This Cttee don’t represent the men.



C.E.	Not the drivers.  They are intervening fr. outside to ferment an illegal strike.

G.A.I.	Shd. this go under Art. 1305?  Both sides got stymied. But even so, unwise to refer.  For i) gettg. more wages than road hauliers agreemt.  ii) Employers are makg. condn of removal of restve practices.  M/L. don’t think it shd. go to arbitrn.

	Earnings are well above £7.5.0. minimum rate; viz £10 for drivers and £8 for rest.

	Object is to embarrass Govt. not to improve condns.  They got substantial rise in Aug ’49.



P.M.	Attitude of T.G.W.U.?



G.A.I.	Urging men to return to work.



M.W.	Shall distribute 1/= ration for all and more for some – but all in corned beef – by Saty next.



H.M.	There is a subtle brain behind this.

	Housewives are getting tired of this Smithfield business.



G.A.I.	Is Smithfield really necessary.



C.E.	Shd. be w. party of officials to consider meat distn in Ldn.  Believe we cd. remove Smithfield bottle-neck.



M.W.	Not short-term because of cold storage.  Considering long-term spread of Ldn. meat markets.  But the bad men wd. get into the other depots.



H.M.         x/	Start a rumour tht. we are going to abolish S’field.



A.B.	Advocate firm and quick action.  Support x/.



E.Sh.	I was for going slow.  On basis of M/L. statement to Em. Cttee this seemed a justifiable strike because wage appln  had bn. dragging on for a year and men had held back because of wage freeze.  Raised again in June when T.U.C. were re-considg. wage freeze.

	Secondly, not alleged at Em. Cttee tht. there was conspiracy with Comms. behind it.

	Arbitratn.  I favoured invokg. it.  Told it cdn’t be done.  There shd. be some machinery wh. can be invoked.  Disturbg. tht. such doesn’t exist.



P.M.	Do you suggest machinery for dealing with unofficial strikes?



E.Sh.	Realise diff. for Unions, in unoffl. strikes, to do other than say “return to work”.  But Govt. can’t allow nothg. to happen.



                  x/	Shd. be some means of bringing 2 sides together.

	Troops have had to be called in 3 or 4 times in last year.

	V. serious. i) effects on training  ii) may create ill will betwn. Servicemen and strikers.



	When “essential service” is affected, Govt. must intervene.  But is meat an essential service?  I don’t think troops shd. be brought in too soon.

	C.E. asks for 1.000 vehicles and 5.000 men.  Can’t go on producg. these nos.  Esp. in summer, with T.A. camps.



P.M.	What is alternative?



E.Sh.	None – save consider x/ as long-term problem.

	Abolition of Smithfield wd. or might cause even more serious trouble with the men.



A.V.A.	Get at unofficial interveners from outside.

	Continuous repetn of unoffl. strikes.



P.M.	Att. Genl’s memo.  Note his position.

	Wd. this be a case when prosn could be taken?



Att.G.	Yes, if informn (evidence) available.  Considering it.

	But G.A.I.’s statement on comp. arbitn makes it more diff.  Seems tht. Order 1305 is dead lr. where Trade Board.

	But illegal strike is tied up with 1305.  Can it be argued tht. strike is illegal if Arbitn under 1305 is impracticable.

	Surely M/F. cd. make meat traders invoke 1305.

	Don’t want to go on shutting my eyes – as in memo.

	But not easy to operate criminal side of it if M/L. side is not being operated.



G.A.I.	No diffy. if evce available, fr. prosn of members of Port Cttee.

	But consider expce of recent years in prosn of strikes as such.  Case at Betteshanger – 1946 or so or earlier – fines and never paid.  Newcastle: employers paid fine.  Middlesboro’: only 1.000 men and more successful.

	Procdgs. v. nos. of men exacerbates feeling.

	Wd. like to see case made v. members of Port Cttee.



J.G.	Civil actions for damages have proved salutary with miners. Union leaders can use it to prevent further strikes and re-assert authy.

	On criminal procdgs. and impt. – that only makes martyrs.

	Doesn’t make for good industrial relations.



P.M.	But are we to leave law un-enforced?

	Wd. like to see a good case v. inter-meddlers eg. Port Cttee.



A.S.C.	It is the action of unoffl. strikers wh. puts arbitn out of possibility.

	That meets Att.G.’s argument above.



Att.G.	Doubt that.  It wd. mean tht. you cd. never have arbitn after a strike has begun.



E.Sh.	Wd. support procdgs. for conspiracy, if evce available.

	Practice varies fr. industry to industry on Arbitn.



J.	Small group instigating strife – if can be proved – is appropte for severe action qua sedn or conspiracy.

	But procdgs. v. larger nos. – shd. end in fines, not impt.



G.T.	Don’t touch individual striker, rank and file.  But get at instigator.



H.D.	Go for Port Cttee and get them in jail. Korea wd. help you.  Leave the others alone.



C.E.	Diffy. will be to get evce. 



		P.M.	{ This gives Att.G. a line.

			{ Approve recommns of Em. Cttee.

			{ Let E.Sh. put his point to M/L. or submit memo.

			  on it.



		2.	Parliament (resumed).		[re-Enter W.W. Exit M.W.



W.W.	W.S.C. ready to help Govt.  But he thinks H/C. may press for debate.

	Must watch their attitude

	Silverman, on behalf of Govt. supporters, askg. for fixed day: if it can’t be promised, will make a fuss at Ques. today.



P.M.	H.M. must watch temper of H/C.



H.M.	Will try the line tht. sitn is fluid, not in public interest to debate it now.



A.B.	Heartily support action taken.  Wdn’t debate demonstrate solidarity of H/C. in support of collective security.



P.M.	Effect on Soviet of things wh. might be said in debate – might push them into wrong attitude.

	Can say: clearly will have to be debate some time, but inopportune now.



J.G.	Comm. Party will prob. go hard for trouble over this in T.U.’s.

	To back up our people in T.U.’s a unanimous decn by H/C. wd. be valuable.  Keep open mind therefore: but don’t debate it yet.



K.Y.	Advantages in debatg. it fairly soon.  But not at once.

	Don’t fix a date.

							[Exit W.W.



		6.	Seretse Khama.



G.W.	Two reasons for tempy visit almost exhausted.

	Had hoped they cd. stay in Protectorate outside Reserve.  But have seen Baring and have come to concln we can’t.  Govt. in Reserve has broken down – taxes and courts.  Not because Seretse has w’spread support outside Serowe: much feeling v. him in outlying districts and neighbourg. tribes.  Break down is due to fear tht. S. will return and

                 x/	ruin anyone who co-operated in interim system of govt.

	Ruth has bn. threatening this.

	Also want to build up more repve govt.

	Local reasons are enough to determine our policy, but we must also take a/c of S. African re-actions.

	Re-action in U.K.  Some evce tht. S. wd. accept decision.  Doubt is about Ruth.

	Decn needed in early August.  The cattle case will be settled out of court about end/July.  In Recess; but in my absence.

	V. awkward to delay decn after cattle case is over, until my return.

	Proposals re help to Seretse if he comes here willingly.  Avoid exclusion order.  But written warning tht. order wd. be made if they returned.

	More diff. if they wdn’t go voluntarily.  Might mean i) serving written orders on them.  S. wd. probably accept that. Or ii) d.o. and force. Must be prepared to do that if it becomes necessary.

	Shd. have W. Paper ready to issue if sharper public reaction.

	Don’t decide to publish in advance.



J.G.	On first decision, some re-action in Colonies esp. in Africa where it was connd with Malan’s speeches.  Apart fr. S. case I’m disturbed at rising tension betwn. races in Africa.



	The feeling over S. has died away.  Won’t be revived if S &amp; R go quietly.  If order – or, worse, force – has to be used to remove them, there will be emotion: extent of trouble and re-action can’t therefore be estimated.  Persuade them to leave quietly, even if it takes much longer to do it.



P.M.	You now feel evidently tht. S. will never be fit to be Chief.



G.W.	Can’t be sure.  Trouble is he is only heir.



P.M.	What of argument at x/?



G.W.	Can’t guarantee to re-build adminn in 5 years.



A.	Adhere to 5 years’ delay and to decision tht. they can’t stay in Protectte m’while.

P.M.	Decn suggd involves ultimate use of force if they don’t go willingly.



G.W.	Inevitable: for weakest posn will be to w’draw if they won’t go willingly.



A.B.	She will make diffies in U.K.

P.M.	Not for long.



A.B.	Pay them double to live elsewhere. 



G.W. 	Daren’t offer it – wd. leak.



	Memo. approved.





		2.	Parliament (resumed).



W.W.	Silverman has submd Motion for adjournment – on use of B. Forces.

	And spker is bound to accept it, unless there is date fixed for debate.



H.M.	Will he get 40 Members?



P.M.	Let Ch.Whip divert him.



E.Sh.	Better fix a day next week than risk debate today.



A.B.	Tell speaker we expect debate v. soon.



H.M.	He will want protn publicly – at least by somethg. said in Business Statement.

	Debate might be embarrassing to U.S. Govt.

	Can we say: H/C. shall have debate: posn fluid: don’t yet know what date was suitable: will keep in touch thro’ usual channels.



A.V.A.	No precedent for delaying debate for long if action taken by Govt. which involves some risk of war.

	I wd. fix a day eg. for Thursday next.

						               [Exit G.A.I.

E.Sh.	Must avoid appearg. to resist debate.



R.S.C.	And Govt. shd. take initiative and rob Silverman of his chance.



H.M.	Then announce firm date in Business Statement – Wednesday.



W.W.	And take it at Party Mtg.

	

						                [Exit T.W.

		7.	Civil Aircraft at Hong Kong.



R.S.C.	Now Korea has intervened, I w’draw my original suggn.



							     [Exit Att.G.

		8.	The New Hebrides.



P.M.	Why wasn’t I told earlier of Spender’s letter of 14/1/50?



G.W.	I don’t know.



J.G.	Summd memo.  Best solution is to put Australia in to bat.

	If we don’t, we shall have trouble with French: can’t leave things as they stand.



P.M.	V. good bargain for us.



G.W.	Repercussions on S. African ques. : awkward but not fatal.



H.McN.	Won’t be done quietly.  U.N. will note change – and debate it.



K.Y.	Warn Australians to play it down.



</content>
</cab>
