<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 27-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 55(50)							           4th September 1950



		1.	Birth of Princess Anne.		   [Enter W.W. and E.E.B.



P.M.	Thanks fr. Elizabeth and the King for Cabinet’s message.





		2.	Parliament.



H.M.	Debate of Govt. Motion – 2 days.  To enable wide debate, incldg. increase in Service pay and period of N. Service.  Followed by introdn of Bill.  2nd Rdg. and all stages on next day.  Bill can’t be available until Motion carried: proposed therefore to produce W. Paper containg. text of Bill.



	Motions can’t appear on Order Paper until morning of 12th.   Proposed to hand it in on Fri. and let it be known to Press.



W.W.	Seen B. Hepburn: told him of these proposals.  He was anxious to finish by end/week: but hasn’t seen W.S.C.



P.M.	Terms of Motion (approved by Cabinet) may be commd  to Opposition.





		3.	Defence Programme: U.S. Aid.



P.M.	Diffy because no assurance of U.S. financial aid. 



E.B.	Have sent strong personal message to Acheson.

	Favourable response fr. France (18 mos) and Belgium (24 mos). v. increased length of N. Service.  Hope Dutch and Luxemb. will follow.

	May mean tht. W. group give equal total in man-power.

	Can’t get financial assurance fr. U.S. - £550 m.

	Two consns on this: a) Man-power.  Didn’t think Congress wd. accept our man-power proposals.

	Pressing U.S. to give us at least moral assurance tht. what we spend will be met (?).  Hope to get reply before 12/9, so tht. Govt. can say we are going on with p’mme and U.S. will pay their share.

	Creation of United Force in Europe, under U.S. command, incldg. a German unit.  I have said, on last point, don’t go beyond German Pol. Force of 100.000. – for fear of French apprehensions.  Fr. wd. agree to gendarmerie: if U.S. agreed, posn wd. alter at once.

	Holmes made it clear to me this am. tht. U.S. were ready to increase no. of their troops in Europe.

	Ty. tell me tht. it will be diff. for us to place orders beyond a point w’out assurance of U.S. aid.

	Therefore, my line will be to agree to discuss Europ. Force in tri-lateral: N.A.T.O. – provided tht. U.S. will make their posn clear on finances.



E.Sh.	We are being pressed to increase our man-power contn to W. Europe.

	We are expectg. to get 3¼ Divns. in W. Germany by March.

	2 extra divns in strategic reserve in U.K. by April.

	By April we shall have more than 10 Divns. at home and overseas. And, 4 T.A. Divns. mobilisable in, I hope 6 weeks.

	Finance.  Disturbed. The first £100 m. – orders placed, in excess

                 y/	of amount. If we get no more money, we shall be in trouble.

	Also announcemt. of £950 m. made before Service pay and N.S. decisions.  We need £990 m. w’out much increased prodn indeed none above the first £100 m.

	U.S. were suggestg. aid be related to specific projects.  Are they sticking to that?



H.M.	Cd. we ask U.S. for more than £550 m. by reason of Serv. pay and N.S. decisions?



E.B.	Diff. to ask another Govt. to pay your men.  Mercenary army.  Diff. propaganda point.  Easier to allow them to pay for materials.



H.M.	Don’t ask for more on that basis.  But do ask for more.



P.M.	If we can get more, so much the better.

	Expect another report from E.B. before Parlt. meets.



E.B.	Improved state of morale in W. Europe – during last few weeks.

	Gt. efforts made by U.K. Ambassadors.

	*    Memo. on United Europ. Force shd. come to Cab. on Wednesday.



A.B.	Queried y/.



E.Sh.	On aircraft.  But not for suppl. this year.  Will be on next years’ Estimate.



A.B.	Will U.S. aid by expd only as one years’ allocn.



E.Sh.	Presumably we shall have an informal understanding.



A.B.	Must avoid Marshall Aid situation on defence.

	(Annual) increase in regular  recruitg. since announcement?



E.Sh.	Too soon to give figures.



A.V.A.	Cd. Cab. have informn about despatch of Forces fr. H. Kong.



E.Sh.	2 Batts  2.000 men.

	In Oct. 10.000 will go – the Brigade Group.

	H. Kong replacements from N.S. men.



A.B.	No commitment to send more Divns. to Europe w’out Cab. authy.



P.M.	We are only stepping up Forces on continent in peace.

		4.	Far East and S.E.A..	[Enter C.O.S., J.S., Att.G., Ogmore.



		General.



E.B.	U.S. have become more reasonable because of diffies encountered.

	Warned them not to go on until involved in war with China, and Sino-Sov. Treaty invoked.  H/C. wd. not support us then.

	No need to get China involved in this war.

	U.S. opinion similar to that in U.K. in time of Boer War.  Because of initial smack on the nose.



	Hysteria in U.S. over Korea – Russia and China as a whole emerging to new consciousness tht. they have somethg. to fight for.  M.S. Tung may have promised 8 m. men, if R. will provide material.

	Formosa – we shd. try to swing this on U.N.  And Truman has now agreed to do so.

	Need to take care of Nehru, over this.

	Have therefore proposed initial talks betwn. Franks and Acheson.  Then call in Ambassadors of interested friendly Powers.  Then a wider circle.  All this before we promulgate any proposals in U.N.

	That method is beginning to work.  Want it endorsed by Cabinet.



J.G.	Agree with E.B.  Importance of emergence of Asia problem.

	Any conflict in China wd. make gt. diffce in Malaya.  There are 10 m. Chinese in S.E.A. outside China – v. powerful 5th column.

	H. Kong cdn’t be saved.  ⅔ of popn of Singapore is Chinese.



E.B.	Formosa.  Recommns in para. 15.



P.M.	Relns of Europe and Asia are all important.



E.B.	Let us be firm on para. 15 G.P. 194.  Believe we can carry India and Pak. on that policy.



P.M.	Spinder suggd tht. Formosa belonged neither to China nor Japan and its future shd. be determined by views of inhabitants.



E.B.	Diffy: we announced decn tht. F. shd. revert to China.  Part of policy of ceding extra-terr. rights.  Do we imply tht. this changed merely because Comm. Govt. now in China?  V. diff. to imply that.

	Doubt if U.S. cd. keep it separate by force.  And only argument in favour is the strategic one – wh. won’t look good in U.N. China, if admd to U.N. wd. argue tht. U.S. held Formosa wd. be a standing menace to the mainland.



P.M.	Doubt the strategic conceptn.



C.N.S.	a)  No peace in F/East until Formosa goes over to China.

	b) We don’t think much strategic value in retaining Formosa.

	c)  No strategic value to us.  Some to U.S. if at war with China.

	But Comms. wd. find diffy in holdg. it w’out sea power.



H.McN.	A good working proposal.

	But i) anything like U.K. imposg. her will on U.S. wd. be politically diff. for Adminn.

	ii)  Can’t get Commn w’out concurrence of Chang K. Shek.  U.S. shd. square him.

	iii)  Try to get Nehru to provide leadership of Commn – himself nominally, with a repve on the spot.



A.B.	Support memo.



H.McN.	Politically imposs. to get U.S. to hand F. over now to Comm. China. That is why para. 15(c) is so valuable.



E.Sh.	Suppose U.S. can’t be persuaded to agree. eg. MacArthur’s recent statement – even tho’ Truman snubbed him.  What do we do then? C.O.S. have said we shd. stand aside in hope conflict may be localised. But will it be?  Look at our increasg. commitmts in Korea.

	But if we do stand aside, what about H. Kong?



O.	i)  These proposals will in genl. be welcomed by Comm. Govts.

	May I inform them of these 3 memoranda?

	ii) India will want close adherence to Cairo declaration.

	    Must try to persuade Nehru tht. this para. 15 isn’t designed to delay.



E.B.	Want précis of all these pp. to go to Comm. Govts. and to Govrs. of Colonies in S.E.A.



	[Agreed].



		Korea.  Line of approach.



H.McN.	If Sec. Council is seized of a problem, Assembly can’t recommend.

	But if Sec. Council took it off Agenda, no U.N. organ. wd. control the U.N. Forces in Korea – prs. for 6 weeks.

	Soviet wd. take the point.

	And we pleaded the point to avoid discn of Palestine.



E.B.	I will take further advice on this point.



Att.G.	Whole legal posn is v. diff.



P.M.	L.O.’s and Ld. Chanc. shd. discuss and submit memo. to Cabinet.





		5.	United Nations: Abuse of Veto.



E.B.	Don’t believe there’s any solution.

P.M.	Canadian horse won’t run.



E.B.	I cdn’t support original U.S. plan of a standing Commn with powers of Sec. Council – for may be occasions when U.K. wd. want to use Veto.

	I cd. however support B. in C.P. 196.

	Can’t solve our problems by amendmt. of Charter – it’s a ques. of goodwill not words.



H.M.	If R. had vetoed Korean resoln, we cdn’t have acted as we have done.

	If therefore this veto ques. isn’t solved, U.N. is no guarantee of security so long as R. and satellites are members.



P.M.	We recognised at S. Francisco tht. it wdn’t work if one of big Powers was aggressor or favoured it.

	Only solution then is for States to act under Art. 51.



Att.G.	R. cd. ditch B. by puttg. the matter on agenda of Sec. Council wh. wd. stop action by Sec. Council.



A.B.	Will be awkward debate.  And will give R. a good argument.

	They will say U.K. are as keen on veto as we are.



	Agreed: Resist A.

		   Talk benevolently about B.

					         [Exit C.O.S. and Service Ministers.



		6.	United Nations: Representn of China.



E.B.	Have made our attitude clear to U.S.  Haven’t had a reply.

	They still want us to vote against.  But no grounds for that. Ch. K. Shek represents no-one.  Not proven tht. Comm. China will be R. satellite.  Our policy must be to work thro’ an Indian friendship with China.

	No evce tht. Pekin Govt. have done anythg. to help N. Koreans – save Press abuse of U.S.A.

	Para. 7 of memo.  Feel sure Assembly will settle this on political basis.



H.McN.	I wd. bury this rather than disagree with U.S.A.

	There are 12 or 13 other applns on wh. disagreemt. persists.  Cd. Ch. be embodied in a genl. resoln covering all?



E.B.	Trouble is tht. Nat. China is there.



H.McN.	Siam: precedent over coup d’état.



Att.G.	This will be raised on first day by challenge of credentials.

	And Assembly will have to decide wthr. Tsiang represents Govt./China – on claims of the two rival claimants to be Chinese repves.



	Memo. approved.  Vote in favour of Comm. repve

	Comm. Govts. to be informed.	

							    [Enter G.S., Exit Att.G.



		7.	Strategic Exports to E. Europe and China.



E.Sh. 	Abnormal demands fr. China for goods wh. wd. be useful to N. Korea. Want to keep the supply w’in normal levels.  Also to get these goods included on stop list while Korean war continues.

	U.S. are now becoming more censorious of our policy.



H.W.	I agree with memo. save on one or two details.

	Evce in July of abnormal orders – persuaded firms to decline.

	Agree – but shdn’t send out swarms of letters.  Limit it to firms concerned.

	Also agree tht. w. party shd. go into comprehensive measures – but shd. consider need as well as possibility.

	High feeling in U.S. over this.  Will come up at high level – and connd with military aid.

	We shdn’t be stampeded into violent change of policy.   E.P.C. decided in July v. U.S. plan of genl. blockade.



                  y/	Distinguish betwn. goods of strategic value to R. and goods needed for re-armament by us and our Allies.  If we apply second principle, we can deny to R. (requisitiong. if need by).

	If U.S. press us to genl. blockade a) they must compensate us for essential supplies eg. timber we get fr. E. Europe.  b) If they think we are so near war, they must be ready to pool resources in raw materials – combined boards etc.



E.B.            x/	On manufacturing for defence, precedent shd. go to N.A.T.O. countries. That shd. be a principle.

	We can’t expect U.S. to give us m. tools if we are selling them to R.

	This policy might affect M/S. on metals.  Can’t deal with this on narrow basis.



	Timber – meat.

	R. sure to take counter measures and deny us these supplies.

	Unwise to come out on so narrow a front.

	Cdn’t W. party give one a v. wide brief – starting from x/. and considering what N.A.T.O. countries can do in return w’out prejudicing our posn on timber, meat, non ferrous etc.

	And let me argue the point with U.S.



H.D.	Talk in N. York. Don’t be stampeded.

	China.  How do they pay?   



H.W.  	Thro’ H. Kong.



G.S.	Immediate problem.  a) to preserve what we or N.A.T.O. want.

	For that may I use D. Rgs. to requisition?

	b) Other M/D. proposals wd. be ineffective.

	Thousands of firms are concerned.  Cdn’t influence them all.

	Also they wd. demand Govt. direction, on security grounds.

	V. ineffective in stopping the flow.

	c) Goods destined for Korea wd. go to European destinations not Chinese.

	And we cdn’t make effective explanation.

	My concln if we are to go beyond earlier decn we must have general export control.

	Suggest further considn of ques.



T.W.	Must not prejudice supply of feeding stuffs.



P.M. 	 i) Authorise requisition * of goods needed by us and 			other N.A.T.O. countries for defence purposes.



	Agreed.	ii) let W. party study whole ques. further – and prepare 		brief for E.B.’s discussion in N. York.

			Later negotiations to be handled by B/T. repves.



A.V.A.	But somethg. will have to be said in H/C. on 12/9.

	Plenty of precedent for i).

	Statement by Parly. Sec. B/T. wd. be good defence, if it’s true.



H.W.	Put it on basis at y/ overleaf.

	* subject to inter-departmental consultn and consultn with L.O.’s in each case.

			iii) Further discussion this week on Parly handling. of 			this ques.



	F.O., B/T., M/Supply and M/Defence can look at this from angle (iii) especially and immediate action.



	Officials first and Ministers thereafter.

	To come to Cabinet by end of week – or before 12/9.



	Doms. not to be informed until after next Cab. mtg.



</content>
</cab>
