<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 36-36</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 66(50)							            20th October 1950.



		1.	Sir Stafford Cripps.



P.M.	Regret at his resignation.

			

				

		2.	Yugoslavia. 				[Chas Peake, M.W., D.J.



E.B.	Not solely financial.  Pol. sitn in area and risks if Tito went down. Trouble = drought.  Affected him – and us too (qua maize).

	Wd. be mistake to make it condn of loan tht. he shd. take our advice etc.

	Wd. wreck our own policy to rob him of his independence.

	But we shd. ask him (not as condn) to be more reasonable re C.K. children.

	Also ask for his help in increasg. exports of soft wood.

	Main objection: to keep him afloat.  Suits our purpose.  Avoid adding to our mil. obligns in that area.  Holds Albania as less useful to R.

	Shall have to discuss with U.S.  But they seem to be awaitg. a lead from us.



H.W.	Discns thro’ summer – various Junior Ministers went there and returned with strong convictions of need to keep Tito afloat.  Was about to ask how far our econ. objectives and policies shd. be sorted on that a/c.

	Yugoslavia said to be worth many Divns. to us.

	Y. were running into econ. trouble even before drought.

	Credit for consumer goods wh. we can supply from U.K.  Cd. do that w’out waitg. on U.S. decn re food – of which we can rend little, save whale meat, surplus herrings etc.



	Extravagant Y. plans of development. – in genl. shd. be toned down. But on some, we are interested, eg aluminium and zinc.

	Timber: Y. supplies developed to point where they are nearly our main Euro. supplier.  Contracts lagging now because of disorgann.  We shd. send special mission on timber – apart fr. genl. econ. mission and in advance of it.  Main need = 100 miles of light rails – and a small price for timber available.  Might double their exports in year or so.



D.J.	Overwhelmg. case.  But want assurance tht. help will do good to Y. and ourselves.  Root cause = excessive investmt p’mme, apart fr. drought.  Unless that policy is modified, £5 m. won’t rectify situatn  Under genl. econ. mission can we see tht. Y. adopts more realistic econ. policy.



	Para.12(b). Ty. shd. be consulted in choice of experts.



E.B.	Technicians.  Econ. advisers are easy.  Operatg. technicians also needed.  Favour lettg. U.K. firms take their own experts.



H.W.	Timber Control + private firms (in that order).



E.B.	T.C. don’t cut timber.  Want to get practical men.



H.M.	Cdn’t we give Tito some economic educn?



A.B.	Careful – don’t act like Russians.  And don’t forget tht. aim of b’ward countries is always bldg. up capital equipment.



P.M.	Advice isn’t necessarily the same as orders.  No diffy. in advisg. a man not to go too fast along the right road.



H.D.	Can be done tactfully.

	Timber is well worth having in return for credits.



E.Sh.	Defence aspects are even more important.  His 18 Divns are well worth £5 m. – defence of Adriatic.



H.McN.	Need for gt. tact.  For basis of their separation fr. R. was, not pol., but economic – because R. tried to slow down their capital developmt. Their main problem = shortage of competent personnel.  Any way pol. acceptable to Y. of supplying adminve executive and operational mission.  Thro’ them, filter in advice.

	We can supply food – herring, salt white fish, potato mash etc.



		Memo. approved.





		3.	Leasehold Reform.



Att.G.	Demand – in Party and P.Q.’s is for propn of occupants of houses under long bldg. leases.  But, if we limit tempy legn thus, we must at same time decide, and say, to get on quickly with permanent legn.



A.B.	My Dpt. agree this is simpler proposn.  But leaves large field of hardship untouched.  Esp. ex-Service men.  Thght people occupying part of large houses were protected by Rent Acts.  But courts have ruled tht. rateable value of whole house must be criterion for Rent Acts.



Att.G.	All emphasises need for review of Rent Acts.



A.B.	True tht. long ground lease has bn. publicised most, but only in v. few cases is occupant the lineal descendant of original builder.

	Many such houses have bn. bght. by colliery cos.

	Crown Property cases.



Att.G.	Puts them in same posn as other l’lords.



A.B.	Doesn’t put them right back under Rent Acts.  7.000 cases already.

	Where people have bought Crown lease and sub-let. People are being evicted.



J.	Support Att.G.’s plan.  Wd. cure incidentally the anomaly of the Knightsbridge case.

	This problem will remain, however.  If these long leases are extended for 2 years, the middle man will benefit.



Att.G.	Covered by para. 2(b) of my memo.



H.M.	Need to get on with permanent legn.



H.McN.	Won’t oppose because can’t think of anything to solve wider problem.

	But don’t imagine this solution will avoid pol. difficulties.

	If we were to do justice, we cdn’t limit scope.



A.B.	Won’t satisfy our friends.  



H.D.  	V. disappointing. Hurry up with perm. legn.



Att.G.	Most of the grievances are Rent Act ones.  And we can’t legislate on that with our present majority.  We cd. say tht. since Ridley Cttee rept. addl diffies have bn. disclosed: we are apptg. w. party to see how we cd. amend and consolidate Rent Acts.



P.M.  	Memo. to be submitted by M/H. to Cabinet on Rent Acts problems.



</content>
</cab>
