<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 38-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 68(50)							             24th October 1950



		1.	Council of Europe.	[Enter W.W., E.D., Att.G., Callagan.



		a)	Composition of Delegation.



E.Sh.	Some point in includg. experts or T.U.C. men on occasion – knowledge of industrial side.



P.M.	Dangerous door.  Experts can advise – but not on floor.  Place for Parliamentarians.	Agreed: no non-Parliamentarians.



A.B.	Ministers: don’t defer decision until Agenda known – otherwise may imply lack of interest.



E.B.	Unworkable to have Ministers.  Must declare at same time we aren’t committed to Assembly’s decisions.  Must make it clear tht. Govt.’s decisions are reserved.

	Also Govt. must reserve right to decide what it brings to H/C.

	Genl. discn of C/E. work, but “ratification” only at motion of Govt.



C.	But tell our chaps what Govt. line is.  Agreed:  no Ministers.



		b)	Duplication with U.N. Agencies.



E.B.	I will think of a different term to express my meaning so as to avoid confusion with U.N. “specialised agencies”.

	Federalism.  Assumed on Continent tht. U.K. will stand out and defeat it because of Schuman Plan.  But we want to make it clear if two or three countries in Europe want to make a federal arrangemt. for some service we won’t use veto to prevent it, and want to be free to join or not as suits us.  It’s the fault of the unanimity rule, which I didn’t want.



A.	Layton has a whole bunch of Cttees in mind wh. overlap U.N. organisations.



E.B.	C/Europe is excluded fr. O.E.E.C. field.



H.G.	That is the important point.  So long as it is held, no gt. objn to C/E. overlapping E.C.O.S.O.C.  May be similar examples of useful work C/E. cd. do.



H.M.	Don’t let us get let in – for paying for it too.



E.B.            x/	Keep these activities off the Genl. Budget.  Then if 2 or 3 people want a show of their own, they can pay for it themselves.



		Endorse  Para. 17(5).



A.B.	Don’t have overlapping with W.H.O. – not enough staff.

		Emphasise x/.



	{Don’t boycott others: but don’t be dragged in ourselves.

	{Don’t have overlapping staffs.

	{Keep it off the general Budget.



E.B.	No def. rule: policy – not to interfere with other countries combining, but not part of general Budget.



H.M.	Try also to get it accepted tht. Assembly shall not set up such agencies only recommend to Cttee of Ministers.



		c)	Defence.



E.Sh.	What if Assembly insists on discussing Defence.



E.B.	We shall have to w’draw.



H.D.	I can ensure tht. Govt. supporters on U.K. delegn will follow our line and w’draw.



G.W.	But next year?



E.B.	It’s outside Statute.  But can’t stop people talking if they insist.



		d)	Convention on Human Rights.



E.B.	Can’t avoid going ahead with this on condns agreed with Ld. Chancellor.



H.M.	Gt. pity we are drawn into it.  May be forced to have legn here.

	And inconsistent with econ. planning – elevn of rights of private property etc.



E.B.	No: I am not acceptg. any of new Assembly amendments.



H.G.	Was amendment safeguarding econ. controls added by Cttee of Ministers?



J.	Yes.  I accept E.B.’s position.  Tho’ I regret the position reached.

	My points have bn. met.



E.B.	Have verified in F.O. tht. Dpts. were consulted.  They shd. have made their Ministers aware of it.



H.G.	My Dept. was not consulted until July.









		e)	Reform of Constitution.



H.McN.	Wd. prefer, if we have any proposals, tht. we shd. put them ourselves 		via letting Cttee of experts have a free run at it.



H.D.	Several countries take our view.  Safe enough to let it be considered.



E.B.	“Experts”: officials.  Jebb did it all outset.



H.McN.	We shd. have bn. in a mess if H.D. hadn’t intervened.



E.B.	Not on Statute.  That was done by officials alone.



H.McN.	Can’t be assumed of cautious recommns fr. such a		[Exit E.B.

	Cttee.  Unless we lay down condns eg. limiting authy of

	Assembly.



H.M.	F.O. officials aren’t so good at Parly arrangemts.  And they did not get it all right in early stages.



P.M.	“Experts” on Parly affairs aren’t officials – Parliamentarians.



E.D.	This memo. confines our experts w’in clear policy lines.  And if they can’t make our view prevail, we still have the veto.

	Statute can be amended only by unanimous vote.



H.McN.	Take line it’s too early to decide on amendmt of statute.



E.D.	Already failing to work.  Awkward to refuse even to examine means of making it work.



		f)	Commonwealth Consultation.



G.W.	May I inform Comm. Govts.	Agreed.



		g)	Publicity.



C.	Make it clear in U.K. tht. if you aren’t Federalist you can still be internationalist.

						         [Exit E.D., Callagan, W.W.



		2.	British Sugar Corporation.		[Enter M.W.



Att.G.	Agreemt. is for indefinite period.  Wd. not come automatically to an end by transfer of shares to public corpn or by end of 1942 Act.

	Wd. need specific provn – includg. provn for compensn by arbitn.

	But in fact is not desired to terminate agreement, but only to modify it. And that is a matter for negotn.

	Need is therefore to put Corpn. in strongest negotiatg. posn.



M.W.	Case is made out for Bill, apart from ques. of agreement.,

	Recommend tht. we decide to go on with the Bill now and leave over for settlement by Cab. Cttee ques. how we deal with the agreement.



A.	Recalled history.  Refiners tried to kill beet factories in various ways.

	Doubt if much can be achieved by negotn – unless power taken in Bill to terminate agreemt.



Att.G.	We cd. get more informn eg. re cost of compensn if we took that power and what chance of securing essentials by negotiation.

	Don’t therefore mention this aspect in King’s Speech.

	Agreemt. cuts both ways – not wholly unfavourable to Corpn.  Tho’ on balance advantage of it is prob. with refiners.



E.Sh.	If we pass this Bill, will corpn be able to establish effective control over sugar industry?



Att.G.	That ques. is bound up with M/F. use of his powers.

	Legn wd. certainly put Corpn in stronger position: v. strong. if it included clear power to terminate agreemt.  Remember some agreemt. is requd so long as refineries are in private hands.



J.	Compensn is a matter of policy, not law.

	And this is a crudely monopolistic agreemt. wh. is against public policy.  There is therefore no necessity to compensate for breakg. it.



H.W.	Support that view.  Never contemplated we wd. compensate for loss resultg. fr. brkg. up restrictive agreemts.  This Govt. have never done so.

	Cd. be argued tht. it isn’t a private agreement.  But no need to compensate because they got a Tory Govt. to give statutory cover for their restrictive agreement.



H.McN.	Don’t forget other side of contract by wh. refiners paid a high price to Corpn   for their sugar.  Wasn’t a wholly one-sided contract.



A.V.A.	Cutting in on this will raise such a controversy tht. you wd. be better advised to p’pone until you can deal with whole ques. of sugar industry.



T.W.	If principle of nationalising Corpn is right, we must leave over ques. how we deal with compensn – can’t settle it here.



Att.G.	Provide in Bill tht. agreemt. shd. terminate by given date unless new one has bn. negotiated m’while.  Support T.W.’s view.



P.M.	How far have we worked out our sugar plan – apart fr. puttg. it in Party p’mme?  Cdn’t promise legn w’out knowing what it is?



A.B.	You will either enrage Tate and Lyle or enrage Govt. supporters.

	Public corpn will have v. involved relns with refiners.

	What pol. or organic advantage in this?

	V. unjustifiable to depart from Labour principles on this.

	If we add this to Speech, are we p’poning main issue?

	Don’t let’s compromise our principles.  Eg. if we had natd land in 1946, we shd. have avoided many diffies.  Nationalise or leave well alone.



Att.G.	Favour short Bill on pol. grounds.  Let Tate and Lyle oppose it.



E.Sh.	Must go on with limited Bill – but don’t take any credit for it.

	Our supporters won’t regard it as adequate.  And will even dislike it if it leads to compensation.

	Need we mention it in Speech?  Yes.  Must refer to agreement. (?) Better put it in and consider details re agreement later.



H.W.	How far have we control over Corpn?  How much more wd. legn give.

	See end of memo. – most of directors seem to be outside Govt. control.



M.W.	We are using 1942 Act now.  But next year I lose those powers and under 1935 Act I have no powers.  If I don’t have this legn, I must renew 1942 Act.

	But even under 1942 Act only a minority of Bd. are 100% Govt. controlled.



Att.G.	Tho’ Govt. has veto, Bd. includes many repves of refiners.  And all Govt. control is subject to agreement – which does limit Corpn’s development of beet industry.

	This shd. be a public corpn – its capital ought not to be earng. private profit.  Achievements.  a) Establish socialist organns competing in this industry with private sector.  b) It wd. be in strong competitive posn and cd. dictate terms to refiners.  c) It wd. encourage beet growers.

	Bill passed – wd. avoid major legn wh. mghtn’t be v. good platform.

	If Bill rejected, wd. be a good platform on wh. to fight.



P.M.	Favour limited Bill.



Att.G.	So do I. May be cheaper.

	Is wording of Speech likely to influence ques. of compensn.

	In earlier natns we have taken over all existg. contracts etc.  If you merely terminated 1936 Act, you might be better off than takg. over shares.



H.G.	Don’t think this wording binds us to compensate for contracts.



H.McN.	Go on with this Bill.  G.A.I.,  T.W.,  G.T.



H.W.	Wd. prefer 100% plan. At least make form of this case later 100%





		Agreed:	Approve M/F. proposals.

				A.B. asked that his view (?dissent) be recorded.



						                                  [Exit M.W.

		3.	Printers’ Strike.



Att.G.	If report of court of enquiry is not accepted, I shd. find it diff. to refrain from prosecutg. both sides.

	If I prosecute at all, I wd. prefer to go for both sides.

	Any advice from my colleagues?



G.A.I.	Urge Attorney to pause and consider report before he decides.

	It contains many comments on attitude of the two sides.

	Also employers understood to be willing to accept.



Att.G.	Counsel have advised tht. employers are technically in breach of Order 1305 and employees are certainly in breach.



</content>
</cab>
