<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 52-52</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 84(50).				11th December, 1950.



	1.	Industrial Disputes.	[Enter  Att.G., Wh. &amp; P.



	(a)	Duple Bodies.



G.A.I.	Para. 10.  Mtg. has bn. arranged.  Managemt. have considered repns:

		can go no further than staggered resumption:  no hope of

		reducg. redundancy.



Att.G.	Clear breach of Order 1305.  No gt. public interest.  But Heald’s

		allegn of intimidn at P. Royal works is another matter:  &amp; I

		can’t prosecute for that unless I do for Duple’s.  Diff. to prove

		intimidn since Act of 1946.



G.A.I.	It’s the intimidn that matters, not the object.



Att.G.	But I can only get them for aiding &amp; abetting Duple’s strike.



H.M.	Public interest not engaged.  Don’t want 1305 in further trouble.



Att.G.	Agree re Duples.  Trouble is intimidn suggn.



H.M.	What evce of intimidn?



Att.G.	Resoln tht. anyone who doesn’t contribute wd. be reported to Unions

		as candidate for early removal in event of any redundancy.



A.	Action here wd. high-light inaction over B.O.A.C.



H.M.	Doubt if prosecution is necessary in public interest.



E.B.	Nothing unusual about this sort of strike – happening all the time.

		Thought Att.G. had discretion to overlook this sort of thing.

	If Executive of Union have approved the levy, &amp; we take it into court,

		we shall be in grave political trouble.  Diff. matter if levy is only

		a works’ decision.

	Need for care.



H.M.	Att.G. must decide.  But no pressing need, from angle of public

		interest, for procdgs. in this case.



E.B.	If it isn’t settled soon, M/L. cd. help by announcg. a public enquiry

		under Indust. Cts. Act 1919.  Wd. avoid puttg. Att.G. into diffies.



Wh.	Att.G. cd. also say, in intimidn, tht. insufft. evce.



Att.G.	Heald wd. then produce his evidence.



	

	(b)	B.O.A.C.



Att.G.	I ought to have prosecuted.  My reason:  M/L. won’t refer it to arbitn.

		I ought to be allowed to make that clear.



G.A.I.	Assume men have gone back to work, this morning.





G.A.I.	I am submittg. a memo. on general ques. wtr. Order 1305 shd. be

		kept on.



H.M.	If you want to make a reply in H/C., submit draft to P.M. – who may

		want to consult M/Labour.



Wh.	Wd. encourage pressure for change in the law.



E.B.	Compulsy arbitn in peace-time won’t work.

				         [Exit  3 invitees.



	2.	Korea.



E.B.	Mil. sitn, tho’ grave is less critical than it seemed 2 or 3 days ago.

		Commrs. on both flanks believe they can disengage &amp; hold a

		posn just s. of 38th Parallel – almost indefinitely.

	Procdgs. at U.N.  Efforts of Indian Govt. – there and at Pekin.

		Constructive &amp; realistic approach.  Wu told Rau on que tht.

		Ch. Govt. were anxious to stop the fighting, wh. had bn. forced

		on them.  Cease-fire seems possible.

	Have sent instns favouring cease-fire, w’out strings.

	Have now heard tht. U.S. agree tht. Ch. must have time to consider

		wtr. they wd. agree to a cease-fire.  They won’t be precipitate.

	I’m aiming at a demilitarised zone, w’out using the word.  It was 

		satisf. in Kashmir:  just draw 2 lines.  Has some appeal for U.S.

	Our indicns suggest tht. Chinese nor U.S. want fighting to continue.



G.W.	Menon saw me this a.m.  Latest Indian approaches to China.  No reply

		to main repns.  But official has said:  China might agree to 

		negotns – on condns  i) justice of Ch. posn in Korea recognised.

		ii) not bound by U.N. resolns while not a member.

	6 Power resoln:  India won’t support it.  Rau instructed to seek support

		for simple cease-fire resoln, incldg. refce to negotns with China on

		Korea &amp; Formosa.



E.B.	Formosa – diff. problem.  But we have kept clear line since June –

		negotiation thro’ U.N. in light of events.  We have a free hand.



H.McN.	If Formosa is introduced now, it will make it v. diff. for U.S. to 

		negotiate.



A.B.	P’pone all discn (save cease-fire) until P.M.’s return.

J.	Cd. Nationalists defeat Comm. attack on Formosa?



E.Sh.	E.B. was right in pressing tht. no conditions be attached to cease-fire.

	Improvemt. in mil. situation seems largely due to unwillingness of

		Chinese to make determined attack.



E.B.	Also diffies betwn. R. &amp; China.  R. didn’t want China’s admissn to

		U.N. - &amp; prob. were not behind latest Ch. aggression.



E.Sh.	Significant also tht. Ch. have not made much use of aircraft.



H.McN.	Cd. Cab. see summary of M/D. intelligence e.g. fr. x-examn of p.o.w.



E.Sh.	There isn’t v. much.  We rely almost entirely on U.S. intelligence

		from MacArthur’s H.Q.





	3.	Soviet Proposal for Four-Power Meeting.



E.B.	Offls. have agreed upon a reply.  Only ques. outstandg. is wtr. refce

		shd. be included to Iraqi resoln.

	Draft is forthcoming.  Invites mtg. on broader agenda.

	Text will be available to-day.  Cab. to-morrow?  Reply must go

		w’out delay.

	No attempt made by officials to delimit problems.

			Note taken.





	4.	German Participation in Defence of Europe.



E.B.	Proposed tht. mtg. be held in Brussels on Monday.  To receive 

		report of Deputies.  Ministerial mtg. of N.A.T.O.

	Thght. Cabinets shd. have a chance to consider.

		I gave a warning therefore tht. final decisions might not be

		achieved.

		P.M. not returned:  no Cab. discussion etc.

	Have agreed this a.m. tht. there shd. be a mtg. of N.A.T. Council on

		Monday – with warning tht. I might not be able to give final

		decision of U.K. Govt.

	Don’t want this rushed.  Timing.  German re-action.

	Sent telegram to P.M. in Ottawa.  P.M. has said he is agreeable to

		mtg. on Monday.

	Monday’s mtg. will be preceded by Tripartite of Foreign Ministers.



E.Sh.	Cab. shd. consider Deputies proposals – carefully, this week.

	Joint mtg. of Deputies &amp; Mil. Cttee will be to-morrow.

	Procedure.  Council remitted this to Def. Cttee.  We must therefore

	meet &amp; report to Council.  On Monday Def. Cttee will meet &amp;

	recommend to Council.

 

H.D.	Timing.  This wd. make 4 Power Talks more difficult?

	Persistent G. dodging of issue of re-armament.  Adenauer’s

		statement this a.m.  When you have cleared a formula with the		French, you will have diffy with Germans.



A.B.	Much to be discussed by Cab. this week – after P.M.’s return.

	If we are going on with Item 3, surely we must soft-pedal on Item 4.





	5.	Nepal.



E.B.	Only just missed a civil war.

	Nehru as unreasonable over this as he has bn. reasonable over China.		But he has now come round quite a long way.

	Sent Dening to Nepal – who have now promised various reforms.

		These aren’t 100% satisfactory to Nehru.  But situation looks

		much more promising.

	In our man-power stringency we can’t afford to lose Ghurkas.





	6.	Egypt.



E.B.	Shall have to get Cab. decision this week.



H.G.	Financial talks.  Complete deadlock – no chance of escape.



E.B.	Mine is not quite so bad.





	7.	European Recovery Programme.



H.G.	Definite U.S. decn to give us no more E.R.P.  Counterpart funds

		assumed.  And what is in pipe-line.  But not the addl £1 m.

		I had hoped to get for remainder of this year.

	There will be agreed Anglo/U.S. statement.





	8.	Meat.



H.G.	Argentine have rejected our offer.  They are insistg. on time limit of

		one month:  &amp; revision of £97.10.0. price thereafter.

	I advise Cab. to stand firm against this.



M.W.	On 31/12 shall have to bring ration down to 10d + 2d corned beef.

		Cd. hold it at that until mid/February.  With Uraguay cd. go to

		mid/Mar.  But Argentine are telling M. to hold off.

	If we conceded now, we wd. have to pay £120 – and put up with 

		price increases for meat fr. other sources.

	Cd. increase ration of sugar (EPC) and cheese.  And bacon in Jan.

		But no more meat is available.  Have bought manufg. beef in

		France for £180.

	Announcement by 19/12.  To near Xmas.  I favour making it 

		earlier – for effect on Argentina.  If on Wed. next, it cd. cover

		compensns.



H.McN.	Hope we shan’t mince words re Argentina’s tactics.

	Fish prices?



M.W.	Too soon to mention re - imposition of controls.



H.McN.	Cd. give a hint tht. if anyone tries to exploit the situation we will

		take steps …….



E.B.	Pre-1914 hawkers secured best fish for working classes.

	Improve distribn system:  central frying agency + “stop me &amp; buy one”

		tricycles.  Cooked fish vice fishmongers.



T.W.	White Fish Authority shd. look at this.



H.W.	I favoured cutting off our essential exports to Argentina.

	Ought we not to review that again?

	In Xmas ’47 we brought Miranda to heel by cutting soda ash.

	They are still sensitive to this sort of pressure.

	For this means lower meat ration than at any time – takg. a/c of

		increase in meat prices.

	Can’t give in &amp; give higher prices, after this long fight.



A.	Agree:  let us fight too.  Esp. as we don’t know how long they 

		will go on.



			Agreed:  O.N.C. to consider what retaliatory action we 

			               cd. take.

			               Announce ration changes in H/C. not later

			               than Thursday.



E.Sh.	Make it clear what price Argentina is asking – and what it means

		per lb.



H.G.	Don’t.  Suggests we wd. pay £120 rather than £140.  But point is

		effect on prices in Doms. etc.  Also wd. indicate to Argentina

		what we wd. be ready to pay.

				[Exit  M.W.

				[Enter  N.B., Taylor.

	9.	Coal.



	a)	House of Commons Debate.



H.M.	Motion in H/C.  6 Ministers outside U.K.  Cook recalled.

		Marquand in Canada – also recalled, unless we can pair him.

	Hope Cabinet endorse action wh. I have taken.

	Also 7 sick.

	Govt. spokesman:  Parly Secy. as well as M/Fuel &amp; Power.

	Terms of Govt. amendment:  enquiry wd. hamper N.C.B. &amp; do no

		good;  welcome extra effort by miners;  welcomes Govt.

		effort to secure more output &amp; solve man-power problems of

		the industry.



E.Sh.	Vital point:  was an enquiry, set up by N.C.B.;  &amp; changes of

		organn followed.  Surely that shd. be mentd?



H.G.	Was v. controversial:  we never publd report:  it was concerned 

		only with organn &amp; what they are on is wider ques. of output.

	The amendmt. is too long.



			Agreed:  let H.M. settle – much shorter.  Don’t close 

			               door to enquiry at some time.

			               Say not at this moment.

				[Exit  Taylor.

	b)	Opting for Mines.



N.B.	Measures taken wdn’t give us 40.000.

	Opting wd. give us a real flow.



E.Sh.          x/	Decided not to recruit in mining areas.

	Shdn’t we stand on that pro tem?

	Real need is to keep miners in the mines.  Not to get these young

		men diverted from other industries.

	Services are also in need of man power.



A.B.	Can’t run this idea at same time as you are trying to build up

		status of miners.



J.G.	You wd. get no value out of this.



H.M.	I advise you to put your weight on x/.



H.G.	You wd. lose people fr. the mines by this trick.



</content>
</cab>
