<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 53-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 85 (50)					12th December, 1950



1.	     Mr Fraser.



Telegram of sympathy to be sent.





2.	     Washington Talks with Truman.



P.M.	Received v. friendly manner.  Agreed – 100% candour on both sides.

	Mil. sitn changed while we were there.  At first thought no more than 2 bridgeheads for limited time.  U.S. have never had a knock before – needed sympathy.

	I made a broad statement.  Wished vindicate U.N. but shdn’t be dragged into major war with China.  Gave apprecn of China – chance they wdn’t follow Moscow slavishly – our object shd. be detach them fr. R.  Sitn must go to agreemt. or extension of war.  Stressed importce of Europe.

	Acheson:  U.S. doctrine tht. China is ruled by Moscow.

		They agreed – avoid major war in F/E.  Europe = vital front.

		They were bombing M’churia.

	They feared negotn posn wh. wd. bring in Formosa.  I said no hope of limited negotns .  Both were covered in Cairo Agreemt.

	Project of limited war.  Ec. blockade + S.O.E.  I was v. that. Ch. has all the S.O.E. cards v. us – Indo-China, Malaya etc.  Marshall came down on my side.  I concluded – sooner or later, negotns cease-fire mooted.  Discn of terms.  We favoured leavg. it free – w’out condns.

	China’s seat in U.N.  Case for and v. stated.  We agreed to differ.

	Formosa not immediate issue.  They fear it because jumping off place r. Philippines.  But Ch. fears it because jump off place for Chiang K. Sh.	

		I suggd neutralising it for period under nominal Ch. sovereignty.

	Europe.  They agreed Supr. Commr. acdum. wd. be helpful.  Then heard Spofford plan was moving.  Fait accompli.  In my view, gt. gain to get Commr.

	They said their Forces earmarked for W. were being pulled into F/E.

		But they will make new Divns. available in Europe in ’51.

	Raw materials.  They were v. forthcomg.  Agreed on Steering Cttee – U.K., U.S., France.  Strong claimants:  if one admitted other claims cdn’t be resisted.  Under Cttee a no. of commodity boards on wh. offices wd. get their chance.  Decisions in boards not Steering Cttee.  I put this to Can. Cab. - &amp; no objns raised.

	Canada will also help on r. materials.

	U.S. hesitant on our doing more in defence.  I said we had bn. doing more than they since ’45.  Said we wd. consider doing more:  but cdn’t commit Cab.  There may be more pressure on that.

	Control of operations.  MacA. good general.  They agreed he talked too much.  His intelligence hasn’t bn. good.  I pointed distinctn betwn politico-mil. decns &amp; those for commr. in field - &amp; said we needed more consultn on first.  Put in memo. on informal liaison C.O.S. – which was accepted.

	Atomic bomb.  Truman didn’t realise he’d dropped such a brick.  He had no intn of using it in Korea.  He hoped he’d never have to use it.  Regards it as joint possn of U.S., U.K. &amp; Canada.

		Fullest consultn before using it, save in retaliation.

		I was fully satisfied.

	General atmosphere was good.  They needed our comfort.  Robust confidence of C.I.G.S. was helpful.  Mil. sitn improved while we were there.  Now seems they may be able to hold a line.  As soon as its stabilised, we shd. try for cease-fire &amp; negotiations.  Stressed tht. it’s U.N. affair.

	Met Comm. Ambassadors in Washington.  Also Comm. repves in N. Yk.

	Good talk with Cab. in Ottawa.  They were solidly with us.

		Press conference.  With many ques. off the record.

		Useful talks betwn. officials.

	Procdgs. at U.N.  Asiatics puttg. in cease-fire resoln.  Also a resoln on Ch. intervention, wh. doesn’t brand them as aggressors.

		I said the first was to be preferred.



H.M.	Statement in H/C.  To-day or to-morrow?  Opposn wd. be willing to wait until Wed. &amp; have debate on Thursday.



P.M.	Better to do it at once.  They may suspect disagreemt. in Cab.

		Diff. to say more than was in communiqué.



E.B.	Davies has some suggns for filling out statement.



T.W.	Quicker the better. – qua. public opinion.



H.M.	Worth waiting 24 hrs. to make it a better statement.



A.B.	Diffy.  If you make a much longer statement to-morrow, you invite x-examn w’out defence tht. you’ve only just got back.

		Make it to-day &amp; promise fuller informn in Thursday’s debate.



H.D.	Communiqué was longer than at first assumed.



P.M.	Imposs. to elaborate it a little in statement, and a lot in debate.



H.D.	Anti-climax if you don’t make a statement to-day.



H.McN.	Courtesy statement to-day.  Para. 5. might be expanded.  Otherwise much as drafted.





3.	     Death of Oliver Stanley.



H.M.	Proposed to have tributes in H/C. to-day.

P.M.	Against precedents.  Only leaders of Parties.  Or Ministers dying in office.  V. dangerous to extend it.



J.	Asquith or Alfred Lyttelton.



H.M.	I checked up with Whips’ Office – who said there were precedents.



</content>
</cab>
