<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 54-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 86 (50)					14th December, 1950



1.	     Parliament.

			                                                              [Enter Dep. Ch.Whip

H.M.	Business for next week after Recess.



H.McN.	Will try to get Salmon Bill completed in one day on 24/1.



C.E.	Summer-time.  Order shd. be made w’out delay.



					[Exit D. Ch. Whip

2.	     Housing



H.McN.	As M/W. has had such a success with industry (esp. employers) housing sitn wd. be politically eased by statement as in para. 8.



H.G.	Statement must follow these exact words.  Can’t go further.



H.McN.	Wdn’t want to go further because timber situation.





3.	     Soviet Proposal for C.F.M. Meeting.



E.B.	Amendments.  Para. 2.  Re-insert reference to Iraqi resoln.  I don’t object:  merely reference to what Genl. Assembly has done.  Not open to objn of original wording, which went into substance.

	Para. 3 – merely a drafting change.  And additional para. at end.



A.	Why insert this provocative passage.



E.B.	Because they accuse us of arming W. Germany &amp; deny they have armed the east.



E.Sh.	Evce tht. Bereitschaften have tanks?  We haven’t any.



E.B.	Thought M/D. supported this.  Will check it up again.   *



G.W.	Additional sentence does rule this in, unnecessarily.  Accept only if Fr. &amp; U.S. are insisting.



E.B.	I agree	*

	Para. 5:  first sentence.  Wording.



E.Sh.	What do you gain fr. 2nd sentence.  Provocation again.  Why not omit it.



E.B.	Must make it clear tht. condn of conference is tht. we get down to business.  Can’t overlook R. behaviour on previous occasions.

		I’m not going to put up with this attitude at a further confce



P.M.	They asked for confce on Germany.  We must say it’s not G. alone, it’s genl. attitude of R.



H.McN.	We have said 2nd sentence in 2 U.N. resolns.  No provocation in saying it again.



E.Sh.	No point in makg. such charges at outset of conference.

		Won’t press my view.  



			Agreed: stet second sentence.



E.B.	U.S. amendment on para. 6.  Prelimy examn of issues by officials.

		I am not ready to have merits discussed by officials.

		Tension affectg. world peace – Germany – Austria etc.  Officials bound to get bogged down.  Ministers wd. never meet.  This wd. be seen to be a swindle.  Either have a mtg. or say you won’t have one.



			Agreed		*



E.B.	Want reply despatched by Saturday – before Brussels mtg.



G.W.	Inform Comm. Govts. in advance.



			Agreed.



E.B.	To Benelux in advance also.

	Shown to Adenauer.



H.M.	Revert to idea of high-sounding declaration – peace campaign High level idealistic propaganda.

		Is it too late for this?



E.B.	Diff. to know how to do it in this Note.

	This offer may be rejected by R.  Don’t want to mislead people into thinkg. there’s more in this than there is.



H.G.	A sentence or two in para. 2		



	*   E.B. will consider.





4.	     German Participation in Europe Defence.

					        [Enter C.O.S.

E.B.	Conception of partnership vice aid from U.S.

	American C.O.S. considered this:  &amp; in August/Autumn the implication of U.S. troops in Europe in peace was accepted by Truman – as was implicn by us tht. we shd. do more.  But U.S. made this conditional on use of German troops.

	Rhine line involved evacn of 4 m. Dutch - &amp; that caused alarm in Europe.  Hence plan to fight further east:  on German soil:  means G. must fight.

	I cdn’t see any alternative but to accept principle of G. participn as price for securing U.S. Commr., U.S. troops in Europe, &amp; conceptn of partnership.  In those discns I gathered tht. Fr. wd. take same line – Schuman gave me to understand so.

		But Fr. Socialists wdn’t have this - &amp; Fr. proposal for European Army was put fwd.  That won’t work.

	After further consultn, Spofford compromise has bn. evolved.

		Allows U.S. plan to start, while Fr. calls a conference on Europ. Army.

	Ques. came up while P.M. in W’ton.  A letter sent to Fr. Govt.  I made 2 caveats

i)	U.K.  Govt. not commd

ii)	decision wd. be taken in conference, not by corrce.

	I  have bn. worried by 2 things.

	I am in favour of G. assistg. in Europ. defence.  Am commd in principle.  But don’t want to do it in such a way tht. if R. cut up rough we have nothg. with wh. to prevent another Korea in Europe.

	Talked to P.M. y’day.  Consultns with Kirkpatrick.  Net result:

i)	No one believes G. will respond to this invitn.  

If they don’t, &amp; there is a C.F.M., we shall be in weak bargaining posn then.

ii)	Not sure 51/2 U.S. Divns. will come into Europe if G. does not respond.

iii)	What chance of preservg. our grip on Berlin, if R. made a move there.

	Kelly prefers course I am now going to outline.

	U.S. wanted to dump Spofford plan on G. &amp; ask for answer.

	I prefer 

a)	first to tell Adenauer we have adopted plan, if we do: but don’t ask him to accept or reject.

b)	insist on apptmt of Supreme Commr. &amp; go on at once with formn of integrated force.

c)	in indefinite transition, go on with C.F.M. &amp; discuss demilitarisn of Germany.  We shall not have taken irrevocable step of arming W. Germany.

	Also avoids having to beg Germany to come in, to assist in our defence.  Do no more than create a place for them.



C.I.G.S.	U.S. mil. are anxious to appoint Commr.

	Re-inforcemt. is diff. because Korea.  Bradley favours Nat. Guard divns as soon as ready:  can’t be until the spring.  No reluctance to send them:  but they don’t like sending half-trained troops.  But I urged them to send &amp; train in Germany.  No U.S. Govt. decision.



P.M.	Delays by Fr. proposals.  Then by Korea.  Has defeated our hopes of strength soon in Europe.

	Endorse E.B.’s line.

	Can’t reject Spoffard plan w’out estranging U.S.  But care not to provoke R.  The C.F.M. project enables us to get best of both worlds – don’t play the card yet.



C.N.S.	We want to get on with re-arming G.  But wd. value opp. to talk informally with G. to see how they wd. come in.



Att.G.	On what terms will G. come in?  Only on equal terms?  If so, more diffy. with French.  What is behind their fears.  Genuine fear of G.?  If so, some assurances cd. be given to allay those fears.



E.B.	Have put this to Pleven – tht. N.A.T.O. is r. aggression, not r. R.  If G. was aggressor, N.A.T.O. wd. support Fr. r. them.	

		That assurance has bn. given.  Believe it cd. be given again.

		Benelux have not expd such fears – they assume tht. what was said on this at signing of Pact still stands.

	French are more concerned about their immedte political posn.



A.	Are Fr. doing anythg. militarily?



C.I.G.S.	Trying.  Handicapped by

			a) short length of mil. service.

		b) Indo China absorb more than 1/2 Fr. regular army.

	They have 5 divns in Europe.



H.M.	If it’s ques. of going easy temporarily qua tactics – I understand.

		On fundamentals – we must face re-arming Germany.  And concede the status wh. goes with that.

	Mil. sitn is so weak tht. we can’t afford to do w’out Germany.

	Doubt if R. wd. fight preventive war.

	If we say we daren’t re-arm G., the mil. outlook for us is v. bleak.

	Don’t therefore p’pone for any length of time re-armament of G.



H.McN.	Cd. we re-arm them soon, anyway, because economic diffies.  Even with willing G. &amp; acquiescent France.



C.I.G.S.	U.S. cd. have done it, but have lost much equipmt in Korea.

	Re-inforces E.B.’s plan for delay.



E.Sh.	V. definite views wh. I have put to C.O.S.

	We are in a mess in Europe.

	If we had gone on, on basis of last summers’ agreemt., we wd. have bn. O.K.  U.S. then promised 51/2 Divns.

	Spofford plan is before you – Annex A.  Comg. up at N.A.T. Council.

	In genl. we accept this.  But some other countries will have views.

	Doesn’t alter the principle.  You can’t resist R. aggression in Europe in foreseeable future w’out G. contn.  G. wd. have to fight - &amp; we want them on our side.

	Ques:  when?  Accept principle: implemn is another matter.

	Diffies  a) arms. Our first obligns must be to N.A.T.O. countries.

	French divns aren’t yet equipped.

		   b) Are we thinking of ’54.  Completely unrealistic – may come

		       in 1951.  If Bereitschaften then attacked, you cdn’t organise G.

	Plan.  Say at Brussels we accept this compromise.

		Next step: present this to Germany.  How?  Better to persuade them to apply than seek to impose it.  Thus I agree with E.B.’s tactics.

		If we can let them start traing. in small units, that wd. be useful.

		Wd. this provoke R?  If so, it wd. do so at any time.

	I suspect apptmt of Commr. etc, is a provocative as acceptce of priniciple of G. re-armament.

	There is so little strength in Europe tht. we can’t afford to alienate U.S. – on whom we must rely.



H.G.	Approve E.B.’s tactics.

	What will U.S. attitude be, if G. won’t come in?



E.Sh.	Spoke to Adm. Sherman last night.  He advised caution in approach to Germans.  C.N.S. believe he now favours sending U.S. troops w’out condition:  &amp; avoidg. begging Germans to join in.



H.D.	The arming of G. wd. be much more provocative to R. than other measures.  The R. are nervous of G.  So am I.  Don’t give arms to G. until we have integrated force in being in Europe.



J.G.	Case in Annex B. is v. disturbg.  Labour Party are makg. ground in G. because opposn to re-armament.  Workers &amp; students are those who oppose it.

	We, as a Party, don’t want to find ourselves opposed to G. Trade Unions &amp; Social Democrats.  Can we do anything to bring them round.



E.Sh.	Don’t swing to other extreme.  Adenauer &amp; Schumacher are in favour of a G. contribn – tho’ on terms unacceptable to French.



			{Tactics proposed by E.B. approved.

			{Comm. Govts. to be informed.





5.	Egypt.



E.B.	Have always feared E. wd. let us down at critical moment.

	Need for troops in E. in peace = guarding stores. (E. reply: take them away &amp; Gippies won’t steal them.)

	Revision of Treaty has turned into nationalist cry “clean out.”

	Wd. now prefer to substitute term “Alliance” vice Treaty.

	We shall be v. short of man-power in future war. We shd. use the 25m. in Sudan &amp; Egypt.  Develop industries there, wh. wd. be useful to us in war and m’while raise standards of living.

	Uganda too.

	Hence – idea of transfer of m’tenance respons. for the last to E.

	In discns, took a chance on Israel.  He replied – no chance of agreemt. betwn. Arabs &amp; Israel.  In the end, he said no pol. opposn in Egypt if U.K. &amp; Israel make bi-lateral settlement, just as Eg/U.K. settle bi-laterally.  Must avoid religious opposn wh. cd. spread thro’ Moslem world.  I have made tentative approaches to Israel. (v. secret) &amp; gather they wd. welcome discussion of some defence arrangemt.

	Hence	

i)	transfer base m’tenance to Egypt.

ii)	Clear agreemt. for all facilities in E. in war for Britain or her Allies.

iii)	privileges for B. troops (? in war) on 1936 Treaty basis.

iv)	in peace:  B. technicians there.  Asked also for some uniformed personnel.

	Is this a basis for settlement?

	May C.O.S. study this sympathetically from angle of defence needs?

	I want Eg. For. Minister to go home next week.  And real negotn must start in January.  Want then to go for alliance w’out time limit.  Ultimately wd. like Turkey to be included.

		Also Sudan.



C.I.G.S.	Hope tht. Israelis wd. accept B. striking force there?



E.B.	Can’t say yet.



C.N.S.	Our anxiety:  this may impair our ability to defend M/E.

		We shd. like Robertson &amp; Air C-in-C to come home &amp; discuss.

		To see how far we can go to meet E.B.’s view.



H.G.	V. important financial implicn – esp. idea of new base in Palestine.  V. high cost.

	Hope E.B. won’t give any further hint of this to E. For. Minister.

		Wd. make Jan. negotn much more diff.

	Wd. rather suspend or adjourn.  Worried about (b) in memo.

	We haven’t played all our cards yet.  E.g. U.S. pressure.



H.McN.	Don’t say anythg. to Eg. now to lead them to suppose we were thinkg. favourably of this plan.  Cabinet now considg. this plan.

	No secrets in Cairo.  He will exploit this “concession” to his own pol. advantage.



E.B.	I’ve seen him 6 times.  Of course, I’ve outlined this approach already.  Only want now to tell him tht. we want to study it further.



H.W.	E. For. Minister will exploit E.B.’s tentative conversn anyway, if he wants to.



G.W.	Don’t want A., N.Z., &amp; S. Afr. to learn of this from Egyptian leaks.

	Adds weight to plea for caution.



			Agreed

i)	send For. Min. away on basis – interesting talk, I am studying it., let’s resume in Jan.

ii)	C.O.S. to study as in (a) of memo.



				              [Exit C.O.S.

		6.	Summer Time in 1951.



C.E.	Prepared to accept shorter of 2 extensions.

	But don’t like it.  Violent opposn in Parlt. to anything more.

		Apart fr. agricultural objns, strong criticism fr. educationists.

i)	Double summer time – not pressed.

ii)	Further 8 weeks.



T.W.	This wd. give us political black-eye.

	For the sake of 50.000 tons w’in period of possible fuel crisis.

	Surely not worth the agricultural objns.

	Sauce to ask for it, when we promised help with open-cast.

	Rubbish to do this &amp; not reduce shop-lighting.



N.B.	Put fwd. because thought 100.000 t. wd. be quite significant amount in circs. of this winter.  At time when we shall have specl. diffy. over stocks – esp. power-station stocks.



G.T.	Worth doing this on its merits.  Double time also.

		A boon to industry.

	Farmers always have opposed it – on same arguments.  Shown in practice tht. rural diffies are not inseperable.



H.McN.	Asked to believe M/F &amp; P. calculn are correct to .002.

	But handicap to agriculture is obvious &amp; inevitable.



H.W.	Favour C.E.’s proposal i.e. 8 weeks.



H.M.	Starting with bias in favour of M/F &amp; P., I have grown to sympathise with rural view.  Economic importance of home food prodn  I believe addl. 3 weeks shd. be adopted.

	Politically, I wd. sooner consider shop-lighting than this.



E.Sh.	Support H.M. – 3 weeks wd. be enough.

	Economic in fuel consumptn.



N.B.	Expect we shall have to stop shop-lighting after Xmas.



C.E.	Do it generally – not in 1d nos.



H.G.	a) any economy more important than inconven. to agric.

	b) link with shop-lighting.

	Bring in after Xmas both 8 wks’ summer time &amp; cuts in lighting.



T.W.	Saving is only 10.000 t. p. wk. for 4 weeks.

	Think what you can get on a Sat. morning.



A.	3 wks’ extension is enough – no more.



 J.G.	60.000 t. at a cost of v. bad feeling.

	Surely there are simpler ways of saving 60.000.

	Early summer-time increases absenteeism.



G.W.	Fuel crisis is worst of all evils.



J.	Favour longer summer-time.



H.G.	1/4 to 28/10



	P’pone until after Xmas &amp; consider all proposals for fuel

		economy.



</content>
</cab>
