<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 55-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 87 (50)					18th December, 1950



1.	Defence.



P.M.	Truman asked me to do more on defence – I promised to consider, w’out commitment.

	Have considered:  so has M/D.:  both concluded some acceleration is inevitable.

	Was planning still related to 1957.

	New hypothesis needed.  Must avoid assumptn war inevitable.

		Truman’s decln, I suppose, nec. to give him powers.

	Acceleration: completion of paper plans:  but some new expre

C.O.S. likely proposals i) – iii) in brief.

	This will all come up after Xmas.

	But m’while Acheson’s statement at Brussels (as in brief).

		What response can we make – to induce other Europeans to do more. Conception of Anglo-American partnership.

		As we shall have to accelerate, I recommend formula in note – re acceleration.

	E.B. &amp; E.Sh. support this.

	Avoid committal to a figure.  Resist U.S. pressure for a figure.

		c.f. experience in summit.  Stick to statement re acceleration.

	Read summary of Acheson’s probable statement.

	Danger of U.S. failg. to keep balance betw. defence &amp; econ. stability.

		But we must keep in line – in case they put too much in F/East.

	Read draft of E.B.’s reply.



H.G.	Spoke to E.B. before he left.

	Agree:  no new figure.

		shdn’t accept double pre-Korean rate because ours far above other countries.

		support draft.

	Implications	

a)	Acheson’s approach is too like August – aid concept.  Criticism of slowness of Nitze exercise.  Shipping away from partnership.  

	   			                    [Enter A

		      Don’t like being urged to do more &amp; then look for some aid.

	Almost all $ 5 b. = equipment.:  v. little free dollars.  That isn’t aid.

b)	Diffies. at home unless we know implicn of acceln.  £1.100 m. in 51/52 already.  If 3.6 were to be completed in 2 yrs:  or if M &amp; D.P. were to be completed in 2 yrs. (our share prob. £5 vice 3.6) we shd. be near 2.000 m. in 51/52.  Must have some idea of what we are going to do.  Prob. by getting Services to say what they need.  Much addn to present p’mme wd. involve more controls.  Even now, L.I.M.O.S.O. orders will prob. be needed.  If much more, prs. clothes rationg. &amp; divn of labour.

		Don’t want to alarm Cab. but all these may have to be considered.  Requisitiong.: power to compel firms accept defence orders.



H.W.	Even on present p’mme shall go long way in this dirn.

	A 3 yr. p’mme in 2 wd mean doublg. pre-Kor. rate.

	Don’t get commd such a formula.  Don’t let them gain currency.

	Speed up w’out increasg. 3.6?  Hardly possible.  Cdn’t have recession in 2nd or 3rd yrs.  Acceln therefore means increase in total p’mme.

	We thght. our share of M &amp; D.P. wd exceed 3.6m.  Serious if U.S now think M &amp; D.P. not enough.  Wd. wreck Eur. economy.



H.G.	We must say to U.S. – adequ. guarantees on r. materials.

		E.B. will insist.



G.W.	Parity of restns – cd. that be agreed.  If we have to ration clothes, U.S. shd. do so too.



H.W.	They never did in 1939/45.

	If we are to have standard of refce – make it 1938 base.



H.D.	Time for discn of fair shares, if we avoid new figure now.

		We have done more than any, relatively.

	Risk tht. slight addn to def. p’mme wd. seriously unbalance economy.

	If G. reluctance helps us to concln tht. G. re-armament is not immedy practicable, it follows tht. other Europ. must do more.  This is reason for doing more.



P.M.	U.S. may bust themselves – inflation.



C.E.	Doubtful of “increase &amp; accelerate”.

	Our economy is strained by 13 yrs. of war economy.

	Disappointed at response of other Europeans.

		We go to 2 yrs. mil. service.  Others don’t follow.

		They have diffies.:  but so have we.

	Care to avoid language implying further strains on U.K.

		Cd. we “increase” w’out going over to war economy?

	Must see some signs of vigour in other Eur. countries.



T.W.	Respond in words to U.S. – but not to their panic.

		Remember limits to what more we can do.



A.	Danger tht. talk of acceln will increase prices etc.

		We must have p’mme to see wtr. it is practicable.

	Astronomic U.S. figures will involve infln.



P.M.	Things we can do apart fr. prodn.  E.g. training of reserves in batches.

	Also prodn of aircraft.

	Don’t have a figure before a p’mme.



H.McN.	Cd. we add this to E.B.’s statement.

	N.A.T.O. doesn’t put a proper plan.

	U.S. &amp; U.K. try to make promises good.  Others don’t.

	“Foolish offer figure:  commit to acceln &amp; increase if practicable.  But ask for further N.A.T.O. definn of mil. needs over next 2 yrs. &amp; fin. and econ. implicns.”



H.G.	Want a real basis with U.S.  They haven’t accepted our 3.6.

	Reason probly – diffce of view on strategic risks.  Lack of common appraisal of that.

	Structure of N.A.T.O.  Mily on abstract need.  Never related to practical realities.

	90% of defence prodn in U.S., U.K. &amp; Canada.  Rest of N.A.T.O. can do v. little.

		Those 3 Powers shd. get appraisal of need &amp; what can be done to meet it.



A.B.	Don’t like tone of Acheson’s statement.

	Pooling &amp; partnership wd. be better than “we will help you if…”

	This language puts weapons in hands of their enemies in Europ. countries.

	Marshall Aid was pol. diff. to digest.  This is worse.

		Can’t get spirit.



P.M.	They are thinkg. all the time of Congress.



A.B.	Failg. to get Europ. response, they fling in G. re-armament, wh. makes v. inflammatory sitn.  This invites R. attack now.

	U.S. must leave us out, if they use this language.

		U.K. relief at end of M. Aid.  U.S. must not offend natl pride.

	If we go on 10/15 yrs. at this rate, we shall exhaust world’s resources.

	

		Agree = no figure.  Ask A. to modify language.  Soft pedal on G.



P.M.	E.B. will insist we are not in this Eur. queue.

	G. re-armament:  U.S. will prob. soft-pedal on that now.



H.D.	Don’t be committed to re-arm G. before 4 Powers mtg.



E.D.	Sov. note will prevent (because Fr. fears) any immedte   action on G. re-armament.

	U.S. are windy.  But don’t forget sitn is worse.  Accelern is requd on merits – not merely in response to U.S.  If so, let’s do it voluntarily so we can range ourselves on ride of U.S. in pressing others to do more.



G.W.	As partners, we shd. warn U.S. re language etc.



H.M.	Support P.M.’s formula.  Sympathise with much said re U.S.

	But don’t under-estimate gravity of sitn.  I believe G. shd. take share:  tho’ accept E.B.’s tactics m’while.  We can’t, in end, promise to protect G. while they do nothg. to help.

		Anyway, unrealistic.  Look at R. strength (215 Divisn &amp; better air than all Eur. together).  F/East is v. disquieting.  Degree of armament in W. is v. low.

		Agree other Europ. haven’t done their share.  One thing wh. is doubtless worrying U.S. adminn &amp; Congress (&amp; worries me) is:  if we tell France etc. she can have aid of x, regardless of p’mme, risk they wd. blue the money w’out producg. the defence.

	Where shd. we be if R. attacked us and won?  Our duty is to put our defences in good state.

	I don’t know what defence we shall get fr. 3.6. – no picture of B. defence posn.  M/D. told E.P.C. acceln wd. be requd – aircraft prodn in particular he said was bad.

		We need a memo on this by M/D. &amp; C.O.S. – what we are doing &amp; what more shd. be done.  On what elements is acceleration needed.

	Don’t under-estimate gravity of mil. balance in Europe.

	Must force U.S. to send troops to Europe.

	Doubt if it’s wise to delay G. re-armament for fear of provokg. R.

	R. may not want war.  If Eur. shows quickly she can build up defence, they (R.) may be more co-operative.

	We mustn’t drift.



P.M.	Agree it is serious:  but don’t let U.S. panic.

	U.S. are preparg. for inevitable war.  We are trying to prevent it.

	Doubt if R. want war.  They believe they can bust us fr. w’in.

		Must steer careful course.

	Immediate line:

	Keep out of queue.  Stand in with U.S.  Don’t let our acceln be measured by America’s – they start fr. diff. standard:  both defence (less than ours) &amp; standard living (higher than ours).

	Let us join with U.S. in pressing the others.



J.G.	U.S. policy (raw materials) has meant we shall get less for our 3.6m.  They are reducg. effectiveness of our prepns.

	Agree with H.G. on need to examine econ. implicns.



H.G.	E.B. will stress that, anyway.



A.B.	I do not advocate our being so weak tht. we don’t provoke G. to attack.  What I meant was:  strengthen our posn before offerg. provocn of G. re-armament.



J.	Endorse that.

	“Increase or accelerate” is dangerous unless you say what you will increase etc.



A.B.	Yugoslavs tell me tht. precipitate re-armg. of G. wd. alienate Y. who suffered much fr. G.

	Don’t assume all is well behind Curtain.



			Agreed

1.	Approve formula proposed.

2.	N.B. to explain views of Cab. to E.B.

3.	C.O.S. m’while to consider at once what acceleration – so tht. its econ. implicns can be considered.



</content>
</cab>
