<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 58-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 4(51).				18th January, 1951.



	1.	Press Council.



H.M.	V. long delay.  Nothg. satisf. in this plan, except that it is some

		plan at last.  Gives undue influence to proprietors:  no repn

		of outside public.  T. of r. are also too tight.

	What shd. be our attitude?  There will be P.Q.’s.

	Journalists are takg. it up.

	We might say:  noted, departs fr. R. Commn scheme endorsed by

		H/C:  seen unacceptable to journalists:  assume proprietors will

		be discussg. with journalists &amp; more acceptable scheme may

		emerge.  W’hold comment m’while.



H.D.	W’out laymen, better have nothing.



G.A.I.	Insufft. repn of editors.  Managemt., rather than editors or 

		proprietors, wd. be represented.

	Support H.M.’s tactics.

	Rotatg. chairmanship – Newspp. Society is too weak to hold up v.

		the other.  Need for independent chairman.



A.B.	Adhere to R. Commn recommns.  Put proprietors on wrong foot.

		Independent Secretariat wd. help.



H.M.	Let journalists run the opposn:  but we can say tht. this plan doesn’t

		accord with R. Commn recommns.  Second point wd. preserve

		our liberty of action.



			Agreed.



				[Enter H.H.M.

	2.	Balance of Civil Pay.



H.G.	Memo.

	Those who have had balance/pay in past have enjoyed preferential

		posn.

		Shd. we acquiesce in that, w’in field wh. we control?

		The other system is fairer.  Why shd. body of working class

		taxpayers go on paying for pref. treatment for public servants.

	No need to change now, if Cab. think not worth the row it might 

		involve.



E.Sh.	Beg Ch/E. not to press this.  If arguments evenly balanced, wiser to

		retain status quo.

	Principle applies to manual workers in public service as well as others.



H.G.	Most of them are not called up.



P.M.	Broadly spkg. it is black-coated who benefit.

E.Sh.	Adminve cost.  Proposals for simplifying procedure – wd. cut work

		by 50%.

	Bad time to make a change anyway.  Formidable case wd. have to

		be made for a change.

	Service Ministers are v. makg. a change.  If State does less than

		private employers, controversy wd. be raised.



P.M.	Let drowsy dog sleep?



A.B.	Not so easy.  N.H.S. – convention tht. doctors etc., are not civil

		servants.

	Decide against – but w’hold announcemt. until		[Enter  E.B.

		war breaks out.



C.E.	Cdn’t do that.  I shall have to discuss with Police.

	Gave details of effect on Police.

	Majority of “manuals” will bet at least as much in Army as outside.

		Problem is smaller.  Increased Serv. pay has changed posn.



H.G.	That assumes tht. pay of regulars will be given to conscripts in war.

		Must not assume that.



C.E.	You won’t be able to avoid that in war.



H.M.	L.a.’s were compelled by legn in ’39 to give balance/civil pay.



P.M.	Better leave this ques. until war breaks out.



G.T.	Can you – ques. arises now, thro’ calling up of reservists.

		Equality of sacrifice is needed.  Can’t compel private employers

		to do this.  Therefore, stop creatg. privileged class of public 

		servants.



P.M.	Carry on existg. practice, pro tem.

	Consider implications – e.g. natd industries etc.



H.G.	I will consider further:  and prs. have an offl. Cttee.



E.B.	Don’t strike overmuch for uniformity:  creates more discontent

		than it solves.  War Grants scheme, with discretion, was wiser:

		can’t avoid means test if you are trying to remove hardship.



P.M.	Because of incidence of taxation, State pays even in private industry

		but employer determines who shall benefit.



H.H.M.	M/P. experience shd. be made available to any Cttee.

					        [Exit  H.H.M.



	

 

	3.	Convention on Human Rights.



J.	On 1st:  I prefer Assembly text.  Can Att.G. and I meet w. party &amp;

		discuss these points?

	Must make it clear tht. decns e.g. on requisitiong. are by Ministers and

		not for the courts.

	Wd. prefer small amendments in Assembly text.  Who is to decide?

	Art. 25 wd. confer on private individuals right to bring such issues

		to the Commn.



H.D.	On Assembly text:  must reserve right to tax and to nationalise

		(incldg. requisition).  Wd. prefer that stated in positive terms.

	We shall be under pressure to accept jurisdn of the court.



J.G.	Accept memo.  Want it clear tht. Protocols may be accepted

		separately in Col. territories.  Cd. not apply 7 at once in

		Colonies.



J.	Second Protocol.  “….. so far as resources permit.”  Who is to judge?

		Can Commn rule tht. our resources allow of our doing more for

		education in a Colony.



A.B.	Also “due regard to religious educn.”  Who is judge of that?



P.M.	These attributes of sovereignty are all to be transferred to a Cttee,

		respons. to no-one.



Att.G.	We must continue to resist jurisdn of any such Commn.  So long as we

		do, it doesn’t matter.



H.M.	I have always bn. against this Convention – all of it.  Humbug.



A.	Prefer a frontal attack of this nonsense.  Don’t express any sympathy.



Att.G.	Not merely Layton.  Some Tories &amp; Labour supporters keenly

		favour it.



A.B.	Why start such a court off with these v. touchy subjects.  Shd. rather

		build up its authority by startg. with prosaic subjects like

		co-ordn of steel &amp; coal indies.  This is not the end at wh. 

		supra-national bodies should start.



J.G.	These arguments really go against whole Convention, wh. we have 

		already signed.



E.B.	Cttee of experts mtg. this week.



	Ld. Ch. Dpt. represented on Working Party.

			{  Let Ld. Ch. &amp; Att.G. meet the working party.  Settle

	Agreed.	{  instns to Cttee of Experts.  But make it clear that 

			{  Cab. have not finally decided.



A.	Protocol added.

	Let it still be clear that we resist, still, the jurisdn of the Court.



A.B.	Even so, decln of principle alone wd. be dangerous.



C.E.	Inconsistent with our conceptn of unwritten constitution.



Att.G.	Danger that a Conserv. Govt. might accept jurisdn of the court.



H.M.	Cd. a subsequent Govt. then contract out



E.B.	Yes:  on 6 months’ notice.



H.G.	Assert right of Parlt to decide.



H.D.	The 2nd Protocol isn’t capable of suitable amendment.

		I shd. prefer tht. this be dropped altogether.

	The 1st cd. be made acceptable.



P.M.	Don’t think much of the 3rd.

	Doesn’t prevent “single list” system.



J.	Prefer 1st part of 3rd Protocol &amp; only last 3 lines of alternative text.



H.M.	If we argue for deletion of 2nd Protocol, you may have awkward 

		sitn in Parlt.



A.B.	Keep religious liberty &amp; educn separately.



Att.G.	“….. with due regard to the liberty of parents to ensure religious

		educn of their children.”



P.M.	3rd Protocol:  restrict to home territories.		[Exit  Att.G.

					[Enter  Ogmore.



	4.	Cocos Islands.



J.G.	Para. 13.  We shd. get it as condn.



O.	C.O.S. now think it more urgent to get air-strip prepd.

	See Menzies:  tell him decn:  say we cd. have agreemt:  &amp; urge him

		to hurry up.



J.G.	Privately.  For Singapore Govt. are responsible.  And Malaya are 

		concerned.  Premature announcemt. wd. cause trouble.

		No public statement, until all this settled.

				          [Exit  O.

				          [Enter  Scott, F.O.

	5.	Korea.



E.B.	Peking Govt. have rejected latest proposals of First Cttee.

	Frustrated efforts of P.M.M. – wh. was credit to Commonw. &amp;

		created world opinion in favour of confce betwn. e. &amp; west.,

		vice too dramatic talk of war.

	This approach went a v. long way to meet China:  &amp; to moderate U.S.

		policy.

	Not sure wtr. their answer is final rejection.  It may not be.  Tho’ most

		people assume it is.

	N. Yk. have bn. considerg. what step if this rejected.  Has bn. assumed

		tht. we shd. be almost bound to support condemnatory resoln.

		But that opens many possibilities – blockade, sanctions etc., 

		&amp; might lead to war.

	On Saty we recd draft U.S. resoln.  Gross points for resoln.  Similar

		paper fr. U.S. Embassy in Ldn.

                 	i)	Is it a rejection?  Yes:  for lays down condns wh. are impossible.

                 	ii)	Does it offer any basis for counter proposals?  Can’t find any.

		Even to suggest that to U.S. wd. inflame them.

	But don’t want hasty decn – don’t want it prominent in any resoln.

		Have counselled v. hasty decn.

                 	iii)	What shd. U.N. do?

		No condemnatory resoln shd. go beyond Korea.  It shd. not

		authorise genl. counter measures v. China generally.

	C.A.S. went to W’ton last week for consultns with U.S. C.O.S.

		He &amp; Franks are explorg. posn in non-committal talks – to

		ascertain U.S. intentns.  We shall get final draft of resoln

	Our aim has bn. restraint – negotns – limit any condemnation –

		avoid precipitate action.

	One diffy. of condemnation:  we haven’t admitted Ch. to U.N. 

		membership.

	Have therefore urged delay:  Cease Fire Cttee:  discuss:  hold hand(s)!!

	But I think weight of U.S. public opinion will force U.S. Govt. to

		speak.	

	Must keep in consultn with Comm. P.M.’s.

	Shall have to consider later what we do if U.N. authorise sanctions.

		Also posn of H. Kong.

	We assume Truman still does not favour war with China.  Assume we

		shd. keep as far away as poss. fr. anythg. wh. might provoke

		genl. war.

	Will U.S. hold b’head in Korea?  If they do, sitn will be altered.

		If they had held a line, P.M.M. plan might have succeeded.

	Reply on C.F.M. just going.



H.M.	Tel. fr. Peking suggd China might reject approach but stop fighting.

		They don’t seem to be fighting acc. to Press this a.m.

	Cd. U.S. be pressed not to pursue them if they w’draw?  Don’t let’s

		make same mistake as we did in going beyond 38th.





E.B.	I will remind Tedder of this point.

	If advice of our C.O.S. had bn. heeded, we shdn’t have bn. in this 

		mess. Hand it to them.  Cdn’t have had better advice, 

		intelligence or informn.



E.Sh.	Doubt if you’ll restrain U.S. for long.  Their conversns with C.A.S.

		are not re-assuring.  Bradley has said they can’t hold a big

		enough b’head.  Tho’ Collins has said they’ll fight.

	U.S. considerg. action they cd. take after condemn. resoln.  But they

		don’t seem to know.



P.M.	Marshall will be saner on this than Bradley.

		{	Keep steady:  try to stiffen U.S. to hold on in Korea:

		{	China may make a second offer.



A.B.	Instead of condemning China’s action in Korea, cdn’t we condemn

		their reply to our approach.  Wd. carry no consequences.

		Wd. avoid diffies in future of having condemned Ch. as

		aggressor.

	U.S. actg. unilaterally, in condemning Ch. reply – w’out consultg. us.

	Maybe, we shan’t be able to re-assert one influence over U.S. without

		an open rift.



P.M.	In reply to ques. by E.Sh:  no U.K. re-inforcemts.  What about U.S.

		puttg. some S. Americans in.

	May have to condemn Ch. action in Korea.  Don’t want a Cttee to

		consider sanctions.



H.G.	a)	Keep brake on as long as we can.  But brake, not break.

			Because of posn in Europe.

	b)	Sanctions.  U.S. can do little more.  They will ask us to do things.

			Cd. we consider in comm. grps. e.g. rubber.



E.B.	Wd. prefer to handle this on same basis as E/W. trade.



A.	Not a rejection.  An Oriental reply.



P.M.	This confirms view tht. I shd. not make a speech during coming 

		week-end.



C.E.	Hope we shall influence U.S. – diffy. of swinging U.K. public 

		opinion behind U.S. in aggressive action.



E.B.	When time comes, I shd. make the speech.  This is F. Affairs.  

		I don’t want to do it at a time or in a way provocative to U.S.A.

		Feeling in U.S. is bad:  needs v. careful handling.

	We must not lose U.S. support in Europe.

		Pacific-firsters have quadrupled their power in last 

		2 months.

	The less we say publicly on this sort of issue, the better.



</content>
</cab>
