<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 60-60</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 6(51).				        23rd January, 1951.



	1.	Meat                                  [Enter  K.Y., M.W., Ogmore &amp; Strang.



M.W.	As in memo.  Announce cut &amp; consider in 2 or 3 wks. wtr. we shd.

		make fresh approach to Argentine.



P.M.	Stand firm.  No concession to blackmail.



H.M.	Then we must press them too – by w’holdg. exports.

	But negotns since May – m’while world prices have risen.  They have

		a case for some increase.



T.W.	Consumer angle.  Workers w’out canteens can’t go on with 10d ration.

		Opinion in provinces is getting v. restive.



H.G.	Must now consider where this will end.

	Tried hard bargaining - &amp; have lost.

	Thought, on last occasion, we were in sight of agreement.  Chilled

		meat give them climb down.  But they weren’t authorised to

		negotiate.  Propn of chilled, as well as price.  Ty. authy to go to

		average price of £117 if they wd. accept propn of (?) 75% chilled.

	People are prepd to pay more for (quality especially) meat.

	Don’t therefore let us get in mood of excessive obstinacy.

	Tell Amb. in B.A. we are ready to go near £120 if enough chilled.

		How does he advise us to proceed?

		Seek a way out on these lines.  Tho’ m’while we must cut 

		ration and avoid immedte approach.



M.W.	They cdn’t give any assurance of propn of chilled.



H.D.	Para. 2(b).  Means of pressure?



M.W.	No:  for we shd. have bn. commd to pay £120 with no assurance

		re chilled.  They wdn’t resume shipment w’out assurance on

		price.



K.Y.	Immedte approach to Argentine wd. yield no result.



P.M.	What of their assumed diffies?



M.W.	U.S. bght. large amounts for stock-piling etc.

	Also farmers induced to hold back.



H.McN.	Increase of 3d a lb. wd. mean people cdn’t buy much more.

	We must therefore make it clear tht. £120 is our top price.

	If so, we must be sure we can hold 8d indefinitely.



M.W.	We can – if public will stand it.



H.McN.	They won’t stand it, unless we make it clear we are in a fight with

		Argentine.



H.W.	Shall we win, in the end, if we try to stand out on basis of so low a

		ration.  Argentine diffies have not matured.



H.G.	On £120 p. t. at 50% chilled:  1d and 1½d frozen &amp; chilled.

	Ty. authy to go to 3d on chilled.  M/F. wd. pass on 2d.

	Allowg. for 5 Dom. consequentials, the resulting increase wd. be 

		1¼d if spread over all meat supplies.  Wdn’t people be ready

		to pay that?



H.W.	Needn’t increase real c/living because fish &amp; rabbits, now being 

		eaten, are dearer.  (Real, not index.)



A.	We are not going to beat Argentines down.

	Public wd. pay another 1½d if they cd. get more meat.

	Take the cowardly line.



J.	Prices are rising – get a long-term agreemt.



A.B.	Argentines are only doing for meat what Australia has done on wool –

		seekg. best price they can get.

	Seek easiest way of getting the meat quickly.



H.McN.	i)	No point in approachg. Argentines until we know what U.S. are 

			doing.

	ii)	Approach thro’ Barings wd. prob. help if F.O. don’t object.



			Agreed:   Announce ration change as proposed.

			              {M/F., F.O. &amp; Ty. to consider method of

			              {    makg. a new approach.

					       [Exit  M.W.



	2.	Korea.



K.Y.	……………….

	Press for delay.  Then i)   how do we follow up discns with China?

			                  ii)  if we fail on that, how do we vote?

	Various points in resolution:-

		a)	We shd. support good offices clause.

		b)	Aggression clause.  Shd. alienate U.S. if we opposed it.

			    Effect on Chinese:  Indians think it wd. slam the door: 

			    we &amp; Canada doubt that.

		c)	Wdn’t wish to support Coll. Measures Cttee &amp; sanctions.



P.M.	P.M.M. started initiative for settlement.

	Ch. reply – we said we shd. consider.  U.S. jumped in against.

		We shd. keep that door open.



W.E.	Mil. sitn is better.



P.M.	Indians think Ch. don’t want genl. war.  They may be holding off.

	We shd. continue our earlier policy.  We didn’t like U.S. resoln &amp; 

		urged them to put it in 2 parts.  We can’t deny Ch. has commd

		aggression:  but we don’t want sanctions etc.

	Continue to urge divn of resoln.

	This vote must have steadied U.S.



A.	Must vote v. clause notg. tht. Ch. have rejected proposals.



K.Y.	Jebb’s suggn:   Chairman to ask Peking wtr. elucidn replaced original

		reply.  Or refer to Cease Fire Group.  Neither was adopted.



P.M.	There shd. be some positive proposal to replace U.S. resoln.



J.G.	Last Ch. reply will be taken by publ. opinion as a new approach.

		Mustn’t carry on discn on basis of U.S. resoln.



H.McN.	Why did Rau not favour tabling Peking note?  He favours settlemt. by

		negotn.  He must have some other view re handling it.



H.D.	Jebb shd. talk further on this with Rau &amp; Pearson.



P.M.	In principle support any effort designed to promote negotiation with 	Ch.  Support anythg. to get that discussed before U.S. resoln.  In last 	resort, disagree with some clauses of U.S. resoln.  Can’t yet decide how 	we shd. ultimately vote.



H.G.	Ch. reply = demand for 2 things wh. we know U.S. won’t concede.

	Forthcomg. only on cease-fire proposal.

	Somethg. in St. Bennett’s argument tht. purpose of Ch. reply is to

		divide Asiatic &amp; W. powers.

	We don’t want break with U.S. either.

	What do F.O. believe Ch. really means – in long term, what

		prospect of ultimate settlemt.



K.Y.	If Ch. cd. get some satisfn on recognn &amp; Formosa, they might accept

		settlement.

	Elucidn means they are still makg. 2 long-term demands.

		But some readiness to agree to timetable on negotns wh. wd.

		be in line with Principles.

	Of course they also have in mind splitting Allies.



H.G.	Any discn with State Dpt. on elucidn?



K.Y.	Not yet.  Franks is now to make strong repns.



A.	Explain also to U.S. Amb. here?



P.M.	He can’t influence Acheson.



A.B.	Fight for better climate of U.S. opinion (thro’ ceasefire) to discuss

		long-term issues re F/East.



H.McN.	Austin’s statemt. – inconsistent with P.M.’s W’ton talks.

	Can we not ask W’ton (because of that &amp; also Gross) to admit tht.

		this is not helpful.



K.Y.	We were going to ask Franks to do so.  Also re MacA.’s speech

		comparing Ch. aggression with Pearl Harbour.



P.M.	Statement in Parlt?



A.	Salisbury doesn’t press for one, if we think it embarrassing.



K.Y.	We cd. only say in light Ch. reply pressing for time to consider.

		That might help.



A.B.	Chronicle of events:  might help.



P.M.	What of supplementaries.



K.Y.	Can Jebb say now tht. he won’t vote for U.S. resoln.



P.M.	Urge delay:  say there will be amendmts on resoln:  can’t say how he

		will vote until seen how resoln emerges.

	Support condemnn Ch. action:  he can say that.  But reserve right to

		dodge word “aggression”.  Tho’ in last resort we may have to

		accept it.



P.M.	Other Comm. Govts. to be kept informed.   

 



</content>
</cab>
