<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 62-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 8(51).				25th January, 1951.

				[5 p.m.]



	1.	Korea.                                              [Same invitees as for a.m.	                                         



K.Y.	Jebb must know what to do on a vote, when it comes.  U.S. resoln

		substantially as it stands will be put to vote before end/week.

	Issues	a)  “rejected all U.N. proposals.”  No longer true.

			b)  “has itself engaged in aggression in K.”

			c)  “Coll. Measures Cttee to consider addl measures &amp;

			              report.

	Voting first by paras.  Then as a whole.  Unlikely any paras. will be

		voted out.

	We can’t vote now for a) as it stands.  U.S. might alter

		it.		            Vote against.

	On b) P.M. used a difft. and deliberate phrase.  But is

		diffce substantial?  We thght. U.S. phrase wd. import

		sanctions &amp; ours wdn’t.  On reflection I doubt if any

		save a lawyer wd. understand the difference.       Accept that.

	On c) diff. to oppose considn of measures.  But we know

		U.S. want to get some measures applied – at least

		dipl. &amp; econ. sanctions.                                         Vote against.

	On vote as a whole:  can’t vote for it at this stage if

		a), b) &amp; c) all stand.  Must be one further attempt at negotn.

	If, however, they alter a) to meet us, more diff. choice.

		Shd. we insist on follow-up of Ch. reply before we vote.

		Or shd. we vote for it, but make it clear we want negotns to

		continue &amp; tht. we don’t favour genl. sanction.

		We shd. then follow with positive proposal for followg. up with

		negotns.



P.M.	Can., Austr. &amp; N.Z. will support.  Tho’ Austr. will say they disagree

		with it.



K.Y.	Yes:  &amp; S.A. &amp; France.  Tho’ all agree with our policy &amp; not with U.S.

		resoln.



P.M.	V. diff. choice.  Aggression has bn. commd.  But U.S. have insisted on

		putting it in worst light – e.g. refusal to divide resoln.



K.Y.	Asian resoln unlikely to get much support.



P.M.	Cd. we support that &amp; if it fails vote for U.S. as pis-aller.



H.McN.	Cd. Indians be asked to move U.N. to invite Ch. elucidn?



K.Y.	U.S. wdn’t listen.  Stone-wall to our repns in W’ton.  Austin has said

		door is shut, after being told that further elucidn was recd.



H.McN.	On a) we shd. seek amendmt. e.g. by omitting “all”.  That wd. make

		it easier for us to vote against clause if our amendmt failed.

		Preferable to put fwd. a clearer amendmt.



J.G.	This resoln might lead to major war.  Drafted before events of last

		week.  Depends on 1st clause.



H.D.	Are we to be led by stages to war v. China?  It wd. be grave error

		in strategy (COS).  Inconsistent with P.M.’s statemt.

		Unacceptable to publ. opinion.  Plays into hands of R.

		We must therefore prevent it.

                  	2) Must try to restrain U.S.  Diff. to do.  Tel. fr. Franks:  U.S. will

		hate our voting against resoln:  but that feeling will pass.



H.M.	Cd P.M. approach Truman.



P.M.	He can’t now go v. Congress.  He has allowed them to go too far.



J.	Means splitting, not only with U.S., but all our friends.



A.B.	But if we vote for it &amp; say we don’t believe in it, we proclaim

		ourselves as satellites of U.S.

	We were ready to go as far as agreeing to ‘brand’ if other clauses

		were out.

	Surely U.K. cd. give a lead to the world, as against U.S.



H.McN.	Not so simple.  U.S. publ. opinion thinks our choice is betwn. India

		&amp; U.S.  India has given this lead.  We wd. be followg. it.

	Franks says storm will blow over.  We had one over Pal. - &amp; it

		blew over in the main.

	Dilemma:  Soviet plan:  if it splits us fr. U.S., it succeeds:  if we

		support U.S. on this, it has relative success.

	Conclude:  make our posn clear:  push Ch. further to negotiate.

		Vote against a) unless amended.  Also against c).  But for b).

		Then, after explanns, vote for resoln but go on trying for negotn.



H.W.	Not unimportant to keep India in good heart.  She is vital in Asia.



P.M.	Vote v. a) and c) – not against b).

	[If a) stands unamended – vote v. whole resoln.] 

	If all our amendmts rejected, abstain.



K.Y.	We shall have made our posn clear on each para.

	Criticism of Gt. Power for abstaining on major issue.

	If we can’t vote for, we ought to vote against – self-respect.

		E.B. up to week-end favoured standg. with U.S. in last resort.

	If we vote with U.S. when everyone knows we oppose the policy our

		internatl standing &amp; influence is destroyed for ever.

	If ever we are to stand v. U.S., this is the time.  For all our friends

		agree with us on the merits.



H.M.	On balance, agree with K.Y.



C.E.	Agree.  If we vote, we wd. feel bound to support coll. measures.

		But our people wdn’t stand for that.



A.	Agree.



J.G.	Quite wrong to abstain or vote for.



H.G.	If we vote against:  shall seem to oppose those paras. we do support.

		Therefore, I wd. prefer to abstain.



K.Y.	Qua troops in Korea I don’t like refusing to vote for b).



C.N.S.	Abstain on that a/c.



H.G.	What do you lose by abstaining?



P.M.	We asked for separation.  Consistent to abstain.



H.McN.	We cd. abstain in Cttee &amp; consider then wtr. we shd. vote against in

		Assembly – when we see if vote wd. be effective.



J.G.	If we don’t vote against, we shall surrender our moral leadership.



K.Y.	We won’t vote for because closes door on negotns.  How then can we

		justify not voting against it.



H.D.	It’s c) I most object to.  That’s why I favour clear vote against.



			By a majority:  Agreed to instruct Jebb to vote against.   

						[Exit  K.Y.



	2.	Defence Programme.



	Man Power.



P.M.	Def. Cttee endorse plan for 15 days’ call-up.  But doubt 3 months’

		proposal.  This applies to Army.

	R.N.  No objn.

	R.A.F.  Bulk have reserve oblign.  



A.H.	10.000 Z. reservists.



P.M.	But only wanted for 15 days.		[Exit H.McN.



V.C.I.G.S.	15 days’ plan:  needed to stiffen T.A. – until in 3 yrs.  Nat. Ser. men

		come along.  To get T.A. Divns. more ready to go to NATO

		defence &amp; to M/E.



A.B.	Assurance tht. good use will be made of them in the 15 days.

		Otherwise v. bad publicity.



J.S.	Shall do our best.  But they are going to T.A. camps.  Better than last

		year because of nos.  But it’s mobilisation exercise, purpose of

		wh. is to detect faults &amp; errors.  Agree:  tell them this when they

		arrive:  it’s a rehearsal.



C.E.	Make Cab. views known to offrs. at unit level.



H.D.	Selection?



J.S.	Those already earmarked as requd for these Divns.



H.D.	Needs to be explained in P.M.’s statement.		[Re-enter  K.Y.



J.	Age?



V.C.I.G.S.	A few over 40:  none above 45.



P.M.	Must try to avoid men over 40:  as you are implying that these men 

		will be embodied in these T.A. Divns. on outbreak.



H.M.	Enough to give assurances tht. these over 40 will be few &amp; for jobs

		like AA Batty.



P.M.	M/L. can look at this ques. again.

	*Consider White Paper on this, for details, as soon as poss. after 

		statement.



			Agreed:  15 days’ plan approved in principle.



P.M.	Three months’ plan.



V.C.I.G.S.	More important qua readiness for war.  Stiffens BAOR. &amp; Strat. 

		Reserve.  Those Divns. – now 60% strength.  Shd. rise to 75% in

		summer:  then fall.

		They have 60% young N.S. men.

		In emergency they wd. have to fight at 70% strength &amp; mostly

		youngsters.  In ’39, 120.000 Reg. Army Reserve.  To-day, none

		U.S. Divns. in Korea were in same state &amp; took a knock.



P.M.	Partial mobilisation for a period.  Implies specially dangerous 

		period.  Wd imply risk of war in summer.



H.G.	C.O.S. think there is a risk this summer.  Dangerous to reject it if it

		wd. materially strengthen B.A.O.R. this year.



A.B.	M/D. &amp; Serv. Ministers don’t support this.



J.S.	Didn’t lightly w’hold our support.  Wd be advantageous militarily.

	If we thght. we cd. thereby hold R. attack this summer, we might

		support.  But it wd. do no more than give BAOR a better 

		chance to get out.  We decided tht. on balance we cdn’t 

		recommend it.



P.M.	I think we must reject this 3 months’ plan.



V.C.I.G.S.	In that case wd. want to call 10.000 for 15 days’ under 11(iv).

	Also want 5.000 for AA Command for 3 months.



P.M.	* Try to get this stiffening by volunteers.  -  Agreed.

	Para. 11.(vii)  Korea – reinforcemts.   Rejected.

	R.A.F. Plans.   Approved.



P.M.	Para. 14(iv)   Try to get this voluntarily.



C.A.S.	They expect call-up – in Ldn. anyhow.  They wd. understand.

	I wd. prefer to call them up.

	These are 40% of 1st line Fighter strength.



			Agreed:  Do para. 14(iv) by embodiment, not volunteerg.



	Pay for 15 days’ men.



H.G.	Regular rates + bounty.  Much higher than N.S. pay.  V. big

		precedent.  They shd. receive N.S. rates.



H.W.	Conscripts get that pay after 18 months.  These will all have served

		18 mos. or more.



H.G.	That was to persuade them to stay on.



J.S.	T.A. will be getting regular pay.



P.M.	N.S. men:  untrained.  These and trained men coming up for service.

		Can’t equate them with 18 yr. old N.S. men.

	Publicity is to be on basis tht. these are men needed for Army.



V.C.I.G.S.	Everyone of these men will have had at least 2 years’ service.



			Agreed:     Pay as proposed by C.O.S.  Make it clear

			               { tht. this is because they are trained men:

			               { &amp; this is not therefore a precedent.



	Call-up (Numbers).



P.M.	As in his memo.



T.W.	On behalf of Scotland &amp; self – inexpedient to do this anyway.

		But we are doing expansive p’mme.  Our lack of manpower

		will become more pronounced.  We are losing labour.  E.V.W.’s

		are going.  German PoW.’s qualifying for natn, after wh. they can

		go.  W.L.A. abolished.  Ty. have abolished our pool labour, by

		end/51.  L.e.a.’s increasingly reluctant to supply children.

		W.A. Cttees  apprehensive of labour for lifting potatoes.

	¾ of all farms – only one or two workers.  Dislocn therefore is

		disproportionate.

                  y/	Industry wd. assume we aren’t backg. expansionist p’mme any longer.

	If Agric. must make a contn, let M/L. &amp; ourselves to devise scheme to

		get 7.000 a year fr. farms wh. cd. let them go.

		Or:  if deferment is w’drawn, wait until after harvest of 1951.



P.M.	Yet you can’t tie agric. workers to the land.  And they will go where

		we don’t want them.  Let’s have these where we do want ‘em.



A.B.	Can’t accept y/.  Other industies have expansion p’mmes.

	Exchanges report men going into agric. to escape N.S.  V. serious.

		Like the income tax farmers.  Suppose they keep their sons out

		of N.S. also.



H.G.	Blanket imposed when we had to run autarchic policy re imported

		food.  Don’t need to do so now.



A.B.	Para. 13. – exceptional hardship can be looked after.  We shan’t take

		men who absence wd. close down the farm.



A.	i)	Safeguard only sons.

	ii)	I opposed abolition of W.L.A.  I wd. now revive it.  }To be

					        }considered.  

A.B.	N.F.U. cd. run such an organn.  Don’t let Ty. pay for it.    }



			Agreed:  Def. Cttee conclusions endorsed.

			               Agric. deferment.  Announce at once.  Fix 

			                  suitable date some time ahead.



	Production.



P.M.	Clothing.

	Works Services.



A.B.	All this depends on formula – to avoid worst impacts on economy.

	Can’t endorse all that’s in this memo. e.g. in para. 53.



P.M.	Much will have to be worked out later.



	Civil Departments Plans.



P.M.	D(T) Cttee report approved apart from black-out equipmt. &amp; materials.



	Civil Defence.



P.M.	As in his memo.



C.E.	Phasing.  Shdn’t work to 2 dates.  Military workg. to 1952.

	Country unprepared for air attack if it comes.  V. little in the 

		£150 m. wh. is c. defence for ordinary public.



P.M.	That is a fair statement.

	We must either break our backs with prepns or choose priorities.

	We are preventg. war.  Active def. more likely to do that than

		passive defence.  Provn of much public shelter wdn’t be a

		deterrent.

	The risk must be accepted.



C.E.	Let it be a Cab. decision – if so, I can’t dissent from it.

	I shd. wish to say it’s a Cab. decn to concentrate on active defence

		in pursuance of policy of preventg. war.



</content>
</cab>
