<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 71-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 17(51).				5th March, 1951.



	1.	Offices of Profit.	[Enter  3 L.O.’s



C.E.	Questions for decision:-

	a)	Paras. 8-9:  renunciation of remuneration.  If this shd.

		disqualify, escape shd. not be provided by renouncg. 

		remuneration:  might prevent person of limited means from

		serving.



S.G.	Many offices for wh. M.P.’s needed:  this prevents their services

		being used.  E.g. membership of Advisory Councils where

		paymt. can be made.



A.B.	E.g. Local Emplt. Cttee:   Advisory Cttee on Disabled Persons.



S.G.	Also:  not easy to say wtr. M.P. is disqualified.  Wd be helpful in

		case of doubt if M.P. cd. remove the doubt by renouncg.

		remuneration.



H.M.	Dislike general provn for renunciation.

	Some exceptions already – where clear tht. expenses don’t permit

		“profit”.

	Awkward if we offer posn to 2 M.P.’s:  &amp; Tory accepts but Labour 

		can’t afford to.

	I wd. prefer to continue to make specific statutory provisions in each

		(new) case.  Or dare we say it can be done by aff. resolution.



Att.G.	Bill will allow travelling &amp; subsistce at top C. Service rates – but no

		“loss of remunerative time”.



P.M.	Doesn’t that cover most cases?



A.B.	No:  for the office permits a claim for “loss of remunerative time”.



Att.G.	I think it wd. be dangerous to allow renunciation, as a general

		proposn.  A man apptd Director of B/E., even if he renounced

		remuneration, wd. be thereby in favourable posn to get other

		directorships etc.



C.E.	Cl. 2(3) a) and b) set out reasonable provision.  If desired to exempt

		particular office, it shd. be done in the Bill creating the office.

		We can’t foresee the need in advance, in genl. legn.  May create

		more problems than it solves.



A.B.	Do we need to go on with this Bill at all:  Tendentious speeches &amp;

		headlines – even if “official” concurrence of Tories were secured.

		Don’t trust Tory back-benchers.



P.M.	Are we pledged?

Solr.G.	4 Indemnificn Bills in this Parlt:  &amp; on each occasion Govt. has 

		accepted view tht. law shd. be clarified.



C.E.	This shd. be cleared up.  Negotns in my last para. will take some time.



A.B.	But do we have to proceed in this Parlt.



H.M.	There’s nothg. to be ashamed of – no muck to rake.

	Bill must be completed:  then consultn with Opposn:  can’t pass this 

		Session anyway – at most, publish.



A.B.	That wd. be maladroit.

	And 18 cases hanging about for wh. Indemnity Bills wd. be needed.



			General view:  we must go on with this, w’out prejudice

			                         to later discn of wtr. Bill shd. be introduced

			                         in current Session.



P.M.	Renunciation of remuneration:  Endorse C.E.’s recommendation.

	After further discn:  Agreed:

		 i)  No general provision for renunciation of remunn.

		ii)  M.P. may serve on a Cttee whose members may claim loss of

			remunerative time, but he may not claim for loss of 

			remunerative time.



	b)	Emoluments in Kind.



J.	Goes too far.  E.g. my tea as Govr. of Tate Gallery.



Sol.G.	Endorse that:  we were sure you cdn’t cover every possible abuse.

		We therefore limited remuneration to money payment.

		To introduce ambiguous phrases like C.E.’s makes nonsense of

		attempt to clear up this jungle.



Att.G.	“Significant benefit in kind”



Solr.G.	Prestige is convertible to money.  Stick to plain language, if our 

		object is to make the law intelligible.



H.M.	Principle is right.  Surely we can find words.



A.B.	Can’t find water-tight formula.



C.E.	This is even more important than money payment.



Att.G.	“Any material &amp; tangible benefit in kind”



J.	Gt. need here is for certainty.  Must leave no scope for interpretn –

		“substantial” or “material” are impossible.

 

Solr.G. 	If you try to stop all evasion, you will get a Bill like a Finance Bill.

		Do avoid ambiguities.



			Agreed:  See wtr. a formula can be devised.



	c)	Office or Place.                               No comment.

	d)	Number of Ministers in H/C.                    ..

	e)	Contractors.



P.M.	G.P.O. case?



S-G.	Led to 1931 Act.  It’s illogical.  We have re-enacted it:  as it hasn’t

		led to any controversy.



J.	One-man company.



S-G.	See Cl. 6.



Att.G.	I shd. wish existg. law to be enlarged to cover services.



Sol.G.	A v. large task.



	f)	Enforcement.                    No comment.



C.E.	g)	Relief from Disqualification.  This = substantial change.  A

	simpler procedure.  Means (because no Bill) tht. H/L. will have no say

		in it.

			Agreed.



	h)	Local Authority Staffs.



C.E.	Present sitn anomalous.  Employee of co. council can’t be elected.

	My Cttee recommends as in para. 18.



H.M.	Not sure.  If you disqualify any, mustn’t you cover all the chief 

		offrs?  A M.O. or Edn Offr. may have as strong a pol. influence

		as the Deputy Clerk.  Much to be said for repealing existg. law

		and leaving it to good sense of l.a.’s.



P.M.	Why prevent them fr. standing outside own area?



Att.G.	Support S.G.’s Cttee.  Wrong for M.P. to be in posn to advise a l.a., as

		senior officer, e.g. on housing.



H.D.	Disqualifn shdn’t be limited to constituency.  Agree with C.E. on that.

	But on range of officers, I agree with H.M.

	But sure you can’t leave it to good sense of l.a.’s.

	Endorse therefore C.E.’s recommn but go to all chief officers.



A.B.	Where do you draw the line?  Accountants, Ch. Engineers etc.

	I wd. limit disqualifn to Town Clerk.



P.M.	Is this a practical point.  Do such people want to stand.



C.E.	Must amend Co. Council’s Act, wh. disqualifies any officer of 

		co. council.

	I incline to view tht. you can’t go beyond Clerk and, at most, Deputy.



P.M.	Base it on returning officer duty.



H.M.	I wd. prefer to repeal the co. council provision, as archaic;  but leave

		the rest to adminn – after a Govt. declaration of view.



			Agreed: (provisionally) limit to Town Clerks &amp; Deputies.



	i)	Directors of Steel Companies.



S.Genl.	Bill applies to directors of Corpn but not of companies.

	Conflicting considerations – as in memo.



C.E.	My Cttee endorses this, unanimously.



H.G.	I agree:  comparable to senior officials of Boards of socialised indies.

		Wtr. they can be M.P.’s is matter for Board, not for Parlt.



A.B.	These men shd. not be M.P.’s.



P.M.	Place-men.



Sol.G.	Yes:  but diff. to disqualify scores of existg. Members.



J.G.	Steel Corpn surely cd. handle this – by saying their directorship wd.

		not be renewed.



H.M.	Wd prefer to deal with it by statute (because place-men argument)

		even tho’ we give longish period of notice e.g. the life of

		[present] Parliament in wh. this Bill is passed.



J.	You wd. have to extend to all employees of these companies.



A.B.	No.  Can distinguish betwn. directors &amp; employees.



H.McN.	Future apptmts, made by Minister, are indefensible.

	But existg. apptmts, not so made, are different.  Views of M/S. shd. be

		ascertained.

			             To be considered further.



		Agreed:  Revised Bill to be considered further by Legn Cttee.

			      Any further points of principle to come again to 

			             Cabinet.

				[Exit  3 L.O.’s

	2.	Korea.



E.B.	Franks told tht. ques. of crossing 38th has bn. reviewed, in light of

		opinions of “joint” C.O.S.;  and expression of U.S. Govt. views 

		has bn. promised.  Tho’ not received.



A.	Para. 3(?) of F.O. memo.  Have we had a guarantee of consultn?



E.B.	Don’t think so.  Only an understanding at desk level.



A.B.	Surely we must get it.



P.M.	We await it, in Acheson’s reply.



E.Sh.	Isn’t it U.N.?  If so, can’t conclude it betwn. U.K. and U.S. Govt.



E.B.	Good Offices Cttee.  Message fr. President of U.N. has elicited no

		response.  Sitn hardened, after Stalin interview in Pravda.

	R. peace offensive will prob. start off now in new direction.  4 Power

		Mtg. will prob. be scene for resoln roping in China.  Also a new

		anti-U.N. offensive will prob. be launched by R.



E.Sh.	This emphasises need to make it clear tht. U.N. controls action in 

		Korea.



E.B.	Diff. – when no-one save U.S. and Comm. is doing anything.



E.Sh.	Signs tht. China are mounting a spring offensive.  May start in 

		3 wks. or so.  They are getting new supplies of armaments.





	3.	Japanese Peace Treaty.



H.G.	Discussed betwn. Dpts.  No comments.



P.M.	Para. 8.  What happens to the money?



H.W.	That is still being considered, with Ty.



H.D.	Make it clear before statement is made.



H.M.	Written answer?	}

				}If oral, make it shorter.

H.G.	Matter of public concern.  Many P.Q.’s.	}



J.G.	Want opportunity to consult Col. Govts.



G.W.	And Comm. Govts. too.



H.McN.	Wd help us, if we cd. say so in H/C.

		{	Clarify (e.g. para. 8)

		{	Consult other Govts.

		{	Do it in writing or, if oral, much shorter.

	After discussion, - is it necessary to make a statement at all?

			Adjourn for further discussion.





	4.	University Education in Dundee &amp; St. Andrews.



H.M.	Waste of time of 1st class industrialist.



H.D.	And doesn’t sound like a Scot.



H.McN.	Not a matter for conciliation – it’s for a finding.



A.	Support H.McN.



H.G.	May we suggest other names.



			H.McN. &amp; H.G. to discuss &amp; consult H.M. 



</content>
</cab>
