<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/8/0 images: 72-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 18(51).				8th March, 1951.



	1.	Matrimonial Causes Bill.	[Enter  W.W., Att.G.



H.M.	Amendment tabled for rejection of Bill, wh. wd. enable divorce

		sitn to be presented on basis of 7 years’ separation.  Raises

		religious ques.  We cd. be neutral, as Govt. was on Herbert’s

		Bill:  and everyone (incldg. Ministers) cd. have a free vote.

		Promoter wd. prefer that.

		Or we cd. propose a R. Commn  &amp; we cd. then defeat the 

		Bill.  Objectn:  some day Commd wd. report &amp; Govt. wd. have

		diffy.



P.M.	Let it take its course.



J.	If the Bill were carried, there wd. be stronger case for Commn.



P.M.	The Bill wdn’t get through.  H/L. wd. throw it out.

	Ministers to be free to vote as they pleased.



H.McN.	If 2nd Rdg. is carried, Party pressure both for &amp; against facilities for

		further stages.



P.M.	No reason why we shd. give facilities.



A.B.	They were given for Herbert’s Bill.  I favour this Bill.



H.D.	Time is now v. giving facilities.



E.Sh.	Ques. of divorce laws is much wider than this Bill.  We cd. refuse 

		facilities on that ground.  Wiser course (some day, not now) wd.

		be to appoint R. Commn.



P.M.	We shd. delay that until more experience of legal aid system.



Att.G.	If we say we are neutral &amp; Bill gets 2nd Rdg. diff. to avoid Herbert Bill

		precedent of giving further facilities.

	Diff. to go on refusing either to legislate or to appoint R. Commn.



P.M.	Can’t accept view tht. because Bill gets 2nd Rdg. we must give 

		facilities.



H.D.	If it takes its place in queue, it surely won’t get thro’.

	It will be behind Transport Bill – wh. we must obstruct.



A.B.	R. Commn wd. only pile up worse trouble for the future.

	No fact-finding.   This is principle.  R. Commn wdn’t help.



J.	Function of R. Commn is to prepare public opinion for change – by

		hearing evce &amp; ventilatg. arguments.

H.M.	Favour, on balance, a R. Commn.



P.M.	Bound to be composed of partisans:  &amp; likely to have various 

		minority reports.



			Preponderant view in Cabinet:  in favour of apptg. R.

			Commn.

			Agree:  announce this in Friday’s debate.

			             Get promoters on that basis to w’draw Bill.

			             If they are ready to w’draw it, movers of

			             Amendmt won’t press it.



H.McN.	Then, if that line is taken by Govt. spokesman, Ministers can’t

		vote for the Bill.



A.B.	I disagree.  This is Private Members’ Bill.  I’ve said I wd. vote for it:

		pledged to promoters.



E.Sh.	Govt. are now involved if they decide to appoint R. Commn.



H.G.	Not unless Att.G. argues tht. piece-meal legn on this subject is wrong.



Att.G.	And that is the reason for a R. Commn.



T.W.	Att.G. cd. say no promise of further time.



A.B.	That means tht. vote on 2nd Rdg. is merely demonstration.  And no

		reason why Ministers shd. not be free to vote as they wish.



P.M.           x/	Say we will appoint R. Commn:  tht. we won’t therefore provide 

		provide further time:  but H/C. can express an opinion on

		2nd Rdg. – free vote.



J.G.	Better try to persuade promoters &amp; opponents to scratch the match

		on basis of R. Commn.



H.G.	P’pone announcg. R. Commn until after the vote?



A.B.	I agree with x/.



			A.B. to see promoters.

			Att.G. &amp; W.W. to see movers of amendment.





	2.	Parliament.                            }

	N.A.T.O. Command Organisation.}



H.M.	Business for next week.



	12/3:  Navy Estimates.  Fechteler may be raised.  Our idea was to

		wait until wider announcement cd. be made.



E.Sh.	Separate Iberian command can be kept out of debate.

	Admy view:  command ques. shd. emerge after Mulvey’s Motion

		has bn. put (not in opening speech).  And I can follow on

		W.S.C.



W.W.	But when we saw Opposn, it was understood tht. in p’poned debate

		we shd. make statement early.  We ought to do that.



H.M.	Then original statement shd. be made by P.M.



H.D.	Callaghan cd. do it.



E.Sh.	Much wider than Admy ques. – N.A.T.O.



P.M.	If he wishes wd. be appropte.



E.B.	Public opinion needs to be satisfied  i) on this particular appointmt

		ii) tht. steps have bn. taken to ensure this won’t happen again.



E.Sh.	Will Speaker allow genl. discn of command structure (incldg. air &amp;

		land) in debate on Navy Estimates?



P.M.	Surely.



E.Sh.	Then not by Callaghan.



H.M.	Statement by P.M. after Ques., re command structure.



P.M.	No:  because it’s argument not announcement.



E.Sh.	Indicated course of discn on other commands.  Not ready to announce.



A.	Temper in H/L. suggests tht. you wd. get away w’out that in H/C. on

		Monday.



H.G.	M/D. must make the statement in 2nd part of debate.  Get an agreement

		tht. debate will be in 2 parts:  &amp; tht. Opposn won’t raise this

		ques. in 1st part of debate.



E.B.              *	Promise W. Paper on command organn as a whole, when all is settled.*



E.Sh.	Agreed.





	3.	Parliament.



H.M.	Business for next week.

	Tuesday 13/3.

	Durham County Council.



W.W.	In makg. new appointmts l.a. has bn. askg. what Union applicant

		belongs.

	In all appointmts so far, all save one have declined to say.  And that one

		has bn. appointed.  A new h’master will take office on Monday,

		and the other masters will then walk out.



G.T.	If they do, I can act.



H.D.	N.U.T. are mtg. Co. Council, and sound hopeful.



H.M.	Budget 10/4.                        }     I propose to announce these dates

	22/3 to 3/4 Easter Recess.   }    to-day.



A.B.	Driving the H/C. too hard.



H.McN.	Tories want longer.  Cd. you not make a deal with them.



H.D.	Ministers over-worked;  and Members faded.



H.M.	If we give extra week, we must drop some Ministerial Bills.



A.	Ministers must be more reasonable in Legn Cttee.



			Agreed:  extend Recess by one week.





	4.	Korea.



E.B.	Am circulatg. a long memo – in 24 hrs’ time.   | Meant memo. on

				|  Germany (Wilford

E.Sh.	Confirmn of Chinese offensive.	|  F.O.)



</content>
</cab>
