<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/58/30 images: 236-239</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY MS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1944.SECRET.W.P. (44) 680.22nd November, 1944.WAR CABINET.CIVIL AVIATION.Note by the Secretary.BY direction of the Prime Minister I circulate herewith the Memorandum,which the Minister of Aircraft Production read to the War Cabinet to-day, onthe Civil Aviation discussions with the United States representatives at theChicago Conference.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,22nd November, 1944.Memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production.&apos; The main points in issue are as to the share in traffic between the differentoperators on the same route.2. The provisional agreement (Great Britain; United States; Canada)laid it down that the number of services to be run by the operators of eachnationality should be decided upon the basis of the traffic embarked in each country for transport over the route.   (This has been referred to as Frequencies.)3. The division of the traffic was to be on the basis of each aircraft carrying80 per cent, of its maximum load, e.g., if on route New York, Montreal, Londonand return, the traffic embarked was per day : New York (United States)      .........      50Canada     ...      ...       ...      ...      ...      ...      20Great Britain     ...       ...      ...      ...      ...      70140this would be 60 per cent, of the total capacity to be provided, i.e., Total capacity to be provided would be 233. This wouifl be divided between the three countriesin the proportion of traffic embarked : Pei cent.United StatesCanadaGreat Britain4. A further provision was inserted (against our desires) to provide a means of increasing the share of frequencies of any country whose aircraft werepersistently carrying more than their share of the traffic. This is referred to asthe escalator clause.[28673]Copy No.501402014070140of 233 - 83-0 = 36-0of 233 = 33-0 ^ 13-0of 233 = 117-0 - 51-0
5. If any country&apos;s aircraft consistently (over one year) were operated atmore than 65 per cent, of their capacity, that country would be entitled to anincrease of frequencies to reduce its loading to 65 per cent. This increase wouldnot mean a decrease of other operators&apos; frequencies and so would lead to a net increase of frequencies.6. The Americans were only prepared to accept this system of frequencyallocation provided they were granted the fifth freedom, i.e., the right to pick up and set down traffic on any of their routes originating in and destined forcountries other than America, e.g., Koute: New York, London, Cairo, Karachi.United States aircraft could pick up in London and set down in Cairo orKarachi and vice versa.This we were prepared to grant provided that the air services between inter-mediate points (e.g., London-Cairo) were adequately protected against unduecompetition by the through aircraft.7. It was also understood that this intermediate traffic picked up wouldnot count towards the escalator clause, which should be concerned only with the through traffic between terminal points.8. Similarly, the determination of frequencies on the Main Route (in the example given, New York-Karachi) would depend upon the traffic carried throughon that route and not upon traffic picked up and carried between intermediatepoints.9.   At the last moment the Americans put in a further claim which com-pletely altered the w-hole arrangement and effect of the draft.They claimed the right to duplicate any intermediate service with theirthrough aircraft irrespective of whether any of the traffic originated in America,e.g., in the case given above, New York-London-CairO-Karachi. They claimed to run as many aircraft from London to Cairo as we did, and the same from -London-Karachi, regardless whether any of the traffic at all originated inAmerica.10.   The difference between the tentative agreement and their present claim is (in the case stated) : -Tentative agreement.Through route New York-Karachi. Frequencies fixed on basis ofembarkations in New York and in Karachi subject to effect of escalatorclause.Through route New York-London.   Frequencies fixed in the same way.Between London-Cairo-Karachi the Americans have no frequencies, but their through running aircraft are allowed to pick up and set down subjectto protection of these intermediate services by a fare differential.A merican claim.New York-Karachi. Frequencies fixed on basis of all passengers carried by American or Indian aircraft in either direction irrespective of the lengthof route travelled (e.g., passengers Cairo-London would be counted in).New York-London frequencies fixed in same way.London-Cairo-Karachi and vice versa. Americans entitled to run as many services on each leg of the route as the local operators are running andto pick up and set down passengers,- It is not certain whether they agree a differential charge or not.11. It will be noted that this gives the Americans the right to duplicate(and with the escalator clause eventually to monopolise) every route in the worldbetween any two points wherever they are, provided they are not both in the samecountry.R. S. C.Ministry of Aircraft Production, S.W. 1.



</content>
</cab>
