<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/40/37 images: 452-461</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  September 1943.The circulation of this paper^has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of .-^^^MOST SECRET. &apos; CoPy No\ 2 5W.P. (43)&apos; 387.2nd September^ 1943.WAR CABINET.IRELAND.AS arranged at this morning&apos;s Meeting of the War Cabinet, I attach thedraft of a letter from President Roosevelt to Mr. de Valera (prepared, it isunderstood, by Mr. Gray, the United States Minister in Dublin). This draft was handed by the President to the Prime Minister, who has asked that it should beconsidered at once by the War Cabinet.A. E.Foreign Office, 2nd September, 1943. -  *Draft.16th August, 1943.  ,In your Excellency&apos;s speech at Cork on the 14th December, 1941, youexpressed a special sympathy for the people of the United States on the occasion of their entry into the war and made acknowledgment of American assistancein the establishment of the- free Irish nation. In this statement you reaffirmedyour policy of neutrality, with the added qualification that toward the UnitedStates it would be a friendly one. Excerpts of this speech were transmittedthrough your Minister to this Government and were duly acknowledged by thePresident. In his note of appreciation he pointed out the danger threatening allfree nations if they hesitated to unite in common defence of their liberties,trusting to fortune and the efforts of others for escape from the fate of thosesmall States which elected the separatist policy.Since December 1941 the military situation, has changed so fundamentallythat it appears profitable to re-examine our respective policies in the light of our common interests. The obvious approach is now less from the viewpoint of warand more from the viewpoint of the peace that must follow. You have spoken ofthe ties of blood and sympathy that unite our two nations. It should be clear toyou and to the Irish people that these considerations have continuously and notablyshaped the policy of this Government toward Eire in spite of the exactingpressures of the war.In 1940, after the fall of France, when the British Commonwealth of nations was in desperate need of arms of every nature, when the American Governmentwas anxiously preparing for the attack which reasonable foresight warned us would not be long delayed, we allotted, you 20,000 rifles which could ill be spared.Although Eire, with reason, blocks the export of Irish funds to the UnitedStates and requisitions the property in the United States of&apos; NaturalisedAmerican citizens resident in Eire, who under your laws may also be regarded asIrish nationals, we have never interrupted the flow of American remittances toIreland.At a time when every ship was of vital importance we permitted you tocharter two serviceable cargo vessels to assist you in importing your essential supplies. Both these vessels, sailing under neutral markings and-defenceless,have been sunk by the Axis.[26021]
The American Red Cross is now in process of forwarding to you upwards of a half million dollars&apos; worth of medical supplies so that.you may be preparedagainst attack either by the Axis Powers or by epidemic disease.As long as possible we permitted the unregulated purchase and export ofthe things which your national economy required, though you very properly byexecutive order have conserved for your own people the things of which you hadno surplus.Requests for certain amounts of steel, copper and aluminium by the IrishSugar Company for maintaining your nationally-owned plants have beendisallowed by the agencies charged with the allocation of strategic materials forour war effort. We have recently been informed that without these materials the1944 crop of beet cannot be processed, thus leaving the Irish people without sugar.By direction of the President the request will now be approved.It is believed that the Irish people should be informed that this is not anauthorisation for the sale of surplus commodities, but the allocation of strategic materials in short supply for their special benefit. Though the amounts are smallin relation to American production, the steel that will help to produce Irish sugarwould have made either a certain number of tanks, the copper so many shell cases,the aluminium so many airplane parts or would have satisfied civilian needswhich now will not be satisfied. It is as if you sent us foods which you need for your own people.   &apos;In accordance with this policy of special consideration for the Irish people,we have approved the reallocation to Eire by our Allies, the British Common-wealth of Nations, of various materials in short supply originating in the UnitedStates. In reduced, quantity but nevertheless sufficient to maintain your national economy, you have been supplied with American petroleum products allocated to you by Britain. This has enabled you to transport by motor truck practicallythe entire required supply of domestic heating fuel from your peat bogs to yourtowns and cities. In 1942 this amounted to about a half million tons of turf (peat)for the city of Dublin alone, involving a truck mileage of between fifteen andtwenty million miles. It may here be observed that American city dwellers,denied the use of their motor cars for escape to sea. and countryside, do hot enjoy the thought of the representatives of Japan, Germany and Italy driving theirautomobiles about Ireland with American gasoline.Though coal is temporarily in short supply in the United States, we permityour ships to refuelatour ports on equal terms with our combatant Allies. by our contribution of American coal wherever practicable to the common war effort, Britain has been able to supply you with a coal ration, reduced to a thirdof your normal consumption, but still sufficient to operate your railways andpermit a limited public gas service. Since 80 per cent, of the people of Dublincook by gas some four hundred thousand persons have thus been preserved fromserious hardship.Enough steel has been furnished you for horseshoes and agricultural toolsmanufactured in Eire, enough woollen and cotton yarn to keep Irish millsoperating. Irish manufacturers as a rule have profited financially by neutralityduring this period.In spite of great efforts on the part of the Irish farmer, Eire, after the 1942crop, was still in need of a considerable percentage of her wheat requirements.The United Nations without question granted export licenses for the amountsrequired.For the year 1939-40, during which war prevailed for six months, Irishimports appear to have been normal. For the following full year of war theyrose by value, a half million pounds. For the following year they declined about one-third. In the spring of this present year the Irish Minister for Finance,presenting his budget to the Irish Dail, pointed with pride to the fact that sincethe outbreak of the war Eire had imported goods to the value of  17 million inexcess of what she had exported.Irish exports, chiefly live stock, have found, a ready market in Britain.Britain has been fortunate in having them available at her door a,nd Irish farmershave been fortunate in finding the only market open to them glad to receive allofferings. &apos;Thanks to this policy of friendship and supply normal standards of livinghave been less impaired in Eire as the result of war than in any country in Europe.It has not always been easy in view of American opinion to maintain thispolicy. Friendship is not a one-way street and it cannot be denied that americans were mystified and saddened by your Excellency&apos;s public protest against the useof bases in Northern Ireland by American forces, sent there&quot;specifically to forestall
Axis attack. Following this protest came the statement of the Cardinal Primatethat &quot; British and United States troops are overrunning our country against the will of the Nation.&quot; The official censorship approved the publication of this statement together with the publication of resolutions applauding it, adopted bythe Corporation of the City of Cork, though suppressing that portion of a pastoral1of the Bishop of Achonry which condemned the bombing of Irish Nationals bythe Germans.While this Government accepts the suggestion that your Excellency&apos;s protestwas not made in an unfriendly spirit but to assert a claim to sovereignty overNorthern Ireland, it is unfortunate that your Government made no protest against/-&apos;he German bombing of the cities of Northern Ireland, with the attendant murder-of Northeiri Irish people. Moreover, since the Irish Republican Army has issued a manifesto declaring war on the United, States and is now presumably at warwith us in conjunction with their Axis allies, Americans could only feel thatpronouncements exciting antagonism against our troops in Northern Irelandconstituted encouragement to this subversive organisation and endangered the lives of American soldiers.Many Americans understand and sympathize with the reasons whichprompted Irish neutrality; how at the outbreak of the war Eire should wish toexercise her new sovereignty by declining to be involved in a conflict which at thetime may have seemed not to involve her survival as a free nation and later afterthe fall of France when the victory of the Axis appeared inevitable, howprudenceand self-interest dictated ther contihuahce^of that policy.Your friendly promise that your neutrality should be benevolent toward theUnited States was duly appreciated by the American people, but unfortunatelyby reason of your geographical position it has operated in favour of the axis power and against the United Nations. This has become increasingly apparentsince the loss of the French channel ports. Every ship and airplane assigned tothe defence of the Western approaches and the southern supply lines from theAmerican continent would have its operating radius increased by 200 miles werethey based on Southwestern Eire rather than on Northern Ireland. Whether thisunfavourable differential be measured in terms of increased fuel costs, diminishedoperating efficiency or in losses of ships and seamen who might otherwise havebeen saved is a problem for the military statisticians when the data are available.But the handicap is heavy and real and American opinion feels a sense of grievance that you make no contribution to the&quot; safety and maintenance of a supplyline by which in so important measure your national economy is maintained.The presence in Eire of representatives of Germany, Italy and Japan, thepowrers which treacherously attacked us, still further weighs down the balance,of Irish neutrality in favour of our enemies. For on the territory of Eire theyare in a favourable position to spy on us while we are not in a favourable position to spy on them. We recognize the good faith of the Irish Governmentin attempting to prevent and suppress the activities of enemy agents, but it isnaive to believe that they are preventable as long as enemy missions enjoy dipio-matic immunity to come and go, and to negotiate for espionage under the cover of correct social relations. The danger is the greater because of the number ofmisguided but reputable Irish nationals who oppose your Government and look to the Axis Powers as the hope of Irish liberty.It is naive also to&apos; believe that the regime which prepared and precipitatedthe downfall of Austria, Czechoslovakia, Poland, Norway, Belgium, Holland.France, Greece and Yugoslavia by fifth column organisation has not also laid thegroundwork for an inside job on Eire, the key position for a major attack uponBritain. The recrudescence and mysterious financing of the banned IRA. in1938, the capture of parachutists and sea-borne agents in Eire possessing large sums of money, the strange escape from prison and long-time harbouring of aconvicted German spy by respected Irish citizens points to such a conclusion.^ hey raise the question also how many agents are now undetected and at large.vV&quot;e know that you have interned and jailed hundreds of members of fheso subver-sive groups, but their friends and sympathisers are free and constitute a depot of potential enemy agents. Since they work with honest convictions as. well as for pay, they are faithful to their employers and often above suspicion.The operation of these spy agencies is facilitated by the ease with whichthe border between Eire and Northern Ireland may be crossed. It is in fact likecrossing from Connecticut to Massachusetts. North of the border the military installations of the United States are readily studied and estimated. between northern Ireland and Britain there is no political barrier and the agent returningwith reports of United Nations military dispositions has no&apos; difficulty in
re-entering Eire. Once there the coastline with its hundreds of fishing craftplying the costal waters offers exceptional opportunity for rendezvous with enemy submarines. How disastrous has been the information as to United Nationsshipping thus conveyed we do not know, but it is reasonable, knowing theefficiency of the German spy system, to believe that it has been costly to the peopleof the United States.Despite these circumstances which have made Irish neutrality gravelydisadvantageous to the American people, their Government, as you know, hasscrupulously respected it and has never questioned your right as a free nation to maintain it. While the Irish nation was defenceless and while the AmericanGovernment lacked the means to equip your army and assist adequately in thedefence of your cities, they have never felt justified in suggesting the reorientstion of your policy. Now, however, the outcome of the war is no longer in doubt.Our victory is assured though it is not yet won, and it appears to the AmericanGovernment to be a friendly act to offer the Irish people a share in that victoryas we have given them a share of our supply.Since, in view of the military situation, such an offer cannot be construed asa plea for aid or as an effort to purchase co-operation, it does not appear that your past policy should be a bar to the acceptance of it. While it is true thatregardless of your decision we shall win the war, it is also true that Eire canplay a notable and honourable part in contributing to the shortening of itsduration by leasing us bases for the protection of the Atlantic supply lines andby the elimination of Axis spy centres on Eire territory.Your Excellency&apos;s statement, made on leaving the United States in 1923,tc the effect that if America ever needed Irish help it would not be lacking,makes it clear that your personal inclination must now be to join us andhasten the retribution due the totalitarian Powers which have plotted againstyou as against&apos; us and have murdered your people and destroyed your property.It was recently stated in your Dail that the Irish taxpayers had been mulcted amillion dollars to pay for damages resulting from the German bombing of yourlighted cities and the killing of seventy-eight Irish citizens. It has been announced that the Axis, by submarine and air attack, had sunk a dozen of yoursmall fleet of ships. For these acts of war you now have the opportunity toexact satisfaction.But in the American view, even more important than retribution is yourplace beside us in the post-war future. The American people want your closefriendship and the binding tie of common effort in the crushing of totalitarianlawlessness, and the re-establishment of international law. The american people wish to be able to share their supplies with you in the difficult years ahead when the needs of Allies and enslaved peoples must be the first charge upon our resources. We believe that your interests, both spiritual and material, are bound, up with ours and that if you fail to recognize the fact our traditionalfriendship must inevitably be weakened. We believe that we have done our part to;maintain this friendship.  It is for you to do yours.The American Government trusts that your Excellency will favour them witha reply at your early convenience and will understand that the AmericarjGovernment&apos;s obligation to the American people will require the publication ofthis note and your reply thereto.







</content>
</cab>
