<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/2/0 images: 246-248</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Bxitesk BSa^y&apos;s (kresm&amp;eat j * -Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   November 1916.SECRET. G.-91.EOOD PROSPECTS IX 1917.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries.THE outlook grows more difficult. Our own requirements are larger; the Allies can export nothing to us ; and, while France and Italy look to us for assisting their importation, we have to meet an increasing demand for larger exports of coal and munitions of war. Tonnage and its security present the most serious and alarming problem. Our heavy losses are not being made good, and 33 per cent, of our requirements arrive in neutral bottoms. The German policy is to sink or intimidate neutral ships; ocean liners, upon which we depend largely for wheat, will not escape much longer, and meanwhile the demand for military transport shows no signs of decrease.Bread-stuffs.This year&apos;s yield of home-grown wheat will probably be about 7,500,000 quarters, and,we shall require to import about 28,000,000 quarters. Excluding our oversea army, our average consumption is 650,000 quarters a week. Our stocks of wheat and flour to-day, which now stand at their maximum, including the home crop just harvested, amount to four months&apos; consumption. The crops of North America have failed; the Argentine prospects are still doubtful; but there has been a serious drought and the locust has travelled farther south than for many years past. The Indian outlook is somewhat better. The Australian crop had a large carry-over, of which the Government have already purchased 500,000 tons. The surplus of the new crop can be shipped from January onwards, and will require about 100 ships a month for six months to come. Russian supplies are unavailable, and those of Roumania threatened.   In short, there is a world&apos;s deficit.These circumstances made the corn trade very nervous and reluctant to carry heavy stocks. A Royal Commission was accordingly set up, which I think has had some steadying effect upon public opinion by eliminating the chances of &quot;profiteering.&quot; Bread is very expensive, 10d., and may well go higher; but considering the high scale of wages, the absence of pauperism, and the number of persons now earning money who earned little or nothing before the war, lOd. is in some ways equivalent to 8^d. in time of peace.   In August 1914 the quartern loaf cost Qd.To reduce the price of bread by Id: per loaf below its commercial figure would cost from 15,000,0001. to 20,000,0001. a year. In France a * wheat subvention is paid by the State, amounting roughly to 25s. a quarter. The result was that last year wheat became cheaper than oats, and was accordingly fed to cattle.Economy in wheat is imperative, and its importation must be stimulated in no niggardly degree. It has been decided that the consumption of wheat must be reduced (as our Allies have already done) by extracting a larger proportion of the flour, and also by allowing the admixture within defined limits of substances such as maize.Potatoes.Here, as in Germany and France, the potato crop has failed. Our home crop is seriously diminished, particularly in Ireland. As compared with 1915, present forecasts indicate a shortage of some 1,800,000 tons, or 24 per cent. The crop is diseased as well as small. Prices, which were 4L per ton in 1913, are now 101. per ton, and will rise still further. A shortage of seed potatoes is probable. It may be advisable to take steps for special planting in Malta, Spain, the Channel Islands, and the Canaries. Home production of early potatoes can also be encouraged. [1223]
As regards home supplies, it must be remembered that commandeering at low-prices will seriously diminish next years crop.Fish.Prices have risen from 100 to 400 per cent., which is serious, as the fried fish shops supply cheap and wholesome food. In Bradford, for instance, these shops supply every week two meals per head of the whole population of the town. Prom now until June our total supply of fish is expected to be some 64 per cent, below normal; 80 per cent, of the first class steam fishing-vessels have been taken by the Admiralty, and new trawlers are requisitioned as they leave the slips.Live-stock.The.statistics published by my Department on the 5th June show the highest recorded numbers of, live-stock. The. last five months have doubtless reduced this great population, as foodstuffs are costly and labour scarce, causing much anxiety among stock-owners, who are uncertain&apos;about maintaining their dairy herds, especially owing to the fear of milk prices: being curtailed. Many herds have already been dispersed,, but the bulk of the milking cows have probably found their way into the hands of smaller farmers, only a small proportion having gone to the butcher. After two years of war we are justified in encroaching upon our reserve capital. Germany, it would seem, has already lost a million head of stock.The feeding-stuff difficulty is considerable. Tjbis year&apos;s hay crop has been good, but roots are only.moderate. In time of war there is always a competition between live-stock and citizens for feeding-stuffs, especially cereals and their by-products, and if it comes to a critical stage the live-stock must be sacrificed. This affords the momentary compensation of cheaper meat, as well as releasing food for the people, followed by ultimate loss, which will injure husbandry for many years.Prospects of 1917.Difficulties of cultivation steadily increase. The War Office is arranging for younger farm, labourers to be replaced by elder men now serving in the Reserve and Home Defence. , Great efforts are also being made to secure further dilution of agricultural labour and the employment of women ; but unless the labour scale can be maintained at approximately its present level in many counties it has already been largely reduced land will go derelict, yield will decline, and live stock must he greatly diminished. It is essential that the maximum number of ploughmen should be retained over the new year, to ensure the. cropping of spring cereals, potatoes, and roots, otherwise next,harvest will be a disaster.It may prove desirable to establish some central food department to supervise and co-ordinate the varied relations of the State with the import, purchase, and distribution of food. The War Office and Admiralty are large buyers. Fish and dairy produce are . extensively purchased in Holland and Norway through the Restriction of Enemy Supplies,; Department. The Board of Trade is engaged with the importation of meat. The import of brewing materials is restricted. Sugar and wheat are controlled by Royal Commissions. Potatoes may demand similar treatment. The whole field and the general prospects might be suitably submitted to the continuing and comprehensive survey of a central body.Not before August 1917; will war policy be free to dissociate itself from the influence of home food supply.C. &amp; B.October 30, 1916.
135Wheat Imports.The probable requirements of the importing countries and the estimated available supplies from exporting countries during the twelve months ending the 1st September, 1917, are provisionally stated as follows : Estimated requirements  Qrs.United Kingdom...         ..         .. ..         ..         ..      28,000,000France........ 14,000,000Italy   ..         ..                     .. ..         ..                  10,000,000Other countries   ..         ..         .. ..         ..         ..      20,000,00072,000,000Estimated available supplies  Qrs.United States     .. .. .. ..      21,000,000Canada..                     .. .. .. ..         ..      13,000,000Argentina         ..          .. .. .. ..                   10,000,000India   ..&apos;                  .. .. .. ..        ..       6,000,000Australia          .. .. 10,000,000Other countries ..         .. .. .. ..       3,000,00063,000,000Though the supply from Australia given above represents the quantity which may he expected under existing conditions, it is probable that a further 7,000,000 qrs. might he available from the old and new crops, if arrangements could be made for bringing it to market in time to be of service.Tonnage.The freight space which is estimated to be required to carry the necessary imports of grain and feeding-stuffs in the eight months November-June is as follows: *	Estimated Requirements for Eight Months.	Equivalent Weight in Tons of 2,240 lb.	Shipping Tons of 40 cubic . feet.Wheat      ... Barley            ..                       .. Maize           ..	Qrs. 16,700,000 2,000,000 3,170,000 8,400,000	3,580,000 357,000 442,000 1,800,000	3,580,000 518,000 773,000 2,250,000Other grain, ricemeal, &amp;c,        ,. Oil seeds Oil-cake	Tons. 200,000 970,000 200,000	200,000 970,000 200,000	300,000 , 1,285,000 275,000Total         ..		7,549,000	8,981,000PBKTED AT THE EOBEIGN OPWCE BY C. K. HARRISON 7/11/1916.

</content>
</cab>
