<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/2/0 images: 263-264</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.G.-96. 4CAVALRY IN FRANCE.Note by Lord Curzon, forwarding a Report op the Shipping ControlCommittee on 1. Transporting Horses from Abroad direct to France.2. BrifUj^baM part of the Cavalry from France to England forI CIRCULATE the report of the Shipping Control Committee on the two questions remitted to it by the War Committee on the 9th November (Paper W. 0.-84, Conclusion 7 (2)), viz., the idea of shipping horses direct from America to France, and the idea of bringing back part of the cavalry from France to England for the winter.I regret that, a Cabinet having been fixed for the same hour as the meeting of the Committee, I could not attend the latter. Not having heard the arguments, I cannot dispute the conclusion. But, before accepting it, I should like to have submitted the officers who attended from the War Office to a very close cross-examination on certain aspects of the case.There remains the question of the Indian cavalry, which I understand the War Committee are to discuss with Sir Douglas Haig. If the Commander-in-chief were able to dispense with the Indian cavalry altogether as to which I give no opinion, since it is a question that concerns the India Office, as well as the military authorities-it is calculated that the saving in shipping would be approximately as follows: Animals. Saving in conveyance of horses by cutting out the supply of animals from America would be eight ships of 4,000 tons gross for two months each.Fodder.-Saving in feeding 6,600 horses in France would be about eight ships a year.C. of K.November 14, 1916.On the 13th November, acting upon instructions received from the War Committee, the following points were investigated by the Shipping Control Committee in consultation with the War Office: 1. Transporting Horses from Abroad direct to France,Sir W. Birkbeck (Director of Remounts) explained the present system to remount depots in England, at Liverpool and Avonmouth, where the horses remain under observation, and from which they go to reserve units for training before proceeding overseas.By landing horses in England and putting them through this preparation all the unsuitable, unfit, and infectious cases are weeded out. If horses went direct to France,, the net result would be an increase permanently of 23,000 horses in the remount depots in France.Direct shipment to France would mean very large and expensive additional arrangements, while from the veterinary point of view there would be a certainty of importing infection into the army zone. [1277]Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   November 1916.
After hearing Sir W. Birkbeck&apos;s evidence, the Committee decided that they could not recommend the direct shipment of horses from abroad to France. The representa-tive of the Admiralty who was present also concurred in the view.2. Bringing back part of the Cavalry from France to England for the Winter.i     There would be no difficulty in finding ships to convey the horses ; they could be brought in the Channel horse-ships that&apos; always return empty. I       The difficulty exists rather in finding quarters in.this country.   All the cavalry barracks in England are full, but, subject to Lord French&apos;s decision, accommodation could probably be found in Cornwall, Devon, and Somerset for 12 or 13 out of the52 cavalry regiments now in France.__The reason for putting the cavalry in the westcountry is on account of the hay and fodder question. In Kent, for instance, there are no forage arrangements.General Sir C. Heath said the scheme was practical. General Stuart-Wortley said that from his point of view it was desirable. General Birkbeck said that of course the military side of the question had not been considered, and must remain a matter for Sir Douglas Haig. -From the tonnage point of view, at first sight, there does not seem much saving. The economy in fodder-ships would only amount to three large ships.The figures will be re-examined, but it is doubtful whether the saving of three steamers is.sufficient to warrant the dislocation in training and general disorganization.Indian Co.valry.The question of removing the Indian cavalry from France was also discussed. The present strength of this cavalry in France amounts to 11 regiments of 600 each, say, 6,600 horses. If the cavalry were removed to India their horses could be left in Egypt on the way East, and so make good the shortage of horses there.It is understood, however, that Sir Douglas Haig holds strong views in favour of retaining the Indian cavalry in France; the matter therefore appears to be one for the War Committee&apos;8 meeting with Sir Douglas Haig on the subject of horses referred to in the War Committee&apos;s Conclusions of the 9th November.PRINTED AT THE FOREIGN OFFICE BY C. R. HARRISON.-17/11/1916

</content>
</cab>
