<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/72/0 images: 25-32</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret(54) 357 COPY HO.23rd November, 1954CABINETEAST/WE ST TRAPS:COPPER WIRE AND CABLEMemorandum by the Minister of DefenceBast August, copper wire and cable were removed from the embargo list.2.        Since then, Russia and her satellites have ordered 20, 000 tons from Paris Group countries, including 95000 tons from this country.    Theyare negotiating orders in this country for a further 24,000 tons, all for the heaviest calibre wire.3. This seems to confirm that Russia is so short of copper that sheis prepared to use this expensive method of building up a stockpile.4.        This has alarmed the Americans and some other Paris Groupcountries and we are being pressed to restore the embargo.5.        The attached report by officials - Annex - sets out the strategic a-nd political considerations and possible courses of action.6,        Though I am new to this subject, I am not convinced that controlof trade with the Soviet bloc serves any very useful practical purpose, or that in a future war the possession of stocks of way materials for defence production will make a great deal of difference to the outcome.     There isno reason to believe that any system of controls can prevent Russia frombuilding up sufficient stocks of complete equipment to see her through the initial phase.    On practical grounds, therefore, I do not feel that the case for restoring the embargo is a strong one.7.        Politically, an extension of the embargo list would be mostunpopular in this country,.    On the other hand, a refusal to extend it wouldbe most unpopular in the United States.    We are already having trouble with the Americans over control of shipping.    So far, we have refusedto impose transaction controls until this shipping problem is settled,and Italy has hitherto refused to impose transhipment controls unless they are also applied to our Mediterranean colonies.    I understandthat this creates delicate problems, particularly in Malta, where weare already in trouble with the local Government over the grant of privileges to the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation command which wehave set up there.    We are about to begin talks with the Americans onthe restrictions on trade with China, and these may prove difficult.
8. If a compromise is thought necessary, I suggest we should gofor &quot;quantitative&quot; control, if it can be made effective0 It all turns onChile, who is not in the Paris Group,9. If this is agreed, I suggest the global figure should not be lessthan 10,000 tons.H.M.Ministry of Defence, S. W.I.22nd November, 19540
^7ANNEXEAST/WEST TRADE:   CONTROL OVER COPPERNote by OfficialsExports of copper to the Soviet bloc from the United kingdom have been prohibited since 1949, as part of the system of security controlsintroduced at that time.    A similar embargo has been applied by all theother countries of the Paris Consultative Group on security controls -United States, Canada, Japan and most Western European countries.2. When the security controls policy was reviewed early this year,the Cabinet decided that a shorter embargo list, more rigidly enforced,would probably be equally effective from the security point of view, andcopper was one of the items which they considered should be removed fromthe embargo list, though they recognised that the Americans, at least,were likely to press for its retention.3. This proved to be the case, and in the course of the international discussions on the United Kingdom proposed &quot;short list&quot; Ministers finallyauthorised the United Kingdom representatives to accept the continuanceof embargo over all forms of copper except uncovered cable and wire;and it was agreed that exports of cable and wire by the Paris Group countries should be reported and watched but not restricted.4. The exclusion of copper wire and cable was justified on theground that these items are not normally put to strategic uses, and that itwas thought unlikely that the Soviet bloc would buy large quantities of copper in the form of cable or wire.    This expectation has been falsified.Since August, when wire and cable were freed from embargo, the bloc hasordered some 20,000 tons from countries of the Paris Group, including9,000 tons from the United Kingdom.5. This development has caused serious concern to the U.S.A.and some of the other members of the Paris Group, all of whom (with theI ****** jv**ju,**^)0ssible exception of Belgium)/are now-prepared to cog the .ombargo on1* 4uytjse, tS uncovered wire and cable restored.    If the Soviet bloc demands for wirercM^4*c*j continue on a substantial scale - and they are already negotiating for a/4**4^fc*4UMt ^&quot;further 24,000 tons from the United Kingdom - there is a danger that their imports in the form of wire and cable will tend to stultify the embargo wehave agreed to maintain on copper itself.    This is particularly the casesince a large proportion of the sales already made, and the whole of the24,000 tons referred to above, relate to wire of the largest gauge, whichsuggests that the bloc may possibly be buying it for general use as copper,rather than as wire.6. It is urgently necessary to determine the United Kingdomattitude to the Paris proposal for the restoration of the embargo, as theinternational discussions on the proposal are already taking place.Unfortunately the matter cannot be dealt with in isolation solely on itsintrinsic merits, since there are also important political and other generalimplications..    The relevant points for consideration are set out below.
Strategic considerations7a The general case for and against the embargo on copper was setout in Appendix II to C. (54) 46 - (copy attached) which was considered inFebruary.    From the strategic point of view copper is one of the comparatively few commodities on which denial to the Soviet bloc,   coulddemonstrably limit their war preparations.     It is a substance of prime importance in war-time and the indigenous production of the bloc is insufficient to meet even their current needs, let alone to build up thenecessary stockpile for war.     On the basis of recent and prospectiveorders it is thought that sales of wire and cable from the Paris Groupcountries might well total some 60,000 tons in 1955, or about 14 per cent ofthe Soviet b3.oc&apos;s  own production of virgin copper, which would representa substantial contribution towards meeting their deficiency,8. On the other hand, it is unlikely that the wire and cable, ifused as such, would be devoted to military purposes, or that the extracopper would affect the extent to which the bloc uses copper in currentmilitary production.9. Since the imposition of the embargo the Soviet bloc has beenimporting copper, by devious means at the rate of approximately 150,000tons a year.    We should hope, however, that most of this would be cut off by the introduction of transaction controls in the United Kingdom and trans -shipment controls on the Continent - new enforcement measures to beintroduced as part of the &quot;short list&quot; scheme.Political considerations (United Kingdom)10. The new strategic control lists contain items which we ourselveswould not have included on their strategic merits.    They can only be defended as a compromise, and the decontrol of copper wire and cable was an essential part of that compromise.    If we give way on such an importantitem as this we shall in future be unable to defend the lists as a wholebecause the balance of compromise will have been upset.11, The object of the review of the lists was to expand trade so faras consistent with security.    We should be open to the most hostilecriticism from political and commercial circles if we re-introduce controls over the first item in which we achieve our objective of expanding trade and prevent our manufacturers accepting probable orders for 1955, totalling about  7 millions.    The freeing of copper wire has been widely publicised;it would not be easy to convince the critics that it is a commodity of sufficient strategic importance in itself to warrant the re-introduction of control so recently removed.12. The re-introduction of restrictions on a major item like copperwire would create uncertainty in the minds of the Russians and of traderswhich might seriously prejudice our prospects of expanding trade witiiEastern Europe.    If we give way on this item it will be feared that we may give way on any other items for which the Russians are prepared to placelarge orders.Political considerations (International)13. The United States Administration accepted the reductions of the embargo list proposed by the United Kingdom on the understanding that the controls would be effectively maintained and more rigidly enforced.    UnitedStates officials have already indicated that the Administration are disturbedthat they have failed, so far, to secure this quid pro quo.   In so far as the
difficulties can be traced, rightly or wrongly, to the United Kingdom there isa risk of ill-feeling between the Americans and ourselves.    This could doconsiderable harm, particularly in relation to Her Majesty&apos;s government&apos;s policy of securing United States agreement to relaxations in controls on trade with China.14. The main problems still unresolved are shipping and enforcement measures.    For shipping, Her Majesty&apos;s Government have found difficulty in accepting proposals which have been agreed to by all theother members of the Paris Group.    The proposed enforcement measuresconsist of the trans-shipment licensing scheme and the introduction by theUnited Kingdom of transaction controls.    The trans-shipment licensingscheme has been delayed because the Italians have been insisting that itshould be applied in our Mediterranean dependent territories, about whichthere has been difficulty.    Meanwhile the introduction of transactioncontrols has also been delayed.15. Any appearance of subordinating strategic to commercial considerations in appraising the copper wire problem would certainly, in this context, be taken badly by the Americans.16. This is not only a question of our relations with the Americans.&quot;We must think also of our position in the Paris Group.     The danger ofoverstraining the goodwill which holds the Group together must be balancedagainst our commercial interests in any particular item.     If we go too farin pursuing a line of our own in the Group we shall fail to retain the co-operation of other countries in carrying out the control scheme as a whole,to the detriment of security, or of our own trade if we continue the controlsunilaterally.Alternative courses open to the United Kingdom17. There are three possible courses open to us in the Parisdiscussions on copper wire and cable, viz.(a) accept the proposal for the restoration ofthe embargo;(b) suggest instead that exports of copper wireand cable be permitted within specified limits;(c) press for the continuance of complete freedom to export.18. The restoration of the embargo could be justified on purelystrategic grounds (by treating it as part of the embargo on copper itself)and would satisfy the Americans and the other Paris countries, but it wouldgive rise to the difficulties referred to in paragraphs 1 0 to 12.19. The adoption of quantitative control (restriction on future exports)would also satisfy the strategic requirements, and it might possibly be acceptable to the Americans and in Paris, provided the upper limit for exports was sufficiently low.    From the strategic point of view an appropriateannual global limit of exports for all Paris countries would be about 4,000 tons;anything above about 10,000 tons would be difficult to justify strategically0Under this arrangement we could not hope to secure a quota for the UnitedKingdom big enough to avoid the criticism referred to in paragraph 11.    Itmight, however, make it rather easier to meet it.
20. The third course is the only one likely to be fully satisfactorypolitically in the United Kingdom.     But it will be realised that it is a somewhat weak case strategically, would be bitterly opposed by the Americans,and would place us in a most difficult position in the Paris Group.22ND NOVEMBER, 1954.
Production Consumption(thousands of tons) Country (thousands of tons)985	U.S.A.	1 ,291377	Chile	26292	Northern Rhodesia	nil202	Belgian Congo	nil200	Canada	117192	Germany	215106	Rest of Europe	35193	Japan	92163	Rest of World	1U6nil	U.K.	3U82,610 2,586Supply position in the Soviet bloc2.     Soviet bloc production has been rising steadily and in1952 reached an estimated total of U.11 ,000 tons.    Plannedproduction for 1955 is 63/1,000 tons but the bloc has recentlybeen unable to fulfil the planned rate of increase and it islikely that production in 1955 will fall far short of thesefigures 43.      Soviet bloc imports are estimated to total at least100,000stons a year.   Little of this is imported direct fromproducing countries, most of it being shipped through deviouschannels and at premium prices,,U*      The total quantity of copper available to the bloc in1952, can, therefore, be estimated at about 500,000 tons.Consumption in the Soviet bloc5,     There  is abundant evidence that the Soviet bloc countries are very short of copper (for example, not only are they willingto pay high prices for imports but they are taking various measures to develop substitutes, especially in the electricalindustry).    They would no doubt use more copper if they could get it but it is not possible to estimate the maximum amount.6,      There is no infermation about the way in which copper isassigned to various uses in.the bloc but the electrical industryis no doubt the greatest user.    Some indication of the quantityrequired for peacetime defence uses may be derived from the35   Now estimated at 160,000 tons- 1  -REPORT BY THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL, SECURITYEXPORT CONTROLS WORKING PARTYWorld -production and consumptionThe following table snows world smelter production and consumption of virgin copper in 1952 (the Soviet bloc beingexcluded):-
experience of the U.K.;    out of 550,000 tons consumed in theU.K.  in 1 952 (a peak: year in the defence production programme)some -100,000 to 150,000 tons were estimated to he required forthe defence industries.7.     Mo estimate can be given of the amount of copper the blocwould need in war hut here again some indication can be derivedfrom our own experience.    In the peak war year of 19^-2, UnitedKingdom consumption was 820,000 tons as against some 350?000tons in 1938.Case for an against an Embargo on Copper8.     The defence view is that copper merits embargo because ofits importance in the electrical industry and its extensive usein war in the production of military equipment and munitions.The development of the Soviet electrical industry is known to bebehind schedule, partly because of shortage of copper.    Thepower generating system would be a weak link: in the  chain of soviet industrial production in war.9.      In wartime,  the consumption of copper increases enormouslyand by far the greater part of it is used for direct military purposes;    in the last war our consumption of copper doubled and half of it was spent in ammunition.10.    The bloc is very snort of copper and appears to be dependant upon imports for about 20 per cent, of its supplies.If tnere are no restrictions on its imports, the bloc will be free to develop its war potential not only by assigning more copperto industry but also by building up the very large reserve itwould need in war, when all imports would probably be stopped.11.   Against this it is argued that the peacetime uses of copper are so multifarious that it can only be regarded as abasic industrial product and that, even though it plays a vitalpart in wartime production, this is equally true of other products of general utility wnich we should not think ofembargoing.    Further, it would be inconsistent with the principle on which the present embargo list is based to include copperin order to hamper the Soviet bloc electrical industry, which isno more than a sector of the bloc&apos;s general economy.    Even thoughcopper production in the bloc is behind schedule  supplies are adequate to meet the current needs of defence production.12.    Copper is now becoming much more plentiful outside the bloc and it will become increasingly difficult to make our controlseffective, even if they are re-inforccd by the general impositionof transaction and transhipment controls.    These additionalcontrols would of course interfere with the free operation ofthe London Metal Market.13*    The removal of the embargo on copper in its primary formswould enable the sterling area to obtain a substantial increasein exports to the bloc    But the present embargo also coverssemi-fabricated forms, such as wire and strip, which are widelyused in the electrical and other industries.    Freedom to sellsemi-fabricated copper products would probably result in alarge increase in U.K.  exports of manufactured goods for these industries.

</content>
</cab>
