<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/32 images: 198-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

SECRET COPY NO. 53

W.P.(G)(40) 232

3rd September, 1940.

WAR CABINET.

EMPLOYMENT OF TROOPS ON HARVEST WORK.

Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War.

1. During the harvest season, 1939, soldiers were allowed to volunteer for giving agricultural assistance and volunteers received their military pay plus 1/- a day (of which the farmer paid 6d and Army Funds 6d), in addition to pay, at the recognized civil rates, for overtime when worked.

2. The Ministry of Agriculture are again this season urging that soldiers should be allowed to volunteer for harvest work and, since the financial inducement offered last year appears to have been insufficient to attract enough volunteers, the Ministry have suggested that during this season the farmers should he allowed to offer volunteers the usual civilian rates of pay and that the War Office should either withhold Army pay or pay it in addition to civil pay, unless men voluntarily give it up.

3. This year, however, owing to the imminent possibility of active operations in this country,  I cannot see my way to agree that soldiers should be allowed to volunteer at will for harvesting, since freedom to do so would inevitably conflict with the performance of military duties and might, in the event of invasion, lead to very serious difficulties.

On the other hand, where military exigencies permit and it is in the interest of the State that help should be given, it seems right that the soldier should be called upon to do harvest work as a duty. I suggest, therefore, that power should be taken by means of a Defence Regulation under the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, 1940, to require any soldier so detailed by his Commanding Officer to perform agricultural work (as may be ordered) as a work of national importance necessary for maintaining supplies, etc., essential to the life of the community. Soldiers detailed for this work would receive their Army pay without additions.
The farmers employing the men will be required to paythe civil wage rates applicable to this type of labour, such payments being credited to Army 3?unds as a set-off against thecost to the State of pay and allowances of the soldiers so employJ*Such a regulation would enable the military authorities Lboth to provide men at short notice for- essential work on the loudwhenever the military situation allowed without  he dislocation thaimight be oaused by any voluntary system. ;4*&apos;       ihe&apos;Hoae Policy Committee had a draft Defenoe Regulationbefore them at&apos;their meeting on 3rd September (H.P.G. (4-0) 276) n^mapproved the Regulation subject to the War Cabinefs approval- of &apos;tHfpunderlying policy.The War Office,3rd September, 1940.(K.2218).   .

</content>
</cab>
