<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/52/41 images: 560-565</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 391:lUh July, 1944.WAR CABINET.REPORT   OF   THE   SPEAKERS   CONFERENCE   ON   electoral reform AND REDISTRIBUTION OF SEATS.Joint Memorandum by the Home Secretary and Secretary of State forScotland.1. The Report presented by the Speaker in his letter of the 24th May to thePrime Minister deals with : (1) Redistribution of Seats;(2) Reform of the franchise for Parliamentary and local government; and(3) Methods of Election.A further report is to be made by the Conference &quot;on the conduct and costs ofParliamentary elections and related subjects.&quot; As regards Method of Election,the Conference rejected Proportional Representation and the Alternative Vote,and make no proposals for any change in the existing system.Redistribution of Seats.2. The Departmental Committee on Electoral Machinery recommended thatpermanent machinery should be established to effect any necessary measures of redistribution periodically. The Speaker&apos;s Conference accept generally theproposals of the Departmental Committee for standing machinery, but, whereas the Departmental Committee recommended three Boundary Commissions, one for england and Wales, one for Scotland, and one for Northern Ireland, the Speaker&apos;conference recommend that there should be a fourth separate boundary commission for Wales and Monmouth.3. The Departmental Committee recommended &quot; a review of the state of constituencies, coupled with redistribution proposals where necessary . . . .during the normal life of every Parliament,&quot; the idea being that there shouldbe a review before every General Election, and that &quot; in normal circumstances thestatutory-life of Parliament determines that a General Election will take place at not more than quinquennial intervals.&quot; The Speaker&apos;s Conference recom-mends that greater latitude should be left to the Boundary Commissions, and thatthe Boundary Commissions should be required to undertake a general review &quot;, at intervals of not less than three years, and not more than seven years,&quot; and should in addition have authority to submit special reports at any time recommendingchanges in respect of any particular constituency or group of constituencies.4. The Speaker&apos;s Conference have recognised the difficulty of undertaking a general redistribution at an early date, when, owing to the shifting of thepopulation due to war circumstances, some constituencies have lost a largeproportion of their normal residents and other constituencies are abnormallyswollen. The Conference accordingly proposes that there shall be, in the firstinstance, a partial redistribution of &quot; abnormally large &quot; constituencies only. Anabnormally large &apos;&apos; constituency is one in which the electorate &apos;&apos; under the1939 Register was not less than approximately 190 per cent, of the quota.&quot;This scheme will involve a temporary increase in the membership of the Houseof Commons, and the Conference recommends that the temporary total increaseshall not exceed twenty-five Members.[27827]
5. As regards a general scheme of redistribution, the report says : &quot; TheConference are in favour of a general redistribution of seats as soon aspracticable.-&apos; and &quot; the Boundary Commissions shall begin to prepare a fullredistribution scheme immediately after the completion of the temporary schemeof sub-division of abnormally large constituencies.&quot;G. The Conference recommend that for the purpose of this first generalscheme of redistribution and for the purpose of subsequent schemes of redistribution-tion, the Boundary Commissions should be subject to a number of rules, includingthe following : -That the total number of Members of the House of Commons shall remainsubstantially as at present.That there shall be no reduction in the present number of Members forScotland or for Wales and Monmouthshire.*That constituencies at present returning two Members shall be abolished,except where after local enquiry by the Boundary Commissions it is foundin any particular case that abolition is undesirable.That the City of London shall continue as at present to return two members, tReform of the Franchise.7. The Conference recommend the assimilation of the Parliamentary andlocal government franchise, the limitation of the business premises&apos; qualificationby excluding the spouse, and the free and automatic registration of the universityelector.8. Legislation will be necessary to carry out the recommendations of theConference, and, in connection with such legislation various questions will arisefor decision. The immediate question, however, is what is to be the legislative programme for giving effect to the recommendations of the Conference? Shallthere be an omnibus Bill dealing with all the matters on which legislation will berequired as the result of the recommendations of the Conference, or shall there be, at an early date, a Bill dealing only with the Eedistribution of Seats 1 our provisional view is that the best plan is (1) to introduce as early as practicablea Bill dealing with redistribution only; and (2) to leave for later legislation theremaining recommendations of the Conference, including such recommendations as they make in their second report. The Redistribution Bill should not,we think, arouse serious controversy if the recommendations of the Speaker&apos;conference including the recommendation that there should be a separateBoundary Commission for Wales are accepted. The remaining recommenda-tions, besides being possibly controversial in themselves, are bound up with the resumption of local elections. They will therefore have to be dealt with beforethe end of the present year when the temporary legislation suspending suchelections comes to an end. If it is decided to assimilate the two franchises therewill be strong pressure to resume local elections in 1945; and if this is conceded,various consequential problems will have to be dealt with in the Bill. these considerations strengthen our view that Parliamentary redistribution should bedealt with separately.If our colleagues approve of this proposal we will arrange for the drafting of the Redistribution Bill, which is already in train, to be proceeded with as quickly as possible with a view to its introduction before the summer recess sothat the second reading could be taken immediately after the recess.9. We would propose to include in this Bill provisions to give effect to theNovel recommendation of the Conference that there shall be a separate Boundary* The Home Secretary thinks that he should draw attention to the fact that this recom-mendation is a guarantee of not less than the present number of seats for Scotland and Waleswith no guarantee that there will not be less seats for England or that the proportion of seatsfor England on a population basis will not be reduced. It is true that the number of Englishseats will be temporarily increased in practice, but the principle remains.f We think that we should warn the Cabinet that opposition to this proposal may beexpected, certainly from the Labour Party, and possibly from Liberals and others. The votingat the Conference was 15-13.We sympathise with that opposition. Mathematically, the City would not be entitled to separate representation at all, and we would have thought that the claims of the City on theground of its history and traditions would have been sufficiently met by one Member. Actuallythe proposals involving a smaller &quot; business &quot; electorate will materially diminish the numberof City voters.
Commission for Wales and Monmouthshire, and to the recommendationsmentioned in paragraph 6 above.We would also propose that the Bill should include provisions for a partialmeasure of redistribution applying to &quot; abnormally large &quot; constituencies &quot; forthe purpose of an election held before general redistribution has taken effect.&quot;In connection, however, with the proposals of the Conference for a definition of &quot; abnormally large &quot; constituencies a question arises on which a note is appended; and we ask for the approval of the Cabinet to our proposal that theBill should depart in this matter from the recommendations of the Conference.10. If the Cabinet approve our proposals we ask for authority to proceedwith the preparation of the Bill for submission to Parliament, subject, of course,to examination by the Legislation Committee in the usual way.H. M.T. J.Uth July, 1944.APPENDIX.THE proposal of the Speakers Conference is that &quot; an electorate which under the 1939 register was not less than approximately 190 per cent, of the quota (53,110) for Great Britain .... shall be deemed to have been abnormallylarge.&quot; There are, in fact, nineteen constituencies having an electorate larger than 100,909 (which is the figure arrived at by applying the Conference^ formula)and one (Horsham) with an electorate of 100,834. All these constituencies arein England. If they are divided in accordance with the formula recommendedby the Conference they will yield the 25 additional seats which the Conferenceproposes, see table below.There are six other constituencies having an electorate of over 95.000. Ofthese, one is in Scotland (East Renfrew, with an electorate of 98,083); the otherfive are in England (Lewisham East 96,321, Nottingham Rushcliffe 95,132,Chester Wirral 97,603, Derby Southern 95,896, Spelthorne 95,675). Whetherthe word &quot;approximately&quot; would on a legal interpretation cover electorateswhich are 2 per cent, or more below the standard is by no means clear, but itappears that by the use of this word the Conference intended to throw on the boundary Commissions the responsibility of deciding whether any of these sixconstituencies should be included and one or more ox the twenty larger con-stituencies excluded. No indication is given as to the grounds on which the boundary Commissions could properly decide that one of the constituencies withan electorate of over 100,000 should be displaced in favour of a constituency withan electorate of under 100,000.The questions therefore arise .Is it right to use in the Bill the word &apos;&apos; approximately &apos;&apos; or some equivalentword, and to leave to the Boundary Commissions the responsibility of deciding whether they are or are not charged with the duty of considering these sixconstituencies ?Ought the Boundary Commissions to be saddled with the responsibility ofdiscovering for themselves what grounds, if any, there may be for preferringone or more of the six smaller constituencies to one or more of the twenty largerconstituencies ?If the members of the English Commission take one view and the membersof the Scottish Commission another, is it to be assumed that the Speaker willsomehow secure agreement?The task of the Boundary Commissions would be much simplified (and so,incidentally, would the drafting of the Bill) if it were decided that the constituencies to be divided are those with electorates of over 100,000 and toschedule the twenty constituencies in the Bill. We propose that in this respect the Bill should depart from the recommendations of the Conference.
Table.(a) Under the formula proposed by the Speaker&apos;s Conference, the followin17 constituencies would qualify for an additional member : 1939 Electorate.108,059106,892123,439102,197119,290Constituency.Birmingham : Mosele)BlackpoolIlford   ......Bucks : WycombeChester : AltrinchamEssex Epping    ...South-EastHertford : St. AlbansKent ChislehurstDartford ...Middlesex TwickenhamUxbridge ...Surrey EpsomMitcham  ...West Sussex :- Warwick NuneatonTamworth(b) The following constituency would qualify for two additional members : Middlesex : Harrow ...(c) The following two constituencies would qualify forthree additional members : Essex : RomfordMiddlesex: Hendon ...Horsham and Worthing107,162108,383102,990114,992134,935108,216140,299132,818103,162100,834112,503118,131168,594207,101208.609The additional members of the House of Commons would therefore be-(a)(&amp;)1726Total25



</content>
</cab>
