<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/42 images: 474-487</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
miTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1939.SECRET.W.M. (39)108th Conclusions.Copy No.   39TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 408 (39).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, December 8, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The    Right    Hon.    Winston    S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P.,  Secretary of State for  theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The   Most   Hon.   the   Maruess   of zetland,   Secretary   of   State   for.India and Secretary of State for burma (Item 7).Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General  Sir  W.  Edmund  Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[20458]b
WAR CABINET 108 (39).minute no.123467891011Contents.Subject.The Air situation the Naval Situation ...H.M.S. Nelson.Orders regarding opening of A.A. fire.General report.Suggested air attack on bases used by German mine-layingseaplanes.The Military Situation        ...Finland ...Invasion by the U.S.S.R.Finland ...      ...      ...      ...      ...Supply of aircraft and munitions.Air requirements of the army in France   ...      ...The Middle East and India.........Soviet threat to British interests.ItalyAnglo-Italian economic relations.The BalkansAttitude of Roumania towards threatened Soviet aggression, andquestion of the British guarantee.League of NationsForthcoming Meeting of the Council and Assembly.War Cabi net Arrangements ...Page.351351352352352353356357357358359
The Air \    rf]ie Secretary of State for Air said that a formation situation. 7 Heinkels had been engaged by our fighters off the Scottish coast(Previous on the previous day.   The results of the engagement were not reference: certain, but it was thought that at least four of the enemy aircraftW.M. (39) 107th had been so seriously damaged that they were unlikely to haveConclusions, reached home. Four of our aircraft had been slightly damaged, butMinute 1.)        we had sustained no losses or casualties.A number of German aircraft had flown over the thames estuary and off the coast of East Anglia during the previous night.There had been much fog and the fighters sent up had not been ableto make contact.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The NayalSituation.(previous kef erence:W.M. (39) 107thConclusions,Minute 3.)H.M.S. Nelson.2. The First Lord of the A dmiralty gave the War Cabinet an account of his visit to the Commander-in-Chief, Home Fleet, on theprevious day. He thought that it was most important that the factthat the Nelson had been damaged by a mine should be kept secretas long as possible, and he therefore advocated withholding the newseven from the Dominion Prime Ministers. If the informationleaked out, the Admiralty would, of course, at once publish a state-ment that the Nelson had been damaged. It appeared certain that,from the accuracy of its position in the fairway, the mine whichhad struck the Nelson had been laid by a submarine. The Nelsonwould not be ready for sea for some days, and it was hoped that bythat time means of clearing the Channel would have been found.The powerful nature of the explosive in the mine could be judged from the fact that casualties had been occasioned by men beingflung upwards into the deck above. It spoke well for the Nelson&apos;srobust construction that she had not been more severely damaged.It had been agreed with the Commander-in-Chief that it wasinadvisable, at the present moment, to move ships in and out ofharbour more than could be avoided. He proposed therefore to ease off somewhat the degree of our patrolling activities for a short period. This would give a welcome respite and would enable somere-fitting to be car-ried out. The First Lord hoped that our counter-measures would have developed sufficiently in the next fortnight tomake the position more satisfactory.The First Lord referred to the fact that certain german aircraft, although within sight and range of our A.A. guns, hadnot been fired on. It appeared that these opportunities had beenmissed owing to the somewhat rigid rules with regard to openingfire, which had been framed with a view to safeguarding our ownaircraft.The Chief of the Air Staff said that this matter was being examined, as a matter of urgency, by the Commands and authorities concerned.General report. Continuing the First Lord reported the following german attacks on shipping : S.S. Britta (6,214 tons), Norwegian. Torpedoed and sunk.6 crew missing.S.S. Tajandoen (8,519 tons), Dutch. Torpedoed and sunk.62 survivors picked up by S.S. Louis Sheid (Belgian), whichha,d subsequently run aground in Bigbury Bay (Devon).S.S. Thomas Walton (4,460 tons), British. Torpedoed and sunk outside Narvik.   14 crew missing.S.S. One Toft (2,135 tons), Danish. Sunk in the North Sea,;6 missing.H.M.S. Jersey, which, as reported at the previous meeting, hadbeen torpedoed, had been safety docked.   2 officers and 8 men hadbeen killed and 40 injured.   The ship was very seriously damaged.[204581 &apos; b 2Orders regardingopening of A.A.Fire.
Suggested air The Minister without Portfolio asked whether an effective blowattack on bases could be struck at the German mine-laying operations by air attackused by German on their seaplane bases.seaplanes118 ^^le Chief of the Air Staff said that he had had an Appre-ciation of the position prepared. It would be necessary to determine what proportion of mine-laying was canned out by aircraft and what proportion by submarines; and then to decide, on the assump-tion that attacks on German seaplane bases would be successful,whether the interference with that proportion of the mine-layingwhich was carried out by aircraft would counterbalance the effectof the German air attacks on our Naval bases which would almost certainly follow.The First Lord of the Admiralty suggested that this matter should be discussed at one of the periodical meetings between theAdmiralty and the Air Ministry to discuss matters of common concern.The War Cabinet(i) Took note of the above statement.(ii) Agreed that the question of air action against the Germanseaplane bases, with a view to interrupting the Germancampaign of mine-laying from aircraft, should bediscussed at one of the periodical meetings between representatives of the Admiralty and the Air ministry and a report made to the War Cabinet.The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 107thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Secretary of State for War said that there was nothing to report from the Western Front.In reply to a question by the Prime Minister, he said thatthe General Staff did not attach particular importance to the reportsof German shipping concentration at Hamburg.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Finland.Invasion by theU.S.S.R.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 107thConcl conclusions,Minute 5.)4. The Secretary of State for War said that the Russians were reported to have advanced some miles towards the main Finnishdefence line, but that there was no confirmation of the Russianclaim that they had broken through.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the Finnish minister, whom he had seen earlier in the morning, had stated thatthe Finns were holding their own on all fronts and were confidentof continuing to do so under present conditions.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Finland.Supply of aircraft and munitions.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 107thConclusions,Minute 6.)5. The Secretary of State for Air said that, in accordancewith the Conclusion reached by tihe War Cabinet three days earlier(W.M. (39) 104th Conclusions, Minute 7), representatives of theFinnish Government had been put in touch with the Gloster AircraftCompany. He understood that some difficulty was being-experienced, since the Finnish Government wished to pay by instalments, whereas the firm wished to receive a lump sum payment for the aircraft to be despatched. The total amount involved was 85,000, and he hoped that it might be possible to arrive at a rapidsolution of the difficulty, so that the aircraft could be despatchedwithout delay.At a later stage in the Meeting the War Cabinet were informed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer that arrangements had been
made whereby the Gloster Aircraft Company would proceed at once to give delivery of the aircraft, on the understanding that theGovernment would cover them against loss.Reference was made to the very circumstantial report whichthe Minister of Supply had received from the Italian ambassador to the effect that 50 Italian aircraft had been flown to Finland,refuelling twice in Germany en route. The Secretary of State forForeign Affairs said that the information which he had obtainedconfirmed the fact that Italian aircraft had been ordered by theFinnish Government some time back, and it was possible that someof them had arrived. He had not been able to obtain any confirma-tion of the report that 50 Italian aircraft had flown to Finlandin the last few days.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs added that theFinnish Minister had informed him that the Finnish Governmentwere anxious to buy respirators and other military stores. He had asked the Minister to make direct application to the War Office.The Secretary of State for War said that, although we wereshort of respirators, he thought we ought to make every effort tohelp the Finnish Government.This suggestion met with approval.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Air Require-ments of theArmy in France.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 75thConclusions,Minute 8.)6. The War Cabinet had under consideration a Memorandumby the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence on the subject of theAir Requirements of the Army in France (W.P. (39) 127).The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence paid a tribute tothe goodwill of the two Services which had. resulted in the agreement reached and which reflected particular credit on their two represen-tatives, who were its authors. He also expressed appreciation ofthe help which he had received from the Lord Privy Seal and colonel Moore-Brabazon.He then went through his Memorandum in detail, the main points dealt with being as follows : The Agreement which was summarised in paragraph 4 showed that the new arrangement would be considerably simpler than theexisting scheme. A new Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief wouldbe appointed in France, whose position would be analogous to thatof the Army Commander-in-Chief, except that the former, unlike the latter, would not be under the French. The Bomber squadrons in France would be detached from the Bomber Command.Paragraph 4 (d) aimed at dispelling a possible source of futuremisunderstanding by making it clear that in exceptional circum-stances such, for example, as might arise from a German invasion of the Low Countries the command of the Bomber Squadrons inFrance might pass temporarily to the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief, Bomber Command, but only on the authority of the Chiefsof Staff Committee with War Cabinet sanction.Paragraph 4 (/) brought out the important point that ordersfor the employment of the Bomber Squadrons in France would besettled 1&apos; in consultation &apos;&apos; between the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief and the Commander-in-Chief, British Expeditionary Foi&apos;ce.The point here was that they were equals.The Prime Minister assumed that the term &quot; in consultation &quot;did not give the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief the right torefuse the requests of the Commander-in-Chief, British Expedi-tionary Force (unless, of course, he had countermanding orders from the Chiefs of Staff, approved by the War Cabinet), but that it
gave him the necessary latitude to express his view as to how the bomber Squadrons should be employed, or how the needs of theCommander-in-Chief could be met.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence explained that thePrime Minister&apos;s point was answered by paragraph 4 (g). whichendeavoured to show that the satisfactory working of the arrange-ment must rest, ultimately, on the goodwill of the parties concerned and their intention to carry out the Agreement in the spirit inwhich it had been drawn up. He believed that this would be thecase, and that it would therefore be unwise to attempt beforehandto defiue the conditions too precisely.Paragraphs 6 to 10 dealt with a point which, though not specifically referred to him by the War Cabinet, was a corollary tothe Agreement, namely, whether the Air Ministry&apos;s plan for produc-tion would continue to provide the number of bombers likely to berequired for the army. The answer was that there was no dangerof the Army being short of its requirements at least until 1942.Part II of the Memorandum dealt with the &quot; development ofprototypes of an aircraft susceptible to mass production methods and complying as nearly as possible with the requirements of theWar Office.&quot; It showed that the Moore-Brabazon conception of aprototype had proved impracticable. Nevertheless, when the presentAir Ministry programme for medium bombers came to an end, as itwould, in 1942, a new type of aircraft to replace the Blenheim wouldbe required; and it was perhaps desirable that the War cabinet should give consideration now to the steps-which should be taken toproduce a prototj^pe which would fulfil the requirements of theArmy after 1942.The Secretary of State for A ir interposed that the Air Ministryalready had plans in hand to supply the needs of the Army after1942, and that the Air Staff had, moreover, been in consultationwith the War Office about the prototype of the new type whichwould replace the Blenheim.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence suggested that inthese circumstances the War Cabinet need not be concerned with thedevelopment of prototypes raised in Part II of his Paper.The Prime Minister said that the War Cabinet was most grateful to the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence for his good offices in this matter and to the War Office and Air Ministry for theagreement which they had reached in such a spirit of goodwill.The Secretary of State for Air likewise expressed his indebted-ness to the Minister and to the Lord Privy Seal and ColonelMoore-Brabazon, whose suggestions had been most helpful. he added that the success of the arrangement which had been reachedwould depend entirely on the spirit in which it was carried out.The Secretary of State for War thanked the Minister for thepains which he had taken to produce the arrangement. At the sametime, he would not conceal bis view that the proper solution of this problem was the creation of an Army Air Arm. In accepting thepresent arrangement, as he did, he therefore felt it desirable to placeon record what he regarded as the principles on which the present arrangement should be worked, since it was likely to be taken as the pattern for other theatres of war.He felt that the appointment of an Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief in France was a great advantage, but considered that thisOfficer, as the Senior Air Officer in France, should be the air adviser to the Commander-in-Chief, B.F.F., instead of the Air OfficerCommanding, Air Component, and that the latter should be aliaison officer. This, however, was not a point of principle, and could be settled under paragraph 9 of the Agreement.   Referring-
to paragraph 4 (/) of the Memorandum, he said that the PrimeMinister had settled an important point in insisting, as he had, thatthere should be no ambiguity as to the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief having a definite responsibility in meeting the requirementsof the Commander-in-Chief, British Expeditionary Force, otherthan in the exceptional circumstances in which the bomber squadrons in France might be temporarily placed under bomber command by order of the Chiefs of Staff, with the approval of theWar Cabinet.With reference to paragraph 4 (g), he would have preferred that the Commander-in-Chief, British Expeditionary Force, shouldbe the channel for requests from the French for Bomber support,rather than that these requests should be made direct to the air officer Commanding-in-Chief, his reason being that it was to beanticipated that the Commander-in-Chief, British ExpeditionaryForce, would frequently have occasion to call upon the French fortheir support (in, for example, tanks and guns), and that it wouldbe helpful if he in return could offer British Bomber support. Thiswas a point, however, which he would not press.Finally, on the question of the prototype of an aircraft forthe special requirements of the Army, he said that he would beprepared to accept the arrangement which had now been reached between the War Office and the Air Ministry, on the understanding,however, that the War Office should have a say, not only in thequestion of the training of the personnel who would be using these aircraft, but also in the design and production of the aircraft.By this he meant that the War Office must be recognised to havea claim to be consulted at every stage, in the same way as theAdmiralty had been consulted under the arrangements in forcebefore the transfer of the Fleet Air Arm.In reply to a question by the Prime Minister, he explainedthat &quot; by consultation &quot; he meant a close association between theAir Ministry and the War Office, but not, for example, the rightof War Office inspectors to visit factories.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence explained that, inregard to the Fleet Air Arm, the arrangements had been that theAdmiralty as the users should be kept continuously in touch withthe design and production of the aircraft which the Air Ministrywere responsible for supplying.The Lord Privy Seal expressed his satisfaction that the Generaland Air Staffs had been able to find a basis of agreement. Never-theless, there were certain points which left him anxious.First, from the point of view of the Air Staff, he deploredanjr step which might result in a division of our Bomber Force,and he thought there was a danger that the present arrangement might result in the Bombers allotted to the Army being regardedas Army machines only.Secondly, from the point of view of the Army, he had hopedthat the outcome of these negotiations might result in the secondingof more Army Officers to the Air Force, thereby improving theknowledge of air matters in the Army.Lastly, he hoped that the War Cabinet would not rescind its decision regarding the need to produce a special prototype for army requirements. The particular proposal of Colonel Moore-Brabazonhad been found impracticable, but in his view this was no reasonfor abandoning the principle. The Blenheim was an expensive typeof aircraft, and when its production came to an end he felt thatits work could very well be done by a cheaper and mass-producedtype. He therefore hoped that the War Office and Air ministry would, in their consultations, give particular attention to the experimental production of a cheap type of this nature.The Secretary of State for Air said that he would be preparedto accept the agreement as set out by the Minister for Co-ordination
of Defence in his Memorandum but, if there was any question ofits variation, he would wish to consider any new points raised.With regard to the question of a prototype of a cheapermachine, he said that the careful study which had been given tothis matter had not been encouraging; and it had become clear what the Moore-Brabazon conception was impracticable. He agreed,however, that the Air Ministry in their consideration of the typeof aircraft which should replace the Blenheims, would take intoaccount the possibility of producing a cheap aircraft on mass-production lines.The Prime Minister said that he did not think that the point raised by the Secretary of State for War in regard to the WarOffice being consulted as to design and development constituted a variation of the agreement reached. He therefore suggested thatthe War Cabinet should endorse the Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence&apos;s recommendation that the Agreement, as set out in his memorandum, should be accepted. He considered that the questionof the production of a prototype to meet Army requirements wasa separate matter, and that the discussion had shown that there wasno need why the War Cabinet should repeal the decision which theyhad taken on this latter point.The War Cabinet agreed (i) to approve the Agreement contained in the Joint Memo-randum by the Deputy Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff and the Deputy Chief of the Air Staff as to theAir requirements of the Army (Annex I to W.P. (39)127), together with the Explanatory Comments containedin Part I of the covering Memorandum by the Ministerfor Co-ordination of Defence (W.P. (39) 127).(ii) To re-affirm the decision reached by the War Cabinet onthe 13th November, that steps for the Development ofprototypes of aircraft susceptible to mass-productionmethods and complying as nearly as possible with therequirements of the War Office, should be continued.(iii) That the War Office should be consulted at all stages asregards design and development of Army Air require-ments.The middle east and India.Soviet threat toBritishinterests.(previous reference:WM. (39) 34thConclusions,Minute 15.)7. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretarv of State for Foreign Affairs on the Soviet threat to Britishinterests&quot; in the Middle East (W.P. (39) 150).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theproposal put forward in his Memorandum was that we should take such steps as were immediately practicable, so that we might beready to counteract any anti-British activities by the SovietGovernment in the Middle East.The Secretary of State for India said that he entirely agreed with the proposals in the Memorandum, but that it would, of course,be necessary for him to consult the Viceroy before any actual steps were taken which affected India. In this connection the Secretaryof State drew attention to the fact that some time would elapse before India could be provided with adequate defence against air attack.The War Cabinet-Authorised the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, inco-operation with the Secretaries of State for War andIndia, to take the necessary steps forthwith to organisean effective intelligence system in certain regions in theMiddle East, as set out in his Memorandum W.P. (39) 150.
8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, as arranged at the meeting of the War Cabinet noted in the margin,he had satisfied himself, in consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Minister for Economic Warfare, that we shouldbe justified in informing the Italian Government that we proposedto spend not less than  25 millions in Italy in the period up to the31st December, 1940, on the purchase of raw materials and manu-factured goods, and in freight payments. He had, therefore, theprevious day sent a telegram (No. 712, by telephone) authorisingHis Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Rome to inform the Italian authori-ties accordingly, making it clear at the same time, however, thatthe undertaking was subject to the prices being reasonable, the goods(in particular the aircraft and armaments) corresponding with our requirements, and the delivery dates being acceptable.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The Balkans.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 107thConclusions,Minute 8.)Attitude ofRoumaniatowardsthreatenedSovietaggression, andquestion of theBritishguarantee.9. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that at an.interview the previous clay M. Tilea, the Roumanian Minister inLondon, had said that he had been recalled to Bucharest for three days for consultation. It was of the utmost importance that heshould be in a position to give a clear answer to the roumanian government on the question whether our guarantee applied in thecase of Soviet as well as German aggression. M. Tilea had argued that, if we made it clear that our guarantee applied to Sovietaggression, that fact alone would be sufficient to prevent suchaggression; but if. on the other hand, we did not make it clear, theRoumanian Government, who were much more frightened of theU.S.S.R. than of Germany, might well go to great lengths to secureGerman protection against the Soviet. He (the Secretary of State)had replied that it was impossible for us to define our positiondefinitely until we knew what Avould be the attitude of Turkey andItaly. M. Tilea had professed to think that the Turkish Govern-ment were anxious to agree upon mutual defensive arrangements,and that they would go to the assistance of Roumania even if theU.S.S.R. limited its aggression to Bessarabia, M. Tilea hadprofessed himself hopeful also regarding the attitude of Italy.In this connexion the Secretary of State referred to telegramNo. 106, dated the 6th December, 1939, from His Majesty&apos;ambassador, Rome, reporting the substance of a. conversation whichthe Counsellor of his Embassy had had that evening with the italian minister for Foreign Affairs, which may be summarised asfollows :  The Counsellor had asked Count Ciano whether he had any information to support the view that the U.S.S.R. either now or later might turn their attention towards the South. To thisCount Ciano had replied at once that anything which touchedthe Balkans would be the immediate concern of Italy. TheItalians were keeping a very careful watch,, and up to date, theyhad no reason to suspect that there was any move in prospect.The Counsellor had then said that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwere naturally much exercised about such an eventuality andshared Italian concern. Count Ciano had replied that he hopedthat the status quo would be preserved in the Balkans. He hadevidently had no wish to go further than that.In the same telegram Sir Percy Loraine had reported a, conver-sation in which the Hungarian Minister had stated that, from information received from Budapest, it was clear that no attackeither by the Soviet or by the Soviet in conjunction with theGermans was being premeditated in the Balkans, since both Powers[20458] cAnglo-Italian,economic relations.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 105thConclusions,Minute 11.)
(previous reference:W.M. (39) 39thConclusions,Minute 10.)(previous reference:W.M. (39) 69thConclusions,Minute 5.)were too fully occupied at the moment to desire war in the Balkansor the Black Sea. The Hungarian Minister had added that, in theevent of Hungary being attacked, it was hoped and thought that she would receive armed assistance from Italy.In these circumstances, the Secretary of State did not feel thatthe attitude of either Turkey or Italy was sufficiently clearly definedto make it possible for us to give a final answer to the question raisedby M. Tilea. It would be necessary, therefore, to answer his question more or less on the lines of replies already given both by ourselves and the French.The Minister withotit Portfolio said that the Roumanianswere now raising difficulties in regard to oil and had indicated that they proposed to apply a quota system for all countries.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that this change of attitude was no doubt due to the great fear in Roumaniaof invasion by the TJ.S.S.R.The Prime Minister said that he did not believe that turkey would go to the assistance of Roumania in the event of Sovietaggression against Bessarabia, and in a conversation the previous day the Turkish Ambassador had made it clear to the Chancellorof the Exchequer that not even a Soviet approach to the mouthsof the Danube would be regarded by Turkey as a casus belli, though they would fight if the Straits were threatened.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence said that very similar views had been expressed to him on the same occasion bythe Turks. The view had also been expressed that a joint German-Soviet invasion of the Balkans was probable on a broad front,the Germans passing through Yugoslavia and the Soviet going byway of the Black Sea.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he believed thatthere was a great movement in Germany against Herr von ribbentrop&apos;s pro-Soviet policy, and that we were still far from a situation in which Germany and the U.S.S.R. would act in realunison with one anotiher. If such a situation were ever to arise,it would be one of the utmost gravity through the power of Germanyto exploit the resources of Russia, though no doubt it would bringwith it compensation in a change of attitude on the part of Italy,Japan and other countries. For the moment, however, it would hethought, be premature to anticipate a solid alliance between germany and the U.S.S.R.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.League ofNations.forthcoming meeting of theCouncil and assembly.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 107thConclusions,Minute 10.)10. In the course of the discussion recorded in Minute 9 above,the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he had instructed Mr. R. A. Butler above all things to avoid giving theimpression that we were not clear as to our attitude towards theU.S.S.R. He was to have no hesitation in condemning the Sovietaggression on Finland. As regards the suggestion that the U.S.S.R.should be expelled from the League, he was to prevent this being brought forward if he could, but if it were brought forward, he wasunhesitatingly to vote for expulsion. As regards sanctions, he wasto state clearly that in our view these were not practicable.The War Cabinet approved these instructions.
War Cabinet 11.   The Prime Minister said that on Thursday, the 14thArrangements. December, the day on which Parliament was to adjourn for the christmas Recess, both Houses would be meeting at 12 Noon. he proposed that the Meeting of the War Cabinet on that day shouldbe at 10 a.m.It was also agreed that the Meeting of the War Cabinet on saturday, the 9th December, should be at 10-30 a.m.The War Cabinet took note of these arrangements.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,December 8, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
