<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/172/2 images: 10-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(73) 10216 October 1973CABINETLATE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE OCTOBER 1972 RENT increases memorandum by the Secretary of State for scotland the PROBLEM IN scotland, The problem described for England and Wales in CP(73) 98 affectsScotland also.    Though the law is different, legislation would be needed toenable relief to be given to councillors who might be surcharged and alarger number of councils is involved,,2.        The crucial questions are what we would legislate for, and when.Despite the objections to a general amnesty (paragraph 6 of CP(73) 98),which some would undoubtedly interpret as weakness, I consider that any form of selective amnesty would be unworkable in Scotland,,    In particularI judge that a compromise on the lines of that suggested by the Secretary ofState for the Environment would be much worse in Scotland than a generalamnesty.    Faced in Scotland with a possible total of 32 audit reports(relating to 18 authorities who were late in implementing the Act and 14others against whom default orders had to be made) I should find it invidiouto exercise a discretionary power to pick and choose between them.    If wefollowed the line suggested in CP(73) 98, it would be difficult to have todefend, firsta a decision to apply surcharges only to the somewhat randomselection of six authorities against whom further proceedings had to betaken before they complied with the terms of the default orders, and second, the amount of the surcharge in each case.    Again, to relievethose concerned of personal liability in respect of surcharge would, inScotland, also relieve them of liability to disqualification (sincedisqualification is not automatic, though it follows on bankruptcy).l-^iv&apos;:! ^,.,.--1.. . j .3,        As regards timing, precipitate action would strengthen the handsof those local authority members who are still rebellious, and might provoke some general criticism.    As an alternative to a general amnesty,my preference in Scotland would be to continue as at present under theexisting law, giving ourselves plenty of time and maintaining the possiblesanction of surcharge.    There is no fixed time limit on my decision andthus no legal reason why I need give decisions on audit reports for many months,    I would hope therefore to defer until a more favourable time any final decision and announcement about the general amnesty which may wellbe the only practicable course at the end of the day.COPY NO        g &apos;(confidential
CONFIDENTIALSUBSIDY IMPLICATIONS IN scotland.        The point raised in paragraph 9 of CP(73) 98 does not arise inScotland, where default cannot increase an authority1 s entitlement tosubsidy.conclusion.        I consider that the choice lies between a.        a general amnesty; orb6 a two-stage procedure on the lines outlined in paragraphabove.In my view, it would be desirable to explore first the possibilities ofcourse b0G scottish Office16 October 19732CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALANNEXDEFAULT ORDERSGlasgow*Lanark CountyMidlothianAlloa*BarrheadCowdenbeath*Clydebank*Cumbernauld*Denny and DunipaceDunfermlineFalkirkKilmarnockKirkcaldySaltcoats**Those for which order from Court of Session had to be obtained.LATE IMPLEMENTATION AND LOST INCOMEAberdeen CityDundeeEdinburghFifeWest LothianArdrosaanBuckhavenDumbarton BurghInverurieKintoreMuybolePaisleyRenfrewRutherglenSteven stonStewartonTranentWhitburn16 October 1973CONFIDENTIAL


</content>
</cab>
