<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/94/0 images: 163-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.THE CABINET.AIMS OP THE  GERMAN FORCE IN THE BALTICPROVINCES.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.I circulate a memorandum which has been prepared by the General Staff incompliance with instructions issued at the Prime Ministers Conference of 12thNovember. ( &apos; !Uv^-c   i (JjiJAppendix B contains a note on the projected agreement between General Denikinand Galicia.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.1st December, 1919.1. Strength of German force. The number of German troops in the Kovno Shavli Mitau Liban area is estimated at 35,000 to 40,000. In addition there areabout 4,000 Germans operating under Colonel Bermont near Riga. Some of thesetroops are returning to Germany, but only in small numbers at present.2. Character and aims of the German troops. The German force is mainlycomposed of adventurers and of would-be settlers in the Baltic States. Although itincludes loyal and obedient elements, whose evacuation may offer no great difficulties,our latest report states that some 25,000 maybe regarded as lawless, undisciplinedmen, recognizing no authority but that of their immediate superiors, and said to berapidly developing into marauding bands.The German troops are led by officers who may be divided into two categories : (a.) Those actuated by patriotism, who hope to acquire fresh ground for Germanexpansion, both political and economic.(6.) Those influenced by self-interest and adventure.    Many of these have noprospects in Germany and wish to open up new careers in Russia, whilstothers prefer to continue fighting rather than to settle down to a quietlife in a restless and uncomfortable Germany.The soldiers are serving in the hope of obtaining good pay, loot and oppor-tunities of settling down in conditions better than those offered by their owncountry. They bear strong points of resemblance to the German mercenaries of the17th and 18th centuries.3. Motives of the undertaking. The driving power is supplied by the Prussianmilitary party, mainly from patriotic motives. The leaders of this party, men likeGenerals Ludendorff, Hofman and Lossberg, supported by some of the leading permanentcivil officials and certain capitalists, have not given up their hopes of a great Germanrevival in future years.Their motto is &quot;Augen Ost,&quot; i.e., &quot; Eyes to the East.&quot; They realize that, inWestern Germany, there is no hope of territorial or even commercial expansion. TheEast, on the other hand, provides an unlimited field for German thrift, brains andenergy. They have hopes of ultimate territorial gains by means of German settlers,and their immediate object is to help the German Baits to overthrow the Letts, and toestablish their ascendency in Lithuania and Courland. Their ulterior aim is thedevelopment of Russia by German brains and enterprise. To such men and theircapitalist backers the Baltic Provinces are merely the gateway to Russia, which theyhope to enter as soon as she has settled down and again has a stable Government.It must not be forgotten that the original object of the German forces was to holdthe line against the Bolsheviks on this sector of the Russian front. Towards the endof 1918, when the German soldiery were streaming back to Germany in disorder, theLettish Government did their best to induce German troops to remain behind in order(B19/551)  90   L2/19  H&amp;S   7746\vo
to protect the country against the Bolshevist invasion which was then an imminentdanger. On 29th December M. Ulmanis, President of the Lettish Council, concludedan agreement with the German Commissioner, Herr Winnig, by which the right ofLettish citizenship was granted to such German soldiers as took part in. the deliveranceof Latvia from the Bolsheviks. There is little doubt that prospects of settlement inLatvia were held out to the German volunteers, especially by the Baltic landowners,Avho were German in sympathy, but at that time were making common cause with theLetts against the Bolsheviks.4. Attitude of the German Government. The German Government, like thePrussian Military Party, are anxious to keep Bolshevism out of Germany, and for thisreason would prefer to hold it at arm&apos;s length, instead of withdrawing their troops totheir own frontiers, and thus allowing Bolshevist influence to approach considerablynearer to German territory. They are now doing their best to recall the Germantroops, probably not so much because they disapprove of their action, but because theyare anxious not to incur the displeasure of the Allies. They know that the Allies arestrongly opposed to the German intrigues in the Baltic States, and will bring constantpressure to bear on them as long as these intrigues continue. Although the GermanSocialist Parties are known to have been in communication with Moscow, there isno evidence that the German Government is implicated, and the German MilitaryParty would certainly prefer the victory of the anti-Bolsheviks.The German Government in Berlin have shown themselves willing to co-operatewith the Allied Commission which, under the direction of General Niessel, has gone tosupervise the evacuation of the German forces of the Baltic Provinces. Brigadier-General Turner, the British member of this Commission, has expressed his opinion thatthe German Government intend to act in good faith, and are anxious to clear up thesituation. He considers that the German Government might have acted with greatervigour and produced more visible effect,, had the Allies given stronger evidence of theirdetermination to insist on the withdrawal of the German troops at an earlier stage in thesituation; before the German and German-Russian forces had become so disintegratedand undisciplined, and before their organized recruiting and financial support hadassumed its present dimensions.5. Powers of German Government to control. The German Government is atpresent in a difficult position, between an Extreme Socialist Party on the one side and aReactionary Monarchist Party on the other. It depends on the army for its existence,and the army is more or less in the hands of the Prussian Military Party, i.e., of menwho are heart and soul in favour of the present action in the Baltic States.Consequently, when Noske gives orders he lacks the power to ensure their beingobeyed, and knows full well that they will probably be evaded or openly disregarded.The German Government is so dependent on the support of the military leadersand higher permanent civil officials that it dare not check or oppose the methodsadopted to recruit and supply the forces in the Baltic Provinces. For the same reason,it is powerless to insist on the recall of the German troops. *General Staff,War Office,l$lh November, 1919.This paper was referred to General Haking for his comments, which are attached as Appendix A.
APPENDIX A.NOTES by LIEUT-GENERAL BAKING.I think the foregoing paper on the &quot;Aims of the German forces in the Baltic Provinces &apos; is a truestatement of the situation.I am rather doubtful, however, whether any party in the German Government is really desirous ofgetting the Germans out of the Baltic States, and I do not think the mutter will be brought to asatisfactory conclusion until more drastic means than &quot; Allied Missions&quot; are applied.The best test would be to create a military blockade across the East Prussian-Lithuanian border andbetween the German and Baltic ports. This would prevent all Germans passing to and fro; it wouldprovide a means of repatriating the Germans now in the Baltic States; it would completely strangle therecruiting, financing and supplying of Bermont&apos;s and Eberhardtfs Germans, and, most important of all,it would raise the prestige of the Allies and lower that of.the Germans in the Baltic Provinces, a mostdesirable matter at the present moment, when the&apos; prestige of the Allies is undoubtedly on the wane iuthose Provinces. Furthermore, having once shown Germany definitely that the Allies insist upon alltheir orders being carried out, the way will be thrown open to improve the conditions of Germany andbring her back to become a respectable member of the European family.If this blockade is established and the German Government is really anxious to comply with theAllied demands, the withdrawal of the Germans will be comparatively simple, and there may be nooccasion for the Allied troops to fight, If, on the other hand, the Germans do not wish to withdrawtheir nationalities from Lsttland and Lithuania, and wish to continue their present policy of evading theAllied demands, the presence of an actual military force on the East Prussian frontier appears to be theonly possible means of making Germany bow to the inevitable.If the Germans under Bermont and Eberhardt lose their cohesion and turn themselves intomarauding bands the Lithuanian Government will probably think it is necessary to arm their peasantsand a great deal of loss of life will follow, because the Letts and Lithuanians hate the Germans and willseize any opportunity of killing them off. It will be necessary, therefore, for the Allies to inform theLithuanian and Lettish Governments that they must &quot;round up&quot; the Germans Avith properly constitutedmilitary bodies and hand them over to the Allies on the East Prussian frontier.R. B. A. Hakino, lieut.-general.London. 24th November, 1919.APPENDIX B.NOTE ON THE PROJECTED AGREEMENT BETWEEN GENERAL DENIKIN ANDGAL 1 CIA.On the 6th December, Denmiss, Taganrog, reported that there was every prospect of an agreementbeing come to between Denikin and the Galicians (Ruthenians) serving with Petlui&apos;a&apos;s force, with a viewto their joining the Volunteer Army. It appears, however, that although their Delegates agreed tocertain terms the headquarters of their force refuse to ratify them. The terms which had been agreedupon were as follows : (1.) The dissolution of the Galician &quot; Government,&quot; the members of- which were offered accommoda-tion in Odessa, provided they lived there as private individuals.(2.) The transfer of (ialician troops to Denikin&apos;s command, excepting those wishing to return totheir homes.It had been intended by Denikin to despatch such Galicians who joined bis forces to a part of thefront remote from the Polish frontier, probably because these men are natives of country now--inoccupation by Polish troops, who have been driven out by the latter and are therefore, in all probability,very hostile to the Poles. No promises were made by General Denikin to the Galicians regarding thefuture state of their country, and it is understood that those who joined his forces were to joinunconditionally or not at all.On refusal of the ratification of the above agreement, General Denikin attacked the forces of Petluraon the front Tulchin Yampol and drove them back a distance of 40 miles, capturing a series of towns upto the line Zhmerihka -Mogileff. The Galicians appear to have taken no part in the operations, andwithdrew to the Vinnitza area. Should the Galicians, as a result of these operations, decide to discontinuetheir connection with Petlura and come over to Denikin on the original agreement, there seems no reasonwhy the relations between the Volunteer Army and Poland should become more strained. Any possibilityof independent action by the Galicians against Polish- troops or territory will be obviated by Denikin&apos;sproposed transfer of their forces to an area remote from Poland, and provided that the Poles are informedby Denikin or the Russian Delegation iu Paris, of the fact that he has made no promises to these menregarding the future status of Galicia, and further, that he has no intention of trespassing on the territorynow in occupation by Polish forces, such an agreement might result in a rapprochement with the Poles,,rather than reverse. ,General Staff,War Office,19th november, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
