<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/94/0 images: 192-193</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
rrt Is the Property oSUBSIDY TO PUBLIC UTILITY SOCIETIES.Memorandum by the Minister of Health,Ur fHIS.?1t*JI v.?The present terms to Public Utility Societies are not sufficientlyIttrective to induee more than a few of them to start building.   The totallumber of houses provided for in schemes submitted by those societies istoly 2,075..   C^ing to the increase in the cost of building since the termsrere first announced, it is impossible, except in a few districts where &apos;exceptionally high rates can be obtained, for a Public Utility Societyto pay any interest at all on its privately subscribed capital;   it wouldactually Incur a deficit which, would &quot;have&apos;to be. met out of private funds.I recently received a deputation composed of representatives ofassociations interested in Public Utility Societies, who made it clear toW that we could not count upon the provision of houses by-those societiesunless they were offered better terns.,-  The proposal then put forward was-ifthat the Government should gut.rmtee 4 per cent interest on the private&amp;y[subscribed capital of the Society.   I--understand that the Treasury wouldnot agree to an amendment of the term3 in this form, but I suggest as analternative that the rate of subsidy should be increased from 30 per centto 50 per cent of the loan charges between now and 1927, and that after1927 it should remain as at present at 30 per cent.I have reason to believe that this alternative would be acceptable tothe Societies.In the following figures a comparison is made between the estimatedaverage amount of the State subsidy during the years ending March,1927,where)(a)   Loan charges on Government loan of 675 at 6 per cent...&quot;Interest at 4 per ;cent on  225Repairs (15 per cent   f rents)Management, voids,insurance,etc.(12 per cent of.rents)xclusive of rates (12/6over period ..  ad42.16 * 8.9.0. 0.4.17.6.3.16.060.12.2.32.10.0
    s   d.Balance to be met by subsidy      28.   2, 2*(d) Loan charges on  900 at 6per cant. 57.   2.0.50 per cent subsidy.        &apos;    23. 11. 0.Assuming that rents will rise during the transitional periodthe&quot; 50 per cent subsidy would probably be less favourable to theSociety than the 4 per cent guarantee during&apos; the first few yearsof this period but more favourable during the last few years,     Fora few years after 1927 the private lenders will stand to make aloss/ as it is not to be supposed that the 20 per cent drop in thesubsidy could immediately be made good out of rents.The present terms for Public Utility Societies compare veryunfavourably with those given to local authorities, and unless we areto abandon the hope of getting houses built through the medium ofthese Societies I am sure that we must offer them better terms.   The 150 subsidy will not meet the case as the industrial..companieswill not lock up a large amount of capital in bricks and mortar.     Ineed hardly point out that, even under the more generous termswhich:I   propose the liability of the Exchequer will be less if thehouses are provided by Public Utility Societies than if they areprovided by-local authorities, unless the local authorities obtainmuch higher rents than we can at present anticipate,I hope therefore that the Cabinet will sanction the revisedterms how suggested and will authorise me to include a provision tothis&apos; effect in the Housing Bill.0. ADDIson.o i o    cn oMinistry of Health.

</content>
</cab>
