<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/94/0 images: 208-214</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-JL^gJ?.?climen* is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesties Government.)CONFIDENTIAL.Copy No.  (jMONTHLY  STATEMENTofEmployment of British Vesselson 31st OCTOBER 1919.(a,) 1,600 Gross Tonnage and over,(b) 500-1,599 Gross Tonnage.SHIPPING INTELLIGENCE SECTION (R.B.),MINISTRY OF SHIPPING,London, S.W. 1,
CONFIDENTIAL.(a) Employment of British Vessels of 1,600 GrosExcluding vessels in such employment (e.g,, in the Great Lakes) :1919.Mar,  Anril.May.June.July.Aug.Sept.Oot.Passenger Vessels.No.Tonnage.Cargo Vessels(Tramps and LinenNo.220 I 132162701817044167817624911841011021374913559111147873930167171,67620913010711532954541586271,7802,897232502,891232573,1793,1808422012122414894321,8782,908236573,2011079410834457544146121102272,0819790964535592,91123469165150192342,1107285957342,911232613,214 13,204411194149487482,132586110702,918223733.214231130122715613111532,1252,944222703,236I. $Requisitioned Vessels : (excluding Wheat, see b.)(a) British : Navy -War&apos;Office   -Sugar -Pyrites  and   IronOre.Other minerals andgeneral cargoes.^ Repairing     (fromServices in 1.,i.e., with no indi-cation ol return toowner&apos;s account).AustraliaNew ZealandIndia   -Other colonies, &amp;c.France -Italy.....Other Allies, &amp;c. -(b) Vessels carrying- Cereals andsimilar   food   stuffs  fordischarge in: United KingdomFrance -Italy.....Other destinations -II. Vessels under notice of requi-sition but not yet allocatedto a particular Service.III. Vessels temporarily released toowners, with an obligation toresume Government Service.Totals  -IV. Vessels at present free fromAdmiralty requisition^: ^(a) Vessels trading on behalf ofAllied Governments, fyc.France -Italy.....United States      -Other Allies -      -     -Neutrals, &amp;c.       -(&amp;) Other   Vessels not includedunder previous heads.*Totals   -V. Vessels fitted for carriage of............... petiolevm in bulk.VI. Passenger and Cargo Vesselslaunched and completing.GRAND TOTAL17441101487635252158,135237,9^72,88592,0884117107173559,5864,495291455,18621,74827,59020,8146,2123,421,290624 I 3,952,840 I 2,320 I 9,720,1117222115313106511,604No.2,944222703,236Tonnage. I13,673,211,151,6&quot;351,23115,176,1For notes, tee page 3.
Tonnage and over on 31st October 1913.render them not available for ocean-going trade or requisition;      i -ANALYSIS OF FREE VESSELS SHOWN UNDER IV. (b).---&quot;	No.	Tonnage. 1	No.	Tonnage,(1) Colonial registered vessels permanently abroad:- xi f s.  .       ,.                 ( Passenger vessels     -&apos;     -(a) Australia      -     - i n            i v &apos;                           ( Cargo vessels   -     -     -     -(b) Canada -     -     -    assenSer v^sels     &quot;     &quot;      &quot; v &apos;                            I Cargo vessels   -     -     -     -/ \ r\4.\.   n t   -    p     ( Passenger vessels    -(c) Cther Colonies, &amp;c. \ n      b     , v J                   &apos;       ( Cargo vessels   -	19 &apos; 83 13 31 9 31	58,601 227,096 35,230 114,824 22,658 81,553	186 116$ 161 1.179$	&apos;  539,962 300,343 783,857 7,069,494(2) \United Kingdom registered vessels trading abroad ;-(a) Passenger vessels     -     -      -     -            -      -(b) Cargo vessels    -     -     -     -     -     -     - &apos;   -	72 44	175,485 124,858		(3) Passenger vessels repairing or surveying      -Cargo vessels repairing or surveying   -     -     -     -	45 116	298,370 485,487		(4) Other vessels [not under full requisition):  $Passenger Liners on berth - :     -      -      -$Cargo Liners loading on berth, including Tramps chartered to Liner Cos., &amp;c. /&apos;            &quot; *                 . -...................       -	350 829	2,798,586 4,270,908						Vessels trading for Colonies but not permanently abroad Cereals for discharge in United Kingdom  -      -Cereals for discharge iii Europe, destination not determined -Ore, phosphates, lead, &amp;c, for discharge in United Kingdom Sugar, rum, nitrates, &amp;c, for discharge in United Kingdom -Oils, kernels, timber, &amp;c, for discharge in United Kingdom Timber for discharge in United Kingdom  -      -General cargo and munitions for discharge in United Kingdom Coasting United Kingdom&apos;      -      -     -     -Cable repairing and laying       -      -      -      -      -Whaling supplies    -     --     --     --     -	89 111 4 72 15 21 45 68 50 5 3	356,651 458,567 18,143 232,403 60,822 72,797 144,238 255,664 126,201 19,442 9,536	483	1,754,464			2,125	10,448,120NOTES.* For analysis, see page 3.% For analysis, see page 4,5 To ascertain the number of vessels actually in the service of the Allies on the date of this return the number given underI. and IV. on page 2 must be included. In addition, a number of vessels shown under ore, phosphates, lead, &amp;c., under(3) on page 4 load outward for an Allied Government, A comparison of the numbers shown under 1. and. IV. for the8 months does not therefore give an accurate criterion of the vessels in Allied service at the different periods.&quot; Requisition &quot; is here used to mean &quot; requisition for full Government service.&quot;(pin &quot;requisitioned vessels&quot; and &quot; vessels repairing (from Services in I.)&quot; are included; 142-563.606 G.T. Governmentowned vessels, prize vessels, and time-chartered foreign vessels sailing under the British flag.o  (33) AS 7819  Pk 428  50  11/19  B&amp;S (Sch C 56)
Detailed Analysis of Passenger and Cargo Liners included under IV. (b),See note at foot of page 3.L-To United Kingdom.(Including Liners discharging part cargoes in N. France.)No. of PassengerV cssels.No.Tonnage.No. of CargoVessels.No.     Tonnage.11141485407643010274132359762141167763503,7043,14062,194125,234831,174282,39854,162699,116259,42664,70017,7932,403,0419,85113,04113,23924,87351,72036,14746,66928,77611,55271,053. 6,85349,75832,013395,5452,798,58618363041461057019673186639142121355219741411810219082957,96793,858117,283186,745305,500631,597464,5911,008,946349,17085,01012,7073,313,37460,488111,088125,25453,790209,99725,917100,57135,26631,34218,72451,3305,24792,55228,1987,770957,5344,270,90875607224,41413,450137,621175,4851637441,77522,518100,565124,858Route.Egyptian Ports and ILK. (including N. France).Mediterranean (other than Egyptian Ports), Bay Ports, and U.K. (including N. France]W. Africa and U.K. (including N. France).S. and E. Africa and ILK. (including N. France).Australia and New Zealand and ILK. (including N. France).India and Burmah (up to and including Rangoon) and ILK. (including N. France).Straits (including Singapore and Java) and Far East and ILK. (including N. France).N. America (including Canada and Gulf) and ILK. (including N. France).S. America (Atlantic) and ILK. (including N. France).West Coast N. and S. America and U.K. (including N. France).Scandinavia and ILK.Total.II. To Countries other than United Kingdom.Route.Mediterranean and Bay Ports, and N. America (including Canada and Gulf).Africa (W., S. &amp; E.) and N. America (including Canada and Gulf).India and Burmah (up to and including Rangoon) and N. America (including Canada andGulf).Australia and New Zealand and N. America East Coast (including Canada and Gulf).Straits (including Singapore and Java) and Far East and N. America, E. and W. CoastsIndia and S. America (Atlantic and Pacific).N. America and S. America.Australia and New Zealand and West Coast N. and S. America.India and South and East Africa.India and Australia.India and Far East.India and Egyptian and Mediterranean Ports.Indian Coastal Trade.N. America and Canada and Central America.Australia and Egyptian Ports.Total.vGrand Total.III. Other United Kingdom registered Vessels Trading Abroad.Area of Trading Routes.In Australian Seas.In American (including Canadian) Seas.In other Seas (principally Indian, Chinese, and Java Seas).Total.
COMPARATIVE STATEMENTS.(1) Comparison between British Tonnage July 1914 and 31st October 1919.	No. of Vessels.	.. , .,... Tonnage.		No. of Vessels.	Tonnage.July 1914 ----Add :-Launched     -Transferred from foreign flags and other causes. Prizes   -      -      -      -Alterations to gross tonnage (net gain). Totals	4,068 1,214 362 144	17,516,876 5,703,643 1,476,153 611,778 225,507	Deduct :  War Josses Vessels interned in enemy pnrts or captured. Marine losses Transferred to foreign flags and other causes. Totals	1,775 279 498	7.424,190 1,029,460 1,904,138	5,788	25,533,957		2,552	10,357,788Position 31st October 1919 = 3,236 of 15,176,169 tons.(2) Comparison between Monthly Net Reduction or Increase in Vessels available forTrade or Requisition (excluding Oilers),November 1918.	December 1918.	January 1919.	February 1919.	March 1919.	April 1919.	May 1919.	June 1919.	July 1919.	August 1919,	September 1919.	October 1919.Gain 3	Gain 29	Gain 28	Gain 13	Loss 19	Nil	Gain 1	Gain 17	Gain 15	Loss 10	19	Gain 23The alterations during October 1919 were as follows: Additions. Deductions.Launched  -      -      -      -      -      -      -   35       Marine Loss......1Conversion from oil tanker and other causes -    3       Transferred to foreign flags and other causes     14Net gain.......2338 38(3) compaiuson between monthly number of requisitioned vessels for army, NaVY, andAllies (excluding Wheat, Sugar, Ore, and Oilers).November	December	January	February	March	ADril	May	June	July	August	September	October1918.	1918.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.1,027	865	843	870	652	481	400	345	301	265	233	193(4) Comparison between Monthly Total Figure of British Vessels, 1,600 Gross Tons .and over (including vessels launched and completing but excluding Oilers).November	December	January	February	March	April	May&apos;	June	July	August	September	October1918.	1918.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.	1919.2,896	2,925	2,953	2,966	2,947	2,947	2,948	2,965	2,980	2,972	2,991	3,014A 3
j(b) Employment of British Vessels of 500 -	Passenger Vessels.		Cargo Vessels. (Tramps, Cargo Liners, and Coasters.)		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.l, Requisitioned vessels :  British : Navy -         -         -         -War Office   ...... Pyrites and iron ore -         -         -         -Other munitions and general cargo Salvage       -Repairing     -         -         -         -India -France -        -         -        -        -Other Allies	9 b 2 2	6,142 9,160 1,776 2,030	28 10 2 1 1 2 1	25,197 9,425 2,3521 1,029 537 2,121 884II. Vessels tauter notice of requisition but not yet allocated to a particular service.	 	 	-	 III. Vessels temporarily released to oioners with an obligation to resume Government service.	 		 	IV. Vessels at present free from requisition: &apos;				(a) Vessels  trading on behalf of Allied Govern^				yients, fyc.:  France -Italy    -        -        -i        -Other Allies     -         -         -Neutrals, &amp;c.	8 2 2	8,072 2,412 2,462	228 7 44 20	220,921 8,806 39,622 22,721(6) Other vessels not included under previous heads*	155	164,376	428	420,643Total   ,	188	196,430	1   772-	754,258V, Vessels fitted for carriage of petroleum in bulk  *VI. Passenger and cargo vessels launched and completingGeand Total   -No.960713980Tonnage.950,6887,14215,244973,074* For analysis, tee page 7,
1,599 Gross Tonnage on 31st October 191.9.ANALYSIS OF FREE VESSELS SHOWN UNDER IV. (b).-					No.	Gross Tonnage.	Total.								No.	Gross Tonnage.(1) Colonial registered vessels permanently abroad :  , s  .       ,.   I Passenger vessels       ..... la) Australia in      0     , v &apos;               1 Cargo vessels...... n\ r-     1      ( Passenger vessels..... lb) Canada  -in              1 v &apos;               \ Cargo vessels...... , s ni.1            Passenger vessels..... (cj Other    - \ n             , v &apos;               ( Cargo vessels                   -      -      -      -(2) United Kingdom registered vessels trading abroad:  z x  .       ,.   ( Passenger vessels       -      -      -      -la) Australia I n             , v ;               j Cargo vessels     ------n     i      ( Passenger vessels              -      -      -      -lb) Canada  -in              1 v &apos;                I Cargo vessels...... , s nn          ( Passenger vessels..... (c) Other     -\n             , v &apos;               1 Cargo vessels     -     -     -      -   . -(3) Passenger vessels repairing, fyc, or laid up  -Cargo vessels repairing, fyc., or laid up       -					10 41 7 34 1 36	10,716 42,169 8,298 36,866 926 41,171	129 61 55 67 249 22	140,146 60,344&apos; 58,651 72,681 230,162 23,035					5 4 7 15 30	5,469 5,125 6,749 16,111 26,890							17 38	19,655 38,996										-	Passenger.		Cargo.		Total.				NTo.	Gross Tonnage.	No.	Gross Tonnage.	No.	Gross Tonnage.		(4) Liners on berth (excluding regular coasting lines:  ILK.- Med. U.K.-Holland  -U.K.-W.C. Africa U.K. Norway  -U.K.-Channel    Islands and N. France. (5) Coasting (including regular coasting lines and Miscel-laneous coasting vessels). (6) Miscellaneous cargoes from overseas for discharge in U.K. .-Pitwood -Whale oil General (including timber other than pit-wood). Pyrite3 and iron ore	2 10 1 12	2,492 1M75 1,143 10,360	15 15 5 4 3	17,993 15,068 7,148 5,069 1,933	17 25 5 5 15	20.485 26,543 7,148 ,  6,212 12,293			74	75,362	175	154,800	249	230,162			1 1	1,332 1,381 .	1 I 16 2	1,407 1,105 16,114 1,696	1 1 17 3	1,407 1,105 17,446 3,077									583	585,019

</content>
</cab>
