<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/94/0 images: 215-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MANDATES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.A good deal of correspondence has recently taken placewith the Governments of the Commonwealth of Australia, NewZealand, and the Union of South Africa on the subject of Mandates.I have selected the more important documents, and they have nowbeen printed for the purpose of record. It will be observed thatthe correspondence falls under two distinct headings: section (I)deals with the question of the steps which are still required to givevalid international effect to the position of Mandatory Powers;section-(II). is concerned with the question of the procedure whichwill be necessary to enable the Dominion Governments concernedlegally to exercise powers conferred upon them by the Mandate intheir own mandated territory.M.November 27, 1919.[1538 A]
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]1SECRET.CORRESPONDENCE AS TO MANDATES.I.Steps still required to give valid international effect to theposition of Mandatory Powers.41843No. 1.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNORS-GENERAL.COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.NEW ZEALAND.(Sent 11 p.m., July 18, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by Nos. 3, 5, and 17.]Confidential. Special Commission on Mandates appointed by Council ofprincipal Allied and Associated Governments, 26th June, with myself as chairman,has agreed upon following form of Mandate for such territories as may be governedin accordance with para. 6 of Article 22 Covenant of League of Nations, i.e., SouthiWest Africa and former German Pacific Colonies.  Begins : Preamble.Germany having by Article 119 of the Peace Treaty signed at Versailles on the28th June, 1919, renounced all her rights to X, the Principal Allied anc[ AssociatedPowers confer upon Y a mandate to govern X. Y accepts the mandate thusconferred upon it and will execute the same on behalf of the League of Nations andin accordance with the following provisions[Note. X equals mandated territory, Y equals Mandatory Power.]Article I.Y shall have full power of administration and legislation over X as an integralportion of Y, and may apply the laws of Y to X, subject to such local modificationsas circumstances may require. Y undertakes by all means in its power to promotethe material and moral well-being and the social progress of the inhabitants of X.Article II.Y, hereinafter referred to as the Mandatory Power, undertakes that the slave-trade shall be prohibited and that no forced labour shall be permitted, except foressential public works and services, and then only for adequate remuneration. Itfurther undertakes that the traffic in arms and ammunition shall be controlled inaccordance with the principles contained in the Brussels Act, 1890, or any Conven-tion amending the same. The supply of intoxicating spirits and beverages to thenatives of the territory shall be prohibited.Article III.iThe military training of the natives, otherwise than for purposes of internalpolice and the local defence of the territory, shall be prohibited. Furthermore, nomilitary or naval bases shall be established or fortifications erected in the territory,Wt.    - /153  40  f.o.P.   11/19  [1542] B
Article IV.Subject to the provisions of any local law for the maintenance of public orderand morals, the Mandatory&apos; Power guarantees in the territory freedom of conscienceand the free exercise of all forms of worship, and undertakes to allow allmissionaries the subjects or citizens of any member of the League of Nations, toenter into travel and reside in the territory for the purpose of prosecuting theircalling.Article V.The Mandatory Power shall make to the Council of the League of Nationsan annual report to the satisfaction of the Council containing full information withregard to the territory and indicating the measures taken to carry out the obligationsassumed under Articles I, II, III, IV.Article VI.The consent of the Council of the League of Nations is required for any modifi-cation of the terms of this Mandate. If any dispute whatever should arise betweenthe members of the League of Nations relating to the interpretation or theapplication of these provisions which cannot be settled by negotiations, this disputeshall be submitted to the Permanent Court of International Justice to be establishedby the League of Nations.  Ends.Form is being submitted by members of Commission to their respective Govern-ments and proposed to publish as soon as possible after it has been approved bythem. In the meantime, please inform your Ministers that form should be treatedas strictly confidential.[To Australia only: I am telegraphing form of Mandate direct to your PrimeMinister.][To Union of South Africa only: I have communicated form of Mandate toSmuts. Please communicate it to Hughes, Prime Minister, Commonwealth ofAustralia, for his confidential information, adding that I have also telegraphed itto Governor-General, Commonwealth of Australia. If he has already left, pleaseinform him by wireless.] Milner.41843No. 2.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNORS-GENERAL.COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.,UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.NEW ZEALAND.(Sent 4 p.m., July 18, 1919.)Telegram.(Paraphrase.)July 18, Secret. My telegram of to-day ;* confidential, form of Mandate.Insertion of Article establishing open door was pressed for by Japanese delegate onCommission, who made his agreement to the form subject to a reservation on thispoint. I have no intention of accepting his view, however, which was notsupported by any of the other delegates.[To Australia: Your Prime Minister is being informed.][To Union of South A frica: When acting on my other telegram, please informHughes, and add that I have telegraphed to same effect to Governor-GeneralCommonwealth.] Milner.
47030No. 3.New Zealand.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 12 noon, August 13, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by Nos. 4 and 9.]With reference to your telegram 18th July, Confidential,^ my Ministersenquire whether form of Mandate may now be made public both in New Zealandand Samoan Islands. Liverpool.47030No. 4.New Zealand.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 6 p.m., August 14, 1919.)Telegram.Your telegram 13th August.! Form of Mandate not having been yetapproved it is not yet possible to publish. Shall inform you as soon as it isapproved. Milner.47957 -. -No. 5.Union of South Africa.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 10.45 p.m., August 15, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 7.]August 15. Confidential With reference to your confidential telegram18th July*, relative to Mandate, my Ministers state that it is imperative that thenecessary powers whereby the administration of South-West Africa will be conferredon Union Government, should be in their hands by the 5th September at latest, andask therefore that you will expedite the passing of Mandate to enable them to layit before Parliament as early as possible. Buxton.47642No. 6.South Africa.The HIGH COMMISSIONER to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 4.43 a.m., August 16, 1919.). Telegram.[Answered by No. 8.]August 14. Am sending Prime Minister, Union, Memorandum with referenceto Caprivi&quot; Strip. Am asking that clause should be inserted in South-West TerritoryBill, which, if it be so finally decided, will enable strip to be actually part ofBechuanaland Protectorate or at least fully administered by it. This I thinkessential. Possibly you already settled question with Prime Minister, Union. Havenot yet seen him as am still in Bechuanaland Protectorate. Buxton.
47957No. 7.Union of South Africa.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.: (Sent 7.15 p.m., August 19, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 10.](Paraphrase.)With reference; to your Confidential&apos; telegram 15th August,^ I am sorryto say that I see no prospect of a Mandate being conferred by date mentioned,although I have been doing my utmost to expedite issue. However, I have consideredhow far it will be possible to meet your Ministers&apos; wishes. It has been definitelydecided on the one hand that Union of South Africa is to be Mandatory Power forSouth-West Africa. On the other hand the main lines of the Mandate have beensettled by sixth paragraph of Article 22 of Covenant of League of Nations. Whilethe actual form of Mandate which I have telegraphed to you cannot in thesecircumstances be published yet as a definite instrument, I see no objection to itssubstance being communicated to Union Parliament, emphasis being laid onprovision that Union will have full power of legislation and administration overSouth-West Africa as an integral portion of South Africa. I trust this will meetrequirements of case satisfactorily. Milner.47642No. 8.South Africa.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the HIGH COMMISSIONER.t(Sent 5.45 p.m., August &quot;20, 1919.)Telegram.August 20. Your telegram, 14th August, t Caprivi Strip. Mandate for aUGerman South-West Africa will certainly be given to Union. This was virtuallydecided at Paris months ago, and the matter cannot be reopened. If, as- a matter ofadministrative convenience, you wish strip to be attached to Bechuanaland Protec-torate and Union Government is willing, I can see no reason why this should notbe arranged locally between you and Union Government. Union would remain the&apos;mandatory, High Commissioner being in respect of this strip its agent. Milner..47957No. 9.Commonwealth of Australia: New Zealand.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 6 p.m., August 20, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 14.](Paraphrase.)With reference to my telegram [18th Julyi] [14th August $ ], Form of Mandate,.I am sorry to say that I see no prospect of any Mandate being conferred beforePeace Treaty discussed in [Commonwealth] [New Zealand] Parliament, althoughI have been doing my utmost to expedite issue. Your Ministers may wish to makesome statement to Parliament, however, on nature of Mandate, and I haveaccordingly considered question. On the one hand that [Commonwealth] [NewZealand] is to be Mandatory Power for [New Guinea] [Samoa] has been definitelydecided. On the other hand, main lines of Mandate have been settled by sixthparagraph of Article 22 of Covenant of League of Nations. While the actual form
of Mandate which I have telegraphed to you cannot in these circumstances bepublished yet as a definitive instrument, I can see no objection to substance beingcommunicated! to Parliament, emphasis being laid on provision that [Common-wealth] [New Zealand] will have full power of legislation and administration overterritory as an integral part of [Australia] [Dominion]. I trust that this will meetrequirements of case satisfactorily. Milner.49669-   No. 10.Union of South Africa.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 1.40 p.m., August 27, 1919.)Telegram. t[Answered by No. 11.]August 25. With reference to your telegram 19th August, * South-West AfricaMandate, Ministers enquire whether you have any objection to form of Mandate asshown in your telegram 18th July, Confidential,! being laid on the table of theHouse of Assembly as a draft only and not for publication.-Buxton.49669No. 11.Union of South Africa.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 1.20 p.m., August 30, 1919.)Telegram.&quot;Your telegram 25th August,! Form of Mandate.  No objection. Milner.49669No. 12.New Zealand.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 1.20 p.m., August 30, 1919.)Telegram.My telegram 20th August. $ Government of Union of South Africa haveproposed that form of Mandate shown my telegram 18th Julyt should be &quot; laid ontable of House of Assembly as a draft only and not for publication,&quot; and I havereplied that I have no objection. Milner.50126No. 13.Commonwealth of Australia.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 1.20 p.m., August 30, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 16.]August 30.  Have received following telegram from your Prime Minister: Begins: &quot; Mandates. Would be glad if Government would send me forthwithofficial telegram setting out exact terms of Mandates for Pacific Islands asagreed to by Council of Four.&quot; Ends.* No. 7. f No- 1- t No-10- 5 No. 9.[1542] C
Please inform him that I am sorry not to be able to add anything at presentto my telegram 20th August,* except that Government of Union of South Africahave proposed that form of Mandate shown my telegram 18th Julyf should be&quot;laid on table of House of Assembly as a draft only and not for publication,&quot; andthat I have replied that I have no objection. Milner.51897No. 14.New Zealand.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 1.14 p.m., September 6, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 15.]September 6. Urgent. Confidential. Your telegram 20th August, withregard to Mandate. Following is substance of telegram received from AdministratorSamoan Islands: Begins. Meeting of Faipules equivalent to Native Parliament has been fixedfor 10th September. Most essential I should be in position to discussMandate as various questions will undoubtedly arise which I could notanswer definitely unless permitted to give terms of Mandate. I have alreadyannounced in Samoa that German rule is at an end, that British rule hasbeen definitely established, and that New Zealand had been entrusted asmandatory for Samoa. Delay in publication of Mandate, however, createsimpression amongst natives and Germans that matter still open tofundamental revision. Population for some years have been led to believethat development of public affairs&quot; would coincide with Great Britaintaking over at the end of War. In native mind cessation of hostilitiesended the War, and they cannot understand why anticipated developmentnot commenced. Something specific is very necessary to meet adversecriticism already commenced.  Ends.In view of difficulties which Administrator is experiencing my Ministersconsider it important that the minds of the natives should be set at rest as regardsterms of Mandate, and strongly urges that permission be given to Administrator tocommunicate to the meeting of Faipules on 10th September, either the full text ofthe Mandate or a brief summary of its terms. Please telegraph immediatelywhether this may be done. Liverpool. a51897No. 15.New Zealand.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 12.10 p.m., September 8, 1919.)Telegram.Urgent. 8th September. Your telegram 6th September.^ No objection tosubstance of form of Mandate being communicated to Faipules on lines indicatedmy telegram 20th August.* Milner.
52632 i   \ I     TNo. 16.Commonwealth of Australia.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.    &quot; *(Received 7.45 p.m., September 10, 1919.)Telegram.Mandate for Pacific Islands. Your telegram 30th August,* Prime Ministerstrongly urges making available precise terms of Mandate as approved by Councilof Four. Ferguson.---53581No, 17.Commonwealth of Australia.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 2.15 p.m., September 13,1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 18.](Paraphrase.)With reference to your telegram 18th July,t regarding Mandates, followingmessage from Prime Minister : Begins: &quot; I strongly urge that paragraph 6 of earlier draft dealing with ultimateincorporation of mandated territory in certain events should be reinserted,and particularly the proviso that safeguards as to the military bases,fortifications, &amp;c, shall continue in the event of incorporation. This is ofspecial importance because similar proviso will then be enforceable inislands north of Equator which might otherwise be fortified at futuredate.I object strongly to the wording of draft of Article four which gives absoluteright of entry to any person, however objectionable he may be, who callshimself a missionary. Suggest substitution of words to following effect: Begins: &quot;Undertakes to allow all reasonable facilities to accreditedmissions as regards access of missionaries who are the subjectsof or citizens of any member of League of Nations.&quot;  Ends.Otherwise satisfactory.  Hughes. Ferguson.53481No. 18.Commonwealth! of Australia.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 11.30 a.m., September 20, 1919.)Telegram. *(Paraphrase.)Referring to your telegram 13th September,! please communicate following toyour Prime Minister: As Chairman of Mandates Commission I dEd my bestto obtain a form of Mandate which would be most favourable to Australia. Noobjection to the form finally adopted has been raised either by New Zealand or bySouth Africa, and I think that it would be unwise to reopen question now.As regards your first point, the Commission it was quite evident were notprepared to insert provision for incorporation of Islands in Mandate, and tocontinue to press for it would have been useless. The fact that no provision forincorporation is included in Mandate will not in the least prohibit an appeal to theLeague of Nations to allow such incorporation if there is a bond fide demand on the
part of natives in future, and League would be pretty certain if agreeing to it toinsist that reservation as to fortifications be maintained.As regards your second point, your proposal seems to me to be really lessfavourable to Australia than article adopted by Commission. Expression &quot; allreasonable facilities &quot; would make it possible to appeal to League whenever it wasconsidered that reasonable facilities had been withheld. Further I do not agreethat absolute right of entry is given to persons who are not bond fide missionariesor to whom legitimate objection can be taken. The rights conferred are conferredon missionaries as such, and further are &quot; subject to the provisions of any local lawfor the maintenance of public order and morals.&quot; It seems to me most undesirablethat any narrow interpretation should be placed upon this proviso; the powers whichyou will possess under it are very wide. Milner.56654No. 19.Commonwealth of Australia.The PRIME MINISTER of the COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA toMr. LLOYD GEORGE, PRIME MINISTER of the UNITED KINGDOM.(Received September 26, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 21.]Secret and confidential. Re Mandates. I am greatly disturbed by period ofdelay in official confirmation of terms. In present situation in Pacific OceanIslands, where Japan is and has been long working to oust Empire and Australianshipping from Pacific Ocean, and to secure trade for herself, I am powerless to acttill the Mandate has been approved officially. Utmost expedition necessary; pleasedo not cease to urge on. Hughes.58842No. 20.Commonwealth of Australia.The PRIME MINISTER to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 4.42 p.m., October 13, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 21.]October 13. Secret. Mandates. Now that Peace has been formally ratified,,surely I may expect terms of Mandate to be ratified by Allied Council withoutdelay. Matter of greatest importance to us, as we go to an election forthwith.Early reply requested. Hughes.58951No. 21.Commonwealth of Australia.The PRIME MINISTER of the UNITED KINGDOM to the PRIMEMINISTER of the COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.(Sent 7 p.m., October 15, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 23.]October 15. Secret^ Your telegram of 26th September, your telegram 13thOctober,^ Mandates. I quite agree that issue should be expedited in every waypossible, and will continue to do my best to help.   You will remember, of course,.
that Mandates have to be submitted to Council of League of Nations under Article 22of Treaty and that Council not yet formally constituted and cannot be constituteduntil after the formal ratification of the Treaty of Peace. Pending approval byCouncil of form of Mandates and their issue, I do not think you can do more thancarry on administration of territories to be mandated to Australia in accordancewith the terms of the draft telegraphed to you by Milner on 18th July,* which mustbe regarded as provisionally authoritative. Should be grateful if you would let meknow exactly what damages Australian interests are suffering through delay, asthis information may help us to put pressure on other members Council LeagueNations to approve Mandate immediately.-Lloyd George.63068No. 22.Union of South Africa.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OP STATE.(Received 7.25 a.m., November 4, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 24.](Paraphrase.)November 3. Can you inform me when the Mandate is likely to be completedfor South West African Territory, so that the Union Government can proceeddefinitely to act as mandatories, and that ordinary civil law can supersede martiallaw? In South-West Africa my experience conclusively showed that - to allconcerned the present state of affairs is highly inconvenient, and that the soonerit is brought to an end the better for everyone. This is also the view of my PrimeMinister. Buxton.64480&apos; No. 23.Commonwealth of Australia.The PRIME MINISTER of the COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIAto the PRIME MINISTER of the UNITED KINGDOM.(Received November 6, 1919.)Telegram.To Mr. Lloyd George, Prime Minister, London.Following from Prime Minister. Begins: Mandates. Your telegram.!Commonwealth of Australia regards delay in formal approval of our Mandateover Pacific Ocean with apprehension. Urgent question of administrationinvolved. There is also widespread general disappointment at long delay anddoubts being expressed freely as to whether the principles and decision embodiedin Treaty of Peace are ever to be given effect to. In view of the state of publicopinion, and use of which the disloyal and pro-German elements are making ofthis, I most strongly and earnestly urge immediate settlement. Ends. Hughes.63068No. 24.Union of South Africa.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 6.53 p.m., November 10, 1919.)Telegram.(Paraphrase.)November 10. W7ith reference to your telegram 3rd November,! I quite agreethat issue of Mandate should be expedited in every way possible, but exactly when** No. 1. f No. 21. t No. 22.[1542] D
it will be completed it is impossible to say. You will remember that under Article 22of Treaty, Mandates have to be submitted to Council of League of Nations, andthat Council hot yet formally constituted and cannot until after formal ratificationTreaty of Peace be constituted. Pending Council&apos;s approval of form of Mandatesand their issue, I think Government of Union of South Africa can do nothing morethan carry on administration of South West Africa in accordance with terms ofdraft, which must be regarded as provisionally authoritative, telegraphed to youon 18th July.* Milner.65570No. 25.Commonwealth of Australia.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 10.40 a.m., November 15, 1919.)Telegram.[Answered by No. 26.](Paraphrase.)Referring to my telegram of 10th September, t my Prime Minister sendsfollowing: Begins : Secret. Mandates. No answer yet received to my previous urgent tele-&apos;gram. Over six months have passed since the Council of Four agreed tothe Mandate for Pacific Islands, and nearly six months since the Treatyof Peace containing basic terms of each class of&apos; Mandate was signed, yetSupreme Council&apos;s approval has not been, given. This is most unfortunate,and causes my Government great embarrassment, and is calculated tocreate serious situation. The Japanese are working assiduously to securetrade of islands; they are endeavouring to acquire titles to land andminerals and oil rights, and we can do nothing failing formal appointmentas mandatory. I have sent Prime Minister urgent telegram in reply to onefrom him setting out urgency of settlement.Position of Government in view of financial, economic, and general conditions^ including Bolshevism and Sinn Fein, is sufficiently difficult in any case.We are in the midst of an election campaign; it is surely not too much toask that this question of Mandate, which ought to have been settled longago, should be dealt with at once, very urgent. Hughes. End of PrimeMinisters message.Ferguson.65570No. 26.Commonwealth of Australia.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 10.10 p.m., November 19, 1919.)Telegram.(Paraphrase.)November 19. Your telegram,^ received 15th November. Following messagefor your Prime Minister : Begins: &quot; Mandates. Please refer to Prime Minister&apos;s message to yon15th October,^ in which he pointed out that Council of League to whichMandates have to be submitted cannot be constituted till formal ratifica-tion. This depends on deposit, which has not been found possible yet (seeconcluding words of Treaty). It is not our fault that, owing to unfortunateaction of American Senate, constitution of Council of League of NationsNo. l.t No. 16.X No. 25.S No. 21.
has been so long delayed and appears.now altogether in jeopardy. I amsincerely sorry for the embarrassment which the delay causes you, but Ican assure you that to us, too, it is intolerably embarrassing in many ways,and that, speaking for myself, I have left no stone unturned to put an end.to it. It seems to me just possible that, in view of long vista of uncertaintycaused by American situation, the four other Principal Allied and Asso-ciated Powers may be induced to go ahead by themselves and issueMandates without waiting for&apos; constitution of League, leaving it toAmerica to adhere if and when it suits her. This would not be altogethersatisfactory, but would be better than present position. Any way, as a lastresort I am trying it. Will let you know at once if effort meets with anysuccess. Milner.&quot;
SECRET.48978No. 1.New Zealand.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 8.45 a.m., August 23, 1919.)[Answered by No. 2.]Telegram.Urgent. Legal Advisers of my Government will be glad to receive definiteinformation as to legal position of Samoan Islands. Presumed to be Britishprotectorate, not British possession, and that legislative authority will be conferredon New Zealand Parliament. Is Order in Council to be issued under ForeignJurisdiction Act conferring authority on New Zealand Parliament, or will authoritybe conferred by Imperial Act ? At what date will new status of Samoan Islandscommence?    Please telegraph reply. Liverpool.48978No&quot;. 2.New Zealand.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 6.5 p.m., August 26, 1919.)[Answered by No. 3.]Telegram.August 26. Urgent. Your telegram of August 23rd.* Am advised thatSamoan Islands will not be British possession, nor will they strictly be Britishprotectorate. Finance Act, 1919, for purposes of Imperial Preference, distin-guishes between territory which &quot;becomes under His Majesty&apos;s protection&quot; andterritory which &quot; is a territory in respect of which a mandate of the League ofNations is exercised by the Government of any part of His Majesty&apos;s Dominions.&quot;His Majesty will, however, undoubtedly have jurisdiction within meaning ofForeign Jurisdiction Act, and it has been assumed as regards territory in respectof which Mandate will be conferred on this country that necessary authority can begiven by Order in Council under that Act. There seems to be no reason whynecessary authority should not be given in respect of Samoan Islands by such Order.Telegraph whether your Ministers concur in this view. If so, you will doubtlesstelegraph to me in due course any observations which they may desire to offer ondrafting of Order. As to date when Mandate will be operative, I can at present addnothing to my cipher telegram 20th August.t Milner.* No. 1.Wt.      -/153  40  F.O.p.  11/19  [1538]t See No. 9 in Section I.bCORRESPONDENCE AS TO ISSUE OF MANDATES.n.Procedure necessary to enable Dominion Governments legallyto exercise powers conferred upon them by the Mandatein their own mandated territory.
51580No. 3.New Zealand.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 6.25 p.m., September 4, 1919.)Telegram.Your telegram 26th August.*   My Ministers approve issue Order in Councilunder Foreign Jurisdiction Act, conferring jurisdiction on New Zealand Parlia-ment over Samoa, and suggest Order to following effect: Recite surrender Samoa byGermany and that by Mandate received from League of Nations His Majesty hasin right of his Dominion of New Zealand acquired full jurisdiction as mandatory ofLeague to govern territory as if part of His Majesty&apos;s dominions, subject only,to conditions of Mandate.    Title, Western Samoa Order in Council.    Limits ofOrder, Islands of Upolu and Savaii, in South Pacific, together with islands adjacentthereto situated between thirteenth and fourteenth degrees of south latitude andone hundred and seventy-first and one hundred and seventy-third degrees longitudewest of Greenwich.    To be known as territory of Western Samoa, and not to beincluded within limits of Pacific Order in Council.    New Zealand Parliamentempowered exercise or make provision for exercise on behalf Majesty in territoryof all jurisdiction acquired by Majesty, and for this purpose to make or authoriseto be made laws for peace,,, order, good government, as fully as if territory partof New Zealand.    In exercise of authority so committed Parliament may conferon any courts either in Samoa or New Zealand jurisdiction necessary for administra-tion of justice, and may confer legislative, executive, judicial powers in respectterritory on such authority or authorities as Parliament thinks fit.    Powers to beexercised in accordance with Mandate for the time being in force.  Majesty&apos;mayrevoke or amend Order.   Order to come into operation on date thereof.   This formof draft order is suggested by Sir John Salmond, Solicitor-General of New Zealand. Liverpool.53567No. 4.New Zealand.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 8.40 a.m., September 16, 1919.)[Answered by No. 5.]Telegram.As New Zealand Parliamentary Session will be very short, it is essential thatlegislation for government of Samoan Islands should be introduced without delay.Draft Bill is now ready. Is there any objection to legislation being submitted toNew Zealand Parliament in anticipation of ratification of Treaty and issue ofImperial Order in Council mentioned in your telegram 26th August ?t-Liverpool.53567 &quot;-&quot;No. 5..New Zealand.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 4.45 p.m., September 18, 1919.)[Answered by No. 7.]Telegram.18th September. Urgent. Your telegram 16th September,! Samoa. , It isnot clear how New Zealand Parliament can legislate for government of islands inadvance of proposed Order in Council, which cannot be issued until Mandate
oformally conferred and accepted. Suggest Bill should be confined to acceptance ofMandate when formally conferred. This should not give rise to any administrativeor legal inconvenience, as it would be possible to insert in proposed Order in Councilany provisions that your Government may desire giving them power to makeprovision for interim government of islands pending legislation by New Zealandk Parliament so as to cover any possible period between commencement of Order and&quot; meeting of New Zealand Parliament if not then in session. Until issue of Orderin Council administration of islands could continue to be provided for by means ofProclamations issued by local administrator, which by the Imperial Indemnity Act,when passed, are to be validated and kept alive unless or until superseded by otherprovision by the new legislative authority.-Milner.54382No. 6.Union of South Africa.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 8.30 p.m., September 19, 1919.)Telegram.September 19. I have assented to Treaty of Peace, and South West AfricaMandate Bill. It is a short provisional measure expiring on 1st July, 1920, unlessextended by resolution of both Houses. It gives the. Governor-General in Councilwide legislative and administrative powers, but protects native reserves. Amsending text by mail. Smuts in House of Assembly gave pledge that if Mandate inany material respect went beyond or deviated from Article XXII of Treaty, theUnion Government would reserve acceptance till Parliament had been consulted. Buxton.Note : The Text of the A ct is as follows: No. 49, 1919.&quot; ACT for carrying into effect, in so far as concerns the Union of South Africa,the Treaty of Peace between His Majesty the King and certain other Powers ;and for carrying into effect any Mandate issued in pursuance of the Treaty tothe Union of South Africa with reference to the territory of South-WestAfrica, lately under the Sovereignty of Germany.Whereas at Versailles on the 28th day of June, 1919, a Treaty of Peace, a copy Preamble. ,of which has been laid before Parliament, was signed on behalf of His Majesty,and it is expedient that the Governor-General should have power to do all such   1things as may be proper and expedient for giving effect in so far as concerns theUnion to the Treaty, or to any Mandate issued in pursuance of the Treaty withreference to the territory of South-West Africa:Be it enacted by the King&apos;s Most Excellent Majesty, the Senate and the Houseof Assembly of the LTnion of South Africa as follows: 1. The Governor-General may make such appointments, establish such offices, Power togivaissue such proclamations and regulations and do such things as appear to him tobe necessary for giving effect, so far as concerns the Union, to any of the provisions and Southof the said Treaty or to any Mandate issued in pursuance of the Treaty to the Union Mandate&quot;04with reference to the territory of South-West Africa, lately under the sovereigntyof Germany, and any act of the Governor-General in that behalf shall be lawfulnotwithstanding any provision to the contrary in &amp;ny law contained.2. Subject to the provisions of section four of this Act, the Governor-General Laws formay by proclamation at any time  2 &apos;we&apos;b(a.) Repeal, alter, amend or modify any laws in force within the said territoryincluding such proclamations as have been or may be promulgated duringthe military occupation thereof;(b.) Make new laws applicable to the said territory;(c.) Delegate his authority in this behalf to such officer in the said territoryas he may designate to act under his instructions.
Penalties,Land Settle-ment.Alienation ofState rightaor nativeaeserves.Duration a  Aot,Short title3. Any proclamation or regulation made under this Act may provide for theimposition of penalties in respect of breaches of the provisions thereof, and shall be-laid before Parliament as soon as may be.4. (1.) It shall be lawful for the Governor-General by proclamation to apply to-the said territory, with such modifications as he may deem necessary having regardto the conditions obtaining therein, the provisions of all or any of the following lawsto wit: the Land Settlement Act, 1912, the Land Settlement Act Amendment Act,1917, the Crown Land Disposal Ordinance, 1903, of the Transvaal, and the CrownLand Disposal Amendment Ordinance, 1906, of the Transvaal.(2.) Save for the provisions of sub-section (1) of this section, no grant of anytitle, right or interest in State land or minerals within the said territory or of anyright or interest in or over the territorial waters thereof shall be made, and notrading or other concessions shall be granted without the authority of Parliament.(3.) No land within the said territory now or hereafter set apart as a reservefor natives or coloured persons shall be alienated save under the authority ofParliament, provided that nothing in this section contained shall be deemed toprohibit the Governor-General, in respect of land contained in any such reserve, togrant individual title to any person lawfully occupying and entitled to such land.5. The provisions of this Act shall cease to have effect on the first day of July,nineteen hundred and twenty, provided, however, that by resolution of both Housesof Parliament the operation of such provisions may be extended for any periodmentioned in such resolution.6. This Act may be cited as .the Treaty of Peace and South-West AfricaMandate Act, 1919.56348No. 7.New Zealand.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 6.50 am. September 30, 1919.)Telegram.Your telegram of the 18th September,^ Samoa. A Bill will be immediatelyintroduced into New Zealand for the acceptance of any Mandate which may beconferred for the government of Samoan Islands. Government of New Zealanddesires the Order in Council under the Foreign Jurisdiction Act to provide that fulljurisdiction over Sainoan Islands may be exercised by the Governor-General inCouncil till the New Zealand Parliament makes other provision for that purpose. Liverpool.60509No. 8.Union of South Africa.The SECRETARY OF STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Sent 1.40 p.m. November 8, 1919.)[Answered by No. 9.]Telegram.(Paraphrase.)Private and Personal. To a question asked in the House of Commons whetherin any legislation promoted by Parliament of New Zealand affecting Samoa enact-ments will be subject to disallowance an answer was returned that it is not under-stood that legislation to be passed by Parliament of New Zealand in exercise of itsauthority over Samoa will be subject to disallowance. Question recently raised byNew Zealand how legislative authority in respect of Samoa could be conferred onNew Zealand Parliament. I.replied that as His Majesty would undoubtedly havejurisdiction within meaning of Foreign Jurisdiction Act necessary authority couldbe conferred by Order in Council under that Act.  Ministers thereupon approved
issue of Order which, though not finally settled in form, will recite that by MandateHis Majesty in right of his Dominion of New Zealand has full jurisdiction asMandatory of territory as though part of His. Majesty&apos;s dominions subject only toconditions of Mandate and empower Parliament of New Zealand.to exercise ormake provision for exercise on His Majesty&apos;s behalf in territory of all jurisdictionacquired by His Majesty and to make or authorise to be made for this purpose lawsfor peace, order, and good government as fully as though territory were part ofNew Zealand. . Order will be drawn so as not to provide for power of disallowance,which explains answer in House of Commons. I see, however, that in dealing withMandate Bill*, Smuts seemed to hold the view that the Parliament of the Union ofSouth Africa had power already to legislate for South-West Africa, and the Speakergave opinion to this effect. This opinion I do not understand, especially as referenceto South African precedents appears to ignore Letters Patent passed to enable theauthority of the Cape to be extended.In view of political situation no doubt General Smuts&apos; position is difficult, butterritory cannot by Peace Treaty or League of Nations be added to dominions ofthe Crown so as to become ipso facto an integral portion of any British Possession.To enable Legislature of such Possession to legislate for such territory some formalaction by Crown necessary. Mere assent by Crown wouldxnot validate an enact-ment by such Legislature purporting to provide for government of territory not yetwithin its territorial jurisdiction if such enactment were ultra vires. I consider aseparate formal instrument by the Crown (such as the Order in Council accepted byNew Zealand) the necessary and proper means of enabling the Union of SouthAfrica to carry out Mandate since a Mandate to the Union is equivalent to aMandate to His Majesty in right of his Dominion of the Union of South Africa.If Union proceed without proper legal authority I fear that their acts may besuccessfully questioned later in the Courts. This, of course, is a matter for GeneralSmuts to consider, but for this reason and also for the sake of uniformity it seemsdesirable that His Majesty should make use of existing machinery and pass anOrder in Council as for Samoa for South-West Africa. Owing to the delicacy ofGeneral Smuts&apos; position in the matter I have not raised this question officially, butif you think desirable please discuss with him, or, if not, advise in what form youthink question should be raised.Your Government, you will remember, had contemplated that an Act to validateproceedings in South-West Africa- during military occupation should be passed byImperial Parliament (see your despatch of 6th December, 1918, No. 906). This willbe done by Imperial Indemnity Bill now under consideration which provides interalia as follows:Begins : &quot;All laws, ordinances, proclamations, and other legislative acts made,issued, or done by the authority for the time being administering any terri-tory in the military occupation of any of His Majesty&apos;s forces during thepresent War for the peace, order, or good government of such territoryshall be deemed to be and always to have been valid and of full effect bothduring such occupation and after the determination thereof until repealedor superseded by such lawfully constituted legislative authority as mayhereafter be established for that territory notwithstanding that any suchlegislative act may have repealed or been inconsistent with the lawpreviously in force in such territory.  Ends.&quot; Milner.65380No. 9.Union of South Africa.The GOVERNOR-GENERAL to the SECRETARY OF STATE.(Received 4.6 p.m. November 13, 191.9.)Telegram.November 13.  Private and Personal,With reference to your telegram Private and Personal of 8th November,! untilto-day my Prime Minister was away and therefore could not discuss the questionwith me before.  I thought it well to show him unofficially your telegram.  He is[1538]C
considering it carefully, and will give me his observations. As to the necessity ofan Order in Council, he takes a somewhat different view, and asks me to expressvery strongly the hope that, as regards Samoa, Order in Council will not be issueduntil you have,had opportunity of considering his views; issue would prejudice theposition.-Buxton.66520No-. 10.Union of South Africa.SECRETARY OE STATE to the GOVERNOR-GENERAL.(Received 2.35 a.m., November 19, 1919.)Telegram.(Paraphrase.)(Private and Personal.)  November 15.My telegram of November 13th.*  Following from Prime Minister: Begins: &quot; I wish to make following observations on private and personal messagefrom Secretary of State which Governor-General has shown me unofficiallyin regard to proposed Order in Council to confer legislative jurisdictionover Samoa on New Zealand.&quot; That uniformity is desirable I agree, and I made every effort beforeI left London in July last to secure conference bejween Dominion represen-tatives, Colonial Office, and Crown lawyers to settle uniform manner ofdealing with Treaty of Peace and question of mandates. Sudden depar-ture to their countries of Dominion Ministers prevented this idea beingcarried out, and I had to follow my own advice in dealing with mandatequestion in Parliament of the Union of South Africa.&quot; Nationalist opposition challenged me both on authority of Union tolegislate for South West Africa and also on question of competence of Unionto deal with Peace Treaty. On former point I explained that His Majestywas competent through Royal prerogative to extend legislative jurisdictionof Union of South Africa; that in this case His Majesty had tacitly done soas [ ? group omitted] of the Great Powers who conferred the mandate overSouth West Africa on Union of South Africa. His Majesty&apos;s act in thisregard was full, free, and complete expression of his will and sufficient assuch to confer all consequential or implied authority on Union.&quot; In his formal ruling the Speaker also held in substance that under thecircumstances mandate had effect analogous to Orders in Council which hadformerly extended jurisdiction in older Colonial precedents and was suffi-cient to confer legislative jurisdiction on Parliament of Union of SouthAfrica.&quot; My own view is that King&apos;s (? one group omitted) in exercising Royalprerogative is not of matter of mere legal form under an Order in Council,but one of substance, and substantially he has declared his will court shouldgo behind that act [sic].&quot;I go further, however, and question whether proposed Order inCouncil is correct procedure. Mandate over Samoa is given not to UnitedKingdom, but to New Zealand; that is to say, to His Majesty not in his. British Government, but in his Dominion Government. King in his BritishGovernment or Privy Council is not concerned, therefore, and British Orderin Council is beside the point. It would only apply where effect is to begiven to mandate like German East Africa, which was conferred on HisMajesty in his British Government, and it is not clear that Foreign Juris-diction Act applies even there. Any Act purporting to confer jurisdictionover mandated territories like South West Africa or Samoa must emanatefrom His Majesty in his Dominion Government, on whom alone mandatewas conferred, and who has, I assume, same prerogative to extend jurisdic-tion as King in his British Government. If any formal act is necessary thepurpose of its form will have to be carefully settled, and to follow precedentstaken from Constitutional phase which has passed away will not do. Oldprecedents do not apply to entirely new Constitutional situation which has
arisen. Signature by King&apos;s Dominion Ministers of Peace Treaty recogniseDominions as equal members of League of Nations, and conferment of man-dates on them by League of Nations or Great Powers mark new departurein Constitutional position in Empire.&quot; In regard to power of veto, this is practically admitted, but matter isvery much larger than that, and I strongly deprecate isolated action on oldlines in case of Samoa. Thereby constitutional controversies would be setgoing in various Dominions, and intervention of courts would be invited.British Empire&apos;s future demands that Dominion status which follows fromabove innovations should be put on regular constitutional basis, and actionsuch as is now proposed in Order in Council might prejudice position.&quot;I would ask, in view of great constitutional importance of pointsinvolved, for careful consideration of whole question by War Cabinet, andin case my views are not approved I would ask that until whole matter hasbeen gone into and settled at next Imperial Conference action on the SamoaOrder in Council be deferred.&quot;Question will arise when mandates in their final form as given byGreat Powers and approved by Council of League of. Nations reachDominions and have to be accepted in a form which will have to be carefullysettled so as to be in accord with new constitutional position of Dominions.There is no special urgency, therefore, in settling issue raised by NewZealand. In the meantime Dominions could, if necessary, act in mandatedterritories on basis of military occupation, as heretofore, apart from man-dates.&quot; Ends. Buxton.o

</content>
</cab>
