<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/94/0 images: 300-305</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property of &apos;3His Britannic Majesty^ Government, IJJ)N\ fl.H.1-2.^g^L^^fi^and-urfl by the Minister of Health on the proposedlnoree.se of cash benefits and contributions.As a result of the depreciation of money, the cash benefitsunder the National Health Insurance Acts which have not beenincreased since the original Act came into operation in 1912, arenow wholly inadequate.     If these benefits were increased inproportion to the rise in the cost of living and the averageincrease, in the wages of the insured population, they wouldrequire to be doubled.     But in view of the liability which suchan increase would impose on the Exchequer and having regard alsoto the unemployment insurance contributions which, as a result: of the proposed extension of unemployment insurance, will beposal, payable in respect of some ten million insured persons hithertoinsured against sickness only, I propose to increase sicknessbenefit for men and women by 5/-, disablement benefit by 2/6 andmaternity benefit by lo/^.&apos;   These.proposals would, I believe, begenerally accepted, by Approved Societies and the increase in thecontributions of employers and workers-&apos; which they involve wouldnot be likely.to meet with any serious opposition in Parliament-Sricj. The need for amending legislation is urgent. , ApprovedSocieties which for months have been restive have now becomeclamorous.   Their members demand that the cash benefits shallbear a closer relation to the cost of living, and their officialsand staffs are insistently demanding the living wage which onlyan increased, administration allowance will provide.     In view ofthe inter-rel tion of old age pensions, unemployment insurance-      and health insurance,,, I have withstood this pressure as long aspossible in spite of most urgent appeals from representatives ofinsured persons and their societies.    For many weeks the financial/questions
questions involved have been before the Treasury] and while, inview of the complications inseparable from the concurrent demands,on the one hand of Approved Societies and doctors, and on theother hand of other social services, I have refrained frompressing for an earlier pronouncement, the time has now arrivedwhen I am compelled to ask the Cabinet to sanction the immediateintroduction of a Bill embodying these proposals.Even if immediate legislation is obtained for the revisionof cash benefits and contributions, some time must elapse beforethe changes can take effect.    The contributions cannot beincreased -except from the beginning of a half year (January orJuly).    Before that half-year begins millions of contributioncards have to be printed, distributed to Approved Societiesthroughout the country and distributed by them to their members:dies for new stamps have to be cut and millions of stamps haveto be printed and distributed to looal post offices for sale tothe public.    T,;is is a work of months.   At the best the schemecannot be brought into/ operation before 1st July, 1920, whiledelay lii passing the Bill will delay it further till January 1921,If these urgently needed amendments are delayed until January, 1921.the growing unrest among insured persons and the staffs ofApproved Societies will be gravely prejudicial to the working of,National Health Insurance: and unless a Bill oan be passed beforethe end of February at the latest, a critical situation will becreated.Dotailsi of Proposals ,The details of my proposals arc as followsSickness Benefit (Men)   to be increased from 10/- to 15/- a week,&quot; &quot;   (Women)   &quot;   &quot; &quot;        &quot;   7/6   to 12/6 &quot;   &quot;Disablement &quot; (Men &amp; Women)&quot;&apos; .  &quot;.        &quot;   5/-   to 7/6   &quot;   &quot;Maternity Benefit.   As to this there are alternative schemes..Under one plan it is proposed, in view of the new health/services
services contemplated by the Ministry, to retain the cash Jbenefit at 30/-.   Another proposal is to raise the cashbenefit to 40/-,   In a memorandum (CP.211) prepared by theChancellor of the Exchequer a maternity benefit of 50/-, is,however, contemplated..dical Benefit (including drugs)    The contribution to thisbenefit out of Insurance funds is at.present 6&apos;/6d. per insuredperson per year.     It is proposed to increase this to 9/6., themaximum amount available if the weekly contribution is not tobe increased by more than 3d.     I am advised that it would notbe practicable to increase the weekly contributions by more thanthis amount simultaneously with the extension of unemploymentInsurance to some ten million persons hitherto Insured againstsickness only..,   The total cost of medical benefit (includingdrugs) at&apos;present is lo/9d., and the extra Exchequer contributiontowards meeting this is. 4/3d.    The extra Exchequer contributionwas originally limited to the 2/6d. conceded by the GovernmentIn.1912, but it has since been increased by mileage grants andwar bonus,;, the whole cost of which has fallen upon public funds.The doctors are novv asking for 13/6d exclusive of mileage;   thelatter will cost approximately  350,000 for Great Britain, whichis ilie equivalent of an addition of 6d.. to whatever is fixed asthe flat.rate capitation payment..  Drugs are estimated to cost2/6d. per insured person..    On the basis of this demand, the totalcost of medical benefit, including mileage and drugs , would bo16/6d.     I do not think, however, that there is any need toconcede the doctors1 demands in.full.    A capitation rate of10/- (excluding mileage) would, in my opinion, secure the /continuance of the panel system; and I am bound to admit thatin many oases this would represent the value of the services asactually rendered now.     But while the negotiations have made -it clear that a capitation rate of 10/- might be accepted ,grudgingly by the majority of insurance practitioners, we should,I believe, lose many good men, and I think it would ho unwise toconcede the bare minimum required to prevent a strike.   I haveto remember also thafe practice costs have greatly increased, the:* . /demands
demands of many demobilised and discharged men for medical w 1attendance represent a material a del it Ion to the medical man1 saverage work, and I intend under the conditions of the nowRegulations to exact a much better standard of service from allthe Insurance practitionerso    The success of the Ministry ofHealth depends above all upon the willing co-operation of themedical profession, and I am satisfied that their goodwill, whichIs so ess ential, cannot be secured except by conceding a figure whichthe moderate men will regard as fair.     I therefore ask, for theauthority of the Cabinet to offer a rate-of.il/6d., which withmileage is equivalent to 12/-., or l/6d, more than the bareminimum for which I believe the continua oo of the service canbe secured.On this basis the total cost of medical benefit asfrom January will be 14/6 d., instead of 10/9d. at present, towardswhich the Insurance funds will contribute 9/6d.   The extraExchequer contribution will then be 5/- instead of 4/3d. as atpresent.   This means that of the total increase of 3/9d., insurancefunds will contribute 3/- and the Exchequer only 9d.   I oughtto add that it is an essential part of the bargain that the newrate should take effect from the beginning of 1920.[Sanatorium Benefit,     It is proposed to abolish this benefit andIto throw upon local authorities and the Exchequer the sameresponsibilities in respect of the insured as arc undertakenat present in respect of the uninsured.    The estimates of.cost hcreunder given assume an equal distribution of the transrferred charge between local and central funds.jjJBgnsejs of Administration of Approved Societies.      It is proposedto increase the allowance&apos;under this head from 3/5d to 4/6 perannum in respect of each insured person.iSStributions.     It Is proposed to increase the rates by 3d. a weekfor both men and women. 2d extra being paid by the employerand id by the worker.   The rates will then be as follows:-
Employer	5d	instead	of	3dWorker	5d	11 &apos;i	ft	4d				&quot;7T&quot;Employer	5d	ii	it	3dW orker	4d	ti	i?	3d	9d	ii	it	6dTho scheme assumes that corresponding unemployment benefits-(15/- for men and 12/6d for women) will be provided by thescheme which the Ministry of Labour is preparing.    A memorandumhas already been submitted showing the difficulties which willarise if the unemployment benefit be fixed at more than 18/* aweek (men) or 12/6 (women).The additional cost to the Exchequer.The cost of the changes /must be considered in connection withthe negotiations now in progress with the doctors,    If the newrate is limited to 10/-*, tho bare minimum which will secure thecontinuance of the present service, tho total cost of medicalbenefit including mileage and drugs will bo 13/-, and thoadditional cost to the Exchequer of the complete scheme will bo(i) If maternity benefit be retained at 30/-  1,550,000,(ii) &quot; &quot; &quot;        &quot; increased to  2,  1,725,000(lii)   &quot;         &quot;            &quot;        &quot;        &quot;          &quot;  2.10s.    2,400,000Under (ii) and (iii) the redemption of the reserve values willalso be prolonged by five years, i.e. to 30-35 years instead ofthe present estimated period of 25 -30 years; were it not for this,the additional: cost to the Exchequer under either of those schemeswould be increased by a further  500,000.If, however, as I propose, the new capitation rate is 12/*,including mileage, the lowest figure which will secure the goodwillof the medical profession, the Exchequer liability will boincreased by  1,050,000.    Assuming that maternity benefit isincreased as I propose to  2 and not to 50/-, the additional costto the exchequer of the complete scheme will thus bo  2,775,000.
Ministry of Health. C.ADDIS0N.5,12.19.Maternity Benefit.&apos;       - .:V-:&apos; -&apos;&apos;-The view of my advisers is that if this benefit must be... -increased it need not be brought up to more than 40/-.   Thereis no pronounced demand for material increase of th s cashbenefit; the public expectation seems rather for improvedhealth services in.respot of pregnancy and child-birth.   Theadditional cost of  700,000 to public funds involved by anincrease of the benefit-to 50&apos;/-( 1,200,000 if the redemptionperiod for reserve values be not extended) is therefore notregarded as essential.

</content>
</cab>
