<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/278/0 images: 55-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
o 4*HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)E C R E T. Lp.  168 (58).COPY NO.f3CABINET. PENSIONS FOR MEMBERS&apos;OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.As I promised in my memorandum of the 8th July (CP. 165 (38)) I circulate a draft Bill for consideration by my colleagues.(Intd.) J.S,easury Chambers^, S.W.I., 12th July, 1938.
DRAFTOE AB  I  L  to provide  for the making,   in  certain  cases,  of a.d. 1938. grants to, and to the widows of, persons who have been Members of the House Of Commons; and for purposes connected with the matter aforesaid.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : 1. (1) For the purpose of enabling grants to be The House made to, and to the widows of, persons who have been of Commons Members of the House of Commons, there shall be Men\bers constituted a fund, to be called the House of Commons   un &apos;10 Members Fund (hereafter in this Act referred to as &quot; the fund &quot;).v(2) The fund shall be administered by the trustees thereof, who shall, subject to the provisions of the First Schedule. to this Act, make out of the fund15 such periodical or other payments to such persons, being persons who have, after the passing of this Act, been members of the House of Commons or the widows of such persons, as the trustees may, having regard to the financial circumstances of the persons to whom the20 payments are made, and to the resources and commit-ments of the fund, in their discretion think fit.(3) The officer responsible for the payment of the salaries of Members of the House of Commons shall deduce137-4A
A.D. 1938. from each payment thereof a sum calculated at the rate of twelve pounds per annum and shall, pay the amount so deducted into the fund, and, for the purposes of income tax, the salary of any such Member shall be treated as reduced by the amount of any such deduction. 5The reference in this subsection to the salaries of Members of the House of Commons shall be construed as including a reference to so much of (a) any salary or pension under the Ministers of theCrown Act, 1937; or 10(b) the salary of the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster or of a Law Officer of the Crown, not being, in either case, a person to whom a salary is payable under the said Act; or(c) the salary of an Officer of the House of Commons 15or an Officer of His Majesty&apos;s Household,as relates to any period during which the person to whom the salary or pension is payable is a Member of the House of Commons; and the requirement in this subsection that a deduction shall be made from 20 each payment of -salary shall, in relation to a Member who does not draw his salary, be construed as a requirement that, on each occasion when a payment of salary would have been made if the Member had drawn his salary, a sum equal to the deduction which 25 would have been made shall be set aside; and any sum so set aside shall be dealt with as if it were a sum so deducted.(4) The trustees of the fund shall be entitled to exemption from income tax in respect of all income 30 derived from the fund or any investment thereof, and any claim to exemption under this subsection shaU be made, and any such claim shall be allowed, in the same manner as in the case of the exemption allowed under8&amp;9Geo.5. subsection (5) of section thirty-nine of the Income Tax 35c 40. Act, 1918.Trustees of 2. (1) There shall be trustees of the fund who,the Fund.    subject to the provisions of this section, shall be appointed and may be removed by order of the House of Commons.(2) The said trustees shall be not more than seven 40 in number, of whom one, being the Public Trustee or
a corporation entitled&apos; by rules made under subsection (3)  a:d. 1938. of section four of the Public Trustee Act, 1906, to act      -as custodian trustee, shall be custodian trustee of the ^ gg&apos; 7&apos; fund, and the remainder shall be managing trustees. 5        (3) No person shall be appointed to be a managing trustee unless he is a Member of the House of Commons, and, on ceasing to be a Member of the House of Commons, a managing trustee shall vacate his office.(4) The managing trustees may act by a majority 10 of those present at any meeting of the managing trustees at which a quorum is present.(5) The procedure of the trustees shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, be such as the trustees may determine, and the quorum for any meeting of the 15 managing trustees shall be three.(6) A direction of the managing trustees shall con-tinue in force until revoked by a subsequent direction of the managing trustees, notwithstanding any changes in the persons who are managing trustees and notwith-20 standing that, by reason of a dissolution of Parliament or for any other reason, there are for a time no managing trustees.(7) The provisions set out in the Second Schedule to this Act (being certain provisions of subsection (2) of 25 section four of the Public Trustee Act, 1906, as modified for the purposes of this Act) shall have effect with respect to the functions of the custodian trustee and the managing trustees respectively.3. (1) The provisions of the Third Schedule to Supple-30 this Act shall have effect with respect to the investment mentary of the assets of the fund. provisions.(2) The trustees may accept any property given or bequeathed by any person to the fund; but they shall as soon as may be realise any such property, other than 35 money or securities in which they are authorised to invest the assets of the fund.(3) The custodian trustee may charge such fees as he is authorised to charge under the Public Trustee Act, 1906.40 (4) The trustees may employ such officers and servants, if any, as they think necessary in connection with the management of the fund, and the expenses of137 A 2
A.D. 1938.  the management of the fund, including the fees of the -      custodian trustee and the remuneration of any such officers and servants as aforesaid, shall be defrayed out of the fund.(5) The Government Actuary shall from time to 5 time, as requested by the trustees, make a report to the trustees on the general financial position of the fund on a date specified in the report, and every such report shall be laid before the House of Commons.The date so specified shall, in the case of the first 10 report, be not later than the end of the year nineteen hundred and forty-three, and in the case of subsequent reports, not later than five years after that specified in the last preceding report.(6) Accounts of the trustees shall be prepared 15 annually in such form and in such manner as the Comp-troller and Auditor-General may direct, and the Comp-troller and Auditor-General shall examine and certify every such account and shall lay a copy thereof, together with his report thereon, before the House.of Commons.    20(7) So far as is consistent with the due performance -of their respective functions under this Act, the trustees of the fund, the Government Actuary, the Comptroller and Auditor-General and their respective officers and servants shall treat as confidential all information relating 25 to the making or refusal of grants in particular cases; and in particular, but without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision, there shall not be included in any accounts or report laid before the House of Commons under  the  last  preceding  subsection  any 30 identification of the persons to whom grants have been made.Short title. 4. This Act may be cited as the House of CommonsMembers Fund Act, 1938.
SCHEDULES.A.D. 1 FIRST SCHEDULE.Limitations on powers of trustees as respects    Section payments out of the fund.5 1. The annual amount of any periodical payment made out of the fund to any person by virtue of his past membership of the House of Commons shall not exceed one hundred and fifty pounds or such sum as, in the opinion of the trustees, will bring his income up to two hundred and twenty-five pounds per annum, 10 whichever is the less.2. The annual amount of any periodical payment made to a person by virtue of her being the widow of a past member of the House of Commons shall not exceed seventy-five pounds or such sum as, in the opinion of the trustees, will bring her income 15 up to one hundred and twenty-five pounds per annum, whichever is the less.3. No payment shall be made to any person by virtue of his past membership of the  House  of Commons unless he. has attained the age of sixty years or, in the opinion of the 20 trustees, is, by reason of mental or bodily infirmity, incapable of earning his living.4. No payment shall be made to any person unless that person, or, as the case may be, her husband was a member of the House of Commons for periods together amounting to ten years :25 Provided that the trustees may in special circumstances make such a payment as aforesaid notwithstanding that the fore-going requirements are not complied with.5. For the purposes of this Schedule the income of any person shall be ascertained in such manner and on such principles 30 as the trustees may determine.
A.D. 1938. SECOND SCHEDULE.Section 2. certain provisions oe subsection (2) oeSection Four oe the Public Trustee Act, 1906, as modified for the purposes of this Act.1. All sums payable to or out of the income or capital of 5 the fund shall be paid to or by the custodian trustee, and the assets of the fund shall be vested in him as if he were sole trustee.2. The management of the fund and the exercise of any power or discretion exercisable in relation thereto shall be vested in the, managing trustees. 103. As between the custodian trustee and the managing trustees the custodian trustee shall have the custody of all securities and documents of title relating to the property of the fund but the managing trustees shall have free access, thereto and be entitled to take copies thereof or extracts therefrom.        154. The custodian trustee shall concur in and perform all acts necessary to enable the trustees to exercise their powers of management or any other power or discretion vested in them, unless the matter in which he is requested to concur is a breach of trust or involves a personal liability upon him in respect of 20 calls or otherwise, but unless he so concurs the custodian trustee shall not be liable for any act or default on the part of the managing trustees or any of them.5. The custodian trustee, if he acts in good faith, shall not be liable for accepting as correct and acting upon the faith of 25 any statement of the managing trustees as to any matter of fact, nor for acting upon any legal advice obtained by the managing trustees independently of the custodian trustee, nor for acting in accordance with any directions given to him in writing and purporting to be signed by or on behalf of the managing trustees.   30THIRD SCHEDULE.Section 3. POWERS OF INVESTMENT.So much of the assets of the fund as is available for invest-ment may be invested in such securities as the trustees think fit, being either  * 35(a) securities in which a trustee may invest trust moneys under  the powers  conferred by section one of the
3bd Sch. -cont.Trustee Act, 1925, as extended by any subsequent A.D. 1938. enactment; or(b) the stocks, funds, bonds, mortgages or debentures ofany public body incorporated in the United Kingdom by 15 &amp; Yfj or under any Act of Parliament or of the Parliament Geo. 5. c. 19. of Northern Ireland; or(c) the bonds, mortgages, debentures, or debenture or rent-charge stock of any railway, gas, electric light or power company in the United Kingdom; or(d) the preference stock or preference shares of any such gas,electric light or power company which has paid a divi-dend on its ordinary stock or shares at a rate of not less than three per cent, during each of the five years imme-diately preceding the date of the investment,and the trustees may from time to time realise, convert or other-wise deal with any such securities : vProvided that the proviso to subsection (1) of section two of the Trustee Act, 1925 (which restricts the purchase by trustees of securities standing at a premium) shall not apply.
House of Commons Members Fund.DRAFTOF-ABILLTo provide for the making, in certain cases, of grants to, and to the widows of, persons who have been Members of the House of Commons; and for purposes connected with the matter aforesaid.CCCLIV B.   (4.)12th July 1938.137-4

</content>
</cab>
