<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/278/0 images: 392-395</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ffllS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT bCRET.,  r,\ COPY NO.      - &quot;;.P. 191  (58). -CABINET.STATE OF TRADE - JULY, 1958. Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate to my colleagues a summary of the reports submitted to the Board of Trade Advisory Council on the state of trade in July, 1938.O.F.G.S.Board of Trade,25th August,  1938.
in3NFIDENTIAL. A.C.415.BOARD - OP - TRADE ADVISORY COUNCIL. STATE OF TRADE - JULY,  1938.Summary of reports submitted by Members of the Board of Trade Advisory Council (supplemented in some cases with statistical information from other sources).OVERSEAS TRADE.    Imports in July ( 73.9 million) showed a decline of  11.6 million as compared with July,  1937. Imports of raw materials and articles mainly unmanufactured were  7.1 million less, but imports of food, drink and tobacco increased by  2,3 million.    Exports of United Kingdom products ( 37.5 million) declined by  10il million,EMPLOYMENT. Employment at the 18th July showed a slight improvement  as compared with 13th June, mainly due to resumption of work after holiday stoppages.    It is provisionally    estimated that at the 18th July the number of insured persons aged 16 to 64 in employment (exclusive of persons within the agricultural scheme) was approximately 11,371,000,  or 58,000 more than at the 13th June, 1938,  but about 300,000 less (on a comparable basis) than at the 26th July, 1937.RAILWAY TRAFFIC.  For the five weeks ended 31st July, 1938, railway traffic receipts decreased by  983,000 or 5.3 per cent, compared with the corresponding period of 1937,    (As from the 1st October last,  charges were increased by 5 per cent,  except suburban passenger fares within the London Passenger Transport Area).SHIPBUILDING. With the exception of armament orders, few new contracts are being placed.SHIPPING. The amount of laid-up British tonnage on the 1st July,  1938 was 245,000 tons,  compared  with 57,000 tons a year previously.      Conditions remain very difficult for shipowners,  although one or two signs of improvement can be seen.
COAL. The demand for both inland  and export has-e-gain &quot; &quot; -shewn a reduction in recent weeks.      The output for the 27 weeks ended 9th July was 125,000,000 tons as compared with 130,000,000 tons in the corresponding period of 1937.ENGINEERING. Exports of machinery for the first six months of 1938 were 240,000 tons as compared with 207,000 tons in the first six months of 1937.    The position as regards new business, however,  remains disappointing.MOTOR INDUSTRY. New registrations of mechanically propelled vehicles amounted to 30,506 in June, 1938,  a decline of 9,848 on the corresponding period of 1937.COTTON.    The level of -production remained low in July but the industry expects that the decline may come to an end after the normal holiday slackness of July and August.    Exports of piece goods amounted to 113 million square yards in July, 1938 as compared with 177 million square yards in July, 1937.WOOL. The general activity of the wool textile industry in July showed little change.    Exports of woollen and worsted yarns and manufactures amounted to  2,300,000 as compared with  3,500,000 in July, 1957.CHEMICALS. The trade remained depressed in July, but in some quarters an improvement in the near future is expected. A few products in the heavy chemicals section showed an improvement on the month,  but in the main there was little change to report.POTTERY. Unemployment in the pottery, earthenware, etc. industry in June was 18.4 per cent,  as compared with 12.6 per cent, for June,  1937.    Prospects in the general earthenware and china sections were discouraging, other sections show little change.TIMBER. The consumption of softwood in the United Kingdom is being maintained, but excessive stocks have still to be worked off.    The outlook for hardwoods is better.
NON-FERROUS METALS. Prices recovered generally in the last half of June and in July, mainly owing to American purchases.    The demand from industry in the United Kingdom has only heen moderate.AUSTRALIAN TRADE.  Imports of merchandise daring June were  11.1 million as compared with  10.6 million in june 1937:    Sales of wool in July were 980 hales compared with 3,500 in July,  1937;    It is  reported that secondary industry continues to expand,  the increase in the value of factory output during the last five years being estimated at 60 per cent.CANADIAN TRADE. Wholesale prices and the physical volume of business declined in June.    The index of the physical volume of business was 108.3 as compared with 110.7 in May. Grain prices fell as a result of favourable crop conditions.SOUTH AFRICAN TRADE. June was the third successive month in which imports showed a decline on those of the corresponding period of 1937.    The output of gold in May was the highest monthly output recorded, but activity in diamond mining continued to decline.    Industrial activity in April showed a further set back.

</content>
</cab>
