<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/216/1 images: 5-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTr, ?- - COPY NO13 January 1983CABINETREPORT OF THE MINISTERIAL GROUP ON LOCAL GOVERNMENTORGANISATION AND FINANCEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department1.       The Ministerial Group on Local Government Organisation and Finance (MISC 79)has been considering under my chairmanship a range of matters affecting thefinancial arrangements for local government in Great Britain and possible changesin its structure and functions.    This memorandum summarises our recommendations,which are set out in more detail in the attached note.DECISIONS ALREADY TAKEN2. Following my minute of 18 June to the Prime Minister, it was agreed thatthe Group should not explore any of the sources of revenue which have been putforward as possible alternatives to reformed domestic rates (assigned revenues;local income tax; local sales tax; poll tax).    The Group&apos;s recommendations onlegislation to regulate subsidies from local authorities to public transport, asreported in my minute of 8 July, were accepted and are contained in the TransportBill.    Finally, my minute of 20 July reported, among other things, that we did notfavour the creation of a separate Exchequer grant to help finance local authorityeducation.DECISIONS TO BE TAKEN3. MISC 79 now makes the following recommendations:a. The Greater London Council (GLC) and the Metropolitan County - Councilsshould be abolished.b. Public Transport in the London area should be reorganised by makingthe London Transport Executive responsible to the Secretary of State forTransport (instead of the GLC) and by converting it, in two stages, into aMetropolitan Transport Authority.    It would co-ordinate, and distributeGovernment financial assistance between, the London Underground and busesand the South Eastern commuter services of British Rail.c. A scheme of discounts on domestic rates should be introduced forhouseholds consisting of a single person.    This would provide flat-ratediscounts of the order of  1.50 a week on rate bills of over  3 a week; or50 per cent of smaller rate bills.    The cost would be about  140 to 170 million a year.    In presenting the scheme we should say that provisionfor it will be made in the Rate Support Grant settlement each year.d. County Councils should provide separate rate bills;   but the existingcollection system should not be changed.e. Council tenants should receive annual rate statements.1 ICONFIDENTIAL^_ ,    -    21
CONFIDENTIALf,       The maximum rateable value below which non-domestic rates may be, paid by instalments should be increased.-  .     g.       Local authorities should be put under a statutory obligation toconsult local representatives of industry and commerce before fixing ratesor precepts.h. Non-domestic property should be revalued;    but we do not recommenda revaluation of domestic property in the near future in England and Wales.i. We should consult interested parties on streamlining valuationprocedures as recommended in a recent  &apos;Rayner&apos; scrutiny.j.       There should be no change in local authority electoral arrangements.The measures in d, e and f above are already in force in Scotland.4. There are two matters on which the Group were unable to reach agreement.k.        The Inner London Education Authority.    This is a special committeeof the GLC.    If the GLC is abolished new arrangements will therefore needto be found for organising education in inner London.    Most members of theGroup think that a single body should be retained but reconstituted as ajoint board of the inner London boroughs.    A minority of the Group considerthat education should become the responsibility of the inner London boroughs.I1.       Measures to restrain local authority current expenditure. Mostmembers of the Group think that we should not introduce new measures tocontrol local authority current expenditure or rates.    There is minoritysupport in the Group for -i.        canvassing,  in a consultative document or elsewhere, asystem of selective central controls on the current expenditureor rates of English and Welsh local authorities;ii.      &apos;capping&apos;  increases in non-domestic rates.Either measure might be associated with a requirement that local authoritieswhich wished to spend or rate highly should hold a  &apos;town poll&apos; or offerthemselves for re-election.LEGISLATION5. All the matters discussed in paragraphs 3 and 4 above (except those atParagraph 3 f and h.  require primary legislation.    There is no prospect oflegislating in the present Parliament.    We should, however, be ready to legislateas quickly as possible after a General Election.    Legislation to set up aMetropolitan Transport Authority and on rating reform could probably be ready forintroduction in November 1983;    legislation to abolish the GLC and the Metropolitan!Counties early in 1984 provided that preparations begin and announcements are madesoon.ANNOUNCEMENTS &gt;^-       The exact means and timing of announcements will depend on our decisions ofsubstance.    But MISC 79 considers it important that the decisions should bePresented as a package, not piecemeal.    Some of our supporters may think that theydo not go far enough, particularly in the field o  domestic rates.    But they can beldefended as a reasonable compromise between local freedom and the legitimate mods2CONFIDENTIAL rt I
CONFIDENTIALof central government.    A good deal of support for them can be found in therecent reports of the Select Committees on the Environment and Transport. Weshall need to be able to indicate in some detail how we might organise the relevant!local authority services if we decide to abolish the GLC and the MetropolitanCounties.    The Secretary of State for the Environment favours an announcement orco-ordinated set of announcements in March.    This would permit a timely reply tothe report of the Environment Select Committee on alternatives to domestic rates,and would facilitate the early implementation of M1SC 79&apos;s recommendations.CONCLUSION7.       I invite my colleagues to endorse the recommendations in paragraphs 3 and 5,and to decide the issues in paragraph 4 above, and how our conclusions should bepublicly presented.W WHome Office13 January 19833CONFIDENTIAL^^^fc^^^^^^^^ _ ....._______ n l\
1 CONFIDENTIAL | HLOCAL GOVERNMENT ORGANISATION AND FINANCEReport by the Ministerial Group on Local GovernmentOrganisation and Finance (MISC 79)INTRODUCTIONL This report sets out MISC 79&apos;s recommendations, incuding those alreadyreported in the Home Secretary&apos;s minutes of 18 June, 8 July and 20 July to thePrime Minister. Paragraphs 2 to 6 recommend changes in the structure andUnctions of local government; paragraphs 7 to 31 discuss, and recommendcertain changes in, the financial arrangements for local government;Paragraphs 32 to 34 suggest how and when the Group&apos;s proposals might bePresented and put into effect.^AL GOVERNMENT STRUCTURE AND FUNCTIONSSie_Greater London Council (GLC) and the Metropolitan County Councils. The GLC and the six Metropolitan County Councils (West Midlands, GreaterManchester, Merseyside, Tyne and Wear, South Yorkshire and West Yorkshire)a count for a disproportionately large part of current local authorityoverspending. Their minor functions duplicate those of the London boroughs and&quot;Metropolitan districts; their &apos;strategic role&apos; is too readily inflated to the point * conflict with central Government over national policies. They are unpopular,n t only among our own supporters, but also in the country at large. We nsider that there is an overwhelming political case for their abolition, whichWe accordingly recommend.&apos; There are a number of problems with which we shall have to deal if we decideto abolish the GLC and the Metropolitan County Councils. We do not regard anyof them as insuperable.a  We shall need to keep to a minimum the costs of transition, whichcannot be satisfactorily estimated as yet. It will probably be best forMinisters to supervise the transitional arrangements themselves and notleave decisions exclusively to the local authorities and their staff.CONFIDENTIAL
H | CONFIDENTIAL |b. We shall need to explain and defend the implications of abolishing theGLC and Metropolitan County Councils for the services they provide.Paragraph 4 below recommends that the GLC&apos;s main function, the control ofLondon Transport, should be entrusted to a Metropolitan TransportAuthority; paragraphs 5 and 6 discuss the future of the Inner LondonEducation Authority (ILEA). Some London-wide arrangements, probably ajoint board of London boroughs, will probably be necessary for the GLC&apos;sresponsibilities for highways, traffic management and strategic land useplanning. Abolishing the Metropolitan County Councils will haveadministrative disadvantages for the organisation of the police service; butthese can be satisfactorily resolved by setting up joint boards of themetropolitan districts to act as police authorities. Similar joint boards ofmetropolitan districts will probably be necessary for fire, transport andland use planning. Most of the GLC&apos;s and Metropolitan County Councils&apos;minor functions can be carried out satisfactorily by individual Londonboroughs or metropolitan districts. Annex A sets out in more detail theGroup&apos;s provisional recommendations about how these authorities&apos; functionsmight be reallocated.c. Our political opponents, especially the present leadership of the GLC,will try to portray abolition as a vindictive reaction to the fact that the GLCI. and most of the Metropolitan Counties are under Labour control.    We, forour part, shall need to emphasise the likely benefits to ratepayers.sd. Once the intention to abolish the councils is announced they may beginto act irresponsibly or mischievously, and they may not cooperate in thepreparation of the legislation. We shall need to be ready to counter orrestrain any such action.{ie. A decision to abolish the GLC may be criticised on the grounds thatthere should be an elected body which can represent London as a whole.iThe Group thought it important to have some kind of representative bodytbut felt that it would probably be possible to create one by developing therole of the London Boroughs Association.......Public Transport in the London Area4. If the GLC is abolished, new arrangements for the control of transport inLondon and the surrounding area will be inevitable.   Even if the GLC is retained,there is a strong independent case for organisational change to make transport_2_ 1H 1 CONFIDENTIAL |
1 CONFIDENTIALPolicy in London more coherent, notably by rationalising and co-ordinating theLondon Underground and the London commuter services of British Rail (BR). Inthe Group&apos;s view this would best be done by converting the existing LondonTransport Executive (LTE) in two stages into a new Metropolitan TransportAuthority (MTA), appointed by the Secretary of State for Transport andresponsible for allocating grant (which it would receive from the Government)among BR&apos;s London commuter services, the Underground and London busoperators. It would approve investment in these services and would have ageneral obligation to ensure that public transport was provided efficiently andcost-effectively throughout Greater London and for commuters into it. Annex Bdescribes this proposal in more detail: there will be consequential changes inlocal government financial arrangements in London.ii inner London Education Authority5- ILEA is formally a special committee of the GLC. If the GLC is abolishedsome new arrangements must therefore be found for organising education in&apos; inner London (the old London County Council area).   The Group has been unableto reach agreement on whether a single body with this responsibility should beretained. Some members take the view that any authority whose sole responsi-bility is the provision of education (and the careers service) throughout London1 will, like ILEA, be congenitally profligate.   They conclude that education shouldoecome the responsiblity of the inner London boroughs, acting either alone or ingroups, as it is of the outer London boroughs and the districts in theMetropolitan counties. Most members of MISC 79, however, take the view that asingle body should be retained but reconstituted as a joint board, consisting ofPersons nominated by the inner London boroughs and the City of London, whor would themselves be councillors of those authorities.   They argue that a singleeducation authority for inner London is better able than individual boroughs orgroups of them to deal with the problem of falling school rolls while trying tot improve  educational standards;  and that fragmentation would create serious[t management problems, both at school level,  given the existing distribution ofschools and population, and for further and higher education.    It would alsof&apos;e cause upheaval in the finances of local government in London:   it would probablybe necessary to devise a new, overt and contentious mechanism to distributes me of the benefit of Westminster&apos;s and the City&apos;s high rateable resourcesamong other inner London boroughs to replace the covert redistributive effectsin of  the   ILEA  precept.     There  are  also  political considerations:     when weconsidered the future of ILEA in 1980 and 1981, there was strong evidence ofj opposition  to breaking it up and we concluded that the Authority should be |retained (CC(81) 1st Conclusions. Minute 4; CC(81) 3rd Conclusions, Minute 5).I | CONFIDENTIAL |^ 3_?_i_C^H
JCONFIDENTIAL |An announcement now that we intended to break up the ILEA would lead to a 10vigorous campaign by the education lobby to retain it. This might overshadow urthe political benefits we can expect from announcing a decision to abolish the SeGLC. stsh6. The Group has considered whether individual inner London boroughs should Pabe able to &apos;secede&apos; from whatever arrangement generally replaces ILEA; butconcludes that it would be best not to proceed in this way. A right of secession anwould tend to disrupt the organisation and financing of education (particularly ^ as, after changes of political control, individual London boroughs might reverse wi-previous decisions about whether to secede); it would also set an unfortunate Woprecedent in allowing individual local authorities to decide for what services they w would make themselves responsible.in&lt;FINANCIAL ARRANGEMENTS n 7. At an early stage the Group reached the view that none of the alternatives re&lt;to domestic rates canvassed in the Green Paper on that subject (local sales tax,local income tax, poll tax,  assigned central Government revenues) should beadopted;     and that  the Government  should not  attempt  to introduce a new ^Exchequer grant in support of local authority education.   The Home Secretary&apos;sminutes of 18 June and 20 July reported those conclusions.  0iSUj8. The Group has therefore considered how the rating system might bereformed, to remove or mitigate some of its perceived unfairness anddisadvantages; and has examined possible measures to discourage or preventlocal authorities from imposing excessive burdens on their ratepayers to supportunreasonable levels of expenditure.Rating reform:  discount scheme9. It is a widespread criticism of domestic rates that single occupiers pay asmuch as large households. MISC 79 recommends that, to meet this criticism, arate discount scheme should be introduced for households consisting of only oneadult occupier. The scheme would provide for a flat-rate discount of the orderof  1.50 on rate bills of over  3 per week: for lower rate bills there would be a50 per cent discount. It would assist about 5 million ratepayers. The discountwould be on gross rates, ie before rate rebates. The annual cost would be inthe range of  140 to  170 million. Annex C sets out the Group&apos;s reasons forpreferring this method of altering the incidence of domestic rates to otherpossible discount schemes or surcharges.4I 1 CONFIDENTIAL |
[ CONFIDENTIALj H10- If we announce that we intend to introduce a discount scheme on these ??hnes, we shaU need to indicate whom we intend to pay for it. The ChiefSecretary, Treasury considers that a discount scheme should be seen as astructural change within the rating system, and that there is no reason why itshould be linked with an increase in the proportion of local authority expenditurefor from central Government funds; and that any increase in centralGovernment support would undesirably reduce local authorities&apos; accountability^ financial responsibility to their electorate. Most members of the Group,h wever, consider that the political advantage of introducing a discount scheme^ be lost unless we can say that it will be paid for by central Government. Itw uld be very awkward to suggest that other domestic ratepayers, some of themWorse off than the scheme&apos;s beneficiaries, should bear the cost; and the Green?aPer on Alternatives to Domestic Rates said that &quot;any new measures should not MUrease the relative burden on industry and commerce&quot;, as would be the case if^-domestic ratepayers paid part of the scheme&apos;s costs. The Group thereforeCommends that in presenting the scheme we should say that the GovernmentWil1 make provision for it in the Rate Support Grant (RSG) settlements eachye&amp;r, and will take into account the effective reduction in rateable value at thel6Vel of individual authorities in calculating each authority&apos;s entitlement toSrant. In reality, it will be impossible to say who has paid for the scheme if itsCost is taken into account in fixing the overall amount of central GovernmentSuPPort for local authorities through the Rate Support Grant.^Hlg_reform: other measuresU&apos; The Group recommends the following reforms of the rating system. &gt; . County counciis, which precept on the rates of the districts or Londontroughs, should provide, through them, separate rate bills to ratepayers,together with details of the rate or precept they levied in the previous year;so should any other major precepting authority, for example the Receiver ofthe Metropolitan Police or any new joint boards created in Greater London&lt;* the metropolitan counties. This should increase ratepayers&apos; awareness&lt;* how much they pay in rates to each authority. Payment would continue tobe made to the district or London borough, as at present._5_1 CONFIDENTIAL ji-- (^mmmmmmM^HH
wm^^^???????????????????????????????????????????????????^^? | CONFIDENTIAL |b. Council  tenants  should receive  annual rate statements,  to increasetheir awareness of how much of their inclusive rent consists of rates.c. The maximum rateable value below which non-domestic rates may bepaid by instalments should be increased, with the new limit decided afterconsultations with the local authority associations.d. Local authorities should be put under a statutory obligation to consultlocal representatives of industry and commerce before fixing their rates orprecepts.Arrangements similar to the first two of these measures are already in force inScotland. All Scottish ratepayers already have the right to pay rates byinstalments.12. The Group recommends that there should be a revaluation of non-domesticproperty in England and Wales. The Secretary of State for the Environment andthe Chief Secretary, Treasury propose that the revaluation should take effectfrom 1 April 1987.13. There is a considerable weight of professional opinion in favour of arevaluation of domestic property as well, on the basis of capital values ratherthan the present basis of hypothetical rental values. Unless the private rentalsector is revived, a move to capital valuation of domestic property may well beinevitable in the long term, and would be more comprehensible to ratepayersthan is the present system. But such a change would establish the principle of atax based on the capital value of personal assets. Nor is a revaluation on thepresent basis desirable in the near future. It would cause resentment amongmany ratepayers; and local authorities might not feel obliged to make fullyoffsetting reductions in their rate poundages, so that the pressure on them tohold down their expenditure would be reduced. The Group therefore does notrecommend that there should be a domestic revaluation in the near future mEngland and Wales.?14. The Group also recommends that interested parties should be consulted onthe changes in valuation procedures recommended in a recent &apos;Rayner&apos; scrutinyof the Valuation Office.ICONFIDENTIAL
I confidential] H15. Separately from MISC 79&apos;s work, the Secretary of State for Scotland willbe seeking colleagues&apos; agreement to legislation early in the next Parliament torectify some of the anomalies created by the existence of separate valuationsystems North and South of the Border. He also proposes that there should bea full rating revaluation in Scotland, covering domestic and non-domesticProperty, using the existing methods of valuation, in 1985. He will seek othercolleagues&apos; views on this proposal in the light of the Cabinet&apos;s discussion of MMISC 79&apos;s report.Measure* tn Restrain Local Authority Expenditure and Rates16. The level of domestic and non-domestic rates, and the speed with whichthey have increased in recent years, remain a matter of great politicalconcern in many parts of the country. Indeed, much of the criticism of ratesas a system of local taxation is due not to their structure but to their level. . The abolition of the GLC and the Metropolitan County Councils,recommended in paragraph 2 above, and the establishment of newarrangements for education in inner London should help to restrain localauthority expenditure; the GLC, ILEA and the Metropolitan Counties accountf r about two-thirds of the amount by which local authority currentexpenditure exceeds the Government&apos;s targets. The powers to controltransport subsidies contained in the Transport Bill, (which are based on therecommendations by MISC 79 reported in .the Home Secretary&apos;s minute of 8*% to the Prime Minister) should lead to greater economy in an area of localauthority spending which has in recent years been marked by outstanding^responsibility and extravagance. Some of the minor changes to the ratingAstern which the Group recommends can also be expected to increase thePressure for economy in local government.18- It would be wrong, however, to exaggerate the effects of the changesAscribed above on local authorities&apos; behaviour. Abolishing the GLC and theMetropolitan Counties will bring no relief to aggrieved ratepayers elsewhere.So*e of the lower-tier authorities in the conurbations which will be involvedin carrying out new functions if the GLC and Metropolitan Counties are |abolished are themselves just as profligate.7_1 confidential]L-- 8 I
H | confidential |19. The Group has therefore considered proposals to control individual localauthorities&apos; current expenditure or rates;  or to &apos;cap&apos; non-domestic rates.Selective Controls on Local Authority Current Expenditure or Rates20. It would in principle be possible to establish a new system of selectivecentral controls on the current expenditure or rates of English and Welshlocal authorities (their capital expenditure is already cash-limited). The mostsuitable arrangement (because the least susceptible to successful legalchallenge) would probably be for the Government to set a limit or limits onrate increases. The limits would vary for different groups of authorities torecognise their different circumstances. Authorities which wanted to raiserates further would have to apply to the Secretary of State for theEnvironment for permission to do so. The limits would be set so that only afew authorities would be caught. The rest would be free to determine theirexpenditure and rates provided they kept rate increases within the specifiedlimits.21. An alternative arrangement would be for the Secretary of State for theEnvironment to select a few authorities for scrutiny and to set individuallimits on their rate increases, subject to Parliamentary approval.22. A selective control scheme would have a number of attractions. Excessivelocal authority current expenditure remains a major structural problem incontrolling public expenditure; an announcement that the Governmentintended to take steps to curb excessive rates would be supported by manymembers of the public.23. On the other hand, any scheme to control individual authorities&apos; currentexpenditure or rates would raise major difficulties.a. It would involve an important shift in the balance between centraland local government. Ministers would for the first time be setting &amp;limit on the amount which English and Welsh local authorities couldspend. Efforts so far to restrain local authority spending by settingtargets backed by holdback of RSG have left intact the principle that inthe last resort local authorities should have the freedom to raise rates to8------confidential
1 confidentialPay for local services: that would not be the case if expenditure or ratecontrols were introduced. Moreover, if any local authority sought tojustify expenditure higher than that permitted by rate limits which thegovernment had prescribed, Ministers would have to form a detailedjudgement of what that authority could justifiably spend. Many voters mayattach little importance to the constitutional relationship between centraland local government; but many of our own active supporters holdstrongly to the view that local matters must remain for local decision anddoubt central government&apos;s ability to reach better decisions than those n the spot. It was in this spirit that our manifesto for the 1979 GeneralElection said that local government independence should be increased.The limits set would be susceptible to challenge in the courts, whereMinisters&apos; decisions could be subject to detailed scrutiny.c  Any scheme would involve a significant shift in power and responsi-bility to the Secretary of State for the Environment from other Ministerswho are responsible for local authority services. The Attorney Generalnas advised that the legislation providing for a scheme would need toconfer authority upon the Secretary of State for the Environment todecide whether a given level of expenditure should be permitted. Inreaching that decision he would of course be entitled to discuss thematter with his colleagues; but the final decision would be his alone andcould not be taken collectively. He cannot delegate the exercise of hisdiscretion. It would be difficult to reconcile such an overriding authoritythe Secretary of State for the Environment with, for example, theHome Secretary&apos;s statutory responsibilities for the police and fireservices and the Secretary of State for Education and Science&apos;s statutoryresponsibilities for the education service.. There are political arguments against as well as for controls. First,there is a danger that an announcement that we intended to legislate toc ntrol local authority expenditure or rates would arouse expectations ofa much wider-ranging system of controls than would be possible inPractice.   The control could in practice bite on no more than twenty to9^^^^^^^^^^^ confidential ^^^^^^^^^^^^^^B
H 1 confidential |thirty authorities. Secondly, and in consequence, the Government wouldbe blamed for those rate increases which the system did not prevent: weshould indeed be regarded as approving rate increases right up to thelimit. Thirdly, there would be a more general tendency for the blame forthe shortcomings of individual local authorities to be put on to theGovernment.24. A system of selective controls over local authority current expenditurealready operates in Scotland, although it differs from the arrangements which Jsome members of the Group think would be appropriate in England and Wales. !Annex   D   describes   the   Scottish   system   of  controls   and  discusses   its &lt;relevance to the question whether there should be selective controls over the ]current expenditure of English and Welsh local authorities. 1c25. A minority of the members of the Group take the view that the balance of cargument favours further action to restrain local authority expenditure, and Ithat the establishment of a new system of selective controls could bring tvaluable benefits, both substantial and presentational. They argue that over ta period of years the existence of such a system would reduce the expenditure tof the highest spending authorities and encourage the rest to be more ceconomical. They believe that many members of the public would regard it as 1&lt;the least that could be offered if we do not abolish the rating system itself,and that we shall be strongly and rightly criticised if our package of proposals dincludes no measures directly aimed at limiting the burden of the rates.  They asuggest  that we  should,  in  a consultative document or otherwise, publicly Pcanvass the idea that there should be new powers for selective central control rof local authority expenditure or rates. 1w26. Most members of MISC 79, however, take the view we should not seek P:powers to control local authority current expenditure or rates in England andWales; but should continue to rely on the rate support grant system and ongrant holdback to restrain local authority current expenditure.   They believe b&lt;Tlthat, far from reducing expenditure, a system of central controls could even+ r?increase it, since it would appear to endorse rate increases up to the limit set10H | confidentjaT
[confidential!by the Government, and that limit would have to be set high in order to avoidcatching more than a manageable number of authorities. They further takethe view that it would be unwise even to go so far as to suggest in public thata system of controls is a possibility for the future if local authorities do notshow more moderation in their expenditure than in the past. They considerthat it would be unwise to suggest a policy which we would have great difficultyin carrying out.?llCapping&quot; increases in non-domestic rates27. Ministers have been under intense pressure from industrial andcommercial ratepayers for some protection against profligate local autho-rities, m some areas of the country over 70 per cent of local governmentrate revenue comes from industry and commerce, yet industrial andcommercial ratepayers have no vote and little influence over local governmentI decisions.     Some members  of the Group take the view that the measuresi recommended in paragraphs 11 and 12 above are an inadequate response to% pressure for effective controls on non-domestic rates and will not satisfyr the expectations raised by the statement in the Green Paper on Alternativesto   Domestic   Rates   that   &quot;the   Government   will  keep   under   review thee contribution that industry and cpmmerce make through rates to the cost ofs local services and does not rule out the possibility of measures to reduce thatI, contribution if it should become essential to do so.&quot;   They believe that, if weLs do not put forward the idea that there should be new measures to control local,y authority expenditure and rates, we should make clear that we intend to takely Powers to &apos;cap&apos; increases in non-domestic rates.   Authorities could then notol raise their non-domestic rates by more than a prescribed amount; any^rther money would have to be raised solely from the domestic ratepayers towhom they are accountable at the ballot box; and this would increase the ,efc Pressure to reduce spending,ndon 28  Most members of the Group take the view, on the other hand, that onve balance we should not take powers to &apos;cap&apos; increases in non-domestic rates.en ^ consider it the inevitable result of any such scheme that domesticjt ratepayers would be faced with large rate increases, especially in areas of the11| confidential] ioB
H | confidential |country where authorities raise a large part of their revenue from industrialand commercial rates. . Many of these authorities would choose to makedomestic rate increases rather than to cut spending and would seek to put theblame on the Government. These members take the view therefore that weshould rest on and promote the measures to help industrial and commercialratepayers proposed in paragraphs 11 and 12 above, perhaps together with ameasure of relief for empty commercial and industrial property, a proposalwhich the Secretaries of State for Industry and the Environment and the ChiefSecretary, Treasury are considering separately.Another Approach:  the &apos;Town Poll&apos;29. Either selective controls on local authority current expenditure or rates,or &apos;capping&apos; increases in non-domestic rates, could be combined withmeasures to strengthen local accountability. Authorities wishing to spend, orincrease rates or non-domestic rates, above a prescribed limit would have toseek the agreement of local electors, either by calling an election or by &amp;&apos;town poll&apos; (broadly similar to a &apos;local referendum&apos;, though the latter phrase isone to be avoided). Although there are good precedents for such a procedurein local government, we had, of course, to withdraw a similar proposal in 1981when it became clear that many of our own supporters in Parliament, underpressure from Conservative local councillors, would not support it. But if theidea were put forward again in a consultative document, it might commandsufficient popular support to make legislation possible.Measures to Restrain Local Authority Expenditure and Rates: Conclusions30. To sum up -a. Most members of the Group think that we should not mention publiclythe possibility of new measures to control local authority expenditure orrates in England and Wales, and that we should continue to rely on therate support grant system and grant holdback to restrain local authoritycurrent expenditure.12zI 1 confidential] I
1 CONFIDENTIAL | Hb. There is minority support in MISC 79 for:i. canvassing, in a consultative document or otherwise, selectivecentral control over local government current expenditure or rates;ii. &apos;capping&apos; increases in non-domestic rates.c. Either selective controls on current expenditure or &apos;capping&apos; could becombined with a &apos;town poll&apos;.jgcal Authority Elections31. The Group considered the case for changing local government electoralarrangements in a way which would make local authorities more accountable totheir electorates. They concluded however that increasing the frequency oflocal elections - the only course which stood any chance of having this effect -would bring insufficient benefits to outweigh the political and other diffi-i culties of making such a change.kANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPLEMENTATION3 legislation1 32. All of the Group&apos;s recommendations except for a non-domestic revaluation(paragraph 12 above) and an extension of the right to pay non-domestic ratesbyinstalments  (paragraph  11c) require primary legislation.    There is noProspect of putting through the necessary Bills in the present Parliament, nomatter how long it lasts.   The Group recommends that legislation should bey lntroduced  as   early  as possible after the General Election,  so that their benefits of changes in local government finance or structure will be seenis during the next Parliament:    abolition would take some two years to complete-Y after the enactment of legislation.    It is also relevant that elections to theMetropolitan County Councils are scheduled for May 1985. The Secretary ofState for the Environment&apos;s advice is that legislation on rating reform couldbe ready for introduction in November 1983; and that legislation to abolish theGLC and Metropolitan Counties could be ready early in 1984, provided thatPreparations begin soon and that announcements are made in March. In thesecretary 0f State for Transport&apos;s view, legislation to convert LTE into anMTA could be ready for introduction in November 1983.j | CONFIDENTIAL | H
I 1 confidential |Announcements33. MISC 79 recommends that Ministers should announce as one packagewhatever reforms of local government finance and organisation the Cabinetagrees upon, so as to achieve the maximum impact. The timing, manner andcontent of announcements will clearly depend on the outcome of the Cabinet&apos;sdiscussion.Presentation34. The precise presentation of the changes which MISC 79 recommends willclearly need further consideration, in the light of discussion in the Cabinet,by the Ministers primarily concerned. But there are three general pointswhich could be made in presenting the measures recommended in this report.a. The package should not be seen in isolation, but as a stage in aseries of measures to bring more discipline into local authority activityand expenditure which are now beginning to have some success.b. Central Government has a legitimate interest in the level andstructure of local taxation; but it is also of importance to retain ahealthy local democracy. Unless we are prepared to take the majorconstitutional step of controlling local authorities in detail the level oflocal taxation must be a matter for local decision; within that framework,and taken together with the Group&apos;s recommendation that rates shouldremain the main source of local revenue, the Group&apos;s proposals shouldhelp to ensure that local authorities take appropriate account of theGovernment&apos;s views.c. The reports of the Environment and Transport Select Committeesprovide support for the Group&apos;s recommendations that rates should remainthe main source of local government income; and that a MetropolitanTransport Authority should be set up for the London area.Ik? | confidential I j
1 confidentialANNEX A&quot;REDISTRIBUTION   OF   THE   GLC&apos;S   AND   METROPOLITAN   COUNTY COUNCILS&apos;RESPONSIBILITIESintroductionThis annex sets out MISC 79&apos;s provisional recommendations on how thefunctions of the GLC and the Metropolitan County Councils might be carriedout if those authorities are abolished, as the Group proposes.GLC2    The GLC&apos;s present functions are as follows -i     Policy responsibility for London Transport,ii.   For the whole GLC area, acting alonea. Fireb. Waste Disposalc. Flood Protectiond. Coronerse. Licensing of entertainmentf. Smallholdingsui  For the inner area onlya. Education (though the ILEA)b. Building controliv   for the whole GLC area, sharing responsibility with the boroughsa. Planningb. Transport (Highways)c   Historic Buildingsd.   Civil Defenceconfidential ii-1 -a o
I 1 CONFIDENTIAL | jv. For the whole GLC area, concurrent with the boroughsa. Housingb. Assistance to Industryc. Arts and Recreationd. Tourisme. Parksvi. Local funding and support, in outer London, for -a. Magistrates courtsb. Probation and aftercare service3. Arrangements for public transport in London and education in innerLondon if the GLC is abolished are discussed elsewhere in the Group&apos;s report.The GLC&apos;s other functions might be reallocated on the following lines -i. Boroughs acting independently in their areasa. Building control (inner boroughs changing to national system)b. Historic   Buildings  (to be  subject  to same  central control aselsewhere)c. Housingd. Assistance to Industrye. Tourismf. Licensing of entertainmentg. Parksh. Smallholdingsii. Voluntary joint committees of boroughsCivil Defence (in five groups)iii. Mandatory joint committees of BoroughsWaste DisposalH J CONFIDENTIAL |
1 CONFIDENTIAL [ Hiv.     Joint boards of boroughsa. Fire (perhaps several separate brigades)b. Highways, Traffic, Planningv       Groups of outer London boroughsLocal financial support fora. Magistrates courtsb. Probation and aftercare serviceVi.     Thames Water AuthorityFlood Protectionvii.    A new London Committee of the Arts CouncilArts in London (including the South Bank)^gopolitan County Councils.   The Metropolitan Counties&apos; present functions are as follows -Responsibility   for   public   transport   policy,   acting   through thepassenger transport executives.Financial and policy responsibility for the police through the policeauthorities.confidential I I^_1 J_ 13 J
H 1 confidential |iii. Acting alone &apos;a. Transport (Highways)b. Firec. Waste Disposald. Trading Standardse. Animal Healthf. Food and drugsg. Smallholdingsh. Coronersiv. Shared with districtsa. Planningb. Civil Defencev. Concurrent with districtsa. Housing (reserve)b. Tourismc. Parksd. Artse. Assistance to Industryvi. Local funding and support for the probation servicevii. Part or full ownership of airports6H I confidential I
1 CONFIDENTIAL | 95.   These functions could be redistributed as follows -i       Districts acting independentlya. Housingb. Assistance to Industryc Tourismd. Trading Standardse. Food and drugsf. Parksg. Artsh. Small holdingsii      Voluntary joint committees of districtsa. Waste Disposalb. Civil Defenceiii. Joint boards of districtsa. Policeb. Firec. Transport ) perhaps ad. Land use planning  ) single bodyiv. Groups of districtsLocal funding and support for the probation and aftercare servicev*      Districts acting through agenciesAnimal health (with the adjacent shire counties as agencies)v*-*     New regional airport authoritiesArrangements for the coroner service are under separate review.1 CONFIDENTIAL | ^ H
I confidential]ANNEX BPUBLIC TRANSPORT IN LONDONIntroduction1. The present arrangements for the provision of public transport in theLondon area are unsatisfactory. The Greater London Council (GLC) hasexercised its powers over the London Transport Executive (LTE) in acapricious and irresponsible way. London Transport is an overcentralisedand inefficient public sector industry. There is insufficient co-ordinationand rationalisation between the Underground and bus services which LTEprovides and British Rail&apos;s (BR) South Eastern commuter services.2. MISC 79 therefore took the view that it would be appropriate to set up aMetropolitan Transport Authority (MTA), appointed by the Secretary of Statefor Transport, whose central duty would be to ensure that public transport inthe London area was provided efficiently and economically. The Group alsoconcluded that it would be better to convert the present LTE into a MTA thanto set up a completely new MTA with powers over LTE and BR&apos;s Londoncommuter services. This approach should avoid the need to create a whollynew organisation and should make it possible to improve the organisation ofPublic transport in the London area with maximum economy and minimuumdisruption. There would be two stages in converting LTE into a MTA.Stage_One3-   The GLC&apos;s responsibilities for LTE, including the power to appoint the LTEBoard and to pay grant in support of London Transport&apos;s operation would beI        transferred to the Secretary of State.    He would also be given the powers Hnecessary to convert LTE into a MTA.I        4.   The   Secretary   of   State   would   direct   LTE   to   establish  the  London ?Underground and London buses as separate subsidiary undertakings, each withits own management board and financial structure.   LTE&apos;s staff, property andether assets would be divided between them except to the extent necessary toservice the Executive&apos;s continuing functions.| confidential] ^... ?
H 1 CONFIDENTIAL |5. LTE would consult BR about measures to co-ordinate and rationalise theiroperations..6. The Secretary of State for Transport would assume all the GLC&apos;s powersof direction over LTE.7. LTE would for financing and control purposes be treated as a nationalisedindustry, with borrowing controlled through an External Financing Limit (EFL).Stage Two8. LTE would be converted into an MTA. It would be responsible for puttingforward to the Secretary of State a plan to provide efficient and cost-effective public transport services throughout the Greater London area andfor commuters into it.9. The MTA would assume responsibilities for BR&apos;s London commuterservices. Their precise nature needs to ,be settled in the light of policydecisions on BR following the Serpell report, but the main features would beas follows -i. The MTA would allocate operating subsidy and other grants among BR,the London Underground and the London buses.   The total level of grantwould be  fixed  and paid to the MTA by the Secretary of State for 1Transport;    the MTA would not have precepting powers or other sourcesof income. 1ii. The MTA would have the power to transfer service obligations andproperty between operators.iii. In formulating its plan, the MTA would review with the BritishRailways Board (BRB) how a consistent level of fares, a coherent farestructure and desired level of services could be achieved.iv. The MTA would review the BRB&apos;s investment plans for its commuterservices and would be able to pay grants towards such investment.H | CONFIDENTIAL |
I confidential 1 IFinancial Implications10. Under these proposals the financing of public transport would no longerbe a local government responsibility. This would by itself unjustifiablyimprove the financial position of London ratepayers relative to ratepayerselsewhere in the country; the Group therefore proposes that there should bean offsetting reduction in the financial support given to local government inLondon. Officials are considering how this should be done: the solution islikely to involve -i. reducing London&apos;s share of rate support grant (RSG);ii. changing the London rates equalisation scheme to transfer resources Hfrom those London authorities which do not receive RSG.H. Officials are also considering how precisely the financial arrangementsfor the MTA would mesh in with those for BR. The Secretary of State forTransport would need to decide how much grant the MTA could pay taking intoaccount both the needs of BR&apos;s business as a whole and plans for local publictransport expenditure in other areas.Sgport by the House of Commons Select Committee on Transport12. The Select Committee&apos;s report on transport in London recommended theestablishment of an MTA with function and responsibilities broadly similar to, those proposed above.   The main differences between the Select Committee&apos;sProposals and MISC 79&apos;s recommendations are as follows -I i.    The Select Committee proposed that the MTA should be a completelynew body, with powers over LTE, which would be retained in broadly itspresent form.i3 ii.   The Select Committee proposed that the MTA would take over theGLC&apos;s responsibilities for traffic and highways; MISC 79 considers thatthese functions would be better assigned to the London boroughs, actingr through a joint board.I | confidential]
H | CONFIDENTIAL |iii. The Select Committee proposed that the MTA should be a fullyrepresentative body with a majority of local authority members; MISC 79recommends that it should be a small body, with no more than 15members, most of them not members of local authorities.iv. The Select Committee proposed that the MTA should have preceptingpowers; MISC 79 recommends that it should be wholly financed by centralGovernment, with an offsetting reduction in the financial support givento local government in London.iiiiiIc1Is3MH | CONFIDENTIAL |
1 I confidential] IANNEX CDISCOUNTS ON DOMESTIC RATESIntroductionThe most common complaint about domestic rates is that single occupiers payas much as large households. This annex explains why, in MISC 79&apos;s view, itwould be best to meet this complaint by introducing a discount scheme forhouseholds consisting only of a single person (giving a reduction in grossrates - ie before rebates - of the order of  1.50 a week on weekly rate billsof  3.00 or more; and 50 per cent for lower rate bills) rather than by someother sort of discount scheme or by domestic rate surcharges.Surcharge or discount?2- The burden of local taxation would correspond more closely than atPresent to the benefits derived from local services if we introduced eitherdiscounts for small households or domestic rate surcharges in respect ofhousehold members who, though earning, are not personally liable to payrates. in principle a surcharge is preferable in that it extends personalliability to pay rates to a wider range of local authority voters and thusshould strengthen local accountability.3    A surcharge, however, suffers from two major disadvantages.a. Its administration would be burdensome and costly; with a discountscheme, by contrast, it would be for households to demonstrate theirentitlement.b. A surcharge would be very difficult to present as an attractivechange in the rating system.MlsC 79 therefore recommends a discount scheme.| confidential] H
confidentIaT]A new scheme or an improvement in rate rebates?4. It would be possible to improve the existing rate rebate scheme, forexample by raising the income limits. But the Group takes the view thatdiscounts for small households are desirable as a structural change in therating system, not as a social policy measure; and that it would be politicallyunacceptable if the Government&apos;s main response to criticism of domestic rateswere to amend the terms of the rate rebate scheme. MISC 79 thereforerecommends that a new discount scheme, separate from rate rebates, shouldbe introduced.5. Rate rebates or supplementary benefit should continue to be available tohouseholds which require them even if they qualify for discounts; discountsshould therefore be on gross rates, ie before rebates.Who should qualify?6. In the Group&apos;s view a discount scheme for single adult households, whichwould benefit about five million ratepayers, best meets the need to devisearrangements which can be defended as fair, are administratively feasible and 1are not unreasonably expensive.    It would meet directly the criticism that 1rates fall unfairly on households which consist of only one adult and thusmake few demands on local authority services.7. Other possible bases for eligibility, though superficially attractive, sufferfrom severe disadvantages -i. A discount for households with only one earner would bring in morethan two thirds of all households.ii. Eligibility for discounts could be limited to households consisting of asingle retirement pensioner or of pensioner couples. But it would bedifficult to defend singling out retirement pensioners for bettertreatment than recipients of other social security benefits or other smallhouseholds.confidential |
1 | confidential | HA flat rate or percentage discount?8&apos; A flat-rate discount has some disadvantages compared with a percentagediscount: it would have to be uprated periodically if it were to be a lastingreform rather than a short-term relief; this would involve the Governmentdirectly in determining the size of households&apos; domestic rate bills and thusshift some of the odium of increasing expenditure and rate bills on to theGovernment and away from local authorities. MISC 79 takes the view that theadvantages of a flat-rate scheme, however, outweigh these drawbacks. Thecosts would not rise automatically and would thus be easier to control thanwith a percentage scheme; and, among those ratepayers who qualified, a flat-rate scheme would concentrate resources where they were most needed byProviding the greatest proportional benefit to those with low incomes.I I9  A simple flat-rate discount has the drawback that it would add substan-tially to the large number of households which already paid no rates, thusundermining our policy of increasing the accountabilty of local authorities totheir electorate. For this reason the Group recommends that the flat ratediscount should apply only to rate bills of more than  .3.00 per week, with ratecills below that level reduced by half.confidential I , QI-_-1 io
|[ I confidential] HANNEX DCONTROL OF LOCAL AUTHORITY EXPENDITURE AND RATES IN SCOTLANDI Apart from the level and distribution of aggregate Exchequer Grant, the maininstrument of influence over local authority expenditure and rates in Englandand Wales is a system of automatic penalties for overspending againsttargets. In Scotland there are no such automatic penalties; but the Secretaryof State has discretionary power -a. to reduce grant to individual authorities;b. to impose reductions in the rates levied by individual authorities; and Hc. to impose across-the-board reductions in grant.Powers a. and b. are subject to approval by the House of Commons. Over thelast three years, the Secretary of State has used a. and c; b. is effectivefrom 1983-84.2.   In  taking  selective  action  a.  or b.  against individual authorities,  the MSecretary of State must have regard to criteria which are laid down inlegislation.    He may, at his discretion, allow a local authority to reduce its Hinitial rates demand as an alternative to his imposing a loss of grant or areduction in rates.3- The power to take selective action enables the Secretary of State to Hintervene directly, and flexibly, in the expenditure and rating decisions of afew authorities whose behaviour is out of line with others&apos; and is judgedexcessive and unreasonable. It is not designed to cope with widespreadoverspending by a large number of authorities, to which the Secretary of Statehas responded by imposing across-the-board cuts in grant (c. above).4- There is no doubt that the power to take selective action in Scotland hasheen made to work. The Secretary of State has used it,- and has been able tosecure substantial cuts in the expenditure and, in some cases, the rates atieast of those authorities subject to selective action.| confidential]
H 1 confidential |5. Equally, it is clear that the power is not a direct precedent for thediscretionary action which would be associated with any general limit or limitson rate rises, of the kind discussed in paragraphs 20 to 26 of the report.6. Some members of MISC 79 think that the Scottish experience tells againstthe introduction of any such limit or limits. Discretionary powers should beeasier to exercise in Scotland than in England, because only one Secretary ofState is involved, and he has only 65 local authorities to deal with, as against413 in England and 45 in Wales. Yet over the last three years, the use ofdiscretionary power in Scotland has not stopped local authority currentexpenditure from rising as fast as in England and Wales.7. Other members of the Group think these objections illfounded.Expenditure in Scotland is significantly lower than it would have been withoutselective action; and the cuts imposed on individual authorities which soughtto challenge government policy have had a salutary effect. The Scottishsystem relies exclusively on discretionary action, whereas any limit on raterises in England would be additional to the existing system of automaticpenalties for overspending. The combination of automatic penalties andselective controls would be more extensive than anything which yet exists inScotland, England or Wales.1 confidential |

</content>
</cab>
