<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/14/37 images: 468-475</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1941.SECRET.Copy No.    &amp; (8W.P. (41) 15.January 24, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.ANTI-GAS PRECAUTIONS.Memorandum by Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security.FOLLOWING the discussion at the War Cabinet* on the 20th January,1941, I circulate the following note about anti-gas measures for the civil popula-tion. The note has been drawn up on the assumption that there should be no press and broadcast publicity about anti-gas precautions. I appreciate that there are good reasons for such a course of action, but I feel bound to say that the absenceof publicity will make it more difficult to secure a rapid and widespread improve-&apos;ment in the preparedness of the civil population to meet a sudden gas attack.The value of a respirator, for example, lies only partly in the efficiency of therespirator itself. The balance and no small balance depends on the extent towhich the public are practised in the habit of putting it on quickly and wearing it.Even with the aid of advance publicity it is impossible to guarantee that thefirst onset of a gas attack will not result in casualties. The risk must inevitably-be increased possibly quite seriously in view of the immunity we have hithertoenjoyed if there is no public warning of the increased likelihood of gas attack in the near future. I suggest, therefore, that the War Cabinet should review their policy in this matter.H. M.Home Office, Jantiary 24, 1941.(a) General public.1. Every member of the public should be in possession of a respirator. Allrespirators have been fitted with an additional filter known as &apos;&apos; Contex &apos;&apos; toincrease their protection against particulate gases, i.e., arsenical smokes. Thereare over 10 million respirators in national reserve in addition to 3 millionreserves in the hands of local authorities.2. In March 1940 arrangements were made through the Wardens&apos; organi-sation for a special inspection of respirators in the hands of the public. Localauthorities were then asked to institute a system of inspection by Wardens atNOTE.Personal Protection.* W.M. (41) 8, item 4.

Printed for the War Cabinet.  January 1941.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (41) 15.January 24, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AMD KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.ANTI-GAS PRECAUTIONS.memorandum by Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security.FOLLOWING the discussion at the War Cabinet^ on the 20th January..1941, I circulate the following note about anti-gas measures for the civil popula-tion. The note has been drawn up on the assumption that there should be no press and broadcast publicity about anti-gas precautions. I appreciate that there are good reasons for such a course of action, but I feel bound to say that the absenceof publicity will make it more difficult to secure a rapid and widespread improve-&apos;ment in the preparedness of the civil population to meet a sudden gas attack.The value of a respirator, for example, lies only partly in the efficiency of therespirator itself. The balance and no small balance depends on the extent towhich the public are practised in the habit of putting it on quickly and wearing it.Even with the aid of advance publicity it is impossible to guarantee that thefirst onset of a gas attack will not result in casualties. The risk must inevitably-be increased possibly quite seriously in view of the immunity we have hithertoenjoyed if there is no public warning of the increased likelihood of gas attack in the near future. I suggest, therefore, that the War Cabinet should review their policy in this matter.H. M.Home Office, January 24, 1941.NOTE.Personal Protection.(a) General public.1. Every member of the public should be in possession of a respirator. Allrespirators have been fitted with an additional filter known as &quot; Contex &quot; toincrease their protection against particulate gases, i.e., arsenical smokes. Thereare over 10 million respirators in national reserve in addition to 3 millionreserves in the hands of local authorities.2. In March 1940 arrangements were made through the Wardens&apos; organi-sation for a special inspection of respirators in the hands of the public. Localauthorities were then asked to institute a system of inspection by Wardens at* W.M. (41) 8, item 4.
regular intervals. The issue of &quot; Contex,&quot; which began in May and continued until September, gave a special opportunity for inspection by Wardens, and thereis reason to believe that this inspection was largely carried out.3. The number of faulty respirators reported at the March 1940 inspectionwas surprisingly small, and the number of unserviceable respirators returned bylocal authorities in the period April to December 1940, was at the rate of lessthan&apos;4 per cent, a year. This evidence is not, of course, conclusive, because thestandard of efficiency of the Wardens&apos; inspection and of their reporting of defectsis not uniform.4. Local authorities are now being instructed to arrange for a furtherthorough inspection of respirators to be carried out by the Wardens. This cannotbe done at the moment, as the Wardens are occupied with the drive for improvedfire-prevention measures, but it is planned to begin by the middle of February.It must be realised that without Press publicity this inspection must take time probably not less than a month as it means house-to-house visits byWardens. This time could possibly be somewhat reduced if limited local publicitywere allowed, e.g., posters inviting the public to bring their respirators to aparticular place for testing.5. Although the public are not carrying their respirators about with themmuch (and this has the advantage that the wear and tear of the respirators is reduced), there are indications that they have not put the gas danger altogetherout of their minds. Thus there is a steady demand for respirators, to replace those lost as a result of bombing.An order to compel the public all to carry their respirators from now on mustbe ruled out on the score of publicity, and there are other objections-it wouldbecome increasingly difficult to enforce if gas were not used. A broadcast messagehas, however, been prepared and is always kept available for issue at a minute&apos;notice, telling the people that the enemy have used gas and that everyone musthave his respirator readily available at all times.(b) Civil Defence Services.6. The Civil Defence Services are equipped with respirators appropriate to their class of work and also with protective clothing. All Civil defence personnel are put through a basic course in anti-gas precautions, including care ofrespirators and protective clothing.(c) General Instructions.7. The general public have been supplied with literature on the subject of gas and public lectures have been held and courses arranged for members of thepublic by local authorities all over the country. It is improbable, however, that more than a small percentage of the general public attend these lectures. Withoutpublicity it is difficult to take effective steps to ensure that the general public are properly educated. A further leaflet has been prepared. This leaflet is designed for household distribution. It is not proposed to issue it at the moment, but tostore it locally until gas is used and then to issue it forthwith. In the meantime,Regional Commissioners have been asked to hold conferences with representativesof local authorities so as to get further instructions going. If public lecturescould be advertised locally, with a certain measure of publicity, this would be helpful.Cleansing Organisation.(a) Civil Defence Services.8. Cleansing facilities are provided at all Civil Defence depots and thecleansing facilities have been arranged on a scale which will permit of the civil defence Services receiving treatment independent of the general public.(b) General Public.9.   There are two classes for whom provision must be made (1) Those who are wounded as well as contaminated;(2) Those who are contaminated only.
Provision has to be made not only for the cleansing of the people, but also for the decontamination of their clothing and the supply of fresh clothing while their own clothes are being decontaminated. The division of responsibility between the Ministry of Home Security and the Health Departments in thismatter has recently been reviewed and it has been decided that the latter shall,in addition to their responsibility for cleansing the persons of the general public and providing new clothing, assume responsibility (hitherto that of the Ministryof Home Security) for the decontamination of their clothing. In order to avoid any interruption, it has been arranged that the Ministry of Home Security will carry through to completion a number of current negotiations, and that theservices of their technical officers will be available to the Health Departments as required.10. For those who are wounded as well as contaminated, arrangements aremade at first aid posts and hospitals. A scale of provision was laid down aconsiderable time ago and steps are being taken to ensure that the authorities concerned carry out the directions already issued.11. With regard to those who are contaminated only, it is judged impracticable-able in England to rely mainly on the first aid posts and hospitals for cleansingthese people. Generally, neither the facilities nor the staff would be adequate for the purpose without serious interruption of their normal functions. In some areas in England arrangements have already been made for cleansing thecontaminated unwounded, e.g., at Public Baths, but generally the provision madefalls short of requirements. Steps are therefore being taken as a matter of urgency to secure increased provision in all areas where the risk of attack isconsidered to be most real.The provision will be met by adaptation of public baths and wash-houses and increased facilities at existing First Aid Posts. The public will also be advised to go at once to their own homes or friends&apos; homes if they are near and cleansethemselves there. It is also hoped to use the services of &quot;Neighbour Groups&quot;or &quot;Housewives&apos; Services&quot; who can direct people to houses where there arewashing facilities. Immediate cleansing is of first importance if injury is to be avoided.12. In Scotland it is considered, subject to any enlargement of the existingscale of provision that might be found necessary, that the number of, and facilities at, hospitals and first aid posts is sufficient to enable contaminatedpeople to be cleansed there, except those who are so lightly contaminated thatthey can go to their own homes.13. Arrangements have already been made with some of the larger chemiststo put on sale to the general public pots of Chloramine-T ointment. In additiona scheme is being worked out for supplies of bleach to be issued in an emergencyto chemists generally. They would then make up bleach cream which could beput in buckets outside their shops, and contaminated members of the publiccould apply the cream themselves.14. For decontamination of clothing of the general public on any large scaleresort must be had to the laundries. Some local authorities have already made arrangements with the laundries, but in many areas the position is unsatisfactory.This is in some degree due to difficulties with the Laundries&apos; Association. further discussions have been taking place and it is hoped that the difficulties have been overcome. If not, it will be necessary in an emergency to use requisitioningpowers.15. Fresh clothes have to be provided for people while their own clothesare being decontaminated. It is hoped to make arrangements to combine thisprovision with the, provision of clothes for homeless persons.Decontamination Squads.16. Decontamination squads are provided by every local authority inaccordance with an establishment laid down. Their duty is to decontaminatestreets, buildings and materials. They have all received special training andare provided with the necessary equipment.   They are not on a whole-time basis.
as the view has been taken that it was unnecessary to have decontaminationsquads always standing by. They are in the main drawn from the men belongingto the cleansing departments of the local authorities.At present these men are reserved by reason of their primary occupation at25, but it is proposed by the Man-Power Committee and the Ministry of Labourand National Service to raise the age to 35. It will be necessary therefore thatthere should be some deferment of the calling-up of a proportion of the menunder 35, and discussions are already taking place on this with the Ministry ofLabour.Anti-Gas Precautions in Shelters.17. In July 1940, instructions were issued that arrangements should bemade for securing that public shelters could be made gas-proof. Now that sheltersare being used for sleeping, adequate ventilation is of the first importance. It is impracticable to reconcile this with efficient gas-proofing. Local authorities aretherefore being informed that further steps to provide gas-proofing in naturallyventilated shelters should not be taken for the present and that reliance must beplaced on the respirator as the first line of defence.



</content>
</cab>
