<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/276/0 images: 24-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
lHI^JDQ.CyMglT-IS,THg, PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S OOVERMvlBET.SECRET COPY NO.      tyO__CP.  77(58)CABINET AGRICULTURAL MARKETING BILL Memorandum by the Mi nj.stsr^ of Agriculture and Fisheries.L. At&apos;the meeting of the Cabinet on the 23rd March itwas agreed that the above Private member&apos;s Bill introduced by Major Procter under the ten-minutes rule should, for the timebeing, be blocked, and that I should prepare a memorandum for the consideration of my colleagues.2. &apos;    The object Of the Bill is to amend the agricultural marketing Acts, 1931 and 1933, under which schemes made under those Acts may contain provisions requiring the board to impose upon and recover from any registered producer, who contravenes - any provision of the scheme, such monetary penalties as may be specified by the scheme.      The Bill accepts the principle that registered producers should be fined for offences against the scheme, but seeks to substitute proceedings before a court of summary jurisdiction.3, The Marketing Acts are based on the principleof industrial self-government.      A marketing scheme cannotcome into operation unless it is accepted by a majority ofthe registered producers voting on a poll, and once a schemeis noted into existence it is binding on all registered producers,save such as are specifically&apos;exempted by or under the scheme.
4. It is recognised that there is some measure ofoppositien to the present powers of the Marketing Boards to impose penalties, although much of this criticism is in-formed,,      The reasons for giving those powers were clearly stated by the then Lord Advocate in Standing Committee on the Agricultural Marketing Bill, 1931:-&quot;It was suggested that the effect of paragraph (c) might be tnat the Board under the Scheme would be in a position of prosecutor and judge.      It would be creating the offence and exacting the penalty.      That may be, but the view is that offences by registered producers which are within the ambit of the Scheme are properly domestic concerns, which ought to be dealt with domestically. Theoretically it is, no doubt,  apen to objection, but in practice, there are many analogies, and ne difficulty arises.      The penalties are specified in the Scheme. They are not in the uncontrolled discretion of the Board.&quot; 5. Before imposing penalties, the Boards must giveproducers the opportunity of being heard.      The suggestion frequently made that the Boards should hear witnesses on bath is based on a misunderstanding of the functions of the Board. A marketing Board is not a oeurt of Law.      The proceedings before it are in no sense legal proceedings but are in the nature of an inquiry to elicit facts before arriving at a decision.      A producer on whom a penalty is imposed has the right to go to arbitration.;    The Arbitration Acts apply, and in default of agreement, the arbitrator is appointed by the Minister.   - The arbitrator may award such penalty (if any) as he thinks just, within the limits, laid down in the scheme. He may sit where he chooses, hear witnesses on oath, and generally apply the Rules of Evidence.
If a Marketing Board exceeds its jurisdiction, its decisions can be made subject to review by the High Court.Contraventions of the scheme are considered by the Board in public. Penalties imposed are recoverable as civil debts.6* The real issue raised by the Bill is v/hethercontraventions are to be regarded as offences against the public weal and punishable under the criminal law or as    , offences against the proper interests of registered producers as a body, but not against those of any one else, and as such punishable under a code of self-discipline.7. Many of the contraventions of marketing schemes arise from breaches of determinations made by Boards under general powers conferred on them by the- schemes.    If the proposed Bill were to become law, and such offences were tried by Courts of Summary Jurisdiction, the effect would be that criminal effences would continually be created by marketing boards.    It is important that the creation of new criminal offences should remain the sole prerogative of the State.    Moreover,  the trial of such actions in the Courts would transfer the issue between the producer and the Board to the State,  and the producer, if convicted, would suffer the stigma of having been convicted for a criminal offence,  although he might not in the least have offended against society,8. The exercise of disciplinary powers by statutory bodiesis no new thing. I need only cite the powers of Trade Unions, and of the governing bodies of the Medical and Legal professions. In addition,  the Coal Mines Act, 1930, contains powers identical with those contained in the Agricultural Marketing Act, 1931. I,The provisions are   repeated in Clause 12 of the Sea ffish Industry Bill of this session, which has passed its Committee
Stage.     Mr. Beec-hman and Mr. Petherick, whose names appearas supporters of Major Procter&apos;s Bill, were members of theStanding Committee that considered the Sea Pish industry bill, but did not propose any amendments to Clause 12..9.. There is not,  in my view,  justification on general grounds for the reversal of policy proposed by the Bill.If there were there would still be some important subsidiaryissues for consideration.     But these need not be considered at the moment, since it seems clear that the subject is not one that can appropriately be dealt with by a PrivateMember1s Bill introduced under the Ten Minute Rule.10,.        In the time available., I have not had an opportunityof consulting the Secretary of State for Scotland, who hasconcurrent jurisdiction in this matter.11.        In the circumstances I recommend that the Government Whips should be instructed to block the Bill.(Intld.)    W. S, M. .Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries. 25th March, 1938..

</content>
</cab>
