<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/276/0 images: 28-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. Q.P.  78 (88).CABINET. SUPPLY OF WAR MATERIAL TO PORTUGAL. Note by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.I circulate herewith,  for the information of my colleagues,  two papers on the subject of the Supply of War Material to Portugal (Annex I and II respectively).2. The above papers were considered by the Committeeatof Imperial Defence on Thursday, the 24th March, and the draft Minutes of the discussion are attached (Annex III).3. I took action- in accordance with Conclusion (a)of the above Minutes,  and the Prime Minister gave the necessary authority to the Foreign Office to take action on the lines suggested.(Intld.)   T.W.H.I.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1., 25th March, 1938.COPY NO.x     G. I.D.  Minutes,  314th Meeting.(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   March 1938. SECRET Copy No.&quot; *w tD.P.R. 259.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.SUPPLY OF WAR MATERIAL TO PORTUGAL. (Previous Paper No. D.P.R. 123.)Note by the Secretary.THE accompanying copy of a letter from the Foreign Office relating to the supply of war material to Portugal is circulated for consideration by the Committee of Imperial Defence, as a matter of urgency, by direction of the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.(Signed) M. P. A. HANKEY.2 Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, March 23, 1938.ENCLOSURE.Copy of a Letter dated March 22, 1938, from the Foreign Office to the Committeeof Imperial Defence.[W 3332/75/36]*   *   *MAY I refer to our official letters* W 3332 and W 3418/75/36 of the 15th and 17th March, covering copies of telegramst from our Ambassador at Lisbon about a proposed exchange of assurances with the Portuguese Government!You will have seen from these telegrams that the Portuguese have suggested an exchange of notes embodying, on our side, an assurance that the integrity and independence of Portugal and her Empire are of the first importance to Great Britain, and that the latter would use all the means at her disposal to assure these ends, in the event of an attack or a real threat of attack, during the period which may elapse between the&apos; placing of arms contracts in the United Kingdom and the actual deliveries. In return for this, Portugal would, it appears, be ready to promise to the United Kingdom not only the artillery contract at present under discussion, but all future contracts for armaments and ammunition of calibres larger than rifles and light machine guns, as well as to undertake to rely in general on the United Kingdom to assist them on the basis described above.If this artillery order is in fact placed in the United Kingdom, it will, of course, ensure not only that the Portuguese army will be armed to a great extent with material similar to our own, but that similar contracts will be placed in this country &apos;for years to come. For the same reason the political importance of preventing this order going to Germany is self-evident. These points were fully appreciated by the Committee of Imperial Defence when they discussed the question in January,\ and finally decided to authorise Vickers to continue negotia-tions with the Portuguese with a view to the eventual conclusion of the contract. At the same time, for reasons connected with our own rearmament, it was evidently* Not reproduced. f Appendices 1, 2 and 3. % F.A.O./2nd Meeting, Minute 3.[16908]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
2doubtful whether the delivery dates which Vickers would be able to offer would, in fact, be attractive enough to secure the order. If, however, as now appears, an assurance on the lines suggested is going not only to clinch the matter of the artillery contract but also to bring in a general undertaking about all arms contracts, except those for rifles and light machine guns, we feel that it deserves the most earnest and favourable consideration possible.        ,To these purely Anglo-Portuguese considerations must be added certain factors which occur to us in connection with the Spanish situation. The proposed assurance would not only allay the anxiety undoubtedly felt by the Portuguese regarding their future relations with Spain, whatever the outcome of the war may be. There is also good reason to suppose that British interests in Spain may suffer very seriously, and, in view of future possibilities, there is every advantage in making it clear, to the world in general and to the coming administration in Spain in particular, that we are strengthening in every way the ties of our alliance with Spain&apos;s co-partner in the Iberian Peninsula. Whichever party may win in Spain, there will undoubtedly be more respect for our interests there and more desire for our goodwill if it is realised that our connection with Portugal has been greatly strengthened.The legal position, as we see it, is briefly as follows : We are clearly bound by treaty obligations to defend Portuguese territory, metropolitan and colonial, in case an attack is made upon it by the armed forces of another State. Though this obligation springs from old treaties, it has been reaffirmed again and again in later instruments. Legally, it can be said to be qualified now only in so far as we should not be obliged to take action which conflicted with the Covenant of the League or the Kellogg Pact. Many times, in response to questions in the House, His Majesty&apos;s Government have acknowledged this obligation, but they have always proceeded then to add an apparent qualification such as the following : &quot; that His Majesty&apos;s Government reserve to themselves the right to determine the circumstances in which help may be given or withheld.&quot; Further, in the various lists His Majesty&apos;s Government have sometimes given of their special obligations to defend foreign territory to Parliament, &amp;c, though they have referred to their allies, Iraq and Egypt, Persian Gulf States and the like, they have sometimes accidentally or intentionally omitted Portugal altogether.The qualifications, which have been added on such occasions to this effect, might only mean that it is for His Majesty&apos;s Government to determine when the casus fcederis had arisen. If so, the words of course are legally correct, but it was quite unnecessary to-say this, because the same observation applies to every possible treaty of alliance (even to some extent where it is provided that another body like the Council of the League is to pronounce on the casus fcederis) and we do not add words of this kind when speaking of obligations as regards (for instance) Egypt or Iraq. It is not unnatural, therefore, for Portugal and the rest of the world to try and read more into these words; and it is natural for them to read the complete answer as meaning : &quot; We are in fact bound to come to PortugaFs assistance by treaty, but we shall reserve our right when the time comes to decide whether we shall fulfil our treaty obligation.&quot;Moreover, if the qualifiation did not mean something of this kind, it is difficult to say exactly why we should have added it. Yet.(apart from the facj^&quot; that a statement of this kind appears to be open admission of a cynical position with regard to treaty obligations which is not in accordance with His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s usual attitude) it can seriously be suggested that to make statements of this kind is emphatically to get the worse of every possible world. We admit the obligation and will probably, as is the British way, actually fulfil it when the time comes. On the other hand, we deprive ourselves of all the advantage that we might have in Portugal by a clear affirmation of the obligation. Further, by pursuing the policy of leaving the world guessing as to what we mean to do we make it all the more likely that a case calling for the fulfilment of that obligation will arise. It seems in effect that we can do all that Sir Walford Selby suggests in his telegrams under reference, without actually increasing our existing legal obligations, by simply reaffirming the existing obligation of assistance arising out of the ancient alliance, without the ambiguous additions hitherto made, and openly placing our obligations to Portugal under the Alliance on the same footing as our obligations to Egypt and Iraq. In short, -we have the obligations and should have to fulfil them if the casusifcederis arose; if there is advantage to be gained by saying so, why not say it&apos;?
We feel at the same time that in offering Portugal a definite statement&apos; of our policy on these lines, we are entitled to ask them for something equally definite in return. &quot;We should, I think, ask for a formal assurance, on the lines already indicated by the Portuguese Under-Secretary of State for War (Sir Walford Selby&apos;s telegram* No. 38 of the 16th March), to the effect that ail contracts for armaments and ammunition of calibres larger than rifles and light machine guns would be placed in Greatr Britain, making it clear that we consider this&apos;definition to include aircraft and their equipment, and also naval material. Armed with such an undertaking, even in the event of our not being able to meet all Portugal&apos;s requirements for these types of war material, we would at any rate be in a position to offer advice which could hardly be disregarded about the quarter in which the order should in fact be placed. We should further make it clear, in the case both of the artillery contract and the future Portuguese orders for arms from this country, that, while every effort will be made to secure the earliest possible delivery, His Majesty&apos;s Government must reserve to themselves the right of determining the delivery dates in view of the requirements of their own rearmament -ment programme. Again, we feel that in the interests of precision we might omit the reference in the Portuguese formula to the somewhat ill-defined eventuality of &quot;a real threat of attack.&quot; Finally, we should propose that the exchange of notes, or its substance, should be made public.In view of the necessity for an immediate decision, in the absence of which the artillery order will probably go to Germany in a week or two, I should be very grateful if you would let me know as soon as possible whether the Committee of Imperial Defence would have any objection to an exchange of notes on these lines. We have, in fact, told the Ambassador that we hope to let him have our reply in a few days.I am sending copies of this letter to Troup, Pownall and Boyle.WWW(Signed) GEORGE MOUNSEY.Appendix 1 to Enclosure.Copy of a telegram, No. 36, dated March 14, 1938, from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Lisbon to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.HEAD of Military Mission reports that, during frank unofficial conversation on 12th March with their Portuguese colleagues on armaments, it was made clear by Portuguese that they are alarmed at their state of defencelessness during long period which they fear may elapse between placing of contracts in Great Britain and actual deliveries.British Mission believe that this is real key to difficulties which have arisen hitherto as regards Portuguese re-armament policy and were given to understand that a statement by His Majesty&apos;s Government (if necessary in secret) 6n lines of that made by Prime Minister on 7th March in House of Commons, but addressed specifically to Portugal, assuring her Government that whole weight of Great Britain&apos;s influence and other available resources would be brought to bear in event of attack or real threat of attack during such period would remove present hesitation to [ 1 group omitted : rely] solely on Great Britain.It was suggested to head of Portuguese Mission that such effective guarantee could not be expected without corresponding assurance from Portuguese Government to effect that they would so rely on Great Britain. This suggestion appeared to be accepted by him as a natural and reasonable corollary likely to be acceptable&apos; to Portuguese Government. I have discussed this with Military Mission and am in general agreement; -please see my immediately following telegram.* Appendix 3.
Appendix 2 to Enclosure.Copy of a telegram, No. 37, dated March 14,  1938, from His Majesty-&apos;s Ambassador&apos;in Lisbon to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.MY immediately preceding telegram.Portuguese experts seem to realise that military danger threatens from a. clear-cut victory by Franco as well as by Spanish Government reverse. They are impressed by discovery of an Italian mechanised unit close to Portuguese frontier which has hitherto taken no part in fighting in Spain.I hear that Germans are pressing their artillery tender (see my telegrams Nos. 20 and 29) and are being indirectly helped by delay in submission of British tender. I hear confidentially that they have offered to supply whole Portuguese artillery requirements for about  4 million, some 60 per cent, of which would be paid for in colonial produce. This offer, face-value of which is deceptive, may attract Portuguese Government, especially if Messrs. Vickers&apos; tender is delayed much longer, or if it is found to be highly priced when submitted.If you agree on feasibility of guarantee proposed in my immediately preceding telegram, I suggest matter should now be put on a higher plane, and that I should be authorised at once to ask Dr. Salazar officially whether Portuguese Government will be prepared to respond as suggested if His Majesty&apos;s Government give proposed guarantee.I feel, in the absence of some such definite action at present moment, Portuguese may slip into the arms of authoritarian States.Appendix 3 to Enclosure.Copy of a telegram, No. 38, dated March 16,  1938, from His Majesty&apos;s-Ambassador, Lisbon, to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.MY telegrams Nos. 36 and 37.Admiral Wodehouse had a conversation with Head of Portuguese Mission on the 15th March at the latter&apos;s request. Head of Portuguese Mission delivered a message from the Under-Secretary of State for War that,: if an exchange of notes could be arranged, all the Under-Secretary of State&apos;s difficulties would be-removed and all contracts for armaments and ammunition of calibres larger than rifles and light machine guns would be placed in Great Britain. Portuguese Government are already committed to Mauser rifles and Dreyse guns (see my despatch No. 53), and state that they have made arrangements for manufacture of ammunition for these in Portugal.2. This conversation is of great significance as the Under-Secretary of State for War has been under suspicion for some time as being in the hands of Germany and Italy. Admiral Wodehouse is strongly of opinion that, if an exchange of notes can be arranged in which Great Britain will reaffirm that integrity and independence of Portugual and her Empire are of first importance to Great Britain and that she would take all means at her disposal to ensure these ends, the danger of Portugal drifting away from-alliance and difficulties as regards co-operation, facilities in war and placing of orders for material would be resolved.
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   March 1938.SECRET D.P,R. 260.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.SUPPLY OF WAR MATERIAL TO PORTUGAL. (Previous Paper No. D.P.R. 259.)Note by the Secretary.THE attached note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Armament Orders from Foreign Countries relating to the supply of war material to Portugal is circulated for consideration by the Committee of Imperial Defence, as a matter of urgency, by direction of the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.(Signed) M. P. A. HANKEY.2 Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, March 23, 1938.ENCLOSURE.Note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Armament Orders from ForeignCountries. -       -THE Sub-Committee on Armament Orders from Foreign Countries had before it to-day a War Office letter stating that Messrs. Vickers, as the result of previous discussions with the Portuguese Government entered into with the cognisance of the Committee, have now been asked to quote as quickly as possible actual delivery dates for artillery equipments on British Service patterns, equivalent to those specified in the attached list.*It is understood that a German offer of supply has been made to the Portuguese Government, and that an answer forthwith is therefore requisite.While fully appreciating (1) the special political case for sanctioning this supply to Portugal, more especially with a British Military Mission in the country, (2) the deleterious effect in the long run of preventing acceptance of foreign orders by munitions firms in this country, the Sub-Committee come with regret to the conclusion that commencement of delivery under this order before 1940 could not be approved, without certainty of very grave damage to the defence programme, more especially in respect of (a) Admiralty gun require-ments, (b) requirements for the rearmament of the Field Artillery.I was asked to report the above conclusion at once, as it was understood that the matter needed decision forthwith and the Foreign Office had it in mind to suggest for consideration at the next meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence a settlement of the Portuguese rearmament question in favour of British industry on lines raising somewhat wide political issues.(Initialled) W. A. R.March 22, 1938.* Appendix. - /Copy No.   101r[16909JTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
2Appendix to Enclosure.Extract from Translation of Letter received by Vickers from&apos;&apos; the Sub-Secretaryof State for War.Jfe Ji. Jfc&apos; Ji. M, M.w -7V&quot; ffc W -VT &apos; W(a) Guns.1st.   Horse-drawn.27 Batteries,       108-87 mm. (3-45-inch) Equipments.2nd.   Tractor-drawn (motorized).24 Batteries, ire:, 96-87 mm. (3-45-inch) Equipments. 10 Batteries, i.e., 40-152 mm.. (6-inch) Howitzers. 12 Batteries, i.e., 48-60 pdr. (5-inch) Equipments.9 Batteries, i.e., 36-94 mm. (3-7-inch) HA. Equipments.9 Batteries, i.e., 36-40 mm. H.A. Equipments.It would be desirable that the 27 horse-drawn 87mm. Batteries could also be drawn by tractor.(b) Ammunition.102,000 complete rounds for 87 mm. (3-45-inch) Equipments.10,000 complete rounds for 152 mm. (6-inch) Howitzer.14,400 complete rounds for 60-pdr. (5-inch) Equipments.18,000 complete rounds for 94 mm. H.A. Equipments.36,000 complete rounds for 40 mm. H.A. Equipments.Drawings, dimensions and other technical information necessary for the manufacture in Portugal, in State Arsenals or their subsidiaries, of the said ammunition should be supplied with the ammunition stated above and also the licence to manufacture for the Portuguese Home and Colonial Army only.Descriptions of all the types of material, with drawings or photographs, ballistic data, &amp;c, should be delivered to the Ministry of War with their required tender for supply. It is again confirmed that the Portuguese Ministry of War will only be interested in artillery material of British manufacture if it is exactly equal to that used in the British Army and with which the British Army reckons for mobilization, and war stock models or antiquated types will not be acquired.*M, MJ iA(. JA. M.&quot;7V1 ,&quot;71* &quot;/V -A&quot; W
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   March 1938. SECRET. Copy No.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the DRAFT Minutes of the 314th Meeting held on March 24, 1938.&apos;    * * * * * *(5)-SUPPLY OF WAR MATERIAL TO PORTUGAL. (Papers Nos. D.P.R. 259 and 260.) (Previous reference :  D.P.R. Minutes of the 27th Meeting, Minute 2.)THE COMMITTEE had under consideration the following papers :  (a) Note by the Secretary, covering a letter from the Foreign Office relatingto the supply of war material to Portugal.   (Paper No. D.P.R. 259.)(b) Note by the Chairman of the Sub-Committee on Armament Orders from foreign Countries.   (Paper No. D.P.R. 260.)SIR ROBERT VANSITTART explained the Foreign Office proposal for an exchange of Notes between Great Britain and Portugal which had followed on the discussions regarding the contract for the rearmament of the Portuguese artillery. Unless something was done, not only was the order for the Portuguese artillerjr equipments at stake, but our whole position in relation to the supply of arms to Portugal would be prejudiced. It was well knoAvn that Germany and Italy were making a strong anti-British drive in Portugal. The proposal was so eminently justifiable that he hoped that it would meet with the full approval of the Committee.SIR THOMAS INSKIP thought that the Committee&apos;s duty was almost too obvious. In return for an unequivocal statement of policy by Great Britain; we were to receive an assurance that all the Portuguese armament contracts would be placed in the United Kingdom. He suggested that, subject to the approval of the Foreign Secretary, he should, in advance of next Wednesday^ Meeting of the Cabinet, recommend the Prime Minister to authorise an exchange of Notes.SIR ROBERT VANSITTART said that Lord Halifax was in full agree-ment with the proposal.SIR SAMUEL HOARE considered that the exchange of Notes on the lines suggested by the Foreign Office was essential and should be done at once.Mr. STANLEY referred to the statement in Sir Arthur Robinson&apos;s Paper that delivery of the order could not start before 1940 without very grave damage to our own defence programme.SIR THOMAS INSKIP pointed out that under the Foreign Office proposal His Majesty&apos;s Government reserved &quot; to themselves the right of determining the delivery dates, in view of the requirements of their own re-armament programme.&quot;SIR MAURICE HANKEY asked whether we were making any provision at all to deal with all the foreign orders to which we were committed. If not, it would take years and years.&apos;   [16930-1]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
SIR ARTHUR ROBINSON said it was&apos; contemplated that-Messrs. Vickers could begin.gun. deliveries to Portugal in 1940. .   -y-t^t0&apos;j&apos;.-.r, oc.; toMr. HORE-BELISHA said that as&quot; there appeared to be ho question of giving : Portuguese requirements priority over orir own, he hoped that the suggestion would be adopted. Nevertheless, it ought to be realised that we made no provision for capacity to meet this type of order,&apos;which not Only came from Portugal, but also from Egypt, Iraq and Belgium, to say nothing of the Dominions.. In. the light of the new Cabinet policy, he considered- it would be wise to allocate a pool of capacity to meet foreign orders.    ;   ,:SIR ROBERT VANSITTART pointed out that on page 3 of the Foreign Office Memorandum it was pointed out that even if we ourselves could not meet all Portuguese requirements for war material, we should be in a position to offer advice as to the quarter in which the orders could be placed. This had been done in the case of Egypt.   vLORD WEIR said that the reason why we had always been able to accept foreign orders for warships was that we had a steady demand for the British Navy and consequently a strong shipbuilding industry as a background.. With our small Army we had no industrial background for orders for field artillery, and there was hardly any inducement for firms to go into that business.LORD WINTERTON stressed the value of the armament export trade, especially as some countries would be satisfied with a long-term policy. Germany was supplying arms to foreign countries and as a result we lost both politically and economically.- SIR RICHARD HOPKINS said that even with a long-term policy the question of payments for armament supplies would arise.SIR ARTHUR ROBINSON said that Messrs. Vickers had been instructed to sound the Portuguese authorities on that point.(Sir Samuel Hoare left at this point.)SIR REGINALD HENDERSON said that the Admiralty were being pressed to undertake orders from Turkey, which country was presumably as important as Portugal.   They also had demands from Chile.LORD SWINTON stressed the importance of having a priority list of armament supply to foreign countries.SIR THOMAS INSKIP explained that this matter was dealt with by the Subcommittee on Armament Orders from Foreign Countries; priority lists had been prepared, and were the subject of periodical review.Conclusions.       . The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed (a) That, subject to the concurrence of Lord Halifax, the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence should recommend to the Prime Minister that he should authorise, in advance of next&apos; Wednesday&apos;s meeting of the Cabinet, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to arrange for an exchange of Notes between His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Portuguese Government, embodying, on our side, an assurance that the integrity and independence of Portugal and her Empire are of.;, the first importance to Great Britain, and that the latter would use allthe means at her disposal to assure these ends, in the event of an attack during the period which may elapse between the placing of- arms contracts in the United Kingdom and the actual deliveries-; andon behalf of Portugal a formal assurance to the effect that all contracts for armaments and ammunition of calibres larger than rifles and light machine guns would be placed in Great. Britain, it being made clear that this definition should include aircraft and their equipment, and also naval material. . ,
: That in the exchange&quot; of&apos; Notes? it should&apos; be made clear in the case both of the artillery contract now under consideration and the future .. ,,x...., Portuguese orders for.arms from this country, that, while-every; effort *,..-:&quot; ;&apos;. will be. made to secure, the earliest possible delivery,&apos; Pi is Majesty&apos;s .&apos;, Government must reserve to themselves the ,right.. of ^de^erminingotBe ...  &quot;delivery dates ifr view of the requirements of their own. rearmament ...&quot;  ... -programme. -r.- r; &apos;   U tdi-io^(c) That tbe exchange of. Notes or its substance should be made public..   /&apos; -(d) That the above conclusions should be reported to the Cabinet.   . .Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1. March 24, 1938.

</content>
</cab>
