<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/276/0 images: 141-146</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT*       -------- ,TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.SECRET.CP.   87 (38). . COPY NO. t/4CAB I N E T. PROPOSALS FOR ACCELERATION OF THE AIR PROGRAMME. Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.1.      The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence has referred in his paper (CP. 86 (38)) to the relation between Scheme L, as now submitted by the Secretary of State for Air, and the decision already reached by the Cabinet providing for the due distribution and use of our available resources.2.      As the result of detailed examination and discussion,extending over several months in the latter part of last year,and the preparation and consideration of the reviews of theMinister for Co-ordination of Defence (CP.  316 (37) and cp. 24 (38)), the Cabinet on 16th February, 1938, reachedthe following conclusion:-&quot;That the figure of  1,650 millions should be taken as the maximum sum which can be regarded as available for all defence purposes over the five years. 1937,-41&quot; (Cabinet 5 (38) Conclusion 9 (a) (i)).Of this  1,650 millions,  80 millions was earmarked for expenditure on Air Raid Precautions, other Civil defence measures, and interest on borrowed money.      This leaves 1,570 millions for the three Defence Departments.3.      The Cabinet further agreed that the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence should prepare a plan for the allocation of the  1,570 millions between the three Defence
5.      The Secretary of State for- Air states that the best estimate of cost of Scheme L which he can give is the estimate of  567 millions over the five years 1937-41, already given for Scheme K.      This estimate is, however, given with reserve, as it is Impossible to estimate with precision the cost of acceleration^6.      Since Scheme L contemplates a slightly larger force than Scheme K,  it is clear&apos;that Scheme L can hardly cost less than Scheme K, and may well cost a good deal more.7.     When the Secretary of State for Air proposed to theCabinet on 14th March than Scheme K should be adopted,  theMinister for Co-ordination of Defence and I both pointed outthat this was inconsistent with the Cabinet decision quoted in paragraph 2 above.      Thus:-&quot;The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence confirmed.the view of the Chancellor of the Exchequer that the adoption of Scheme K , would wreck the Armament Programmes recently adopted by the Cabinet.      This was shown by certain sketch-figures which he had sent out to Departments as a basis for discussion in the allocation of the available funds.      The adoption of Scheme K would mean the alloca-tion of so much of the available money to the Air Force as to reduce the quota avail-able to the Navy and Army very seriously&quot;a8.      The Prime Minister in his announcement to Parliament on 24th March stated that further efforts should be made to increase production, and to &quot;accelerate the completion of theDepartments.     The Minister has explained in his paper the steps which he has taken to make provisional allocations.4.      The Cabinet on 16th February also agreed that there should be a further enquiry in 1939 to consider whether it is on balance necessary and possible to authorise programmes of wider scope and involving greater expenditure than those which can be compassed within  1,570 millions.
illRearmament Programme&quot;.      Acceleration, however,, need not necessarily involve any substantial increase in cost, though it may lead to expenditure being incurred in an earlier rather than a later*year.9.      The Prime Minister also stated that &quot;there must be an increase in some parts of the Programme, especially in that of the Royal Air Force and the Anti-Aircraft defences.&quot;     ButI, at any rate, never understood this to mean abandonment of the decisions reached by the Cabinet in February last.10.    As I see the matter, what is required in order to carry out the policy implicit in the&apos; Prime Minister&apos;s announcement to Parliament on the 24th March, is a programme for accelerating the completion of the existing Air Force Programme,  together with some increase in the first-line strength.      The need for such increase, (particularly in fighters), was recognised in the reports of the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence on Defence Expenditure, and I accept it.     This should not involve &quot;wrecking&quot; the financial limitations adopted by the Cabinet  . six weeks ago, though I recognise that whatever scheme is agreed to now is not necessarily final, and that the Air Programme, like the rest of the Defence Programmes, will again be subject to review.II. In my view,  therefore, the degree of expansion nowauthorised should be considerably less than that asked for bythe Secretary of State for Air, but the scheme now authorisedshould be so planned as to permit of further expansion if, ata later date,  this should be deemed necessary. k12. I appreciate the force of the arguments adduced by the Secretary of State for Air against the adoption of a course such as is here indicated.     A long-period programme is
- o3*^.rx*usly... pcf.-^gr*e^^ in planning production orders and in arranging for the intake of personnel and so forth-      I cannot, however,  feel that these difficulties should prove insuperable.*   Moreover, about a year ago the Secretary of State for&quot; Air was authorised to take certain. steps which went beyond the then authorised pr._grarrx.ie ,  but which would facili-tate the adoption of a further expansion scheme (Scheme H), if decided upon.      I should he willing to agree to a limited expenditure on measures of. a similar character to those then adopted, as a foundation for a further expansion, should this prove necessary.13.    There are two further points to which I would make some reference.      The Air Ministry proposal involves the placing in the immediate future of the very large contracts necessary for the attainment of the increased first-line air strength proposed and of reserves on the Scheme K scale.      The Secretary of State states that he hopes to obtain completion of the new&apos; first-line air strength together with reserves on the Scheme K scale by March, 1940.      Can this be done?     The assumption is that the additional labour force required, estimated in the region of 100,000,  is obtainable at the .dates, and in the numbers necessary.      At the present time, there can, of course-, be no assurance that the very large increase in labour envisaged will,  in fact-, be obtainable,  in which case the carrying out- of the new programme proposed might well extend over a far longer period than 2 years.14c    We ought, I think, most seriously to consider whether the sounder and.more business-like plan is not that we should now organise a smaller degree of expansion, within the limits of the resources which are in sight;    while at the same time making plans so that,  if at a later date further additions are
&quot; 11decided upon, these additions can he easily fitted into the scheme originally approved.15.    Another consideration concerns the relationship between the strength already attained by the Royal Air Force and its readiness for war, (including the provision of reserves). The past 3 years have seen a succession of schemes for the progressive expansion of the Royal Air Force.      In consequence, the figure given for the first-line strength at present attained is, I understand, substantially larger than the mobilisable strength, while the reserves behind the existing first-line strength are far below the standards aimed at: (particulars on this matter were given in a recent C.I.D. paper, D.-P.(P).  22).      J%  mm       - a.inim*mi&quot;*vif&quot;-&quot;&quot;WOMWIWHtt16.    These considerations raise serious doubts whether the right course really is that the Air Ministry should now be authorised to place orders and incur commitments in respect of a scheme foreshadowing so large an expansion of our first-line strength, rather .than concentrating our main endeavours on improving the readiness for war of the force already authorised,  and building up reserves behind the first-line-. ,/17.    Recent&apos;events in Europe, serious as they are, have done nothing to increase the financial resources of this country, to diminish the vital importance of those resources as an essential element in our defensive strength, or to change the force of the proposition approved by the Cabinet in February last that  1,650 millions (of which  1,570 millions is for the three Defence Services) was the maximum which should be regarded as available for defence purposes over the five years 1937-41.     Acceleration is justified, but does not involve abandoning this proposition.      I recognise that something more than Scheme F, which is the scheme at present authorised,  is
necessary and is attainable within our available resources. But I submit that we should not approve Scheme L, but instead that we should ask the Air Ministry to plan as rapidly as possible a further expansion of the Metropolitan Air Force which will go beyond Scheme F but which will not involve the extremely serious commitments of Scheme L.18.    This intermediate scheme should be complete in itself, and should be so devised as to permit of yet further expansion if, on a later review, it should be decided that this course is both necessary and attainable within the limits of our available resources.      The completion of this intermediate scheme should be pressed forward to the utmost extent found practicable.(ihtld.) J.S.4th April, 1938.

</content>
</cab>
