<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/276/0 images: 487-488</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.AGRICULTURAL MARKETING SCHEMES. powers of Boards to Impose and Recover penalties.MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES.1.      In my memorandum CP. 77 (38) dated 25th March, 1938,. I sought the views cf my colleagues on the action to he taken with regard to the Private Member&apos;s Bill introduced by Major Procter, which proposed to amend the provisions of the Agricultural Marketing Acts, 1931 and 1933 under which schemes made under those Acts may contain provisions requiring the board to impose penalties upon and recover from any registered , producer who contravenes any provision *f the scheme,  such J:.. monetary penalties as may he specified by the scheme.2.      The Cabinet decided (Cabinet 17 (38), Conclusion 10) -(i) To approve the proposal of the Minister of Agriculture-and Fisheries in CP.-77 (38) and summarised above, that the Government Whips should be instructed to block the Agricultural Marketing Bill.(ii) That   the whole question should be considered by theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries in consultation with the Secretary of State for Scotland.3.      The question was again debated in the House ofCommons on 7th April, 1938,  on an amendment to the Sea fish industry Bill moved on Report by Mr. Dingle Foot.      On that occasion I said -&quot;I will consider all that has been said in its wider aspect in relation to the entire system of agricultural marketing,  and if greater justice can be brought about is, I shall be happy to consider what can be done;   but in the meantime,  I ask the House not to make a piecemeal alteration in the matter involving the important principle of industrial self-discipline&quot;.The amendment was defeated.4.      I drew attention,  in CP.77 (38), to the fact that agricultural marketing boards are not the only statutory bodiesS C R E T.CABINET.1 P.118(38).1.
who exercise disciplinary powers.   .  It seems desirable,therefore, to &quot;the Secretary of State for Scotland and myselfthat the question of procedure should be examined by ourDepartments in consultation with the other Departmentsconcerned.      At a recent inter-Departmental conference onthe subject it was agreed that Ministers should be advised -(i) that the question should be remitted to a DepartmentalCommittee comprising members with a knowledge oflaw, administration and industrial and agriculturalorganisation (including probably two or three members of Parliament with these qualifications)5(ii) that the terms *f reference might be:&quot;To enquire into the present arrangements for the imposition and recovery of penalties for contraventions of schemes established under Statute for the organisation of agriculture and other industries, to consider whether any modifications *f -these arrangements are desirable and practicable, and to make recommendations&quot;;(iii) that.in view of the general tissues involved theCommittee might be appointed by Treasury Minute.5.    . The Secretary of State for Scotland and I concur in these recommendations and submit them for approval.6.    . If these recommendations are approved it is proposed that an early opportunity should be taken to announce in the House of Commons, by Question and Answer, that it is intended to appoint a Committee with the above terms *f reference,     :The personnel, which may take a little time to settle, could be agreed subsequently between the Ministers concerned.* W.  S. M.19th May, 1938,

</content>
</cab>
