<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/129/0 images: 214-214</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I /   7 ?//^ lima &amp;MrV&amp;&amp;*[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1921.SECRET.CP. .CABINET. TURKEY.Since the latest telegram from the Viceroy on the Turkish question (CP. 3412) I have received the following telegram from the Governor of Bombay on the same subject.E. S. M.18th October 1921.From Governor of Bombay, 15th October 1921.Moslem question. In view of present situation in India, I feel bound to urge once more upon you my opinion that it is imperative that action should be taken on the Turkish question, which should restore the lost faith of Islam in our attitude towards it. My point of view, and my anxiety to assist in this question, is well known to you from various private letters and telegrams that have reached you from me, but once again an opportunity, so it seems to me, presents itself in the exhaustion of both the combatants in Anatolia, and in other factors of the situation which should be taken immediate advantage of to put Englancfs position right. In regard to above, I have all along held view that, shorn of the Khilafat question, the non-co-operation movement is easily settled, but so long as all Moslems in India are either actively hostile or sore and distrustful, as they are at present, the situation will remain serious.We have now for very many months tried by patience and firmness to save situation from becoming worse out here, but I can only repeat what I have so often urged, that unless we get back to a policy of reconciliation with Islam the situation in India may at any moment become a grave one.I hope you will not think that I have misread either this situation or the home difficulties, but I have spent most of my life in studying Islam in Turkey and else-where, and I am absolutely confident that a continuation of our present policy towards Islam, or what appears to the public to be our policy towards Islam, will lead to results fatal to our rule in the East.4753     100 10.21

</content>
</cab>
