<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/129/0 images: 236-240</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EGRETRefer red to Committee of Home affairs this Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Maj88ty&apos;s Government.National Health Insurance (Prolongation of Insurance) Bill.MEMORANDUM.The provisions of the National Health Insurance Acts under which persons cease to be insured on com-completing twelve months of unemployment and the corre-sponding provisions with respect to insured women who marry have been found to give rise to cases of hardship in the present period of prolonged unemployment. The Bill, therefore, proposes to prolong the insurance of persons who are able to show that their absence from work has been due not to any change in their normal occupation, but to inability to obtain employment.The cost of providing benefits in these cases will fall on the funds of Approved Societies, and no additional cost to the Exchequer beyond the normal statutory contribution is involved. .178-2.a
[11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.]   National Health Insurance (Prolongation of Insurance).DRAFTOP AB I  L LTOExtend temporarily  the period  during which a.d. 1921. persons who are unemployed   may  remain insured under the general provisions of the National Health Insurance Acts, 1911 to 1921.BE it enacted hy the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, hy and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : 1. (1) Where an insured person, being a memher of Extension of an approved society, continues to be unemployed after the period during expiration of the period of twelve months mentioned in ^Q^ceasbo-subsection (1) of section thirteen of the National Health to be em- b10 Insurance Act, 1918 (which relates to the position of ployed may insured persons ceasing to he employed), he shall, not- return in-withstanding anything in that subsection, remain while sured-this Act continues in force an insured person if and   ^Geo-5-so long as the conditions laid down by this section are  &apos; &quot;&quot;15 fulfilled in his case.(2) The conditions to be fulfilled by an insured person for the purposes of this section are (a) that the approved society of which he is a memher is  satisfied,  or in the case of a20 dispute it is decided in manner provided bythe National Insurance Act, 1911, that the 1 &amp; 2 Geo. 5. insured person has not since the commence- c- 55-ment of the period aforesaid been unemployed for any reason other than inability to obtain25 employment, or such incapacity for work as is mentioned in subsection (4) of the said section thirteen; and178-2 A
National Health Insurance   [11 &amp; 12. Geo. 5.] (Prolongation of Insurance).A.D. 1921.Amendment of provisions relating to continuance in insurance of married women.Short title and opera-tion,(6) That the total number of the contributions, to he calculated in the prescribed manner, paid by or in respect of the insured person during the two years ending on the fourth day of July, nineteen hundred and twenty, was not less 5 than eighty, or in the case of a person who entered into insurance after the first day of July, nineteen hundred and eighteen, that the total numher of contributions, calculated as aforesaid, paid by or in respect of him either 10 during the period between the date on which he entered into insurance and the thirty-first day of December, nineteen hundred and twenty, or during the period between the date on which he entered into insurance and the date 15 on which he ceased to he &quot;employed, was a numher not less than three-quarters of the numher of weeks comprised in the period.2. The provisions of subsection (1) of section twenty-two of the National Health Insurance Act, 1918 (which 20 relates to the position of a married woman who ceases to be employed), shall not, while this Act continues in force, apply in the case of any woman as respects whom the approved society of which she is a member is satisfied, or as respects whom in the case of a dispute it is decided 25 in manner provided hy the National Insurance Act, 1911, that she did not voluntarily cease work, and that since the date on which she ceased work, she has, except when incapable of work by reason of some specific disease or some bodily or mental disablement, heen available for, 30 but unable to obtain, employment.3.   (1) This Act may he cited as the  National Health Insurance (Prolongation of Insurance) Act, 1921, and shall be included among the Acts which may he cited together as the National Health Insurance Acts, 1911 35 to 1921.(2) This Act shall be deemed to have had effect as from and after the thirty-first day of December, nineteen hundred and twenty, and shall continue in operation until the thirty-first day of December, nineteen hundred and 40 twenty-two :Provided that (a) if any person who has hy virtue of the pro-, visions of this Act remained in insurance is at
[11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.]   National Health Insurance 3(Prolongation of Insurance).the date of the expiration of this Act, or was A.D. 1921. within the period of four weeks preceding that.       &quot; date, incapable of work, he shall not cease to be an insured person until four weeks after 5 the date on which he again becomes capableof work; and (b) no person shall by virtue of the provisions of this Act become entitled to any benefit in respect of any period before the passing of 10 this Act.t
National Health Insurance(Prolongation of Insurance).DRAFTOF AB  I  L  .LTo extend temporarily the period during which persons who are unemployed may remain insured under the general provisions of the National Health Insurance Acts, 1911 to 1921.CXXXIX.   (2.)26th October 1921.178-2

</content>
</cab>
