<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/129/0 images: 241-244</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
the Property   f^&apos;i;y&apos;b&apos; Govern    nt.Ill &amp; 12 Geo. 5.] Facilities. 1DEAF TOP  A .BILLTOAuthorise the Treasury to guarantee the payment a.d. 1921. of loans to be applied towards the carrying out of capital undertakings, or in the purchase of articles manufactured in the United Kingdom required for the purposes of any such under-takings, and to amend the Overseas Trade (Credits and Insurance) Act, 1920, and the -Overseas Trade (Credits and Insurance) Amend-ment Act, 1921.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : 1.-^(1) If the Treasury are satisfied that the pro- Power of ceeds of any loan proposed to he raised, whether within Treasury to , or without the United Kingdom, by any government, j^&quot;mtcc any public  authority,   or  any  corporation   or  other oans&apos;10 hody of persons, are to be applied towards or in con-nection with the carrying out of any capital undertaking, or in, or in connection with, the purchase of articles manufactured in the United Kingdom required for the purposes of any such undertaking, and that the application15 of the loan in the manner proposed is calculated to promote employment in the United Kingdom, the Treasury may, subject to the provisions of this section, guarantee in such manner and form and on such terms and conditions as ; they think proper the payment of the interest and principal20 of the loan or of either interest or principal:173-5CP.3423ThinHis liDrrytent i
2Trade Facilities.    [11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.]A,D. 1021.        Provided that the aggregate capital amount of the Joans the principal or interest of which is guaranteed under this section shall not exceed the sum of twenty-five million pounds.(2) No guarantee shall he given hy the -Treasury 5 under this section after the expiration of twelve months from the commencement of this Act.(3) Such sums as may from time to time he required hy the Treasury for fulfilling any guarantees, given under this section shall he charged on and issued out of the 10 Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof.(4) All sums paid from time, to time in or towards the repayment of any sum issued out of the Consolidated Fund under this section shall be paid into the Exchequer. 15(5) The Treasury shall, as soon as maybe after the expiration of each quarter of the year during which guarantees maybe given under this section, lay before both Houses of Parliament a statement of the guarantees given under this section during that quarter, and shall, so long as 20 any such guarantees are in force, lay before both Houses of Parliament in every year within one month after the thirty-first day of March an account up to that date of the total sums, if any, which have been either issued out of the Consolidated Fund under this section or paid in or 25 towards repayment of any money so issued.(6) In this section the expression &quot;capital under-taking &quot;means an undertaking involving capital expen-diture.Amendment        2. (1) The provisions of the Overseas Trade (Credits 30 of 10 &amp; ll   .an(i Insurance) Act, 1920 (inthis section ref erred to as &quot;the rod ll &amp; ^2 PrmciPa^ Act &quot;) as amended by the Overseas Trade (Credits Geo. 5 c, 26. an^ Insurance) Amendment Act, 1921 (in this section referred to as &quot;the amending Act &quot;), shall be extended so as to authorise the granting of credits and the giving of 35 guarantees in respect of export transactions between the United Kingdom and any other, country whatsoever. -(2) In subsection (2) of section two of the principal Act (which makes provision with,respect to the period within which credits granted under that Act are to be liquidated), 40 for the words&quot; some date not later than six years from the &quot;said eighth day of September,-nineteen hundred and &quot; nineteen/&apos;there shall be substituted the words &quot;some
[11 &amp; 12 G-eo. 5.]      Trade Facilities.3&quot; date not later than eight years from the said eighth&apos; a.d. 1921. &quot; day of September, nineteen hundred and nineteen,&quot;   and in proviso (a) to subsection (1) of section one of the amending Act (which limits the period, within which 5 guarantees are to remain in force) for the words &quot; eighth day of September, nineteen hundred and twenty-five,&quot; there shall be substituted the words &quot;eighth day of September, nineteen hundred and twenty-seven,&quot; and notwithstanding anything in the principal Act as amended 10 by the amending Act the power of the Board of Trade to renew a guarantee may be exercised at any time so long as no guarantee is&quot; in force after the eighth day of September, nineteen hundred and twenty-seven.(3) This section shall be construed as one with the 15 principal Act and the amending Act, and those Acts and this section may be cited together as the Overseas Trade Acts, 1920 and 1921.3. :(1) This Act may be cited as the Trade Facilities Short titleAct, 1921. -       and repeal.20 (2) The enactments set out in the Schedule to this Act are hereby repealed to the extent. mentioned in the third column of that Schedule.SCHEDULE.Enactments Repealed.25     Session and Chapter.- Short.Title.. Extent of Repeal.3010&amp;11 Geo.5. c. 29.The ^Overseas -Trade (Credits and Insurance) Act, 1920.  &apos;Id section one the words &quot;. being one of the countries &quot; specified in the Schedule &quot; to this Act&quot; and the words &quot; specified in the . &quot; Schedule to this Act &quot; ; section three ; Schedule.11&amp;12 Geo.5. 35    c- 26-Theie Overseas Trade (Credits and Insurance) Amendment Act,. 1921.Section two.
Trade Facilities.DRAFTOF ABILLTo authorise the Treasury to guarantee the payment of loans to be applied towards the carrying out of capital undertakings, or in the purchase of articles manufactured in the United Kingdom required for the purposes of any such undertakings, and to amend the Overseas Trade (Credits and Insurance) Act, 1920, and the Overseas Trade (Credits and Insur-ance) Amendment Act, 1921.CXXXV.   (5.)20k October 1921.173-5

</content>
</cab>
