<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/129/0 images: 306-309</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]-.-Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1921.SECRET. &quot; C.P.-3437.CABINET.WEEKLY SURVEY OF THE STATE OF IRELAND. ;Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland.I SUBMIT for the consideration of the Cabinet my survey for the week ended the 17th instant.General State of the Country.Observance of the Truce.Although the complaints of drilling and of Sinn Fein Court activities show no diminution, there have been no collisions between members of the Crown Forces and the I.R.A. such as occurred during the preceding two weeks, notably at Tipperary, Galway and Dunmanway. The most serious breaches of the truce have been the illegal arrests of civilians, either for the purpose of bringing them before the Sinn Fein Courts or in order to prevent them appearing as parties, witnesses or officials before the legally established Courts of the country. The number of illegal arrests reported during the past week was twenty, of which seven were of persons who are known or believed to have been taken before Sinn Fein Courts, and seven of persons who attendance before the ordinary Courts was thereby prevented. In addition, two-cases were reported of persons being succesfully intimidated from proceeding with actions instituted by them in the ordinary Courts.The boycott of British and Belfast goods is being actively pressed, and attempts have recently been made in the Six Ulster Counties to start a counter-boycott of Catholic shopkeepers.Although there has been little actual violence except in Belfast, the state of feeling throughout the whole of the Six Counties Area is becoming increasingly-dangerous, particularly in co. Tvrone. The establishment of a large I.R.A. camp at Sperrin and the frequent drillings reported to be taking place, in other parts of Tyrone has undoubtedly caused feelings of great apprehension among the Unionist farmers of that county, and counter-preparations are being made by the U.V.F. The situation in the rest of the Six Counties Area has been eased to some extent by the disbanding upon the protests of the Irish Government of several I.R.A. camps which had been established there since the truce, but drilling on an extensive scale is still being carried on and counter-activity on the part of the U.V.F. is becoming increasingly manifest. The Divisional Commissioner of Police for the Six Counties reports that a meeting of Protestants and Orangemen, representing all Ulster, was recently held at Portadown for the purpose of forming Land, Fighting and Boycott Committees. The object of the Land Committee is to make provision for the &quot; planting &quot; of Protestants from the South of Ireland, and that of the Boycott Committee to organise a counter-boycott as a weapon of retaliation against the Sinn Fein boycott of Belfast goods. The Fighting Committee is stated to be composed of ex-service men and members of the U.V.F. whom it is intended to arm and equip for the protection of the Protestant population of the Six Counties.On the 13th instant, the house of a Sinn Fein farmer, at Meenagowan, Omagh District, was attacked by a party of disguised men armed with revolvers and rifles. Several shots were fired into the house, which was then broken into, and a new revolver holster, together with the sum.of 100/., was stolen by the attackers.Situation in Belfast.The situation in Belfast has remained comparatively quiet during the week. Several minor disturbances of the nature of stone-throwing and other assaults upon individuals took place, but there was no great disorder. A few isolated acts of revolver firing occurred on the 1.5th instant in the areas of Little Georges Street, North Queen Street and North Thomas Street, causing one death and three cases of wounding.&quot;   The first-named street is a Unionist locality, the two latter being[7165]
both partly Unionist and partly Roman Catholic. Two of the wounded persons are Catholics, and one is Protestant. No particulars in regard to the dead man Lave yet been obtained. About 10 p.m. on the same day, a bomb was thrown from Isabella Street into Little Georges Street, both of which are Unionist localities. It exploded about ten yards from where two Constables were standing. Neither Constable was injured, but two Roman Catholic houses were damaged by the explosion.Trials of Civilians by Court-Matrtial.Four trials of civilians by court-martial were concluded during the week, resulting in three convictions and one acquittal. Two of the convicted cases were those of Constables of the Royal Irish Constabulary, who were charged with the assault and attempted murder of two civilians at Salthill, co. Galway, on the 15th May last. Sentence of fifteen years&apos; penal servitude was imposed in each case. Another Constable, who was accused of participating in this crime, was found not guilty and released. The third conviction was of a civilian who was charged with attempting to assist a number of &quot; wanted &quot; persons to evade arrest. Sentence of one year&apos;s imprisonment with hard labour was imposed in this case.Internment Orders.The following statement shows the position as regards internments up to the15th instant:  Total orders made ... ... ... ...      4,368Orders cancelled for reasons other than release       239 Releases ordered ... ... ...       484-       723Number of persons now interned    ... ... ...      3,645The number of appeals awaiting hearing is now reduced to 1. Seventeen appeals were recently withdrawn.State of the Police Forces. *   The following figures show the present strength of the Irish Police Forces : Royal Irish Constabulary.Regular Force.   -Strength on the 9th*October, 1921       ... ... ...    13,957Retirements        ...         ... Resignations Dismissals or discharges ...	4 12 4	. Total wastage ,     Recruits            ...         ...	20 Nil	Net decrease	20	20Strength on the 16th October, 1921 Total wastage since closing of recruiting (the	10th July, 1921)	13,937 507Auxiliary Division.Strength on the 9th October, 1921       ... ... ...      1,408Resigned            ...         ...    , ... 5Discharged (medically unfit)         ... ... 8Dismissed           ...         ...         ... ... ^ 1Transferred to Transport Division ... ... 1Total wastage ... 15Recruits            ...         ...         ... ... NilNet decrease&apos;                  ...         ... ... 15          15Strength on the 16th October, 1921      ... ... ...      1,393Total wastage since closing of recruiting (the 10th July, 1921)        117
f Dublin Metropolitan Police.The strength of the Dublin Metropolitan Police has remained unchanged throughout the week at 1,143.Present Political Situation in Ireland.The week in Ireland has been politically uneventful. With the proceedings of the London Conference enfolded in an impenetrable veil of secrecy, the Irish public has had little food for speculation on the possible developments of the situation, and its attitude towards the progress of the negotiations betrays no sign of impatience or anxiety. There has been an agitation conducted for several weeks by the &quot; Freeman&apos;s Journal&quot; and the &quot;Irish Independent,&quot; the two leading Nationalist newspapers, for the immediate release of all interned untried prisoners. The Roman Catholic Hierarchy, at their annual meeting at Maynooth on the 11th instant, passed the following resolution : &quot; In common with our people, we welcome the Peace Conference that opens in London to-day.&quot; Fraught as that historic Conference assuredly is with issues of trans-cendent importance for the welfare of Ireland and England, we earnestly hope and pray that, under the Divine guidance, its deliberations will eventuate in a peace which will satisfy the national rights and aspirations of the Irish people, and thereby induce a condition of permanent friendship between the two . , countries.&quot; A golden opportunity now exists of establishing that blessed and long-wished-for concord by a great act of national freedom untrammelled by limita-tions, and free from the hateful spirit of partition, which could never be any-thing but a perennial source of discord and fratricidal strife.&quot; That memorable Conference enters on its solemn work supported, as we know, by the prayers and good wishes of the British and Irish peoples for its ultimate success. We appeal for co-operation on all sides to facilitate the removal of its undoubted difficulties. Especially do we appeal for a cordial observance of the truce so happily established, and so faithfully kept outside one unhappy district.&quot; And, as a very potent factor towards the attainment of peace, we urge with all earnestness the immediate liberation of the internees, whose prolonged confinement, in most cases without charge or trial, is, to say the least, a cruel hardship and exasperating cause of resentment and illwill.&quot;To further the object of peace and to obtain the Divine assistance, we hereby order that a Novena in preparation for the Feast of All the Saints of Ireland, which falls on the 6th November, be celebrated throughout Ireland, beginning on the 28th October, the devotion to consist of the Rosary, Litany of Loreto, either said or sung, together with the recitation of the Litany of the Saints of Ireland recently approved by the Holy See, followed by the Prayer for Peace and Benediction of the Most Holy Sacrament.&quot;An important recent development of the situation is the growth of a strong feeling amongst the Southern Protestants that the special interests of their com-munity entitle them to a direct share in the peace negotiations, and in an important speech&quot; delivered at the Dublin Diocesan Synod, Dr. Gregg, the Protestant Arch-bishop of Dublin, insisted that any equitable settlement must contain provisions similar to those of ss. 5 and 64 of the Government of Ireland Act, expressly safe-guarding the rights and liberties of religious minorities.H irish Office, S.W.1, October 21, 1921.
Statement showing Total Number of Serious Outrages from January 1, 1910, to september 3, 1921.Weekly Totals to Week ended October 15, 1921, and Totals at that date.		Week ended-						Nature of Outrage.	Totals from Jan. 1, 1919, to Sept. 3,1921.	Sept. 10, 1921.	Sept. 17,1921.	Sept. 24,1921..&apos;	Oct. 1,1921.	Oct. 8, 1921.	Oct. 15,1921.	Totals to Oct. 15, 1921.Courthouses destroyed	88							88R.I.O. vacated barracks destroyed	522							522R.I.C. vacated barracks damaged      ..	121							121R.I.C. occupied barracks destroyed   ..	25							25R.I.C. occupied barracks damaged	267					1		.   268Raids on mails       ..          ...	2,567							2,567Raids on coastguard stations and light-houses	97				* *			97Raids for arms      ..          ..	3,220						1	3,221Raids on offices of rate collectors and Petty Sessions clerks	122							122Policemen killed    ..	405				* *			405*Policemen wounded	683	* *				1		684f .Policemen fired at, &amp;c.	Not recorded	2				1		Soldiers killed	150	* *			* * -			150Soldiers wounded   .	345				.			345Soldiers fired at, &amp;c.          ..	Not recorded	1						Civilians killed]:    ..         ..	196				;.. ... - r			196Civilians wounded ..         ..	185				...			185 &apos;Totals	8,993	3		1		3	1	8,996Arrests  for   outrages   and   political offences			* a					* ** This figure includes six Special Constables, t This figure includes eleven Special Constables.I These figures do not, include casualties in Ulster riots during period June-September 1920; twenty civilian deaths occurred in Londonderry riots and sixty-two in Belfast riots during that period.N.B.-The above particulars do not include outrages of a kind which are not now being committed, e.g., 119 raids on revenue offices, which occurred during the months of April and May 1920, and resulted in the destruction of many official documents and much other public property. Minor forms of outrages (e.g., intimidation, cattle-driving, &amp;o.) are also not included. The Agreement for the cessation of hostilities came into force on the 11th Jvly, 1921.O

</content>
</cab>
