<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/129/0 images: 620-622</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT! IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT). fe.C RE T.0 A. B I IS T._346.fr3REPORT BY THE GENERAL OFFICER COMMANDING-IN-chief ON THE SITUATION IN IRELAND FOR WEEK ENDING29th. Ootober, 1921i(Circulated by the Secretary of State for War.,) 1. GENERAL MILITARY SITUATION.There la nc new development in the general situation. The usual activities of the rebels continue with regard to training, commandeering of houses, holding of Republican Courts and boycott of British and Belfast goods.     Breaches cf the spirit of the agreement of July 11th. under the above heads are reported from all divisional areas.    A few instances are shewn in Appendix I.Tflhile actual proof does not exist regarding the importation of arms and machine guns there is strong pre-sumption from the number of rifles in evidence since July 11th. as compared with the numbers shewn in captured docu-ments as being in possession of rebel units prior to that date, and also from the open boasting of rebel leaders as to the increased efficiency of the I.R.A. that such impor-tations have taken place.GHQ.Ireland. 1/11/21.(Sgd) - C.P.N. Macready, GENERAL,%   Commanding-in-Chief,. IRELAND.
APPENDIX   I.At Lisduff, Co*Longford, ort October   13th* about 60 men were seen marching in fours.     The leader was In I.R.A. uniform; The advanced guard of these men were armedcNear Ballymahohj Co.Longford, on October 13th,,three hundred men^paraded, all of whom a^e reported to have been armed.At Delvin, Co,Westraeath, about 150 re omits I.R.A, are under-going instruction.     All are armed, and they are instructed in route marches, use of arms, and ambushes.At Edenderry, King&apos;s County, the Workhouse has been commandeered by I.R.A. and a sentry armed with a service rifle and fixed&apos;, bayonet is posted at the gate.At Taylor!s Cross, near Birr, King&apos;s County, about midnight on October 15th. a party of troops&apos;met two parties of I.R.A. each 40 strong, most of whom were armed with rifles.At Cavan October 19th. two I.R.A. officers attended a dance in uniform.     They had an escort of 6 to 8 men, of whom two were seen to have revolvers.At Virginia, Co.Cavan, on October 17th,, two sergeants of the Middlesex Regt. returning to Camp at about 11.15 p.,m. were fired at.     Two shots were fired from shot guns, but neither took effect.make   House, Roscrea, Co*TIpperary. has Keen occupied by I.R.A. to the number of about 50, most of whom are armed.At Clontarf, Co.Dublin on 18th. October, 8 fren armed with rifles were seen marching along the road.It has been reported by an Informant that a&amp; Bamba Hall, Dublin, 50 Thompson Machine Guns and 4GyOOO rounds of ammunition we retire delivered from Londonderry.At Dublin on October 00th. a party of I.R.A. mostly In uniform were seen in the street.At Gort, Co.Galway, on 21st. October, at the funeral of a rebel, twelve men all armed with rifles, marched beside the coffin, and a volley was fired over tho grave.At Kells, Co.Meath, during the week ending October 22nd. two I.R.A. &quot;officers&quot; in uniform called at the Workhouse and arranged to take It over as accommodation for an I.R.A. detachment.At Loughllnstown, Co.Dublin, on October 23rd. a Column of abou^t 1000 rebels were seen on the march.     On a subsequent date a field day was held at the same plaoe by about the same number of rebels at which a Lewis Gun was in evidence.
A Corporal of the 1st. Bn.Lancashire Fusiliers was held up hy an armed civilian on the main read running through PHOENIX PARK, Dublin, at about 19,00 hours on the 25th, Instant and told to clear out or he would be shot.     The civilian said he was a Republican Policeman on duty.An Officer Commanding a Battalion in Dublin was buying some articles in a shop in Dublin about 15,00 hours yesterday, when 3 armed civilians entered the shop, and told the proprietors that they would Inspect his stock.     They proceeded to,sort out all English and Belfast Goods, and told the proprietor to get rid of then, or they would come back and. burn down his shop.An N.C.0, of the 1st, Bn,Lancashire Fusiliers, was proceeding on a tram from Rathfarnham to Harold&apos;s Cross, on the evening of the 27th, Instant when 9 civilians got Into the tram.     They all produced revolvers and explained the various patterns to each other.     They said that they had been training and hoped to have an opportunity of using their revolvers soon.

</content>
</cab>
