<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/24/0 images: 12-12</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(64)32 18 June 1964. 10.30 a.m.

1. Parliament. (oral)

L.P.S. As in statement.

2. Accommodation for Parliament. (oral)

L.P.S. H.A.C. recommend agreed Motion to accept need for more accn but remitting site and technical aspects for further considn.

L.Ch. Nothing in it for Lords.

L.P.S. Touché! Describe as for H/C.

3. Federation of Rhodesia &amp; Nyasaland. (oral)

M.W.P.(C) Debate on pensions for former public servants of Fedn. of R &amp; N. Opinion against Govt. Salisbury now tabling Motion, on wh. House can divide. We shall be defeated.

Ch.Sec. Settlement negotiated with great difficulty. Don‟t reopen: bad precedent.

L.Ch. But expatriate civil servants (our responsy) are being better treated than ex Fed, c.s. Morally indefensible. Therefore consider (a) whether can improve public presenntation of present decision: (b) Whether shd. amend settlement. (Precedent of W.Indies.)

P.M. L.Ch : Ch.Sec : M/S C.R.O.: See D.T.C. to consider – urgently.

[Exit M/S C.R.O

4. Foreign Affairs. (oral)

a) S. Africa_

F.S. Sec. C. resn. on apartheid to be debated today. See para 8. If we abstain we shall be alone (?apart from France). Pat Dean recommends vote for, with suitable explanation. We shd. then take part in enquiry, saying that we were doing so in order to limit objections.

P.M. Right. Note that Oppn. (H. Wilson) have come out against ec. sanctions. If we don‟t participate in study, U.S. may not be reliable. On para 12. P. Dean will make it clear our policy unchanged.

b) Laos

F.S. Poles have changed proposals. Must await these: but I will accept them (for confce. in Zurich) if they are acceptable.

5. U.N.C.T.A.D. (oral)

S/S.I. Final outcome met Cab.‟s views. Nothing mandatory in Final Act;

chapeau acceptable: all our reservations on record.

India‟s influence over 75 waning: Pakistan‟s growing (?Chinese influence).

Tanganyika &amp; Ghana most extreme of Africans: but Nigeria also.

N.Z. has withdrawn from 75.

Ch.Exch. Congratulate S/S.I. But watch new instn.

S/S.I. I will submit proposals on this – voting procedures etc.

6. International Liquidity. (oral)

Ch.Exch. Intl liquidity. Our initiative in 1962 now seen to be justified. Little progress on new methods of financing trade unlikely: but some expansion of resources of I.M.F. v. desirable. E.E.C. oppose, since already inflationary. But some modest expansion may be agreed before Tokyo meeting.

7. National Insurance: Earnings-related benefits etc.

C.P.(64)118&amp;121.

[Enter M.P.N.I.

Ch.Exch. Two issues: do we have a scheme: do we publish a W.P.?

M.Lab. Flat rates so low that impede mobility of labour. General agreement on this: and para 6(vii) of Ch. Exch.‟s memm. wrong. N.E.D.C. support me.

Economies of labour wd. offset the £50m. (wh. includes sickness: unempt. alone wd. be only £20m.) - and even that is paid by contributions, not Exch.

Ch.Sec. If sickness must be included, cost, to economy, is £50m. of which half is addition to costs of industry, and half reduces taxable capacity of employer.

Therefore increases difficulty of keeping expdre. (espec. social benefits if flat rate benefits must go up) within our W.P. target limits.

On merits, doubtful whether will do the trick qua redundancy; less welcome to T.U.‟s than increase in flat rate benefits (?and F. Allces). See also other problems entailed, particularly as regards contracting- out. These will precipitate earlier demands for increase in flat rate benefits.

On sickness, nothing for long-term sick except for, s. ben, after 6/7 months.

On redundancy, labour will be less willing to look for new work.

W.P. wd. be great hostage to fortune: vide Crossman.

S/S.I. I support M. Lab. And some cushion for change to long-term sickness socially better than other way round.

M.P.N.I. Both sides of industry wd. like – but realise difficulties of – combinn.

of more flat rate benefits &amp; more gradn.

Social case for proposals v. strong. Sickness essential: and short term widows v. desirable. Cushion for 6 months of sickness v. important.

Logical extension of decision to relate retirement pensions to earnings: if that was right, so is short term scheme.

And, if we don‟t do it, how defend discussions with T.U.C. and B.E.C. over last 12 months.

Ch.Sec. Old age (permanent fall in income) v. difficult from redundancy (temporary interruptn.). And sickness argts. invalidated by no payment for first months.

F.S. Time to review Beveridge – circs. have changed. Therefore do this qua unempt.

In sickness less defensible on first month and drop after six months.

W.P. purports to be basis of discussion - and then makes detailed proposals wh. are a definite Govt. plan. Doubtfully wise before Elecn. Confine to basis of discussions. Or use only in manifesto – except that that is too short to do justice to it. Therefore prefer W.P. with less precision on detail.

Ch.Exch. No. Ec. benefits v. doubtful; since increase in benefits too slight to affect attitudes. On sickness, impossible to justify drop after 6 months.

And in any case W.P. like this is v. vulnerable. Reserve for manifesto.

L.Ch. I support Ch.Exch. Emphasis on short term cdn‟t be sustained.

A new Beveridge enquiry is one thing: piecemeal patching is another.

Ch.Duchy. Can‟t justify doing nothing after more than a year‟s discussions with T.U.C. &amp; B.E.C. - who think scheme will affect attitudes.

Therefore produce a W.P.

M.P.N.I. Industry may be on our side in theory: but no agreement on details of a scheme. Therefore concentrate on policy – ? in Parly. statement leading up to manifesto.

But watch claims of old and chronic sick – wh. shd. have priority.

Beware of hypothecating expdre – &amp; leaving none for these.

L.P. I agree. Must do something for old &amp; sick as well.

But on economic grounds, these are transfer payments. Is that relevant?

Not necessarily a gross debit item on economy.

I agree with Ch. Exch. on W.P. Reserve for manifesto.

M.T. I support proposal in light of experience with redundancy in railway workshops. But don‟t expose in detail at this stage, particularly since sick must be included.

M/S.E.&amp;S. I support proposal: people do enlarge commitments with prosperity and an interruption is all the more serious. And counter-cyclical

argument is important economic argt.

M.H. Ec. advantages not v. great. In any event no time now for rational discussions before Election.

M.A.F.F. Public opinion will give priority to old and chronic sick. And ec. advantages arguable. Therefore no W.P. now.

M.H.L.G. Key quen is whether scheme wd. make employers more ready to deal with over-manning. Good employer tends to supplement unempt. benefit &amp; will therefore welcome this.

But only as part of package – espec. old and sick. Must increase basic benefit &amp; increase that still further for old &amp; sick, in 1965. Then can do w.r. benefit at same time.

M.Lab. It would encourage employers.

S/S.I. Therefore put economic priority first (bse. it ensures growth). And since Tsy. contribute nothing directly, room for something for sick &amp; old. (Extra burden on industry, by comparison with wage increases, v. small.)

M.P.N.I. Diffl. of 10/- a week for chronic sick &amp; old might cost £50m. - about the same.

Ch.Sec. Contribn. not indefinitely elastic. If some of it absorbed by this, less elastic left for flat rate increase &amp; special priority for old &amp; sick.

L.P.S. Move in this general direction, with little detail in each category and blurring priorities and timing.

M.W.P.(D) Agree. Avoid W.P. or a Parly. statement: launch by P.M.‟s speech in country.

S/S.S. Adopt w.r. ben. for unempt.: but consider whether the £30m. for sh- t. sick shd. be spent on chronic sick and old.

L.P. Can‟t ignore sh-t. sick.

Ch.Exch. Cab endorse w.r. scheme in principle &amp; reject W.P. Now discuss at future meeting how w.r. scheme shd. be related to other proposals in this field in terms of priority. But if a package of this kind, must reserve for manifesto if not to be outbid.

P.M. I agree. Cttee. shd. consider contents of package and manag timing of publication. And no public commitment to principle of w.r. benefits until this exercise done.

Ch.Exch. I will consider whether P &amp; N. Cttee. appropriate for this exercise.

[Exit M.P.N.I.

8. Trade Unions &amp; the Law. C.P.(64)119. [Enter Att.Gen.

Sol.Gen. Scot.

M.Lab. Acrimonious discussion with T.U.C. when I rejected legn. But I offered to begin enquiry before, instead of after, Election.

L.Ch. Little advantage in accelerating enquiry, wh. will take months anyhow.

Avoid any implied undertaking – e.g. “review” - “sympathetically” – to alter law. Therefore let Cttee. start now, but make clear a long and non committal process – particularly in view of further case sub judicie.

M.Lab. I accept this: but I never meant my proposal seriously – but rather to embarrass T.U.C!

Att.Gen. Even so, stress that immunity of T.U.‟s still affected &amp; that point at issue in R. v. B. was posn. of T.U. officials who were claiming to be above law.

L.P.S. And political advantage in appearing to press on with this enquiry.

Don‟t be too disingenuous about motives: otherwise we shall seem weak if we do nothing.

M.L. But, if we press on now, T.U.C. may refuse to participate. Therefore use as a threat only. (Clear that it embarrassed Woodcock).

Ch.Duchy. T.U.C. might not be able to call our bluff. Suppose they accept our offer? We must then be ready to go ahead.

M.H. On understanding that we will ask the body to consider R.V.B. point early but it is for them to decide.

Ch.Whip. And not irrelevant that earlier proposal – no enquiry till after Elecn. -was made when we thought of summer election. To that extent circs. have changed.

P.M. Even so, don‟t want enquiry without T.U.C. on it. Therefore act as proposed but leave T.U.C. guessing about what we shall do if T.U.C. reject offer.

9. Burma: War Damages Claims. C.P.(64)116

Ch.Exch. As in memm. Therefore legislate in general terms – not merely Burma – to overthrow new principle.

L.Ch. All previous legal opinion has regarded claim as inadmissible. But watch political trouble of retrospective legn. Even so, must act as proposed if to be consistent with earlier utterances.

Ch.Exch. And the ex gratia £10m. was meant to be final – tho‟ companies

refused to accept it as such.

Att.Gen. Compensn. by legn. e.g. - Suez – is one thing: but hitherto no English law practice that act of state creates right to damages. V. unfortunate that Scots law different.

S/S.I. But retrospective legn. to overthrow judgment of H/L. v. serious politically: defer announcement till after Election.

Att.Gen. V. difficult on this basis to handle litigation wh. will continue in interim.

Sol.Gen.S. Cd. raise another interlocutory point – about admissibility under English law!

P.M. Get that going and merely refer claimants to earlier statement &amp; say nothing to add.

L.Ch. But legn. next session v. urgent.

P.M. Agree. [Exit M.H.L.G.

[Exeunt Att.Gen &amp; Sol.Gen. S

10. Retail Prices. C.P.(64)117

Ch.Exch. Fair stability to October. Will say more about economy as a whole later.

11. Foreign Office Building. C.P.(64)113&amp;114

M.P.B.W. As in memm. Must have Admy. for re-housing. M.Def. already has 1 m. sq. ft. in Whitehall – wh. exceeds by 200,000 sq. ft. all other Depts. together!

S/S.D. But this is years ahead. Half of our staff of 24,000 already out-housed. I can‟t settle at short notice how to out-house part of central core of 10,000, most of which must remain in W‟hall.

M.W.P.(C) But we must be housed suitably and centrally.

M.P.B.W. I agree. That means Admy.

S/S.D. But I can‟t accept that now – when reorgn. is in full swing.

M.P.B.W. O.K. No public announcement: but plan on this basis.

P.M. Agree.

</content>
</cab>
