<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/24/0 images: 16-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(64)36 7 July 1964. 5.30 p.m.

1. Malta. (oral) [Enter C.D.S. &amp; C.in C. Med.

P.M. A break on nuclear bases v. embarrassing to us – and U.S. Damaging to appear to refuse indepce. on this basis.

S/S.D. I always stipulated no concession on nuc. facilities. But religious issue also outstanding.

Neither we nor U.S. admit where our nuclear bases are or are not.

Proposed formula therefore v. dangerous. We shd. have to concede same in respect of Aden, Singapore etc.

Therefore postpone negotns.: nonsense to try to put this Bill through at this stage in Parlt.

C.S. I don‟t mind about Bill. But how can I say no agt. after nearly a year of negotns.

S/S.D. But I can elide nuclear issue, if postponement; since qun doesn‟t „t arise until indepce.

P.M. F.S. (absent) also wants delay – partly because of U.S. and partly because of religious issue.

But C.S. in v. difficult posn. ?Say 2 (if not 3) points outstanding and no time for legn. Therefore break off and resume later.

S/S.I. A private understanding about nuclear?

S/S.D. No: it wd. leak. Public agt. better.

P.M. Shd. have to consult U.S. about formula.

S/S.D. Both we &amp; U.S. may eventually have to give up o‟sea nuclear bases.

But not too quickly: and not like this.

S/S.E.S. ?Better to have no def. agt. - and no fin agt.

C.S. And have it said that we are letting them starve because they won‟t let us maintain a nuclear base there?

S/S.D. We don‟t necessarily want such a base in Malta. But we must keep the right to have one there – and in Cyprus, Aden etc.

C.S. B.O. wants to remain P.M. He has a majority of one! He dare not risk a defeat on this issue. He might prefer indepce. without a defence &amp; finance agt.

H.S. But indepce. depends on our legislating. And we now have no time.

P.M. Agree. Only a wholly non-controversial Bill cd. now get through.

C.S. Then he will say we have refused indepce. on nuclear base issue.

S/S.D. But he can‟t take this line if he wd. be content with a secret understanding about nuclear base.

C.S. I agree. It‟s illogical: but he wd. leak anyhow.

C.D.S. C. of S. have considered. Can‟t jeopardise U.S. – U.K. understanding not to confirm or deny n. base.

And imminence of Mintoff v. dangerous.

C.S. B.O. is our only friend: this will break him – disastrous if C.D.S. right.

?Consult U.S.

P.M. Must go for postponement; but consult U.S. first and ascertain whether they too will fight to maintain the principle of neither affirming or denying.

But must say legn. now impracticable.

H.S. If it gets us out of giving M. indepce., it wd. be worth it.

Ch.S. Yes. If we want a base in M, it must remain a colony.

P.M. But that is really reversing Cab. decision to grant indepce.

But no altve.

C.S. If so, we mustn‟t break during C‟w. P.M.‟s Meeting. V. difficult.

M/S. E.S. Must emphasise issue affects not only us but whole of Western Alliance.

</content>
</cab>
