<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/24/0 images: 17-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(64)37 9 July 1964. 2.40 p.m. H/C.

Malta. C.P.(64)134 [Enter C.D.S.

P.M. Risk that other bases cd. still want some assurances. But C.S. now in a jam: if no agt. B.O. will break on this issue.

Cd. we say (a): and then incorporate in agt. clause providing that either party can raise any aspect, if necy.

L.Ch. Or, if radical change of circs, either party can raise it?

L.P. A wide open door for Mintoff, if he gets in.

S/S.D. But letter is to be shown to B.O.‟s Cab. That gives it a certain status: and increases risk of leak – to our potential discredit.

P.M. Agree: cd. not risk leak of (b) or (c).

C.S. But M. Cab. have instructed B.O. to exclude n.w. from agt.

P.M. Then give it up &amp; remain as we are?

F.S. Essential to keep B.O. if possible. Therefore concede (a), preferably orally: couple with understanding that agt. can be reviewed if either side wishes.

C.S. That makes agt. valueless.

P.M. No – not if only either side can raise any change of circs. Confine to this, plus (a).

S/S.D. If in writing, for publicn. – not a secret letter, wh. wd. leak.

But even (a) dangerous: Cyprus, Aden &amp; Singapore Govts. will ask for similar undertakings.

C.D.S. Malta might be needed for n.ws:-

a) if ejected from Cyprus, M. might be needed for Canberras for CENTO,

b) for nuclear depth charges.

Moreover, we can‟t abandon agt. with U.S. neither to confirm nor to deny presence of n.w.‟s.

S/S.D. Switch attacks to religious issue?

C.S. He may not break on that. But do we want to break at all? It wd. destroy B.O. and open way for M. And suppose he accepts indepce. without def agt?

L.Ch. But must clear n.w.‟s with U.S. first.

C.S. And let M. go back discredited and put blame on n.w.‟s?

P.M. Better to have nothing on paper: but I will see B.O., say (a) and offer clause in agt., making it possible for either side to raise any issue.

L.Ch. And explore religious issue further. Even if we agree it with B.O., H/C. might reject it.

C.S. Even so, play it long, and keep as final grounds of break if necy.

S.S.D. L. Ch. &amp; I will meanwhile draft a cl. for def. agt. Allowing either party to raise new issues. And show to Ch. Secy.

Ch.S Not a review! Otherwise must review finance agt too! Can‟t have a finance agt without a def. Agt.

L.Ch. I agree. Provision for considn. with no obligation to amend.

</content>
</cab>
