<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/24/0 images: 20-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(64)40 21 July 1964. 10 a.m.

1. Malta. (oral) [Enter P.M.G.

C.S. Reached agt. Change in electoral law abandoned: defence point satisfy.: Oppn. front bench won‟t oppose.

P.M. As satisfy. as can be. Therefore must legislate in this Session.

Ch.Whip. May be necy. to leave final stages till autumn: but shd. be manageable provided House does not rise till Friday.

P.M. Go ahead: congratulate C.S. [Exit C.S.

2. Economic Situation. C.P.(64)143&amp;144

Ch.Exch. Prospect of deficit on B.P. – growing. Trade and production figures v. enigmatic.

On home front, self correction of boom is happening. Prodn. increasing more slowly than thought. Growth rate declining from 6% to 4% - levelling out. Some pressure on prices: but not intolerable.

Exports not too bad: but rise in imports, after plateau, baffling.

Must therefore borrow – U.S. swap: IMF standby etc. Defensible.

No further contraction of demand practicable at present: but it is excessive. Longer term more questionable. 4% growth rate basis of our expre. plans: but doubtful if will be achieved. Expre. now rising at 5% rather than 4.1% - i.e. increase in tax rates necy. Therefore big shift in resources necy. – particularly defence (intl. commitments).

P.M. Gloomy: can we raise productivity to 4% pretty quickly – e.g. 2 years.

Ch.Exch. Incomes policy the key: nothing can be done until after election.

S/S.I. Increase in prody. is itself responsible for high imports. Rest is probably pre-election stockpiling of consumer goods: but perhaps not.

M.L. Vacancies levelling off. Sitn. stabilising itself to some extent: but heavy pressures building up in labour field, particularly engineering. Crunch will prob. be deferred until after election – and then we must deal with it.

Ch.Sec. 65-66 prospect – v. depressing: larger annual increase than in any year since Korea (apart from ‟63-4, when we stoked it up).

Bldg. industry not self corrective: may be an addl. stimulus to inflation by drawing in labour and forcing up prices.

M.P.B.W. Bldg. indy. now brimful: no more. Yet tendering still keen. Pace of implementn. of capital projects usually slower than expected.

M.T. Incomes policy related only to rates, irrelevant. In conditions of excess

demand, it is wages wh. matter. Tenders now keen only in relation to profit margins.

P.M. Preparatory work on Ests?

Ch.Exch. On defence, enough done: scale of problem known. It is decisions that are required.

S/S.D. If commitments are retained, we can‟t cut – even in areas where war unlikely.

M/S. E.S. School meals! Increase charge &amp; modify income scale = less hardship!

What about capital payments? Use mandatory policy to fall within limits of existing B. Rate.

S/S.I. Plan for imports control available. But beware of any hint wh. wd. encourage forestalling.

M.A.F.F. OECD expect new measures!

F.S. Not until after election! How do we publicly handle regular statistics before election.

Ch.Exch. No surprise if we borrow – by various means. Trade figures unpredictable: but v. bad luck if they go on being high.

M.W.P.(D) Must watch all announcements between now &amp; election.

P.M. Must reconsider, especially on defence after election.

3. Postmen‟s Pay. (oral)

P.M.G. Sitn. deteriorating in London: stable in provinces. T.U.C. have not responded yet to UPW‟s appeal: but may do so today.

If so, we must choose between large increase in first year or plugging arbitrn.

Ch.Exch. We may be pressed on former – to keep if PRU justifies: to abate in next 2 years if it doesn‟t. Shall we show willing to examine it? And do we leave it to them to propose it – or propose it ourselves?

M.L. Pity if soln. proposed by W‟cock. Better for Ch. Exch. to put it forward?

Ch.Duchy. 5%, plus abatement, might be wearable. If done, shd. be on our initiative.

H.S. It wd. be a surrender! 5% was our (P.M.G.‟s) original proposal: we cut it on incomes policy ground. Can‟t go back.

Ch.Exch. But Armitage Cttee.‟s report – in interim – has said comparisons too narrow. That is an alibi.

P.M.G. I wd. stick to arbitn.: can‟t be seen to give way. UPW morale must be shaken by pay packets at end of this week.

M.H. Public opinion not on our side. Therefore don‟t wait until we are pressed by T.U.C. and then give way.

M.H.L.G. ?Stand by 4% &amp; arbitrn., but put aside 1% for payment if arbitrn. so decides.

M.H. Oppn. believe we must make one more advance – e.g. to 4½%.

H.S. We must back the H.S. We have been wrong to oppose him hitherto: we can‟t let him down now.

P.M.G. We cd. agree t. of r. for P.R.U in 24 hours and job cd. be done in four weeks. Emphasise this publicly.

P.M. Shd. I see Smith?

Ch.D. He has rejected this offer already. Don‟t let P.M. risk a snub.

L.Ch. Cd. concede 5% after P.R.U. – not before. Therefore offer settlement after 4 week P.R.U. survey.

H.S. Yes: get full publicity for this.

M.W.P.(D) And make it as dramatic an “advance” as possible, even tho‟ it isn‟t really any change.

P.M. Offer 4 week settlement (T. of R. in 24 hours): acceptance of whatever is recommended: say altve. is arbitrn.

P.M.G. And a simplified form of P.R.U.?

P.M. Put it out in as plain and simple a statement as possible.

M.S. E.S. Beware of over simplifying (i.e. devaluing) P.R.U.

P.M. Let P.M.G., M.W.P.(D)., Ch. Sec., M. Lab. draft a statement for tomorrow‟s papers: and if satisfy. to them, let it issue.

M.A.F.F. ?And concede payment of part of P.R.U. offer, even if arbitrn. necy.

P.M. Consider this too. I must see draft statement in p.m.

[Exeunt P.M. : F.S. : P.M.G.

4. Nuclear Propulsion for Merchant Ships. C.P.(64)136

[Enter Parly Sec. M.P.

Ch.Exch. As in memm. No great priority at present: other things are more important.

M.T. Two new factors – a) Cook &amp; Lockcroft say, if Vulcain adopted, no further r. &amp; d. needed. Therefore ignore para 6.

b) shipbldg. industry and shipowning industry now interested: and customer (ICI at Billingham) who wd. charter for transport of oil from N. Africa to N.E.

Reactor wd. be a Vulcain: and we shd. let it on basis of no charge over &amp; above conventional propulsion.

Vulcain already upgraded in terms of shaft L.p.

Ch.Sec. A new proposition. Can‟t settle until we have considered it.

Much more attractive, if Clore now interested.

L.P.S. Will take time to consider. Must meet pressure for Parly. statement.

M.T. Cd. announce decision in principle on Wednesday.

S/S.D. On basis of detailed project study of promising project – and subject to its satisfactory outcome.

Ch.Sec. And to commercial interests being prepared to risk their own money.

[Exeunt S/S.I. : Parly Sec. M.P. : M/S.S.O.

5. Small Satellite Launchers. (C.P.(64)146&amp;147 [Enter M.Avn.

M.Avn. Basis of our space effort is participn. in intl. orgns. – ENDO, ESRO etc.

If to contribute effectively and get orders, must display technical competence – i.e. to put satellites into orbit and control them.

This requires small and cheap launcher – by devt. of B.K. rocket over 4 or 5 years at £2m. p.a. (with subsequent firings at £2m. p.a.).

Industry wd. support this. Not geared to any ELDO or ESRO programme – but desirable as basis of our contribn. to them.

Not much hope of offsetting savings. [Exit L. Ch.

Ch.Sec. Might be useful. But item 2 and lack of savings rule it out. And no need to decide now – in advance of decisions in autumn on our participn. in second ELDO launcher programme (wh. may be v. expensive).

M/S. E.S. Examine, with other space activities, towards end of year.

S/S.D. Dangerous, technologically, to fall too far behind. French are going to do what M. Avn. proposes. See para 5 of C.P.(64)146. I will co- operate with M. Avn. in proposing how this cd. be done – with savings.

M.P.B.W. No: not savings. Go ahead on merits.

Ch.Sec. Already reviewing economics of space. Wait till that complete in autumn.

S/S. E.S. Approve in principle, subject to offsetting economies.

</content>
</cab>
