<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 4-4</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.5(59). 5th February, 1959.
1. Defence White Paper. [J. Amery, Redmayne, Alport.
Approved subject to amendments.
[Exit Amery
[Enter B.C., Boyle.
2. Service Widow’s Pensions.
P.M. Summarised issues for decision.
First ques : Pensions (Increase) Bill.
H.A. On past policy not yet due. From ’25 to ’56 we have waited for a larger increase in c/living. Now only 7% since ’56 Act. – and unlikely to go for long over 9% this summer. But there are some, who didn’t benefit by Act of ’56, who have suffered 14% increase.
On other hand, posn. now of greater relative stability – argument for action. Also case for legn. wd. be stronger after Election.
Last Act benefited only those whose salaries were under £1500. Wd. prefer now to weight it in favour of those who have bn. longest in retirement. Wd. be confined to C. Servants, l govt., teachers, fire &amp; police – with correspondg. action under R. Warrant for Forces. But effect also on industrials in natd. industries. At 7% for those under £1.500, w’out repercussions, cost wd. be £8 M. (£2 M on l.a.’s) in a full year.
My bias is in favour of legislating now – early summer.
K. There wd. be pressure from those over £1.500. A v. repercussive field. A dangerous step.
H. Strong public case for taking this out of an Election. – esp. if action is inevitable w’in 12 mos. after.
B.C. Will add to pressure for increase of retirement pension. But in past we have managed to keep them separate. Pressure shd. not be irresistible.
H.W. Wd. certainly have some effect on rlway pensions. Diff. to avoid some action.
M. In my natd. indies. – el. follows l.a.’s : some increase will follow : ditto for gas. Will affect miners – &amp; in due course will go thro’ the economy.
On merits : can’t avoid it in a year or so. Wd. prefer to do it now.
I.M. Agree. It’s now or December. Better now.
Services.
D.S. Grigg recommendn. : widows shd. in future enjoy 1/3 rd. of husband’s pension. We have accepted this publicly in reln. to men still serving. We can’t decline to apply it, as Cttee. intended, to those whose husbands have retired and are still alive. Formula shd. not be applied to existing widows.
H.A. In the past we have held the posn. tht. increase shd. be confined to those still serving. My diffy. is : if we extend to first class, can we hold it against existg. widows. Latter wd. have v. wide repercussions.
P.M. Cd. we, in W. Paper, limit announcemt to. 1st. class. This wd. cover Grigg report. Existg. widows cd. then be dealt with at same time as Pensions Increase.
Agreed.</content>
</cab>