<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 6-6</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 10(59). 17th February, 1959.
1. Cyprus. [Enter Redmayne, R.A. Allen.
P.M. G. &amp; T. accepted our decln., subject to points on Annex. But clear that Makarios won’t do so, at present. Propose to leave G. a day in which to bring pressure on M. Karamanlis is coming : hope he will bring pressure on M. No reason to fear that G. &amp; T. will weaken. M.’s real objn. is to G. &amp; T. troops and T. veto: but he may shelter behind objn. to B. sovereignty over bases.
Some statement will have to be made on Thursday.
2. Alan Nunn May.
R.A.A. Decn. – no ppt. in ’58. Applied again for holiday this year. Has bought a house: taken out insurance for children. Caccia, after consultn. recommends holding it back until after August, when Congress is in recess. But S.Ll. thinks never will be appropriate time &amp; favours issue now.
R.A.B. Will be a fuss in Press.
D.S. No actual harm if he did defect.
P.M. Let us have report on his pol. activities: if he is no longer in close contact, we must let him go.
Agreed : R.A.B. to get up-to-date report &amp; inform Cab.
3. Cuba.
R.A.A. Batista wants to go to Bermuda. Convenient to have him away fr. Caribbean. But extradn. treaty with Cuba – &amp; we cd. receive a request.
Agreed : Reject this appln.
4. Export of Arms.
a) Cuba.
R.A.A. Castro is applying for balance of order wh. we suspended. We have bn. paid. S.Ll. wants genl. authy. to proceed with that subject to course of general discns. with Cuban Govt.
P.M. Consistent : continue to supply to legitimate (recognised) Govt. S.Ll. shd. have discretion to authorise this.
b) Dominica.
R.A.A. S.Ll. favours giving 4 patrol boats condl on their ordering another 4. And no sharper weapons for 6 months.
D.E. Can’t we also get civil orders at same time.
P.M. We shd. try for a mixed deal – and refer back to Cab. before takg. final decision.
5. Guy Burgess. [Enter Att.G.
R.A.A. Deteriorating – drink, homosexuality, megalomania. May well present himself (sick mother). Cdn’t then refuse admission : or prosecute.
Att.G. S.2 offence wd. be v. technical : he left behind some official pp., but they were of no importance. We shd. be ridiculed if we prosecuted.
x/ Cd. I.O. put him to strict proof of his identity.
P.M. We shd. follow the line at x/.
Instruct Emb., if he applies, to require him to prove that he is not R.
Instruct I.O. similarly.
F.O. and H.O. to concert means of keeping him away.
[Exit Att.G.
6. Agricultural Policy : Small Farmers Bill.
J.M. V. strong opposn. to Bill has developed in Scotland, esp. to tapering off of Marginal Prodn. scheme. Fear they will shift from beef to sheep.
V heavy pressure on Tory M.P.’s in agricultural seats.
Possibilities : i) increase subsidy to hill cattle, in Price Review. (Wdn’t meet
pol. pressure.)
ii) drop Cl. 3 of Bill (too late : Bill now in H/L.).
iii) promote another Bill amendg. Cl. 3 so as to give greater
flexibility in tapering off M.A.P.
Godber. On agric. grds. M/Ag. cd. not support (ii) – and prob. not (iii) : v. serious repercussions in E &amp; W. and N.I.
On i) he wd. not oppose if necessary on pol. grds.
Wd. consider (iii) – tho’ doubt if we cd. accept it.
R.A.B. Prefer either i) or alternative legn. applying to E. &amp; W. as well as Scotland.
J.M. x| Best course wd. be promise to re-consider posn., with a view to fresh legn., if
| result is as serious as is forecast. There is a year before anyone suffers.
P.M. Do (i) and also x/ (in debate in H/L. if it is raised). L.P.S. to settle form of x/.</content>
</cab>