<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 19-19</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 27 (59). 30th April, 1959
1. Parliament. [Enter E.H.
R.A.B. Business for next week.
Whitsun Recess : 15/5 to 2/6.
2. Space Research. [Enter A.J., G.W.
Hail. Limited project – evolved by Cttee. of R. Socy. and backed by A.C.S.P. Scientists are satisfied there is important work to be done. First step is to get instruments. Required in any event, if we are to do anything at all. We need not at present pre-judge either satellite or vehicle. All we need do now is send Massey to U.S. for technical discn.
This project shd. not founder, or succeed, acc. to decisions on defence policy.
Steering group.
a) Do we make public statement? I favour it. For if we start this p’mme, Universities must be told well before Oct. term – &amp; Massey’s team must go to U.S. Scientists will be critical if we don’t seem to be active on this. Mouse – prs., but nil wd. be worse. Not wedded to form of announcement.
D.S. Important potentialities. To m’tain our posn. in science, we must take our part in this. Can’t do that on basis only of U.S. vehicles. They will insist on knowledge of what we are doing – soon wd. be awkward on commercial grounds.
If we can’t announce decn. to go into this business, don’t say we are going to ride on U.S. backs.
O.G. Cospar offer is open to all. But Caccia says U.S. wd. also go into a bi-lateral arrangement with us.
D.S. Only on basis of U.K. participn. (on vehicle).
Hail. Not acc. to Todd’s informn.
A.J. Agree on instrument p’mme &amp; mission to U.S. But I don’t think U.S. vehicles is adequate alternative to our own capacity to launch. We now have all data for decn. to do a p’mme of our own. This is attractg. young minds therefore we ought not to exclude ourselves.
D.E. Can we afford to compete w’in West on this? Shd. we not rather co-operate – in competn. with Soviet Union. Can’t we join up with Europe?
Hail. On first step (instruments) we can act alone.
Ch.H. Prestige argument. Chapman Pincher has already declared v. L.P.’s plan. Public re-action will be the same.
G.W. Support L.P. Larger p’mme shd. be measured v. other possibilities – e.g. research into supersonic aircraft etc., These are more commercial projects.
H.A. Can’t hope to rival U.S. in all research. Don’t go beyond instruments – reserve other ques until later.
A.L.B. Can we avoid statement – to avoid anti-climax.
Hail. Must say something about instruments &amp; about mission. Needn’t mention cost at this stage.
Decision to fly in U.S. rockets doesn’t pre-judge later decision to fly them in our own.
Wording of statement can be re-considered.
M. Support H.W.’s view. Reconsider statement. Doubt if we shall be able to afford project of our own.
R.A.B. We mustn’t take on too much. Won’t cost grow? Revise statement.
Hail. A.C.S.P. support.
I.M. Statement (amount and U.S. vehicle) will do more harm than good. Limit announcement to mission.
A.J. We ought to start work on adapting B. Knight.
G.Ll. Agree with M/D. If there is statement, make it appear that we reserve substantive decision.
H. Cd. Canada &amp; Australia contribute?
A.J. The important U.S. work is on defence side. We haven’t bn. in touch with them – only with civil.
P.M. Let us decide merits – look at statement later.
From scientific angle what matters = instruments : vehicle is not important. Rocket is not of scientific importce.
From prestige angle, rocket is. But only point of getting up is to enable date to be obtained.
Quite separate points. Public are interested mainly on second.
Actually, we are not in posn. to decide larger ques. We haven’t looked at competing research demands(cf. H.W.). Can’t do it before next year’s Estimates. Prs. we ought to say that.
Whatever ultimate decn. re B. Vehicle, we have started preliminy. work (instruments, mission) – to put ourselves in position to take major decision.
D.S. Agree : want to keep posn. open. Wd. like to add decision to make design studies on adaptn. of B. Streak etc., That is equally a preliminary preparation. (£50.000 over 6 months).
P.M. and L.P. to concert a draft statement.
[Exit A.J., G.W.
3.
Commonwealth Education Conference.
H. I want a total of £10 M. – for presentational purposes. viz., £7 M fr. U.K.
A.L.B. We did pick out education at Montreal, for preference. Strong support for larger figure. Our main emphasis is on teacher-training. Colonial share shd. not come out of C.D.W.
H.A. Every project rises in cost by 20% p.a. At Montreal we contemplated prs £1 M. p.a. We now start at £1.3 M. – and H. says £1.75 M.
On financial grds. we must look narrowly at these projects. No one is willing to accept any compensating reductions.
Preliminary estimates suggest larger increase in a single year than ever before.
H. Hope to get £3 M. from Canada &amp; Austr. Rhodesia mght put in something. No one else can be expected to do anything.
D.E. Teacher-training is more important than post-graduate study. Cd. we hope that others wd. contribute when it’s advantages are more plainly known?
H.A. We have to ration all sorts of productive expenditure – this can’t be exempt.
O.G. More money doesn’t always produce results – quality can fall off : this is our experience in Br. Council.
H.A. We may get £10 M. in the end. But don’t offer more than £6 M. to start it off. This is 5 year plan, after all.
Agreed: as at x/.
[Exit H.W.
4.
Commercial Policy : Dollar Imports.
A.L.B. On details : I am nervous re rum : hope it will be excluded. On citrus &amp; other fruit I hope I can consult W. Indies – tho’ sums are small. They will be here on 25/5.
H.A. We planned to consult Doms. &amp; Colonies on paper : revise final offer in light of comments.
Wd. prefer to include books but omit periodicals.
D.E. Paper back editions of classics wd. rush in.
P.M. Make it all books save fiction? At least look at categories.
H.A. We are bound to make a move in next month or so. We shall be even more criticised at home if we have to move under pressure. Also a modest offer will have more effect if volunteered.
P.M. Admit that, despite awkward cases, volume of Ango-U.S. trade has increased. Worried about our export of U.K. cars : why don’t we liberalise more on cars – they don’t take up existing quota.
D.E. Because we have separate quotas for Fr. and G. But we cd. open U.S. quota further – to equal Fr. &amp; G. quotas together. I wd. like to do that – esp. as we can’t liberalise on textiles or oil equipment.
O.G. } Unless we do this, we put our existing export trade to U.S. in jeopardy.
M. } For pressure on Adminn. will grow.
H.A. Ready to cut it down from $17m to $15m.
H.A. Work down to $15m.
Cut out rum : consider books : try to include cars. Send out our proposals for comment, before Commonwealth officials meet.
May be possible to p’pone announcement until Whitsun recess.
5.
Iceland: Fishing.
O.G. Skipper who was advised to stand trial on one charge was convicted on others.
J.H. For fishing betwn. 4 and 3 miles, we shd. continue to advise them to stand trial. (Not betwn. 4 and 12).
Iceland have cheated. Must ask them for assurance they won’t do it again.
Industry mght be persuaded to offer to pay (estimated) fine for offence w’in 4 miles.
Submission to trial is an act of grace.</content>
</cab>