<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 23-23</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 31(59). 12th May, 1959.
1. Information Services : Exports of Books. [Enter Alport, O.G.
Ch.H. Enlarged upon his memo.
H.A. Don’t dispute importance. But never any off-setting economies. My concern over growth in expenditure is even more acute in reln. to oversea expenditure. Blocked currency is esp. difficult.
Can’t accept this new expenditure (likely to grow) until I see where I am. Shall see my way clearer in a month.
Ready to agree tht. anything can start wh. can be got w’in existg. ceilings of expenditure this year plus
Shall have to take this line on increase of £¼ m. next year. (to a total of £16¾ m.) And ready to review remainder later.
all proposals for new expenditure.
Alp. Pressed by our repves. in I. and P. to counter influx of R. books etc., We ought at least to start this p’mme. Can distinguish between Ch.H.’s various proposals.
Ch.H. Only asking for £100.000 next year – don’t want £¼ M. But expenditure, if this p’mme approved, will rise later, inevitably, in 2nd. &amp; 3rd. years.
R.A.B. You cd. find another £150.000 on vernacular languages &amp; Br. periodicals.
H.A. If these alternatives are discussed with Ty., we can get phased plan.
Hail. Why cut B.B.C. in favour of books – the first being more potent.
Ch.H. Because there is waste in B.B.C. overseas p’mmes.
A.L.B. In Colonies we keep out the Soviet lead-in material : but after independence we shan’t be able to ensure that. Support p’mme, esp. for library schemes &amp; cheap books.
Hail. Scope for Anglo-U.S. project. Cost less &amp; avoid duplication.
Ch.H. U.S. concerned only with American books.
D.S. Worth this money to get more Br. books read. Mght avoid need for defence expenditure.
G.Ll. Support that view – based on my experience in S.E.A. Books have impact on rising middle-class minority.
A.L.B. Better to raise this again in July than make too small a start.
H.A. Let Ch.H. give me minimum figure for each of 3 years.
D.S. And consider increasing it in July.
O.G. W. party shd. re-consider priorities. [Exit Alport, H.A.
2. Foreign Affairs.
a) Middle East. Iraq. All M/E. countries feel that, on balance, our decision was
right. Even Nasser has said this to Canadian.
b) Mtg. of Foreign Ministers. First hurdle surmounted – seating of the 2
Germanies. Next may be Poland/Czecho. S.Ll. will avoid handling that.
3. Parliament.
R.A.B. Business for next week. Progress with legn. – satisfactory.
P.M. Unprecedented scale of effort in 4th. year of a Parlt. Large legislative projects. We shd. take credit for that.
4. I.L.O. Conventions.
I.M. Discrimination. We can’t ratify – for reason given. Mild difficulty from F. Brockway etc., Otherwise not likely to be trouble.
Memo. approved.
5. Education : Church Schools.
R.A.B. Pressure by R.C.’s is coming : will be asked wtr Govt. going back on negotiations foreshadowing 75% grant on primary &amp; secondary.
On other side warning that Free Churches will object. Theirs is a plainly anti-Roman line : with high emotional content. Their extreme fringe will harm us in some constituencies, esp. in E. Anglia Devizes and some marginal seats esp. where Liberals are running a non-conformist candidate. We may
Next move : G. Ll. shd. see Opposn. carry it off, but it’s quite serious.
We can’t go back on merits or on negotiations. But we might say we haven’t time for legn., so late in session. We wd. have to declare intention to legislate later. On balance prefer that – wd. at least avoid charge that we are rushing Free Churches.
G.Ll. I favour other course. We have all Parties &amp; all R.C. &amp; C of E. authorities now in favour of doing this : go forward while all are agreed. We always expected Free Churches to make a fuss but thght they wdn’t press it – is this still so? R.C.’s are beginning to get cross – &amp; if we don’t legislate will assume we have given way to Free Churches.
Ch.H. On balance, get it over before Election. Statement of intention wd. serve to keep it alive.
J.M. From angle of re-action in Scotland, I wd. sooner get it over.
J.H. Support Ch.H. Easier to defend action taken, in election campaign.
D.S. Also, on a mere declaration, Opposn. cd. hedge more easily.
I.M. On balance support R.A.B. – if 2 other Parties can be firmly associated with declaration.
E.H. In debate on Bill, individual Labour M.P.’s will be free to speak against, but will not vote against it. Front Bench wd. support. They wd. also support a statement.
P.M. We can’t abandon our position on this. Solely ques of tactics.
Discussion adjourned.
5. Cabinet Procedure.
P.M. i) Next Cabinet, other than for emergency business, on 28th May.
ii) Only another 8 weeks of session. Start no fresh hares. Avoid rows over small issues ; watch Dpl. administration in the dog-days of July etc., Thought shd. concentrate on future (for manifesto).
iii) Public presentation of dollar liberalisation. Ch.H. to watch timing.
H.W. No sign of progress on my subjects – Decca, or shipping.
P.M. Alternatives [or additional??] : play it down as product of strength of £.
play up increase of anglo-U.S. trade v. background of which these protectionist acts shd. be seen as exceptions.
R.M. cf. export of B. cars : where large unemplt. in Detroit.
Ch.H. to discuss with Ty.</content>
</cab>