<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 33-33</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 42 (59) 16th July, 1959
1. Parliament. [Enter O.G., E.H.
R.A.B. Business for next week.
2.
Federation of Rhodesia &amp; Nyasaland.
P.M. Long discussions with Welensky. Efforts to get Oppn. agreemt. to preparatory work for 1960 review. Doubtful if they will agree, tho’ may be less hostile than before. We must have a plan. Ours is to have a preparatory Commn. incldg. local repves. : Oppn. will prob. press for Parly. (U.K.) Commr.
We propose 26 members : 13 fr. Africa, of whom 5 are to be Africans : from U.K., 6 P.C.’s of U.K. Parlt. and 6 others, of whom 2 wd. be fr. other Commw. countries with experience of Federal system. This apart fr. Chairman.
Wd. be advisory only – in prepn. for 1960 review.
A.L.B. Welensky’s talks with them didn’t go badly – they may agree.
P.M. Propose announce this on 21st. July, for debate on 22nd. Commn. wd. not begin to work until Nov.
3.
Nyasaland : Emergency.
P.M. Devlin Rpt. – completed but not yet submitted.
Normal procedure wd. have bn. to collect Govr.’s obsns. &amp; publish together.
But better, esp. if awkward rpt., to get it over before Recess.
Now looks as tho’ we can’t have a single African debate because this is now lagging, and it is a long report.
If it can’t be done earlier we must publish, with Govr’s comments, on Monday, 27th. July. Then offer debate on Wed. 29th. &amp; adjourn on Thursday.
* Copies, when available, will be circulated to Cabinet.
K. B.B.C. asked if Devlin cd. give interview on report – a month ago. I said, as L.CH., that it wd. be improper for a judge so to appear.
R.A.B. Hard to get H/C. to debate if no publn. before 27th.
P.M. But damaging to publish before week-end because Sunday newspp.
E.H. Prefer Thursday 6.p.m &amp; see 1922 that evening.
Agreed : aim at publn. on Thursday 6.pm.
[also Hola documents at same time.]
4.
Police. Ch. Constable of Nottingham.
R.A.B. Telling Watch Cttee. to review their decision. Alternatives : dismissal of Ch. C., followed by an enquiry, which Cttee. won’t like. But, if they ask me to hold enquiry, I can only do it under 1921 Act – and we’ve have enough of that.
5. Nationalised Industries. [Enter E.M.
R.A.B. No need for immediate decisions.#
Padmore’s valuable rpt. – cd. form basis of 2 Bills, but neither wd. be suitable for 1st. Session of a new Parlt.
Financial &amp; organisational recommns. are broadly acceptable.
Prices : Ministerial intervention shd. be preserved, but shd. be rare &amp; overt.
Procedure (para 20). We shd. say v. little on this in Manifesto. Leaves our hands free, and avoids provoking discussion.
M., H.A., H.W.All agreed with this presentation.
E.M. Accept this concln. – because can’t go fwd. w’out discn. with Bds.
R.M. Word of caution re financial targets : more thought needed on this.
D.E. Can’t expect Bds. to borrow in market if Ministers control prices. Wd. like to examine this more carefully.
R.A.B. Much more work to be done. Welcome views of other Ministers.
6.
Post Office.
R.A.B. Ministers bless this plan in principle.
Main ques : do we announce before or after an election? Main argument is tht. publn. now wd. precipitate discussion on natd. industries.
Present, in due course, as a natural evolution – not a violent revolution.
H.A. Point of doubt : do we under-estimated strength of Parly. objns. so this removal fr. Consol. Fund. Hard to guess in advance.
Certainly favour delay, as proposed.
E.M. Two points on para. 10
i) accept omission of proposal tht. all tariffs be subject to neg. resoln.
But believe we shall have to concede this point to Opposn. for
existg. posn. is v. untidy.
ii) contn. to Exchequer &amp; agency charges. Ready to settle with H.A.
But we shd. have a target, as other natd. indies., and charges &amp;
contn. shd. take a/c of that.
RAB. Ready to re-consider (i).
[Exit E.M.
7.
Gas Prices.
M. Informed Tuesd. tht. 3 Bds. propose modificns. amountg. to increases. Due to heavy losses last year.
E.P.C. advised me to inform Cab.
Suggest I seek to p’pone until first wk. in August.
H.A. Strong financial case for this. On timing, Aug. wd. be preferable.
J.M. 10% for Scotland is swingeing.
M. Due to increased cost of coal, wages – &amp; in Scotland uneconomic production. Hope is rationalisation betwn. gas &amp; electricity.
8.
Spain : Abolition of Visas.
Memo. approved.</content>
</cab>