<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 42-42</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 55 (59).
29th October, 1959
1. Parliament. [Enter M.R.
R.A.B. Business. Concldg. stages of debate on Address – ending Tuesday.
Private Members’ Motions. Shall have to make modest concessions – prs. 2 Wednesdays. Shall consider what effect on legislative p’mme.
P.M. Take wed. p.m. up to 10. p.m 3 Cttee.s upstairs : to avoid morning work &amp; allow part-time membership. A thought for considn.
H.B. Try to more with agreed time-tables.
R.A.B. Will bring up resoln. on procedure – for introdn. in Feby.
2.
Foreign Affairs.
a)
Meeting of Heads of Govt.
S.Ll. W. Summit – de G. seems to have accepted 19/12 : Adenauer joining for German business. He also contemplates big Summit in Apl. followg. a visit to France by Mr. K. Better close with this qua W. Summit.
b)
Supply of Arms to Cuba.
I will explain posn. to U.S. – who have sold helicopters &amp; transport aircraft – &amp; say we can’t avoid exchange proposition. Careful presentn. Will bring up, at next Cabinet, in light of U.S. views.
3.
Betting and Gaming Bill.
Part I
P.M. Thought new Cab. shd. have opportunity to consider – tho’ early Govt. approved in principle.
H. Told 6.000 shops in B’ham area alone.
R.A.B. Unlikely, I think.
J.M. 300 illegal ones in Glasgow now.
R.A.B. Scramble at start, but will settle down.
R.M. Are restns. (e.g. no sitting down) necessary?
Hail. Yes : gives effect to R. Commn. report.
Ch.H. Will it be illegal for one man to place bets for his mates – i.e. runners.
R.A.B. No. Licensed runners wd. be ludicrous. Thus, no mention in Bill.
Part II.
RAB. Cl. 10. brings law of gaming up to date. Satisfy. But Cl. 13 – gaming in clubs is more doubtful. Suggest incldg. a limit (e.g. of £1) in Cl. 13(b). Wd. wish to discuss wth K. &amp; Att.G.
Att.G. Concerned at this. Wd. permit gaming in any club, w’out supervision. Not sure that limit suggested will suffice to allay anxieties.
Cd. you subject gaming to control by Justices with exemptions for bridge, whist &amp; cribbage?
I.M. You can’t have a schedule of permitted games – too many.
Limit : diffy. is that stakes are quite out of scale with card money.
Hail. To bring law into line with existg practice need not mean much more gaming.
R.A.B. Don’t want to try to deal with bogus clubs in this Bill. Can’t therefore risk inspn. to ensure compliance with Cl. 13.
Genl. view : in support of R.A.B.’s line.
I.M. Fruit machines. Income to reputable clubs. Why not limit the percentage accruing to proprietor?
Ch.H. Can we drop this?
R.A.B. Will consider that.
Genl. View : re-examine in mood of generosity to fruit machine.
[Exit Att.G.
[Enter G.W.
4.
Civil Aviation – European Control.
D.S. Higher speeds &amp; greater heights make international control inevitable. This gives us a chance to go in with Six on something. Let us see wtr we can find basis of co-opn. – &amp; not decide at outset tht. we can’t.
Many problems to solve. Let us try to solve them together.
G.W. Support this. Joint mil/civil study may be requd.
S.Ll. Avoid appearance of sabotage – by saying in advance we wish to be members.
Agreed. [Exit G.W.
5. Commercial Policy : Liberalisation.
a)
Question of Principle.
P.M. First, do we agree there shd. be immediate further liberalisation?
H.A. We agreed in July we shd. have to do it soon, tho’ not in Aug/Sep. Argument no less strong now. No case at all on b/p. grds. for refraining. And pressures in U.S. to go v. far in cutting back on expansionist policies – aid &amp; trade. Current pressure at G.A.T.T. mtg.
K. Support. We agreed at Montreal over 12 mos. ago to set this course. Also U.S. movement cd. be v. dangerous.
H. Doms. expect this now. But wd. hope for quota on bacon (for Canada).
R.A.B. Not sure we shall be able to m’tain favourable b/p posn. Swings can be v. quick &amp; strong. Need for caution : strike that note at outset.
H.A. Results of refraining (on b/p) wd. be graver than of doing this. My proposal is designed to protect our b/p. posn.
R.M. Support. Estimate of imports resulting may well be high.
Agreed : some measures must be taken.
b) Detailed Provisions.
R.M. Paper. This is manufactured stuff, not wood pulp.
J.M. Won’t damage Scottish interest.
H.A. Textiles. If we can’t compete with U.S., at their wage levels, it’s a poor show.
P.M. Cdn’t we concede this in return for better deal on U.S. wool tariff?
D.E. We have chosen to protect b/p. by going competitive : can’t job back into protectionism on particular projects. Can’t go on selling quality clothing in U.S. &amp; expect to keep out their cheap quantity stuff.
We must go for a 2-way trade in clothing.
J.H. Canned Pigmeat. Can’t distinguish between this &amp; un-canned. Want to omit it all.
R.M. Content.
H.A. “Meat other than pigmeat?” Yes.
J.H. Omit Liquid Milk – Agreed.
J.H. Can add Flower bulbs : if agreement with Dutch in time.
H.A. Announcement. Inform Doms. Announce in Parlt. before Nov. 4th. – viz., before debate in G.A.T.T. ends. Agreed.
6. Commercial Policy.
European F.T.A. : Frozen Fish.
P.M. Alternative courses – as in brief.
We shd. make it clear we don’t accept principle tht. fish is industrial.
H.A. Fishing is even more emotional for Norway than for us. Downright refusal wd therefore wreck 7 negotiations – with lamentable results.
I therefore favour conditional offer – i) vol. agreement on quantity ii) lapse if Law of Sea altered to our disadvantage. They may be readier to take i) than ii).
Quantities. At present imports are unimportant : but idea may catch on with consumers &amp; imports may grow substantially.
Hail. Scientists think this will be natural development here.
H.A. If so, we shd. be able to compete w’out tariff.
J.H. Fishing industry v. worried. Law of Sea likely to go in favour of Scandinavians. N. now trying to have it both ways : we understood they wd. be satisfied if canned fish were treated as industrial.
I cd. accept conditional proposal so long as ii) is firm. We shd. tell Coulson we are adamant on ii).
Frozen fish is the thing of future. We are doing 40.000 t. or so. Quantity under i) shd. not be increased.
R.M. Our economy doesn’t depend on fish. This is a political ques only in U.K.
J.M. Ready to accept. But will cause pol. row in Scotland.
S.Ll. Time is against us. Delay means worse terms. U.S. &amp; Six are getting wary of Seven.
N. won’t accept ii). We shd. be ready to modify that in direction of review vice lapse.
Agreed.
Can we use Swedes as middle-men in negotns. – procedure.
J.H. Swedes &amp; Danes wd. support us on ii).
H. S. Africa will claim tht. this affects hake – &amp; we may have to compensate them on that.
Doms generally are not being brght along enough – by early informn. &amp; are getting more suspicious.
P.M. These pol. diffies must be weighed v. great economic advantages of preventg. ourselves being strangled by the Six.
Procedure. Enlist support of Sweden as intermediaries – start with i) as positive offer. On ii) we “reserve our right” to re-open : better formula than “all bets off”. E.g. reserve our right to re-negotiate tonnages if Law of Sea goes to our disadvantage.
7.
Egypt. Suez Canal Company.
H.A. No. concerned about 400, holding 30/40,000 shares at £4 a share.
No escape from income tax liability – short of legn.
Agreed : care in presentation (Ty. to brief Ch. Hill : Fin. Secy. to see Cttee.
of M.P.’s.)
8.
Trinidad.
I.M. Propose to appoint as Govr. the (W. Indian) Ch. Secy. All support, incldg Hailes.
Deputn. here seeking full internal self-Govt. – with Govr. apptd. on advice of W. Indian Ministers. Can’t accept that. But this appointmt. wd. take sting out of it : &amp; avoid break-down of conference.
P.M. New departure. Cab. shd. know.
9.
Wages Policy.
P.M. Propose to appoint Cttee.
H.A. Wd. welcome that.</content>
</cab>