<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 47-47</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 60 (59).
26th November, 1959
1. Parliament. [Enter M.R.
P.M. Business for next week.
2.
Companies Act.
P.M. Statement circulated, as requested. Foreshadows legn. on Bldg. Societies. There is also a Private Members Bill next spring.
3. Foreign Affairs.
a) Refusal of a B. ppt. to a man in China who interrogated Br. prisoners (Korea)
S.Ll. Approved – on basis tht. he can get travel cert. for return to U.K. only.
b) Supply of Arms : Caribbean.
S.Ll. Supply wd. bust embargo, &amp; annoy the U.S. Large order in money terms.
My own view : balance lies against giving authority. Pray in aid the embargo &amp; say things are not yet sufficiently settled in Cuba.
P.M. Business with Cuba is doing well. How wd. payment be secured? Cd. we offer to supply for cash but not on long credit, Govt. financed.
S.Ll. W. Allies won’t provide, if we don’t. If they buy from behind Curtain, U.S. will be pleased because may turn scale v. Castro.
H.A. If supply damaged relns. with U.S., it wd. do us more harm economically than we wd. gain by expanded trade with Cuba.
S.Ll. U.S. anxieties – their base in Cuba. Agreed : decline to supply, on basis proposed.
4. British Forces in Europe. B.A.O.R. [Enter C.S.
P.M. Recommn. from Def. Cttee.
H.W. Not now asking for full £5 M. – but minimum necessary amount over £1620 M.(?).
H.A. This wd. add £9 M. p.a. on overseas bill + £5 M (or prs. less) on home budget. On second point, I hope we cd. still get it w’in total of £1620 M. On first, I’m more worried : our overseas posn. is worsening &amp; will prob. so continue next year. Surplus (£250 M) on current a/c this year, offset by capital investment : but next year it won’t balance. Against request for increased aid, no prospect of redns. in overseas costs.
If we must do this, for pol. reasons, we shall have to reduce elsewhere, prob. in aid to underdeveloped countries. That is opposite of direction in which we want to move.
H.W. May be able to reduce a little, if others do.
P.M. Pol. oblign. to W.E.U. We don’t want to dishonour this now,
We shd. at least refrain from raising it as an issue at present. Just carry on. when we are striving to turn 6 : 7 to our advantage.
D.S. Keep oblign. on basis of nos., not divns.
H.W. We wd. put it in whatever way suits Army best.
C.S. Army plan was made on basis of 60 units at home &amp; 64 abroad. This means 10 more abroad. Will make it 40 : 84 – an unbalances distribn.
N.ATO commitment, when given to WEU, was 18% of Army : now it will be 30%. Is this a sensible distribution? Certainly not in longer term.
P.M. For the moment we must carry on.
I.M. Contrary to general policy – i) reduces aid to underdevelopeds &amp; ii) Europe is not area where we are most likely to need troops.
[Exit C.S.
5. Defence : Ballistic Missile Early Warning System. [Enter G.W.
H.W. Article by Ch. Pincher : based on leak from Washington.
P.M. Why shd. we contribute twds. cost?
D.S. Only a fraction of what it wd. cost us to put up our own.
H.A. Agree in principle, but don’t accept at once figures of cost to U.K.
H.B. Amenity : no-one (but me) will believe that this is only spot for it. We shall have to seek other means of re-building our prestige as protectors of amenity.
I accept need &amp; location. We must be prepared for a row &amp; face it. Hope we can undertake to remove it, when no longer needed.
Agreed : F.O., Ty., M/D &amp; Air Miny. to consider how to negotiate a
smaller U.K. cost., &amp; to co-ordinate any statements. (Para 17 (b)
not approved).
[Exit G.W.
[Exit M.R.
6.
S.E.A.T.O. Laos.
P.M. Apprehensive re appointing a Commr. or designating Thailand as country responsible for action.
S.Ll. Prefer that this shd. be arranged secretly on an informal basis.
P.M. In principle, we can’t refuse to have any planning in SEA. when we are always plaguing U.S. to do just this in M/E.
I.M. Even if informal there is bound to be a leak.
S.Ll. Can’t help that – so long as no formal resolns.
H. Nash (N.Z.) doesn’t agree : hope we can have 2 days to talk him round.
D.S. At least this must be done to retain confidence of Asiatics.
Memo. approved.
7.
Tanganyika.
I.M. Constitutional reform. Urgent. Unity among nationalist parties. They &amp; Chiefs favour it. Risk : if we give this to backward country like T, awkward repercussions on Fedn. C.P. Cttee. therefore suggested a modified franchise pending conference in ’60. On that basis we can go fwd.
H. I agree.
8.
Piccadilly Circus.
H.B. Memo. for informn.</content>
</cab>