<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 55-55</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 12 (60).
23rd February, 1960
4.
Law of the Sea.
J.H. Fishing industry have made their statement. Govt. statement welcoming it will be made to-day. Good officers : our trawlers don’t much like the matching gestures we suggested – save wiping the slate clean.
5. Federation of Rhodesia &amp; Nyasaland. [Enter Alport.
P.M. H.’s telegrams. He has worked hard &amp; made some impact. But evident they are in highly emotional state.
I.M. This is posn. we foresaw, some wks. ago.
If issue is narrowed to 4 (or better 3 : for March is a 6-month review period) weeks. Bargain with White head was to offer concessions on Rhodesia in return for our policy re Nyasaland. Hard to justify R. concession even with quid pro quo. Now we are asked to give first w’out the second. This will be surrender to W. and W. For my posn. was made clear in speech at Leeds, which was cleared with them.
P.M. Accelerated rate of releases has occurred. Nos. down to 260.
I.M. If we give concession to Wh., we get nothing in return.
But can’t blk. Fedn. for sake of 3 more weeks of B.’s detention.
P.M. Quid pro quo on Rh. must be safeguards for Africans in R.
This is choice of evils : when we have chosen we can consider presentation.
After discussion, general agreement that Course B. is inevitable.
R.A.B. Politically diff. in H/C. But we can wear it so long as were all following our course, after a short delay.
I.M. Tragedy is that we have given away R. concession.
P.M. Argument has ceased to operate with Europeans in Fedn. As with N. American colonists. The intelligent Europeans haven’t tried to answer our arguments. They merely say they won’t be messed about any longer.
I thought they might be bluffing. H. is satisfied they are not. And will be forced (by their public opinion) into foolish action.
[Make it clear there is no commitment on Rh. concession, save to talk.]
If they did, it wd. seem foolish to have allowed it to happen for a mere 3 wks. of continued detention of one man.
Mitigations – shd. be considered.
I.M. Weeks ago I said I contemplated Cab. wd. have to accept Course B. But implications on myself will have to be considered – in personal talks with P.M.
P.M. If we adopt Course B., H. shd. stay there &amp; tie it all up, on the spot.
Press here think tht. one of our diffies. is views of Govrs. This may help us.
Mitigations &amp; presentation – to be discussed separately.</content>
</cab>