<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/18/0 images: 66-66</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 27 (60) 26th April, 1960
1. Parliament. [Enter M.R., Att.G.
P.M. Debate on Censure Motion – by agreement betwn. Front Benches will last only 3 hours. Better that Opposition shd. closure it – move it, tho’ we wdn’t approve it. It is Opposition who wish to avoid long debate which mght disclose differences in their ranks.
R.A.B. Usual to have a time limit for Censure Motion, in order to keep a House.
D.S. Wd. prefer to get this clear at beginning of debate.
P.M. We shd. not appear to be accessories to Oppn. desire to avoid a wider debate.
R.A.B. Aim at a division not later than 8. p.m.
P.M. If they propose closure, we had better vote for it.
R.A.B. We can’t guarantee access to H/C. on day of Princess M.’s wedding. We had better therefore concede that H/C. shd. not meet.
P.M. May look churlish not to meet. Atmosphere is not so good.
2.
Foreign Affairs.
a)
Disarmament.
S.Ll. In bad propaganda posn. Tho’ initial plan tabled, we have made no further initiative. Now agreed to table a paper on principles and another on (?) time-table. This will adjourn before Summit.
Nuclear Tests Conference will continue thro’ Summit. Not much progress likely before then.
W’ton prepns. for Summit went well.
b)
Europe.
S.Ll. In W’ton point was pressed tht. we haven’t proved tht. we shall be damaged by acceleration. A more convincing presentation of our case is urgently needed.
H.A. V. diff. to produce a net figure. Trying to get Fr. and U.K. officials to prepare an agreed statement.
P.M. That wd be v. helpful.
* Wd. like to mention this in a reply to de Gaulle.
c)
Cyprus.
Latest telegram suggests agreement reached on bases.
But Makarios is eroding his own position – which is alarming for the future.
d)
Missiles: European Co-operation.
H.W. European I.R.B.M. U.S. offer : sell Polaris &amp; you provide logistics : or we will help to promote European manufacture. Second alternative (objectionable to us) is not going well : U.S. is pressing first. No European enthusiasm.
D.S. Discns. re co-opn. in aircraft production. Good progress with French. Then Germans were anxious to come in. Vertical take-off : and electronic/radar environment. Mtg. soon to clinch a tripartite plan of procedure. F &amp; G. also interested in B. Streak for space.
3. Civil Aviation: European Air Traffic Control. [Enter G.W.
D.S. Previously approved in principle.
Para. 3. approve not sign.
Another example of somethg we can do in Europe, &amp; brks. across division of Six &amp; Seven. Switz. and Scand. mght come in.
Opportunity to sell our equipment.
H.A. No opposn. : but hope ultimately there will be charges for use of equipment &amp; services.
S.Ll. Support.
G.W. Content – subject to amendments of convention to match technical needs.
[Exit G.W., Att.G.
4.
House of Commons : Members Fund.
R.A.B. If we resist this, we may increase pressure for M.P.’s pensions.
H.A. They are led away by their brokers’ advice. Think they can get 85% into equities. Unwise. Also, shd. we push M.P.’s ahead of our general legn. – privileged posn. cdn’t easily be defended.
H. Charities governed by R. Charter have bn. allowed to extend investment in non-trustee stocks.
R.A.B. Ready to see them – persuade them to wait : it H.A. will join me.
5.
Education : Salaries of University Staff.
H.A. Last increase Aug. ’57. And that was post
This is a grievance. Also Burnham award (covering analogous people in techn. schools &amp; colleges) was effective from October. dated from a decn. in March.
Distinction between improvement (as is this) &amp; re-assessments (C. Service, Pilkington, etc.,) But awkward tht. C. Service awards (executive &amp; admin’ve.) will carry heavy retrospection.
Ques for judgement is degree of hostility of Univ. staffs if we give no retrospn. U.G.C. think there will – unless we go back to date of Burnham award (Oct. 59). Compromises wd. be 1/1 – comparable to doctors. Wd. be addl. embarrassment if we don’t go at least to 1/1 because Universities contain medical element.
D.E. Fr. Dpl. angle I don’t want retrospn. For I have vacancies on staffs of higher technology colleges – &amp; I compete with Universities in filling these. New scales will make it harder. Under Burnham no retrospn. is allowed. Retrospn. here therefore wd. be dangerous if it stimulated demand for it from teachers.
R.A.B. Strong case for retrospn. on merits.
M. No stronger than in any wage negotn. which takes a long time to settle.
J.M. Sc. teachers wd. pick this up – esp. if it went beyond 1/1.
E.H. No strong argument on merits – extends retrospn. to new profession. 1/4 wd. be just : and doubt if it wd. cause much resentment.
R.A.B. Dissent. UGC. have held them off – and now need encouragement.
P.M. 1/1 wd. be a sensible compromise.
H.A. I wd. accept that.
P.M. Prs. in all circs. it wd. be better not to base ourselves on principle at all – and offer 1/1 retrospection.
M. In that event make it clear we are against retrospn. in future.
Agreed : retrospective to 1st Jan.
6. Economic Situation.
H.A. Bank advances continue to rise. Time therefore to put into opn. a modest element of control, by scheme of special deposits worked out. Accompanied by modest element of h.p. control.
Mtg. of Ministers to-morrow. Announcement on Thursday.</content>
</cab>