<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/45/0 images: 92-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY  OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  March 1951FESTIVAL OF BRITAIN: FESTIVAL GARDENS company memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsFestival Gardens Limited has exhausted its cash resources and requires imme-diately a substantial loan if it is to complete that paft of the Festival scheme.Ministers decided that a Company should be formed to prepare and managethe Gardens and the Amusement Park. The Chairman of the Company is ShHenry French, the other members being Lord Latham, Mr. I. J. Hayward (leader of the Council) and Mr. D. H. Daines (Chairman of the Finance Committee), of theLondon County Council, Sir Giles Loder, Sir Arthur Elvin, Major Joseph andMr. Gwilliam Hill, representing the National Amusements Council, four represen-tatives of the Festival Office (the Department in general charge of the Festival), the clerk of the L.C.C., and the Managing Director, Mr. Crainford.2.   In June 1949 the Festival Office took a figure of  770,000 as required tocover the cost of construction and preparation and the running costs for the year for which the Gardens were to be open.   This was divided roughly into:  ^:&apos;f V: &apos;q^&apos;bS&apos;M) &apos;        r   .&apos;        &quot;t     .   \&quot;: :!     q   /.y-&quot;:        (a) Company&apos;s share of work on site and constructionalexpenditure and other overheads before opening     ...      500,000(b) Running expenses for one year   ...      ...      ......      170,000(c) Demolition and reinstatement      ......&apos;    ......      100,000(Other construction work was then intended to becarried out by sponsors of features at their own expense.)The estimated revenue was  670,000.Accordingly financial provision was made by the Festival of Britain (Supple-mentary Provisions) Act, 1949, for a loan of  570,000 from the Exchequer and 200,000 from the London County Council, who stipulated that their loss shouldnot exceed  40,000.The Exchequer money passes through the Festival Office. Interest is charged on the whole loan. At that stage a loss of  100,000 was assumed.3. After the Company had come into being the scheme was somewhat alteredand in particular it was decided that the gross expenditure and revenue figures should include certain items which the previous estimate had assumed would beprovided entirely by sponsors. In June 1950 the Company estimated a total costof  1,100,000 with a.revenue of  1 million. By spacing their payments for work done against revenue the Company expected to be able to finance the additional cost without additional loan capital.4. By November 1950 the estimate of outgoings had gone up to  1,625,000divided roughly :-.   :-   &apos;  (a) Capital expenditure On site and construction   ...      ..; 1,060,000(b) Other pre-opening expenditure   ...      ......... 100,000(c) Running expenses for one year   ...      .......      ... 220,000(d) Demolition and reinstatement    ...              ...      ... 90,000(e) Contingencies............      ...... 150,00040300CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.     3CP. (51) 8415th March, 1951 *CABINET
2 &quot;IThe expected revenue was reduced by over  200,000 when Parliament! decided&apos;- *against full Sunday opening. Despite increased charges the revenue estimate was-kept at  1 million, involving at :that staged loss of abottt  572,000. This raised thequestion whether the Company would be able to manage without a further loancapital, and the Company on 1st January, 1951, confirmed to me that it could do so.. . x 5. On 6th March, in answer to a Written Question, and basing myself on thelatest figures supplied by the Company, I said that expenditure&quot;; *on the Gardens-wasprOving to be in excess of earlier estimates, owing to the general rise in costs and wages, the bad weather, and labour disputes but that (although it was notpossible to obtain a-firm-final-estimate) I understood thatMie total (expenditure was likely to be about  1,625,000. The revenue was expected to be  1^053,000, with anexpected loss on six months&apos; operation of  572,000.      v   ; r -v6. Two days later at the Public Accounts Committee the Chairman of theCompany stated that a closer examination of the contractors&apos; costs (which had beencompleted at &quot;a meeting of-the Company&apos;s Finance Committee that morning) made it plain that the outstanding expenditure would be much larger than had been7. An immediate review was made by the Treasury. It now appears on themost recent figures-given by the Company^^with:proper authority that the total cost will be approximately   458,000.     &apos; .    ., v .    -.;.  This will be divided:- &apos; y;;V--(a) Capital cost on site and construction ... ... ,   1,625,000&apos;          (b) Other pre-opening costs ... ... &apos;    250,000(c) Running costs ... ... 376,000(d) Demolition and reinstatement ... ... ... 90,000(e) Contingencies    ... -   ... ... ... 117,0008.   On these figures, and on the.present assumption that the Gardens will bej open for only six months, the expected loss may be as much as  1J million. Muchi[ the greater part of this increase is due to the fact that the Quantity Surveyors have come to a point where they are &quot;certifying for payment contractors&apos; bills for amountsvastly larger than were provided in the estimates or were anticipated up to thepresent month. The reasons,for this increase include:  ...(i) recourse to uneconomic methods of catching up with arrears;(ii) the continuing very wet state of the site, which severely hampers outdooroperations; &apos;       -      - \-&apos;-(iii) the constant loss of time from labour troubles; and       ;(iv) the cost of avoiding further labour troubles!9. These latest estimates raise two major financial difficulties! The higher thetotal of the contractors&apos; costs the larger the sum must be paid for work in progressin order, among other things,.that the contractor can continue to pay wages.-, TheCompany has run so short of cash that it will not be able to meet necessary cashdisbursements for more than about another week.The second difficulty is the complete unreality of the loan structure againstpresent costs.. It is absurd to continue any. longer, the statutory, limit of  770,000on the loans that will be made to the Company against contractors&apos; costs of 1,625,000 (the coincidence between the present estimate of the contractors&apos; costs and the previous estimate of total costs is purely incidental).10. After consultation with the Chancellor and on the figures given to me by the Company&apos;s Office, I am satisfied that a further loan of  1 million must bemade to the Company. This will involve legislation to amend the Festival of Britain(Supplementary Provisions) Act,: 1949. -       .....I must take the earliest opportunity to correct the false impression which Xunwittingly gave to the House about the total cost. At the same time I must indicate the need for this further large loan capital arid state the intention of the Governmentto introduce legislation for this purpose at the earliest possible date.&apos; Wheri thathas been done, the Chancellor agrees that arrangements for an advance againstthe ultimate loan of  1 million should be made to. the Company to enable them tocarry&apos;on. &apos; :&apos; :&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;r&quot;&apos;  &apos;. .11. This is a very sorry business. I am not satisfied about the contract andits supervision and I propose to institute a thorough, enquiry into this aspect of the
matter^.f;L propose also to, request the Company to, appoint immediately; with,thenecessary powers; an executive Vice-Chairman with; full authority to put the affairs of the Company in order and to review the revenue policy, i.e., the policy of charges]for admission after the first few weeks of experience.    ; ;p O12. Development expenditure on the scale that has had to be undertakencannot be liquidated, by any conceivable revenue from the Gardens in the sixmonths of 195.1 for which the Gardens will be effectively open. If the Gardensand the Amusement. Park prove popular,; it is the intention of the Leader of the.London County Council to negotiate for their continuance.; When those circum-starices arise I-should expect that reasonable financial arrangements could be madewith the London County Council by which, over the subsequent period for whichthe Gardens open, a due proportion of the surplus income on future operationshall accrue to the Treasury in reduction of its loss.13.   I ask my colleagues (1) To take note of the situation&quot;described above;(2) To agree that I should make an immediate Parliamentary statement super-sedingmy statement of 6th March (see paragraph 5) and announcingthat the Government will introduce legislation at the first opportunityto provide for a further loan of  1 million from the Exchequer;(3) That, as legislation cannot be introduced in time to give statutory authorityfor the immediate advance which is necessary, the Chancellor of theExchequer should be invited to agree to an advance from the CivilContingencies Fund. :      ,H. M.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,15th March, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
