<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/45/0 images: 127-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT      JThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limitedbeen strictly limited.      ^It is issued for the personal use top SECRET Copy No. 2qCP. (51). 9020TH MARCH, 1951CABINETPOST OFFICE TARIFFSMemorandum by the Postmaster-general at the Cabinet meeting on the 19th March, at which consideration was given to the proposals which I submitted in paper CP. (51) 71, it wasagreed that I should submit to the Lord Presidents Committee proposalsfor securing that telephone rentals could in future be altered withoutrevising existing agreements.   I am arranging for this to be done(CM. (51) 21st Conclusions, Minute 4).2. The view was also expressed that the proposed increases in PostOffice charges should be introduced only when, under impending wage claims, substantial awards had been granted.   The programme of intro-duction of the increases proposed in CP. (51) 71 was as follows:-Inland printed papers To come into force on 1st June 1951Money orders and C O. D. To come into force on 1st July 1951Telegraph charges To come into force on 1st July 1951Charges for local calls      To come into force on 1st October 1951&apos; from public kiosksOverseas parcels To come into force as soon as possibleExchange line and    - To come into force on 1st January 1952.special circuit rentalsIf we were to wait until substantial wage increases had actually been awarded, it would not be possible to announce the foregoing programmebefore the Budget, and the additional cash yield expected by the chancellor in 1951/52 could not be included in the Budget figures and might not, infact, be realised.   Apart from this aspect, I feel.that it would be unwise,from the purely business point of view, to wait until the Post Office accountsare in deficit before taking steps to increase the charges and ensure thatthe Post Office finances remain on a satisfactory basis.   I consider it wouldalso be unwise politically for the Post Office, the oldest-establishednationalised organisation, which has a tradition of service to the publicover a long period of years throughout which it has shown successfulcommercial results, to allow itself to go &quot;into the red&quot; instead of takingprudent action in advance to avoid such a situation.   I feel that the best course would be to adhere to the programme of increases set out above(subject to the variation in paragraph 3 below), on the basis that thesesteps were being taken in order to avoid a loss on the Post Office services.; -1-
3. I would, however, now propose to omit any reference in mypre-Budget announcement to increases in exchange line and specialcircuit rentals,   I think it would be sufficient to say at this stage thatI propose to introduce legislation (in whatever form the Lord presidents committee may think best) to simplify the whole procedure for alteringrental charges.   I could base this case upon the events of 1949 and the waste of man-power involved in the present system.   This would enableme, if necessary, later in the year to propose an increase in rental chargeswith effect from such date in 1951/52 as suits the conclusions of theLord Presidents Committee.4. On this basis, my announcement before the Budget would relateto the increases in tariffs set out in paragraph 2 excepting the telephonerental increases.   The cash yield would then become  6,320,000 in1951/52 and  8,190,000 in a full year.5. In accordance with the Cabinets suggestion, I have discussed withthe Chancellor the alterations in Post Office charges which should bemade at the present time.   The Chancellor would prefer that increasedPost Office charges should produce a cash yield in 1951/52 of the 9,320,000quoted in CP. (51) 71, paragraph 16, but this can be securedonly if the Lord Presidents Committee decide that the telephone rentalsin existing agreements should be varied, without individual notice, by thelegislation to be promoted;  in that case, the new rentals could become effective on 1st October 1951, giving the yield the Chancellor desires.(If the effective date were 1st January, 1952, the yield would be 7.,470,00Q,) Any increases in other telephone charges to secure a yield of this order in 1951/52 would raise the total Post Office surplus in afull year to a level which would be quite indefensible on Post Officegrounds.N.E.Post Office Headquarters, FJ. C. 1. ,20TH MARCH, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
