<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/45/0 images: 328-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
- J(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE -PROPERTY-OF-HIS BRITANNIC MAJES-TY&apos;S GOVeI^/eNTISECRETCP.(51) 115 COPY NO. 3/24TH APRIL, 1951CABINETSOVIET PROPOSAL FOR A MEETING OF FOREIGNMINISTERSPRELIMINARY TALKSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs agreed on 19th April to try to provide the Cabinet with an appreciation of the course of the talks in Paris about an agenda forthe proposed Four-Power meeting (CM. (51) 29th Conclusions, Minute 9).2. My colleagues will recollect that in earlier discussions on the proposed Four-Power talks and on the framing of an agenda wewere concerned at the probability that the Soviet delegate would insist-on placing an item on German demilitarisation at the head of the agendaand there was general agreement that it would not be practicable toproceed with the meeting if the Soviet Government insisted on confiningthe agenda to the demilitarisation of Germany and other purely Germanproblems (CM. (51) 11th Conclusions, Minute 6).3, For the first few weeks of the meeting the Russians didindeed take.the expected line, and met with the unanimous resistance of the Western delegates.   On 28th March, however, M. Gromykoannounced that the Soviet Government were now prepared to see Germandemilitarisation reduced from being the first and main item to asub-item under the Western first item, thus accepting it as one amongthe &quot;causes and effects of present international tensions in Europe&quot;.(M. Gromyko still insists that it should be the first sub-item and thispoint has not yet been conceded to him - see paragraph 11 below.)4. On a. superficial reading M, Gromyko&apos;s move on Germandemilitarisation looks like a genuine concession, but in point of factit covers an important change of tactics.   Instead of concentratingsolely on German demilitarisation, the Russians are now turning thespotlight on We stern rearmament;  instead of concentrating on anattempt to prevent the rearmament of Germany they are now trying toget an agenda which will commit us to revision of our policy ofrearming ourselves.   Another way of expressing it would be to saythat they are trying to manoeuvre for a position where they will beable effectively to undermine the defensive effort of the North atlantic treaty Organisation.5. This development in Soviet tactics is due partly to the firmnessdisplayed by the Western delegations on the German item but mainly,it is believed, to a growing realisation by the Soviet Government thatwhile our German policy is in itself unlikely in the near future to affectthe present balance of world power, the scale and impetus of the rearmament of the Atlantic Treaty nations as a whole is rapidlybuilding up an effective obstacle and deterrent to any aggressive plansthey may have in mind.
6, The new Soviet approach is a double-headed one:-(a) They demand the inclusion of an item on the Atlantic Pact andon the establishment of United States bases.(b) They insist on drawing up the passage in the agenda onarmaments in such a way as to bring disarmament.   &apos; to the front without relating it to the existing level ofarmaments.7. To concede (a) would be to admit by implication that the atlantic Pact is a caude of world tension and so to enable the russians to launch a propaganda and diplomatic offensive designed to raise doubts about Western firmness and Solidarity in carrying through our obligations under the North Atlantic Treaty and our rearmament programme.   Wecannot make any such admission or expose ourselves to such a risk,8, As to (b) there has been some divergence of view among theWestern delegations.   While there has been unanimous opposition tothe Soviet text as at present drafted, which would commit the fourMinisters to a discussion of disarmament and how to implement it without any direct relation to the present level of armaments, we forour part have hitherto taken the view that it ought to be possible toproduce a text which, while leaving the word &quot;reduction&quot; in a prominentposition, would nevertheless relate it firmly to the existing level ofarmaments.9, This view has not been shared by the United States andFrench Governments.   In deciding the best course to follow inthese circumstances, I have had two main considerations in mind:-(i)  In negotiations of this kind it is highly important to maintain a united front:  it is the only safe position from which to deal with the Russians.(ii)  The United States position is not founded on mere intransigencebut arises from conviction that any formula which placesreduction of armaments before consideration of theirexisting level would, in fact, from our point of view, bedishonest, since until some adjustment of the level hasbeen agreed, we cannot reduce and are in fact compelledby the existing Soviet preponderance to increase.10. I have found these considerations of sufficient weight tojustify me in authorising the leader of the United Kingdom delegation in Paris to assure his United States and French colleagues, if they maintain their firm opposition to any compromise, that, so far as an agreed agendais concerned, we will join them in refusing to admit(i)  any reference to the Atlantic Pact or to United States bases(ii) any reference to armaments in which deduction1 precedes&quot;level&apos;.11. In return we shall ask the United States and French delegates to agree to the promotion to the leading place under Item I of the sub-item dealing with German demilitarisation.   I have reason to believethat the United States and French Governments will meet us on thispoint and so enable us to offer a bargain to the Russians which would at
Foreign Office, S. W. 1,,24TH APRIL, 1951,any rate give them satisfaction on one point to which, they attach importance.12. . Whether the Russians would be prepared to settle on these terms is something which can only be found by asking them, and ourthree Delegations are at present concerting tactics with a view toselecting an appropriate time and manner for indicating to Gromykothat we have come to our sticking place, so far as an agreed agenda isconcerned.13. I have twice underlined that phrase about an agreed agenda.The point is that if the delegates fail to agree on an agenda acceptable to them all, there are two other possible courses which would stillenable a Ministerial meeting to take place.   The first is to work on askeleton agenda, a mere tabulation of single headings such as Tension,Germany, Austria and so on.   The second is the device of a splitagenda, which in effect means that each side will be free to set downits own version of the agenda, leaving the Ministers to agree on theorder and manner of the discussions as best they may.   I do not think we should refuse either of these courses if it proves impossible to attain an agreed agenda;  and it may well be in our interest at a suitablestage to offer them ourselves and so confirm our fundamental willingness to proceed to a Ministerial meeting.14. There is a certain risk that the Russians, when they are madeto understand that we are unwilling to yield over the issue explained above (involving inclusion of a reference to the Atlantic Pact and theprominent placing of the reduction of armaments), may decide that it isin their interest to break off the discussions altogether.   I do not regard this as probable, but it is a possibility which must be borne in mind.15. I would add that if we do get an agreed Agenda on the linesof the bargain indicated in paragraphs lu and 11 above, there are two further points to which I have drawn Mr. Davies&apos; attention with a viewboth to safeguarding our position and to setting the discussions on a morecoherent basis.   The first is the possibility of getting the Russians toaccept a written proviso, in the final communique, for example, to theeffect that the formulation of the Agenda cannot be held to commit anyof the four parties on substance.   This would obviously be of great value in combating Soviet propaganda attempts during the interim period to throw doubts on our intentions of going through with our ownrearmament and that of Western Germany.   The second is the possi-bility of obtaining Russian acceptance of our view that at the MinisterialConference Item I on the causes of international tension will be taken asa whole.   Mr. Davies will consider with his colleagues how best to proceed on these two points.H.M.


</content>
</cab>
