<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/45/0 images: 470-473</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY-OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)COPY NO. h iCABINETINTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE,33RD SESSION, GENEVA, JUNE, 1950RECOMMENDATION (NO. 88) CONCERNING THEVOCATIONAL TRAINING OF ADULTS INCLUDINGDISABLED PERSONSMemorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service desire to obtain the decision of my colleagues on the action tobe taken with regard to the acceptance of the Recommendation (No. 88;concerning the Vocational Training of Adults including Disabled Persons,which was adopted by the International Labour Conference at its Thirty-Third Session in June, 1950.    A summary of the provisions of theRecommendation is contained in Annex I to this memorandum.2. The law and practice of the United Aingdom is in generalaccordance with the provisions of the Recommendation and I proposethat it be accepted without reservation.    I accordingly seek authorityfor the issue of a Command Paper in the terms of Annex II to thisme mo r andum.A.R.SECRETCP.(51) 13326TH MA&quot;i , 1951Ministry of Labour and national Service, S.W.1,26TH MAY, 1951.
ANNEX I summary OF THE PROVISIONS OF RECOMMENDATION NO. 881. The Recommendation consists of -1 paragraphs.    It firstenunciates the principles which the Conference considered should govern the provision of vocational training for adults.    It is recommended thattraining should be worked out and developed in the light of the situationand trend of the employment market and in co-operation with employers&apos;and workers1 organisations.    In this part of the Recommendation, Govern-ments are also urged not to allow training to be used as a substitute forunemployment benefit or assistance systems and emphasis is laid on the function of training as a means to re-employment.2. The remainder of the Recommendation lays down detailed pro-visions concerning the application of these principles with regard to thescope, methods, and organisation and administration of training.    Specialsections of the Recommendation deal with the training of disabled persons and co-operation between States Members of the International LabourOrganisation in measures to promote the training of adults.3. In dealing with the scope of training the Recommendation providesfor training to be given to certain specific categories of persons, andstress is also laid on the need for supervisor training.    It is recommendedthat the arrangements should include not only initial training but alsorefresher, supplementary and upgrading training.    With regard to themethods of training, importance attaches to a provision under which employers are to be encouraged to provide training in accordance withtheir employment requirements.    This part of the Recommendation alsounderlies the need for training to be given either on the job or in con-ditions approximating as closely as possible to ordinary industrial con-ditions.    The question of standards with regard to the qualifications andtraining of instructors in training institutions is also dealt with.4. The section of the Recommendation which deals with training forthe disabled urges the provision of facilities for the disabled in accordancewith the principles and methods recommended for the able-bodied so faras medical and educational conditions permit.    Certain additional pro-visions based largely on United Kingdom practice are suggested to meetthe special needs and circumstances of disabled persons.
ANNEX ii draft OF PROPOSED COMMAND PAPERINTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE,33RD SESSION, GENEVA, 1950RECOMMENDATION (NO. 88) CONCERNING THEVOCATIONAL TRAINING OF ADULTS INCLUDINGDISABLED persons at its 33rd Session in Geneva in 1950 the International LabourConference adopted a Recommendation (No. 88j Concerning theVocational Training of Adults including Disabled Persons.    The text ofthe Recommendation was presented to Parliament in Cmd. 8185.2. The Recommendation enunciates the principles which should govern the provision of vocational training for adults.    It lays downdetailed provisions for the application of the principles as regards:the scope of training;  methods of training for production workers;training inside and outside undertakings;  training of supervisors andinstructors;  and the organisation and administration of training.Special sections of the Recommendation deal with the training of disabled persons and international co-operation in the training of adults.3. The law and practice of the United Kingdom is generally inaccordance with the provisions of the Recommendation and His Majesty&apos;sGovernment propose to accept it.


</content>
</cab>
