<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/45/0 images: 553-561</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY   OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  May .195.1SECRET Copy No.CP. (51) 1472Sth May, 1951CABINETSCHUMAN TREATY:  ALLIED CONTROL OF GERMAN HEAVYINDUSTRYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs in CP. (51) 108 of .13th April, Ministers were asked to consider the situation created by the French proposals:  (a) To initiate discussions between the three Occupying Powers and, to theextent that they are concerned, the Benelux countries, about the conflict of jurisdiction between the Schuman Treaty Institutions on the one handand Allied Controls over German coal and steel and the international authority for the Ruhr (I.A.R.) on the other.(b) To inform the German Government, in advance of these discussions, ofthe line which they proposed to pursue, i.e., that as soon as practicableafter the Schuman Treaty comes into force, through ratification in the parliaments of member countries, the functions of the I.A.R. and of theHigh Commission in respect of German coal and steel should cease, andthat the present limitations on German steel production and capacityunder the Agreement on Industrial Controls should be removed.2,  As the result of consideration of CP. (51) 108 on 16th April Ministers:  (i) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to announce that the United KingdomGovernment would be willing to participate in the discussions proposedby the French Government.(ii) Invited the Foreign Secretary to do his utmost to persuade the FrenchGovernment to limit any public statement, or any statement to theGerman Federal Government, to a similar promise to enter into discus-sions on this question, and to refrain from indicating at this stage their readiness to abandon these Allied controls as soon as the schuman treaty came into operation.(iii) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for the committee of officials which had considered the Schuman Plan at an earlier stage toprepare, for the Cabinefs consideration, a report on the implications of the Plan as finally agreed on the future of the United Kingdom coal and steel industries. (CM. (51) 28th Conclusions, Minute 2.)3.   Since Ministers reached these conclusions, the following importantdevelopments have occurred on this front:  (i) The Schuman Treaty has been signed by the six participating Govern-ments. In order to secure German signature, the French Governmentfound it necessary to inform the German Government that they intended &quot;to press at the forthcoming discussions for the abolition of the existingAllied controls over German heavy industries. The announcement onthis step was, however, deferred as a result of our representations, andthe French Government introduced some modifications into the letter in order to make it clearer that His Majesty&apos;s Government was not committed.40645 ,b ^31
(ii) The official Working Party are preparing a full report about the schuman treaty as it affects&apos; United Kingdom interests, and about the advantages and disadvantages to be derived from United Kingdom participation or association with the Treaty. This report will be ready shortly. In thev, meantime, an interim report by the Working Party, containing asummary of the provisions of the Treaty has been circulated to theEconomic Policy Committee (E.P.C. (51)44).(iii) A preliminary and exploratory meeting has been held at official level withthe French and Americans. The object of this meeting was to elucidatethose aspects of the Schuman Treaty which have a particular bearing on the continuance of Allied controls in Germany, and to provide. Ministers with information on which they could decide whether the institutions set up under the Treaty Will render unnecessary the continuedoperation of existing Allied controls. It was made clear at this meeting that the United States Government is in full agreement with Frenchintentions to abolish existing Allied controls. A record of this meetingwill be found in Annex A.(iv) The German Federal Chancellor has decided to submit a Bill on the schuman Treaty to Cabinet On 30th Or 31st May. It will go immediately thereafter or at a week&apos;s interval to the Bundesrat (Upper House) and thence to the Bundestag (Federal Parliament). Although it should bepossible to count on ultimate ratification the process in both houses would certainly be eased by an indication of Allied intentions to remove the existing controls over German heavy industries as the Schumatt Plantook effect. Conversely, any indication that, the removal of these controlsWas the subject of serious debate between the Occupying Powers might cause considerable trouble for the Federal Chancellor both on his right and On his Left Wings.4. In my view we have now received, as the result pf tripartite official discus-sions,: as much information as we can get about the working of the Schuman Treatyinstitutions in the field now covered by Allied controls over German heavy industries.I do not think that the official Working Party&apos;s final report, covering the implications of the Schuman Treaty for the United Kingdom coal and -steel industries, will help us to decide whether the institutions of the Schuman Treaty will adequately replace the existing Allied controls in their essential aspects. Further, I regard it as impor-tant that an urgent decision should be taken by Ministers about our policy towardsthe future of Allied controls if we are not to be subjected to damaging accusationsby the French, Americans and Germans of holding up the discussions of substanceproposed by the French and thus in effect hindering the ratification of the schuman treaty by the German Federal Parliament.5. The information about the Schuman Treaty given to us by the Frenchstrengthens my previous conviction that with the coming into force of the schuman treaty it would be both desirable and wise for us to give up the existing Alliedcontrols over German heavy industries, which are becoming increasingly difficultto enforce and at least one of which we have maintained solely in the interests ofthe French. To summarise briefly arguments developed at greater length in annex B:  (i) We have no interest in maintaining the I.A.R. in existence; the effect ofits main function (dividing German coal between internal consumption and export) will be attained by the operation of the High authority under the Schuman Treaty.(ii) The essential function of the Allied Coal and Steel Control Groups is to supervise the completion of the reorganisation process in the german coal and steel industries; The French have confirmed that this functionwill not be affected by the Schuman Treaty, and there is little difficultyin abandoning any secondary functions. . .tl (iii) The raising of the limit on German steel capacity may involve us in some immediate loss of scrap. Supplies of German scrap have, however,decreased very rapidly in any case; and it is increasingly difficult toenforce the existing limitation on capacity. Over the long term the schuman Treaty (Article 54) is likely to be our most effective safeguard.r against any excessive increase through foreign investment of Germansteel capacity.
6.  I therefore ask my colleagues to approve the recommendations that:  (i) we should agree, to the disappearance of the International Authority for the- &quot;      Ruhr, of those function? of the Allied Coal and Steel Orpups which dpnot concern the reorganisation of the German- coal and steel industries,and of the existing controls on German crude steel production and capacity, to take effect as soon as practicable after the Schuman Treatybecomes operative.(ii) We should enter into discussions at the earliest convenient moment withother interested Powers about the modalities of the abolition of theseAllied controls. -Foreign Office, S.WA.2Sth May, 1951.-    ANNEX ASchuman Plan and Allied Controls in GermanyRecord of a Discussion on 21st May between British, French and AmericanOfficialsA brief record of the clarifications obtained from the French at yesterday&apos;conference on various points of the Sehuman Treaty is given below. The questionsput to the French were based on Annex B of the paper of the Official working party on the Schuman Plan. (F.G. W.P. (51) 24.) The principal French spokes-man was Hirsch, of monnet  staff, supported by Leroy-Beaulieu, the FrenchEconomic Adviser in Germany.(a) Controls by Military Security board in the French view, all controls over German steel capacity, including that ofelectric arc furnace capacity, should disappear after the ratification of the schuman plan. The controls enforced through the Military Security Board over the enduses of finished steel would, however, remain in force.(b) Reorganisation under Allied High Commission Law No. 27Hirsch confirmed the statement already made by Leroy-Beaulieu to the allied high Commission in Germany to the effect that the Schuman Treaty was not intended to cover the process of deconcentration and reorganisation of the german coal, iron and steel industries. It would therefore remain a responsibility of theAllied High Commission, even after the ratification of the Schuman Treaty, tocomplete reorganisation under Law No. 27, including the protection of foreign interests and such measures as might be necessary to ensure against&quot; re-nazification.&quot;(c) Control of Investments by the Allied Coal and Steel GroupsIt was agreed that, pending the completion of reorganisation under Law No. 27,the Allied Coal and Steel Groups (or any successor body) should exercise controlover the investments of the existing coal and steel companies for the limitedpurposes of protecting foreign interests and carrying out the deconcentrationprogramme. This control might continue for these limited purposes after the high authority had begun to exercise its powers under Article 54 of the Treaty. At thisstage German investment schemes would be submitted to the High Authority (forconsideration from an economic point of view) through the Coal and Steel Groupsas trustees for the shareholders.(d) Position of Allied Countries under the Schuman treaty the French explained that, in their view, holding companies controlling ironand steel companies would be subject to the provisions of Article 66 (i) of the Treaty40645 B 2
and would fall under the definition of &quot; enterprises &quot; in Article 80. Thus, if theGermans adopt the&quot; holding company &quot; form of structure as a link between, theirCoal arid Steel industries, there would be no risk of these industries falling outsidethe provisions of the Schumah Treaty. &apos;       &quot; ;1$)i&apos;G6htfol ofInvestments under the Treaty -      1 .       :The French gave explanations on various aspects of Article 54: - (i) They confirmed that the first two sub-paragraphs of the Article referredto different types of investments, the second (for which the unanimous agreement of the Council is required) covering investments outside theiron and steel industry but of benefit to it. The example given was a, scheme of railway electrification.(ii) The French explained that the phrase &quot; ses fonds propres &quot; referredexclusively to self-financing by the companies concerned and that theprohibition in the case of an unfavourable opinion by the High authority was intended to cover all forms of unsecured loans (e.g., from Govern-ments or banks).(iii) When asked about the practicability of enforcing such restrictive controls,the French maintained that the High Authority&apos;s power of procuringand checking information and of imposing heavy fines in cases ofcontravention would render the enforcement of controls possible.(iv) The French were asked directly whether the effect of Article 54 would beto provide a check on excessive expansion of the German steel industry.They made the formal and pious answer that the High Authority would reach its decisions under Article 54 in the light of the interests of thecommunity as a whole, and the Article was not conceived as restrainingcapacity in any country. The only limitation which they envisagedwas on nationalistic autarchic expansion tending to need direct or indirect protection contrary to the principles of a free market.Mr. Tomlinson, the Financial Attache of the United States Embassy,intervened to say that he had been given to understand that the emphasisof the Schuman Plan would be on the expansion of production.(/) Exports in time of shortageThere was some detailed discussion of Article 59 (iii) about the procedure tobe followed by the High Authority in times of shortage. Hirsch gave the followinginterpretation of this article:  (i) The High Authority makes a general estimate of, e.g., the coal consump-tion of the community as a whole and of the coal which it is necessaryto export outside the community. He said that the phrase &quot; en fonctionde &quot; was fairly vague since it was impossible to be precise over a50-years&apos; period. It means &quot; tenant compte des affaires existantes.&quot;(ii) In the light of these estimates a division of total resources will be madeamong the participant countries, including an estimate of the amount which participant countries should export to the others.(iii) Governments of participant countries may then deal freely with the quotaallotted to them, so long as the amount reserved for delivery to otherparticipant countries is not affected.(iv) Governments must, however, consult the High Authority about the amount which they export outside the community or allocated to the coal andsteel industries in their country. If their exports to countries outsidethe community are decreased, or increased at the expense of theirdomestic coal and steel industries, the High Authority will again inter-vene. The High Authority has, however, no powers of intervention ifexports outside the community are increased at the expense of generalhome consumption.The French confirmed that non-participant countries had no safeguard underthe Treaty against cuts in coal exports from the community. The community wouldtake its decisions in the light of the interests and obligations of its members.Hirsch implied that it would try, in regard to coal and steel exports, to act as if itwere one country. He also mentioned obligations under G.A.T.T., which the com-munity would have to honour like its constituent member States. He did not specifically -cally refer to United Kingdom coal exports last winter.
(g) Date of expiry of I. A.R. r     -  t, . , iThe French confirmed, that the intention of M. Schuman&apos;s letter to dr. Adenauer (our telegram No. 1140 of 16th April) was that the international authority for the Ruhr should cease to function as soon as the High authority had started to operate under the interim provisions (2:2 IV). They further con-firmed that this function would be among the first exercised by the High Authority.(h) Exports in the Interests of Western defence the French were reminded that under the &quot; guarantee of equitable apportion-ment&quot; given by the Federal Government to the Allied High Commission, theGermans had undertaken to see that there was a reasonable balance betweenGerman internal consumption and export in the case of goods in short supply.This guarantee applied, inter alia, to finished steel and scrap and to exports outsidethe Schuman community. The French confirmed that there was no specific provi-sion in the Schuman Treaty which ensured that the needs of countries outside thecommunity would be given due priority in this connexion, when the Council orthe High Authority came to allocate coal and steel under Article 59. Hirsch, how-ever, emphasised that the needs of Western defence had been very much in the minds of the drafters of the Treaty, particularly in the case of Article 59. he explained that the rather curious procedure under which allocation in time of shortage should be undertaken in the first place by the unanimous decision of theCouncil and, failing such a decision, by the High Authority, had been designed toprevent the Germans, who were not members of N.A.T.O., from disregarding theneeds of Western defence. If the Germans blocked a decision of the Council which took due account of defence needs, the question of allocation would then come before the High Authority which would act in a responsible way in relation to theobligations of the greater part of the community.The French further explained, incidentally, that Section 22 of the InterimProvisions, which lays down that German interzonal trade in coal and steel shallbe regulated between the High Authority and the Federal Government, does notin any way affect the Security powers of the High Commission. It was intendedto prevent any implicit recognition in the Treaty of the Soviet zone as territoryforeign to the Federal Republic.ANNEX BInternational-Authority for the Ruhr (I.A.R.)The information which has been obtained about the Schuman Treaty showsthat its objects cover the objects of the Ruhr Agreement, and that the proposedHigh Authority will absorb the only essential function of the I.A.R This is the division of German coal production between internal consumption and export (notthe country-wise allocation of exports). It is in the general interest of the UnitedKingdom that:  ^(i) Germany should export sufficient coal to fulfil the needs of at least the major European consumer industries.(ii) Germany should retain sufficient coal to provide at least for those industries which contribute most to Western defence and to righting the Germanbalance of payments.2. These objects have naturally proved increasingly hard to reconcile in theforum of the I.A.R., which the Germans have always regarded as a servitudeimposed upon them and as an obstacle to equal status in the European community.It is indeed doubtful whether the Germans would for much longer continue to implement the decisions of I.A.R. in this sphere. Most of the main importers ofGerman coal are participants in the Schuman Treaty, and they are likely in the longrun to have their needs met more fully and more readily under the Treaty (wherethe Germans are equal partners) than under the Ruhr Agreement, In times ofample supply, German coal should be available freely throughout the Schuman
&quot;Community.&quot; In times of shortage, there will be allocation within the &quot;Com-&apos;munity&quot; of its total coal resources either by the Council of Ministers actingunanimously, or failing&apos; that by the, High Authority,&apos; Participant; governments would be free to determine their exports outside the &quot; Community &quot; provided thatdeliveries within the &quot; Community &quot; are not affected and subject to consultationwith, the High Authority. In practice this might mean that the French or Belgianswould-receive preferential treatment in respect of German coal exports vis-a-visfor instance the.Danes and the Swiss. This might (though not necessarily) be against our interest; but it is probable that the Germans will do all that they canto maintain their exports to some countries at least outside the &quot; Community.&quot; :3. In general I consider it in our interest to see the I.A.R. abolished. For our part we get nothing out of it at present except a share in the odium aroused amongthe Germans by an unpopular organisation. In the future it can only become more ineffective as the Germans tend to refuse co-operation. Nor could it, in my view, usefully assume any powers to prevent reconcentration and &quot; re-Nazification &quot;or to control investment for which provision is made under Articles 18 and 19 of the ruhr Agreement. These are functions which in the long run can best be exercised by the Schuman Treaty High Authority (prevention of re-concentrationand controlof investment) or by the Federal Government under a contractual arrangement with the Allied High Commission (prevention of re-Nazification). It will be recalled that we agreed to the establishment of the I.A.R. largely because we wished toobtain French agreement to the establishment of a German Federal Government;if the French, in view of the establishment of the Schuman Treaty High Authority,are willing to contemplate the abolition of the I.A.R., we may regard ourselvesas honourably discharged from that bargain.The Allied High Commission^ Powers Over German Coal and Steel4. The powers of the Allied High Commission are exercised through the tripartite organisation of the Combined Coal and Steel Groups. By far their mostimportant function is the deconcentration and reorganisation of the German coal,iron and steel industries under Allied High Commission law No. 27, The french have now formally confirmed that the Schuman Treaty is not intended to coverthis process, and that ratification will not in any way affect the powers of theAllied High Commission to carry out its functions in this field. They have furtherconfirmed that, even after the Schuman Treaty has been ratified and the high authority has started to supervise the investment programmes of coal and steelenterprises within the &quot; community,&quot; the Coal and Steel Groups will be able toexercise their powers of controlling the investment programmes of the Germanindustries with a view to the protection of foreign interests and to the completionof the deconcentration programme. The most important functions of the high commission in the control of the German coal and steel industries will thus be safeguarded even after the Schuman Treaty is ratified and begins to take effect.5. The functions of the Coal and Steel Groups outside the sphere of reorganisation are in general of little importance. It may be mentioned that wehave a continued interest in maintaining and increasing German coal production(which was at one time the primary task of the Coal Control Group):\ This functioncan safely be left to the &quot; High Authority &quot; to be set up under the Schuman Plan.The immediate effect of the Treaty may be to reduce the profits of the german coal companies, by imposing a levy on their output and by abolishing dual pricingfor exports to other countries within the community,&quot; In the matter of invest-ment, however, the High Authority can and probably will assist the German coalcompanies under Article 54 of the Treaty (see Appendix I) both by direct financialassistance and by guaranteeing loans raised from other sources. The net effect ofthis action should be to increase German coal production.Removal of Present Limitations on Steel Production and Capacity6, The present position is that there is a nominal limitation on Germancrude steel production of 11 -1 million tons per annum, but steel used or exportedfor the purposes of Western Defence is permitted outside this quota. This control,which was instituted as a temporary system after the New York meeting of Foreign
Ministers in September 1950, and has been maintained in the Agreement cmindustrial Controls of MarGh 1951, at the insistence of the French, is more nominalthan real and is largely unworkable. German steel production has been fluctuatingbetween annual rates of 13-3 and 12 million tons in the last six months. the controls On steel production and capacity in the Agreement on Industrial Controlsare operated on a licensing system&apos;which permits additions and modernisationsprovided they do. not substantially increase the capacity of the plant in question ofof the industry as a whole. It must be recorded that the practical- difficulties in operating these controls are bound to grow, as German co-operation becomes morereluctant under changing political conditions.7. These controls were instituted for security purposes. The Chiefs of Staffagreed at a meeting on 1 2th February, 1951, that the security risk involved inwaiving restrictions on steel-making capacity was acceptable. They added thatthere would be definite advantage if the lifting of restrictions were to result in anincrease in the availability of steel for Western rearmament as a whole. Even inthe absence of a German military contribution, German industry, with steel as itscore, can be of substantial assistance to Western defence programmes and the prolongation of controls cannot fail to discourage the Germans from providing such assistance.8. There are, moreover, Strong political reasons for removing existingcontrols on production and capacity at an early date even apart from the schuman treaty. Under the policy, approved by the three Foreign Ministers in Brussels and now being worked out in detail, of placing upon a contractual basis all reserved powers now exercised by the High Commission except those which must be reservedfor a Peace Treaty, there will be little prospect of retaining effective controls overGerman steel production or capacity. It is, moreover, our avowed intention tobring Western Germany fully into the community of Western nations as an equalpartner without disabilities save those imposed by the absence of a formal peace treaty, the occupation of Germany in the interests of Western Defence and themaintenance of our position in Berlin. Apart from the fact that to stand againstthe removal of the existing controls on German steel production and capacity would expose us to the charge of trying to provoke German resistance against the schuman plan and thus of obstructing its realisation, it is very doubtful whether, in terms ofour German policy, we can afford to stand out for long against Franco-american agreement to remove these controls.9. Under the provisions of the Schuman Treaty, there would be no limitation on German steel production (except possibly in time of slump) but investment programmes involving the extension of capital plant would, under Article 54, be liable to scrutiny by the High Authority. Approved projects might receive director indirect financial assistance from the Authority. Projects which are not approvedwould be entirely dependent on &quot; self-financing &quot; from their own funds and wouldbe unable to raise any form of unsecured loan. The French consider that, in thelight of the High Authority&apos;s powers to procure and check information and to imposeheavy fines on the firms concerned, it should be quite practicable to enforce control under Article 54. In answer to enquiries, the French would not admit that thisArticle would operate to check excessive expansion of the German steel industry.They would not-say more than that the High Authority would reach its decisions inthe light of the interests of the &quot; community &quot; as a whole and that the Article was notconceived as restraining capacity in any country, although they, admitted that acheck envisaged on policies of nationalistic and autarkic expansion. It is, however,very unlikely, in view of French efforts in recent years to restrain German expansion,that the High Authority on which French interests would in effect be substantiallyrepresented, should not in fact operate as a check on indefinite German expansion.Indeed, over the long term, the High Authority is likely to provide the best means ofcontrol that will be available to us against such expansion.10. Over the long term therefore the removal of the existing limitations on theGerman steel industry and the substitution of the machinery to be set up under the schuman Treaty will probably be advantageous to us. It must, however, beadmitted that some of the immediate consequences may be less palatable. Anincrease in German steel capacity will in the first place result in an increased con-sumption of ferrous scrap by the German steel industry. This, in turn, may furtherreduce the scrap available for export to the United Kingdom. I doubt whether thisdisadvantage is as grave as it may appear at first sight.   It must be recognised that
the supply of German scrap for export is diminishing rapidly quite apart from the schuman Treaty, and in spite of the continuing pressure which has been brought tobear in Germany on. the Federal Chancellor and German officials. It must furtherbe recognised that, when the Schuman Treaty comes into effect, the supply of scrapas well as of coal and steel will be controlled by the High Authority, and we must assume that priority will be given to the needs of the &quot;community.&quot; The french have made it plain that non-participant countries have no safeguard under theTreaty against cuts in coal exports from the &quot; community &quot; and the same will apply to scrap exports. Unless therefore we are prepared to oppose the wholeconception of the Schuman Treaty (which I regard as impracticable and politically impossible) or to drive a bargain with participant Governments at a later stageabout the supply of scrap to the United Kingdom (which is hypothetical), it will be a difficult to count on further supplies from Germany when the Treaty is ratified.Moreover, I am very doubtful whether, even if we succeeded in maintainingtheoretically the existing limitation on German steel capacity, it would be possibleto enforce this limitation in practice for much longer against German, French and american opposition.11. In so far as our difficulties in.obtaining scrap lead us, as I believe theymay, into purchasing semi-finished steel in Germany in its stead, the removal ofexisting controls on steel production and capacity should operate to our advantage.It must, however, be recorded that there is no specific provision in the schuman treaty which ensures that the needs of countries outside the &quot;community,&quot; even for purposes of Western defence, will be given any priority when under Article 59a period of shortage is declared and the High Authority starts to allocate the coal and steel production of the &quot; community.&quot; This may be held to nullify one of theadvantages which we might hope to gain from lifting the existing restrictions. Ingeneral, however, it is my view that the disadvantages of acting in this sense are substantially outweighed by the political arguments which I have advanced inparagraph 8 above. ,APPENDIX article 54 of the Schuman treaty the High Authority may facilitate the carrying out of investment programmesby granting loans to enterprises or by giving its guarantee to loans which they mayobtain elsewhere.With the concurrence of the Council acting by unanimous vote, the high authority may assist by the same means in financing works and installations whichcontribute directly and principally to increase production, lower production costsor facilitate marketing of products subject to its jurisdiction.In order to encourage a co-ordinated development of investments, the high authority may, in accordance with the provisions of Article 48, require enterprisesto submit individual programmes in advance, either by a special demand addressedto the enterprise concerned or by a decision defining the nature and the size of the programmes which must be submitted.Within the framework of the general programmes described in Article 46, theHigh Authority may, after having given the interested parties an opportunity topresent their views, issue an opinion on such programmes, accompanied by a justi-fication. It it obliged to issue such an opinion when so requested by an enterprise.The Hugh Authority shall notify the enterprise of its opinion and shall bring it tothe attention of the Government concerned. The list of opinions shall be made public.If the High Authority recognises that the financing of a programme or theoperation of the installations which it entails will require subsidies, assistance, pro-tection or discrimination contrary to the present Treaty, the unfavourable opiniontaken by virtue of this justification shall have the force of a decision as defined inArticle 14, and shall have the effect of prohibiting the enterprise concerned fromresort to resources other than its own funds to put such programme into effect.The High Authority may impose fines not exceeding the sums unduly devotedto realisation of the programme in question on enterprises which violate the pro-visions of the above paragraph. - -* - &apos;   &apos; *


</content>
</cab>
