<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/35/8 images: 82-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1943.SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (43) 108.March 12, 1943.WAR CABINET.POWER TO APPOINT GOVERNMENT  DIRECTORS TO CERTAINWAR  PRODUCTION  UNDERTAKINGS.AT the Prime MinisterV request, I submit for the approval of the WarCabinet the following proposals for amendment of Defence Regulation 54CA,which empowers competent authorities (mainly Supply Departments) to appointGovernment directors to companies engaged in war production,2. The existing Regulation (see Appendix I) was made on theXOth- February, 1943. A Motion for its annulment has been tabled in the Houseof Commons, but has not yet been debated. Informal consultations have beenheld; with Members supporting this Motion; and, after considering their repre-sentations, the Lord Presidents Committee decided (L.P. (43) 15th Meeting,Minute 1) that the existing Regulation should be revoked and replaced by a newRegulation in the terms set out in Appendix II.3. The main differences between the existing Regulation and the proposed new Regulation may be summarised as follows : (a) It has been suggested that, under the existing Regulation, the power toappoint Government directors might have been exercised in caseswhere the amount of Government assistance given to the company wassmall, or even in cases where no capital grants had been made, if the firm were engaged mainly on Government contracts.In the new draft, it has been made clear that the power will be exercisable only where the company has received, or is about to receive,from the Government substantial advances or grants of a capitalnature.(b) The existing Regulation provides that, if the board of directors pass aresolution objecting to a proposed appointment of Governmentdirectors, the Minister shall not proceed with the appointment unless he assumes that measure of responsibility for the company which is involved by the appointment of an authorised controller under defence regulation 55 (4). This provision was designed as a safeguard, butobjection has been taken to it on the ground that, it implied someextension of the classes of case in which an authorised controller mightbe appointed. The Members supporting the Motion for the annulmentof the Regulation have suggested that this reference to authorisedcontrollers should be deleted. The mere deletion of these words would,however, produce the result that Government directors could not beappointed to a company if the existing board of directors objected tothe proposal; and this would defeat the whole purpose of the regulation.In view of the objection taken, to this reference to the power toappoint an authorised controller,, the Lord Presidents committee decided that the best course would be to omit entirely proviso (b) to paragraph (1) of the existing Regulation thus withdrawing the rightMemorandum by the Lord President of the Council.[25155]
of a board of directors to make formal objections against a proposal toappoint Government directors. Thus, the proposed new Regulationwould empower a competent authority to appoint Government directorsto a company, even though the existing board of directors were opposedto this course; but the opposition of the existing board would not put the competent authority under any obligation to proceed with themore drastic measure of appointing an authorised controller to assume responsibility for the affairs of the company.(c) The proposed new Regulation will provide that appointments of Govern-ment directors shall be reviewed by the Minister annually.4. It is not considered likely that the proposed new Regulation will prove acceptable to the Members supporting the Motion for the annulment of theexisting Regulation. Though the alterations outlined in paragraph 3 (a) and (c)above will meet some of their criticisms, the change explained in paragraph 3 (6)is not likely to commend itself to them.The Lord Presidents Committee considered, however, that the new form of regulation now proposed could be more easily defended than the existingRegulation. In its new form, the Regulation would confer a straightforwardpower to appoint (not more than three) Government directors, even against thewishes of the existing board of directors, to a company engaged in war prOduc-tion in which a substantial amount of Government money had been invested;It is not unreasonable that the Government should have the right to berepresented on the board of a company in which it has substantial financial interests; and it will be easier to defend that proposition if the issue is notclouded by suggestions (which would be put forward in respect of the existingRegulation) that the power may be used to extend the field within which privateundertakings are to be brought under the authority of a Government controller.Por these reasons, the Lord Presidents Committee considered it expedient that, before this issue was debated in Parliament, the existing Regulation shouldbe revoked and replaced by a new Regulation in the form set out in Appendix II.J. A.Privy Council Office,Great George Street, S. W. 1,March 12, 1943.


APPENDIX I.COPY OF STATUTORY RULE AND ORDER 196.Order    adding   Regulation    54CA   to    the \ Defence. (General) Regulations, 1939.-   .After Regulation fifty-four C of the Defence (General) Regu-lations, 1939, there shall be inserted the followingRegulation:-I&apos; 54ca.-(1) If a competent authority is satisfied, with; respect Addi-to any war.production undertaking carried on by.a company,1: tlonalthat, for the purpose of improving the efficiency of the war pro-  0 war-pro-ductionof the undertaking, it is expedient to associate with the. auctiondirection of the company one or more persons nominated by the undertaking -authority, the competent authority may give directions appoint- ings.ing to be a director of the company any person appearing to theauthority to be experienced in the direction of companies of alike character; and any person so appointed shall be deemed for all purposes to have been duly appointed to be a director ofthe company in accordance with the articles of associationthereof, and to have any necessary qualifications for being such a director, and shall continue to hold office as a director until he is removed from that position by directions of the competent authority: -Provided that (a) the powers conferred by this Regulation shall not be exer-cised with respect to any company, unless it appears to thecompetent authority that the exercise thereof is expedientin the public interest, having regard to any expenditure orinvestment of public moneys incurred or made, or proposed&apos;   to be incurred or made, in connection with the company orthe war production of the undertaking; \(b) before appointing any person, in exercise of the saidpowers, to be a director of any company, the; competent authority j shall serve upon the company notice of theappointment proposed jto be made, and, if within seven days after service of the notice a resolution objecting to theappointment is passed by the board of directors of the com-pany and communicated to the competent authority, thecompetentj authority shall not make the appointment unlessan order Is made under paragraph (4) of Regulation fifty-five of these Regulations authorising an authorised controller to exercise functions of control on behalf of His Majestywith respect to the undertaking carried on by the company;(c) the number^ of persons appointed under this Regulation tobe directors of any company shall not be sufficient to con-stitute a majority of such directors on the board of directors,and shall not in any case exceed three;
to^46a^(d) no director appointed under this Regulation shall, unless it is otherwise agreed between him and the company, -be5entitied to receive any remuneration out of the moneys ofthe company in respect of his position as a director.(2) In this Regulation the expression &apos; war production under-taking &apos; means an undertaking which, in the opinion ofthe competent authority, is or should be principally engagedupon the production or supply of articles required forthe use of the armed forces of the Crown or otherwise for the prosecution of the war or the defence of the realm, or upon the performance of services required for such purposes, and theexpression &apos; war production &apos; shall be construed accordingly.&quot; *Printed by His Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office Press,Drury Lane, W.C.2.(6875)   Wt. 9-1   70   3/43   d.l.   G. 416
APPENDIX II.Draft of Proposed Order Revoking Statutory Rule andOrder No. 196 and Substituting a New Order Therefor.Regulation fifty-four CA of the Defence (General) Regulations,1939, is hereby revoked and in lieu thereof there shallbe inserted the following Regulation:  54cA.-(i) If a competent authority is satisfied, with respectto any war production undertaking carried on by a company,that, for the purpose of improving the efficiency of the war pro-duction of the undertaking, it is expedient to associate with thedirection of the company one or more persons nominated by theauthority, the competent authority may give directions appoint^ing to be a director of the company any person appearing to the.authority to be experienced in the direction of companies; andany person so appointed shall, unless previously removed bydirections of the competent authority, continue to hold office asa director for a period of one year from the date of his appoint-ment and no longer but without prejudice to the power of the-competent authority under this Regulation to re-appoint him orto appoint another, person by directions given thereunder:Provided that (a) the powers conferred by this Regulation shall not be exer-cised with respect to any company, unless public moneys^of an amount which is in the opinion of the competent authority substantial having regard to the circumstances ofthe case, have been or are proposed to be expended by wayof advances or grants of a capital nature to the company for the purposes of its undertaking or in providing capitalassets for the Use of the company;(&amp;) the number of persons appointed under this Regulationto be directors of any company shall not be sufficient to constitute a majority of such directors oh the board of,directors, and shall not in any case exceed three.(2) A person appointed under this Regulation to be a directorof any company shall be deemed for all purposes to have been duly appointed to be&apos; a director in accordance with the articlesof association! of the company, and to have any necessary quali-fications for being such a director:Provided that no such director shall, unless it is otherwiseagreed between him and the company, be entitled to receive anyremuneration out of the moneys of the company in respect of hisposition as a director; and for the purposes of any provisions ofthe articles of association of the company restricting the number or regulating the retirement or appointment of directors a director appointed under this Regulation shall be deemed notto be included among the number of directors.
(3) In this Regulation the expression &apos; war production under-taking &apos; means an undertaking which, in the opinion of the com-petent authority, is or should be principally engaged upon the^production or supply of articles required for the use of the armed forces of the Crown or otherwise for the prosecution of the war or the defence of the realm, or upon the performance of services-required for such purposes, and the expression &apos; war produc-tion &apos; shall be construed accordingly.&quot;Printed by His Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office Press,Drury Lane, W.C.2.(6876)   Wt. 9 1   80   3/43   d.l.   G. 416a-Q



</content>
</cab>
