<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/110/0 images: 603-618</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A433h;SECRETReport Jo. 68DIRECTORATE Off INTELLIGENCE        (Home Office)&quot;72 T-Scotland House,  S.W.I.  19th August,  19201793REPORT ON REVOLUTIONARY ORGANISATIONS         IN THE UNITED KINGDOM, ---------------COO-------t--------  (Circulated by the Home Secretary)THE &quot;COUNCIL 03? ACTION&quot; .................................PAGEATTITUDE OP THE RANK AND FILE...................&apos;........    &quot;TRE COAL.MINERS........................................,THE ENGINEERS ......................................&quot;.....THE &quot;NO RENT&quot; STRIKE....................................THE HOUSING QUESTION.....................................&quot;THE COMMUNIST PARTY. OP GREAT BRITAIN&quot; .....V........____OPPOSITION TO PATRIOTIC MEETINGS........................ANTI-GERMAN OUTBURST AT RAMSGATE .........................UNREST IN THE LOWER DECK................................FEELING AMONG EX-SERVICE MEN ............................MR. MALONE, M.P.........................................GEORGE NICHOLSON........................................IRELAND.................................................wTFFTTFFFFFFFTTTFTFFTSUMMARY 1 2 6 7 8 9 910101112IE1213     The event of the week has been the establishment of the&quot;Council of Action&quot;, which tried to regularise its position inthe Labour world by obtaining authority from the Conferenceheld on August 13th.  It is being borne in upon moderate menthroughout the country that the &quot;Council of Action&quot; and itssubsidiary Committees are Soviets and that the establishment ofsuch bodies is in conflict not only with the constitution of thecountry but with the constitution of Trade Unions themselves.The revolutionaries alone have no misgivings.  It has been agala week for them and some of their speakers have shown symptomsof intoxication.     The publication of the wireless messages indicating thatthe &quot;Daily Herald&quot; is subsidised from Russia has, to ;)udge fromthe apologetic tone of the &quot;Herald1s&quot; disclaimer, shaken theposition of the paper.  The publicity happens to have struckthe exact psychological moment.     Though the industrial situation is grave there areencouraging symptoms.  The miners are determined to strikeunless their demands are granted and the gas workers are nearlyout of hand but there is a strong body among responsible labour which would be glad to defer the struggle.  Moreover, the output in engineering centres has improved during the last three months -an encouraging symptom.The/
     The tension over tho Polish question is largely artificialand is really due only to the fear of conscription, hut therearo genuine grievances in the increase in rents, railway fares,bread and ooal, and behind.all hangs the dark shadow ofunemployment,  Hever haa there been greater need for propagandashowing that the Government is not the cause of all the evilswhioh mankind has to suffer,     A new role has been found for Mr. Ramsay Macdonald, whohas lately consented to swallow his principles and serve on the&quot;Counoil of Action&quot;,  He has been asked to become a sort of advisory Chancellor of the Exchequer in Georgia.  Mr, Tom Shawand Mrs, Snowden are other members of what the &quot;labour leaser&quot;terms a &quot;unique deputation&quot;,     While there is no improvement in Ireland, there is adecrease in grave outrage, probably owing to the heavy casualties incurred by those who take part in them.
THg &quot;COUNCIL OF AOTIOM&quot;          The Labour Conference which met on August 13th  and     claimed to represent some 6,000,000 Trades Unionists endorsed     the formation of the &quot;Council, of Action&quot; and authorised  it  to     order any form of strike considered neoessary to seoure          I.   An absolute guarantee against any support  for               military or naval attacks on the Soviet Government;         II.   The withdrawal of any naval forces blookading               Russia.        III.   The recognition of the Soviet Government and the               establishment of unrestricted trading relations               between Great Britain and Russia.          The Conference further authorised the Counoil to impose a     levy, equal to one halfpenny per member, as and when required.          The proceedings of the &quot;Council of Action&quot; have been     fully described in the Press and constitute a surprising     chapter in British industrial history.   In form, the body is a     Central Soviet and is in conflict with not only the  Constitution     of the country but the laws governing Trades Unionism.               ^The Council is entrusted definitely with  the          executive power to call out at a moment1s notice and          without question this or that section of the Labour          Movement.  It can organise, and is prepared to  organise,          complete control of foreign policy, and of that domestic          production and distribution of commodities which, in the          last resort, determines policy.&quot;     The arrogation &apos;of power to call a general strike cuts at the     roots of trade union policy as, in the great majority of cases,     a ballot of members is essential before even the properly     elected Union officials can call their men out.   This fact     seems to have dawned even on the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; (the official     organ of the &quot;Council of Action&quot; and of Moscow)  for  looal     councils are expressly warned that &quot;they are not in  any  way to     usurp the powers  of Trade Union executives,  especially so far     as the withdrawal of labour  is concerned,  but are to act as     centres of information.&quot;  nevertheless,  they are &quot;to act in    &quot;accordance with any instructions received from the national                                                    Council/
       Council  either  direct  or1through the medium  of the  &quot;Daily       Herald&apos;&quot;.   It is  interesting to note, in  this connection, tha       Mr. Brace.  M. P.,  President  of the  South Wales Miners1       Federation, prophesies &quot;chaos&apos; and  disruption&quot; should  the       &quot;Council of Action&quot; remain  a controlling  authority  over       Trade Unions.  .           The formation of  local councils has  been general through       out the country,  but so far they are merely  the Trades and       Labour Counails,  with  power to co-opt.  Generally they seem t       be shy of Communists and  it seems probable that when  the       Communists  succeed in  capturing,them the  more staid Labour       elements will drop.out.   Though sturdy opponents of the       Soviet system like Mr. Ramsay Mac cbonald have swallowed their      principles  and  joined  them, any attempt on the part of these       local Soviets to  meddle in affaire outside the Polish question                                                i       would arouse opposition from the bona-rfide Trades Union      branches.  At the same time, the fact remains that they are    ... ,  in existence and  are, welcomed by the extremists as the machin       for the revolution which  they try to convince themselves is       imminent.   It will be  remembered that the National Counoil      reoommended their formation in order to deal with strike      arrangements, and questions of supply and transport.  The^ use      of these councils, in  the event of a miners1  strike, for       instance, is therefore apparent.  They owe their existence       to the genuine fear of conscription that  exists in the lower      middle and working classes and not to any tenderness for      Russia, for if there were no question of war there would be a      very feeble response to a strike-call to  enforce recognition      of the Soviet Government.ATTITUD5 Off THg RAM AND fflLB           It is now possible to form some estimate of the opinion      of the rank and file on the &quot;Council of Action&quot; and as their                                                         views/
views are an exceedingly important factor in the situation,I give at length the reports of some of my correspondents.Yorkshire          &quot;All the various socialist groups have been     working overtime during the past week in this area.     The big talk at the Labour Conference, the     exaggerations in the &quot;Dally Herald1  about the crisis,     and the establishment of the &quot;Council of Action&apos;     have all put the local oracles in a very important     frame of mind and wild revolutionary speeches have     been made.  There have been no outside speakers with     the exception of Ebury at Leeds,  Wallhead at Bradford     and Bromley and Ponsonby at Sheffield.          &quot;Ebury at his meetings announced, in a very     jubilant manner, that the British Central Soviet  is     now firmly established. , They could  call it     Council of Action1  or any other  name they like.  It     did not matter,  revolution is imminent and the     Government have got the Twind upf  as never before.          &quot;Bromley,  at Sheffield,  addressing 2,000 people at  ...  Paradise Square, said amongst other  things that 15     of  his  colleagues in London jjad practically taken over     the Government of the country for the purpose of peace or     war.  They wanted to avo&apos;id a strike  but would not stand     any playing with by the Government.   If a strike occurred     they would not  be so foolish as to let the  people starve.     The bakers and railwaymen would keep things going.     He  further said that the &apos;Council of Action&apos;  deputation  :     had faced the Premier with the  chicanery of dirty secret     diplomacy and the absolute deception practised by the     people  who hold the. liveB of hundreds of thousands in     their dirty hands.   The Labour  leaders were determined to     carry through their  mandate from  the workers  within the  -     next few days.   The  &apos; Council  of Action1  had saved this ;     oountry from being already mixed  up  in a holocaust of     slaughter.   He  also  urged that  money granted  by the     French  Chamber  to restore Northern France had been used     to  support General Wrangel,  and that France was becoming     once  again the  1 Bully of Europe&apos;.          &quot;Mr.  A.  Ponsonby following Bromley  said  he was     proud to be  on  the same platform with a  Member of the     present Government&apos;.   At one  time he  thought  it would     require a general  election  to put Labour  in power but     they were  in power now.         &quot;All thosp places  where the socialist cliques could     not  arrange  meetings  for last week-end have held them     during  the week.   The  same  sort of speeches have been     made  at each, but  it  is clear from those  I  attended     that  the great mass of  the  workers are no^  in the least     disturbed by the * crisis&apos;.  For example, on August 13th,     I attended a much  advertised demonstration at Farsley;     this place is exactly  5  miles from Leeds and midway     between Leeds and Bradford.  For  the  whole  10 miles     one oan see  large  engineering,  iron and textile factories     and hundreds of  thousands  of workers with no possible     attraction except  the picture houses,  the public house     and street corners.   The houses are  only fit to eat and     sleep in and consequently the people  stand about in the     streets  in the evening.  At this meeting, half an hourafter/
       after the  advertised  time,  I  counted  60 people,       yet within a stone&apos;s  throw  were hundreds of workers       in  all directions.  I entered into conversation       with some  of these  and in nearly every case found       they had not the  remotest conception  of the facts       of  the Russo-Polish affair  and the crisis, hut all       were emphatic about calling up papers going in the       fire.            &quot;I have been in  constant touch and conversation       with the local socialists and Trade Union leaders,       and,  although they  have been  giving off wild stuff       on  the platforms, I find them all very nervous as to       the- outcome and especially,  as to the great apathetic       mass of the workers,  who are  still only concerned       with horse-racing,  cricket, allotments and other       amusements.   The  leaders fear that these men will       not respond to a  general strike call and that such     .  a call would eventuate in chaos and upheaval in       which  they would  be the joint  prey of the Government     .  and the mobs.            &quot;Great; uncertainty also  prevails amongst the  .     more advanced section of the  Independent labour       Party  and  the Communists as to the motives behind       Thomas, dynes and  their change, of tone: at the       Congress on the ISth.  They suspect some treacherous       move by these men hy which  a  sort of Keren sky or floske       regime may  be finally set up  if the present Government     .  cannot carry on against the organised labour       agitation.            &quot;Prom  the foregoing circumstances it is clear       that as far as this area is concerned an attempt at a       general strike would produce the utmost confusion.       The hurried local 1  Council  of  Action&apos;  formations are       simply a change of name for the Independent Labour      Party  and  other more advanced, groups,  who have been       agitating for the past 3 years pn the Russian question     .  and except  for:the purpose  of protecting unwilling       men from being forced  into the Army (as was done by       the  Shop Stewards during the war) I do not think they      will carry  much weight with;the great mass of rank      and file.           &quot;If the  time comes for a  real fight the saner      men, who have, been great constitutionalists when it      suited  themselves, will all be found to be ohiefly     .  engaged in  getting revenge upon the ^Bolshevik1     - section&quot;. !            .......     Confirmation  of this report has been received fromBull and  South Yorkshire and other parts of  the country.The,reports  show  that although the men would refuse response to calling up notices, they would: support the Governmentin countering Bolshevik action.                                        Midlands/
Midlands           &quot;Numerous working class citizens are asking why      these extremists are allowed by the authorities to make      suo-h violent speeches against the State and to advocate      revolution in such an open manner.  I have learnt from      good authority that the revolutionaries are doing their      utmost to &quot;bring about an industrial upheaval on this      Russian question.   They believe it to be a case of      &apos;now or never&apos;  and that if they cannot force the issue      within the next few months, before&apos;trade conditions go      against them, their cause will be delayed for many years.&quot;           &apos; Among the majority of work people in the. London  area,      a strong feeling against the Bolshevik regime appears      to be growing,  although there is determined opposition to      any intervention on behalf of Poland,   It is true that      the attendance  at  extremist meetings has been unusually      large but this  has been due.to the urgent whips sent out      from Headquarters.   The general attitude towards the      ;&apos;Council of Action&apos;  as such appears  to be one of      indifference.      South Wales           Very large audiences&apos;have  attended  meetings in  this      area and have passed extreme resolutions supporting  the      Council of Action&apos;.   In  Swansea alone the numbers reached      over 9,000.   A  speech which may be taken as typical      was made by Noah Ablett,  Miners&apos;  Agent for-Herthyr Tydfil,      on  August 15th.  He  said  that he was firmly convinced      that the &apos;Council  of Action&apos;  would eventually become the      real Government.   The present system of Government in  this      country  must  be  overthrown  and  a system of Bolshevism  and      monopoly by the workers substituted.   Prom the  reports      received it  appears  feeling in  South Wales is running  high.      Sootland           Great  activity  is  being  shown in  revolutionary      organisations, and the&quot;Russian  situation is  being closely   *   watched.   The rank and  file  socialist  members, are somewhat      in  the dark,as to what  action their  leaders  are preparing      to  take,  but  rumours  have been.circulated  that  the time      has  arrived,  or will  arrive  in  the near  future,  for  the    - people to  seize the  reins of  government.   Much  of what is      transpiring in revolutionary  circles is  kept very secret,     but  strong appeals for unity  among the workers are being     made by  the leaders  of various factions  so as to show  an     unbroken  front in view of possible contingencies.      Socialists and the general public are  strenuously opposed     to military action against Russia.     Efforts are being made to&apos; arrange monster  &quot;peace&quot;demonstrations throughout  the country on  Sunday next, and alarge meeting  is expected  in Trafalgar Square.                                                 THE/
m COAL mmm           As forecast in these reports for several weeks,      the miners&apos;  delegates have ordered a strike ballot.      The returns are to be made by August 30tb and a national      oonferenoe of miners1 delegates has been arranged for      September 2nd.  This will be preceded by a full meeting      of the Triple Alliance on August 31st at whioh a deoisi      regarding co-operation will doubtless be taken.  It  is j      possible at this juncture to say what form, if any,  co-      operation will take, but it seems likely that if there      is no result from the Conference with the Coal Owners      another &quot;Negotiating Committee&quot; will attempt to mediate      between the Government and the miners, on the lines      followed in the railway strike of last year.  Suoh a      committee would scarcely intervene before the result of      the ballot is known as it is considered that the threat      provided by a ballot majority for a strike would be  a      powerful weapon.           Among other 5rade liaionists there is still jittle      sympathy with the miners, but the announcement of a,.-      further increase on ooal on September 1st is unfortunate      and should, if possible, be attributed to the increase      in railwaymen13 wages.           The following are summaries of the reports regarding      the probable course of the ballot. from various ooalfielde.      South Wales           There is every indication of a large majority in      favour of a strike,      Lancashire and Cheshire ,           An &quot;overwhelming&quot; majority in favour of a strike      is expected.                                              Yorkshire/
      Yorkshire           A marked  difference  is  discernible  in  comparison      with  the mood  of  the last few weeks.  Local officials      are advising the  men to &quot;support  a  strike and their      recommendation is likely  to  be followed.   It is, however,      widely believed that the  Government will grant  the wages      increase and that the demand for the  14s. 2d. reduction      will  be dropped by the  minors.      M or thumb o r?.an d and Durham           There seems  little doubt that the voting-will be      largely in favour of a  strike.  Many  of  the miners think,      however, that  the Government will  give way  and  if it does      not,  September 18th is  thought to  be  the date on which      tho strike will begin.  ,      MidjftKfls           The attitude of the  men is  less  certain than in      other districts,  although Mr, Smiliie carries extraordinary      weight. There was less absenteeism during  the  last weekV      which fact indicates that the men  are trying to lay aside      money.      Scotland           A majority for a  strike is  considered  probable,THE MG POSERS                  . .:  .           There hes been little  apparent movement in the      engineering Unions during the week, but&apos;it is reported      that  Tom Mann  and his  lieutenants  are preparing to  extend      the ban on overtime and piece work.   In  Coventry under      the bonus  system  there  has  been  a  noticeable increase in      output during  the last  four months and the men  are  really      working hard,  even turning  out in  the reduced hours as      much  or more  than in pre-war times.           At the first annual  conference ,of  the  Amalgamated                                                  Engineering/
Engineering Union, held in York recently, lino committees,representing each railway system, were appointed to dealwith members in railway workshops, dockyards and other worksnot covered by the general engineering industries.  A Nation1Advisory Committee was also appointed to consult with theExecutive Council.     The &quot;Daily Herald&quot; reports that the Electrical TradesUnion ballot has resulted in a three to one majority in favoof amalgamation with the Amalgamated Engineering Union.THE &quot;NO RENT&quot; STRIKE     My correspondent sends the following report regardingpreparations for the &quot;No Rent^ strike on Monday next.;          &quot;On August 15th Glasgow tramway employees decided     to withdraw their labour on August 23rd as a protest     against the increase of rents, while the District Council     of the Glasgow Municipal Association recommends their     members to support the strike.  The Glasgow branch of the     Scottish Operative Tailors and Tailoresses has also     approved.          &quot;Resolutions in favour of the strike have been     adopted by a conference of Edinburgh and Leith Trades     Unions and Labour organisations, and by a demonstration     held by the Falkirk Housing Association.          &quot;Musselburgh and Fisher-row Co-operative Society     decided at a special meeting to close their shops and to     grant a full holiday with, pay to their employees, in order     that they may support the strike movement.  ,          &quot;The Glasgow Housing Association has been very active     during the week.  The leaders of the movement are very     hopeful of success in their fight, against the new Rent Act     and they say it will have to be repealed.  On the other     hand, many Trade Unionists with whom I have discussed     the situation are very sceptical of the success of a 24     hours&apos; strike.  There is no doubt that the increase in     rents is extremely unpopular with all grades of the workin     classes.&quot;     It is reported that the Glasgow District Council of theAmalgamated Engineering Union has decided to recommend members to join in the strike.  A similar recommendation has been adopteby the Clyde District Committee of the Boilermakers Sooiety.     Efforts to arouse interest in the subject have not been                                                 successful/
    successful in the Newcastle district.   Only 30 people  attended    a meeting on August 14th although invitations had been sent    to all local labour organisations.-  It was resolved to    concentrate on propaganda in the works and faotories and  on  an    open air campaign.         The National Union of Ex-Service  Men  has circularised all    branches on the subject and declares that  &quot;it is  only  part of    a general campaign.  More depends upon it  than we may  imagine.&quot;    Branches are urged to redouble their propaganda efforts Curing    the next two months.THE BOUSING QUESTION         The Government scheme for the regulation of  employment    in the building industry has not been  well received by many  of    the operatives concerned.  In spite of 1he guarantees  offered    the men have a firmly rooted antipathy to  dilution and to    payment by results and maintain that in any case  they  are sure    of employment for at least five years.         The Building Guild movement, on the other hand&quot;, seems to    be making some progress.  A report just issued from the    Manchester headquarters, states that Guild committees  have been    formed in 45 towns.  This report eulogises the support given    by the Co-operative Wholesale Society and  continues &quot;in this    alliance, amongst other possibilities, we  may discover the    way to break the rings and combines that now so remorselessly    hold to ransom  the whole building industry.&quot;THE COMOTIST PARTY Off GREAT BRITAIN&quot;         On August 8th the Provisional Executive Committee of thus    party held its first meeting at Chandos Hall.  It was  resolved    to apply to the Labour Party for affiliation, but an amendment    was carried in whioh it was stipulated that the application                                                     , should/
       should embody a  statement  of  the  objects, methods and       policy of the Communist Party,  The amendment  is further       proof  of the  dissension in the party and was doubtless the I       work of the anti-parliamentarians.  Nevertheless, the party!       is  likely to  grow.           My Coventry correspondent1s report of the local       branch of the Communist Party may be taken as  typical; he  I       states that there is much  dissension regarding affiliation I       with the Labour  Party and  that the meetings have &quot;broken                                                                 1       up  in  an afegry mood&quot;.           According to &quot;The Communist&quot; 145 branches of the Party!       have been formed in England, Scotland and Wales.  A member I       of  a local Committee estimates the membership at about      17,000..     ^ ,            mi&amp;  *  . Wm&amp;  SsOPPOSITION TO  PATRIOTIC MEETINGS           There has latterly been a marked increase in the&apos;      hostility shown  to speakers from patriotic platforms.      Following upon the.&apos; treatment, of People&apos;s League speakers,      to which  I referred in my  last report,  instances have      occurred  at Glasgow, Aberdeen, Coventry and Southampton,      In the last two towns the platforms were rushed and the      speakers, who Mionged to  the Reconstruction Society, rough]      handled.           At Leeds also a platform was stormed on August 10th      and -fee speakers hustled into the street.  .ANTI-GERMAN OUTBURST AT RAHSGATE           Ex-Service men  and visitors at Ramsgate have interferel      with the loading of  two Gyrman vessels which have been      chartered by a Danish Company to transport surplus coke sol      by the  Ramsgate Corporation.   German sailors have been      stoned  and repeated  attacks made on the  barbed  wire  barrict                                                     erected/
f . 4 *       erected by  the  harbour  authorities.   The  Corporation  states       that  the coke was  sold,  in the first  place,  to a London       firm  and that the  Controller of Mines has granted a licence       for export  to Denmark;  the leading is proceeding under       police  protection.            In the  early  morning  of August 17th  the hooligan       element in the  crowd wounded six constables and a baton       charge  became necessary.UNREST IN THE&quot;LOWER DECK           My Coventry correspondent, who has conversed with       sailors on leave,  states that they were much concerned at the       treatment of the recent deputation to the Admiralty, and       said that the lower deck was very indignant.  These men went       so far  as to say that they thought the loyalty of the Navy       could not be relied upon- if  the present attitude of the      Admiralty were maintained.   They further stated that Naval      ratings  are taking more interest in politics, are following      the industrial situation very closely and that during a      recent  cruise of a section of the Fleet to Norway,  Sweden      and Denmark much bolshevik literature was distributed among      seamen who went ashore,  especially at Stockholm.FEELING AMONG EE-SERVICE MSN           On August 18th some 300 discharged men marched from      Shepherd&apos;s Bush  to The Grove, Hammersmith, and from there-&apos;      sent  a small deputation  to the  deputy Mayor to demand redress      of their grievances regarding unemployment pay.   The      deputation was promised  that  the  arrears of. pay should, be      paid  the following  day and this  reply was considered      satisfactory.  A second  meeting was held on  August  13th under      the auspices  of  the West London branch of the  International                                                     Union/
                                                            i 4 * \      Union of Ex-Service Men. at which strong speeches were      made by extremists named Jones, Turner, Banks and Bruce.   A      The first named referred lo the success pf the deputation      to the Mayor and stated that they would demonstrate  whenever      they failed to get satisfaction by ordinary methods.           Similar scenes occurred at Leicester,  owing to the      delay in linking up the extension of unemployment pay.      My correspondent states that the incident caused much      irritation and that he was much surprised by the anti-      Government attitude of the men,Mr, MALONE,  U.P.           On August 15th Mr, Malone addressed some 700 of his      supporters at the Town Hall, Leyton, on &quot;Why I became a      Communist&quot;.  His defence was feeble  when questioned as  to      his reasons for retaining his seat after being elected as      a Liberal.  He replied that as the Communist Party had      decided to make use of Parliamentary machinery, he intended      to retain his seat.  The meeting, which was packed by      extremists, concluded with the singing of the &quot;Red Hag&quot;  and      Mr. Malone then addressed an overflow meeting outside the      hall.   The impressions of his audience may be summed up  in      the remark of one of them - &quot;Well, he&apos;s a poor speaker,  but      he must have some brains or they wouldnft have made  him  a      Colonel&quot;. GEORGE NICHOLSON           Nicholson has resigned his position as &quot;Chief of the      Labour&quot; Section of the League of Nations Union&quot; on /the ground      that Lord Robert Cecil refused to allow him to publish a      manifesto against intervention in Poland.  A confidential      report states that he is always suggesting that the  workers      should carry on with revolvers and has hinted at the                                              assassination/
 &apos;   ftIf440     assassination of Ministers as well as General  Denikin     and Monsieur Millerand.   Doubts  are expressed  about  his     sanity and suggestions have been heard that  he must  be     an &quot;agent provocateur&quot;.   Re has  now teclared himself ready     to speak for any Branch  of the &quot;Daily Herald&quot;  League.IRELAND          In all about  10 offences of an indictable nature     were reported during the week.   176 of these were  directly     attributable to  Sinn Fein, 8 were of an agrarian nature     and 26 were serious crimes largely due to  the  lawless state     of the country.   The number of outrages reported to  the     police shows a decrease  but this cannot be taken as  showing     any real improvement in  the state of affairs,  as  many     cases are not reported to the police at all, or are  delayed    &quot;owing to the restricted  postal facilities.   Amongst  the     crimes committed by Sinn Fein were one murder  and  the burning     of 15 vacated Royal Irish Constabulary barracks, three court-     houses and four  coastguard stations.  There  were 17  raids for     arms by masked and armed men.          There is, however,  a growing, disinclination to  take     part in outrages which are becoming increasingly costly to-     Sinn Fein in casualties.          There were  24 oa\ses of robbery of mails and other     aots of highway  robbery.   Eight  persons were kidnapped for     trial at,  or in  obedience to,  the orders of  Sinn Fein Courts.     The number of such disappearances is now over  100.          Relations between the civilian population and the     military in Munster are  becoming more and  more strained and     matters are particularly bad in  both Ridings of Cork.          The Tail way position remains  unchanged  though there     are signs  that the  employees are becoming  tired  of being                                                       forced/
forced out of work by Sinn Fein,  The Labour. Congresspassed off quietly in Cork and there is no noticeableindustrial.....unrest though the tendency to force up wagescontinues.     Party feeling is still very bitter in the north and isbeing inflamed by paragraphs in tho &quot;Freeman^ Journal&quot; andthe &quot;Irish Independent&quot; which are doing much harm.     The Lord Ivlayor of Cork has been arrested and broughtto England.

</content>
</cab>
