<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/28 images: 252-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.May 1945.SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (45) 278.1st May, 1945.XWAR CABINET.DEFECTS IN THE MAY ELECTORAL REGISTER.Joint Memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State forScotland.1. We have received representations from various quarters with regard todefects and difficulties which have arisen in connection with the Register of electors which is to be published on the 7th May, and it is apparent that, if aGeneral Election is held on this Register, considerable numbers of persons will be unable to vote, some because their names have been omitted from the Register, andthe majority because, having removed from the address at which they were registered on the 31st January (the qualifying date for the Civilian Register),they are unable to attend at the polling place in the constituency for which theyare registered.2.   The cases affected may be grouped as follows :  (1) Omissions and Inaccuracies. -A certain number of names have been omitted from the Register through the failure of the machine to passinformation in time from National Registration records to- the electoral registration officers, for example in the case of persons who attained theirmajority before the 31st January. A few omissions have been corrected underthe ordinary claims procedure, but the public generally has not taken the trouble to inspect, in the short time available, the published lists to see if theyhad been registered as electors. These omissions have come to notice chieflyfrom special steps which have been taken by National Registration Officers to check National Registration records, and as they are brought to light,Electoral Registration Officers have been inserting the names, or in some casesadding supplementary lists where time permitted. But all the omissionscannot be made good, and they will continue to come to light for some time after the publication of the register on the 7th May, because the checking by national Registration Officers has not been completed. In any event, nocorrections can as the law stands be made after the 7th May. It is not possibleto give any estimate of the number of omissions, but it is believed that theywill not be considerable and may not exceed 1 per cent, of the Electorate.In a few cases also in rural areas persons have been registered for the wrongpolling district because the address on the identity card referred to the postaltown and not the village.(2) Removals Since Qualifying Day (%lst January).(a) Evacuees who have returned home will be registered for theirevacuation address. They would naturally prefer to vote in their home constituency, but without the compilation of a new registerit would be impossible to arrange for the transfer of theirregistration to their home locality. They are not eligible forpostal voting facilities as the law stands, and will be virtuallydisfranchised.(&amp;) Various classes of workers have moved since the 31st January,either under direction of the Ministry of Labour or in response to a request to do so, or have returned home on the completion oftheir work. Particular attention has been called to the positionof building operatives who, on varying dates since last autumn,[29818]
have been brought to London from the provinces for bomb damagerepairs. Their number is estimated at between 40,000 and50,000. The majority live in hostels and, as they are fed in thehostels, have not been obliged to report a change of address.Some may be registered for their home constituencies for whichthey would probably prefer to vote, but they will not be able todo so if they have not returned home when the Election takes place. It is doubtful, as the law stands, whether they areeligible to vote by post, and anyhow they have not applied to doso within the prescribed time. Some may be registered for a london address, not necessarily in the place where they are nowliving, since workers have been transferred from one area toanother, and others may be registered for some intermediateaddress outside London, where they were previously working.(3) Members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces. Tt is estimated by the service departments that 90 per cent, of Service men will have been included inthe Service Register, their declarations having been received by the15th March, the last date for such receipt, but declarations from theremaining 10 per cent, will now be out of time for inclusion in the MayRegister. In particular, declarations may be expected from emergencycommissioned officers in the Indian Army and persons similarly situated in the Colonial Forces, -who were made eligible for registration by Section 3of the Representation of the People Act, 1945, and have had only a short time in which to make and send home their declarations. There has alsobeen delay in notifying Electoral Registration Officers of the attainment of majority by persons who have made service declarations.(4) Merchant Seamen Ex-Prisoners of War who have recently beenliberated from camps in Germany; Section 20 of the Representation of thePeople Act, 1945, enables servicemen who are ex-prisoners of war to be registered on return to this country, but does not apply to Merchant Seamen.(5) Business Voters who failed to apply before- the 1st March tobe included in the Business Premises Register. Although they were alkrweda month (February) in which to apply, and there was considerable publicity,both locally and nationally, it appears that many did not do so.3. As regards these various classes, there has been informal consultationwith representative registration officers in England and Scotland to ascertain whether anything can be done to secure registration after the 7th May of those not registered, and to give facilities for postal voting in respect of those who have moved. Registration Officers are anxious to make an election in the May Registeras comprehensive as possible, but it is their unanimous opinion that they couldnot undertake the burden which would be imposed on them by an attempt to coverall the classes in question. Their resources have been strained to the limit in producing the May Register, and they are now faced with the task of dealingwith applications for postal voting by Service voters, and in a few weeks theywill be engaged on preparatory work for the October Register, for which the qualifying date is the 30th June. In their view any attempt to rectify allthe hard cases which have arisen on the May Register will break the machinewhich has to deal with postal voting for the Forces, and wreck the foundationwork for the October register.   They said, however, that they could deal with :(a) a supplementary Service Register covering declarations by members ofthe Indian Army and possibly other servicemen and Merchant Seamenex-prisoners of war, and(b) a scheme of absent voting for persons who have moved by reason of warcircumstances from the constituency in which they are registered,provided that some date, preferably a date early in June, is fixed by which applications to be entered on the Absent Voters&apos; List areto be received.4. As the law stands at present, a person can claim inclusion in the AbsentVoters&apos; List only if the Registration Officer is satisfied that &quot; by reason of thenature of his occupation, service or employment &apos;&apos; he may be unable to vote in person. To extend the range of the Absent Voters&apos; List to cover evacuees andothers who have moved owing to war circumstances would introduce a newprinciple and would considerably extend the volume of absent voting.   It would,
of course, not give the evacuee a postal vote in respect of his home address, butI can see no other solution to prevent the virtual disfranchisement of personswho have moved.5. From the foregoing analysis it will be observed that at an election heldon the May Register many persons will be unable to vote either because their names will not be on the Register or because they will be absent from the constituencies in which they are registered. Many of the imperfections will disappear when the October Register is published, although it will still not bepossible, without legislation, to deal with persons who move after the 30th Juno the qualifying date for that Register.6. If a general election is unlikely before the October Register comes intoforce, any necessary improvements could be incorporated in the proposed electoral reform Bill. If on the other hand we must try to improve the May Registeron the basis that a general election may be held on it, then it is necessary toprepare a Bill to give effect to our proposals, made after discussion with the registration Officers, and get it passed into law by the 1st June.H. M.T J.Whitehall, S.W.1,1st May, 1945.




</content>
</cab>
