<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/192/28 images: 210-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
?ms document is the property of her britannic majesty^ government cp(76) 103 copy no    8112 November 1976CABINETHEALTH AND SAFETY AT WORK ETC ACT:  SAFETYREPRESENTATIVES AND SAFETY COMMITTEESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for employment. On 23 September the Cabinet decided (CM(76) 24th Conclusions) to defer consideration of my proposal to make regulations and approve a code of practice on safety representatives and safety committees until officials had made a further attempt to reach agreement on the costs of implementation.This work has now been concluded and the Appendix sets out the agreed viewsof the officials of the Departments concerned.2.        It will be seen that as a result of meetings between representativesof the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and local authority associations thelatter agreed to reduce their earlier estimates substantially (from 88 million to  44 million).    Officials believe however that the latterestimate is still too high and that a more realistic figure of resource costs would be  29 million, of which 20 per cent could be absorbed.    The costin cash terms in a full year would therefore be  23 million for England andWales with an additional  2.5 million for Scotland.    They stress however that there is no prospect that the local authorities will accept this lower figure or indeed reduce their latest estimate.   As regards the rest of thepublic sector officials take the view that the estimate for costs in the CivilService and fringe bodies should remain at  5 million since they werecalculated in the first place on more realistic assumptions than thoseadopted by local authorities.    On the other hand costs to the national health Service have now been put substantially higher, at about  6 million.However in so far as I have already expressed the hope that the additionalcosts in the public sector other than for local authorities can be absorbed,I set the total additional bill in a full year at approximately  25.5 million.3.        My colleagues know well from previous discussions how strongly take the view that I should make these regulations without further delay andI still recommend that I should do so and that  25.5 million should be earmarked in the rate support grant for local authority expenditure in1977-78 for this purpose.    If however this is not agreed we must consider1
what alternatives are open to us.    It will certainly not be sufficient merely to announce that I have decided not to make the regulations without giving any indication as to when they will be made.    The proposals have been published by the Commission and are already being widely used in manyindustrial organisations as a basis for consultation.    Indeed many of themore progressive employers are already operating, in agreement with theunions, procedures which are similar to those recommended by theCommission.   A decision not to make the regulations will be regarded by employers - and indeed by the TUC - as an indication that the Governmentis not willing to put pressure on employers in the public sector to give theirworkers facilities which have already been developed extensively by employers in the private sector.4.        There would not be the same criticism if the regulations were laidwith a later operating date.    The Commission have proposed a lead-in period of four months between the making of the regulations and their operation but the provision of a longer period could be presented as allowingmore time for necessary discussions between employers and unions about theoperation of the regulations in their particular circumstances and for theresolution of any differences.    Clearly this argument would be stretchedbeyond credibility if we chose too late a date.    If it were decided that noresources could be provided in 1977-78 we might adopt 1 April 1978 as the operative date, but I am convinced that any later date would not be acceptable.5,        There are two other alternatives -a. To exclude local authorities (including education) and theNational Health Service from the regulations.I cannot recommend thiB and I know that the Health and SafetyCommission and the TUC would be strongly opposed to it.   Againit would be thought that a large part of the public sector has been excluded, not for sound reasons of policy, but solely on grounds of cost.    The argument that these are generally low risk sectors ofemployment ignores the fact that they contain some high risk areas,and any attempt to devise a phased introduction by category of riskwould pose great practical problems.    Confusion would also be caused because the trade union structure would run right acrossboth the included and excluded sectors.b. To make regulations to operate from as early as possible in1977 and to allocate  10 million to local authorities through rate support grant.This is the alternative which I proposed in my earlier paper (CP(76) 73).Its merit is that it would not, in my view, be unreasonable since itcould be argued that the cost to local authorities in 1977-78 would be2
most unlikely to amount to their estimates for a full year.    In thatperiod too we would monitor developments and be able to reviewfuture requirements much more accurately in the light of theexperience we at present lack,recommendation,        I must stress again that it is essential to make some progress withthese regulations.    If my colleagues are not willing now to set aside thefall sum of  25,5 million, for local authority expenditure in 1977-78 and subsequent years, 1 ask them to agree -a. either to set aside  10 million in 1977-78 and to review thesituation during that year, orb. if this is not acceptable, to agree to my laying the regulationsnow with a delayed operating date of not later than 1 April 1978,A BDepartment of Employment12 November 19763
(confidential)AppendixDRAPT REGULATIONS ON SAFETY REPRESENTATIVES AND COIgUTTEESWE VISED ESTIMATES OF COSTSSUGARYMinisters were not satisfied at the considerable divergencebetween the initial estimates of public sector costs of implementing the proposed regulations prepared by the Health and Safety Executive(the ), Local Authorities Associations and departments.    A Cabinet&quot;meeting of 23 September called on a working group of officials toProduce fresh estimates on an agreed basis.    The working groupconsisted of officials from DE, DOE, DES, Treasury, DHSS, CSD and DTpand the the.Local Authorities (including Educational Establishments)2     Officials have met representatives of the LAAs and the localgovernment trades unions.    The LAAs have considered guidance notesprepared by the TUC for their member unions, and on the strength ofthat guidance have revised their estimate to  40 million.    DOE/DEShave also prepared a revised estimate of costs of  29 million(resource costs).3     While the gap between the two sets of estimates is now considerably&quot;&quot;arrower than it was before, there is still a difference of some it million, due mainly to different views of the amount of time that*afety representatives would spend on their functions.    Officials do*ot ,ee any prospect of bringing the two estimates any closer together;they represent, perhaps &quot;pessimistic&quot; and &quot;optimistic&quot; views of how-individual trades union representatives will interpret the regulations.Departmental officials would accept the DOE/DES estimate as that more likely to be realistic.    The the officials, however, still believe the revised figures exaggerate the likely costs.^ Similar details have not yet been provided by local authoritiesin Scotland. Their overall costs are expected to be roughly lOJf ofthose for England and Vales, and on that basis  3 million (resourcecosts) should be added to the DOE/DES figures.5     The figures quoted above ore in terms of resource costs.    The^AAs ore of the view that none of their  40 million could be absorbed,*hile officials consider that, very roughly, local authorities could*hsorb at least 20* of resource costs, giving a cash cost, that ise*tra expenditure, of  23 million (some  251 million includingScotland) based on the DOE/DES estimate of resource costs.    This ise*plained in more detail at Annex A.-1-( confidential )
C confidenttaT)Other Public services     (a)       Civil Service.    Further consideration of the assessed costs in the light of the TUC guidance notes has not shown thatany significant reduction can be made in the earlierfigures put forward by CSD.(b)        National Health Service.    The initial estimate of some&amp;2i million has been substantially increased to roughly 6 million as a result of further discussions between officials of DHSS and the NHS.Total Coats7     The table below shows the total costs to local authorities andother public services now considered to be realistic in the light ofthe further discussions between officials. mLocal Authorities(education and non-education sectors) 25 *public Service(a) Civil Service(b) Fringe Bodies national Health Service 6*The equivalent resource costs are  32 million8     It has not been feasible to make a meaningful alternative assess-went based on comparable costs to industry.    The only readily available figures were based on the criteria used by the Health and safety Executive in providing estimates for the public sector.    Thesecriteria have proved unacceptable to local authorities.U)CAL AUTHORITY COSTS  (England and Wales)INTRODUCTION9     The Local Authority Associations were first asked .in August J-p^&quot;^ke an estimate of the costs to local authorities of implementing the proposed regulations.    At that time estimates of local authority    ycosts were also prepared by the Health and Safety Executive (USE).It became apparent that there was a fundamental difference of view between the local authority associations and the TUC (as reflected*n the the estimate) as to how the trades unions would act on theregulations.    Officials therefore brought together representativesQf local government trades unions and the local authority associations(LAAs),  after which the IAAs revised their costs.    These revisedcosts seemed to officials to be still too high, so DOE/DES producedtheir own revised estimates.    The outcome of the TUC/LAA discussions*D.d the bases for the various cost estimates are discussed below.-2-C CONFIDENTIAL j
( confidential)The cost estimates described can be summarised thus:  millionJuly/August     October/November1976 1976Health and Safety Executive 2.8Local Authority Associations(excluding Scotland) 80 40DOE/DES 2k 29The build-up of these estimates is set out in table 3 of Annex A.COMPONENTS OF COST ESTIMATES10   The components of any estimate of local authority costs are:(1)       The number of local authority workplaces.(2)        The number of safety representatives that the unions would want to nominate at each workplace.(3)        The amount of time that safety representatives wouldspend on their functions.(4)       The amount of time spent by representatives in training.(5)        The numbers of safety committees.(6)        The extent to which management would be involved.The above suggests that to a very large extent the factors governing the cost to employers of implementing the regulations depend on thepractice of the trades unions and of individual trades union members,for example:(l)        Many workplaces have employees in three, four- or L.or&amp;:&quot;as&amp;omttIf each recognised union were to exercise to the full its   -right under the legislation these workplaces would havethree, four or more safety representatives.(2)       Similarly,  the amount of time safety representatives spendin performing their functions is a matter largely fortheir own judgement as guided by local and national union officials.(3)        Safety representatives will be trained by trades unions.The amount of time off required for training will thus be determined by the trades unions.(4)        The Act places a duty on employers to form a safetyCommittee at the request of at least two safety represen-tatives.    It is envisaged that a safety committee mightcover more than one workplace,  but the composition ofthe committee and the number of workplaces covered wouldbe settled in consultation between the management andtrade union representatives.-3-c confidential)
( confidential)TUC GUIDANCE11    The TUC Local Government Committee recognises the importance ofthe attitude of local trades union members,    They have thereforedrawn up &quot;guidance notes&quot; for local government unions on the appoint-&quot;&quot;ent of safety representatives.    This guidance suggests that inWorkplaces where there are members of several different unions theredo not need to be safety representatives for each union.    A copy ofthese notes,  which have now the approval of the TUC but have not yetbeen released,  is at Annex B.l2    Representatives of the TUC Local Government Committee discussed this guidance with the LAAs who have said they found it helpful.    the associations have revised their estimate of local authority costson the assumption that the guidance notes would be circulated to member unions and that the member unions would abide by that guidanceat local level.    Although they welcome the tuc&apos;s assurance that theywill use their best endeavours to secure this,  local authority associations have made a clear reservation that they fear the TUCfcay not be able to do so, particularly if their local members decide*o take a strong line within the provisions of the regulations.    Inthe event they have revised their estimate downwards mainly bydeducing their estimate of management costs,  giving a new figure of 40.8 million.DOE/DES REVISION OF THE the ESTIMATE13    There is still a wide divergence between the earlier HSEestimate and that of the LAAs,  although the gap has been narrowedconsiderably.    DOE/DES have looked at the assumptions made in theHSE&apos;S July estimate ( 2.8 million) and has revised them to take account of:-(l)        The LAAs estimate of the number of workplaces(2)        the more realistic estimate of the numbers of safetyrepresentatives at each workplace now made by the LAAs,ie 2 representatives per workplace,  except in theeducation sector where it is        at schools and 5 atFurther Education establishments.(3)        the LAAs view that safety representatives will spend more time on their functions than the had originally assumed.DOE does not think that representatives will spend 10days per year (the LAAs present view) but considers thatin non-education workplaces 5 days is realistic.2 days for routine  (quarterly)  inspections1 day for training2 dnys for other functionsDES considers that for education establishments 8 days-Jill be required for schools.   (Further details areshoi/n in paragraph &apos;* of Annex A).-4-( conhdential)
ik)      management costs at half representatives costs,  asassumed by LAAs.    DOE/DES would not take issue with the LAAs on the values of the components of theestimate apart froin (3) above:  as against the LAAestimate of  40 million DOEYDSS estimate  29 oilLioruOFFICIALS ASSESSMENT OP THS REVISED ESTIMATESIk    Officials have considered:a. -ihich of the two figures is the more likely estimateof resource costsb. how much of the resource costs are likely to be absorbed,RESOURCE COSTS15    The LAAs claim that there have been clear indications fromunion officials at the local level that the unions ore likely to wish to use to the full the powers conferred by tho regulations.On the other hand the attitude of the TUC Local Governpeut Committeehas suggested that tho TUC and member unions will adopt a reasonableepprofich to the implementation of the regulations and will use thorn,as intended,  as instruments to achieve safer working conditions, not as a stick to beat employers.    They suggest thet it is evou possibleth.,t at workplace lovel tlwro i-d.ll be a certain amount of apotny ^safety representatives laay bo umrilling to come forward sad even vhenUorainated may not be as conscientious as the TUC would wish.    Veryoften the functions of the safety representative would be taken on by existing ctaployeoa*  representatives.    On balance it aeeos to officials that the LAAs fears are exaggerated and that the revisedOGE/DES figures are likely to be a realistic estimate of the resourcecosts.CASH COSTS16    The extent to which the resource costs can bo absorbed is amatter of judgement.    The local authority view is that in most cases where a safety representative takes time off work to performnis safety functions then either his work will not get done (whichwill result in a fall in the standard of service provided) or onextra euployeeT  perhaps temporary,  will have to be taken on to do it.1^ either case there   ;ill be a real cost - in tho former this willhe because the fall in standard of service represents an expenditureCut which could,  if taken anyway,  result in real savings.l?   The local authority associations soy, not surprisingly,  that since they have made all oossiblc savings to meet the Government sreduced expenditure targets both for this year and next taey are in*o position to absorb costs.    Out of the   :0 million of resourcecosts they estimate that none can be absorbed in the education sectorQnd that very little can be absorbed in the non-education sector,so virtually the whole  iO million would appeer as real extra expend!&apos;turQ unless the standards of service are cut.( cc^fdentiaT)
( confidential?)18    The local authority associations point out that the extra costs&quot;ill represent a:; additional workload which will oea.i that ixrepeople will be employed.19    The the and the TUC officials feel that the local authoritiesare overstating the difficulties and that by its very nature the**ork of safety representatives will become subsumed,  to a largeextent,  within their day to day activities ::uich as the union workof existing employeos&apos;  representatives is subsumed,20    The difficulty is that ar.y open estimate of absorption in the face of LAA insistence that no further costs can possibly be absorbed&quot;ould bring Ministers into open conflict with the associations.    Uiththat reservation officials suggest that perhaps 20% of resource costcould be absorbed,  bat even this degree of absorption could lead toa reduction in standards.    Applied to tho revised resource costestimate that would give cash costs - e;:tra expenditure - of about^23 uillion.POSSIBLE CONSEQUENTIAL COSTS21    V/hile this report h;.s concentrated on the cost of the uachineryrequired to implement the regulations,  officials would lilce to bringMinisters&apos;  attention the possibility or unidentifiable,  butPotentially substantial,  consequential costs which may arise from therecouue/idctioiis of safety representatives and safety cotiuuittees.PniCSENTATION:  FINANCING THE EXTRA EXPENDITURE22    Ministers called upon officials to try to produce fresh estimateson an agreed basis.    Although officials are broadly agreed on anestinate of some  29 million resource costs leading to net extra expenditure of  23 million in a full year,  there i3 no prospect ofthe local authority associations accepting it.    They will insist thatmillion represents their last word and that this figure alreadytakes into account whatever small costs could be absorbed,23    Ministers are committed to refraining from placing extrafinancial burdens on local authorities without indicating how theGxtra expenditure should be financed.    The local authority associa-tions are insisting in this case that if the regulations arc made the.: iQ million should be added to the total of relevant expenditure inQ full year.    But Ministers are also committed to levels of localauthority expenditure consistent with Cmnd 6393.    This implies thatthe extra expenditure could only be financed by fjo-influencing cuts in services or fro;n the contingency reserve.-6-( confidential )
( confidential )ANNEX a cost ESTIMATES* This annex describes and compares the various estimates of the costs to local authorities of implementing the proposed regulations for safety representatives and safety committees.2 The estimates are as follows, for costs in a full year at 1976prices: mJuly/August  1976: Health and Safety Executive  (the)Local Authority Associationa(LAAs)DDE/DESOctober/November 1976:    DOE/DESLAAs3       The strict cost calculation is:2.881.224.229.240.8Representative^ costsManagement costsTotal Costa number of workplacesx number of representativesper workplacex days per year spent by each representativex cost of each representativeper day- number of workplacesx number of management daysper year per workplacex management cost per day= representative^ costs *management costs^t will be seen that these factors all involve assumptions:    the values assumed for each estimate are set out below.    Because theJjifferent estimates have been built up in different ways it isdifficult to compare them directly;    so in the summary tables the values have been adjusted so the figures are comparable.j*       The workload of safety representatives is a critical assumption.0ES figures of days per year are based on an analysis of hours perJear as below,  and the data of five hours per day for school**aching staff and six hours per day for FE staff.    Based on the*ct,  the draft regulations,  the draft Code of Practice and Guidance&quot;otes,  the work load of a safety representative at an average 300-Pupil (30 staff) school might be as follows:(i)    Formal consultation with employer (LEA) aboutarrangements for co-operation and promotion of measures ensuring employees  health and safety.-7-C cc)nfidenttal)
( confidential)(iii)(iv)(v)(vi)and checking of the effectiveness of such measures (as required by Section 2(6) ofthe Act).Investigation of potential hazards, dangerousoccurrences and causes of accidents;    formalrepresentations to the employer about suchmatters.Representation about individual complaintsinvolving health, safety or welfare;    employer to be informed of any unsafe or unhealthyconditions generally; records to be kept ofsuch complaints and resulting action.Premises inspection (entitlement at least one every three months);    assume oneinspection per term involving preliminary discussion with employer/ees  (one hour),inspection (l  hours), formal report,record of inspection and any follow-upaction (-J hour).Familiarisation with information providedby employer and the about the undertaking(should include technical details about thebuilding and proposed modifications, plant,machinery, equipment and materials used);acquiring a working knowledge of all safetymatters and regulations applicable to the establishments  (covering science,  craft,domestic studies, PE, carotaking etc).2 hours/year5 hours/year9 hours/year9 hours/year10 hours/yearTraining time, assuming a course lastingfive days once every five years.5 hours/yearTOTAL      kO hours/yearQr HFE establishments,  the greater variety of work,  larger physical*ize of the premises  (including multi-site establishments) and greater number of employees night be assumed likely to increase bya*lf the amount of work a safety representative would do.-8-C confidential)
C confidential )TABLE non-EDUCATIONAL WORKPLACES  : COST ESTIMATES(July/August  1976)		the	DOE/CSD	LAAft.	Number of workplaces	40,500	16,000	40,500b.	Reps per worltplsce	1	4	2c.	Number of reps  (a x b)	40,50O	64,000	81,000a.	Days/year per rep	2	4.4	10e.	Rep*s cost per day	 16	 20	 16	Total rep&apos;s cost  (c x d x e)	 1.3m	 5.6m	 13ms.	Management:    Days/year	nil	nil	20h.	Management cost per day			 32i.	Total management cost  (a x g x h)	0	0	 26ci	Total cost  (f * i)	 1.3m	 5.6m	 39mENGLAND AND WALES-9-C confidential)
( CQNFJDEiMTIAL )EDUCATION WORKPLACES: COST ESTIMATES(July/August 1976)TABLE 2		the	DES	LAASCHOOLS				a.	No of workplaces	30,boo	30,400	30,400b.	Reps per workplace	1	3	3c.	No of reps (a x b)	30,^00	91,200	91,200d.	Days/year per rep	2	8	8e.	Rep&apos;s cost per day	 17	 21.25	 21.25f.	Total rep*s cost (c x d x e)	 1.0m	 15.5m	 15.5mg.	Management j days/year	nil	nil	24h.	Management:  cost per day	-	-	 27.6i.	Total management cost (a x g x h)	nil	nil	 20.lmj-	Cost of safety committees at larger schools	-	 l.7ra	 3.4mK	Total Schools&apos;  cost (r * i * j)	 1.0m	 17.2m	 39.0mFURTHER EDUCATION				1.	No of workplaces	7^5	745	745n.	Reps per workplace	4.2	5	5n.	No of reps  (1 x m)	3,129	3,725	3,725P.	Days/year per rep	5	10	10q.	Rep&apos;s cost per day	 29.5	 37	 37r.	Total rep&apos;s cost (n x p x q)	 0.5m	 l.4m	 1.4ma.	Management:  days/year	nil	nil	50t.	Management: cost per day	-	-	 48u.	Total management cost (1 x s x t)	nil	nil	 1.8mv.	Total Further Education cost (r * u)	 0.5m	 1.4m	 3-2m	Total All Education Ck * v)	 1.5m	 18.6m	 42.2mENGLAND AND VALES( CONFiDENTIAL )
( confidential )TABLE 3REVISED COST ESTIMATES (OCTOBER 19?6)Compared with original the and LAA figuresNON-EDUCATION AND EDUCATION COMBINED		the July 1976	LAA August 1976	LAA Revised October 1976	- DOE/DES Revised November 1976a.	Number of workplaces	71,645	71,645	85,000	85,000b.	Reps per workplace	1.03	2.45	2	1.84c.	Number of reps (a x b)	73,794	175,925	170,000	157,035 -d.	Days/year per rep	2.1	9-0	10	6,0e.	Reps1 cost per day	 17.8	 18.9	 16.0	 18.9f.	Total reps1 cost (c x d x o)	 2.8m	 29.9m	 27.2m	 19.47(2)s.	Total management cost	nil	 47-9m	 13.6m	 9.74mh.	Total cost  (f + g)	 2.8m	 8l.2m11&apos;	1   40.8m	 29-21mENGLAND AND WALESIncludes  3.4m for safety committees in large schoolsIncludes  1.7m for safety committees in large schools(confidential)
( confidential)DOE/DES REVISED COST ESTIMATESSHOWING NON-EDUCATION AMD EDUCATION SEPARATELY		Non-Education (DOE)	Education (DES) See Table 5 \	Total DOE/DESa.	Number of workplaces	53,855	31,145	85,000b.	Reps per workplace	2	1.58	1.84c.	Number of reps (a x b)	107,710	49,325	157,035d.	Days/year per rep	5	8.15	6.0e.	Reps&apos; cost per day	 16	 22.76	 18.9f.	Total reps&apos; cost (c x d x e)	 8.62m	 I0.85m*	 l9-47m*S.	Total management cost	 4.3lm	 5.43m	 9-74mh.	Total cost  (f * g)	 12.93m	 16.28m	 29.21mENGLAND AND WALES* 1.7 million added for safety committees at larger schools12-( confidential )
(confidential )TABLE 5DES REVISED COST ESTIMATESSHOWING SCHOOL AND FURTHER EDUCATION SEPARATELY	Schools	Further Education	Totala. Number of workplaces b. Reps per workplace c. Number of reps  (a x b) d. Days/year per rep e. Reps&apos; cost per day f. Total reps&apos;  cost (c x d x e) g. Total management cost b.    Total cost (f + g)	30,400 1.5 45,600 8  21.25  9-45m*  4.73m  14,18m	7*5 5 3,725 10  37  l.4m  0.7m  2. 1m	31,145 1.58 49,325 8.15  22.76  10.85m*  5.43m  l6.28mENGLAND AND WALES* l.7 million added for safety committees at larger schools(confidential)

</content>
</cab>
