<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/54 images: 624-635</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1939.SECRET.Copy No.  4W.M. (39)120th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 120 (39).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, December 20, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The    Right    Hon.    Winston    S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chiefof Naval Staff (Items 1-11).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-11).General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-11).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. G. N. Flemming.f20527]
WAR CABINET 120 (39).Contents.minute no. Subject.1      Visit of the Prime Minister to France     ...2      The Air situation      The Naval Situation ...4      GermanySuggested reprisals against attacks on British fishing vessels5      The Military SituationPossible German intentions.6      Weekly Reports7      Finland ...Invasion by U.S.S.B.8      Finland ...Supply of aircraft.9      Supreme War Council: 4th MeetingSouth-East Europe.Aircraft supplies from the United States of America.Northern Europe: Finland, Sweden and Norway.Agreement with France not to make a separate peace.Peace aims.Fecamp broadcasting station.Acceleration of despatch of British military forces to France10      Italy      .........       ............Attitude towards British contraband control.11      Eire      .....................Intelligence Organisation.12      War Aims
Visit of the 1.   The Prime Minister gave the War Cabinet a brief descrip-Prime Minister tion of his recent visit to France. While conditions on the Britishto France. sector did not, of course, permit of the construction of anything in the nature of the Maginot Line, the defences already constructedhad appeared to him extremely formidable. A great deal of work had been carried out, but a lot still remained to be done. One ofthe main impressions made on his mind by his visit to tJhe Britishsector of the Front had been the vital part played by the anti-tankgun in the modern defensive system. In this connection, he hadgathered from more than one direction, that the French 25-mm.anti-tank gun, on account of its simpler construction, was preferred to our 2-pounder anti-tank weapon.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff observed that theBritish 2-pounder weapon had much greater penetrating power thanthe French anti-tank gun.. The Secretary of Staxte for War said that the War Office were anxious to obtain as many French anti-tank guns as possible to supplement our own 2-pounders.Continuing, the Prime Minister emphasised the difficulty of keeping the men at the Front occupied in the long hours of Winterdarkness. He had been impressed by the efforts made to providerecreation and entertainment. Conditions at the Front were undoubtedly severe, but he had met with the greatest cheerfulnesseverywhere and had received a most heartening impression of the morale of our troops.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.The air situation.(previous reference erence:W.M. (39) 119thConclusions,Minute 3.)(previous reference:W.M. (39) 119thConclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Secretary of State for Air said that patrols over theGerman seaplane bases had been carried out on the previous nightbetween dusk and 2300 hours. Nothing of importance had been seen and no bombs had been dropped. The Germans, however, had put out a tremendous story of aerial activity. The Air ministry had subsequently published a denial.The Lord Privy Seal asked whether, in spite of patrols, theGerman mine-laying aircraft were still coming over.The Chief of the Air Staff said that our patrolling aircraftdropped bombs whenever a light was shown. They would, however,be unlikely to detect aircraft which took off in darkness.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the Commander-in-Chief, The Nore, had reported that hostile aircraft were continuing to operate in the Thames Estuary. He (the First Lord) thought,however, that the Royal Air Force operations were definitelyhampering the German mine-laying activities, and the admiralty were very grateful for what was being done.Continuing, the Secretary of State for Air said that a Londontype flying-boat of the Coastal Command had had an engagement-on the previous day with a Heinkel III bomber in the course ofwhich both aircraft had sustained damage.   Our flying-boat had returned to base.A few raids at low altitude had been reported on the east coast. Fighter patrols had been despatched, but had not encounteredthe enemy.Reference was made to the use by Germany of Flak-ships. TheSecretary of State for Air explained that this matter had beendiscussed the previous evening at a Conference with the Admiralty,,and that the Admiralty were considering what action could be takento deal with these ships.[20527]
The Naval 3.   The First Lord of the A dmiralty informed the War cabinet situation. of certain dispositions which had been taken to guard against the(Previous possibility of a German surface attack on the Norwegian convoysReference:        in revenge for the loss of the Graf Spee.W.M. (39) 119th H.M.S. Hyperion had intercepted the German steamshipConclusions, Columbus (32,000 tons) 500 miles South-east of New York. the minute 5.)        crew of the Columbus had set their ship on fire and scuttled her.597 survivors had been taken on board a United States cruiser.An unconfirmed report had been received that a ship resemblingthe German naval tanker Altmark had been sighted in the south atlantic. The Altmark was believed to have on board 300 british prisoners of war, captured by the Graf Spee. Suitable dispositionshad been made to intercept her if possible.The German policy of attacking unprotected trawlers had continued. Four trawlers had been bombed and machine-gunned.One trawler had been damaged and two of the crew killed.The Danish steamship Jytte (1,877 tons) had been mined and sunk on the 19th December off Newcastle.   Ten men were missing.The destroyer ELhartou,m had reported being missed by a torpedo in the approaches to the Clyde. She had counter-attacked the submarine, but with no visible results.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Germany. 4.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionSuggested to telegram No. 298, dated the 19th December, 1939, from Hisreprisals against Majesty&apos;s Minister, Copenhagen, in which Mr. Howard Smithattacks on enquired whether consideration had been given to the possibilityBritish fishing of taking reprisals for German bombing and machine gunning ofvessels. British fishing trawlers and other breaches of International Lawby action against German ships bringing ore from Narvik. these vessels passed through The Belts at the rate of about four a weekand were understood to go outside Norwegian territorial waterstwice before finally leaving them at Arendal.The First Sea Lord pointed out that while in normal timesthese ships would probably find it convenient to leave norwegian territorial waters on this route, it was in fact possible for themto keep inside territorial waters the whole time.The War&apos; Cabinet took note of the above statements.The Military 5.   The Secretary of State for War said that there had beenSituation. no developments on the Western Front.(Previous The British had suffered their first casualties, amounting in reference: all to one killed and six wounded. These casualties had all occurredW.M. (39) 118th on patrol.Conclusions, Thg Chief of the Imperial General Staff- gave no credence to minute 3.) ^g rep0rt faat ^e Germans were massing large numbers of troopsopposite Luxembourg with the intention of carrying out an attack in this sector. He mentioned that his scepticism was shared byGeneral Gamelin.Possible German        The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs said that there hadintentions.        been some reports to the effect that the possibility of an attackon Holland and Belgium must again be taken into consideration.By contrast, the Foreign Secretary drew attention to telegramNo. 256, dated the 18th December, 1939, from The Hague, accordingto which the officers of the Netherland General Staff had stated thatthey had definite indications that Germany was not preparing any military action for Christmas, and that army leave was beinggranted on a generous scale in Germany.   No German action was
expected before the beginning of January. The Secretary of Stateadded that it was just possible that the Germans were puttingabout rumours about the grant of army leave as a blind.The Foreign Secretary also referred to a report dated the7th December from a source regarded as reliable, to the effect that hitler had given up all intention of inaugurating any large-scale operations on land. Exasperated by our successes at sea, he had,instead, decided to carry out heavy air attacks on our channel ports, Naval Bases and in the Thames Estuary. These attacks weretimed to take place before the end of the year. Hitler had been warned that such a course of action would involve very serious losses, in view of the air defences of Great Britain, and wouldprobably evoke serious retaliation. He had, however, decided to ignore this advice. The High Command had also been told to standby for an attack on the Western Front, but up to the 7th Decemberno decision had been taken.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Weekly Reports. 6. The War Cabinet took note of Weekly Reports by the(Previous Secretaries of State for War and Air (W.P. (39) 167 and 166)!Reference:W.M. (39) 113thConclusions, ----------------Minute 5.)Finland.Invasion byIJ.S.S.R.(previous reference:WM. (39) 117thConclusions,Minute 6.)7. The Secretary of State for War said that the onlyimportant development in Finland had taken place in theKuolajarvi sector, where Soviet troops were reported to havereached the parish of Kemijarvi. A second column was said tohave been advancing in a more Northerly direction from Salatowards Savukoski and so towards Sodankyla. These reports werenot confirmed, but, if true, it looked as if the Russians were aiming at cutting Finland in half.In the Karelian Isthmus the Finns had been harassed by heavytanks (30 to 35 tons).The Chief of the Imperial General Staff considered that itwould be a serious matter if the Russians succeeded in their attemptto drive through to Haparanda on the Swedish-Finnish frontier, asthey would then be in a position to cut the railway from Tornio toNarvik. But the Finns seemed confident of being able to repel a russian attack which the Russians would have to stage in verydifficult conditions. The number engaged could not be large; andno doubt the Finns hoped to counter-attack from the South.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Finland.Supply of aircraft.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 118thConclusions,Minute 9.)[20527]8: The Secretary of State for Air said that the Air ministry had now arranged to supply 10 more Gladiators in Finland,making in all a total of 30. The Finns had also been offered the28 Gauntlets which the Union Government had agreed should be diverted to Finland. The cost of the 10 Gladiators was  90,000,and the 28 Gauntlets  15,000, and he suggested that the BritishGovernment Should make a present of these aircraft to Finland.For the purposes of any public statement, it would be made to appear that the aircraft were supplied to Einland by the aircraftfirm concerned.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was prepared toagree to this suggestion.b 3
The War Cabinet agreed (i) To authorise the Air Ministry to arrange for the supply of10 additional Gladiators making a total of 30 and28 Gauntlets as a free gift to Finland,(ii) That the above aircraft should ostensibly be supplied to finland by the aircraft firms concerned.Supreme WarCouncil: 4thMeeting.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 113thConclusions,Minute 12.)South-BastEurope.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 118thConclusions,Minute 12.)9. The Prime Minister gave the War Cabinet an account ofthe proceedings of the 4th Meeting of the Supreme War Council, thediscussions at which had been, generally speaking, of a very satisfactory nature.  .Most of the time had been taken up with discussions on thesituation in South-East Europe. It had emerged, after some preliminary talk, that the French thought that the first requirementwas concerted diplomatic action in Yugoslavia, Roumania, greece and Turkey with the object of building up a Balkan front. they thought that a great deal could be done without giving a definitepromise that the Allies would co-operate actively other than in thesupply of war material. It was, of course, possible that at some timein the future active Allied intervention would be necessary, but theFrench agreed that this could be only on a limited scale.The Prime Minister said that he had pointed out that any suchaction as the French contemplated might provoke unfortunatereactions in Italy, whose benevolent neutrality at least was essential for any active intervention on the part of the Allies in the Balkans.The French, however, pressed for early action on the lines suggestedby them without consultation of the Italian Government. they stated that they had no engagement not to take steps to build up aBalkan front without first consulting Italy, though it had been pointed out to them that this was in clear contradiction to thestatement made to Sir Percy Loraine by Count Ciano on the16th September after a conversation between the latter and theFrench - Ambassador in Rome. Finally, after some further discussion, the French had agreed that an approach should be made,through the British Ambassador, with the object of letting theItalian Government know that the Allies were proposing to takecertain steps of a preparatory and defensive character against possible aggression in the Balkans by Germany and/or Russia. Ithad also been agreed that the French should continue their secretstaff contacts with Yugoslavia and Roumania, but should take no fresh action in the Balkans until preliminary soundings had beenmade in Italy. His (the Prime Minister&apos;s) own view was that therewould be no very violent reaction on the part of the Italian Govern-ment to such soundings as were now proposed.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs paid a tribute tothe skilful manner in which the Prime Minister had handled thediscussions with the French after his arduous tour of the british expeditionary Force. He himself was not over-sanguine as to theItalian reactions to the intended approach by Sir Percy Loraine.If his fears were justified, further consideration would, of course,have to be given to our whole Balkan policy. The French had agreed that it would be unwise to. put definite questions to theItalian Government, and that it would be better merely to inform them that it was necessary for us to take some steps to safeguardourselves in the Balkans against the possibility of aggression by our enemies in that area. How far we should go in the matter would be dictated by the Italian reactions to such a. statement.   If
AircraftSupplies fromthe UnitedStates ofAmerica.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 109thConclusions,Minute 10.)northern europe:Finland,Sweden and norway.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 118thConclusions,Minute 14.)this procedure were followed, and the Italians proved complacent,they would be in a position later on, if pressed by Germany, to saythat they had never been asked for their approval of the Allies&apos;activities in the Balkans. The French had agreed that it would be best to use Turkey as our &quot; stalking horse &quot; for diplomatic actionin South-East Europe. No doubt, after M. Menemencicglu had seen the British Minister in Sofia, we should have a better ideaof Bulgaria&apos;s attitude, which was an important factor.Discussion ensued as to the method of the proposed approach toItaly. It was pointed out that Count Ciano&apos;s recent speech mightbe construed as a warning to the Allies not to interfere in what theItalians considered to be their particular sphere of interest, thoughadmittedly this had been to some extent offset by Count Ciano&apos;ssubsequent explanations to Sir Percy Loraine. It was suggestedthat it was open to question whether there was any need to make animmediate approach, or whether it would not be better for theFrench and British Staffs to continue their Staff studies until we saw how things developed. If an immediate approach were made and the Italians took the opportunity at once to express theirdispleasure, we might be placed in rather an awkward position. Inany event, we should have to face the possibility of the Italiansmaking capital out of the situation and staking out a definite claim for a sphere of influence in the Balkans.It was argued, on the other hand, that our Ambassador in italy need only indicate that we were taking reasonable precautionsin the Balkans to meet the contingency of the initiative in that areabeing taken by our enemies.The French seemed to have agreed that the first stage wasto secure harmony among the Balkan countries themselves.M. Daladier was very anxious for the early initiation of jointdiplomatic action in the Balkans, and we were pledged to make an approach to Italy on this subject. We could not, therefore, delaytoo long. It was generally agreed, however, that it would bedesirable to give Sir Percy Loraine full information as to thediscussion which had taken place with the French at the supreme war Council, and suggestions as to the line which he should take with Count Ciano. Instructions to make a definite approach shouldbe delayed until our Ambassador had had time to study these suggestions and to give his own views upon them.The Prime Minister said he had informed the French of thedifficulties which we saw in any scheme to obtain a large increaseof American potential for the manufacture of aircraft. He had explained that any interference with our own supplies of machine tools from America would create serious difficulties for us. He had agreed, however, to add a British representative to the Missionwhich the French proposed to send to America.It was evident that the French were in full accord with thepolicy of helping Finland, and were anxious to&apos; consider what further action could be taken to stiffen the attitude of the norwegian and Swedish Governments. They thought that opinion in Swedenwas very much in favour of Finland, and particularly the king of Sweden. They were impressed with the importance of theSwedish iron-ore problem. M. Daladier, in particular, referred toa Memorandum by Herr Thyssen on the vital importance of swedish iron-ore to Germany.The French had shown to the British Ministers a draft of a proposed communication to Sweden and Norway and had promised to send us a copy of the final draft for more careful examination.It appeared from the preliminary draft that they contemplated adefinite guarantee to Norway and SAveden if they should become
involved in hostilities as a result of supporting Finland. TheFrench had agreed, however, that at this stage assistance to Finlandshould be sent ostensibly by armament firms and not openly by theGovernment.The Lord Privy Seal expressed the view that we should give adefinite guarantee to Sweden that we would take up arms in herdefence, if she were attacked by Russia or Germany for sendingassistance to Finland.It was recalled that the whole question of action in Scandinaviawas to be considered by the Military Co-ordination Committee that afternoon with a view to its further consideration by the WarCabinet.Agreement with france not tomake aseparate peace.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 109thConclusions,Minute 7.)Peace aims.Fecamp broad-casting station.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 111thConclusions,Minute 8.)The Prime Minister said that M. Daladier agreed that Franceand Great Britain neither would nor could make peace the onewithout the other. He (M. Daladier) supported the proposal for ajoint declaration, which would be of value primarily from the psychological point of view. The Germans were disseminating agreat deal of propaganda in France designed to drive a wedgebetween the Allies, and they were doing their best to encourage theCommunist element. It had been agreed that the question of ajoint declaration should be studied and a draft prepared.The subject of peace aims was being much discussed in france at the present time. M. Daladier had had a good deal to say onthis subject, and, though he seemed to be speaking impromptu, his views had coincided closely with those which had been expressed on the previous evening by M. Reynaud. The French were clearlyafraid that we should think it sufficient merely to get rid of Hitler.They felt very strongly that the character of the German people would remain unchanged, and that if Hitler were got out of the way,another leader would rise up in a few years and we should havethe whole trouble all over again. It was therefore essential to makeit impossible for Germany to disturb the peace of Europe once more. M. Daladier was not in favour of dismembering Germany,but had developed the idea of the Allies retaining strategic command of the Rhine, not by occupying territory, but by holding posts onthe left bank of the river. The Prime Minister had assuredM. Daladier that we had never thought that it would be sufficientmerety to put Hitler out of the way that was only an essential preliminary. We should require, no less than the French, guarantees for lasting peace, and we had said so in public. We had not specifiedthe nature of these guarantees, and, indeed, we had not yet made up our minds what would be required; but we were, of course,ready to examine the French suggestion for the strategical controlof the Rhine.M. Daladier had put up considerable resistance to the proposal that the Fecamp broadcasting station should be closed down.   Hehad referred to a proposal which had been made from the Frenchside early in November that the station should be closed down as.soon as an air-raid warning was given, and had said that no reply ito this suggestion had ever been made.   It had been pointed out to him that this suggestion was quite unacceptable for technical;reasons.   Finally, after considerable discussion, M. Daladier had agreed that the question should be examined by the British andFrench military authorities in conjunction, and that whateversolution they agreed upon should be accepted by both Governments.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence emphasised theimportance of immediate action on the lines of this agreement.There was a great deal of intrigue going on, both in France and inthis country, by commercial interests who were striving very hard toprevent the station being closed down.
Acceleration of The Prime Minister said that M. Daladier had pressed thedespatch of British representatives strongly to send more troops to France.  HeBritish military had hinted that the French considered that our scale of equipmentforces to was unnecessarily lavish, and that, if we reduced the scale, weFrance. should be able to put a great many more men in the field.(Previous The War Cabinet took note of the above statements and reference: agreed__C^nclus^ons00t 0) That a telegram should be sent by the Secretary of State for minute 13.)&apos; Foreign Affairs to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Rome,describing the action which the French and british governments proposed to take in the Balkans, and making suggestions for the lines of the informal8 approach to be made to the Italian Government,explaining to them what the French and British Govern-ments had in mind,(ii) That our Ambassador should be instructed to report how,in his view, this approach was likely to be received, andnot to make any approach to Count Ciano on thisquestion until his report had been considered by the WarCabinet.Italy.Attitudetowards Britishcontrabandcontrol.(previous reference:WM. (39) 105thConclusions,Minute 8.)(previous reference:W.M. (39) 93rdConclusions,Minute 12.)10. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto Telegram No. 1347, dated the 17th December, 1939, fromSir Percy Loraine reporting that Count Ciano had repeated thatthe shipping question was the only cloud on the Anglo-Italianhorizon. Signor Mussolini was not yet appeased on this subject,and in the course of his speech the previous day he (Count Ciano)had made a very brief allusion to the resolve of Italy to protect hertraffic by land, air and sea.Sir Percy Loraine had replied that he was glad that count Ciano appreciated our efforts to minimise the inconveniencearising from our contraband control. He knew that a stream of complaints on this subject reached Signor Mussolini, but he doubted whether the Duce was told the other side of the story. Sir Percyhad then cited one case in which the British Embassy had receivedalmost simultaneously a written complaint from Count Ciano&apos;s own department regarding the holding up of an Italian vessel and aletter of thanks from the punctilious captain of the same vessel forthe promptness with which she had been released. Count Cianowas very much amused by this incident, and had asked Sir percy loraine whether he thought that there were people deliberatelymaking difficulties in this matter. Sir Percy Loraine had assented,and suggested that the remedy lay in the closer co-operation betweenCount Ciano and himself, for which he had already pleaded.The First Lord of the A dmiralty said that the Admiralty were trying to carry out the contraband control measures effectively. If,however, the War Cabinet were to agree upon determined actionin the case of ships carrying ore from Narvik to Germany, it mightbe thought wise to relax further the contraband control arrange-ments in the Mediterranean so as to avoid difficulties arisingsimultaneously with Italy.The Minister without Port folio pointed out, however, that the stoppage of oil supplies to Germany was of an importance scarcelyless than that of iron ore and that this was dependent on contraband control in the Mediterranean and elsewhere.
?u&apos;e- 11.   The Minister without Portfolio referred to the oral reportIntelligence which he had made to the War Cabinet on the 5th December, and organisation. explained that he had not then asked them for a decision pending(Previous further reports for which he was waiting.   He had now receivedEeference:        these reports and requested that the necessary authority mightW.M. (39) 104th be given to the proposals which he then described.Conclusions, The record of these proposals and the discussion on them isMinute 8.)        contained  in  the  Secretary&apos;s  Standard  File of  War  cabinet conclusions.The War Cabinet:  Approved the proposals of the Minister without Portfoliofor an Intelligence Organisation in Eire, and invited himto continue to keep in touch with this question.War Aims.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 76thConclusions,Minute 9.)12. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (G.) (39) 150)submitting a draft reply, modified after discussion with HisMajesty&apos;s Governments in the Dominions, to the Memorandum on war Aims received from the French Government.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the changesin the earlier draft, made after discussion with the DominionGovernments, were little more than verbal. The draft could dono harm, though perhaps it consisted largely of generalities. he drew attention in particular to the statement in the last paragraphthat His Majesty&apos;s Government would welcome a further exchangeof views on the matter of War Aims, and to the fact that this might lead up to further discussion and to a frank statement ofthe views of each Government. He proposed to give the reply as drafted to M. Corbin, and to say that, though there was nourgency about the matter, we would be glad if arrangements couldbe made some time for a further general exchange of views, notwith a view to any immediate decision on any of the points a tissue, but in order to ensure that the two Governments were thinkingon the same general lines.The Prime Minister said that the French representatives onthe Supreme War Council had been told .that they would shortly be receiving a reply of the kind suggested.The War Cabinet: Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to hand to M. Corbin a reply to the French Governments Memo-randum on War Aims in the terms of the draft includedin his Memorandum W.P. (G.) (39) 150, and to inform him that His Majesty&apos;s Government would welcome indue course a further general exchange of views on thismatter.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,December 20, 1939.



</content>
</cab>
