<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/28/0 images: 148-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Tom       Lieut.-General Dessino. WAR JFFICE,WHITEHALL,-o C.I.G.S. S.W.I.4th October, 1917.I have received instructions from the Russian G.H.Q. inform you of the following The strategical situation of the Armies on the Russian-Roumanian front on the 1st September (old style) can be described as follows rn the NORTHERN FRONT, with the loss of Riga we havestepped being absolute masters of the situation in the Gulf of Riga, and have lost part of the line of defence along the River Dvina.     The change in the strategical situation chiefly consists of the above mentioned.     In regard to Petrograd being directly threatened, the strategical situation has not changed for the 7/crst.     There are sufficient well prepared positions in the rear of the Northern Front, with the aid of which the Armies will have full possibility to repulse the enemy.     Besides, the bad condition cf the reads in Autumn, together with the absence of sufficient good roads, makes an enemy offensive on Petrcgrad on a largo scale by land hardly likely.     Naval operations In the BALTIC in connection with descanto in Finland or at Pernau are more likely, and still more      likely would be a descante on the Isles cf Cesel and Dago, with the Intention to transfer the operations finally on to the Continent.     There are indications that the Germans are planning something of the sort, although the condition of the sea during the next Autumn months diminishes the likelihood of a landing.       We are taking all necessary . steps against this,  on land as well as on sea.
On the WESTERN &amp; SOUTH-WESTERN FRONTS, the lull which has set in does not seem likely to come to an end soon.   The &quot;reconnaissance1&apos; gives reasons rather not to expect an enemy offensive on these fronts,On the ROUMANIAN FRONT, the enemy seems to be re-grouping with the aim to concentrate a group of four or five divisions in the region of Seletin-Radautz-Kimpolung and 4 cavalry divisions have been sent to the north of Chernowitz.   Heavy German artillery is being taken to the south of Chernowitz.   At present local fighting continues in the Ocna and Ireshti regions, in the latter direction the fighting is evidently coming to an end, owing to the enemy having attained no results.   The enemy&apos;s activity is increasing in the Tecuchiu region.   The weather conditions are extremely favourable for the commencement of operations on a large scale.On the CAUCASIAN FRONT; from the Black Sea to Lake Van the enemy is not likely to undertake the offensive, partly owing to the bad state of the Turkish Army, partly owing to the difficulty of bring-ing up supplies.In MESOPOTAMIA, Falkenhayn is working out a plan to start an offensive from Mosul towards Urmia and from Mosul  towards Baghdad with the intention to defeat the Russian Urmia group, and to press back the British to the south of Baghdad.    The climatic conditions there are more favourable for active operations.The above mentioned shows, that no direct danger threatens Petrograd, if only the coast of Finland can be kept.   The most likely regions for active enemy operations are the Coast of the Gulf of Riga, the Jacobstadt and Dvinsk &quot;places d&apos;armes&quot; on the Northern Front,to the south of Ghernowitz on the Roumanian Front, and to the south of Lake Van in the Caucasus.
theOn the lBt March (old style) i *8. when ihe Revolution began, the following enemy forces were opposing the Russian-Roumanian Front: 74 German Infantry and 11.2/3 German Cavalry Divisions, 43 Austrian Ihfatttry, and lit Austrian Cavalry Divisions, 3 Bulgarian and 6 Turkish Infantry Divisions.On the 18th June (old style) l.e. when we began our offensive oh the south-western front 7 German Infantry Divisions wore addedj 1 German Cavalry Division was removed; 4-g Austrian and 2 Turkish Infantry Divisions were removed;    Finally on the 15th July (old style) there were 88 German Infantry Divisions arid 9 German Cavalry Divisions, 40-1 Austrian Infantry, and 11-1 Austrian Cavalry Divisionsj 3 Bulgarian Infantry, 1 Bulgarian Cavalry Division, and 4 Turkish Infantry Divisions.All this shows, that since the 1st March the enemy&apos;s forces on the front did not diminish but on the contrary had 9j Infantry Divisions to reinforce them, whilst 2.2/3 Cavalry Divisions were removed at the same time.The following is important to note concerning the fighting which resulted in the loss of the Riga Region:    The fighting began on the 19th August (old style) by a violent and accurate bombardment, accompanied by the use of many gas shells.       The Germans managed to cross the Dvina at Uexkull owing to sufficient forces, and developed their success piercing the positions of the XII Army,       From the 20th to the 23rd August (old style) our troops retreated to the Venden position which had previously been prepared.       The troops which were situated to the north-west of the gap had to retire under very heavy conditions, as the enemy who had pierced cur lines threatened them from the south-east.       This unexpected occurrence had as an unavoidable result the loss of some of the guns and other material losses .       On the 24th August the troops occupied
1 Uthe Vendon positionsThe troops hurriedly terminated thepositions and order was restored,As the enemy did not develophis success any further, we managed to send forward our advanced guards on the 20th August,      The work of the advanced guards was successful from the very beginning, they occupied importantcapture of trophies immediately had its good effect on the morale of the troops.      The Commander of the Army reports that the morale has improved, order is being restored and fighting capacity is being re-established,     With the&apos; aid of reserves and re-*grouping of the troops, the position has become steadier, and any further advance of the enemy would require considerable efforts on his part.The work of the High Command during Autumn, will chiefly consist of re-establishing the fighting capacity of the Armies. This is in close connection with the condition of the country and with the possibility of providing sufficient supplies for the Armies,      It depends on how this question is solved, as to what tasks car. be given to the Armies.points, in mostcases fighting between! our advanced guards andthe enemy was successful for us.Successful fighting andI have the honour to beSir,Your obedient Servant,(sgd.)nDESSINO.Lt-General.

</content>
</cab>
