<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/28/0 images: 496-497</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
a-^DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT AHNIC, MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET. G.T. 2272.W.vR CABINET.OBSBRVyfOE OP A PAY OP PR IYER. (Copy of letter fror the Archbishop of Canterbury to the Prime Minister.)Lanbeth Place, S.S   1.4th October, 1917.My dear Prime Minister,I an again pressed on the question of asking you to receive a Deputation desirous of urging the appointment by the State of a pay of Special Prayer.   I av approached both by Churchnen and Nonooniormists,  and the Executive Cor:nittee of the Free Church Council ha a pa&apos;5iou a Resolution and transmitted it to me.&quot;   They say:-&quot;This Com-ittct., in viev;&apos;of -ills gravity of the issues irpending at the prtoent crisis, instructs its Officers to confer with the leaders of the Anglican Church and of the World&apos;s Evangelical Alliance in order to request the Government to take the necessary steps to call the Nation to the observance of a Pay of Prayer, provided th&apos;t day be a Sunday&quot;.The position id a little si:*:plified by their request being limited to a Sunday.   We thus avoid the difficulties you mentioned as to the day becoming a mere holiday or rest-day.I have no knowledge how far the objection which you entertained to a Government direction or order or request of this sort still holds good.    I well remen-ber what you have said to me on the subject, and I think you will feel that I have always appreciated your position and the delicacy of the situation.   I must now, however, decide whether or not I am to ask you to receive a Deputation, and myself to accorpany it. I think it is undesirable that I should head such a Deputa-tion to you and be met with a definite refusal.   It i3 not that I personally mind what might look like a rebuff of a personal sort: that is a small matter: what I should feel is that it woula be unfortunate were you to find yourself obliged to take a course or make an utterance which set you apparently in opposition to the organised Christian representatives of the religious life of England.   If therefore you would feel bound, in response to such a request, to say &quot;I cannot receive a Deputation&quot; I should understand your doing so on the ground that you have already mentioned to me.   But I should in that case ask you to allow me to-state to the Committeeswhich have approached me that you have definitely requested that we should not ask you to receive a Deputation.   This might, hardly less than the refusal of a Deputation&apos;s proposal ......
be interpreted as your adoption of an unfriendly attitude . But it would probably be less marked than the rebuffing of a Deputation actually received .If , on the other hand, you are prepared to receive a Deputation and go some way at least towards granting the request, I suggest that possibly you might, either with or without receiving a Deputation, promise that a letter should be written on your advice by iiis Majesty, or failing this, by yourself as Head of the Government j a letter urging the various Churches and Denominations to make the most of a day such as the last Sunday in the year (December 30th),. or the first Sunday in next year (January 6th), for invoking the Divine Blessing upon the deliberate and continued endeavour of the Allied forces to sustain the cause of what is right and true and what tells for the liberty and well-being of the nations of the earth .   You would judge better than I what words to use .   The point is that the act should be National..  It would cease to be an independent and sectional endeavour of the different bodies of Christians in England and would have upon it the impress of a National expression of belief in God and in the meaning, the propriety, and the obligation of public prayer on behalf of a sacred cause . It would be so worded as to avoid a possible implication that if we were asking for prayer we must be in serious straits . We feel entitled as a Nation to ask for the blessing and guidance of God upon our endeavour because we believe it is being carried forward on right lines to a. great issue... Thanksgiving would inherently and rightly form a part of our devotions on that day.I am,Yours very truly,;3d.) RANDALL CANTAB.

</content>
</cab>
