<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/41/0 images: 22-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property^of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, jPrinted for the Imperial War Cabinet.   June 1918.SECRET.IMPERIAL WAR CABINET, 10.Minutes of the Sixteenth Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet, held in London at10, Downing Street, S.W., on Thursday, June 13, 1918, at 1T30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of-   Kedleston,  KG.,  G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.The Right Hon. A. J. Baleour,O.M., M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forWar.The Right Hon. Sir Eric Geddes,G.B.E., K.C.B., M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Robert L. Borden,G.C.M.G., KG, Prime Minister ofCanada.The Right Hon. W. F. Massey, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.The Right Hon. Sir J. G. Ward, Bt.,K.C.M.G., Minister of Finance, NewZealand.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, KG, Minister for Defence,Union of South Africa.The Hon. II. Burton, KG., Minister of railways and Harboursya^d^-Hsasee,Union of South Africa.The Right Hon. W. F. Lloyd, KC, PrimeMinister of Newfoundland.The Hon. Sir S. P. Sinha, Member of theExecutive Council of the Governor of bengal.Maj or-General His Highness Sir Bhupind arSingh Mahindar, Bahadur, G.C.I.E.,G.B.E., Maharaja oi: Patiala.The following were also present:Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, G.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval Staff.General Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclay, Bart.,Shipping Controller.Colonel P. R, C. Grove, D.S.O., Directorof Flying Operations (for Minutes 1to 6). &apos;The Hon. A. Meighen, Minister of Interior,Canada.the - Right Hon. j.^ Calder, Minister of immigration and Colonisation, Canada.The Hon. N. Rowell, President of the privy Council, Canada.Mr. H. C. M. Lambert, C.B.Mr. Philip Kerr.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. S. Amery, M.P., Assistant Secretary.
Representatives 1. THE Prime Minister,&apos; on behalf of the Cabinet, welcomedfrom India. the Indian representatives, the Maharaja of Patiala and Sir S. Sinha.who had not been able to attend the first meeting.The Western 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that there hadFront, been heavy fighting locally along the battle-front throughout thepreceding day, although no big attack had been made. The french had fought extremely well, and had presumably inflicted heavypunishment on the enemy ; but the fighting, on the whole, had goneagainst us. The Germans - had got into the &quot;western edge of theVillers-Cotterets&apos; Forest, *rid also gained ground westward, to thenorth of the Forest. ^Identifications had been slow in coming in,and only 18 German divisions had so far been identified. only, or possibly 4, of these belonged to Prince Rupprecht of Bavariansgroup of armies. It was not quite certain yet whether the GermanCrown Prince had exhausted all his reserves, and possibly he still had4 or o fresh divisions in hand, as well as such other divisions as couldbe got by roulement along his line. The whole tendency had been to draw reserves from the sotith Jand east, and the inference fromthis was that the great mass of Prince Rupprecht&apos;s reserves was still facing the British. According to Field-Marshal Sir douglas haig, they were ready to attack&apos; within forty-eight hours of thedecision of their Command to do so. Of three divisions recentlybrought up to the northern sector of the front, one had been sentsouth through Lille, but there was no evidence to show whether that was being sent to help the German Crown Prince, or toreplace in Prince Rupprecht&apos;s reserve some other division already sent south.The Italian Front.Submarines.Bruges and-Zeebrugge.3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that theItalians now considered that there was no question of the Austriansattacking on the Lower Piave, although General Cavan still thoughtthat an attack down the Brenta line was probable. General Wilsonpointed ou that, the fear of an Austrian attack on the Lower Piavehad caused the Italians to abandon the projected offensive on theAsiago Plateau, and to move their heavy guns away from there. Itwould take some time to bring the guns back if they thought ofrenewing the offensive4. The First Sea Lord reported that a submarine had been attacked, and probably destroyed,.by our squadron in the Adriatic.The total destruction of submarines in the last month had been very satisfactory.5. The First Sea Lord stated that Bruges and Zeebrugge werebeing steadily bombed.Sinking of TwoAustrian Dread-noughts.(i. Admiral Wemyss stated that he had no information, beyond what had appeared in the press, as to the statement that two Austriandreadnoughts had been sunk bv Italian motor craft.Sir B. Borden&apos;sStatement.7. Sir R. Borden made a general statement reviewing, in all its aspects, Canada&apos;s effort towards the prosecution of the war. At iheclose of his^ statement he drew the attention of the Imperial WarCabinet to information which had convinced him that our want ofmilitary success had been largely clue to lack of foresight and prepara-tion, and to defects in the organisation and leadership of our forces,and urged the imperative necessity of putting aside every consideration in appointments except that of efficiency.   He drew attention to
the high degree of organisation which the Canadian forces had beenable to attain under officers of whom only a small proportion wereprofessional soldiers, suggesting that if it was true that in theBritish Army only professional soldiers had any opportunity of risinghigher than the rank of Brigadier-General, that was equivalent to awholesale scrapping of &quot;the brains of a nation in its struggle forexistence. In this connection he suggested that the Canadian Armymight be specially utilised in helping with the training of theAmerican forces, whose problems were identical with those whichthey had themselves solved.8. Mr. Massey expressed his appreciation of the frankness whichhad marked both the Prime Ministers statement on the occasion of&apos;the previous meeting, and Sir R. Borden&apos;s statement on the present occasion. He considered it was essential that the Imperial WarCabinet should clearly understand the causes of our failure both atPasschendaele last autumn, and on the occasion of the breaking ofthe front of the Vth Army in March, in order to be able to find theright remedy. He then proceeded to give a general review of the effort made by New Zealand towards the conduct of the War duringthe last twelve months.The text of Sir R. Bordens and Mr. Massey&apos;s statements will be circulated in a separate document.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,June 13, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
