<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/41/0 images: 82-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Docnment^is the Property-of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, jPrinted for the Imperial War Cabinet.   July 1918.SECRET.IMPERIAL WAR CABINET, 27.180Minutes of the Twenty-seventh Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet, held in London at10, Downing Street, S.W., on Thursday, July 25, 1918, at 11*30 a.m.Present:The Prime Minister of the United Kingdom (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl curzon kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Atjsten Chamberlain,M.P.The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M., M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Viscount Milner, G.C.B.,G.C.M.G., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Robert L. Bordbn,G.C.M.G., K.C., Prime Minister ofCanada.The Right Hon. N. W. Rowell, Presidentof the Privy Council, Canada.The Right Hon. W. M. Hughes, PrimeMinister of Australia.The Right Hon. J. Cook, Minister of theNavy, Australia.The Right Hon. W. F. Massey, PrimeMinister of New Zealand.The Right Hon. Sir Joseph Ward, Bart.,K.C.M.G., Minister of Finance, NewZealand.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon.J..C. Smuts, K.C., Minister for Defence,Union of South Africa.The Right Hon. H. Burton, K.C., Ministerof Railways and Harbours, Union ofSouth Africa.The Right Hon. W. F. Lloyd, K.C., PrimeMinister of Newfoundland.The Hon. Sir S. P. Sinha, Member ofthe Executive Council of the governor of Bengal.Maj or-General His Highness SirBhupindarSingh, Mahindar Bahadur, G.C.I.E.,G.B.E., Maharaja of Patiala.The following were also present general Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff(for Minutes 1 to 7).Major-General F. H. Sykes, C.M.G., Chiefof the Air Staff (for Minutes 1 to 7).Rear-Admiral G. P. W. Hope, C.B., deputy first Sea Lord (for Minutes 1 to 7).Mr. Philip Kerr.The Right Hon. Lord. Robert Cecil,K.C., M.P., Assistant Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (for Minute 7).The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minute 8).Mr. H. C. M. Lambert, C.B., ColonialOffice. -.        !The- Right Hon. the Lord Newton, Con-troller, Prisoners of War Department(for Minute 7).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Wilson,, CM.G., D.S.O., M.P., Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. S. Amery, M.P., Assistant Secretary.
Divisions inEeserve.2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that on thewhole of the German line on the Western front there were 33 entirelyfresh divisions in reserve. Up to the present, 63 German divisions had been identified as having been engaged in the recent operations,and it was, of course, certain that other divisions had been engagedbut not yet identified. Of the army of Prince Rupprecht, identification-tions had been reported of 8 divisions. In connection with any move from the north of the German force, General Wilson said thathutting had been spotted in the vicinity of Bapaume, and thatthere was apparently a small movement south from Lille, butthat there was very little information available on this subject.H.M.S. &quot;Vanity.&apos;13. The Deputy First Sea Lord reported that H.M.S. &quot; Vanity &quot;struck a mine off the Firth of Forth on 23rd July, but had returned to harbour.Constantinople.4. The Deputy First Sea Lord stated that a report had beenreceived from Mudros that Constantinople had been raided by sixmachines on the 23rd July. Considerable damage had been doneby bombs being dropped, on the aerodrome, the Admiralty, andparticularly the dockyard. No massing of troops had been observed.Steamship 5. Questioned as to the protection which had been given to&apos; Justicia.&quot; steamship &quot; Justicia,&quot; the Deputy First Sea Lord said that she wasin a convoy with seven other ships and protected by eight destroyers.The first torpedo struck her in the engine room, and in the courseof a few hours she was further protected by destroyers, trawlers,,tugs, and sloops, which surrounded her during the night. AdmiralHope pointed out that, as she was in tow and proceeding at a veryslow pace, she offered a very favourable target to submarine attackafter being disabled. - The &quot; Justicia &quot; had been picked out of the convoy by the attacking submarines, which were apparentlydetermined to sink her.   One German submarine had been sunk.The Prime Minister drew the attention of the Imperial WarCabinet to a statement published in the press that morning which made no mention of the fact that one of the attacking submarineshad .been sunk. Mr. Lloyd George said that he considered that this statement should not have been passed by the Admiralty PressCensor in its incomplete form, as it was only fair to the British Navythat the sinking of the German submarine should have been made public. It was also very desirable that the Germans should realise that a ship, convoyed as steamship &quot; Justicia&quot; was, could not besunk with impunity.Western Front. 1. THE Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that there wasno news to report from the Western front with the exception of the,   small gains of yesterday, already reported in the communiques.With reference to future operations, General Wilson said thatGeneral Foch was undecided whether to continue his operationswithout reorganisation, or to cease operations for two or three days in order to reorganise and start again. General Foch had not yet received reports as to the condition of his troops, hut, when he had,he would then make up his mind. Questioned as to whetherGeneral Foch had attained all that he expected, General Wilson saidthat, while General Foch had expected to attain more, he wascontent with the result of the operations.
The Air Situation.6. The Chief of the Air Staff reported that he had been investi-gating the question of the increase in the number of Germanballoons destroyed by our machines. There was no change in ourtactics. Our airmen, in default of finding very many aeroplanes toattack, have been attacking these balloons.General Sykes pointed out that there is an inclination on thepart of the German machines to keep well behind the line. This,when taken in conjunction with bad weather, such as we have beenhaving recently, generally meant slight relative increase in ourmissing our airmen naturally incurring a greater danger inreturning in the face of the prevalent strong south-westerly wind.Questioned with regard to any reported movement of troops,General Sykes indicated that, until yesterday, observation and reconnaissance had been much hampered by bad visibility. Yester-day the weather was better, though there was still a high wind anda certain amount of cloud. No definite movement of the enemy hadbeen traced.&apos;During the recent raids of the Independent Air Force nomachines had been lost, although the aircraft defences on theGerman side had bean considerably increasedExchange ofPrisoners of War.Germans in China.7. Lord Robert Cecil drew the attention of the Imperial WarCabinet to the reservation which the German delegates had made tothe agreement with regard to the exchange of prisoners, namely,that it depended on the satisfactory settlement of the position of theGermans in China. He reminded the Imperial War Cabinet that ithad been originally decided to deport all Germans in China toAustralia, but subsequently, owing to the opposition of our Allies,we wished to divert the shipping required for this purpose tothe transport of Czecho-Slovaks to Vancouver. This idea had been abandoned. The effect in China had been most unfortunate, as our change of policy was thought to have been due to Germanthreats of reprisals. Since then China of its own initiative had offered to intern 120 of the most important Germans in China,either on an island or in a secluded temple, and to put the remaining300 or 400 under special restrictions. Except the Belgians all our allies had agreed to this proposal. If we now began to enter into negotiations with the Germans with regard to this principle theymight refuse to accept anything less than being left at completeliberty in China. The Germans attached the greatest importanceto their prestige and future trade in China, and this might leadthem to take extreme measures, though he understood that LordNewton considered the Germans were mainly anxious to save theirface over this question. What he himself wished was to have theauthorisation of the Imperial War Cabinet to go straight ahead and get the 120 Germans concerned locked up before starting negotiationswith Germany about the exchange of prisoners. He quite realised that if subsequently the agreement about the prisoners broke downin consequence of this action a section of public opinion in thiscountry might be very much upset.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointed out that theGermans had previously threatened reprisals in this connection oncivilians under their control.   This would not affect us, as we hadThe Imperial War Cabinet decided that - The First Lord of the Admiralty should be asked to publish anofficial statement to the effect that one of the german submarines which participated in the attack of steamship&quot;Justicia&quot; had been destroyed.
more German civilians in our hands than they had of ours, but itmight affect the Belgians, and this probably accounted for theattitude of Belgium in connection with the Chinese proposal.Lord Newton said that he had discussed the matter confi-dentially with one of the German delegates, and gathered that the trouble had risen entirely from the boast which Von Kuhlmann had made in the Reichstag that the negotiations at The Hague had resulted in our climbing down over the question of the Germans inChina. The chief anxiety of the German Government now was to save its own face in that connection. He would be in favour ofsigning the agreement and then let the Germans make any furtherproposal they chose in regard to their own subjects in China. Hethought himself if the British Government said it would not put any direct pressure for internment on China that that would satisfyGermany. The Chinese were now going to intern them in anycase.Lord Robert Cecil replied that if we made such a statement the Chinese Government would certainly not proceed with the internment.It was suggested that the best thing in view of the futurewould be to repatriate the Germans to their own country, whichCould now be done overland. In answer to the objection that theGermans had previotisly rejected a suggestion to this effect, it waspointed out that they would not be in a strong position if were offered to them the alternative of internment in China or repatria-tion.The Imperial War Cabinet authorised Lord Robert Cecil to press on with the present arrangementsfor the internment of Germans in China, and at the sametime let it be known that we were prepared to agree to thealternative of repatriation for those who prefer it.Channels of 8. Sir Joseph Ward, in  continuing  the  discussion at the communication. previous Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet (Imperial WarCabinet 26, Minute 8), said that he agreed with Sir Robert Bordenthat the evolution in the circumstances of the Empire necessitateda change. The oversea Dominions now represented 16 millions of people who had taken up an immense burden in connection withthe war. They would number some 40 million people before long,and it was obvious that they must have a say in the foreign policyof the Empire. He agreed absolutely with Sir Robert Borden thatthe position which existed before the war could net possibly continue.There must be consultation, in which no doubt the United kingdom would still retain its predominance, and in which it could count upon the loyal support of the oversea Governments. As a matter of fact, the Dominion Governments at present were in a position of having to inform their people about decisions after they hadbeen taken. They backed up these decisions loyally in orderto prevent friction, but the situation could not continue. He con-sidered that the Dominions would have to have their voice on all questions of foreign policy, defence, and also inter-Imperial trade.He instanced more particularly as one of the questions on whichImperial consultation would be necessary after the war, the disposalof the war stocks raised by the different Governments of the Empire,including the Government of India as well as that of the overseaDominions, during the war, and at present immobilised. If theywere all let loose in competition with each other in all the markets of the Empire and of the world outside, there would be heavy depre-ciation, by which the Dominions would be most seriously affected.His own opinion was that it would be desirable to unify all thoseissues in a common Empire stock, with a single rate of interestsaleable anywhere in the Empire and outside.   In any case, the
matter was one which could not be settled by stray visits of DominionFinancial Ministers to London to see the Chancellor of the Exchequer.It involved continuous consultation. In answer to an interjectionfrom Mr. Hughes that this involved some sort of Imperial Federation,Sir Joseph Ward said that he did not necessarily imply that. Noone could now reasonably decide what could be done in the future.That question would have to be settled calmly and dispassionatelyat a subsequent date. At present the war came before anything else.As regards the actual measures required during the war toimprove Imperial consultation, he doubted if any one man could carryout the combined duties already devolving upon the Prime Ministerwhich might be involved in the resolution passed by the imperial war Conference. He associated himself with what had been said by others about the good work of the Colonial Office, and thoughtthat if a separate Ministry was required for Dominion business,the Secretary of State for the Colonies might as well carry on as before. In his opinion, the only way in which the wishes and aspirations of the Dominions could be met at the present time would be by permanent representation on the Imperial War Cabinet.The few weeks, for which the Imperial War Cabinet met at thepresent were not sufficient. In the interval vital matters were settled, and all the Dominions could do was to say &quot;yes&quot; afterwards.This was unavoidable under the existing conditions, but no one could say that it was satisfactory. He pointed out that, since thelast Imperial War Cabinet had met, the British Government had had to make very different decisions with regard to which itsconduct of affairs had been scrutinised since the Imperial WarCabinet had reassembled. Then again there was such a question asthat of the unity of control of the Allied forces. The Dominions hadall been in favour of that, but the British Government had had todeal with certain difficulties in introducing that policy, and it mighthave helped to an earlier solution of that difficult problem if it hadbeen able to say that the Dominion Governments were in favour of that policy, and that it was, in fact, an Empire policy. His suggestion was that each of the Dominion Prime Ministers should leave a Ministerpermanently here when he went back. This would make the voice ofthe Dominions in Imperial affairs a reality. Their voice was only areality when a Minister was actually present in the War Cabinet.This would also greatly help to solve the question of channels of communication, because the Prime Ministers could then telegraphdirect to their own colleagues in this country, who would beempowered to bring the matter forward before the War Cabinet,or to confer on it with the Prime Minister. He considered thissuggestion of Ministerial representation during the war and theperiod of reconstruction immediately after the war as the besttemporary bridge that could be devised. Otherwise he was not infavour of any drastic changes until the matter could be fully considered.Mr. Powell pointed out that the keynote of the whole discussion had been frank recognition of the equality of status between thedifferent nations of the Empire as the basis of any solution. Thequestion of any permanent reconstruction he assumed would be leftuntil after the war, in accordance with the resolution of the previous year&apos;s Imperial Conference. He thought that would commend itselfto public opinion in Canada, which felt that the undivided energiesof the Governments of the Empire should be devoted to the actualconduct of the war. But this did. not imply that nothing need bedone in order to improve the existing channels of communication.What General Smuts had suggested was that the matter should beleft over and not be dealt with piece-meal. But he wished to draw attention to one partial step which had been actually taken duringthe war, namely, the assembling of the Imperial War Cabinet, whieh[530-13J C
Lad undoubtedly been useful. The time had come, in his opinion,for a further step to improve the existing situation, and to meet in some measure the legitimate sentiments of the Dominions. their national sentiment to-day was stronger than ever before, and shouldreceive some expression consistent with the unity of the Empire.He suggested that the status of the Governors-General had largelychanged as a matter of practice, and urged that the change should now be frankly recognised, and that the Governors-General should no longer act as a channel of communication with the ColonialOffice, but should be confined to their position as representatives ofthe Sovereign. That would not involve any action beyond thedecision of the Imperial War Cabinet, and a communication to the governors-General to that effect. With regard to the actual methodof communication, he thought that there was a distinct differencebetween the class of questions which affect issues of war and peace,such as were in fact dealt by the Imperial War Cabinet, andsuch questions as were discussed at the Imperial Conference, ordealt with in the ordinary course of business communications between the Dominion Governments and the Colonial Office. he saw no reason w hy communications of the first class, namely, thosedealing with Imperial War Cabinet matters, should not be betweenPrime Minister and Prime Minister, the British Prime Ministerusing the existing secretariat of the Imperial War Cabinet for thatpurpose, even if communications on other classes of subjectsremained as at present.The Secretary of State for the Colonies expressed his gratefulappreciation of the references which had been made to the greatDepartment with which he was connected. As regards the changes which had been advocated, they were based, not on any allegedshortcomings of the Colonial Office, but on a great central fact of empire, namely, that the oversea Dominions were free nations withan absolute control of their own affairs, which entitled them to adifferent status from that which they had hitherto held. If he offered anything which appeared in the nature of criticism, this wasnot because there was not in the Colonial Office any non possumusor factious attitude towards the change. Their one desire was, ifpossible, to meet the demand which had been put forward, and,above all, to strengthen the foundations of the Empire and to expedite its business.The proposals which had been made fell under two main heads,firstly, those which affected the permanent rearrangement of theBritish Government, and secondly, those concerned with the imme-diate means for securing direct communication between the PrimeMinisters of the Empire.With regard to the first set of proposals, he believed that thetime had come when such changes would have to be made. Theywould have to be considered by the British Government, as theyinvolved changes in its own constitution and methods. He had not put forward any proposals himself, but though he was quite readyto put his views on paper if desired. He agreed with General Smutsthat the wider question could not be settled now, least of all, at twoor three discussions of the Imperial War Cabinet. If the PrimeMinister thought it desirable to appoint a small committee, under,say, Lord Curzon as Chairman, to consider these matters, he wouldbe very willing to serve on it, and the results might then be laidbefore the Imperial War Cabinet. As regards the minor questionsof communication, he agreed with the Chancellor of the Exchequer,who had the most recent experience of Colonial Office administration,as his predecessor, that within certain limits, which should be clearly defined, there was no reason why there should not be direct communi-cation between the Dominion Prime Ministers and the British PrimeMinister. There was in fact nothing to prevent it now except an idea that the Colonial Secretary might possibly feel hurt. He assured them
that there would be no such feeling as far as he himself was concerned.It was necessary, however, for him to consider the- position of- theBritish Prime Minister in the matter. It was not always realised in theDominions that there was only one Colonial Secretary to five Governors-General of the Dominions, that every mail brought a very large numberof communications. It was necessary to find some way of seeing thatthe work could really be done, and that the Prime Ministers control should be real and not nominal. Communications came in not onlyon matters of common co-operation, but there were complaints andcriticisms of different departments which the Colonial Office tried to accommodate. There must be someone to examine the casesgenerally, and to advise the Prime Minister. However, he agreedthat the matter was one for the Prime Minister to decide for himself.He was, however, obliged to put before the Imperial War Cabinetwhat he considered the most important aspect of this question of direct communication, namely, the effect upon the position of the governors-General. He admitted the position had no doubt changedgreatly in practice, hut he did not think it would be fair to the governors-General to come to any conclusion on this matter withoutcommunicating with them more fully than was possible by cable,which he had already done, in order to give them an opportunity ofstating their own views. He did not say that the Governors-general would be opposed to the proposed change in their position, but hethought that they should be consulted.Sir Robert Borden pointed out that the British Government incommunicating with the Dominion Governments did not communicatethrough the King. If there was to be absolute equality of status that course would be the logical correlative to the present system ofcommunication with the Dominions through the Governors-General.The Secretary of State for the Colonies pointed out that the governors-General were the representatives of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment as well as of the Sovereign.Mr. Hughes replied that if His Majesty&apos;s Government avowedlydid not profess to exercise a control over the policy of the DominionGovernments, there was no reason for the Governors-General to occupy this dual position.The Secretary of State for the Colonies agreed, and expressedthe view that he considered the change inevitable in the end, buturged that the Governors-General should be consulted, as their position would be undeniably affected. He suggested the imperial war Cabinet should make up its mind as to the precise nature ofthe changes which they wished to see carried out in this respect andembody them in a despatch to be sent to the Governors-General.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, leaving aside the great problem of future reorganisation, there were two questions : (i.) Whether communication between the Dominion Govern -ments and the British Government should go throughthe Governors-General or direct ?   And,(ii.) If direct, should it go from Prime Minister to PrimeMinister or through the Colonial Office ?As regards the first point, he was quite clear personally thatthe system of communication through the Governors-General wasdoomed, and belonged to a past epoch. As regards the second question, which he considered of less importance, the ColouialSeeretary&apos;s well-founded criticism might, in his opinion, be met withan expedient not unknown in foreign affairs. The Prime Ministerfrequently communicated with Allied Prime Ministers direct, andnot through the Foreign Office orthodox channels. He saw noreason why the Prime Ministers of the Dominions should not com-municate with the Prime Minister on important matters when they
wanted to do so, it being understood tbat communications normallywent through the established machinery of the Colonial Office.In answer to a suggestion from the Chancellor of the exchequer that the Prime Minister also sometimes wanted to correspond with another Allied Prime Minister quite privately, Mr. Balfour said that,while not objecting to that, he did not think it desirable that thisshould occur too often.Lord Curzon pointed out that in India the Viceroy was notmerely the representative of the Sovereign, but also in the positionof the Prime Minister of the Government. As such, his normalchannel of correspondence with the British Government wasthrough the Secretary of State for India. But there were caseswhen he might wish to communicate with the Prime Ministerdirectly. When he had been Viceroy he had, on several occasions,communicated directly with Lord Salisbury or with Mr. Balfour inthat way, and no one had contested his right to do so. There was noquestion of going behind the back of the Secretary of State for India.He knew for a fact that his letters would be shown to the Secretary ofState in every case. He saw no difficulty about the same procedurebeing adopted in the case of the Dominions. There might be casesof&apos; importance in which the Prime Ministers of the Dominionsw^ould correspond with the British Prime Minister directly, and inthose cases the latter would naturally put himself in touch with theColonial Secretary.Mr. Churchill expressed the hope that the larger question ofImperial reconstruction would not be regarded as unattainable ornot worth discussing at the present moment. It was an urgent andvital necessity that could not be passed by. The great nations whichcomposed the Empire could not be pushed this way or that way infuture in matters which concerned either war policy or war prepara-tions. The revolution which the war had caused carried that with it.He realised the immense difficulties in dealing with the question duringthe war, but he realised equally the difficulties in the way of dealingwith it in time of peace. Having some experience as a party politicianhimself he was certain that in the United Kingdom the difficultiesin the way of dealing with the question would be infinitely greaterwhen peace had come. There would be acute party struggles,and the Opposition would strongly object to any prestige which theGovernment in office might acquire by its association with theDominion Governments. The whole question would pass into thearea of controversy with all its difficulties unsolved. He thought itwould be the greatest danger to the Empire if we came out of thewar without settling this question. The metal was now molten and could be moulded. He agreed with the Colonial Secretary that itwas desirable to investigate the question at once.Meanwhile, the first step to be taken was a purely practical one.It was necessary to put the machinery of the Imperial War Cabineton a permanent basis, so that the common policy of the empire should not pass completely out of the control of the Dominions forthe months which intervened between two sessions. He thought itwas perfectly simple for the Prime Minister of each Dominion to select a second Minister, one whom he regarded as next in importance to himself, who could be in this country when the PrimeMinister himself returned to his Dominion. The Imperial WarCabinet could then continue, not necessarily with such frequency as during the present period of most active session, but, at any rate, at frequent intervals. In this way nine-tenths of the present difficultiescould be got over.The Prime Minister considered that this had been one of themost important debates that had ever taken place in the imperial war Cabinet. It affected the future relations and the future-efficiency of the Empire He entirely agreed with Sir robert borden that it is quite impossible that the Empire could continue
on the basis of the United Kingdom deciding the policy and theDominions joining in the bill. There were two questions beforethem, one that of the arrangements which could be made duringthe war, which might be tentative and experimental, the other thatof permanent arrangements for the future. With regard to the first,the discussion had ranged round two proposals. The least important of the two, though by no means insignificant, was the proposal thatthe Dominion Prime Ministers should have- the right to corresponddirectly with their opposite number in the United Kingdom. Thatright was not challenged, and he did not see how it could be challenged. Since the war there had been a new method of com-munication between the Allied Governments of Europe, namely,that between the Heads of Governments directly as regards theconduct of the war. He recognised no limit of his right to correspond with M. Clemenceau or M. Orlando, and had in factcorresponded regularly both with the two Prime Ministers referredto and with M. Clemenceaus predecessors, M. Painleve and M. Ribot.The men who had the supreme responsibility had not only a rightbut a duty tc communicate with each other, and the more closelythey kept in touch the better.. As far as method was concerned,these communications sometimes went through the Foreign Office,sometimes through the French Embassy, at other times by directmessengers. The subject-matter of these communications referredeven more often to War Office questions than to Foreign Officequestions. In each case he communicated them at once to theDepartments concerned. Surely the same principle must apply tothe Dominions, both as regards the conduct of the war and also in reference to questions of peace. There should be the freestcommunication between those who were in supreme charge of thedestinies of the Dominions and the Prime Minister of this country.He agreed that, as the Secretary of State for the Colonies had said, there had existed a sort of feeling that such directcommunication might interfere with the susceptibilities of the governors-General or of the Colonial Office. He thought itshould be clearly understood that there should be the samecommunication between the Prime Ministers of the Empire asbetween the Prime Ministers of the Alliance. He then read to theImperial War Cabinet the following Resolution : (1.) The Prime Ministers of the Dominions, as members of theImperial War Cabinet, have the right of direct com-munication with the Prime Minister of the UnitedKingdom and vice versa.(2.) Such communications should be confined to questions ofCabinet importance. The Prime Ministers themselves are the judges of such questions.(3.) Telegraphic communications between the Prime ministers should, as a rule, be conducted through the ColonialOffice machinery, but this will not exclude the adoptionof more direct means of communication in exceptional circumstances.The second and more important proposal was that dealing withthe machinery for consultation during the war. He agreed as to theincompleteness of the present arrangements. The Imperial WarCabinet had made a marked and very distinct advance in Imperialco-operation and consultation. But it was incomplete. In theprevious year it had met for two months and discussed very vitalquestions. But for his own part he would have preferred it to have met in the autumn because some most important questions arosethen, such as the offensive in Flanders, which had the mostimportant consequences for every part of the Empire, with regardto which he should like to have had the views of the Dominion[530-13] D
Prime Ministers. Subsequently there had been various semi-officialadvances with regard to peace, and again the great question of unity of command. All these matters were vital, and there had been nomeans of communicating with regard to them. He asked them to contemplate what might happen when they now dispersed. Whenthe German offensive had finally failed, the Germans would come forward with proposals which might conceivably be worthconsideration. He was quite clear that the Dominions should be consulted as to the steps to be taken in that case. Then, again, theDominions would be vitally affected by the decision of next year&apos;campaing. There wrere many other points of first-class importancewith regard to which it would be a great strength to the BritishGovernment to have the views of the Dominions. He did not thinkthat the Imperial War Cabinet should separate on this occasionwithout deciding to adopt some measure by which it might bepossible to secure continuous consultation. 1 The suggestion hadbeen made that the Dominions should appoint a Minister who couldexpress their views, and who would he available to attend meetingsof the Imperial War Cabinet.. Those might take place once a week or once a fortnight, or more often if pressure of business demandedit. He considered that this suggestion would enable the sittings ofthe Imperial War Cabinet to be continuous, and would thus providea means of consultation on the most important questions of common interest.As regards the wider question of the permanent machinery ofImperial organisation, he agreed with Mr. Churchill that it wouldbe easier to set up some machinery during the war than after. that had been the experience of the German Empire, - which had been set up in the heat and warmth of a great victory. He feared thatafter the war we should all be so much absorbed with the needs of reconstruction in industry, in finance, and with regard to labour that he almost doubted our ability to concentrate on the question ofImperial co-operation. He would therefore strongly deprecate thesuggestion that the constitution of the permanent machinery shouldbe postponed until after the war. So much had been achieved formankind, through the assistance of the British Empire, that it wouldbe a disaster for humanity, as a whole, if the Empire fell to piecesafter the war. He would therefore suggest that steps should betaken now, not indeed to set up machinery, but for the carefulconsideration of this question of machinery, so that when theImperial War Cabinet met again in the following year, or before,they would have available the judgment of the men whom they haddeputed to investigate and study the subject. He invited themembers of the Imperial War Cabinet to think out the best methodof investigating the problem. It might be possible to set up aCommittee of men of knowledge and experience, who, with the guidance of high authorities on constitutional questions, might go into the matter at leisure, and produce a report in time to send it out to the Dominions before the Prime Ministers came back for thenext session.Mr. Hughes considered that the Prime Ministers first suggestion as to direct communication was most satisfactory, and would serve.With regard to the second suggestion, he thought the weak pointof the proposal was that no one could speak with final authorityexcept the Prime Ministers. Other Ministers could only representthe Prime Ministers. He therefore urged that, in any case, beforethe Prime Ministers separated on the present occasion they should arrive at a clear basis with regard to the attitude of the imperial war Cabinet towards peace terms and the general conduct ofthe war.With regard to the third suggestion, he considered that if aCommittee were set up in this country to discuss and devise ascheme of Imperial Federation, Australia would not have anything to do with it.
The Prime Minister pointed out that his suggestion did not imply a scheme of Imperial Federation, but only the considerationof the machinery for conducting the business of the Empire infuture.Mr. Hughes suggested that xAustralia had not been prepared toadopt its own constitution without a referendum!, and would besuspicious of any body that proposed to discuss the future consti-tution of the Empire. It would at once be said that AustrahVsfreedom was being bartered away. He doubted whether, from theAustralian point of view at any rate, this was the best time fordealing with the matter. A plebiscite of the Australian soldiers atthe front at this moment would be overwhelming against such aproposal. He had discussed the matter in all the Governments ofwhich he had been a member in Australia. He agreed that thepresent position was impossible and rotten. He thought that theview of the Australian people would be that, if Australian represen-tatives were sent to a Council of Empire, they would be entangledand doubly committed if a war broke out, and that the last state would, in fact, be worse than the first.Sir Robert Borden admitted that a similar view was also held incertain sections in Canada. Sir W. Laurier had always taken upthat attitude. He himself had disagreed. He would himself soonergo out of the Empire altogether than adopt this attitude. If hestayed in the Empire it was on condition that he had a voice in theconduct of its affairs.Mr. Hughes agreed with that point of view, but asked the PrimeMinister to re-state his idea.The Prime Minister 6aid that what he had in his mind was onlya committee to investigate the machinery for carrying on the businessof the Empire after the war. There were such questions as foreigntreaties, the co-operation of the different armies and navies of theEmpire, with regard to which he considered that a committee might now be set up to investigate and report to the Imperial War Cabinetin time for the Dominion Prime Ministers to receive it before they came to the next meeting.Mr. Hughes did not consider the case for the proposed Com-mittee had been satisfactorily made out. The Australian Govern -ment could always consult the Admiralty or the War Office. Asregards treaties, at any rate commercial treaties, they were onlybound after they had assented to them. He wished to make it clearthat he was not expressing his personal opinions, but those ofAustralia. He thought that if the proposal were made public itwould cause trouble in Australia, where there was only a narrowspan between those who stood for the Empire and those whowere in favour of disruption.General Smuts thought there was nothing in the PrimeMinisters proposal which was not really implied in the second partof Mr. Hughes&apos; own resolution. He agreed, however, that theannouncement of a Committee sitting to study the constitution ofthe Empire would not only have a bad effect in Australia, but else-where.&quot; In his opinion the third proposal could best be regarded inthe light of the proposal, made with regard to Imperial representa-tion. He suggested that the Dominion Ministers who were left torepresent their Governments in this country could join with othermembers of the War Cabinet informally, without constituting a formal Committee, announced to the world as such, and thresh outthose problems at leisure.Sir Robert Borden saw no difficulty in the suggestion withregard to resident Ministers. Canada had already a Minister inthis country, and could either extend his powers, or, if necessary,appoint another. As far as the third proposal made by the PrimeMinister went, he did not think it desirable to set up a formalCommittee. Such a step might be misconstrued in Canada, wherethere was general satisfaction with the resolution passed at the
Imperial War Conference last year. Nevertheless, there was a great advantage in doing something in the meantime and making prepara-tions for the Constitutional Conference contemplated by that resolu-tion. Unless there was proper preparation there could be no good results. He thought the question should be taken into furtherconsideration.(The discussion was adjourned until Tuesday, 30th July.)2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 25, 1918.o

</content>
</cab>
