<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/4/0 images: 4-4</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 16 (46) 18th February, 1946

1. Free Rice from Siam

E.B. Appeals to U.S. etc. Dipl. diffy. if can be said we are holdg. up on free rice. We shd. yield our claim – on basis supplies to India will be paid for &amp; not v. our sterl. balance posn.

H.D. Agree on condn tht. we don’t pay Fr. Exchequer.

G.H. But Ceylon &amp; Malaya need it - &amp; can’t pay.

E.B. This must be handled in usual way.

P.M. Point doesn’t arise in Colonies.

H.D. Let me discuss this with C.O. No notice of this.

P.M. Discussed often – plenty of notice.

R.S.C. Ceylon has sterling balances.

P.M. When they can pay they must – Fr. sterling balances or other sources. i.e. wherever there is sterling balance the cost comes out of that.

Agreed.

2. Special Commissioner for S.E. Asia: Staff.

E.B. Want to know to-day whr Sanderson can go from M/F – also transport expert. Want R.S.C. to agree to release Empson.

Must get a good staff - essential to pull this together in S.E.A. Food problem first: then political basis.

R.S.C. Empson – commercial treaty negotns.

E.B. Will you discuss with Killearn?

R.S.C. Yes.

P.M. Come to me if any diffy. over staff.

3. Poland: Polish Troops

E.B. V’s. lr. (fr. Yugoslavia) was put in w’out consultn with Poles.

Am asking Tito why he didn’t take it up with us thro’ dept. channels. Rubbing it in.

22

P.M. When is Anders coming?

E.B. Not until U.N.O. over. Wd. like him to come on Friday – to discuss on original basis i.e. ignore Polish. Note for this purpose.

4. Levant Status.

E.B. Diffy. was with de G. When he went, I suggd transferring discns to Ldn. or Paris. Nearly settled it at F.O. but Syrians ran out.

In S. Council discns much use of “exclusively” – to restrict negotns to w’drawal of troops. Trade, schools, food etc., have also to be discussed &amp; I had to dissent.

Thought V. wd. veto if defeated. There were 7 in favour &amp; he had to veto. Had asked Bidault to be generous. Thgt. it a good precedent to get countries to act in spite of veto. Got it that way. Had effect of isolatg. Russians.

This, however, emerges.

a) Greece: R. was accuser &amp; cd. nevertheless use his veto to frustrate views of majority. This is a nonsense.

b) Gathered here (Cab.) after S. Fran. tht. veto wd. be used only at extreme point. eg. on sanctions. Now seems it can be used all the time.

c) State can put on Agenda ques. not affectg. it, tho’ State concerned does not bring it fwd. Then veto decision on it!

Procdgs. at this Session shd. be reviewed - to see where we stand on this.

Surplus troops will be comg. out of Levant at once?

C.I.G.S. Yes

E.B. Can reduce cost there at once. Fr. want transport to help them to move out.

[Enter Wilmot

5. Defence Policy in 1946

P.M. Have examd estimates. Imposed heavy cuts. This is far as we can reduce this year. Debate on Def. generally: then Votes on A/C of Sev. Dpts.: detailed Est. after Easter.

Mtg. of Dom. P.M.’s. Altern of text requd because date not fixed.

Can’t stand this mil. expn for long.

R.S.C. How does this figure relate to that anticipated for Loan discns.

H.D. Higher.

Much concerned qua Budget burdens. Prosp. deficit next year.

But ever more concerned qua drain on f. exchange.

Net payout £1.091.M. Total £1.667M. But £576M = terminal.

23

Grateful for redn: but still heavy. If things go wrong, may have to face Supplies. This is over double the £500M of Coaln Govt. estimates for p. war.

E.B. After 3 years.

H.D. Yes: but tht. – target to wh. we are workg.

P.M. We’ve made big assumptns viz. out of Greece, Italy &amp; Indonesia. All pretty optimistic. Unlikely we’ll do the work.

A.B. Any comparison with U.S., Russia &amp; Fr. – on basis of popn figures. viz. what wd. their expendre be if they had Forces on same scale as ours in reltn to popn.

A.V.A. 2.6 in R. forces in Foreign countries – on basis of repts. on their Elections. Don’t know much re rest of Forces.

Nervous of para. 4(a)(iii) – Fr. my informn.

E.Sh. R. occupn troops can live on the country.

Can we say how far our troops live on sterling rather than dollar sources?

H.D. Not v. easily.

E.Sh. Wd. help to give the picture. Need = reduce the dollar expre of Forces.

H.D. Our mil. expre in G. is partly to fund Germans.

E.Sh. Believe we’re spendg. too much on that. And on people who are going to bite us.

P.M. If A.B. means we are doing more than our share, its true. Can. doing no more. Aust., &amp; N.Z. doing v. little.

E.Sh. What is it costg. us to maintain order in G? Shd. we not getting somethg. out of it?

P.M. Must discuss this separately and later. We have accepted oblign of occupying Germany.

P.L. I agreed on understandg. tht. if need arises troops will be available in India.

Understand some reserves will be available shortly.

E.W. Is B.A.O.R. paying sufft. attn to U.K. needs – caring too much for Germans.

J.J.L. B.A.O.R. is running down v. quickly because no. of veterans in it. The Nazis are m’while pulling themselves together.

E.W. Reduce mil. strengths &amp; build up Soc. Dem. Forces.

24

P.M. They were crushed - &amp; can’t be revived as soon as that.

A.B. Danger of re-action in U.K.

E.B. Much more if you allowed Nazidom to revive.

H.M. Worried over time factor. How long? No indication of any move twds. a solution.

E.B. Earlier assumptn 10 yrs. occupn. Think that too long. But experce after last war shows risk of makg. it too short.

Must look at this seriously – not a side issue.

A.B. Must review. R. forced us into imposs. policy of Govt. thro’ Zones.

Now Comm. are workg. to show ridiculous results of that policy.

P.M. Still under Armistice condns. Can’t pull out this year. Haven’t yet settled any Treaty, still less German Treaty.

J. Must do this – but can’t go on for long. £500M shd. be maximum.

E.B. Remember £500M was then prices. Then figures before you are much lower than anyone thgt they’d be in pv year. Assumed it wd. be 3yrs. before we got down to £500M.

P.L. Remember it comes down throught. year. – and at end/46 the expendre will be running at a much lower rate. That wd. make it look better.

H.D. True: but we can’t show it yet because don’t know when or if Indian troubles will arise.

E.B. For policy reasons don’t want to show the run down. Wd. wreck our dipl. influence. Peace Confce in May: Indonesia: Greece: Famine. U.S. now alarmed at rate of their demobiln.

P.M. Draft W.P. sets our posn on V.E. Day, &amp; follows it down. Then first sentence in para. 8. Argument throughout, stresses continuous redn.

H.M. Are our Commis. in field aware of our problems – re balance/payments. Cd. they be discreetly told – to discourage extravagance.

A.V.A. Brght. this to notice of Naval Staffs. That’s why I’ve had their co-opn in gettg. down to figures wh. prev. were thght. impossible.

C.I.G.S. Confce early March with Commis. That is one of items.

P.M. I will send an informal message to Commis. in all Services.

E.W. Mil. Service. When shall we discuss?

P.M. We will, sometime. What is wrong with this interim statement.

25

E.W. Educn authies don’t know how to plan.

P.M. Two alternatives in para. 13. Can’t get long. term decisions yet.

E.B. M.P. Cttee will submit a plan. Can’t do it now.

Recommend alternative wording in [].

P.L. Para. 9 (d) – don’t last words go rather far. Cd. used v. us if instability recurred at any future time.

R.S.C. “Until condns become more settled.”

P.M. Until condns there allow of their w’drawal.:

Agreed.

S. Small amendmt to show air trooping ceases 1/4 . Will inform Cab. Off.

A. Para. 7 as in my copy.

P.M. Add note: remember changes in value of money &amp; ratio of pay in makg. pre. war comparisons.

Para. 12.

Para. 13 } as in my copy

Para. 14 }

G.A.I. Figures.

E.B. We have these.

P.M. First sentence. Why commit ourselves?

Agreed: Omit. Say something else instead.

P.M. Say instead – “From time to time” vice “annually”.

H.M. Para. 17. V. definite. “Would” vice “will” ?

[Exit C.O.S. &amp; Wilmot

A.B. Will you tell H/C you intend investigate organsn of Forces?

P.M. Will flow fr. P.W.D. Cttee, wh. is mentioned &amp; I will refer to it.

6. India: Constitutional Problem

P.M. Handed in draft.

Will add – durg. absence {Admy. P.M.

26

of Ministers { B/T. H.M.

charge of Dpts { India &amp; Burma. Parly. Secy. with ref. to me

{ as necessary.

Appd: announce in these terms Tuesday.

7. Peace Celebrations: Leakage &amp; Announcement

P.M. Take care of leakages. Trouble over Peace Celebrations. Rpt. – all details out. Don’t let’s have similar trouble over Defence: on India.

Peace Celebrations. P.M. announce date: promise to circulate detail.

If H/C presses for detail, Home Secy. can read it out.

8. Government Information Services.

H.M. Title – prefer Central Office or Information – COY for short.

Outlined recommns in memo.

Two Ministerial Cttees: same Chairman for both.

They needn’t meet more than monthly. Below them 2 offl. Cttees. Pro-term overseas Cttee under Chairmanship of Hector McNeil.

Need for P.R.O.’s to attend &amp; express views at Dpl. conferences.

Ques. at issue still.

a) Ministerial responsibility. Believe H/C. will worry out who is Chairman of Cttee. Better therefore to announce it at outset.

Agreed.

R.S.C. Cd. the Ministerial Cttees be at Parly. Secy. level? I cdn’t come.

H.D. Supported. Agreed: normally delegate this to Parly. Secretaries.

A.B. Want to be one.

A.V.A. One Service Dpt.

E.W. I want my Parly. Secy.

P.M. Nucleus + those running publicity at the time. Composn can be settled by P.M. in consultn with Chairman.

A. a) P.R.O.’s How are they to be recruited? Shdn’t be fr. Dpt. staffs.

H.M. Agree: then shd. be an interchange also with C.O.I.

A. b) Chairmanship of (overseas) Offl. Cttee shdn’t be made public. Doms.

wdn’t like nomn of McNeil – tho’ I think he is excellent.

T.W. Can we see all the pp.

G.A.I. Wd. like to be on Offl. overseas Cttee.

27

E.B. I.L.O. etc., is in favour.

E.Sh. We do some advertising but get no priority because don’t do enough business. Thro’ M.O.L. we are in hands of experts.

P.M. Take it up thro’ the Cttees.

A.V.A. Will write to P.M. re contracting out.

Agreed: so far i.e. title and total resume on Thursday.

E.B. I promised consultn with B. Council.

H.M. Talk btwn decision (Thursd) &amp; publn. Not before.  

</content>
</cab>
