<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/4/0 images: 6-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 18(46) 25th February, 1946.

1. Egypt.

N.B. Note of protest put in v. action of students. King said – too strong.

We declined to w’draw.

2. Spain.

P.M. Shooting of Garcia etc.

E.W. V. good man – deliberate affront to Engl. and French.

E.Sh. Possibility of collusion betwn. Franco &amp; Salazar. Tho’ we are on

good terms with latter.

O.S. No evidence of it.

N.B. But I believe it.

E.W. Cdn’t we apply some sanctions v. Franco.

P.M. Always told they were on point of throwing him out. But I will

consider with F.O.

A.B. Resurrection of R.C. influence – Pope.

N.B. Sp. Republicans want no action wh. wd. precipitate civil war: or econ.

action wh. wd. hurt common people: or early Left Govt. who

wd. have to face serious food crisis before November.

Gradualness.

E.W. That is appeasement.

A.B. Accept N.B.’s statement: but go on – great spiritual re-inforcemt.

to Rep. forces in Spain if overt signs of U.K. sympathy. We shd. consider (soon) what we can do to assume leadership of Socialist

movements in Europe, esp. in Spain.

3. India.

P.M. Statement H/C. Friday. Things quieter. P.L. has given me draft for

statement to-day.

H.M. Everyone knows things are better. Doubt if you need, unless you

get Ques.

P.L. I shall be asked to make one on Tuesd.

37

P.M. Leave it until then, anyhow. Agreed.

4. Aldershot. Mutiny in Detention Barracks.

J.J.L. Seen A.G. this a.m. Awaitg. fuller rept. ½ doz. brght. down fr.

Northallerton (trouth)

Overpowered N.C.O. &amp; warders &amp; broke loose.

Answerg. P. Notice Ques. today.

Mil. or public enquiry – will decide on basis of full rept.

P.M. Is this isolated or symptomatic of unrest at condns generally in

detentn barracks.

J.J.L. No. of old lags there. Reduced some sentences on deserters. Those

sentenced for more serious crimes want the same.

A.B. Suggd there are men here doing heavy terms for fraternisation.

J.J.L. Not aware of that. Must get full facts. H/C. satisfied with review of

sentences for desertion. But disposed twds. publ. enquiry – to

get across the facts on this.

H.M. Doubtful. W.O. might invite help of H.O. experts.

P.M. Consult me &amp; prs. Cabinet before you decide wtr. or not to have public enquiry.

[Enter C.Jones &amp; McNeil.

5. Future of Trans. Jordan.

C.J. Discns with Emir will start to-morrow. Treaty prepd after consultn with F.O., C.O.S., B/T. &amp; Ty.

Project approved in principle by U.N.O.

Objns – some fr. Zionist organisations.

Treaty of Alliance 25 yrs. No time limit for mil. convention.

Promise of U.K. mil. aid in return for compreh. mil. facilities.

Commercial treaty to be discussed later on.

Outstandg. claim by Saudi Arabia. But area covered in mandate.

Propose to leave that to transns betwn. T. Jordan &amp; Ibn Saud.

McN. Our points have bn. met.

H.D. Total charges. £2.200.000 = present cost. of wh. £200.000 =

balancg. their budget. That will be no longer a charge on us.

Favour this plan because it will reduce our commitments in future.

C.O. will consult with Ty. to secure further economies.

T. Jordan to be used as traing. grd. for B. troops. May we assume

corresp. economies in Egypt.

J.J.L. Cl. 8 places addl. burden on B. Army unless we get relief in Egypt.

38

H.M. We surrender a mandate – but we take on a good deal in the way of

additional burdens.

A.B. How does x/ in para. 3. agree with U.N.O. obligns?

C.J. Art. 11.

Articles 3 &amp; 4 follow Iraq Treaty, on terminn of mandate.

N.B. All these mil. arrangemts. in M/E. are re. insurance v. possible

failure of U.N.O. Similar arrangemts. with Iraq were useful

in the war.

E.Sh. Have we ever asked what is our interest in M/E. and what will it

cost? Why don’t we look at it as a whole?

Real ques: do we really believe U.N.O. will produce protn for our

special interest.

R.S.C. Insert “and with the U.N.O.” in Art. 3.?

H.M. Then you will bring in the Sec. Council every time.

N.B. You cdn’t have mil. opns going on w’out intervention by U.N.O.

E.Sh. Doesn’t that ask Russia into M/East. What do we want?

H.M. Then why accept a unilateral burden under Art. 4.?

S. a) Have we the right to station troops in T.J. – under Arts. 1-2.

C.J. C.O.S. points have bn. embodied in this draft.

{ Re-consider Arts. 3. &amp; 4. in light of discussion: and bring

{ up again on Thursday – m’while keeping Emir in play.

[Exit C.Jones. D. Sargent.

Enter Barnes.

6. Shipping. United Maritime Board.

B. Got 6 mos’ extension of present arrangemts. – incldg. our

3 m. tons on charter fr. U.S.A.

Want authy., when publishg. our ratification, to do so v. background

of our policy as presented by B. Delegn.

P.M. Contns to UNRRA.

B. There is escape clause. But we want to do our best, qua prestige.

P.M. Can’t we get more U.S. tonnage on better terms?

H.D. My advisers think M/W.T. have done pretty well. Better to charter

39

than buy &amp; we have checked U.S. proposals for flag-discrimn

&amp; subsidies.

Ask, however, for revised M/W.T. estimate on b/payments posn – to

go to workg. party. i.e. revised in light of this agreement.

R.S.C. Limn of liner sailings. Can’t we expand?

B. No: for 6 months. But we cdn’t anyway. And review in June.

H.M. Agree tht. thereafter we shd. resume freedom of action.

E.Sh. Length of charter?

B. Review in June

H.M. Will B. consult his colleagues v re-constitn of U.N.O.

N.B. Para. 2(3). Reln betwn. this and U.N.O. system.

Agreed. [Exit N.B.

7. Ship-building Industry.

A.V.A. As in memo.

E.B. has told me he thinks seamen shd. be repd on Adv. Cttee. To

join in any discn there re accommn and also defence of m/ships

in war.

The owners feel strongly they shd. not be repd because not concerned.

These matters shd. be handled thro’ Ministers repres.

P.M. a) Official vice unofficial Chairman? Prs. fr. outside both Dpts.

Suspicion.

A.V.A. We want a man of prodn experience – not fr. shipbldg. industry. And

wd. consult P.M.

B. Don’t want Civil Servant.

A.V.A. Have consulted R.S.C. – who suggd someone who had bn. tempy.

Civil Servant in war.

P.M. Indicated grudging agreement.

P.M. b) T of r. imply advice fr. industry to Govt. Won’t Govt. advise

the industry?

A.V.A. Will do so thro’ Govt. repres.

H.M. Omit refce to “H.M.G.”

40

R.S.C. Must advise someone who will initiate action. Wd. have thought it

was the 2 Ministers to act.

R.S.C. c) Para. 4 of t. of r. “Industrial relns” - fear it may cut across

wages disputes.

G.A.I. Have examd this: &amp; satisfied as now drafted. No implicn tht. they

will settle.

E.Sh. d) Repn of sailors’ &amp; offrs. unions. Feel v. strongly in favour. No

harm &amp; some good. A. &amp; A.B. agreed. Those who have to live

in the ships have an interest in design.

B. Familiar problem – keep Cttee on efficient basis. Object of this =

develop efficiency of shipyards. Seaman’s pt/view can be

represented thro’ Govt. repres. Discussed fully with A.V.A. –

I will appoint shipping repres. I shan’t appoint owners in

narrow sense. Will see that I include someone who can spk. for

the men. Otherwise we shall get commd to repres of organn of

users of ships.

H.M. L.P. Cttee – general view was that seamen shd. be represented.

I can see tht. B. wants to be general. Say repres of shipping, both

employers &amp; employed.

A.V.A. Shipbldg. – both sides – wd. prefer not to have shipping in on Cttee

concerned mainly with efficiency of the yards.

E.Sh. The users must surely be on. You can select. Then how can you

exclude someone who can speak for the men. Don’t mean you

must have repres of organisations.

A.B. Can’t have owners w’out men.

B. Wd. prefer to exclude ship-owners. And build up separate

machinery for getting views of shipping (both sides).

P.M. If you bring in owners you must bring in seamen.

Consider now wtr. it is better to leave out all shipping.

B. If you have this composn as in memo. I will nominate persons from

Shipping who include someone who speaks for seamen.

P.M. Repres of Shipping includg. repres of the merchant service. On p.5 of

memo.

B. That isn’t far off what I intended.

A.V.A. Must discuss again with shipbldg interests.

E.Sh. e) Labour force to drop to 90.000. Bear in mind posn of

41

developmt. areas.

Don’t p’mme too much in e.g. So’ton where redundant

labour cd. be absorbed elsewhere.

A.V.A. Must consider dockyard towns also.

P.M. Cttee to work out stabilisation policy – in place &amp; time.

H.M. Read L.P. records on this point. Relation to emplt. policy.

Repeat in Cab. records.

Steering Cttee can guide this. H.D. Agreed.

8. Future Use of Queen Elizabeth.

H.M. Reported discussions on L.P. Cttee.

P.M. But already announced – e.g. in Sunday Times. Prob. by owners.

B. Will enquire into this.

J.J.L. Unfortunate – reactions on Services. S. Agreed.

P.M. How will she be re-converted – luxury etc.?

H.D. Dollar-earning capacity. The richer the Americans are who come here,

the better.

B. This is matter for co. who will run the ship.

P.M. No: we are concerned.

A.B. Outrage r. feelings of S’ton, so short of houses.

A.V.A. The real ques. is: which class of passenger was most profitable, on

basis of owners’ past experience? Are you going to use space for

shops etc.

A. More dollars from the multitude than the millionaires.

A.B. If you interfere with design will you under-write it?

If you allow owners to please themselves, there will be Parly. trouble.

H.M. It’s a ques. which pays best. We must be competitive in Atlantic.

Can we settle every commercial ques. on basis of national scarcities.

B. Must decide at once wtr. to take her off trooping.

42

A.V.A. What class of passengers – can be handled later.

H.D. Decide to take her off and refit.

Let M/W.T. get the informn about method &amp; style of re-fitting.

Announce quickly because of leak at week-end.

H.M. The P.M.’s point only affects publicity.

Take her off the run: Cab. approval to type of refit.

[Exit Barnes.

Enter W.W. G.I. Hall.

9. Select Committee on Elections.

H.M. As in memo.

General legn in this Parlt. And say so.

J. Ready for L.P. Cttee in 3 wks or so.

10. Parliamentary Procedure. Second report of Select Committee.

H.M. P.Q.’s. Para. 6 (c) approved.

Writters Para. 8.

H.D. Most Dpts. are well w’in the new rule already.

A.B. Remember tht. Regionalisation slows up colln of informn. Quicker

executive action outweighs speed of central reply.

H.M. Corrce. P.M. is considerg. Think we shd. accept in principle

P.M. lrs. went right up the hierarchy. Cdn’t they go direct from

Principals.

P.M. Read out letter – brief from E.E.B.

Don’t commit yourself to acceptance. Particularly, Service Dpts.

Tell M.P.’s tht. they will attract more work to themselves if they

insist on high priority.

A.G. 650 lrs. to M/N.I. on his Bill in 3 wks. 90% of these cd. have bn.

answered by the Member. 

</content>
</cab>
