<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/4/0 images: 53-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 67 (46) 11th July, 1946

1. Agricultural Prices. [Enter J.S.

J.W. Agree. Shall have diffies on para. 16 but I accept need for wheat incentives.

C.E. Agree qua

T.W. Tried to avoid automatic increase. Tried to provide inducement for things we know we need most. Consulted Ty &amp; M/F who agree these are best prices.

N. Ireland.

A.V.A. Where will this policy take us? This is now a direct subsidy of wages which

the industry cdn’t pay. A v. awkward precedent for coal, steel etc. V.

dubious policy.

If you knocked out those who employd none &amp; those who cd. afford to

pay more the residue wd. be small.

T.W. Estimate is based on hired labour. (15 ½ M) exlcudg. f. &amp; wife (wh. wd.

have put it to (£25M). This means tht. big farmer will get only 75% of

increased cost. He gets less out of this than anyone.

Acreage paymts only for wheat, sugar &amp; potatoes. Wdn’t cover milk prodn.

b)

H.D. Not enthusiastic. Only £2M p.a. margin between these prices &amp; automatic recoupment, which latter I must continue to resist in principle.

Have made some cuts: &amp; tho’ I don’t like it I don’t now contest it.

R.S.C. I’m concerned fr. same sort of angle. In our price-fixing we have bn. at pains to avoid the automatic principle: &amp; insisted tht. greater efficiency must carry wage increase. Wd. sooner see an acreage subsidy than this. Then it wd. become poss. to vary the grant with quality of soil - &amp; meet “marginal problem”. But what we are doing here is to follow the wage-price spiral.

P.M. The marginal product was the argument for higher prices – but he doesn’t employ labour. Always assumed tht. larger farmer cd. afford his labour costs.

Under these prices the man who will do best is the man who employs none.

Trying for months to get a solution of “marginal” problem.

Our problem = spread increased costs over whole field

a) to recoup in part

to provide incentives. Cdn’t do that by acreage payments.

Re A.V.A. argument, I recognise the danger: &amp; put memo. on it when wage increase was asked for. Repeat this warning – repeated increases in agric. prices will start the spiral. But at this moment, when we want the food &amp; the man-power, we must take an exceptional step. Must make the best of a v. bad situation.

283

R.S.C. Agree you can’t do all by acreage paymt. But £3M. (App A) &amp; £7M (App C) represent wheat, potatoes &amp; sugar; &amp; if you handled them by acreage method it wd. take large slice out of the price rise. Surely it wd. help, even tho’ milk etc., has to be done by price increase.

T.W. Want wheat grown when biggest yield. Price is better incentive for big yields, &amp; choice of better crop. Acreage paymt. wd. tend to get wheat grown on land when barley wd. give a better yield.

E.Sh. Remember tht. the wage increase has bn. given – with official Govt. encouragemt. however we concealed it.

Wage policy = skeleton at feast. Lived with it for 12 months now &amp; it will get worse. And we always shelve it. Ind. Council won’t really do. We shall have to tell Unions they can’t have increases.

Prices are rising &amp; there is inflation.

H.D. Give us facts not fancies.

E.Sh. Must face whole economic set-up which is creating this situation.

P.M. Back to mutton. Why can’t you combine price &amp; acreage payment.

T.W. Already makg. acreage paymt. for the 3 commodities: &amp; our experts think

this increase shd. be made on price item in the composite payment.

Need system wh. will increase efficiency.

a) man who doesn’t employ – largely milk, who will get an

advantage: but first don’t often grow wheat or pots.

The acr. p. has special virtue when aiming at maximum. But expedient only for period you want more than normal prodn. When you are shading off marginal prodn, begin with shedding acreage p.

A. My view is contrary to R.S.C. Acr. p. encourages prodn on uneconomic land: induces farmers to use land to worst advantage. Want it reduced not extended.

But must remember

b) national emergency. This is main justification. That is why I wd. have put an even greater emphasis on wheat vice barley.

c) We are makg. livestock producers kill their stock. Destroying their capital stock. That is a reason for extra assistance.

I wd. therefore represent these prices as exceptional, due to b) &amp; c). Don’t

tie it up to labour costs.

Wheat/barley differenn: satisf. if Can. wheat crop is good. This is promised

tho’ not actual. Take note, however, tht. if Can. crop failed in next

month, then Cab. shd. consider ratio of wheat/barley prices in U.K. so

This is well below farmers’ demand. Needn’t therefore be related to wage increases.

J.S. Want max. prodn in U.K. &amp; can’t therefore avoid supporting these proposals. Duty on this country, as others, to maximise prodn even in uneconomic way. 284

as to encourage greater sowing of wheat in autumn. &amp; greater extractn

of barley fr. animal feeding fr. 1946 crop. Pity we are fixing this 6 wks

to soon.

R.S.C. Repeated acr. p. argument.

H.M. Supported A. Price = better incentive to big yield. prefer to put weight on

that. Remember we are running price control: w’out it a lot of these

prices wd. soar.

Memo approved.

A.V.A. Land increment values. Higher prices for agric. land. Is Ty. looking at this

in reln to subsidies wh. are being paid.

Don’t forget the advantages.

Recommend agreement.

T.W. T.C.P. Bill + my new Bill shd. take the edge off speculn.

[Enter W.W.

[Exit T.W.

2. Parliament. 3. Palestine.

H.M. Business for next week.

[Exit W.W.

[Enter N.B. C.O.S.

P.M. Statement rejected. Harriman asked for something. Issued statemt. re forthcoming consultn.

Memoranda circulated.

a) Situation in Palestine

Interview between Weizmann &amp; Ch. Secretary – in telegr. circulated.

Shows W. says we didn’t know of Palmar organn until present visit to

Pal. Yet this known to most people for ¾ yrs. Want Cab. views on

suggn for release of Agency Members.

Intercept betwn. leader of Hagana &amp; Ben Gurion. – indicates cleft &amp; asks B.

Gurion for guidance.

Bldg. handed back y’day. Damage assessed £P.137.

G.H. Mil. searches ceased. Search for leaders only procd. Not yet announced. Have asked H.C. to consider doing so, after consultn with C-in-C.

285

2 Zionists now on their way to U.K. &amp; Weizmann soon to come too. Joint Anglo. U.S. discns may be advanced by them &amp; convenient to discuss.

P.M. Why not invite &amp; say so – to strengthen hand of moderates.

What of other members of Executive? G.H. 50% of leaders of Agency arrested &amp; still detained.

P.M. Mustn’t let situation run on too long.

P.M. F.O. shd. take strong line in Bucharest.

P.M. Put pressure on Agency people to stop the flow.

N.B. There is a Cttee mtg. in Paris. Get them over here.

G.H. Wise &amp; Liboki coming here

G.H. Some are acting with W. Others detained: on a/c of evce collected. H.C. also wants guarantees fr. those with whom he is treating before he releases these men.

P.M. J. to attend mtg. this p.m. on examn of evidence collected in search.

C.I.G.S. Must let wasps settle. But further action: plans to eliminate Irgun, Stern &amp; later Talmac.

G.H. Illegal immigrants. Now 2.500 in detention. Fills quotas to mid/Sept.

Ship with capacity for 2.000 arrived at Constanza. F.O. asked to enquire. C.O.S. proposing again diversion of these ships to Cyprus. May precipitate diffies in Cyprus as well as Palestine. Risk of another Patria. We therefore feel tht. at this stage it wd. be too dangerous to divert to Cyprus.

N.B. What can we say, unless they are Romanian Jews.

G.H. Only W. is coming. Wd. you want me to get a negotiating Cttee over? , not Paris, we thought.

P.M. Discussions re immediate situation in Palestine. To avoid Arab resentment.

Make that clear: otherwise trouble.

G.H. W. understands that. Shaw’s telegram.

Cd. we divert proposed J.A. mtg. in Paris to Ldn? Trouble: B. Gurion is “wanted” by H.C.

N.B. Better have it in Paris.

W’ton wanted some publn of evce before end of Loan discussions.

P.M. Not prepd to give anything before given to H/C. And want careful scrutiny.

Will do what I can this p.m. 286

H.D. Advices re Loan are favourable now. Don’t rush it.

b) Long-term Situation G.H. Boundaries on populn basis. Gave figures from memo.

G.H. Land laws to prevent it: under Arab Province Control.

Brook: Report on discns with E.B.

P.M. G.H. memo represents restns to offls. to speak wholly v. report of Anglo. U.S. Report. Wd. rather let the offls. put fwd. constructive plan as in G.H.’s second memo.

H.D. Shift ground of debate. Rpt. is a bad one. Can we not move twds. E.B.’s long-term solution. Indep. Jewish State: &amp; Arab territory added to adjacent Arab countries. H’to opposed Partition: but mind is moving twds. Partition. Then you cd. say let the 100,000 go in: &amp; the Agency pay. If we have Partition in mind, why not take it into a/c at once in Anglo.U.S. discns. Disadvantages of G.H. plan: still have mandatory responsib.: finance: strategic needs via Treaty with Arab States.

P.M. Much history in this. Palestine boundaries v. diff. Value of interim scheme: can separate sovereignty &amp; cultural autonomy. Avoids diffy. of tariffs, customs etc.

J. Gt. diffies over boundaries. Wd. involve immed. relinquishment of mandate &amp; thus discns in U.N. Under G.H. you buy time &amp; get boundaries accepted with less diffy.

R.S.C. Cantonisation is best route to Partition. With central adminn boundaries much easier. Eventual solution can then develop. Prov. boundies can be adjusted: national can’t.

P.M. This wd. solve the immigration problem.

P.L. What power to prevent Jews spilling into Arab Province?

E.Sh. Don’t rule out possibility tht. when we can remove econ. Diffies there may be some accommn betwn. J. &amp; A. No short-term solution. Don’t adopt merely negative attitude in discns.

For strategic reasons (C.O.S. memo) Partition as such must be ruled out.

Provincial soln unwise – semi-autonomous Regions to be preferred.

Assistce to Arabs (econ. standards) is essential.

Don’t accept Zionist view. But must do somethg. for Jews in other countries.

287

Most who want to go to Pal. want to go there for economic reasons. Must try to get other countries to treat them reasonably. Jews in C. Europe wd. still be a problem, even if Pal. solved.

P.M. shd. have disns with W. Still has influence. Want breathing space before tackling long-term problem. The 100,000 cdn’t go at once: step up existg. quota: discuss that with Arabs.

P.M. Face up to U.S. offls. to Rec. 1. at once.

Wider issues. Diffies in early

J.S. From angle of U.S. negotiations, must face the fact tht. if we refuse or appear to dodge recommn 2 nothing else will have any effect on U.S. opinion.

P.M. Re-actions of Arabs.

J.J.L. Remind U.S. of our Polcs.

N.B. La Guardia is proposing admission of 120,000 into U.S. He &amp; S. Bloom will have chance of getting this thro’ at U.N.

Hope I may be encouraged to support him in this. Partition. prefer G.H.’s plan. But if we put it

fwd. as alternative to Anglo. U.S. Rpt., we may be in diffy. Have

promised to take it as basis of discussion. Mustn’t start like that. This

finds weakness – viz. Rec. 3 &amp; 6. Put it in under Rec. 3.

Views of C.O.S?

J.

P.M. Put firm line on Rec.1. Plus: we haven’t accepted Hitler’s policy of expelling Jews fr. Europe.

Then Rec. 2

Then under Rec 3. What practical prospects? Inject alternative.

C.A.S. Strategic considns apply whatever the solution.

Our strat. needs (commns &amp; oil) in M.E. depend on retaing. good will &amp; co-opn of Arabs. U.S. becoming increasingly interested in M/E oil.

H.D. C.O.S. apprecn of how their needs cd. best be met – under 3 alternatives, incldg. Partition.

Transfer of Arab popn. Hope G.B. won’t have to pay.

N.B. Many won’t want to go. Some cd. however be absorbed in Lowdermilk Jordan Valley scheme wh. wd. pay for itself.

P.M. Not much in favour of G.B.’s long-term idea. 

</content>
</cab>
