<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/4/0 images: 65-65</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 86(46). 15th October, 1946.

1. U.S. and Canadian Dry Cargo Shipping.

B. Dilemma: U.S. Govt. may be forced to w’draw ships on

chartering 1 m. fr. Canada &amp; 2.8 fr. U.S.A. plus voyage

chartering 50/60 U.S. ships.

so as to sweeten U.S. to continue chartering remainder.

charter (3 m. tons to us).

Deficiency: 4-5 m. tons due to war: bridged by b.b.

Ask therefore for authy to purchase 75 U.S. ships (750.000 t) –

75 Liberty ships cd. be re-sold to U.S. (? Br.) owners hereafter.

Later ques: shall we be forced to buy the ships we voyage-

charter? Effects on B. ship bldg. We are aiming at

stabilising it at 90.000 men over 10 years. If we’re forced to

buy the extra 50/60 ships it will depress B. bldg.

Shan’t therefore consider that unless forced to it. Want authy

then to assure builders &amp; owners tht. they will be taken off

market after 4/5 years if they then threaten B. bldg.

Finance not serious factor – represents what we wd. pay in hire over

3 years.

P.M. All based on assumptns re import/export p’mmes. Any allowance

made for revival of carrying trade? H.D. Procedure – brght up as isolated case: not thro’ Exchange Requiremts.

Cttee. tho’ they were asked to do so. Will M/T. chase his

cost will write off in 2 yrs. &amp; ships will last longer.

H.M. Hurcomb shd. not be hustled by U.S. into buying more than U.K.

needs.

G.H. Concerned only with effect on B. bldg. Hope M/T. will keep in touch

effects on future bldg.

B. Our bldg. p’mme wd. meet that. Fear it mayn’t materialise.

officials?

But on merits a) we must buy the 75 ships on private account. Dollar

b) we must have 35 Baltic coasters.

c) addl. purchases of Govt a/c: I can’t agree yet

because data not supplied to Ty.

B. Don’t need decision on c) now, but thought it right to inform Cabinet.

with Shipbldg. Advisory Cttee on this because t. of r. include

A.B. Abnormal rates of freight shown by these calculns re capital cost

written off in 2 yrs. Timber prices to be raised because freight

rates. Shdn’t whole ques. of freights be examined?

347

B. That’s why we may have to buy c). But if we do, we damage B. bldg.

P.M. Let M/T. put in a memo. on freight rates.

E.Sh. Memo. based on assumptn tht. U.S. &amp; Canada will demand re-delivery.

B. My own impression fr. U.S. Govt.

so regard it. They will then ask us for scrap &amp; build policy.

rates.

{ revival of carrying trade.

[Exit Barnes &amp; Hall. Enter Wilson.

2. International Commodity Policy.

G.A.I. Para. 12. B. bldg. replacing obsolete ships. Avoid shortage of work in

our yards at time of next election.

What evidce?

E.Sh. Cab. considered purchase before &amp; were against it. Aren’t U.S.

pushing this too hard. They’re getting high freight rates. Why

shd. they want to sell, except to be rid of old junk. Our owners

H.D. On facts as now it’s good business. How cd. we control the high

Agreed on a) and b)

c) reserved for discn with Ty.

M/T. to submit mema on { freight rates

{ age of B. mercantile marine

R.S.C. Want same line on F.A.O. and I.T.O. This accords with earlier decns.

P.M. One doubt: helping countries with less purchasing powers – cost to

R.S.C. It’s all for benefit of producers – they shd. carry it.

P.M. Mayn’t you have to make concession on that?

P.M. Not too flat-footed.

H.D. Can’t have burden accepted w’out reference back. B. use of dollars for

improvident good nature expendre.

fall on producers with no contn fr. importing countries. Will they

accept that.

R.S.C. Yes: but we start as in memo.

the benefit of others. Can’t accept any further commitment for

R.S.C. Add: no concession on this w’out reference back.

J.S. Price differential v. diff because concealed.

348

H.M. Agree with memo.

3. Excavators.

T.W. So do we.

Agreed.

[Exit Mcneil.

This excavator is being delivered now

R.S.C. Decisions by Coal Cttee held to cover order of excavator for Finnish

Govt. required for power station. Disturbs relations with Finns

when we are about to do a timber deal with us. They want it

this autumn before winter prevents work.

Will Cab. decide wtr. requisitioning powers of this kind cover goods

ordered by foreign Govts.

E.Sh. Quoted Coal Cttee decision. B/T. represented at the mtg. to a pit: will be erected in

coal p.a.

5 wks.

It gives only 50 yds. of the 500 priority. Will yield 40.000 t. of

Want to increase open-cast yield because drop in mined coal prodn.

Can’t expect any export otherwise. Aiming at 15 m. tons of

open-cast: depends wholly on machinery. Export: will help

B/Trade.

Priority is or isn’t priority. Can’t have exceptions.

P.M. What sequence of events?

R.S.C. They ordered this some time before 1/8. They built special ship to

H.M. L.P. Cttee 27/9 were concerned with new prodn on 1947.

carry it.

Thought allocn wdn’t apply to such orders. – property of foreign Govt.

E.Sh. My file goes back to Dec. 1945. Corrce with Stokes M.P.

P.M. Were you contemplating requisitioning it there? Not until August.

A.B. E.Sh. has had v. generous treatment over excavators.

Set 40.000 t. of coal v. 200.000 standards of timber. Timber wins!

E.Sh. 15/8. Minute: shows we cleared this with other Dpts. F.O., B/T. and

M/Supply.

Clear tht. on 1/8 Coal Cttee hadn’t in mind this export machine.

I favour therefore B/Trade claim.

Cab. cd. also help to enforce L.P. Cttee decision of 27/9 re 30% diversion of Service holdings.

P.M. I will send strong note to Serv. Dpts. A more legitimate spoil for E.Sh.

349

P.M. In future – no absolute priority anyway except by Cab.

L.P. to allocate.

This excavator must go to Finland.

[Exit Wilson.

4. Parliament.

A. When can I get Coinage Bill?

H.D. Probably after Friday next.

5. China: Request for Arms.

P.M. Telegram fr. E.B. Arms for China – to attack Communists.

E.B. recommd refusal of request.

I have informed him I agree. 350 

</content>
</cab>
