<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/4/0 images: 67-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 88(46). 18th October, 1946.

1. Gift from South Africa.

P.M. Gold token representg. £1 m. – gift from people of S. Africa to

people of U.K.

Remarkable tribute.

2. South-West Africa. Smuts strongly objects to last part of formula. I agree with him.

enquiry e.g. in Tanganyika or Austr. mandates.

therefore an appln to U.N. but a notification. S.A. will resent

over Trans-Jordan w’out enquiry of inhabitants. If raised,

Diff. for us to vote v. S. Africa in this.

B. Comm.

E.B. Baltic States – there was plebiscite conducted unilaterally.

H.D. To what extent does U.N. inherit mandates rights of L/N.

C.J. Nothing legal: mandatories to carry on “until other arrangemts. made”.

T.W. Geogr. link. Are we satisf. tht. S. Afr. have taken only practical steps

posn.

A. Recalled earlier discussion. Quoted formula.

Indicates indecision as to our line in U.N. – are we going to

support them at U.N. or not? I recommend we do.

Risk of re-action on us. We might have to submit to independ.

We shall lose nil. by supportg. our best friends. Bad effect if we don’t.

P.M. Mandates Commn no longer exists. Respons. with mandatory. Not

U.S. suggn: &amp; doubtful if U.N. have a locus in this. We handed

acrimonious debate.

Hailey satisfied with method of enquiry.

Recognise however tht. if there is a vote in U.N. it will be against

A. Yes: &amp; Smuts will then carry on.

S. Afr. have said they wd. bring this to notice of U.N.

A.B. Legal rights of U.N. irrelevant. Ques: is this right: shd. we support it

merely because S.A. is member of B. Commonwealth.

they cd. have taken? If so, can we do other than support?

E.B. Was mistake to bring this up now. T. Council not establd – no rules

etc. Will lead to acrimonious debate &amp; will put us in awkward

357

A. He only intends to notify. But can’t prevent debate. And expects

adverse vote. He won’t take it off Agenda because of his

domestic politics.

proposal of incorpn.

C.J. In our trust negotns we shall be embarrassed by support of this. Will

Smuts declare tht. he will continue in acc. with principles of

mandate itself?

(A. Yes: he will do that.)

C.J. We have agreed to inspection. A’s point on Tanganyika won’t arise.

We’re safeguarded – right of veto on transfer to trusteeship.

J. Must support Smuts.

E.Sh. He asks for our support. We shd. give it because of Comm. solidarity, irrespective of merits. Must take long view.

C.J. Commonw. won’t be united. N.Z. led opposition previously to

(A. He won’t now.)

E.B. Annexations – by U.S.S.R. in Poland – also China.

H.D. Main point = don’t school ma’am Smuts in public, for sake of

pedantry. Mustn’t get in posn of voting v. him.

A.B. We must soon establ. some internatl principles to which we will stand.

Otherwise we are in a swither of expediencies.

E.g. that wishes of inhabitants be ascertained by means

acceptable to international opinion.

E.Sh. B. Comm. is a reality. Internationalism &amp; intern. co-opn is in

speculative posn.

P.M. General view: support Smuts. We can omit final part of formula

because we now see tht. this is notification, not appln,

to U.N.

E.B. Authorise me to support Smuts at U.N. – subject to prior consultn with

Doms. as a whole. There are similar territories in Samoa &amp;

Manns.

R.S.C. Is it necessary to “support” a notification?

E.B. I can oppose suggn of addl. machinery – if it’s made – because

T. Council rules not made.

P.M. What about the P.Q.? Read draft answer.

358

E.B. “S. Afr. Govt. is right in notifying U.N. before takg. action.”

P.M. No.

Leave draft answer as now – but omit reference to supporting the

S.A. case &amp; include reference to Hailey’s view.

359 

</content>
</cab>
