<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/4/0 images: 68-68</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 89(46). 21st October, 1946.

1. India.

P.M. Read terms of proposed message to Viceroy – congrats. on formn

of interim Govt.

Agreed.

2. Parliament.

H.M. Business for the week. [Exit W.W. Enter G.T. &amp; F.W.B. &amp; O.S.

3. Germany.

E.B. H.M.’s memo. covered in principle: &amp; H.D.’s met: by my memo.

Haven’t considered J.S.’s.

Hampered in B. Zone –

a) by R. refusal to treat G. as economic whole. They have

taken heavily fr. current prodn &amp; will continue up to

$10 billions

b) U.S. policy was pastoralising (Morgenthan) until

Stuttgart speech. They supported R. &amp; Fr. case – to point

of reducing steel prodn to 5.8 m. tons. And during Loan

talks, cdn’t oppose them too strongly.

c) Fr. policy – detach Ruhr: &amp; decline any agreement w’out

prior consent to that. Now generally realised our policy on

that was correct.

d) At outset, I took the line – let’s get in &amp; put the Zone on

self-supportg. basis. Was told this wd. spell disaster for

W. Europe. Looking back, not sure it was right to let this

political considn outweigh the economic arguments. I refer

to coal exports fr. Ruhr.

Looking back it’s obvious this policy wd. rundown economy of

B. Zone.

In Paris, at CFM time, tried to get B. Zone on self-supportg. basis.

Fr. then wdn’t play because of c) above. Then announced tht., failing

agreemt. to treat G. as a whole, we shd. be forced to make our Zone

self-supporting. Next Day, U.S. agreed we cdn’t be expected to go on

making contn at £80-100 m. p.a. They forced us to 5.8 m. – but all

experience has shown we were right on APW Cttee in our figure of

11 m. Molotov then said they wd. accept increase of level of

industry – but subject to unacceptable condns.

U.S. proposal to merge Zones. We knew it wd. cost us more for

a time. When estimates worked out, figure was larger than

assumed. Conference held in Paris – after long discns have now

submd memo. Before this was completed I had seen Byrnes (before Stuttgart speech) &amp; asked wtr. this meant he wd.

360

overthrow Morgenthau policy. He said yes – with Truman’s

authy. Later saw him &amp; took him thro’ all points in my memo.

Asked H.D. to raise it in W’ton: viz., division betwn. U.S. &amp;

U.K. H.D. suggd to Snyder 411. Not a hostile reception.

Must tackle Ruhr comprehensively &amp; quickly. Vital thing = cut out

bottle-necks. Asked Berlin to give me list of priority needs

(given coal) for machinery etc. – with view to getting it from

U.S. on loan. Even 50/100,000 t. of steel wd. help to break down

bottle-necks. This wd. remove diffies over U.S. appropriations.

Another diffy – Fr. elections, wh. prevented us from making big cut in

coal exports before Nov. Have told Bidault we will do what we

can up to Nov. – but tht. after that we must take the pledge. Fr.

might be helped with coal fr. S. Africa. U.S. can’t help because

of high price &amp; shipping in winter.

German exports. In Coalition days we went too quickly along line –

ruin G.’s export trade &amp; clip her wings. cf. H.M.’s memo. To

save our money we shall have to allow her some (less important)

exports.

Housing. A v. gt. problem in B. Zone. Due to diffy. of coal &amp; labour.

Definite decision needed on ownership of industry – if we are to get

good will of G. workers. Believe we must come down firmly

(to-morrow) in favour of policy of socialisation – particularly

of heavy industries. [Agreed.

Can’t hope to withstand growth of Communism unless we

support social democrats. (Christian democrats have no solid

econ. foundation: mainly anti-Communist like MRP. in France.)

Constitutional development – going fwd. on sound lines.

This memo. outlines a policy – proposes early discn in U.S.A.

(readiness of U.S. officials to grapple with it now). Now is our

opportunity.

P.M. How much do you propose to say in H/C. to-morrow?

E.B. Most of it.

H.D. Tired of cost to B. taxpayer. £120 m. = 1/= in £ on income tax.

A bit much! Ques. is how we can end it?

reduction in charge on U.S. Budget. 4:1 propn not rejected. That

Have we extracted enough in exports? e.g. timber.

Not only a ques. of money. $160 million in food for Germany - &amp; that

amount less in food for U.K.

Discussed with Clayton &amp; Snyder. They are sympathetic. Want sharp

was UNRRA. propn. Promised to consider it.

£250 m. more in 3 years – capital investment required. So far, a dole

not an investment. If the latter, we shd. look at it differently. It

shd. be primarily by U.S. – as a loan. That wd. be much better

if it cd. be arranged – either U.S. Govt. or Reconstrn Confn. If they

can’t cover it all, bring in some neutrals. Mainly dollars, v. little

sterling.

Don’t expect to get back the £80 m. 361

Broad agreement with E.B.’s memo. – subject to above.

Hope additional points in my memo. may also be considered.

H.M. Broad agreemt. with E.B.’s memo.

policy of ownership by German State subject to international

control.

be. Shd. like to see with it a promise of early action to that end.

Clayton believes G. cd. export more if control lifted from innocuous

products like toys, textiles etc. This cd. be examined as part of

H.M.’s memo.

Diffy: when do we get a return on this huge investment. If it’s

5 years, will G. be so independent by then tht. we can’t control

re-payment.

Socialisation. Not merely taking over by C-in-C. – but a deliberate

E.B. assenting – good: puts H.M.G. on the Left, where we shd.

With economic unity of G. secured later, we cdn’t do it so easily.

R.S.C. Agree with general policy.

Only doubts are on manner of implementing it. We shd. do it in way

that helps us most. E.g. a) if we supply G. with up-to-date U.S.

machinery why not send our surplus machine tools to G. &amp; get

the new U.S. ones into U.K.? b) Destination of G. exports. Two

plans. First, let them go free. Second, take them ourselves &amp;

export ours in lieu. B. purchasing agency in G., with authy to

order £10 m. – so far less than £50.000 placed – thus, plenty of

room! What if R. doesn’t agree to our condns re unity. We want

them to continue exporting to E. Europe – wd. suit us better &amp; is

the natural flow of trade.

Awkwardness of bldg. up Germany. E.g. G. housing: needs G.

timber: &amp; we shan’t get it. Must balance needs of U.K. v.

Germany in these matters. Need for careful study.

Reparations machinery. Memo. for O.R.C. (not taken). Position is

decision to increase level of G. industry.

taxpayer to save Germany.

desperate.

Must take a firm line – even tho’ amount is smaller because

A.V.A. Socialisation. Will be asked under what conditions? Plebiscite?

Unilateral action of C-in-C.? We shd. be clear on that, before we

announce.

Investment up to £250 m. Believe it may be more than that. Before

we negotiate in U.S., be sure we’ve put it high enough.

Is it essential to do it by straight advances from U.K. &amp; U.S.?

Cdn’t it be done by international means – e.g. the Bank?

P.M. Be sure which leg you stand on. Take care of criticism – bleeding B.

E.Sh. Don’t make a 2nd mistake in policy (cf. E.B.’s (d)). Gt. care now.

The pol. arguments then outweighed the economic.

This is most important memo. we have had.

362

Says – R. shd. implement Potsdam. This is unrealistic. If we face fact we shan’t get economic unity, then it’s a new situation.

plough back coal into G. industry.

machine tools are all you can get, I think. Machinery for repns

Decide which leg you stand on.

Level of industry plan has never worked.

What is the problem of Germany? Coal: wh. is fundamental to all G.

recovery.

Current cut in exports doesn’t help.

Report of Expert Cttee (Annex). Conclns are most unrealistic –

because you can’t get more food, houses, miners. Right solution:

Exports. Can’t understand what exports are intended. Timber &amp;

will impede recovery.

Socialisation. T.U. leaders in G. aren’t satisfied with people running

G. industry or with denazification measures. Who will run socialised

industry? We can’t spare experts. Germans will have to do it –

will have to be organn for it.

L.P.’s memo. – long-term policy only: no immediate benefits can

accrue.

H.D.’s memo. Do you really think U.S. will pay 4/5ths &amp; leave you

to call the tune?

They will dictate the policy.

Proposal: Make serious effort to get coal prodn right &amp; plough the

coal back into G. industry. End Br. military control over economic affairs. Civil adminn with max. freedom to Germans.

400.000 }

But remember CDU. are in majority in our Zones. (B. &amp; U.S.)

J.B.H. De-nazification. Based on 3 mine managers’ advice – of whom 2 were

Nazi’s.

“Mil. control.” It isn’t so. Cecil Weir controls it. And it is our policy

to give G. more share in adminn.

On the memo. Choice a) Quit b) Self-contained with dollars for

exports c) fusion of U.K. &amp; U.S. Zones subject to conditions.

i) Revision of level/industry ii) coal revival &amp; retention

iii) U.S. share in cost. iv) pooling of all resources incldg. wheat.

Cd. get agreement in Berlin cd. we get it in W’ton.

Socialisation. Final draft slides over consequences of favourable

financial agreemt. with U.S. – they wd. try to call the tune.

I wd. advocate flat decln of policy &amp; burn bridges.

SPD. 900.000 } Results of Elections in Berlin.

Chr.D. 300.000 }

Exports. Low level due to limitns (because of foreign policy) on

coal &amp; food.

Imports of raw materials as well as food required.

Repns policy will also have to be reviewed.

J.W. Genl. support of memo.

Get steel out of G. but only in conformity with B. steel policy.

Reparations machinery – urgently needed for defence work.

363

Deliveries stopped by U.S. action v. Russia. Clay’s policy.

E.B. willing to go on delivering fr. B. Zone to U.K. on the g.t.

Dangers of allowing G. industry to get modern equipment while

ours is old. The whole development of G. export p’mme must be

watched qua war potential.

E.B. There is our expenditure in G. not partly for our security &amp; our trade.

If limns imposed by M/S. &amp; B/T. in our interest, then I can’t be blamed

for the whole of the expense. And beware of inconsistency.

Also how much does Ty. gain by p.o.w. labour? We are charging

reparations labour in Russia v. R. reparations account.

Want both points analysed before this comes up at C.F.M.

Also economic value to G. of bldg. up export connns before we were

exporting.

Shdn’t cost of preventing that be also offset? Will B/T. and M/S. tell me what G. can export w’out harm to U.K.

interests.

P.M. This = short term side of H.M’s memo.

P.L. In 1919 vast reparations proposed - &amp; in the end we lost by it.

This time – attemptg. to destroy war potential &amp; restoring economy.

Believe we must emphasise second point. We must get G. on

her feet. Are we prepared to do that? If not, she will be a

charge on us for ever.

J.S. As in memo. Include among repns to U.S. Govt. pooling of food

supplies for the 2 Zones. They will try to ride out on long-term

Can. contract. But in fact no help fr. there.

E.B. Agreed. Let M/F. give me facts &amp; I’ll take it up at once in

W’ton. Agreed. E.B. I wd. put it tht. G.’s war potential founded on Ruhr industrialists.

H.M. Quoted fr. agreed statement at end of his W’ton discns. Endorsed

common ration standards in 2 Zones. This allocn is

inconsistent with the principles then agreed &amp; announced.

P.M. Agreement with general conclusions in memo?

T.W. Socialisation – steel. What Oppn re-action to announcement, when it

is known we have had to p’pone it here?

We have vested them in C-in-C. We can’t go on holding it.

Can’t give it back. Shall give it to German people?

P.M. Is there agreement with general conclusions? Agreed.

E.Sh. points. We accept posn tht. coal is vital. And after Fr.

elections we shall plough coal back into G. industry.

364

P.M. L.P.’s memo. Was proposing new Cttee on Overseas Ec. Policy.

Cdn’t that do it?

Get this examined by officials first. Then to Cab. thro’ O.E.C. Agreed

4. Timber from Germany. [Enter A.B.

P.M. Will H.D. examine this with Lenanton &amp; J.B.H.?

H.M. A.B., E.Sh. and Barnes are claimants.

P.M. Diff. of opinion re facts.

Is everything possible being done – and what more wd. be possible?

Concentrate on that.

E.B. Housing in Germany. Cd. Services give return of available Nissen

huts?

J.B.H. We are enquiring of W.O. already.

Timber: can’t do more than a bit extra. Unless 50.000 Br. troops cd. be

transferred to timber from training.

F.W.B. V. diff. We shan’t be able to spare the men.

If Cttee try to get at the facts, let me refute H.D.’s statement. 

</content>
</cab>
