<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/2/27 images: 434-457</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK ANDIt&quot;is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO. M-WAR    CABINET.HEER HITLER8S SPEECH.DRAFT STATEMENT.Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate the attached draft of a statement on Herr Hitler&apos;s speech for consideration.I have deliberately made it long;, as theCabinet expressed a desire in this sense;    but I thinkit could with advantage be greatly reduced.difficulty of making a draft at all likely to meet thedifferent views that my colleagues may hold, especially when as here it is so largely, a question of emphasis.But I hope it may afford a basis for discussion fromwhich an agreed draft may emerge.Apart from this, I am very conscious of theFOREIGN   OFFICE.8th October, 1939.

li      Soon after the opening of the campaign in Polandjii was generally expected that Herr Hitler, if and when his troops had overrun that unhappy country, would make &quot;peace proposals&quot;.      These he has now, on 6th October, put forward ina speech to the German Reichstag.2o     His Majesty&apos;s Governmant have already announced that,if proposals for peace were made, they would examine them withcare and measure them against the principles for which theyhad taken up arms, and they feel that it is due from them tostate clearly their views on Herr Hitler&apos;s utterance.,3.      It is necessary at the outset to recall the immediate&quot;background of events against which the  speech is made.     just over a month ago, Herr Hitler, without formal declaration of war,launched an overwhelming attack against the neighbour state ofPolando     He did this in the face of successive appeals fromthe King of the Belgians in the name of the Heads of the 0sl6.-group of Powers, from President Roosevelt, from the King ofthe Belgians and the Queen of the Netherlands, who offeredtheir mediation jointly, and from the Pope, for settlement by negotiation.,      The Polish Government were willing tonegotiate;    but Herr Hitler refused even to delay his attackto allow the Polish Government to receive the terms on which inhis view a settlement could be reached.     Employing all themight of the German Reich, and by the ruthless operation ofair strength, he has succeeded, with the help of soviet forces, in temporarily disrupting the Polish State.      Hehas done this at a price that he holds cheap of ten thousandGerman soldiers killed, and of bringing death, sufferingand bereavement tw countless families in Poland.      Suchis the bare recital of facts, which must be borne in mindin examining Herr Hitler&apos;s presentation of these events.

4.     The first part of the speech consists of statements and assertions, on which His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwould scarcely feel called upon to comment, were it not forthe light that some of the statements throw upon the valueof the proposals made.5.      After dealing with the feats of German arms in Poland, with the humanity with which these were performed,Herr Hitler made historical references to the PolishState and people which are not only a travesty of the truth, hut in direct contradiction with the statementsabout Poland made by Herr Hitler in the recent past.In 1935 Herr Hitler&quot; said:    &quot;Germany has concluded a non-aggression pact with Poland which is more than a valuable contribution to European peace, and she will adhere to itunconditionally........... We recognise the Polish state as the home of a great patriotic nation with the under-standing and the cordial friendship of candid nationalists.The German Reich, and in particular the present GermanGovernment, has no other wish than to live on friendly and peaceable terms with all neighbouring States.&quot;Only last year in 193S Herr Hitler promised, to respectPoland&apos;s rights.      Now Poland is stigmatised as a countryin which conditions were barbarous and impossible, andtherefore deserving of just retribution.     When suchsudden reversals of judgment are possible   in the case ofone country, they are also possible in the case of others andthe lesson will hardly be lost upon the  ether Statesbordering on Germany to whom further assurances are now given.

6.     In the concluding part of the speech Hern Hitler-puts forward his views on the lines   on which a settlement could now he reached and suggests that negotiation should now take place, and that a conference should ultimately hesummoned.     Reference has already been made to appealsmade to Herr Hitler before the outbreak of war from themost authoritative quarters to proceed by way of negotiation and Conference and to those appeals while the Polish state was still intact he made no reply.      Even after the german invasion of Poland had been launched Signor Mussolinioffered his good offices and proposed an immediate conference to find means by which Europe might be spared the thenimminent catastrophe of an extension of the war.      To that proposal the Governments of Prance and the United Kingdomimmediately assented, provided only that a halt was called to the act of aggression and German troops were withdrawnfrom Polish soil.      Herr Hitler again declined the conditions on which alone the holding of a free conference to settleGerman-Polish differences was possible.      It is only afterthe crime of aggression has been committed that he proposesnegotiation - and that,  as it would seem, merely to register and condone the crime.7,      The proposals themselves that Herr Hitler makesare, no doubt purposely, put forward in very general terms.One outstanding omission is that no reparation is offered for the wrongs done by Germany to other peoples.      the czechs are to remain under      a German protectorate, thePoles are apparently to remain under some form of Germantutelage.      In addition Germany is to settle her frontierscorresponding to historical, ethnographic and economic

realities, and to regulate her living space accordingto nationalities.      This involves solving problems which affect practically all the countries of South-Eastern .       ...Europe.      These problems can be discussed at a conferencebut cannot, it seems, be solved there.      For the rest, theGerman colonies are to be returned, a new ordering of markets and regulation of currencies is to be established with a view to the promotion of free trade, and armamentsare to be reduced to a reasonable and economically tolerableextent.      These problems might, it is suggested, be discussed at a conference, which is to meet after fundamentalpreparation,80      To sum up, Herr Hitler&apos;s proposals imply a recognition of the German conquests of Poland and czechoslovakia, and German hegemony in South-eastern europe.      In return for this, and for the restoration ofthe German colonies, we are offered assurances in regardto future aggression, and undertakings to discuss theproblems of economic autarchy and disarmament.   On both these subjects Herr Hitler is extremely vague, and   it isdifficult to judge what in substance is proposed.      It-is on this basis that the Allies are invited to lay down their arms.

9. His Majesty&apos;s Government are fully conscious of thehitter price that war must exact in human suffering;    and,if the issue lay only in their hands, the world wouldcertainly not have had cause to fear all the damage, known and unknown, that war must mean.      They have repeatedlyoffered to bring all the questions at issue bety/een nations to the conference table, if only they could once besatisfied that the German Government was sincerely preparedto lay aside the will to employ force as the arbiter in international affairs     His Majesty&apos;s Government certainlywould welcome and support any genuine efforts to securesuch disarmament, and the adoption of such agreed rules forthe employment of modem weapons of war, as might liberateEurope from the abiding threat of war, that has in theselast years passed under the name of peace.    But for allthese endeavours to bear fruit, one condition is indispensable-sable;    and that is that nations should, feel such confi-dence in one another&apos;s good faith as would permit themto feel quite sure that rules and engagements observed by themselves   would, be equally observed by others.10. And here we touch the real difficulty in judging of herr Hitler&apos;s proposals - and a difficulty much more fundamental than any raised by the proposals themselves,vague and obscure as some of these are.    The plain truthis, and everybody knows it, that in the light of past experience, it is no longer possible to have faith inHerr Hitler&apos;s word, and therefore no reliance can beplaced on any agreement to which he puts his name.11. He d.efends any breach of faith towards other nations by saying that he has carried out his word pledged

999w Cj t-jto the German, people.    But whatever applause such adeclaration may gain in Germany, there must he manyeven there who will realise that any such conception ofinternational obligations is destructive of all respect and trust for him who proclaims it as his owns and to the outside world, it undermines any basis of mutual confidence,on which alone relations of friendly understanding canbe built.12&apos;. It is hardly necessary to recapitulate the assurances that have often been given and not less often contradictedin action by Herr Hitler.    Mention has already been madeof the sharp reversal of Herr Hitler&apos;s attitude towardsPoland.In November 19S5 he said &quot;Germany neither intendsnor wishes to interfere in the internal affairs of   Austria,to annex Austria, as? to   conclude an Anschluss&quot;.      InMarch 1936 he said, &quot;the German people do not wish tocontinue waging war to adjust frontiers&quot;,       In May 1936he said &quot;the lie goes forth again that Germany tomorrowor the day after will fall upon Austria or Czechoslovakia.&quot;In January 1937 he said &quot;the period of so-calledsurprises is now over.&quot;Yet in March 1938 German troops without warningmarched into Austria.

In September last be assured the world that &quot;theSudetenland is the last territorial claim which I have tomake in Europe&quot; and &quot;we have assured all our immediateneighbours of the integrity of their territory as far as germany is concernedc      That is no hollow phrase, that is our sacred will.&quot;130      But even more disturbing than these particularoccasions of failure to adhere to his pledged intentionhave been what must appear radical departures by Herr Hitlerfrom the fundamental principles of his declared policy andcreedoThe first principle relates to the inclusion ofnon-Germans within the Reich.On September 26th, 1958, Herr Hitler said &quot;Weare not interested in suppressing other nations.     We do not want to see other nations among us,&quot;     And on September 28thhe repeated with great earnestness to the Prime Minister thathe had no wish to include in the Reich people of other racethan GermanscWithin less than a year Germany has in effectincluded in the Reich many millions of Czechs, and claims theright to dispose of the fate of many millions of Poles.The second established principle upon which HerrHitler1s policy was based was his judgment of the soviet union.In 1936 Herr Hitler said &quot;We see in Bolshevism abestial, mad doctrine which is a threat to us.      I cannot make a pact with a regime whose first act is not the liberation of workmen but of the inmates of gaols&quot; .......&quot;there are two worlds. In Bolshevist Russia there isdevastation, grim murder and ruin. Here is laughter,happiness and beauty.&quot;

In 1937 he said &quot;We look upon Bolshevism as upon an intolerable danger to the world    o.. -.. .    we should&apos; avoid all.contacts with these poisonous bacilli    .....    Anytreaty links between Germany and present-day BolshevikRussia would be without any value whatsoever.&quot;In 1939 he says &quot;If the sub-human forces of bolshevism had proved victorious in Spain, they might easily have spread across the whole of Europe.&quot;Yet within a few months, the wheel has come fullcircle so that he can say:    &quot;The pact of friendship between germany and Soviet Russia will not only render possiblepeace but a happy and permanent co-operation.&quot;14*     In the light of this history? His Majesty&apos;sQ-overnment feel not only entitled but bound to ask whatreason there is to believe that Herr Hitler5s signaturewould be more certainly honoured now than it has been inrecent years0The position of His majesty s Government hasbeen repeatedly made plain.      They entered the war indischarge of the obligations which they had assured to poland who seemed all too clearly, from the familiartechnique then being employed against her, to be markeddown by Germany as the next victim   of aggression.      Thatwas the immediate motive;    but the fundamental purpose ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government was to redeem Europe from theperpetually recurring fear of German attack and to enablethe peoples of Europe to preserve their independence andtheir liberties.     With the record of the last twelvemonths before them, His Majesty&apos;s Government were forcedto the conclusion that, unless and end could be put to thesesuccessive acts of aggression, such acts would be repeatedwhenever it might suit Herr Hitler to do so, and that the title of European nations to exist would finally depend

only upon his permission and good will.      That prospect seemedto them not tolerable...15...       His Majesty&apos;s Government have said that they do not bythiswar seek material profit for themselves - they know all too well that in modern war between Great Powers victim and vanquishedsuffer cruel loss alike.    But the alternative of acquiescenceseemed, to them one that spelt the extinction of all hope, andthe annihilation of all the abiding values of life, which havethrough centuries been the inspiration of human progressiAccordingly the British people are determined to useevery effort of which they are capable to re-establish for themselves as for others liberty through respect for law, andthe right of all peoples freed from the dark shadow of fear todecide their own lives and destinies.16.        His Majesty&apos;s Government have been at all times willingto lend their whole influence to the search for means of resolving the malajustments in the present world, order.    they agree with Herr Hitler in feeling that the political and economicills which now afflict the nations call for co-operative remedyat the hands of all who have it in their power to  helpB     they believe indeed that no remedy can now be found effective that does not take account of the just claims and needs of allcountries - and, whenever the time may come to draw the linesof a new peace settlement, His Majesty&apos;s Government would feelthat the future would hold little hope unless such a settlement could be reached, through   the method, of negotiation and agreement.    It is not therefore with any vindictive purpose thatthey have embarked on war.    Whatever may be the issue of thepresent struggle, and in whatever way it may be brought to a conclusion, the world will not be the same world that we haveknown before it.     Deep changes will inevitably leave theirmark on every field of men&apos;s thought and action - and ifhumanity is to guide aright the new forces that will bein operation, all nations will have their part to play.

His Majesty&apos;s Government would accordingly hope thatin the task of drawing a future peace settlement, it wouldnot he.found impossible to associate Powers which might at that time be still non-belligerent.17. There is therefore no doubt either about thepurpose which His Majesty&apos;s Government have set themselvesto achieve or about the spirit in which they seek to achieveit.    There will be no ground for war, if the   GermanGovernment can convince other countries that they nolonger desire to dominate other peoples, and can satisfy the world that, if any basis for an acceptable peace settlement could be found, the settlement would be respected.No-one can do this but the German Government and it is for -them to consider practical means by which such essential and certain confidence can be created.




</content>
</cab>
