<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/60/0 images: 16-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
. &apos;   JTK,, r^.,m*nt .* the Property of   ,7 14   jf3 * jj&apos; 1      Board of Agriculture and Fisheries.Report for week ended 30th July, 191$.. ^Silt $jg^ Land Division.Holbeach.      The horses have &quot;been &quot;busy spraying potatoes, carting materials for the builders, and the grass from the various ditohes, and storing in the rickyards for future use. The live stock are going on well.    The women are busy pulling flax.ftatrington.    The farming operations for the week consisted of haymaking, mowing thistles on grass, emptying fold yards, leading and spreading farm manure, ploughing fallows, leading straw to station, and mowing banks, fences, etc.The weather during the week has been very bad with heavy storms.      There still remains one 20 acre field of clover seeds hay to get in.    The largo area of hay has interfered with the usual work, such as emptying yards and ploughing fallows, but the work on the Colony is being pushed forward as quickly as possible, and will mean &quot;full collar&quot; work right up to the harvest. The crops, produce and stock disposed of during the week included 28 stone tail ccrn, 7 stone crushed oats, 60 white leghorn chicksf and 544 eggs.Heath Hill.    The adverse weather which continued during tir: week with heavy storms each day prevented further progress being made with the hay.    A commencement has been made with potato spraying, and this crop is looking remarkably well.      There are now six ex-Service settlers on the Colony who have been accepted, and two more are coming next week.    The Director has secured the assistance of a motor expert for the period of the corn harvest, so that there is a reasonable prospect of the Fordson tractova being kept working full time during the harvest and thereby easing the horses considerably.Kelham Bet ate *Before the weather broke on July 9th most of the crops were showing bnmiatakeable signs of the drought, more particularly the barley and roots.    It has, however, rained at intervals for the last three weeks, and the whole aspect has changed for the better, although the rain came late for the com.    A marked improvement has taken place on every side, and a harvest up to the usual average of well farmed land is expected.    The spell of fine weather previous to July 9th enabled 480 acres of hay to be cleared in excellent condition, but the remaining 30 acres was carried under more difficult conditions.The position as regards the various crops is as follows:-Wheat 207 acres.   This was very poor at the start, being sown in many cases on an impossible tilth, and 72 acres on land which had not been manured for some years..    It has responded to treatment, and is now a very fair crop.Oats-after-turf.   151 aores.    Despite the fact that the grass land ploughed up was some of the worst we had, and also that it was steam-ploughed, this acreage of oats looks extremely well, and should yield more than an average crop of Spring Oats.Oats-after-stubble . 1X7 acres.    Although this crop does not &quot;ITompar-r quite &quot;favourably with the oats-after-turf it looks very promising, and will yield a heavier crop than was expeoted.
1 K 13Barley, 122 acres,    VJith the exception of some of the pieces en the lighter land, which suffered from the lack of rain, this lookB well and will yield an average crop. /    *Dredge corn, 23 acres.    This also looks well, and will yield a good crop.-liinseeg.,.m6 acres.    This was sown to provide food for the oalvas during the winter:   it looks very promising.Sept.. 18 acres.    This was sown on very foul land without farmyard manure. It is an exoellont crop and the leaves are almost touching &quot;between the rows.Potatoes. 21 acres.    At the present time the potatoes look exceptionally well, and as they are of the second early varieties they a*re more likely to esoape any serious damage from &quot;blight&quot;.Mangolds, 14 acres.     Owing to the fact that 11 acres failed, this crop io very small, but will be first rate on the reduced acreage,Swedes. 64 acres.    Taking into consideration the fact that the swedes were all sown on land which was covered with couch and weedst and which (in the ordinary way) should have been bare-fallowed, the crop is beyond expectation.    Not only is the crop good, but the land will be well cleaned at the finish,LIVE STOCK,Fattening barren cows.      These have been fattened on the grass withou any artificial food whatever.    Ten have been sold and the price realised per head is from  5 to  8 more than the cost.Cows in milk.    These are devoted to calf rearing and providing milk forthe employees.    They nave already reared two or three oa-lves each, and our calves show great promise*Sheen,    These have done remarkably well.Flax Production Branch,The harvest has been much delayed by adverse weather in Somerset, Peterborough, Yorkshire and Suffolk Centres, but excellent progress has been made during the present week.    In Scotland the harvest will be commenced about the 2nd of August,    The crops are good in all the areas except in a few instances of late sown flaxo The camps are now in good working order and a methodical system of inspection has been organised.    The workers appear to be well satisfied with the conditions under which they are housed and fed.   In the oase of the city workers, however, some &quot;weeding out&quot; has been necessary owing to the numerous sources from which they are drawn.   Ho such difficulties have been experienced with the female labour which is distinctly good,    V/ith regard to the pulling operations an improved system of supervision has become necessary.    Special provision for ricking and thatching has been made by means of female labour, which is being trained by experts, in these operations,Tithe. Copyhold. Commons and Survey Branch,The applications received during the past week included 5 for altered apportionment, 5 for redemption, 2 for merger of tithe rent-charge and 1 for the enfranchisement of copyhold land while 5 redemptions and       6 enfranchisements have been confirmed,    Under the Commons ActB, 1845 to 1899, the Board issued their approval to the levying of a rate upon the owners of common rights upon Skipwith Common (York, Bast Biding) to meet the expenses incurred by the Conservators of the Common in the execution of their duties.    Among
tha miscellaneous work performed Toy the Branch has been the preparation of a plan to be annexed to an order for the compulsory hiring under the Small Holding and Allotments Act. 1908, by the Carmarthenshire County Council of land at Pins $arm, Llanoaint.Joint Committee of the Board of Agriculture and gj-eheriea and the liinistry of yoo&apos;d.During the past weak a well attended meeting has been held at Honiton, Devon, at which Kr. T. Thomson spoke:   at the discussion which followed, general satisfaction was expressed at the recent change of policy as to the ploughing up scheme and the bulk of the farmers present exhibited a strong tendency to wish to revert to pure grass land farming:   it is felt that in this district opportunities exist to educate the farmers by lectures and other methods to the great advantages of arable land farming over grass land farming, as a business proposition.    The desire for Oii Cake and other concentrated feeding stuffs a3 a supplementary ration for dairy cows and weaning calve3 ie widespread and lack of supplies of these feeding stuffs is causing considerable uneasiness as to the future.During the week ending 31st July 1918, 78,899 maps were sent Overseas, 11,887 to the Air Kinistry, 24,650 to tha Admiralty, 7,394 to the War Office and 384 to Other Services.The number of applications for ordinary issues of the Leaflets was 3,338, in response to which 5,987 copies of Leaflets were despatchad.    In addition 40,500 copies of Leaflets were despatched to applicants for supplies in bulk for distribution. A further supply of 268,000 leaflets was sent to the Government Information Bureaux, principally for distribution at the Bureaux now being established in provincial centres, and 9,500 leaflets were sent to the South Eastern and Chatham Railway for distribution through Booking Offices, as explained in previous Reports.    The July issue of the Journal was received from the printers and distributed.gjghejjea PMfflqn,.ymj^i^lijylive,,,gggMjgu    The Italian Food Controller and members of an Italian Delegation have personally ronsulted this Department with regard to Sngliah fishing methods and the possibility of applying them to Italian waters.    Information, Reports and Memoranda were supplied and measures taken to afford the Marquis de Solati, Commander I.R.H., facilities for acquiring information at fishing ports.The conditions on which a grant would be made from the Development Fund in aid of the repair of Looe Harbour have been settled and communioated to the Lecal Authorities.    The Harbour Provisional Order will now be proceeded with.    An Order altering the Close Season for oysters has been made and w^ll at once be issued.    The many cases of application for relaxation of fishing restrictions continue to throw much work on the short staff of the Department.    A Dutch firm has applied for facilities enabling their fishing boats to use British Ports as a base, but such facilities can only be granted ae the result of an international arrangement and not merely, as in this case, for private commercial purposes.
Permit Section.      35 permits have &quot;been issued and 28 cancelled. Reports have been received of attacks by enemy submarine on the 26th, 27th and 28th inst. in the Lowest oft Area, resulting i&quot;. in the sinking of 11 sailing trawlers.      The crews of two of these vessels wore taken on the deck of the submarine, which submerged after ramming the metis&apos; small boats, leaving the men struggling in the water.    Four men were drowned. Arrangements have been made with the Admiral-in-Charge, Harwich, tc allow night fishing under certain conditions in th? area of his Command.Pishsrme^s Registration and Recruiting Section.WarningsTTave been de3patched t o men intended to make up the remainder of the 300 men to be supplied by the Board for arrears up tc Call XIV and a share of Call XV.    A request for men under Call XVI has been received, and, in view of the proportion supplied by this Board from JSngland and V/aies in the paat the question whether the demand should not be met from Scotland is under consideration.    The Kinistry of Rational Service have circularised their Regional officers pointing out that the terms of the letter directing that fishermen drafted for the Army shall have the choice of enrolling in Section Y. applies equally to men of the old military age as to men under the Military Service Act (No.2) 1918.Mot or^Loan Committee *    A short time ago two of the Directors of a firm from which the Committee have purchased a large number of engines paid a visit to several of the ports at which their engines have been installed, for the purpose of Instructing both the Committee*s mechanics and the fishermen owners on the management of the engines.      The visit was a great success and will, it is felt, do much to assist the Committee1s staff and the fishermen themselves.The normal work of the Board proceeds on lines asSecretary.2nd August, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
