<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/60/0 images: 253-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Po li t ical Int el .1 if one o -J)e par tin en t,Foreign Office,C0M?IMTIAIItaly /004.(August 7th, 1918)II E HO K \ IT P U MonITALY&quot;National Conoo&apos;,The general spirit nrevailing in Italy has perhaps never been so ggod as during the last month whether from the point of view of prosecution of the war or of sincerity in co-operation with the Allies.     Considerable progress had been made, even before the Austrian offensive, tov/ards the establishment, by conciliation of the neutralist or disaffected and toning down of Chauvinist intoler-ance, of that national concord which had been and is among tne foremost aims of the two most influential members of the Govem-neat the President of the Council and the Minister of the Treasury, Both with the unavowed and clandestine neutralism of the Clericals and the open hostility of the Official Socialists the policy of conciliation, helped no doubt by the logic of events, has been notably successful.     In the case of the Socialists^ the speech made by Pilipoo Turati at the close of the June Session of the Chamb3i- (see report of July 10th.    Italy p.3) signified that the solid front so far opoosed to the war by the Official Socialist-party bad at last boon broken through.     Io this connection it is significant that King Yi-vtur Emanuel, when recently he visited the*piovm*a of Emilia, a Suiunghold of Official Socialism, was well received and cheered by Socialist crowds.July has been a fortunate month for the Italian arms. The first week of it saw the* delta between the Old and Hew Have cleared ofThrt War.
tho enemy.     The marshy nature of the ground intersected by numerous waterways made this a work of greet difficulty.     Every islet and neck of kind made a machine gun fortrobc to be separately stormed. But July 6th, however, tho work was successfully accomplished.In the mountain region the curtain of heights oommunling the upoer part of the FreU2el$a volley - Honte Vac Bella, the Col del Rosso and the Col d&apos;Eehele were recaptured during the last days of June.In Albania an Italian offensive was opened early in the month, the immediate objects of which were to push back the Austrian forces from the Malacastra ridge, which dominates the marshy plain of the lower Vojussa, in order to give the Italian occupation breathing space and to clear the communications eastward to   Honastir.     The ridge having been successfully won, the town of Fieri to the north of it on the R. Semeni was taken on July 7th and Berat on the R. Osum on July 10th.    (The Semeni is formed by the Confluence of the Osum and the Devoli).     At the same time French troops operating further east on the right of the Italians pushed north-westward and occupied the watershed separating the basins of the Osum and Devoli.     Heavyy losses of men and material were inflicted on the enemy and the Italiai: position is notably improved by the removal of the incubus which the Austrian occupation of Malacastra represented.     The Italians are said to hafe been everywhere welcomed by the natives of the regionicovered by their advance.     Before the end of the month the Italians occupied the Mali Si loves ridge which occupies the northward bend of the Devoli. while the French on their right had also reached tho line of the Devcli,,     There the advance seems for the present to, have stopped, and the latsst news is of Austrian counter-attacks on the Italian (Semeni) line.
Italy and the Slavs.&quot;^^I^-rrllX.be^^memba*ed^that mn to the summer of 1917 certain sections of the Italian public had through their press done their best to represent the Jug o-v^av^ movement for independence as sold to Austria nad had angrily denounced all suggestions oti. spontaneous abandonment by Italy of the claim (ratified by the Ames in the agreement of April 1915) to a stretch of the Dalmatian mainland, tartly owing to this propaganda carried on in the nationalist and Conservative organs, partly -wing to class sympathy with the Italian minority^of Balmatia, whose superior position there has in the course of the last half-century ibeen undermined by the Slav majority with Austrian encouragement and support, partly to the Belief that oosses3ion of the Dalmatian mainland is necessary to Italy&apos;s security in the Adriatic, this claim to Dalmatia. -finds very consiier-able backing among the propertied class in Italy.     The claim however defies the principle of self-determination (since the vast majority of the inhabitants of %m territory claimed by Italy is Slav) and is incompatible with any lasting friendship between Italy and the JUgo-Slav race.    At the Rome Congress of April 1918 the general formula of sincere co-operation between Italy and the op-pressed nationalities with a view to the liberation of the latter from Austro-Hungarian rule was accepted by representatives of practically all parties in Italy and by the Government,     It was at the time a matter of surprise and congratulation to those who knew his prejudices that even Baron Sonnino declared his adhesion to the principle -c principle of action essentially - affirmed at the Congress.That the acceptance of the formula by the nationalist and con-servative sections did not signify any sincere renunciation of their Jugo-Slav prepossessions but merely their recognition of the obvious advantages to be derived by Italy from the co-operation of
Jhc subject races of Austria is made clear by the attempts madeuring the past 2 months to revive the Anti-Jugo-Sluv press 6cm-;.ign (intermitted since the summer of 1917) and by various indica-ions on the pert of the Minister for foreign Affairs of his un-iillingness to allow the policy of co-operation to be freely dr^veloned -specially as regrrds the Jugo-Slavs.ossicle Ministerial Crisis. -.............................................................., -.....Tension has in con eouence arisen within the Ministry since the resident of Council and the ITinister of the Treasury strongly favour he crosscution in agreement with the Allies of a whole-hearted co-Deration both with Csecho-Slouaks and Jugo-Slavs.     Despatches from ome during the middle pert of July spoke of a formidable campaign sbout to be initiated to force on the resignment of the Minister for oroign Affairs.     Baron Sonnino&apos;s attitude seems subsequently to have fndcrgono -a modification - in articular in the matter of recruiting t Jugo-Slavs for   the Serbian army - ::nd the crisis may bo deferred, jcomamic Matters.It was announced on July 1st that at a meeting of representatives (resided over by the Minister of the Treasury an accord had boon es-&apos;;blishcd between the four chief Credit Banks of Italy viz., the nca Corner ciole, the Credito Italiano, the 3ano&amp; Italiana di Scontolad the 3anca di Roma.     The- object of the accord or &quot;cartel&quot; is to-BSimllate the practice of the various banks in regard to the granting if credits, interest on deposits, branch establishments in foreign ountries, etc, with a view to the elimination of useless competition nd generally to ensure collaboration between them for the promotion i the industrial interests of the nation.This agreement followed on a series of operations (much discussed n the press) on the part of representatives of leading arm..ment firms, he object and effect of -,fhich was to increase the capital of the rmamcnt firms, to consolidate the industries by various fusions and I get as much of the Capital of the Banks as possible- into Italian hands
:    -j       &apos;.L&apos;ho whole movement is looked upon very much askance by tho journals hostile to Signor Mitti, eg., Oiornale d&apos;Italia, and by those of tho extreme Left like Ayant1.     The groat industrialists ore suspected of a desire to gain unfair control over the Credit institutions&quot; of the country to the detriment of smaller industries ana the ordinary depositor.Slornale is also very suspicious of the Bank &quot;cartel&quot; andIdemands publications in full of the act of agreement on the ground that Signer Hittils part in it gives it an official character.Signofc Nitti&apos;s recent visit to London with the results of which he has expressed himself as highly staisfied, marks the completion of a fufcther stage in the financial oo-operation of the British and TJ,S.Governments with that of Italy.Signot Nitti has for a leng time past been exerting himself to effect an improvement of the Italian Exchange.     The Italian press I  of tfuly 23rd reports a statement mode, by him &apos;*n July 19th in Peris to the Secretary of the Italo-Prench Association for economic expan-sion.     &quot;The problem&quot;, he said, &quot;still presents difficulties which, though not insurmountable, have yet to be overcome.     The creation of an Inter-Ally Exchange Bureau..... is a  git accompli, although j this organ, composed of Crosby, Bonar Law, Klotz and myself, is not yet in the full working order in which we hope presently to see it.... If we examine the case of Italy in particular, ,we shall have to acknowledge that a great stop in advance has been taken.     Since my : first visit to the United States in Juno 1917, our allies have accordetolls all the credits and all the facilities that we could ask.....Themonopoly of the means of exchange which I was the first to apply and towards which all the Allies arc gradually moving, was possible with : us bees use our banking system lends&apos; itself to such an arrangement better than that of other countries.     The stabilis. tion and pro-gressive improvement of the exchf-ngc are beneficial results of this
monopoly...... It will not be long^beJtoi^^ Isigned the jrther-day with tne Dnited States, will permanentiy*make, its effects felt. Our Allies did not limit themselves to opening large credits to us in their own countries but also grant us largerate of exchange might be more rapidly effected, but it is necessary to avoid nil harmful counter effects.     To-morrow I hone to dign with the P ench Minister of Finance and, as soon as I arrive in London, with the British Chancellor of the Exchequer, Conventions of which the main lines are already drawn and which will result in further imorove-. mont in the prevailing rates of exchange.     When those preparatory steps have had t&amp;me to effect an improvement in our situation, it will be easy for us to reach further accords with the Allies which will assure to our currency a value which shall better correspond with the political and economic situation of the country.&quot;    !7e understand that negotiations for fixing rates for the lira are al-ready in orogress. The Vatican.The announcement of the resumption of dinlomotic relations between the Holy See and Portugal was followed by that of the appointment of a Nuncio to China..     The latter announcement was the subject of hostile criticism by certain French journals, which see in it a menace to the privileges enjoyed by Prance as protector of Christians in China.     Reference is made to the precedent of 1886 when negotia-tions for the establishment of relations between China and the Holy See were broken off in deference to the nrotest lodged by the Brench Ambassador at the Vatic-n.     The Vatican organ seek to placate their French critics, declaring that the French oosition in China will be fully respected and will be rather strengthened than otherwise by the presence of a Uuncio.exchanges on Spain.,^witsorland and ^reece.The lowering of the

</content>
</cab>
