<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/60/0 images: 335-335</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property of His Majesty&apos;s Government.)

SECRET

BATTLE SITUATION - NOON - 12th AUGUST, 1918.

? 5381

1. WESTERN FRONT.

Stubborn fighting continues on the Battle Front between the ANCRE and the OISE, and with frosh troops, the enemy is putting up a strong resistance to the Allied advance, especially between the SOMME and the AVRE.

The enemy attacked the British troops who had gained LIHONS and RAINECOURT yesterday evening, but was repulsed, and these places are now in our hands.

An operation carried out by us immediately south of the SOMME enabled us to improve our positions between MERICOURT and ETINEHEM and to capture 200 prisoners.

Yesterday the French occupied L&apos;ECHELLE, ARMANCOURT and TILLOLOY, and this morning attacked south of ROYE-SUR-MATZ, and are reported to have reached GURY.

The line now runs from north to south approximately as follows :- west of MEAULTE, western outskirts of BRAY-SUR-SOMME, east of ETINEHEM; east of MERICOURT, west of PROYART, RAINECOURT, (British), LIHONS, (British), railway line west of HALLU, east of F0UQUESCOURT, PARVILLERS, (German), DAMERY, (British), western outskirts of VILLERS-LES-ROYE, cast of L&apos;ECHELLE, ARMANCOURT, (French) TILLOLOY, (French), west of CANNY-SUR-MATZ, western outskirts of ROYE-SUR-MATZ, GURY, LAMOTTE, north of SAMSON, ANTOVAL (north-east of CAMBRONNE).

On the rest of the Western Front there is nothing of special interest to report.

2. ITALIAN AND MACEDONIAN FRONTS.

In Italy successful raids by French and Italian troops have resulted in the capture of 308 prisoners, with material, and in Albania the Italians have captured the ALAMBRETSI heights, north-west of BERAT, and have thereby considerably improved their line.

General Staff, War Office, S.W.1, 12th August 1918. Issued at 12.50 p.m.

For the personal information of the ? Minister only. ?

</content>
</cab>
