<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/60/0 images: 356-356</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
!7his - 079PAlft WAGES CLAUSE::&amp;-:GOVERH?,IENT CONTRACTS.;&quot;f ............. ^,^^y &amp;u-f53^3- Memorandum by the Food Controller. /^li^^am in favour of the extension of the Fair Wages Clausesuggested in the Memorandum by the Ministry of Labour dated June 10th (G.T.4805), but X. think that the precise terms of the proposed amendment might with advantage be modified.If each department which places a contract is to be responsible for adjudicating upon the whole of the contractor^ business, a conflict of decisions is liable to occur whenever a contractor is working for two departments at the same time.    In any case multiplicity of judges may well give rise to some divergence of standards as to what is or what is not a fair wage.   It would, I think be better to set up a single tribunal which would act in consultation with the particular departments concerned, and so secure uniformity. The natural authority would be the Ministry of Labour.   I suggest that in place of the words &quot;to the satisfaction of the Departments concerned&quot; there should be substituted &quot;to the satisfaction of the Ministry of Labour after consultation with the Departments concerned,&quot; or other words to the like effect.I agree,however, with the views expressed by various departments that the imposition of conditions affecting private as woll as Government work will increase the difficulty in finding persons to undertake such work.   In particular, a contractor for some important article may be excluded because in some branch of his business he is not prepared to adhere to the trade union or prescribed standard/   I $ suggest, therefore, that the limitations in respect of private work should be expressed to apply only to work of the same character as the Government nork involved.My department Is- not much concerned with the resolution, as we place but fev; contracts which would come within its terms.   It would net, of course, be possible for the Ministry of Food to assume responsibility for the wages paid by the dealers through whom it distributes supplies, or by any firms whose output may have been requisitioned.J.R.CLYNSS.MINISTRY OF FOOD, 13th August 1918.

</content>
</cab>
