<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/35/42 images: 444-463</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1943.SECRET Copy No.W.P. (43) 14.2.April 5, 1943.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEYffIt is\requested that special care may be taken to&quot;fare the secrecy of this document war CABINET.SUMMARY   OF   OPERATIONS   OF   BOMBER   COMMAND   for fortnight ENDING 1200 HOURS, SUNDAY, MARCH 28, 1943.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.WEATHER over bases has been unfavourable for night attacks, and on twoof the nights on which operations were possible it was necessary to arrange foran early return. Berlin, Duisburg and St. Nazaire were attacked : furtherinformation is available about the great destruction done in two recent attacks on Essen : a total of 1,121 mines has been laid up to the 28th March.Night Operations.Target.St. NazaireDuisburgBerlinBute.22/23 March26/27     ,,27/28AircraftDespatched.357 aircraft457396Day Operations.Target.St. Brieuc aerodrome ...Paderborn railway workshopsMaasluis oil targetBelgium   and   Germany   railwaytargets       ...      ...Maasluis oil refineryNantes St. Joseph locomotive worksN.W. Germany trainsHengelo-Stork works  ...Date.15 March161820     ,,2223     &quot;2426A ircraftDespatched.11 aircraft121213121536In addition 82 aircraft were despatched on anti-submarine patrol.Mining.287 mines were laid during the week. The following successes are reported : (i) On the 17th March a Finnish steamship was reported to be sinkingafter being mined in the Cadet Channel, East of Giedser.(ii) On the 19th&apos; March a minesweeper was damaged off the Ems.(iii) On the 20th March a steamship in convoy near Borkum was mined andbadly damaged. -[25266] -
Operational Achievements.Duisburg (26th/27th March).This attack failed to achieve concentration comparable to that obtained inthe attacks on Essen, and it seems evident from crews&apos; reports that it was scattered over a wide area.Berlin (27th / 28th March).Only a few night photographs are available as yet. These show that tireswere started in built-up areas. Crews generally report a successful attack.1.000 tons of HE. and incendiary were dropped. Nine aircraft of the force of396 despatched (all heavies) were lost.St. Nazaire (22nd/23rd March).Night photographs taken during the bombing indicated that two quitesuccessful concentrations had been achieved. Day photographs which have since been obtained cover only one of these areas, and show less new damage than mighthave been expected. This may well be due to a number of bombs falling into theruins caused by previous raids and also into the water. The undestroyed areaof St. Nazaire is now so small that nothing of the slightest importance remainsexcept close to the water&apos;s edge.Paderborn (16th March).Crews reports and photographs taken during the daylight bombing of therailway workshops at Paderborn indicate that the attack was most successful.The target, however, is so obscured by bursts that no detailed assessment of damage is possible.Results of Previous Raids.Essen.&apos;.The two raids on the 5th/6th March and the 12th/13th March constitute anew level of achievement in the Bomber Command offensive. Results achievedwere certainly more important than those obtained by the 1,000-bomber raidon Cologne.Over 10 per cent, of the total bombing effort of 1942 was devoted to attempts to destroy Essen, but no considerable success was achieved. The immunity whichthe town enjoyed was partly due to the natural protection from identificationprovided by its own industrial haze and smoke, supplemented by immensely strong-searchlight and A.A. defences. Improved technique and navigational aidsprovided the opportunity for dealing a really crushing blow at the most important industrial objective in Germany.Essen, including Bottrop, Gelsenkirchen and the surrounding district form amore or less continuous industrial area with a population of over a million.Essen proper has (or had) about 700,000 inhabitants and some 75,000 of these were directly employed in the main Krupps works, which occupy about 800 acres.In addition to the manufacture of naval, coastal and other heavy guns, of whichit is the chief, if not the sole, producer in Germany, it is one of the three greatmanufacturing centres for railway locomotives in the Reich. Krupps alsoproduce ammunition, torpedo tubes, torpedo air vessels, bombs, tanks, armoured cars, artillery tractors and crank shafts for aero-engines.Other industrial undertakings in Essen, though dwarfed by the enormousKrupps group, are numerous and of considerable importance in themselves, particu-larly the Altenberg zinc-smelting works at Borbeck, the Presswerk plastics works and the Goldschmidt chemical and non-ferrous metal works. The railway trafficcentre Essen Verschiebbahnhof is also very important.. Photographic evidence has revealed the following damage : 450 acres of Essenhave been wrecked. Over an area of 150 acres in the old town adjacent to Krupps75 per cent, of the buildings have been destroyed. At least 30,000 people, mainlyKrupps workers, were made homeless. In the second attack on 12th/13th March,the Borbeck area N.W. of Krupps suffered particularly badly. One housingestate near the works was demolished and another badly hit. About 10,000wrecked dwellings were thus added to the results of the first attack, and a further25-30,000 people rendered homeless. In all, about one-third of the total built-up area of Essen has been devastated, including two-thirds of the city centre.In the Krupps group of factories 13 main buildings have been destroyed and53 separate shops more or less completely put out of commission.  In the Harbour
Foundry works there is damage to the steel works and to some new rolling mills,,while many store sheds have been destroyed and 3 out of 6 chimneys serving the steel furnaces are seen to be inactive. Krupps pattern works has had half itsbuildings wholly or partially gutted, while in the mam Engineering and armament Works two or three workshops and several sheds have been destroyed or damaged. . ,    jIn Vogelheim a Plastic works has been almost totally burnt out, and pitneadbuildings and two collieries have been damaged by fire and H..E. On the KanalHafen, about 20 warehouses and sheds have been destroyed, and over the whole area at least 40 more workers&apos; hutments have been demolished.Conditions in the town are naturally catastrophic. The Essener National-Zeitung reports that all schools have been closed and teachers conscripted for firstaid work. All inhabitants except those required for war purposes have now been instructed to evacuate the city.Some sections of Krupps remained in action after the first raid, but the works-appear to have stopped completely after.the second.The casualties in these attacks were, in the first 14 aircraft and in the second23 aircraft. -Prints 1 and 2 show some of the damage effected. Print No. 3 is a C.I.U-damage plot.Berlin.Further reports of the results of the attack on 1st/2nd March indicate thatthe damage in the centre of the city, particularly in the Unter den Linden, is.more serious than was at first thought. The Leipziger Strasse (comparable to tlieStrand in London) was affected, severe damage being caused to the well-knownWertbeims Store (comparable to Selfridges); The damage in the fashionableDahlem district (where Ribbentrop and Himmler live) aroused considerable interest, and the home of the Japanese Commercial Attache was burnt out.On the morning after the attack it was known in the German Air Ministrythat 1,000 persons had been killed (a figure which might well increase later andhas only been exceeded on two occasions in this country).Print No. 4 shows damage to the Deutschlands Flalle caused in January.Nuremberg.Photographs reveal that the industrial damage caused in the raid of the8th / 9th March was considerably greater than was at first supposed.In the M.A.N. Works the Submarine Diesel test workshop is almost entirelydestroyed, and in the northern part of the works 3 acres of miscellaneousbuildings have been devastated. Two other large shops and several sheds havebeen partially destroyed, and a large building bousing the Administrative Officeshas been seriously damaged. In Siemens Schuckert A.G. (Southern) (Trans-formers) the main workshop, covering an area of 5 acres, has been two-thirdsdestroyed. Five other shops have been destroyed or very seriously damaged, and several small buildings and sheds have been gutted. A timber yard in the northern part of the works has been destroyed, and over 3 acres and at least 20 workers7hutments have been gutted. In Siemens Schuckert A.G. (Northern) (ElectricMotors) four buildings have been wholly or partly destroyed by fire.In the Railway workshops a carriage and wagon repair shop covering 5 acreshas been completely gutted and three sheds damaged.Two works, the Aluminiumwerke Nurnberg A.G. and the SuddeutscheApparate Fabrik G.m.b.H., have been severely damaged by fire, and nine others have suffered damage in varying degrees.In addition to industrial damage, the Goods Railway Traffic Centre (where16 acres of sidings and goods yards have been burnt out) and several goods station buildings and Railway Offices have all been damaged. Many barrackhuts and buildings and unidentified hutted camps have been burnt out, and publicproperty damaged includes the Municipal Buildings in Camerarius Strassc, theTown Gas- Works, and a large group of new Nazi buildings in Bayern Strasse.A Nuremberg paper shortly after the raid contained the followingannouncements:- &apos; &apos;&quot; (i) The great damage caused by the raid requires the assistance of theentire population. Consequently next Saturday and Sunday everycitizen should be prepared to assist in the clearing-up work. &quot; people whose places have been damaged must repair them themselves. Neigh-bours should be asked for assistance. All other citizens will meet at[25266] -   B 2.
their Ortsgiruppen and receive instructions regarding their work.On Saturday work will last from 14.00 to 18.00 hours, and on Sundayfrom 08.00 to 18.00 hours, with a two-hour lunch interval. Tools, should be brought.&apos;&apos; (ii) All people possessing a Nuremberg-Furth ration card for 1942-43 will receive an extra ration consisting of 650 g. of brown bread, 100 g. ofmeal and 60 g. of butter.&quot;Norway.Knaben. Photographs now show details of the damage caused by the attackon the Molybdenum Mine on the 3rd March. The building used to store spare parts and tools has been completely demolished, and the cone crusher has been destroyed by HE. Part of the west tower and the conveyer to the north towerhave been damaged, while the new extensions to the ball mills, classifiers andfeeders have been destroyed. Two new buildings have been largely gutted, andthere is serious damage to part of the N.E. workmen&apos;s hutment.France.Tours. Details of the damage caused during the attack on the 18th Februaryhave now been established.In the Main Railway workshop, an area of 240 feet x 160 feet has been damaged by a direct hit; to the east of this, one workshop is 35 per cent, andanother over 40 per cent, gutted. Of four more shops, two have severe roofdamage, another, along with a connecting shed, has been demolished, and thefourth has been partly destroyed.It is also reported that at the railway junction south of the main station32 engines were severely damaged, some of them beyond repair.Le&apos; Mans. Photographs show that as the result of the attacks on the4th and 9th March one of the Steam and Electric Locomotive Sheds in the marshalling Yard has been severely damaged and the other has a large hole inthe middle of the roof. The Wagon Paint find Repair Shops have sustainedsevere roof damage and two direct hits on railway lines have caused blast damage to trucks.In the Renault works a 6-bay building has extensive roof damage, withparticularly severe damage to the east end caused by one or more direct hits.A 19-bay building has been severely damaged over an area of 2,360 square yards,and a 10-bay building has roof damage over 6 bays. Two more 6-bay buildings have also sustained roof damage.Note. Renault at Le Mans is the shadow factory for Billancourt. Muchof the activity of Billancourt was transferred to Le Mans while Billancourt was out of..action. Le Mans produced M.T., A.F.V. and aero-engines. Probably the tank production of Billancourt had also been transferred there.Aulnoye. Print No. 5 shows that as a result of daylight attacks on the13th January and the 4th and 8th March the factory of the S.A. Lourvril-Montbard-Aulnoye (manufacturers of steel tubes, and reported to be makingbombs) was severely hit and nearly 20 acres (two-thirds of the whole) of theroofing of the main building has been destroyed or damaged. In the marshalling yard, the Locomotive Repair Shop, the Engine Sheds and two other sheds have allsustained some damage.Caen. Lt is reported that during the attack on the 10th February 40 wagonsin the Marshalling Yard were destroyed or severely damaged. A hangar con-taining German supplies was burnt out and the Engine Repair Shops were alsodamaged.Holland.Den Helder. Photographs show that the following damage was causedduring the attack on the 19th February : More than two-thirds of the Torpedo Workshops have been destroyed. Inall, three shops and two sheds have been totally destroyed, and one shop and oneshed partly destroyed.Locomotive Attacks.A reliable source reports that by the middle of January locomotive losses inFrance, Belgium, Holland and Germany were averaging 150 a month as a resultof bombing and machine-gunning attacks. In France and Belgium, additionaldamage was being caused by increasing sabotage.
General Effect of Air Raids.Several sources have reported a growing dissatisfaction amongst thepopulation of towns recently attacked.   This is attributed to two main causes : -(i) The apparent inability of the Luftwaffe and the flak to prevent the attacks from being so successful, and(ii) Dissatisfaction caused by the inadequacy of the measures for assistingthose bombed, and particularly by the acute shortage of furnitureand household requisites, especially crockery.The following extract is taken from an editorial in a Stettin newspaper : &apos;&apos; We must reckon with the fact that terror raids, contrary to last year,will become heavier and -longer than last year. Bloody, burning, scarredtraces are crossing the German face like strokes of a whip wielded by HisBritannic Majesty&apos;s pilots. It is certainly possible to withdraw the Air force from the eastern front for a counter-blow, but what would be gained therebyif meanwhile the decision of the continental war slips out of our hands? &quot;A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, April 5, 1943.
















</content>
</cab>
