<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/208/25 images: 518-540</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(80) 25 COPY NO25 April 1980CABINETCIVIL SERVICE MANPOWER POLICYNote by the Secretary of the CabinetI attach a minute from Sir Derek Rayner to the Prime Minister, which iscirculated for discussion at the meeting of Cabinet on 1 May, whenSir Derek Rayner will be in attendance.Signed ROBERT ARMSTRONGCabinet Office25 April 1980CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALPRIME MINISTERTHE EFFICIENCY OF CENTRAL GOVERNMENT:   LASTING REFORMS1. You asked for a brief account of the work with which I amassociated and for my thoughts in connection with the Cabinetmeeting of 1 May.EXISTING WORK2. The 29 &quot;Rayner projects&quot; which you commissioned last June wereall completed by the year end.     In the main, the work was done byofficials of first class quality.     Some Ministers providedenthusiastic leadership.3. The project officials&apos; reports recommended potential annualsavings of  80 million and once-for-all savings of  50 million.4. I have been impressed with the quality of most of the &quot;proposedaction&quot; documents sent me by Ministers and have agreed them inrespect of 22 projects.     The extent to which Ministers have beenable to accept the recommendations in principle and the pace atwhich, subject to consultation, they plan to implement them areheartening.     The greatest boldness has been in respect of recommen-dations which affect activities inside government and the greatesthesitancy in respect of those which bear upon client groups.5. The possible savings associated with the 22 projects on whichthere are now agreed action documents amount to  18 million per annumand  8.12 million once-for-all.     But it will not be possible to gofirm on these savings until consultations are concluded.     In somecases, savings will be ascertainable only when further work iscompleted.6. The most important.projects awaiting decision are those in theDepartment of Health and Social Security (arrangements for payingsocial security benefits,  50 million per annum) and the Manpower1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALServices Commission ( 8 million pa and  41.5 million once for all).Officials will report to Ministers shortly on the former afterexamining the proposals&apos; implications for Post Office counter servicesThe MSC is to decide on the latter on 22 April.7. You have asked Mr Channon to take responsibility for followingup -the wider implications of the projects.   He is in touch with severaMinisters on such matters as organisational stream-lining; &quot;nannying&quot;of local authorities;   excessive administration;   and modernisation.Success here is perhaps even more important than a successful conclusito the projects themselves.8. I am involved in two pieces of work stemming directly from the&apos;projects, on which I shall report to you in the autumn:  Statisticsi   Following the project on the statistical servicof Departments of Industry and Trade, I am co-ordinating areview of the Government&apos;s statistical services, consisting ofjan exercise on the Central Statistical Office and of a series,of exercises conducted, on &quot;scrutiny&quot; lines, for Ministersin their own departments.  Repayment:   The disadvantages of the allied service systemwere highlighted more than once.   I am supervising a studyby officials of the Treasury, CSD and Property Services Agencof the case for supplying PSA goods and services more completon a repayment basis.9. Cabinet decided last autumn to embody the &quot;project&quot; approach ina new programme of &quot;scutinies&quot;, beginning this year.   A list has beencirculated to Ministers.   It contains 37 scrutinies.   I am taking aclose interest in 16 of these on your behalf, but am in touch with allof them.   I have also been asked by Treasury Ministers to interestmyself in two additional reviews, of the United Kingdom Treasury andSupply Delegation in the USA and of the Rating of Government PropertyDepartment.   The scrutiny programme contains excellent subject matterand examining officers of comparable quality to last year&apos;s &quot;projects&quot;.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL10. The general lessons I would draw out so far as these:a. While a scrutiny may produce excellent results in the fieldexamined and help the Minister to tighten his grasp of it, itsmain value lies in enabling him to become a stronger managergenerally by pointing up for him telling questions which hecan apply elsewhere.    (The review of maintenance economy in theBath District of the PSA by DOE Ministers, now involving MODMinisters, is a good example of this.)b. The scrutiny technique is widely useful. It can he used wellbeyond the &quot;scrutiny programme&quot;.c. Its most important features are persistence during theanalysis and determination in seeing the results through tothe completion of action documents.d. Determined Ministers will best succeed if they make aspecific official responsible for and themselves monitor progressto implementation.11. Finally, Cabinet agreed last October that it should have an annualstatement on the cost of governing and that Ministers should scrutinisethe running costs of their own departments. I offered advice on thisin my letter to the Home Secretary of 22 February. This is a promisingand important exercise because it enables Ministers to reach down intotheir departments and establish and question the cost of activities. Ilook forward to knowing how it works in practice^LASTING REFOBMS12. Some Ministers and officials are by temperament, training andexperience very good managers.   But I doubt whether the Lord President&apos;sexercises of last year, the ongoing efficiency work of departments andthe exercises in which I am associated can by themselves produce thelasting effects on the way in which the institutions and culture ofWhitehall actually operate which your Administration wants.3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALRecn 1       13.    I recommend that, building on and extending its experience so far,Government should decide on a programme with two aims:i. Less Government, using fewer staff better.ii. A more robust and reliable managerial framework, including  Better control and management of resources by Ministersin their Departments.  Better collective control and management of resourcesby Cabinet.  Updated priorities for Whitehall.LESS GOVERNMENT, USING FEWER STAFF BETTER14. What follows complements Mr Channon&apos;s paper on Civil Servicemanpower.15. Mr Channon&apos;s paper shows what the Civil Service costs. Thesefigures are very large indeed.   It helps me to get them into perspectivto remind myself that even my small unit* costs the taxpayer  6,500a month.16. The route to reduce cost is &quot;less Government using fewer staffbetter&quot;.   I suggest that this means looking at what causes   staff numbejand thinking the unthinkable.17*   The &quot;unthinkable&quot; occurs in two sorts of question:   &quot;How muchwork should government do?&quot;   (For example, a Minister might ask, &quot;Whatdoes this activity add to the common good?   Would it matter if I stoppedoing it?&quot;).   The second question is, &quot;How should it he done?&quot;. (Forexample, a Minister might ask, &quot;Could I do this with half the staff?Do the working methods used give me and the taxpayer value for money?&quot;)18.   But I believe very firmly that the &quot;unthinkable&quot; needs setting inthe context of a well thought out manpower policy.   Such a policy mighthave as its aims:       reducing the scale and scope of government activity byceasing or reducing functions*  One US, one Economic Adviser, one Executive Officer, one PersonalSecretary.4
CONFIDENTIALI       taking in no more qualified manpower than can be justified       using this manpower to provide services to Ministers andto the public which are of good quality, cost effectiveand satisfying for staff.19. There are both Service-wide and departmental issues here,teen 2      In the former case, I recommend that in order to get the radicalreform it wants, your Administration should address itself to some(stringent test questions, ega.     Can we reduce the number of functions and activitiesidentified with basic command units (in some cases AssistantSecretary, in others at higher or lower grade levels) by25 per cent?b.     Can we reduce the length of the Civil Service hierarchy byat least three grades, so taking fewer people in and making moreelbow room available for the talent we do consume?   Prima faciecandidates for examination are those of Second, Deputy andUnder Secretary, Senior Principal and one point in the Executiveladder, but others will be able to advise better than I whichsix or so grades might be looked at.20. On departmental issues, I am struck by the force of two recentremarks by Ministers.   Mr Jenkin referred in the Budget debate to theneed for unremitting pressure by Ministers on the cost of administration.I agree that leadership by Ministers in getting down to brass tacks isof great importance.21. Another Minister has told me that he needs the &quot;seeing eye&quot; ofsomeone who is &quot;managerially motivated&quot; to help him.22..   Ministers plainly need someone to prepare the issues for them.Seen 3      I recommend that it should be that of a senior official of provenIaptitude for action.   He should work up for his Minister and PermanentSecretary ways of saving and simplifying.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL23*   These thoughts may be helpful:a. The official should draw on knowledge where it resides.This will often be well down at the CA/CO - HEO/SEO levels,especially in executive or administrative operations.b. Things to be reviewed might include:  Activities and functions that consume large staff andother resources.  Complexity of rules and regulations and its relationshipwith staff numbers.  Areas of work with high staff turnover or absenteeism.  Scope for mechanisation.  Need for, cost and intelligibility of administrativeforms sent out by the department.  Cost of meetings, official travel, non-vocational training.]A MORE ROBUST AND RELIABLE MANAGERIAL FRAMEWORK24. A Minister recently told me that his management problem was apractical one, a combination of the lack of &quot;managerially motivated&quot;officials, ignorance of the right questions to ask and a feeling thathe could not make things happen differently.   He thought that a fewsimple pointers to good management would help.25. I understand that view.   I have already suggested in my advice toMinisters on departmental running costs questions about their departmentas a whole and about its component parts.   The scrutiny programme alsoprovides for detailed questioning of work.   I am very ready to talk toMinisters about their experience so far and to offer them furthersuggestions.    (I would in any case like to talk to Ministers in the courof the work mentioned below,)   But I am convinced that the issues demandsomething more than simple pointers.26. I attach an Appendix containing extracts from my recent submissionon &quot;conventions&quot; (which I now call &quot;lasting reforms&quot;).   You havecommissioned work on these but it may be helpful to set out here themain aims as I see them.6CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL27. All my experience of business and Whitehall convinces me thatyour Administration is right to work for excellence in two types ofmanagement, by Ministers in their departments and by Ministerscollectively around the Cabinet table.28. That is easier said than done.   My recommendations try to helpby dealing with both formalities and people.29. The formalities may seem humdrum and un-British.   But they involvesomething that I regard as of crucial importance to good managementanywhere, especially in government with its responsibility for hugeassets, namely identifying and fixing accountability for managingresources.30. In brief, I am recommending defining or clarifying:- the managerial role of the Minister, from whom authoritydescends (recognising that management is but one of his duties)- the responsibility and the accountability of officials underhim, especially that of Accounting Officers and key managers  the financial framework within which management takes place  the aims and methods of central control and the desirable balancebetween this and departmental control.31. I do not intend this work to be elaborate or protocolaire. Ishall be at pains to include in it practical advice, for example onlooking back at policies which have captured resources and on establishingwhether implementation of agreed policies has brought the looked-forbenefits.32. I have also included two suggestions aimed at testing the waycentral control works in practice and in relation to departmental control,ie the operation of the annuality rule and the cost effects of regulationsand standards, eg in the health and safety field.7CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL33. I firmly believe that such work is necessary and that it wouldcrown much useful -Ehinking that had been going on slowly over thelast 10 years or so.34. My recommendations on people are of extreme importance, in myview.   Definition and systems, however clear and excellent, are nogood unless those who have responsibility care about and work for valuefor money, are encouraged to do so and are rewarded for achievement.35. In brief, I am recommending the examination of changes which wouldupdate the priorities of Whitehall and bring on &quot;managerially motivated&apos;men and women, by  a steady progression towards the employment in postsresponsible for finance and resources of those qualifiedin financial management and management accountancy  revising the rewards and promotion, system, so as to encouragegood managers- devising a &quot;succession policy&quot; so as to fill management posts,especially senior ones, with individuals with the right trackrecord.- providing good leadership and good working conditions forstaff, especially those well down the line and thoserepresenting the Government to its clients and customers.Been 1(para 13)SUMMARY36.     My recommendations areA plan of lasting reform, embodying two aims - less government, usingfewer staff better, and operating within a more robust and reliablemanagement framework.Recn 2(para 19)As part of the first aim the Government should ask stringent questionsabout the numbers of functions needed and of grades in the Civil Servicehierarchy.8CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALBeen 3        Also a senior official of proven aptitude for action should bepara 22)v &apos;   responsible for the preparation of savings and simplification ineach department.37*   I am making no formal recommendation in respect of the secondaim, since the work outlined in the Appendix to this minute has already-been commissioned.7DEREK RAYNER18 April 19809CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALAPPENDIXTHE EFFICIENCY OF CENTRAL GOVERNMENT:   LASTING REFORMS[Note:   The following edited extracts relate to the four aims for aSprogramme of lasting reforms outlined in paragraph 13 of myminute of 18 April and to the programme of work which youhave authorised.]THE SCALE OF GOVERNMENT ACTIVITY1.     I firmly believe that it should be possible to reduce the scaleof Government activity by diminishing its functions and to reduce theIlength of the Civil Service hierarchy.   I think it very important forthe morale of the nation that the Government should adopt a determinedbut measured approach to these tasks, allowing time to think it through.2*     Civil Service manpower policy is the subject of Mr Channon&apos;s paperand is not further considered here.   But I see it as part and parcel ofa complete programme of reform.THE MANAGEMENT OF RESOURCES IN DEPARTMENTS3.     Your Administration is working for excellence in two types ofmanagement, by Ministers in their departments and by Ministers collectivelyaround the Cabinet table.4.     There are obviously limits to the extent to which Ministers can orshould become managers of their departments and of the resources in theircharge.   Moreover, the responsibilities of Ministers differ accordingto the nature of their departments.   Nevertheless, under the authorityvested in them by the Prime Minister and by Parliament, it is indisputablythey who have the ultimate power of management.   Indisputably, too, theonly power under which their officials act is delegated to them by theirMinister.   But there is in many minds a lack of clarity about therespective roles of Ministers and officials.   I therefore recommend thatcn 1 a.     The managerial authority of the Minister should be definedso that his role is plainly established and understood vis-a-visthat of his officials.10CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALb.     No less important, the good habits that Ministers practiseQua manager can be defined for succeeding generations ofMinisters.   One good habit that exemplifies the whole is theneed to look hack at the reasons why resources were committedto particular policy objectives and to compare performanceachieved with target intended.5.     It follows from defining the Minister&apos;s role that one must definethe managerial role of officials.   From top to bottom, officialsshould know the nature and extent of their personal responsibilityfor resources.   I recommend that the responsibility and accountabilityof officials should be clarified in working instructions, somewhat asfollows  a. The authority under which officials operate is that ofMinisters.   They have no external accountability of their own,notably to Parliament and its Select Committees where theirtask is to explain what has been done for and in the name ofMinisters.b. The authority delegated by a Minister to his PermanentSecretary should be both general and specific; the expectationsMinisters have of the official heads of their departments shouldbe defined on an across-Whitehall basis in the interests ofconsistency and have added requirements &apos;special to particulardepartments.c. This should replace the existing letter of appointmentissued to a new Accounting Officer by the Permanent Secretaryto the Treasury and should include specified duties on suchitems as the control of money and manpower; management of thepersonnel of the department; the control of operations andorganisation; and control of the assets in the department&apos;s&apos;keeping, with a special emphasis on land, buildings and otherproperty.   (For reasons explained below I attach particularimportance to the Permanent Secretary&apos;s overall responsibility forthe management and care of his Minister&apos;s most important asset,namely staff.)11CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALd.     Below the Permanent Secretary, the line of accountabilityfor authority delegated by the Minister should continue in aclear line to the lowest levels of the department. Neitherthe Minister nor the Permanent Secretary can manage everythinghimself.   It is essential to good management that specificmanagerial authority should be delegated to specific officerswho should then be given the opportunity to put it to gooduse.   Accordingly, I would propose a definition which inter alia- specified the management responsibility of heads ofunits or blocks of work beneath the Permanent Secretary;- nominated some of those heads as Assistant AccountingOfficers so that the burden of explanation before thePublic Accounts Committee was shared effectively;- in the annual procedures for reporting on staff placeda much heavier emphasis than at present on capacity touse resources effectively and economically; and- enabled Ministers and senior officials to hold theirsubordinates consistently and fairly to account.6.     The Permanent Secretary has two right-hand men, the PrincipalFinance and Establishment Officers.   In part, the results I shouldlike to see span the divide between &quot;spending&quot; departments and the&quot;central&quot; departments (HM Treasury and the CSD), but it is nonethelesssensible to mention them here.   I recommend as follows  a.     At present money is managed by the FFO and other resourcesby the FEO.   The FFO looks to the Treasury; the PEO looks tothe CSD,   This can cause discontinuity in the management andcontrol of resources.   As a matter of general principle, itwould be right to re-integrate the control of resources withindepartments, but it may not be practicable in all cases becauseof the scale and complexity of functions and resources.Nevertheless, I regard the maximum feasible re-integrationpossible as a result to be worked for.12CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALb.     There is a question of huge importance about the nature ofthe skills which should be brought to bear on the managementof resources, notably money.   As part of recommendation 3, Irecommend a planned and progressive movement towards theseresults  .      The PFO should be qualified in financial managementor management accountancy.- Until that can be achieved, no PFO should be appointedwho has no familiarity with the.contribution which canbe made to his work by people with such qualifications.- The PFO&apos;s subordinate staff should have eitherappropriate qualifications acquired outside the Serviceor appropriate training acquired inside the Service.- Such qualified staff should be employed also in unitsreporting to the Permanent Secretary charged with theexamination of operations and management systems andwith the duty of probing in depth where the Minister orthe Permanent Secretary think this necessary.- Such staff should have an absolute right of entry toany part of the department; their programme of workshould be decided by the Permanent Secretary inconsultation with the Minister; and   allowance madefor the greater accountability I want to see   it shouldnot be open to line management to &quot;veto&quot; the applicationof their findings.   (Similar arrangements should be inforce in respect of audit staff working to the PEO, ashe is now, namely staff inspectors, 0 &amp; M and managementservices, whose functions and training should beexamined.)THE MANAGEMENT OF RESOURCES AT THE CENTRE7.    As we face public expenditure over the next two decades it seemsclear that the best possible balance between the collective responsibilof Cabinet and the several responsibilities of departmental Ministersis needed.13CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL8. I recommend that    4_ a.   The aims and practices of central control should he re-stated to update the Plowden concept of partnership betweenthe spending and central departments to take account ofmodern circumstances; to provide a clear postulation andunderstanding of the respective responsibilities of the spendingand central departments; and to provide a basis on which thetypes, numbers and qualifications of the staff needed by thecentral departments can be stipulated.b. Particular attention should be paid in this to -i.   the tasks of the central departments in assisting theCabinet to play its collective role in the allocation andcontrol of resources, including the means by which theCabinet can be assured that systems and operations throughwhich the need for resources is calculated and the resourcesthemselves are managed or spent are well devised andeconomical;ii.   the correct balance, in present circumstances, betweencontrols over micro and macro volumes of expenditure; andiii.   the regime for financial management by Ministers andofficials (see below).c. The role and responsibilities of the central departments inrelation to systems of control within departments and to theefficiency and effective use of resources should also be statedas matters of principle and practice.9. I make that recommendation because, in my view, the relationshipbetween the Cabinet as a whole and individual Ministers must beone in which the former looks to the latter to take the responsibilityfor good management in their departments.     But transitory Ministershave to rely upon the Civil Service to provide them with and tooperate good systems of resource control and management. This14CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALobviously introduces the risk that, in terms of management, theMinister is merely a decorative element.     The underlyingstructures and practices which outlast successive Ministers shouldtherefore be of quality which convinces Ministers that they arestanding on firm ground.   It is, even so, unreasonable for Ministersto divest themselves of their constitutional responsibility for,and they need a means of, satisfying themselves that the systemsare of good design and effectively administered.The financial framework10.   There is already much interesting work going on in Whitehallto reform and strengthen this.     I would regard the main points asthese (necessarily for the purposes of this minute expressed in avery summary form).a. The planning and control of public expenditure would bemore effective if particular departments were responsible forparticular Public Expenditure Survey programmes, rather thanthese being divided between departments as some at presentare.b. The Votes for which a department is responsible shouldcover   i.   its own operational and administrative costs,ii.   grants to bodies outside the department whose costsit meets wholly or partly and iii.   benefits, grants andpayments for whose administration the department is responsible.c. The presentation of expenditures should be in a formatcovering the management needs of the Minister in charge,those of the Treasury and Civil Service Department.   It shouldpromote better cost control, facilitate the development ofmanagement accounting systems and underpin the delegation offinancial authority to appropriate levels of management (whichcould then all the more readily be held accountable for thatauthority).15CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL11. I recommend that the work at present going on in and betweenthe Treasury and Civil Service Department should be broughttogether   with a view to   the   submission of proposals toMinisters later this year covering -- the structure of Public Expenditure Survey programmes- the relationship between these and the organisation ofdepartments- the presentation of information on departmental expenditurein the Supply Estimates, taking account of the needs ofMinisters and senior officials, line management, the centraldepartments and Parliament- the clarification of accountability for particular blocksj.. of departmental expenditure.12. I should like to make two subsidiary recommendations. First,I recommend that the so called &quot;annuality rule&quot; should be examined.13. This is the rule under which money Voted for consumption ina particular year must be consumed in that year if the budget forthe succeeding year is not to be reduced by a corresponding amount.There are two broad arguments.     It is claimed that allowing flexibilitybetween financial years will promote better money management andavoid the incentive to an end year spending spree.   On the other hand,it is said that flexibility would lessen the pressure on departmentsto improve their financial control and the accuracy of their estimatingtechniques and give the impression that Ministers are relaxing theirgrip on public spending.14. It is argued further against flexibility that it would tend toincrease public expenditure.     This is because at presentdepartments &quot;aim off&quot; from their public expenditure programmes soas to avoid exceeding their cash limits.     &quot;Aiming Off&quot; leads toa shortfall in expenditure of about  1 billion per annum. Underend-year flexibility that shortfall would be decreased because theunder-spend achieved by departments in year 1 would be carried forwardinto year 2 so that the department would &quot;aim off&quot; from a higher16CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALtotal; in year 2 therefore it would be likely to spend more thanit otherwise would.     (The fact that this argument can be made is aninteresting comment on the existing state of central control,I think.)13.   These arguments need examination.     My instinct is that existing&quot;annuality&quot; arrangements do much to encourage the &quot;easy come, easy go&quot;attitude to public money, But I am quite prepared to believe thatI am mistaken about this.16. My second additional recommendation is somewhat similar, inthat it also relates to the way in which existing financial planningmechanisms operate to pick up and warn Ministers about costs whichmay be unseen at first.     The Treasury, in consort with the Ministryof Defence, CSD and PSA, have argued to me that there is a need forgreater cost consciousness in the imposition and application ofregulations and standards (eg housing, fire, health and safety). Thisis because compliance may be complex to operate and expensive forboth central and local agencies to police and for the private andpublic sector to respond to.     The aim would be to ensure thatdepartments are conscious of the costs arising from new and existingregulations and standards and take steps to avoid unnecessary costs.17. As part of the current round of scrutinies, the Health andSafety Commission is examining the costs and benefits of regulationsRecn 7 in its field.     I recommend that lessons derived from this exerciseand from other experiences should be promulgated by the centraldepartments.THE CULTURE OF WHITEHALL18. I have a high regard of long standing for many senior officials,whom I regard as among the most dedicated, hard working and effectivepeople I know.   Equally, the junior staff I have encountered thistime round convince me that the Government is the fortunate employerof a wealth of talent and enthusiasm for the public good.17CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL19. However, permanence; privacy; a certain lack of definition ofroles; the steady accretion of pay. and rewards; excellent pensionarrangements; the &quot;easy come, easy go&quot; attitude of the nation overthe last 25 years or so have made a government a comparativelycomfortable place to be.Rewards and penalties v20. It is a real conundrum in a system of hierarchical progressionthrough grades and automatic, incremental progression through payscales to reward equitably those who do very well and penalise thosewho are slack.    In business, higher management decides who should berewarded by special advancement or special payment, but the two setsof circumstances are so different as to rule out any easy read-acrossfrom one to the other.21. However, I regard rewarding success and making the best use oftalent early as so important that I recommend that, building on workalready in hand, proposals should be brought forward to Ministers inrespect of these propositions -a. that success in post where no further hierarchical progressionis possible should be rewarded by bonus payments or by personalpromotion (as opposed to the upgrading of the post)}b. that it should be made possible to advance individuals bytwo or more grades in recognition of their track record, potentialand the needs of the Service; andc. that individuals should no longer be entitled to automaticannual increments.18CONFIDENTIAL
22. I attach much more importance to rewarding success and bringingtalented people on early than to penalising the time server, but Iam certain that as part of the above means must be found of bringingthe cost home to the slack or the profligate.Management succession23. Management skills are, I believe, still underrated where theyare in fact essential to the efficiency, cost consciousness and indeedeffectiveness of Government.     Government has increasingly taken ontasks which were unknown in Whitehall when many of the qualities whichdenote top officials were developed.     Concurrently there has been agrowth in the numbers of scientific and professional staffs, many ofwhose skills are limited to their specialism.     Such skills are oftenof a high order.   Too often, in my view, the recognition of this facthas led to their appointment to management positions for which they .have had no training nor indeed atpitude (this being the only way inwhich their excellence can be recognised).24. I am conscious of many activities to improve awareness ofmanagement skills, both by internal and external courses and bysecondment to industry, and of work through such devices as the SeniorAppointments Selection Committee to bring on suitable people* Therefore,rightly or wrongly, I do not lay the blame for management incompetencewhere it occurs at the door of training or opportunity to learn fromobserving management in the private sector.   Rather it springs primarilyfrom the indifference, of political leadership over the years to thequality of management in their departments, such indifference oftenarising from total lack of experience of running large organisations,and from too ready acceptance that the accountability for the way thedepartment discharges its responsibility is through the AccountingOfficer and his answerability to the Public Accounts Committee.19CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL25. My recommendations for defining the respective responsibilitiesof Ministers and officials and the framework for accountabilitywithin departments should, if successful, go part of the way towardsproducing reform.     But I think it is also necessary that eachdepartment should have a clear plan of succession to its key managementposts.   Such a plan would affect both individuals and specificmanagement practices, eg length of time to be spent in posts acquiringexperience and the training to be undertaken.   The issues are of suchimportance that it would be unreasonable to expect departments to takethem on their own.   So I recommend that the Personnel Group of theCSD should prepare a model &quot;succession policy&quot; for the Service as awhole, which can then be applied to themselves by departments with suchcentral co-ordination as may he needed.   This policy might be submittedto Ministers in draft later this year.Staff morale26. Ministers usually have a close relationship with their Private,Permanent and Deputy Secretaries.     Their relationships with theirother staff are increasingly formal and remote according to grade andlocation.     This is particularly important given that the big battalionsin the Civil Service are not engaged in policy work in Whitehall, buton operational and functional work in the provinces, very often indirect contact with the public.     Unless enough time is set aside togain a better knowledge of people at work,&apos; at all levels, and a consistentinterest is shown in the views of staff on the difficulties they faceand the suggestions they have to alleviate these I doubt whetherMinisters will be actively supported in their drive to improve efficiencyand reduce costs. thr27. Too often staff perceive Government&apos;s intended economy drivesthrough overall cuts in numbers and rarely by the removal orsimplification of functions.     Government proposals often add to thetasks to be done.   The traditional responses to inefficiency or mal-  practice seem invariably to lead to additional checking and monitoringwhile the responsibility for interpreting and implementing complexinstructions (as in Social Security benefits) rests on the most juniorstaff.20CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL28. The use of appropriate office equipment to offset labourintensive tasks seems to me too infrequent.   The development of theuse of computers has been uneven.    Some departments have an over-capacity; others continue to do tasks in a manner appropriate to an -earlier age. =S Modern typewriters, printing equipment, deskcalculators, word processing and mini-computers all have a part toplay in upgrading the quality of life at clerical level.   In myjudgment there is room for more development in these fields, althoughI acknowledge that some advances have been blocked by the staffassociations.29. Personnel policies have been centralised in the CSD sinceFulton.     The Pay Research Unit does a professional job in assessingpay comparability through detailed job comparisons and the presentpension arrangements are generous in my view.   Even so, civilservants often feel they are a deprived class as their masters, thepoliticians, in general show scant attention to the quality of theworking environment.     Accommodation ranges from the very good tovery poor and decor from gimmicky modern to shabby or even decrepit.Work services can be slow to respond to problems of heating, brokenwindows and necessary maintenance while the provision of food andamenities can be very poor compared with large employers of similarstaff. I50.   I believe that Ministers who show positive interest in the well-being of their staffs can reap large benefits in terms of loyalty butthat they and their senior officials have to work hard to keepleadership in their own hands.     Such leadership would improve theworking environment, often at very little cost, and lead to animprovement in productivity through greater staff stability and reducedabsenteeism.    (I should like to see an analysis of staff turnover,particularly in the London area and the South, as the level that I havecome across in my random visits is alarmingly high, in some cases21CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL45 per cent per annum.     Such staff are often engaged where thetraining period is 13 weeks long and during their early months,after training, they need to refer continually to supervisor gradesfor guidance.   This frustrates the supervisors and does not preventlow standards of competence and productivity at clerical level.)10      31.   I recommend therefore that -a. a policy for enabling staff to give of their best should beformulated; and 1b. the Government should seize the psychological advantage inpresenting it.32. I would like to make a further recommendation here. TheNational Staff Side, in a paper they have put to me, have argued thatthe possibility of being called upon to explain to a Select Committee,perhaps several years after the event, every action and everydecision severely inhibits effective management, makes for &quot;alibiconsciousness&quot; and produces mountains of paper in order to record actionsand justify decisions, purely in case of future need.   They haveargued further that the establishment of &quot;departmental&quot; Select Committeeswill add to the burdens of explanation and justification.   They donot complain about all this, but have suggested that the implicationsfor Civil Service efficiency and resources should be appreciated byboth Parliament and the Government.33. I sympathise with this to the extent that as a nation we needto recognise the costs as well as the benefits of Parliamentaryaccountability.   I therefore recommend an experiment whereby in thenext session of Parliament a department should keep a record of thecost of resources committed in support of Ministers&apos; and their seniorofficials1 Parliamentary work and that the results should be publishedin a suitable form.22CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
