<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/128/0 images: 28-34</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SJCRET. 0.P.3308.fTHIS POOOliMT 13 MB ERpyBBTY OF HIS BRIMHI0 MMJSBTyJb SOVERHM3U)C A B IJ E I s   IqSUPPIY AMD TRANSPORT COMMITTEE.FUTURE. OF THE SUPPLY AND TRANSPORT ORGANISATION,Memorandum by thd Chairman of the Supply and Transport &quot;Committee.On Maroh 3rd, 1921, the Cabinet (Cabinet 10 (21) Conclusion 6) had under consideration a memorandum (CP, 2628) by myself and a memorandum by the Pood Controller (0.P.2611) dealing with the Supply and Transport organisation. These memoranda arose out&apos; cf the discussion whioh todk placeiat a Conference of Ministors held on January 10th, 1921, (conclusion 1), in regard to an earlier memorandum by ma (CP.8432) In whioh I raised the whole question of the oontinued existenoe during times of industrial pnaoe of an organisation for meeting strikes.The deoisions taken at tho Conference of Ministers held on January 10th, 1921, and the Cabinet meeting held on March 3rd, 1921, authorised expenditure on the Supply and Transport organisation of  83,050 per annum.     Of this sum not more than  64,000 was to bo spent on emergency food servioes during the present finanoial year, and it was agreed that the whole question of the maintenance of an anti-strike organisation should be reconsidered in the autumn.     I therefore bring the question once more before the Cabinet.I have obtained revised estimates of the oost of the organisation during times of industrial peace together with statements of the expenditure which occurred during theoc-al/
ooal strike 1921, and where no expenditure took plaae, estimates of expenditure for the operation of the full machinery.     The figures are as follows :-Running expenditure Cost during an during normal times,   emergency.per annum. Coal 2,000CommunicationsElectrical servicesFood ServicesMotor SpiritProtectionPublicityRoad TransportStores&quot;.7ator Transport AdmiraltyBoard of Trade (other than food servioes q.v)Scottish Office Supply Department V/ar Office 15,000 ( 290 per week) 300 36* 500Ml Ml Ml 720 Ml 400 MilMlMl 400 MlTotal    55.320 per annum,Sept/Oct.1920  44,700 April/July 1921 40,700 (loss on coal imported this year, say - 1,000,000). 3,566 (perweek). 350 perannum. 97,050 (1921 ooal strike). &quot;300 - per annumNil(Establishment (      100 per week (Other  54,197 ( (1921 coal ( strike).Ho estimatepossible. 60,000 (stores &amp; office pre-miaes) 731 per week  63 per weekMil 800 (1921 ooal strike) 2,000 (1921ooal strike)Nil(Dogs not include (special military (measures,su^h as (the raising of (Defence Force.
As regards tho above sections of the Supply and Transport organisation, I should like my colleagues to bear in mind tho following facts :-POOD SKIiVICIiS. The coal strike and tho threat of ageneral strike this year necessitated a rapid expansion of the nucleus staff engaged in- these services.   This was reduced tc normal dimensions in July, and a progressive reduction of emergency staff is taking place vritb a view to demobilisation on 31st August 1982, or such earlier data as may bo fixed,   The sehftino which will come into force on the 1st October, contem-platos a staff of 6 responsible! and subordinate officers in each of the old 15 Food Divisions, with a controlling staff of 10 at head quarters at an annual cost of 236,500 (the figure given in the list above).       So long as a food transport organisation is necessary it is essential to maintain a separate register of food-carrying vehicles, and this necessity precludes any considerable further reductions of staff,PUBLICITY. The organisation -ised in the last twocoal strikes was base!! very largely on the experience of publicity officers in various Departments.    The services of those officers have since been dispensed with on grounds of economy.I am informed by the Ministers responsible for publicity during tho last ooal strike (Mr. IIcGurdy, Mr. Amery, and Sir Philip Lloyd-Groame) that without publicity officers it will be impossible to restart a publicity organisation at short notice.     ThGy, therefore, suggest that there should be in each of the principal Departments an officer thoroughly acquainted with the work of the Department, having some experience of publicity work, who will be able to devote all his time to publicity in an emergency.
If tho Cabinet decide that a nuclous publicity organisation should &quot;bo retained in being, I suggest that Departments should be Instructed to detail one officer each for this work.PROTECT!Oil. iieither- tho Homo Office nor the ProtectionSub-Committee maintains any special organisation for Supply and Transport purposes.   During a period of emergency, additional work is, of course, thrown on the Police, and some increase of expenditure is involved under that head;   but this would bo tho case whether the Supply and Transport organisation as a whole were abandoned or not.     Indeed, but for tho effective coordination secured by tho Supply and Transport Committee and its Sub-Committee the Police expenditure would have been greater than it has been;    and certainly, if there ware a failure in the food supply and disturbances resulted,  there would ho greatly Increased Police expenditure and possibly heavy claims to be paid under the Riot (Damages) Act, 1886.ROAD TRAIT SPORT. The expenditure on this organisationduring normal times is limited to incidental travelling and other expenses incurred by the 13 Road Commissioners and 90 Road Officers distributed at various centres in the country.   Up to the present these gentlemen have been acting in a volun-tary capacity, but if it is proposed to maintain a permanent organisation for carrying on road transport during strikes it is not likely that thoy will be able to continue to volunteer their services as they have been doing during the period of acute industrial unrest which   has continued
for the past 18 months.    Even if, as private persons, they were prepared to continue to act for the Government in their present capacity,, it woulfi probably be necessary to regularise their position by offering them some form of honorarium or emolument, and at the same time formally to obtain the consent of the various Local Authorities to the assumption of these duties by their officers9SuPPLY DPJP/JtT^ErTT,     This Department is one of the most elaborate sections of the Supply and Transport organisation^ It has under its control through the Civil Commissioners (^ho are of ministerial rank) some 90 or so volunteer Committees throughout the country.   These Committees are responsible for recruiting labour during strikes and generally for carrying on,, in conjunction with Local Authorities, services on which the life of the community&apos; depends.    After the Supply Department and its connected organisations are disbanded it will be impossible to re-create an equivalent organisation at short notice.    It has taken many months to create the present organisations In favour of the retention of the Supply Department, I may mention the following facts:-(1)    The chairmen of Local Committees provide a useful body of trustworthy personnel throxxghout the country, and can be employed to sound local opinion^ and approach Local Authorities unofficially.. -  They can even supersede Local Authorities of doubtful . loyalty. -
(2)    The chairman in conjunction with the local Authorities form an admirable nucleus for setting up a news and propaganda service &apos; in the provinces in the event of dis-affeetion among Post Office employoss; (Z)    Ho cost or expenditure of Public money need be involved since the Chief Inspectors of the Ministry of Health, can, I am informed, quite well keep tho present system in being in the ordinary course of their duties,   ^ven if the entire body- of Chairmen is not maintained, a nucleus of efficient men in important centres would be valuable.(4)    Generally if the Cabinet think that the present organisation is on too large a scale it can be reduced very much and held in readiness-ness for expansion at need.As regards the- whole question of maintaining an organisation to combat,strikes; my personal opinion is that the time has now come for the disbandraent of the Supply and. Transport Organisation.-     This -machinery has been in existence for 2 years and has, I think, served its purpose well...    It was essential that for tho maintenance of order and decent living the Government should take upon itself during the period of unrest which followed the war, the duty of protecting the community frem the irresponsible attacks of extremists.    The war had created in the people
a hat it of looking to the Government for direction and initiative in almost every department of life, and the Government was the only &quot;body which possessed sufficient strength to oppose&apos; the great industrial organisations, This state of things has now passed.     Private initiative has onco more reasserted itself.    The power of the Trade Unions has visibly diminished, principally from economic causes, and the general strike has failed. I do not think it will be tried again in the immediate future.     Moreover every section of Government machinery, however long established or however necessary,  is subjected to fierce criticism and all expenditure is intently scrutinised.It is for these reasons that I suggest that the Government should now disband the Supply and Transport Organisation.     &quot;Thother a publio announcement should be made or not is a matter for consideration.Should, tho Cabinet decide that the Supply and Transport Organisation should continue, I must ask thorn to nominate a new Chairman for tho Committee in view of my forthcoming resignation.(Intd.)      B.G.Ministry of Transport,j3.SeptoJBber 15th, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
