<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/128/0 images: 115-116</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ll-HIS D0CUM.3NT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS JRITAN1UC MAJESTY&amp;3 GOVERNMENT)H3T. , 3322.CABINET.DESPATCH OP ROYAL AIR FORCE DRAFTS TO THE EAST IN VIEW OF POSSIBLE&apos; CONTINGENCIES 4 0IN IRELAND. ACMemorandum by the Air Staff. (* Reference Cabinet 72(21) Conclusion 2) At a meeting held on the 25th of August, 1921, the cabinet took a number of decisions relative to the despatch of draftsfor the Army in India.2. Two of these decisions closely concern the Royal Air Force, These are as follows:--(a) That the drafts for India due to leave this country on October 1st, should not be despatched without further instructions from the Cabinet:-(b) That in the meantime the Commander-in-Chief in India should have authority to retain there all time-expired men.3.      As regards (a), the Air Staff are of opinion that this decision should not be mado applicable to the Royal Air Foroe onthe following grounds(a) The Royal Air Force drafts due for despatch tp the East during the forthcoming trooping season only number 3,300.     Irrespective of these drafts, three air squadrons are in reserve in England against possible emergencies.(b) Ireland is an unfavourable theatre for the employment of aircraft, both on account of geographical and climatic conditions and also because of the nature of the trouble, i.e. a mixture of civil riot and military opposition, makes It difficult to use air forces effectively.(c) The air forces in Ireland are up to strength and General Macready has stated that he will only require that they should be maintained in that condition, and the War Office support this view: this will be possible without touching drafts . for the East. *(d) Air reinforcements are exceptionally urgently       v needed abroad.   In the East the Air Force is alnM?s&amp; daily engaged in minor operations where it is of *\ the greatest value and tends to great economy in the use of ground forces.   Moreover, although the total number of 2,300 is small, these drafts areto a great extent required to make up deficiencies in technical trades, and in a highly technical service even small deficiencies exercise a proportional influence on the efficiency of thejwhole.(e)..
(e) finally, in the oase of Mesopotamia the Royal Air Force has been given increased responsibilities and drafts of air personnel to that oountry will result in the releaso of many times their number of British and Indian trocps. These will be held up indefinitely if the trooping programme oannot be carried out,4, In view of these considerations the Air Staff would urge that these men will be of far greater value abroad, dis-trlbutod in their proper trades in the correct proportion, than retained in this oountry as replacements of extremely doubtful value for Ireland.5, As regards decision (b), that the Commander-in-chief in India should retain all time-expired men, the Air Staff recognise that any preferential treatment of Royal Air Force*personnel mi^ht^give rise to adverse comment.   They do not, therefore, desire to oppose the retention of time-expired -Royal Air Force personnel, should the Indian Government advocate this step, but since the numbers are so small (under 500) they hdpe that it will be possible to allow their return.6. Since the first drafts are already due to sail anearly decision is essential.Ministry. gl&amp;gsway, W.CLumber 16th. 1921

</content>
</cab>
