<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/128/0 images: 235-262</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I    SECRET, 1CABINET.&amp; REPORT OH HEVOEOTI Q:*AHY OROANISATI f. -RE-I circulated ny fne Home floors tary)aIT IS HSQIJSgTKP THAT THIS DOCTTCT TAX BT3 TfTSATJD AS HIGHLY CONFIDENT!A&amp;*2, * hltehall Pardons, 3. .1.* 24th Septerfbeiv 1381* f
\ -M-x-z  ) )i   This Document is the Prooerty of       V-;-    163t His -Srita/unic. Majesty fs Governmentilujg&amp;r-- &quot; ---f^^^^sgffof/Aei g   t-nw DIREOEORATE^Og -3NTELLI0SNCE; i 3tit    . eldi aaoqerX no $-os oXtfaatfJa Bi&amp;JbxfH^ifljpJotgftto^p J^aioaaaii. Report No.124 t   , Scotland House, S.W.1Xia        A   beecboiq odd snex nci-Jv. :e  22nd: &quot;September, 1921.;a*e3ftot7 eoolcf       ^-V f;r/e tr^/ow wctt sol aicod lov/xi;;pr:o        iteaxftei evari        .:     uaz via aie^olqjae eiftf-     REPORT ON REVOLUTIONARY cORGAN/ISATIONS IK THE UNITED KINGDOMfio.t.:-,:,;r,i-;.?, :; fisaxr^o aarl tdaX o3 co oeaaw eotrfio:?    ..Xaoid-X- o      aeciioaofi (0 &amp;aiA* A&amp;.fey v^h^^ojna^Seoretory)erajbsg or ft ftoow^acf ieonexe!t&amp;oO 3 lo Joeaabia or &quot;xocS tocTHK UNEMPLOYED:WvvjJi*....Page 1ancipREfCOMMUNISTS^, .vA .&quot;..&apos;V.* ^vi:*:V*]i c^iof.                  . 9THE YOUNG; &quot;COMMUNIST iINTSHNAT lON^Irdi tx*.......... &quot;12TBE RED TRADE UNION INTERNATIONAL.............. &quot; 14THE C0AL--MINER3--.-.^ * *..... *...................... &quot; 16SYLVIA PANKHURST..................... I......... &quot; 17JOHN MACLEAN................................... &quot;20THS &quot;DAILY HERALD&quot;............................. &quot; 21SINN FEIN IN GREAT BRITAIN...................... JJ 21IRELAND ..............23SUMMARYThough there are signs that the unemployed are becoming tired of their communist leaders and there have been fewer and leas well-attended demonstrations during the past week, the temper of the unemployed is becoming strained and the tendency of the violent minority towards lawlessness is increasing.There were disorderly scenes in Woolwich, Kentish Town, West London Police Court, Clerkenwell Police Court, Hevington and in Aberdeen, but in two cases only had the /   police to draw their truncheons.The Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress and the Labour Party Executive are pressing for the assembling of Parliament to deal with unemployment.The National Administrative Council of Unemployed is making progress in organisation and is arranging large demonstrations for the &quot;week of national agitation&quot;, beginning on October 10th.There is little purely communist activity, owing to the attention paid by the Party to the unemployed.October 2nd - October 9th Is to be a &quot;Red Youth&quot; week of propaganda.A summary is given of an interesting secret report of titie Red Trade Union International Congress at Moaoow.There is much discontent among the miners, especiallyin/
itt!CSbutibi&amp;fl[UaB^DP)ffifaBKC^g^m wages reductione ejpyejp^a after September 3^.n?irFT!I8HBiajority realise trra-^tireir f ineno ialf qoc^J^llQBa^^ders., dijaatio &amp;G$im,00 aiblo.     1rniWooB . ..*SX.olLJ*t.oaeff .:. v The engineer sr., are; negotiating .w,lftlr IVj 1 iffrrgfrnptsringnrBJqpitoifcoa^ federation regarding the prop bead withdrawal of IZjffi bonus -f civ. time, workers 88&amp;/% ftijtaF ^ jgg^j^ffc  4] the employers are reported bo haye refused  an enquiry,.    ..  ^ftyp^ftpnfli^, -g  the ScQfefci&amp;ht3teilMa3fe^gompanies 10 reduce wages on October 1st, has caused a situation whifcb^y^^aslg^ l&amp;b:rfreWGnd($5t&amp; descr/ibes; (as pK^jpal.The Prospect of a Conference; between;.ithe;,&apos;Pr4$ie ; Minister ^n-d. .the *&amp;taa aaio, ie^ersta^jaBr1EefiJbl^^l)etter* The Dail&apos; ffitoecaaa -JksiS. .be*e*i. ,eliarmacli--Jt^-jJt^iiQAldO^fit attitude &apos;0f* .3fri*eh. a^jhbouzv *aaeL .hy. ttHH^pl&amp;aKS^Mlons made to **hei* ^j^tt^rel^chapter^lBafi WMDtfWQIEfc Wr f ......- - * - ^OlUteTHl HOIW.2(last csa%aT- -.....-........ - *.....T8HUSSHA? Altea&apos; &apos;   ...-.....- -....... -..1 -mm$M&apos;m&amp;k,^-v.  -  ^ v -       ...... tHTATOff ,TA/HS,?!I&apos;-.     &apos; &quot;&quot;V &quot;... . 840.&apos;...................-:.!&apos;*.&amp;-. j ^&apos; W3
THE UNEMPLOYED

According to the reports received, there has been a slight decrease in the number of demonstrations and in the size of audiences. The processions include a large number of immature youths apparently concerned only with the possibility of taking part in a riot. It is significant that the "Evening News", which had stated that Westminster had sent a contingent to the demonstration on Tuesday, received a protest from Westminster unemployed assuring them that not a man had gone from Westminster because the unemployed in that Borough strongly disapproved of Communist tactics. It is estimated that about 75,000 men have participated in demonstrations and meetings at the following places, although the audiences in no case exceeded 5,000: Aberdeen, Batley, Battersea (3); Bethnal Green (2); Birkenhead, Birmingham (8); Bolton, Brixton (3); Bury, Camberwell (3); Cardiff, Clapham Junction (3); Coventry (2); Derby, Earlestown, Eccles (2); Edmonton, Farnworth, Fulham (2); Glasgow (2); Highbury, Hockley, Hoxton (4); Lambeth (3); Leeds (3): Leicester, Liverpool (9); Manchester (2); Merthyr, Newcastle, Portsmouth, Radcliffe, Salford, Shadwell Fish Market, Snepherd&apos;s Bush (3); Shoreditch, Stepney (2); Stourbridge, St. Pancras, Stratford (3); Tottenham (3); Tydfil, Walham Green, Westminster (8); Widnes, Wigan, Wishaw, Wolverhampton, Woolwich (3); Wrexham.

The organisation of the unemployed is making rapid strides, although various committees are at present engaged chiefly in spade work: a typical example of the methods followed in London is the following circular letter, addressed to the Camberwell unemployed by F.H. Burnett, chairman of the Unemployed Committee:

"The time for action has arrived. In spite of all the efforts put forward on your behalf to bring the Guardians to a reasonable understanding, they definitely refuse to grant you anything like a fair scale of relief. Before the General Relief Committee on/
on Wednesday, September 14th, Captain Bridger threatened to reduce your relief to 10s. per week, in some cases it has been reduced. Your Committee now call upon you to decide what policy you should adopt. They ? one ask ? to vote by ? below either for or against entering Gordon Road Institution, with or without your wives and children. We have exact information as to the correct procedure in the event of you deciding in favour. I, as your Chairman, will lead you if you decide so. Never was the issue plainer, either we must fight or go out of existence. Many of you have faced death, are you prepared to face life? Either life of non-existence. The vote will be collected at a Social Meeting of the Branch to be held at the Central Rall, on Tuesday next, September 20th, at ?.30 p.m. prompt. You are specially requested to attend, and have your voting paper marked ? by a X. In conclusion, you have your fate in your own hands, then comrades into the breach. Remember you in your unity can decide this issue. They have thrown down the gauntlet, will you pick it up as men? Then, Comrades forward together in serried ranks and smash the rotten thing before us."

The National Administrative Council of Unemployed now controls about one hundred committees in the provinces and over thirty in the London area. P.H. Kealey, of Manchester, has succeeded Crossley and T.L. Pennell has succeeded Dove as organisers respectively of the Northern and Eastern areas. The plans of the National Administrative Council, to which reference was made in my last report, were formulated at a meeting held in the International Socialist Club on September 2nd and 3rd when the main resolution passed was:

"That during a specified period, say one week, all committees shell demonstrate, and if possible hold factory meetings, finishing up with a Mass Demonstration and deputation to the Local Authorities. The National Administrative Council to meet responsible Government officials simultaneously in order to demand the terms of the national policy of the unemployed, i.e. work and full maintenance at Trade Union rate of wages. The immediate putting into operation of the Trading Agreement with Russia, and the recognition of the Soviet Government; to also protest against the reduction of the dole, and against any increase in rent."

It was also resolved that the National Administrative Council should take over "Out of Work", which has hitherto been the organ of the London District Council; Holt, Hannington and Hays were elected as the editorial committee and were given/
^ ttfotttkjwfc^ be heldimmediately after the week of national agitation,,,Jidilowu U Mfcyk Wol8u?l5a!!ic^^,B9^oyiMn* con,mltte6S&apos;:;;! throughout;^ Sports from the secretaries.   The following oopy*8f^fepoW^ubmitted by the;ia f^$^ tl 6 typical-7&apos;&apos;&quot;..&apos;-/$Mwgf$^^f61F^dain^y&apos; ftgtfftpiiaorico3 ; TO* !tetn%M^if Dfgtr^^CcttW^O *3iInxoo2 XanoJ:.tacnc*x-i&quot;The organisation of several of the oouhtry^distriotsohoe land,,Taverham .and.Wymondham. Coatessey and B&amp;wburgh respectively mwW*Mi&amp; mml&amp;mmowas grafted and work^&quot;iltototMvti Witii good results..   The St. Faith18 and foreign ;* found for a number of men.;Qur demand for &quot;Work or Full Rented -te every Rural authority in Norfolk and/a ponfpre(nce of Rural Mstriot Councils on Unemprdylije^^Was&apos; been-&apos;held&apos; at&quot; No-rwioh,;- but they only\-rfiuccoeded^in passing a resolution to be sent to the000&apos; JtootfA&apos;   .eXv.i^ Secret demonstration.-of &quot;women was- arranged&apos; which ^surprised the Guardians and demanded boots for their &apos;&apos;Ui?dfooX(j0ch4ldreh. &apos; A meeting subsequently decided1 to detain the .:,:v     ^ .,...children from schp.pl .until the Vopts were, forthcoming.   On the 16th September1 a mass demonstration took place&apos; and a i-.,.,-;-        deputation of three - Comrades Pennell, Ley and Forster -placed the national demand scale of relief before the local Guardians and also the question of providing boots for the children.   The Guardians &quot;said they were considering the question of increasing their present scale, to include single persons and had&apos; set up ;a committee with the Education Authority on the boot question.   Subsequently a crowd of some 2,000, which had surrounded the Guardians1 offioeB whilst,the deputation was putting forward its claims, met &apos; on Norwich &quot;Market- Place and heard the- result t6f the deliberations.,  Lowostoft&quot;On the .15th September some hundreds of Lowestoffs workless were addressed by Comrade S. Smith, their, new chairman, who stated that the National Demand Scde of Relief would be presented in force to the Board: of Guardians, the following week.   H.S. Adams, a Councillor, interrupted the proceedings but was allowed to address the crowd and after, much heckling was ordered to clear off.Great Yarmouth&quot;On the 10th September the Yarmouth unemployed formed a committee and were given the use of Thome Hall asheadquarters/
&amp; ******bled od I^a^^Guardians with the result thai? AWGSsltWs ^cfeoesInternational Social let cl^sS^tlM^^^M^l^^^ for a:v^series...-.,;-.       %0 Xatcevoa lo aolfosaiossio out&quot;-w *-v1&quot; i;The; demons..... wha.t ^mailer numbersoan^^y^e^a&amp;a M^W/fW i3*       or!-        ;:&apos;t/v,^  so.!? ,-&apos;   s      *iirO     rants to laiftpra &amp; 30$. MsoX.    ..      -throe boroughs rival lead^ ^/iF^lfiaf pr% of.:. the London, District ^q^ili^^pg^^^ n0 , u,7,?An incident occurred in-*Br^xfon3%ri^S^li^m^L6.th,r when a deputation interviewed the Guardians while a c^v^of^, about/:[:: 3,000 was addr ess ed by Panning, Holmes and ,Lyl e.   About 800of the demonstrators marched to the workhouse and threatened to force their way in when told there, was more room: thesituation was critical for about half an hour but the crowdfinally took the advice of the speakers and dispersed.;    On September 20th contingents of unemployed from the&quot;West London District Right to Work Council&quot;, Pulham, Paddingtand Chelsea districts to the number of about 2,000 marched to westminster, when a deputation of nine interviewed the assistant Seoretary of the Poor Law Department of the Ministryof. Health and the Director of Labour Exchanges at Montague Houat the Ministry, of Health the deputation asked that the Islingscale of relief shotad.be put into operation throughout Londonand at the Ministry of Labour the abolition of all labour exchanges was suggested.   The deputation consisted of R. Howe\ mrf   4-fart n&apos;:T\r*es A &apos;
;;: September -21st over SVOOt) tiMmplbyed&amp;S-riOttu EGiAanfcaipj jHprnsey,and Wood Green Burr oMwld^n^n6Wlfc&amp;oto&amp;taBo* e^uft,frfc&amp;j c;or,a 4 iietfooX Bo^o Xcrenjj la *   r dlol f *efuCQd&apos;to recoWe^a&quot; d%p4a$fc$attfcroifqos no0n&apos;:sVptemberOf20thq o&amp;Wen^ysft paraded---Eehti-sh^ Town &quot;and hold a meeting^-^t % s%ef&amp;StWot- where, they wereJoined by a rough e^lemen^wrfo^mli^hed s^cwbing-through the * aoxaaooo odor no ,no*ur.v 0*   fleets r.^.,, a *c&apos;a:&apos;:streets: when they reached EveFshoJJt S^reet:,atitbe,;C,orner of isatevrtl 0* 83*31$ -modsJ i9 aal^n^ u   .*xo -which there is a post offi^e,-a^cBrdori-of polieeevwas^p^t acrossV&quot; the roadv- Two ccnstables^wlrl^assaulted;- ast a-result, of which m eXitejaoYfeSi end        8JtS0two men, named Mward- Wid^etTF&apos;end&apos;?&apos;-Bdward:..Aldridge, were chargedeiKT-tto-fio^      t&amp;zijimomoh of   ....., I5T&apos;: at- Clorkenwell Police Court yesterday.: - Each was fined- 2 or fi&apos;ieaxa jjege neqo oS tmo4 *v.-h -^rco--sent ended to one m6nth&quot;rs&quot;&apos;impriednment in&quot; the- ISecond Division forinsulting&apos;behaviour and to two months&apos; in the Second Division for onoh &amp;7mi rfotfi&amp; m:c:i;:; as       : * .-    F   .  ..  &apos;^0nAssaulting the police&apos;, &apos;the sentences to-run.concurrently.   A sotfcc$. tact&apos;1 akj d.H.1-t-t*i     ...,v ......large crowd demonstrated noisily outside the Police Court..aaeoo.fra rt-:0        r ,  ..... &quot;Jr.,;;&quot;; \,    On September&apos; 2lsV&apos;J.i; Lyle; Chairman; and-rjv Holmes, Vice-chairman of the&quot; Batter sea Uhemplo-yed/Committe-e were each ordered to find a surety in  25c and to find one of like amount themselves, to be of good behaviour^fdrlg^mdStKei- theyrwere -given 7 days to find the money, but sentehoed in default to -21; days&apos;,,.imprisonment. A large crowd of unempldyea^a^sPd^a. disturbance f. in.the course of which five men were arrested. ZzaoUlsix -.^4The Fulham unemployed have adopted&apos; a new mothod* of showing their disapproval of one of&apos; the&apos;Guardians&apos;:: oh September 18th about 60 men, women &quot;and&quot;&apos; children-&apos;&quot;-attended.&quot; the:&apos;eurejoln^ service at St. Augustine&apos;s Churbh, &quot;which&apos; tfrey&apos;&apos;l-eft! soon, after the commepce-ment of the service as a protest against the preacher, the hewart . G.B.S. Probert, who&apos;&quot;is&quot; &quot;c^a^fina^-^f &apos;-t:he&apos;^lecal Board of Guardians. Several of the London leaders eppear;to.fervour disorderlyaction/and G. Barker, Hammersmithji C^. JTeston and G. Green,Paddinpton; A. Glynwood and F. Price, Kensington; R. Brown,move bii.fi&apos; terfciedw oJ&quot; o      fChelsea j S. Hanac.i, Pul8lm?Bifid0S?^. Bl&amp;kv^Aftfcftjiol $&amp;*
,no0iO .a boa noJaaw. .  jdJjtaamwail  %r H?Jl .0 baa wiB .H jjwtBBlanBa ,ooi*S AoovatCO .A ,00*31**4.3S^taStfrftMU an^n a^lqllAt M&apos;f?e?0if e?^SJpd *^ wa*^o%^a**^^^ nou^ iicow &amp;taOn Septet^^^i^^^^^^^j^:*5Si*SS^&apos;*nd cloth-&quot;iprocadatfia    ^b,outXpd.0 accompanied J. JVaughan,thoccasionoeicfsiBolshevik Mayo^of B^^^r^^to SogfeoBj, Eia departure wit^^a^pujaj^n ^Labour ^yora^t^lnvermto; interview, the ^^SfeFa^^^ftxtfifefreooe owl?  . 301VtGf01My Newcastle corrompnclentReports that tne -Newcastle G&amp;teshead unemployed propose, to Remonstrate at iiyton-on-Tyneif the Prime Minister visits -that town to open aged, miners&apos;. y:f-w-noc: -sno o*  ooiro&amp;foaon October 8 th;.. &apos;.    -   i:! :v;-;^     9tv&amp;doif &apos;$cfijxirarii -Speakers at. unemployed meetings in Shoroditcb have done their utmost to bring about a no-rent strike a8 frpm&apos;sopteml 12th, but there is, as yot, no evidence of their success.On September 19th * the cases arising from the disturbs: ih the Art; Gallery, came up for hearing at the Liverpool ?o Court: on the recommendation, of the prosecuting counsel the -majority were bound pver :to keen the peace for 6 months in sum of  5; the nine leaders^will probably be committed for An additional charge of inciting to steal has been made agcB -the Rev. J. Vint Laughland. &apos;:     Oh September 19th about 3,000 people attended a meetii held under the auspices of the Liverpool Trades Council cnl Labour Party in the Stadium when the following resolution was passed:&quot;This, meeting; of...citizens registers its &quot;emphatio ^adherence to the policy . of work or maintenance.    Itfurti
&apos; - 7 - &quot; &quot;Ll&apos;o8^&amp;S t??(&amp;*&quot;a at bled cteacf crtzd BgaJStfeam swoisrawKrJ&apos;&quot;     further calls for an impartial public inquiry-anvla-s, orffr sniJjKBeofi EacJttxrloeefc costf cdv/ -/ex^oeg cause o.;rinto the events.that occurred on, September 11th, when WWi^-^M ^o, col*       a  f-Jr^ccrcprd^id 3%o&apos;XX^b&apos;firjoO ea? ::. M-u - &apos; &apos;     &apos;tDoeiB^loyaA-^-itisane were, in our opinion,-eliocurqO d$wascH nctooil wdfio&apos; c&amp;t &quot;ho &apos;BeXfisotam A&quot; A! j -uhmerdlfully: batoned by the. police without the *xiorrt .1c- plqmpxe od-Jv woXIcl o*&apos; ross^oxrXe^ ie&amp;ioel slightest provocation.&quot; vsia swwb*B J5xsb oetwti Xscdtfotl iiaudiitf&apos;&quot;jEoifgssxrooIt is ;worthy of note that the Rev.&quot; J. Vint Laughland dtf .sevov/cd ,vox:qo 8 jo oeao edfr &quot;irl &apos; jetidl^osxt: i       -    - -ioa.saogg^fgjt^oiice.?Sergeant Tissyman were among the speakers./3nXBao hoiioo; edt sol LoivoX aodd evad ateym o.r ajj^^flftjj correspondent reports that on September 15tha conference of representatives of 43 of the municipalerfw ,ttotejtsff.,*s eo-BJCq afoofr atoew edi&apos;&apos;,?x:.- U/J&apos;&apos; author it les in the West Riding was heid at Ruddersf ield:noXssooo BJii* ao   idtQl&apos;&apos;j-&quot;f%e%rej Members of Parliament were present and a resolution0di qpeS xZlw eW&quot; eoneXJ . - . ,.ait*&apos;!was passed calling upon the Government to promote export tradeodi      .eLi8ux.&apos;o      - :       ,. , - .     ; -J      . .t with,Germany and othor European countries and expressing thef:B&apos;smZtoassoU&apos; ,  .. .., &quot;    .at.-,? ^ opinion that stable employment can be found only, if the world&apos;s &quot; &quot;markets are freed from all restrictions.On September 19th two demonstrations of about 3,000 unemployed were held in Aberdeen, one of the leaders being George Wright, who has frequently been convicted of house- -breaking and theft.   Towards the end of the evening meeting the younger members of the crowd clamoured to be led to the residences of the Lord Provost and Dean of Guild and about 1,000 marched to the latter&apos;s house: a number of police were moved to the spot in taxis and a cordon was drawn up about 50 yards from the house.   Stones were thrown and the police were forced to make a baton charge, whereupon the crowd broke and fled.   Very little danage was done.POPLAR/
POPLAR

Numerous meetings have been held in support of the Poplar Councillors, but in most cases these are attended by same people, who pass resolutions demanding the release of the Councillors or expressing admiration of their action. So far, majorities on the other London Borough Councils show decided reluctance to follow the example of their Poplar colleagues, though Bethnal Green and Stepney may prove the exceptions; in the case of Stepney, however, ? rate appears to have been levied for the period ending March 31st, 1922. The largest demonstration reported in this connection during the week took place at Brixton, where 3,000 assembled on September 18th:   on this occasion Lansbury&apos;s voice assured the audience "We will keep the fight going in here and you carry on outside." The "Daily Herald" is running a fund for the "Counciliors&apos; Kiddies" and claims to have received to date, £400 most of which has been given by Trade Union branches.

The National Union of Police and Prison Officers, which is evincing considerable and probably selfish interest in the Poplar Councillors, is holding frequent meetings outside Brixton Prison: on September 19th Lansbury&apos;s voice was agi? heard, thanking the demonstrators, who had cheered and su? the "Red Flag", for their sympathy.

Nightly meetings are being held outside Holloway Prison, but the audiences have not exceeded 100.

The Poplar Tenants&apos; Defence League claims that the organisation is complete, but that the no-rent strike will not commence until the order is given by the imprisoned Councillors: in spite of extensive propaganda, the leader deplore the "apathy" in certain areas. The Stepney Councillors are also considering the feasibility of a loc? no-rent strike. The/
THE COMMUNISTS

Communist activity remains centred in the unemployed, although the Executive is making comprehensive plans for parliamentary and municipal elections. The present intention is to oppose Labour candidates wherever possible, despite the fact that the Party&apos;s chances on a purely communistic platform are negligible.

There is information which has not yet been verified that the Party intends to flood the country with seditious leaflets urging the unemployed to drastic action: my Coventry correspondent reports that elaborate preparations are being made for the dispatch and distribution of these leaflets within a period of twenty-four hours and it is probable that they will be issued during the "week of national agitation."

The following circular, drawn up by Cant for the London District Council of the Communist Party, indicates the attention which is devoted by the Party to all opportunities of exploiting unrest:

"As you are doubtless aware the Poplar Borough Council have refused to levy the rates from outside bodies and have been sent to prison. Their defiance of the Central Authority creates a situation of which advantage must be taken by the Communist Party, and the Divisional Executive have decided that speakers must be concentrated upon the Borough of Poplar in order that the position may be fully exploited.

"At the same time a parallel agitation has arisen amongst the unemployed of Shoreditch and the neighbouring districts towards a rent strike on the part of the unemployed. It is easy to see that a wholesale refusal to levy rates for the Central governing authority, and at the same time a refusal on the part of the unemployed to pay rent, may very easily have far-reaching results,"

Comparatively few purely communist meetings have been reported during the week, owing to the activity of speakers on the platforms of the unemployed: on September/
- .10^        ..... v:,;September 18th, however, about1 1,500 at tended &quot;a^oommflniat   imeeting in Manchester, which &quot;was&quot; addresseb^yHRiehai4s^ ani.**aa edf at be? t too aqiqsov, :$lri*p^i/iawwraoa, Jenkins; the latter stated that he had been addressingunempj.oyea meetings in Yorkshire for some time.&quot; &apos; v&apos;A,I,.0fl2,   .8noi*OQlo Xmiolprm ^&apos; rtMmm&amp;tm The faxluro of &quot;Red Week&quot; becomes increasinglyapparent, as the branches report results:   Coventry gained..    &apos; ..c aooxuibr b/^xol       .*cd* Joje&amp;, :odft ja^tfjMl&apos; two new members and Birmingham four;   in tho latter City,speakors at a meeting held on September 16th were;     :;&apos;on md rtotdvt mitimxotaH&amp;i^o^ifffv^o-hf severely heckled by thoir audience who oalled them..&apos; &apos; - &apos; .   . : &apos; a-^-dt boon of.abuoiui *tfti&amp;:cd.fr fun? &quot;Bolshies and Russians&quot;.The ex-Service men who broke up the communist meeting. . I rfvTOr^ inotoeBo-x^oe 7afaevjpfi&apos;*at Chepstow on September 11th have formed themselves into,&apos; V&apos;.?\ exit &apos;xol- 06m aai&amp;rf a branch of the British Legxonand have resolved not toallow any communist meetings in ..thoir&quot;immediate    &quot;&quot;neighbourhood, *  ,A.J. Cook has severed his connections1with^lne&quot;Communist Party because he believes that the miners are more competent to carry but their business than anyoneoutside the industry.     He has been severely criticised by Communist Executivo members for the action he tookduring the latter part of the recent ooal struggle, which,it was alleged, was calculated to help the capitalists.Ho states that he- could not remain, a member of the Party,as he believes its tactics are destructive and disruptiveand he is not prepared to take instructions from &quot;anysmall clique&quot;.i   Robert Stewart, the communist candidate in the recent bye-election at Caerphilly,. was disfranchised in Dundee Registration Court on September 14th, because he was a conscientious objector during the war.   .- William Brains.who has for,: some time organised the Communist movement in Birmingham and has been a salaried official of the Red Trade Union International, has announced/
announced that he has "about done" with the latter body, no doubt owing to the stoppage of his salary: he has secured nomination for the post of Midlands organiser which James Stewart is vacating.

Mrs. Helen Crawfurd has declined to stand as a Labour candidate in the forthcoming Glasgow municipal elections on the ground that she "could only stand as a communist candidate to advocate the formation of a revolutionary industrial and political organisation for action which has for its definite objective the overthrow of the exploiters, whether they be capitalists or Labour leaders."

My correspondent had an interview with Dick Beech on September 17th in the course of which Beech stated that the communists are fully aware that no revolution could be successful in this country until the rebels gained control of the Navy. This matter, however, is receiving their special attention at this moment, and they are quite satisfied with the progress made. Beech intimated that he was specially informed upon this point. He inferred that propaganda in favour of Communism was being introduced into the Navy through the Stoker branch of that service, or it may be that the ships of the Navy were to be rendered impotent simultaneously by some action taken by certain stokers on each ship (such as placing a bomb in the machinery). The revolutionaries apparently do not consider the Navy a serious difficulty.

A seaman and ship&apos;s fireman by occupation, Beech attaches great importance to the spreading of propaganda among seafaring men. He is very disappointed by the manner in which the seamen have responded so far. He said that during the recent miners&apos; strike, he urged the Executive to carry on intensive propaganda in the sea-port towns where miners officials should address meetings, in order to bring
bring their true case before the seamen. But the Executive did not agree with this policy. Beech considers that once the mercantile marine is gained the communists&apos; success is certain as they could control the food supplies of the country, but it was no use the miners striking without the seamen because "you can&apos;t eat coal".

Arthur McManus has received a report from Anton Beratz of an International Conference of Communists held in Berlin to discuss the Russian famine, from which it appears that they are counting on the following subscriptions collected in the various countries from communists. It is intended to use the contributions for food and medicines and to make the greatest possible capital out of it for propaganda purposes.

Germany 500,000 marks (German)

Sweden 200,000 marks (German)

Norway 300,000 marks (German)

Holland 380,000 marks (German)

Denmark 220,000 marks (German)

Belgium 110,000 marks (German)

Spain 60,000 marks (German)

Czecho-Slovakia 100,000 marks (German)

Italy 200,000 marks (German)

Switzerland 1,000,000 marks (German)

France 3,000,000 marks (German)

England 300,000 marks (German)

THE YOUNG COMMUNIST INTERNATIONAL

Following the "Famine Week" and the "Red Week" the Communists propose to have a "Red Youth Week" from October 2nd - 9th.

On August 28th the Executive Committee of the Young Communist International issued the following manifesto from Moscow:-

"? ATTENTION? TO BE PUBLISHED IMMEDIATELY BY THE PRESS OF PARTY AND YOUTH!

"The Communist International has named the week from 2nd to 9th October a Propaganda Week. During ? week, then, it is the duty of every section affiliated with the Communist International to intensive propaganda which is to win new adherents for the entire Communist Movement. It need hardly be pointed out that the Young Communist/
- w - -    170ttnoor&apos;:.   .isf- ; r, s   ..13 ..-. \d,m*&apos;tiil^mxi .$i . &apos;.:oii*w &quot;Tte&amp;ijaV/ .^qxroY ed&apos;i&apos;&quot; hef.l.L?ad &quot;xoqaq. .ed,t .2a^xfC^iM^efe.^$$r^f.^1 d0 , *** ; -    thoir utmost tb render the Propaganda V7ook as broad.        .;.. ,.apd ,extpnsiyo as possible. laiiiummoO,  .     &quot;Accordingly, wo call upon all organisations9 &apos;i;;:l&apos;&quot;&quot;&quot;f-&quot;Vtb -obraseiriba&apos; i^i^ir^wMlff &apos;.^he -*     mobilisation off&quot;.aU&apos;;frhfflfr&apos;.tQ*^7*is^&apos;,*?i:sok.   Every Young Workers1 Group   and every Children&apos;s Group ^a-ttapm wopA*H^%i**Wee^^^^^&quot;a^^^S^f^B^ to some; &apos;special task1 every single one of them; they must alsoafi?\,Pd.l.v.ta^P^^-.r,WJiA^^4Failb iWsifcteJ-flftf 1et^ld;! central ,. committee for Propaganda formed by the Parties.arid $a, !&amp;$iapm&amp;^ been formed&apos;xsegqu      ^-&apos;i^&apos;th&apos;e&apos;-youth&apos; must insist upon them being created saw r0^itiL. $J^meftM^li       ^def-n^j^oi^^ha-t the same work iMM?.-*ui.i&apos;^s performed twice or that some special work is:v;t eX,cbix0.        JmMtiilPfeflM^I^AqjMfo.WfSMWfJ&apos; to distribute **   * t^-^^h-Qforces available in conjunction with the Party.. e.to^ im*,mzmb$w&amp;i&amp;&amp;*      ?$$m&amp; fi&amp;HM^f ^df,t0^Hisa,fftfcjoxpao. sr-.s -thQ member shin&apos; of Our sections and of the Children&apos;s ed hXfiOij a a:.o?tf Gr.eup.s*wWfe.4nD$^J!^y-.and the membera of the xoj       -. . : latter for work amongst the Young Movement and the ii tartf  eM^14r.ftgriftflBWP&amp;     *ob1 arcana&apos;? -waXi^jjfflJWffpoae. o^&apos;4,%%vbp^i.ab^ration of the. previously mentioned&apos;-4ii;; - branches, of * the Movement should find expressionaaaera kiai ^rf jJ-fem^^afeand fraternal-help.,,,,And th,is is the a4m:&quot; To^recruit   new followers fOr the phalanx .of theniaao% &amp;a$ no CbfflrmniTat Movement&apos;... We leave it to our(Sections to givo out slogan adopted to the situation beXXMa baa a-in. the individual countries.&amp;amxbw: ,      &quot;Got ready!   Commence reparations at once&apos;.- - K Bouse the indifferent!   Mobilise every single member!eritf -xoi --     ; Recruit; , now members! -   ,     . ;;,.    .&quot;For the Communist International. &quot;For the Young Communist -International! &quot;For the.Phalanx of. the Proletariat!&quot; Propaganda in this country appears to bo in the hands ... of T, 3ell - (organising secretary);/A. J. IJott (&quot;for the Young Communist International,&quot;).;-and,P.E. Lower (&quot;for the .. Communist Youth Movement&quot;): theae men are urging all branches of the Communist Party to arrange daily meetings during &quot;Red Youth. Week&quot; culminating; with a mass domonstra-tion on Sunday, October 9th; they are making arrangements for a Meeting in Trafalgar Square on-that date and are preparing speoial literature.The Young Workers&apos; League, whioh is theEnglish branch of the Young Communist International, issues a monthlypapor/
paper entitled "The Young Worker" which is published by A.J. Nott at 16, King Street, the headquarters of the Communist Party.

THE RED TRADE UNION INTERNATIONAL

A secret report regarding the recent Moscow meeting of the Red Trade Union International discloses the fact that the leaders of the movement are greatly disappointed at the results so far obtained: in the Congress itself there was great diversity of opinion and the delegates were unable to decide on a settled policy, one section holding that trade unions should be destroyed and another that they should be won over for communism. It was finally decided that in regard to England the best policy was "to encourage amalgamation to an even greater extent than now, and by this means to increase Communist influence and pressure on the Committee and older members. Thus by uniting labourers and skilled workmen of the same industrial category and introducing specially qualified workers it should be possible for the extremists to impress their will on the moderates."

In regard to organisation the Congress decided that it was only possible to increase the "Section for liaison with abroad", to which 17 more members were allotted: it was also agreed that the agents of the Third International proceeding abroad should execute commissions for the Red Trade Union International without expense to the latter. The Congress resolved not to publish any new literature, with the excent of the "News sheet of the International Trades Unions" and few bulletins.

Agents in Great Britain have been given the following instructions:

"1. To encourage the organisation and union of existing Trade Unions on a wide basis, so that one single union will embrace all branches of a given industry 2./
2. To attract into the unions unimportant workers, such as clerks who will influence qualified workers and more influential men in the same way as the labourers will gradually influence the skilled workers and specialists. 3. To increase agitation work amongst transport workers, special sailors and employees at harbours, and ? the idea of a Red union of transport workers. Great hopes are cased on the recommencing of ? communication between Britain and Petrograd as a means of assisting in this work, and spreading Communist ideas and literature.

4. To take every possible step to compromise the leaders of the &apos;Yellow&apos; unions, by proving that they are usually working in co-operation with the bourgeoisie. With this aim in view ? are not to be content with making general accusations, but are to create concrete instances and quote them as proof of this.

5. To gradually obtain complete influence over the working man&apos;s press."

Experienced workers were detailed to form a "germ cell" among the printers, in order that they can be won over without breaking from the moderate elements. The Council of the Red Trade Union International seems doubtful as to the success which can be achieved in Great Britain, owing mainly to lack of funds. It was thought that if one or two of the large trade unions could be attached greater results might be obtained.

The question of funds appeared to be one of the most difficult? with which the Congress had to deal: according to a statement made by Zinovieff on August 4th, the Third International can only spare £10,000 for the work of the Red Trade Union International.

The depression of the International Council in regard to the movement in England is well founded, since the British organisers have very little hope that the movement will survive in this country without funds. Kime has stated that "the finance of the Workers&apos; Committees has now come to an end... This office (i.e. Headquarters at Manchester) will be closed on the 25th of this month ... We are going to get a place at Sheffield, if possible, but how we are going to run it without finance from the local committees is a problem which I cannot solve."

In a letter to E. Lismer, Peet bemoans the cost of his recent appeal/
appeal which will prove a severe drain on the depleted funds of the British Bureau. He writes:

"I have received a statement from Desquesnes this morning re Respondents costs in connection with the appeal. I am presented with a bill for £65.15.2. Kime has received a similar statement and his bill is £61.4.6. Its perfectly devilish, but they have got us by the leg. Will you ask ? (i.e. Arthur Booth) to send alone a remittance as soon as he can."

THE COAL MINERS

There are reports of discontent in various coal fields due largely to fears that drastic wages cuts will follow the termination of the temporary settlement on September 30th. My correspondent states that in South Wales, where unemployment is serious among the miners and the cuts will be heavy, there are signs that trouble is brewing. The men allege breaches of the National Agreement and are smarting under what they consider to be "victimisation": they complain that, in complying with the employers&apos; demand for increased production, they have added to the stocks of unsaleable coal, thereby retarding the absorption of about 50,000 local miners.   My correspondent forecasts that the exhaustion of the Government subsidy will be followed by active discontent. The South Wales Miners&apos; Federation has decided to revert, for the time being, to the monthly contribution of 2s. per member with an adjustment of benefits, conditions and practises to the standard existing prior to August 1920: it will be remembered that on that date contributions were doubled.

In Durham and Northumberland the mining outlook is not considered to be favourable: very few collieries are working more than three or four days a week and miners and their wives state that wages should not be further reduced until the cost of living comes down. Most of the men realise, however, that their power of resistance is crippled by their financial position. SYLVIA/
SYLVIA PANKHURST

The altercation between the Communist Party and Sylvia Pankhurst has caused both sides to rush into ? a proceeding from which Sylvia Pankhurst emerges with the honours in that her open ridicule is far more effective than the ? of the Executive.

Sylvia Pankhurst

"Freedom of Discussion"

"The Communist Party of Great Britain is at present passing through a sort of political measles called discipline, which makes it fear the free expression and circulation of opinion within the Party...

"A letter issued by the Executive to branches of the Party recommended the &apos;Plebs&apos;, &apos;Solidarity&apos; and the &apos;Worker&apos; for circulation by the Party, but stated that the question of circulating the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; must be left in abeyance. Many branches took this to mean that the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; must not be circulated and some of the Party&apos;s organisers carried on a campaign against the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; in this sense, making it a question of loyalty to the Party not to take it. Nevertheless, the circulation of the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; has remained larger than was that of the &apos;Call&apos; when the B.S.P. was merged in the Communist Party, though its struggle for existence as an unsubsidised paper was intensified, in face of the &apos;Communist&apos; heavily subsidised, largely advertised and sold at 4d. a quire cheaper to newsagents and branches ...

"Soon after my release from half a year&apos;s imprisonment I met a sub-committee of the Communist Party Executive, which consisted of Comrades W. Paul, F. Peet, F. Willis, and T. Clark. This sub-committee put it to me that &apos;as a disciplined member of the Party&apos; I should hand the &apos;Workers&apos; Dreadnought&apos; over to the Executive, to stop it, or continue it, and, should it continue the paper, to put it to any use or policy it chose, and to place it under the editorship of any person whom it might select; I was not to be consulted, or even informed, till the decision should be made. Thus, with a spice of brutality, the disciplinarians set forth their terms to one who had for eight years maintained a pioneer paper with constant struggle and in face of much persecution. I replied that I could not agree to such a proposition, but would consider carefully, and in a comradely spirit, any proposal that the Party might make to me regarding the paper..

"Later on I suggested meeting the Party Executive, as readers up and down the country were writing to me telling me that certain organisers and members of the Party had renewed their campaign against the &apos;Workers&apos; Dreadnought&apos;. The Party Executive ignored my suggestion that we should meet, but wrote demanding that I should surrender the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; to it within the space of two weeks. To this demand I did not reply, and the two weeks ?aving expired I received a summons to meet the Executive.

"Eventually I did so on Saturday, September 10th. It was a strange scene. Dressed in a little brief authority this Executive, which meeting only fortnightly, is necessarily controlled by the paid officials who are always on/
on the spot, was full of zeal to serve the Communist Party by controlling me, and by bringing to an end the pioneer Communist paper that has been more continuously and drastically persecuted by our capitalist governments ? any paper in the country; a paper that is known to the Communist movement throughout the world.

"&apos;We are not here to consider the good the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; might do, but the harm it might do,&apos; said Comrade McManus, his red silk handkerchief showing so smartly from his pocket.

"&apos;What the committee wants is the death of the &apos;Dreadnought&apos;, &apos;said another comrade.

"Discipline was the watch word of the meeting.

"Comrade McManus made a strange observation that the Party was now engaged in building the circulation of the &apos;Communist&apos;, and when that has been done, &apos;we shall begin to get some good stuff in it and develop a policy&apos;.

One member of the committee has accused us of attacking the &apos;Communist&apos; in these columns. We have not done so; but in any case, it would have been difficult to say anything less complimentary about the &apos;Communist&apos; than that remark of Comrade McManus.

"The comrades intended to enforce discipline in its most stultifying aspect. Comrade McManus, as chairman, informed me that they would not permit any member of the Party to write or publish a book or a pamphlet without the sanction of the Executive. Those who may differ from the Executive on any point of principle, policy or tactics, or even those whose method of dealing with agreed theory is not approved or appreciated by the Executive, are therefore to be gagged...

"Comrade McManus stated that it is he who decides what work shall be allocated to the members of the Party, and indicated that had I been a disciplined member of the Party he would have sent me to work in the Caerphilly election, a type of work which he considered &apos;more suited&apos; to my capabilities than that of editing the &apos;Dreadnought&apos;..

"The resolution for expulsion was proceeded with. Its mover was lately a Conscientious Objector and a member of the N.C.F. In the days when the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; was the only paper in London fully supporting the Russian Communist Revolution and calling for the Soviet Revolution also in Britain, this comrade worked as a clerk in the W.S.F. office, but was unable to see eye to eye with us on this great question. He did not then approve Revolution or the Dictatorship of the Proletariat. He came to us when, as a C.O., he could not find work in an ordinary business office, and left us to take a commercial post at a higher salary when more prosperous days dawned - now the Conscientious Objector has become the disciplinarian."

The Communist Party

"The Executive Committee at its last meeting considered the question of the relationship of Sylvia Pankhurst and the &apos;Workers&apos; Dreadnought&apos; to the Party. "It/
"It will be remembered by the Party membership that this matter came up for discussion at the first conference of the Communist Party held at Leeds... It was decided that the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; should be left to the Executive Committee and the Party chairman for negotiation with those responsible for the paper with a view to arriving at some arrangement whereby the Executive Committee could be placed in control of the &apos;Dreadnought&apos;.



"Since that time various endeavours have been made to secure this. In view of the fact that Sylvia Pankhurst was in gaol it was felt inadvisable by the chairman to press for any definite decision until Miss Pankhurst&apos;s release would enable her to take part in any decision arrived at. Immediately on her release a sub-committee of the E.C. was appointed to approach her in order to ascertain her views and opinions on the question, and the committee reported back that whilst Miss Pankhurst was prepared to consider any proposition which the Executive Committee put before her, she definitely refused to hand over the control of the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; to the Executive Committee of the Communist Party. She further insisted on meeting the full Executive Committee. She was thereupon invited to attend the next full meeting of the Executive but did not reply, although it was subsequently ascertained one day before the Executive Committee meeting that she refused to meet the Executive Committee until the return of Miss Smythe from Moscow. Immediately upon the return of Miss Smythe she was again summoned to appear before the Executive Committee. She attended and was informed that no weekly political paper published by any member of the Party could be permitted outside the control of the Executive Committee, and she was asked to place the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; under the control of the Executive. The matter was exhaustively discussed, and at the conclusion Miss Pankhurst definitely refused to comply with the decisions of the Executive Committee, who had no other alternative but to expel her.



"One point is worthy of attention. After the discussion had gone on for the best part of three hours, and the motion that she be expelled was moved, seconded and discussed, it was just previous to putting the vote that she informed the Executive Committee that the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; in any case would be going out of existence at the next number. Miss Pankhurst further stated that she did not want this fact to influence the voting, but was reminded by one member of the Executive Committee that she apparently preferred the &apos;Dreadnought&apos; to go out of existence entirely, rather than come under the control ? the Executive Committee. The chairman, however, on this statement endeavoured to re-open the whole discussion, but it was of no avail. Miss Pankhurst definitely and finally refused, with the result as aforesaid."

Although Sylvia Pankhurst stated in her paper that the issue dated September 17th would be the last, she now declares that the "Workers&apos; Dreadnought" is to continue. There is, as/
as yet, no evidence as to the source of the funds which are given the paper a new lease of life, but Norah Smythe may not have returned empty-handed from her recent visit to the Continent. In any event the paper carries no weight.

Dick Bolch has declared his intention of joining Miss Pankhurst in forming a left wing independent of the Communist Party and to draw away from it all the more violent elements. This secession, if it takes place will follow the invariable history of extreme movements.



JOHN MACLEAN

In the intervals from agitation among the unemployed, John MacLean is devoting his attention to the work of the "One Big Union Publicity Committee" of which he is provisional secretary. He has always been an advocate of industrial unionism.

On September 17th, about a hundred delegates from Trade Union branches attended 50, Renfrew Street, (the Headquarters of the Socialist Labour Party) on the invitation of MacLean, to consider the question of the One Big Union. The matter was explained at length by MacLean and it was resolved to organise in trade union branches. It was also decided to circularise trade unions, trades and labour councils. Socialist organisations in Scotland and ask them to appoint delegates to a Conference in Glasgow within the next two months and to demand a Special Trade Union Congress to make preliminary arrangements to formulate one big union.

The Committee elected to carry on the work is:-

Harry McShane - Chairman

James D. MacDougall - Secretary

John MacLean - Consulting Organiser

Frank Duffy

William Duffy

Malcolm MacFarlane

A. Armstrong

R. Young

William Watson.





                                                                On/ 
* 8 x mOn September 20;h Jihn MacLean was arreated at thew&amp;mti&amp;&amp;$  ot&apos; &amp;&amp;i otlt Wv- acf- &apos;X&apos;Xiw &amp; t&quot; 3i&apos;ael v,aU*&quot;&apos; oaa atXcltftf&apos;^close of an unemployed demonstration and charged   the atraistta&apos; sotowotf -jaft6?i* WdJ.aa&apos;6-&apos;eiii hbt&amp;rbmi. 6* &apos;^Io  Xtjcfff m.!-*following day, at Glasgow Southern Court, with having said, on vr-iv oa*&amp;&amp;alaV$i&amp;b^fco&apos; b^;ta&apos;*binq&apos;oj^%XvAi,;&quot;&apos; .oa ofc 6* &apos;ao* wSeptember 13th &quot;As long as I am a free man X will say smovos, : awaw^:&apos;1^^&quot;oii^&apos;out&amp;al) -so voJaiiw&quot;-- ni cnftB&apos; JioHjaiB&quot; XXiw amery^- .that la if you cannot gat food In a constitutioual way, I aXda&amp;Xmtot..^ $at&amp;Q&amp;ltifi :oss-?tfa4* -&quot;cwot&quot;&apos; afraid&apos; aaditfiittfcsay take it,r.    Maclean was remanded   to the Sheriff, hailbeing refused, ana is now hunger-striking.,rfatatftyita^iiKaftlJW Xa&amp;.ta*itf to ettec etitf- ai Jeoapaf *- -gBX,&quot;p^ILY-.^t;lD.^M)^^8- rftadff ai a&amp;ai 3 a ta not-,^jii^W^Mi^lW;^W*&apos;^ey*:*&apos;e.*BS.fl&apos;W,ing in each issue elMx*&amp;i &quot;Ml? ?8H^&quot;oyh^&amp;o^*^a^oi.,start a &quot;Back to a&apos;T.S^0^.^^ ^S^g/^a^Wh6 paper is prepared to go Coitoxt wn*%ml*! ,%e*,tav,,writtan last week to a solicitorby HUJi ,$$4wocd.f secretary to the &quot;Daily Heraia Ltd.&quot;.-&quot;to &apos;;;&apos; -mtfoji ^ understand the Registrar of F. iendly Societies u&amp;b Nwitbin the past few days, or quite recently, givenftsfio-saoa -i-a^linS *hat E ^-Tde Union having a Political Fand may &apos;-:-ho*fT invest money from that Fund without tho signature of tha c Oi.tan%AOI3^,B Bmstaas. .jf. ,        &quot;You will see thc,t this is of great interest to ua.&quot;While I am not authorised to consult you professionally - as you are not our Company&apos;s Solicitor -I should be very much obliged if you would oare to give me any specific information you could obtain about this Ruling with a view to our citing it when aaking Unions to invest in the D.II.&quot;$be attention of the Registrar is being called to this. In his issue of the 14th the 23* it or is cuite frank in warning Intending investors in the &quot;Dally Herald&quot; that they will lose their money, adding &quot;Any way, the good it will to to the Movement will never be lost&quot;.3IHH PaiH IM CRXhT BRIDIEIrishman of moderate views in this country are much disturbed by the turn the peace negotiations hava taken,   TVey point out that Da Valera and his party have proclaimed a Ropubllo and have ie&amp;ued bonda in America payable by thaRepublic/
PA I- 22 *add dc feeds ostws a.w/ aooiXo M K&amp;t cI:OS wcTmed^S. crORepublic and the y fear that it will be; difficult to persuade*M   bpzytmlis bap ftotd^da itemed feo^ol^mano&quot; tit &apos;vo eaoXa him publioly to renounce hia declarations&apos;, hbwovor&quot;anxious:Yisi dflv ,lwoO a&apos;x*i*dtfo  vo*8f.iIO da ,^6 sttiwollol he may be to do so.    1 largo; percentage&quot;&apos;of&quot;dO-falai?a*8 XXlw I neat oe*!k * ate I e* SinoX alw rfdSI ^oditrodtfee followers will support him in whatever course&quot;hb mey;&apos;furBue:- IfHioldirdldsuoo a ol 6oo1x dogi domxao government; it at vaSS if negotiations break down theyarc prb380tf%%^f0rmidable, S add od   eo6iwat&amp;* S w mn&amp;o&amp;U    *?,df work* v,aa winter campaign for which prepare^atlOns^artfX^^ln^iiaao., * jsiibii* dc-*3CD&apos;-iwt&apos; wait at fcixa ,aaaxrle% &apos;^ii*d&quot; Tho inquest in the oaae of Michael-llolWeriieyp injuredJuly 28th was resume^ on in an explosion at a Garage in South%trb&apos;0-^^MMi*CLo^the 17th Septei^gr.ot^of^tSel&quot; %T4i^S8e^^t!^^oMclnerney&apos;s oompaMofil&quot;lia^ V^H?S SWIltledoubt, however, that ---frl^&amp;^fttf ^Sl^ifaS^^iWemanufacture of irioeno id$y*l6^a^8$%W&amp; 6We $ flMftIrish Republican Army oonimflbf^ ^f.:llifo^da0^Hioho;Hiekey, who was injured in &quot;an ^xmn^^^M&amp;i^Arsenal on the 15th September, died immedla^to^^ter71admission to the surgery,   Wh*n H?okey1-. blbtbri^lims-^searohecthree membership tickets of the Irish Self-Determinationlet .&apos;ue for himself, his eon and hia wife, were found Inhis pocket.    So far a8 is known Rickey was an ordinarymember of the organisation and there is no evidence to showhis eonneotion with the explosion on the 28th July in thagarage at South Street, Oreonwloh.   I. is, however,significant that both he and Molnerney v-ere members of thesame organisation.    A member of Woolwich iraenal, in theoriginal Irish Republican   Army-orders, was to help in thamanufacture of the bombs at.the parago.Preparations for the big meeting of th6 Ofalio league in the Central E&apos;-ll, W stmiaster, on the 23rd 8&apos; r*t ember, arebeing pushed forward with all1 haste.     Gaelic I-aguersheve been circularised to be particular to present theircards of memberBhip at the door.Various meetings of the Irish Self-De termination leaguehave been held in the provinces and P.J. Kelly, of Liverpool.continues to make stormy speeches:    throughout the truce hehas/
- 23&amp;31750 &amp;^a?SSa^Jv?&amp;iHH%HWite1.t&amp;;:&amp;*k*teto ^6*ito*flj9^iOMritf the aootSS^^^P^P^^^^^^ii^^d%o^i5oo^&amp;fidro^aaafin^^e.^ and ati 0MTO$e!$^W addedito the .sXdY. J^ttlsn-Boyaott-Committee,   ,. va-xo&amp;soXorsl  *0fW&quot; *^fi^ cooperation ofh-M^^^^Mi^Mihm ^^-application awfaok CSboehan, \ m&apos;.&apos;XM:        -tt^i^M^^.^^ ^i^:fe-ito3weeding e, - Is to he. confi[5^a9IH:i% ..^&apos;.]^ia^Ml^f^Jsi&apos; Union at an early ^ift^^fi^ ^^^^;te^^I^^siderit of the   Union. ^1*^$^ John- Turner wereori^io^ arising out of the ...)d%m*im$ffcM^^ R;-id was sentenced to ej^faril ^nWatervitraie and Tsrrter to 12 months1iia;o^apnnian%.&apos;&apos; The third prisoner, B.J, MoCaulay was foundarxXXXoO CosrfaHr -.3Ij0^Bt,viio,t,.guXrty and dlsohargea,    The three men are Sinn Fein  ^ners\ in the lochgelly district,at      0&apos; September 18th about 1,500 people attended ao tXdircy -!- - .meeting of the Irish :So:rJ -Btgrmi:oatlon league in Leeds:the ohair was taken hy Joseph MoKjius; President of theLeeds District Committee and the speakers Included&apos;Mrs. Pinchbeck,   Joaeph Watson, Secretary of leads DistrictCommittee of tha league, Mr. Biker, of Liverpool, who issecretary of the Liverpool District Committee of the League,and Mr* Austin Henry, organiser for West Yorkshire.   Tha     *following resolution was passed:&quot;That wa the Irish S^ilea in Leeds, re-affirm our support of and confidence in President de Valors and Dail Eireann in the stand that they have taken in defence of representative government in Ireland, and are determined to sue fulfilled the principles far which they stand,&quot;The Prime Minister*s note to de valera declaring that&quot;while/
&quot;while! youiinsiBtoon olaiming tha^yeurfcdakega,^^^ oonfereHeefishouldlfcecthere^g^^^ indepentea4vMtfo.W^impo impossible.^ has.--,c.aused ,oonsia ^raFififti^Piipif%&apos;^l^0 Jhe Sinn Feln-leaders.    -     1 .   ,eoddx^ ^Public fiteia^e^n$s^^ door to pesos has-Zoeen^sea ^l^^SliM^li^t^isi^   -aemana thatt heomAff^^fjTfila teoa&apos;ol^-The re I g d*ateii^iM ^eyej-jfchadkf ^^S%^f^no0 a elevates were: cejLIedi. r^OiSjj^ D3the oraers of the epe*o&amp;S3L tf$BitE&amp;&amp; tSfm1^^^^^ ^au1 Rtr.*ublican Army and the . Bftf*  iPP^W^^^^^Mfe^&apos;0 extremist   section of the D?.4&amp; y^fe^^^^J^^^g^ng great difficulty in keeping ^de^o^fr^ Tp^l^^6^ablo that if de Tale r a had as free a hand, as he      Sit jffiffl^ have chosen McNeill ana Childers in place of Mlqhaei&apos; Cjoilins*-  v,m JLXir J \T0  ana Duggan.      . ?::,..v;  ,Vo. ,r ,,:; ,-/. The Extremists,, while still proplaiming ..for- b&amp;l^&apos;--1 independent Republic9 are beginning to realise that ptiblio opinion is very strong in favour of peaoe, that the moderate party can^jaot be pushed on one side too easily, and that lack of financial support would be disastrous.   In thin c ohne c :location i t 1 s: Interesting that ii.if. riosn, p or respond enlts in Dublin have been given the cold shoulder the last few days, the result doubtless, of Americans outspoken, comments on the fairness and reasonableness of: the Prime Minister !s, offer to tho Dail. ni&quot; v *Irish Labour;ha9 another grievance, it is&quot; not represent at the conference to-be held at Inverness. It feels has a. right to be so represented In view of what it has^aon^fcr the &quot;Republic&quot; and particularly as at the last election it refrained from pressing %t*B olaim too strongly on Sinn FeU1 Among st/
Amongst Labour and the younger Sinn Joiners there has boon a distinct move towards Bolshevism.   There is no evidence ,r$hat.this,..,i.s.,,tbe result of Agents ana propaganda from Moscow, and., it,.would appear to have come about from the example that has boon shown them in the methods of terrorism and robbery of which the country has been&apos;so full&apos;.&apos; Shis spirit of lawl0,ssnoDS will have to be seriously reckoned with by the Authorities, in Ireland, whoever they may bo, within the next few months..,c,f.,A.t a meeting of the Cork and District Trades an? Labour tCounpil held at Cork on September 9th- Walton Eewbould, whose j^PQec.h was not too well reoeived and has been sharply rcritic3.sed. by some members of the Labour Party in Cork, said he was very glad to see that tho red flag floated over the Harbour Boards and to hoar that it floated over MaLlow and ;ovor some unpronounceable place in Limeriok.   It was a very good sign,,   The battle of the Irish people against the British Government was part of the Communist battle.   The Communist Party wanted to establish ths rule of the workers in England, Scotland and Wales, and until they had absolutely ana utterly destroyed the present State on the other side, destroyed it politically and all its attendant forces of the British Crown, they could not establish the rule of the Workers on the other sido, and it was because of that tha-t the should of necessity stand for the ind rpendence of Ireland.

</content>
</cab>
