<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/128/0 images: 478-484</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
xHjo, Document lo tho Pjegg^tfoLTo &quot;be destroyed when replaced &quot;by a subsequent number.SEI0RT5T.m  33 62SBORE-T ADMIRAJjiy WEEKLY   INTlLLIOffNOff   5UMvI/RY,t,No. 59..   lst Pot ob er T ,^9,^^Issued by the Naval Intelligence Division Naval Staff, Admiralty, for the information of Recipients only.DISTRIBUTION. Sont by All British Route to307Oopies.0ot)ie3.;3oard of Admiralty ................ 10&apos;ep^Seo .,Naval Sec.,P.A.S,F.,P.A.S. 4Duty Oaptain ...................... 1ilhe Cabinet ....................... 40c.,.Naval Board, Melbourne ....... 2Sac,Naval Board, New Zealand ..... 2Dire ot or, Naval Servioe, Ottawa ... 1P.A.N.A.O. ........................ 1aptain Segrave, R.N. Naval Representative,League of Nations .............. 1ommanders-in-Ohief,The Nore ....................... portsmouth...................... 1&amp; Plymouth....................... 1&apos; Scotland....................6. . 1ff. ApproachesAtlantic Fleet.................   2NthoAmerica &amp; //est IndiesMediterranean ...........OiiiiiS&apos; i)oo******** ********East Indies ............**Af rica....................A.0., Reserve Fleet1 1 1 1 1 1[Y.A.O., 1st Battle Squadron.......   11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1...ok * n * ic o e . . o * .8.A., 1st Battle Squadron LA., 4th Battle Squadron \A., Battle Cruiser Squadron .A0, 1st light Oruiser Squadron I.A., 2nd Light Oruiser Squadron I.A., Srd Light Oruiser Sque,dron 0.ViA* ^ It CiiYlS/j h S 0 m % * * * * o o o o * t e y e ft$ *ov* fr* A a ( L, j r i s t * * I * i t i * t * at I if 9 q i o a i i Il-e A 9        3 /      c , o * o * * a * *o **p****ooeoo***^     TOTAL (Distribution &quot;by Oopy:lng Branch)Admiralty Naval StaffIoDf    ..........P*D*    ............ so .$nT.D..................Intelligence Offioers S.I,0&apos;s -Meddterranean ........Cliina ................-Ikst Indies ..........S. America ...........N. America ...........Ottawa...............D.1.0*3 -Portsmouth ...........Chatham..............Devonport.......0....Rosyth.............Hull.................Liverpool............Queenstown...........Gibraltar............Malta................Colombo..............Singapore............Shanghai.............Wellington...........Oapo Town............Bermuda............e,Ascension ............D *N *Ia, Melbourne .... N.too.v Kong Kong . N,V0C,, Monte Video N.V.O., Oallao ....a . . . o85TOTAL (I.D. Distribution)18 oa2 11 1 1 1 1 11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1,1 1 1 1 1&apos;49
,3-jjT. To he destroyed when replaced&quot;by a subsequent number. 1,INTELLI G-SNOE   SUMMARY.No,. 591, ,,, For thn. week ending 1st October.,. ,193.1, PART . I.. ,   NAVAL , JEMMW^.&apos; GREAT . BRITAIN. Movements, of H.M.r ghjjps,.28th gojtH.M.S. &quot;Thunderer&quot; left Devonport for Vigo.28th September.   H.M.S. &quot;Blenheim&quot; arrived Devonport from the Mediterranean.28thJe]p^H.M.S. &quot;Delhi&quot; left Devonport for Heligoland and arrived 30th September.29th September.   2nd light Oruiser Squadron and 2nd Flotilla arrived Copenhagen from Stockholm.1st October. H.M.S. &quot;DelMJleft Heligoland with Heligoland Sub-Commission for Sheerness.H.M.S. &quot;Thunderer&quot; arrived Vigo.commander-in-Ohief, Mediterranean, inHJJLS. &quot;IRON IflJI-with &quot;Ajax&quot;, &quot;Stuart&quot;, &quot;Senator&quot;, &quot;Sepoy&quot;, &quot;Shark&quot; and yyombtixf&amp;to, - Leave Constantinople 6th October (approx.) formaltality.H.M.S. &quot;Montrose&quot;, &quot;Spear&quot;, &quot;Swallow&quot; and bTrinidad&quot; -Leave Constantinople 13th October for Malta,    &quot;Montroce&quot; vrill call at Piraeus en route.H.M.S. &quot;Speedy&quot; - Leaves Port Said 3rd October;-Haifa 4th October;&apos; Jaffa 5th ,October; Gaza 6t&apos;h Ootober; Alexandria 7th October.H.M*S. &quot;Veronioa&quot; - Leaves Suva 29th September on cruise, visiting Funafuti (Ellioe Is.) Ocean Is. (Paanopa Is.) Taritari (Touching Is.) and Tarawa (Cook Is.) returning bo Suvra 27th October. Due Auckland, November.Oommander-in--0hief, Western Approaches , in ILMcSa &quot;Hoather&quot;, leaves Queenstovm 3rd October to visit ports on ffect Coast of Ireland.   thence to Liverpool and Pembroke-H.M.S. &quot;Espiegle.&quot; - Visits Dar-es-Salaam, Zanzibar, MoTjbasa, Brava, Mogdishu and Kismayu on - present cruise arriving Aden 20th&apos;November.
2.Rear-Admiral Sir John Pitka, E.O.U.a.^ has retired from the Estonian Navy.   Tho Acting Commander of Naval Forces is Commander Johann Horn (Gross of Liberty and Gross of St. George) the Chief of the Naval Staff is Captain SaltsaiThe follo^/ing gunboats are in commission on Lake.PeipuoflAhtiB   -    144 tons displacement;   speed 10 knots; 2 Q,.P. guns and 2-1 pdrs.&quot;Tartu&quot; -    128 ft. x 1^ ft. x 3 ft.   2-1 pdrs.The gunboats &quot;Taara&quot;, &quot;TJku!1 and &quot;Vanomuino&quot; have been disarmed and converted to trade uses.?.y order of the Estonian Government vessels flying., the British flag are alleged to enjoy that same favours as regards harbour&quot;dues as Estonian ships.The new mole at Reval in place of the old jetty is in course of erection and work will bo finished by the end of 1921.     The Baltic Shipbuilding Co&apos;s Shipbuilding Yards have been acquired on lease by the Anglo-Baltic Shipbuilding and Engineering Company Ltd. and work has already been taken in hand.The Depth of water at Narva in summer is stated to be 16 - 21 feet. Four mooring buoys are reported as having been removed.It is reported that six destroyers of the &quot;NovikB  -type are in commission and go out for cruises in the Gulf of Finland.   Many destroyers are in good repair and seaworthy. Five submarines are in commission, the sixth is under repair. The submarine -repair ship has been transferred from Petrograd to Kronstadt.   Trawlers are continually sweeping in the Gulf of Finland.From information received, it appears that Pantherjanski, Commander of the Naval Forces of the Black Sea and the Sea of Azov, is not on gooc] terms with. Nemitz, Assistant to the Coirxiaiader-in-Chief of the Naval Forces at Petrograd.There is no truth in tho report that Russian Soviet have purchased airships in Italy.sweden.Naval, Aviation.   The development of the Naval Flying Station at Hagarnai.) (5-miles North of Stockholm) is to be undertaken shortly;   the reoent destruction by fire of the Naval Aviation. Workshops in Stockholm Harbour has necessitated earlier action than was antioipated.
Italian naval policy now alas at concentration in regard Tyrrhenian .Soa.   To this end, squadrons in like Adrtat and in foreign and colonial waters have been considerably decreased dxiring the past 12 months, and tho ships sor-withdra-vm allocated to.Jihd Main Fleet which is based on Spezia.&quot;The situation remains quiet, and concentration of tho Fleet at Con3tantinoj^le is not at proaont essential.
PART ,1%. PJRSIA.Owing to tho policy of the prei^ntrPer&amp;ian Government, the situation in the provinces is worse than ever, Azerbaijan and Kurdistan are seeahing with di^-c-ontant, disturbances are expected in Kermanshah, there are trouble^-in Haraadan, the settlement of the Gilan question is being delayed at the bidding of the Rusfcian Minister and tho Province of Khoraseanhas ceased for the time being tc form part of Persia,Bakhtiaris and the South generally fear Bolshevik aggression owing to the impending disbandment of the South Persian Rifles and disturbances and robberies are taking place on a growing scale.Afghanistan&apos;TAN. -The Afghans are awaiting the arrival of Ghulam Sadik, one of the Afghan Mission which was recently in London, before coming &quot;to any decision regarding our latest proposals. Prom reports &quot;received of the impression gained, by Sadik, it is likely that he will prove to be of considerable help in influencing his countrymen to enter into friendly relations with H.M. Government,   Ghulara Sadik was due to arrive in Kabul on the 25th September,Meanwhile the Amir appaarsjmore conciliatory.The Resident at Aden has telegraphed urgently requesting to be supplied with arms in order to strengthen the tribes in the Aden Protectorate against Arab aggression. As a defensive measure cavalry have been moved to cover LaheJ..Lithuania has received &apos;de Jure&apos; recognition from Norway and Sweden, and Denmark.RUSSIA.The,Tula Arms Factory (south of Moscow) has received inspections&quot;!, o double its output, and work 3 shifts of 8 hours eac&amp;.     The factory has worked day and. night since 20th August.   The workmen receive increased food rations.Ger^gia,Information received oonfirms the impression that Georgia is, like Azerbaijan, reverting to the status of a Russian Bolshevik Colony.
Siboria.   A report from Ohita states that Merkuloffs authority no longer exists at Vladisvostock.   General Molchanoff is at the head of tho armed insurgents and is arranging for the creation of new looal administration.$mm.-The treaty/ of ueace between Germany and the United States of Amerioa was ratified by the Reichstag on the 30th September.     The Communists voted against it, and the Nationalists abstained from voting.HUNGARY.The Government has agreed to evacuate the Burgenland&apos; by the 4th October.   They will not hold themselves responsible for bands of irregulars.The Conference of Ambassadors has called on the Hungarian Government to annul forthwith thegcalling up of 20,000 $en.GREECE.The Greek Prime Minister and Minister for. Foreign Affairs propose to leave for London on 15th October, but Y/ill probably be asked to postpone their visit to suit the convenience of H.MGovernment.ALBANIA.The Jugc-Slav Government call attention to the state of-civil war prevailing in Albania.   Thousands of Mirdite refugees are seeking to cross into Jugo-Slavia to escape massacre which confronts them if the Tirana Government is victorious. It has not yet been decided whether they are to be admitted.rorogsY.General Harington arrives home on 3rd October, taking passage to Malta in &quot;Surprise&quot;.General Mombelli acts as G.O.C. in his absence, and   &apos; the French cordially accept the situation of French troops serving under an Italian General.Exchangejpf Prisoners,.   Arrangements for transporting the Turiclsh pris oners of^war from Malta and thence to a Black Sea port are in hand.     The question of the exchange has been discussed at Constantinople between our High Commissioner and a representative of the Angora Government.   The latter offer to try the 8 Turkish prisoners accused of war crimes, and will give all facilities to British witnesses, &amp;c.    The proposals for exchange at a Black Sea port are agreed to, and it is hoped that our prisoners will be free by the 15th October.Bil 3iE &amp;S,* An international relief committee has been formed to take over from the American Red Cross.There are between 32 and 33 thousand Russian refugees in Constantinople and its surroundings.   17 thousand are absolutely destitute, and one thousand sleep in the streets.
Tho Allied Governments are &quot;being appealed to for grants, &apos; but such grants can only bo a tcmporary-T?alliative, and the refugees are a continuing liability.Arrangements have boon completed for the despatch of the last 8,000 men of  range11 s army to Bulgaria.Grp ek, operatjonjs. &apos;&apos;. \&apos;The main operations may be considered as finished^ it is not boTiovod that either side contemplates v^Lrrter operations.

</content>
</cab>
