<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/128/0 images: 687-688</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).CONFIDENTIAL. . yC.P.-3396. jCABINET.LEAGUE   OF   NATIONS;THEJ FUTURE 0? ARMENIA *Letter to tho Prime Minister from the Secretary-General of the league cf Nations-LEAGUE OF NATIONS, GENEVA *6th October, 1921.   .Sir,I have the honour to inform you that at its sessionof the 21st September, the Assembly of the League ofNations unanimously adopted the following resolution:&quot;Seeing that the-First Assembly,on November 18, 1980, entrusted the Council with tho duty of safe-guarding the future of Armenia;&quot;And. that the \ Council cn Febrns^y^Sth, 1921, while holding&quot;&quot;that the situation In Adife Minor made action for the time,being impossible, entrusted tho Secretary-General with the duty of watching dovelop-ments in Armenian affairs with a view to procuring subsequent decisions by the Council;&quot;And that In the mean time the Supreme Council in tho revision of the Treaty of Sevresj proposed to make provision for k&apos; National Home for the Armenians;&quot;Seeing, further; the probable imrjliilenoe of a Peace Treaty between Turkey and the Allied Powers at no distant date;&quot;The Assembly urges the Council td press upon tho Supremo Council of the Allies the necessity of making provisions in this Treaty for safeguarding the future of Armenia, and in particular of providing the Armenians with a National Home entirely independent of Turkish rule.&quot;The Council of tho League, considered this resolution at its mooting on 2nd October, and decided to associate itself with the views expressed by the Assembly.-1
Tha Coiwe.il has , the pa fore requested m4 to urge upon -jon the importance of..this matter;,, and to express tho hope that at the appropriate moment the.principal Allied powers will moke provision for safeguarding the. future of. Armenia, and in particular for.providing the Armenians with a National Home entirely independent of Turkish rule,I have the honour to be,Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Signed)       Y*K* WELLINGTON KOO.President of the Councilof the League of nations.Tho Ht... Hon.;David Lloyd George., O.M.,H.P.-2-

</content>
</cab>
