<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/24 images: 426-437</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,.....,-rrJTS THS PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT.COPY NO.)(.,0)2U.WAR CABINET.COAL POSITION.Ninth Fortnightly Report submitted by the Secretary forlanes covering the period 1st to Ihth January, 19L,0.(Previous Report:    Paper No. W.P. (R.) (i+O)^.)(Initialled) G. L.Richmond Terrace,s.w. 1,7th January, 19h0,

;ion and Employment.;rend of production during the fortnight endedJanuary dipped in accordance with the incidence of theiristmas and New Year holidays,  the total quantity of saleable3ai raised being 6,7*10,000 tons for the period.     Compared witha year ago this represents a decide of 1*13,000 tons.     As thexber of pit-days worked were practically the same, the decline,at have been due to the volume of individual absenteeism.ITEM1939Weekending30thDec.191+019U0Weekending6thJan.2 Weeksending6 thJan.(Provisional)   j(provisional)19392 Weeksending7thJan.EstimatedQuantityof saleablecoal raised ITons2,861,000Tons3,879,000Tons6,7h-o,oooTons7,153,000Employment showed a slight recession during the fortnight,the average number of 759,000 wage earners comparing with760,000 for the preceding fortnight.      The number employed;cntinues, however, to remain around 16,000 below thecorresponding level a year ago.      Working time at the pits was affected by the seasonal holidays, the time worked during the&apos;&apos;&apos;o weeks to 6th January amounting to 8Dh-5 days, or slightly morejtiian a year ago.ITEM,ace earnersl&apos;iRe worked(lays1939		19u1	19140	1939Week ending 9 th Sept.	Week ending 30 th Dec.	Week ending 6 th Jan. &apos;provisions onal)	2 Weeks ending 6 th Jan. (Provisional)	2 Weeks ending 7th Jan.7h8,600 5.10	758,700 3.65	758,800 U.80	758,800 8 ;I*5	77h-,700 8.35

-jotv/ithctanding restrictions on shipping facilities good-,,.oSs continues to he made with the export of coal.      The.-, n,ientity of coal shipped abroad during the fortnight endedJanuary amounted to 1,508,000 tons,     Although this was some&apos; tons less than for the preceding fortnight on account.v- of seasonal factors,  the total was 172,000 tons more thanthe corresponding period a year ago.      This indicates thatimprovement in exports is being steadily maintained.rotai Quantityof coalshipped abroad(including thecoal equivalent of colce andl-manufactured1939We oAending30 thDec.Tons679,0001 o) i n1939end:&apos;Jig6 thJan.(provisional2 Weeksending6thJan.(Prcvisional)Tons829,000Tons1,508,0002 Weeksending7 thJan.Tons1,336,000ie Negotiations.In connection with the negotiations now proceeding with italy, the British Delegation in Rome has been informed that in our viewcoking coal required by Italy in 1940 additional to theaillion tons to be supplied by Durham could be obtained fromsennany by rail if seaborne imports fro:.: Germany are cut off.Nevertheless it would be possible to offer from Durham up to aboutmillion tons additional of lower grade coals suitable for coking&quot; the Italians persist in pressing us to supply these.The Italians have already been Informed that in the aggregatedisregarding special qualities we could make available to them^subject to satisfactory payment conditions) enough coal to replaceGerman seaborne imports.

eve re pressure continues to be exerted upon the coastwise0-,t of supplier? fran the North Bast Coast to London and the-3 a result of the scarcity of shipping.      Many gas andicity undertakings in those areas are able to be effectivelyn \ only by sea, and for those which are in seriousljr urgentf coal, special application has &quot;been, made to the Ministry of.r- to obtain the necessary shipments.oves to secure supplementary supplies for London and thern Areas by the alternative method of railing coal directhe North have resulted in the despatch of initial trairloads1 from   Durham to these areas.     Railway transport in generaltinned, however, to be impeded by the persistence of fogvarious sections of the lines, resulting at one time in theof nearly 5,000 loaded wagons of coal and coke in transitSouth.tops ere being taken to build up reserve supplies in they yards in and around London by the acquisition of qualities1 which are not required for industrial and public utilityes, but which have to be raised in conjunction with such coal.ations are proceeding for the&apos;purchase in the first instance.e 10,000 tons of coal ready to be released by the Midlandornated) Eistrict which it is proposed to stock at thei depot of the L.N,E.R.he stock position of a number of public utility undertakingsLondon and Southern areas remains below the safety margin.3-n-don Power Company has again drawn upon its reserve, and the5ea* Bow and Deptford works have on the average tinder-s&apos; supply, while    the Grove Road works have slightly under 5.3 at the Fulham Electricity works are down to 3 weeks&apos;  supply,a;-eide works to 2-g- weeks&apos;, and the Maidstone, Portsmouth andto ^undertakings are down to 2 weeks&apos;  supply.     Among the gas0-n;;.3, the weakest spots are Lower Sydenham and Bromley workssouth Suburban Gas Company with just over 3 weeks&apos;  supply,&apos; Ui&quot;i with 2.8 weeks&apos;  and the Wandsworth District Gas&quot;^h 2 weeks&apos;  supply.

At a meeting of the National Joint Consultative Committee efi.---HPfi- Association and Mineworkers&apos; Federation on 4th January,torkmen asked whether the ov/ners could make any better offer the offer of a minimum increase of 4d per shift for adultsa 2d per shift for youths;    to which the owners replied they:11 not.The workmen then suggested going on to discuss a formula fortomatic increases in wages on condition that the owners agreedapply such a formula, when settled, retrospectively from january.      The owners accepted this suggestion, hut indicatedst they had at that stage no mandate to go any further in thetter, being unable to reach agreement or even make definiteoposals.However, the owners stated that they had in mind a formulaich adjusted wage increases to the full extent of the rise ine cost of living only in the case of the lowest paid workers,at is about 8/6d a shift less fixed deductions for statutorysurance etc. This meant that the rise in wages granted tor. on higher rates of pay would be less than the equivalent ofe increase in the cost of living. It also meant giving lessnwas obtainable under the formula proposed by the men, which to relate the full cost of living index to the average ratefv&quot;ges paid throughout the country.      The men made no formalIt v/as then arranged that a meeting of the Central CouncilCoal Owners should be called on 17th January to put definiteposals before the workmen,  preparatory to a further meeting ofNational Joint Consultative Committee on the following day.svooajPosition.applies for South Wales at French ports to-day areicient provided shipping is available.      In three monthslies will fall, possibly by 25$, due to diversion of labourProduction.      Then supply may not meet demand.

Supplies for South Wales from Portugal are not satisfactory,reasons being partly Internal to Portugal and partly lack ofpping.As regards England and Scotland the position is satisfactorythe moment but unless stocks can be built up during themer by shipments from Canada the position next Winter willmost serious.     At the suggestion of the Secretary for Mines,eetiiig was called by the Minister of Supply on the 12th Januarycinsider the best means of meeting this situation and thevision  of substitute materials, to the maximum which is safe,order to reduce the demand for timber.


</content>
</cab>
