<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/33/7 images: 46-49</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.W.J . (43)7th Conclusions.KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KJEYIt is requested Jthat special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 7 (43).Copy No.   48CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, January12, 1943, at 12-30 p.m.Present:The Right Horn Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon.  Viscount  Simon,Lord Chancellor.The following were also present:The Right Hon Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir . archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Contents.minute no. Subject. ?f*9e1      India        ______        ... .... .... .... ....       28Detention of Gandhi.2      India        .... .... ........ ........       28Food situation.[24911]. Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1%4^.
Detention otGaniihl(previous reference::W.M.(43)4thConclusions,Minute 2.)1. THE War Cabinet had before them.a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for India (W,P. (43) 16)covering copies of the telegram sent to the Viceroy in pursuance of the War Cabinet&apos;decision of the 7th January, and of the Viceroy&apos;s reply, on thequestion of Gandhi&apos;s detention. ;The Viceroy had given full consideration to the War Cabinet&apos;views, but still favoured the course which he had recommended inthe correspondence previously circulated with W.P. (43) 5.;&apos; he added that, in his judgment, it would be an act of weakness to release Gandhi on compassionate grounds at this stage^ now...thathe had hinted that, he was contemplating a, fast.. He also made itclear that, if the course which he recommended were adopted,Gandhi would be kept in detention until his fast was actuallyendangering his health (possibly two or three&apos; days after his fastbegan); and, further, that if after his release he recovered his health and again began to stir up trouble, he would be brought back intodetention the moment he infringed the law.The Viceroy also reaffirmed his view that Gandhi&apos;s personal letter should be answered without further delay in the terms of thedraft set out in his telegram (38-S) dated the 6th January.The general view of the War Cabinet was that, having made their views known, they must leave the final decision in this matter to the responsible authority on the spot.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of Sta,te for India to inform theViceroy as follows : That the War Cabinefs views on this, matter had not changed but that they did not wish to interfere withthe considered judgment of the Viceroy on whomlay the immediate responsibility for handling thesituation that the matter would best be dealt withon the lines he had proposed, both as regards (a) theterms of the reply to be. sent to Mr. Gandhi, and(6) the action to be taken if Mr. Gandhi undertooka fast.India.food situation.2. Reference was made to recent telegrams from the Viceroyreporting the development of a serious food shortage in India.The Secretary of State for India outlined the action taken bythe Government of India to secure a greater measure of centralisation-tion in the control of food supplies, through the establishment of anew Food Ministry at Delhi. In view of the increasing gravity ofthe situation, arrangements had now been made to send out as anadviser to the Government of India an experienced official of theMinistry of Food.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for India to ask the Ministerof State if he could also arrange to send to India an officialwho had had experience in the Middle East in overcoming the tendency of producers of cereals to withhold supplies from the market during periods of shortage.;Offices of the War Cabinet,.S. W. 1,January 1% i%4&amp;.



</content>
</cab>
