<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/104/0 images: 15-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;::i:iS DOCUMENT. IS TH-? PH0?TRT7r OF HIS BRITANNIC,MAJESTY * S JOTEMMZMJ :LONDON TRAFFIC, AUTHORITY.. Memorandum, by the Chancellor of the exchequer.The Minister of T rapport proposes in his memorandum (CP.1042) of the 9th instant that the recommendations of the Report of the Advisory committee on London Traffic (cmd. 636) he accepted and that an announcement he made in the House that the Government accept the creation, position and status of the proposed London Traffic authority and that a Bill is being drafted for early submission to parliament.According to the scheme which the Minister of Transport pro-poses should be accepted, a Board of 3 commissioners would be con-stituted (with salaries amounting for the 3 to  10,000 a year) and their salaries and the cost of their office would be borne on the Ministry of Transport Votes.The Office would be of considerable size as its duties would comprise (inter &amp;lia)(4) the preparation of an authoritative general development plan to which all new London transit schemes would conform. *(6) the selection and prescription of routes to be followed by all or any forms and classes &apos; of traffic;. . (7) the fixing of building or frontage lines of roads.(9) scientific research. (10) the rirht to initiate or oppose traffic legis-lation, regulation and byelaws, and to deal with the revision, simplification, coaification and extension of traffic legislation, regulations\S I C R S T .Copy No.CP. 1104 *CABINET.
and byelaws now in force so far as the London area    - . ., , is concerned,, the confirmation of all new traffic I byelaws&apos;and the fixing of speed limits within, thearea..(11). to act as Arbitrator &quot;between various Authorities.Sir&apos;!?. Geddes also states in hi s. memorandum, that the proposed Bill would &quot;contain provision for making grants or loans, or re- .. couping losses on any&apos; services ordered by the Traffic Authority under the ministry &apos; of&quot; transport the Minister of Health as the representative of Local Authori-ties may probably have objections to the proposal number 7.   I make no comment on &quot;it but I am unable to agree that Votes of. parliament are the proper source from.which funds should be found for paying the salaries of&apos; the proposed London Traffic authority or its office, or for&apos;grants or loans or.in recoupment, of losses on services initiated by.such a Board.-It seems to me that this essentially local problem should be met from local revenues and not from the Exchequer.-, The problem of London traffic&apos; differs only, in size from that which is presented by many&apos;great provincial centres where traffic is congested,- and there would be no answer to such places.as. Glasgow, Manchester or Birmingham if they claimed equality of treatment with London.While I do not object to the constitution of a London.Traffic Authority/ the right solution appears to me to be to charge all its expenses -on the rates.-(intld..)   A.Creasury,.. ^;.t.. 30th April, 192p;.

</content>
</cab>
