<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/104/0 images: 276-276</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Military Secret. 1301 196-sfirom Viceroy, Army Department, to Secretary of Stale for India,&apos;      23rd April 1920.Clear the line.5118.   23rd April.  No. 183.Parti. (1) About 100 Mohmands and Afridis reported in Jalalabad awaiting enlistment in Afghan Army.   See para. 1 of Serial No. 179.(2) Kuram. Reported three companies of Afghan regulars have resumed their old positions on Peivvar ridge, one picket being quarter of mile inside our territory. (Political Agent ?) Knrain is being instructed to address local Afghan authorities with view to early withdrawal of picket.(3) Waziristan. Kabul Khel section evading compliance with terms by migration to Birmal via Khost. Rifles continue to come in from other sections of Tochi Waziris, totals up to 19th being .123 Government, 161 Tribal rifles and Rs. 28,221 lines.   Mahsuds admit 50 casualties in recent operations up Baddar Toi.(4) Afghanistan. Public feeling on the Khalifat question said to be increasing-owing to tone oi vernacular newspapers received from India,(5) Copies have been received from Jalalabad of a leaflet in Urdu inciting Indian troops to mutiny. Leaflet which is issued by &quot; Temporary Government of India War Department&quot; is probably work of Indian seditionists in Kabul and does not appear to be Bolshevic inspired.(6) Party of 28 Russjans arrived at Mazar-i-Sharii: end of March from Termez. They are said to be en route for Kabul.Part II. (7) Derajat Column moved on 8th from Kaniguram to new camp at Ladha half-way between Kaniguram and Dwa Toi. A few shots fired by enemy but no casualties.(8) Aeroplane shot down at Datta Khel in Upper Kaitu Valley on 13th. Aviators brought in safely to Idak on 17th.(9) Frontier constabulary escort of 20 rifles with construction party attacked near Draband on 16th by about 50 of the enemy believed Waziris. Party had eight casualties including four constabulary killed.   No rifles lost.(10) Owing to raid on village two miles east of Chaman Fort carried ont with apparent connivance of Afghan authorities at Spin Baldak, garrison of Chaman is at request of local authorities being temporarily reinforced as a precautionary measure.Paras. (4), (5), (6), and (10) not communicated to Press.

</content>
</cab>
