<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/104/0 images: 405-418</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DISABILITY PENSIONS COMITMt MAIN RSPOBT OH DISABILITY IN PnST-WAB OASES4(Paper No, CUP, 1154)Unless objection is raised to any of ttoa recommendations in this Report, it is proposed that the Cabinet should take note of it at the next Meeting.(Signed)     THOMAS JOKES.Acting Secretary.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W, 26th April, 1920.
(THIS &quot;DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITAIINIC MAHESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) * S E G R g T. Copy Ho. _4C.P,-1154. CABINS T.DISABILITY PBMSIOMS COIvtMITTSB,MAJJiJEPORT Ojj DISABILITY BMSIOffS IN POST-WAR giggg^1.     The Disability pensions Committee submit the following further report, dealing with the pensions of Warrant Officers, Non-Commissionod Officers, and men of the Royal Marines, Army and Air Force, and Petty Officers and men of the Royal Navy discharged after the war for causes other than disabilities attributable to service in the war. 2.     hon-Attrlbutable Cases.The Majority of tho Committee see no reason for varying the soale recommended for present war cases in Section 3 of their first report.   It is observed that &quot;service&quot; under existing Army Warrants includes service in the reserve, while under the Committee1s recommendations it is strictly confined to colour service.    The Committee think that the question of vested rights in the Army may require further examination but, subject of course to the recognition of vested rights, the Majority of tho Committee recommend the application of their proposal to the Army as . well as to the Havy.   The views of the War Office representative on this subject are set out in a separate Minority report herewith.It is recommended that the scalo set out in Section Zof the First Report of the Committee shall apply to Post-War cases subject to the following amendments.(a)
(a) the grant of a pension in the Navy and Army after 10 years colour service, will be-dontintted only to men with vested rights;   for new entrants service pension will he given only  after 14 years:(b) for the Air Force only, in which a man may be required to serve for 24 years before completinghis contract, it is necessery to add a fresh rate,s dover   years. .........................2/9 a day.The scale with these amendments is set out in Appendix 1. 3.   Attributable cases .The. recommendations of the Committee as to the rete of. Disability Pension in cases where no service, pension, is payable are set out in paragraph 5 below... The problem of the.man who is eligible both for a service, pension, and a disability pension is very difficult.   In- the prerwar warrants it was Impossible for a man to draw both service and disability pension though in the actual assessment of disability pension allowance was somethimes made.for long service. . For war cases a new practice was at first introduced of giving a service pension in full and a disability pension in full, but at that time the service pension was small.     The Committee do not consider that it ia practicable to revert to the pre-war practice; -at the same time the service pension has since been, increased and it would be extravagant to pay both pensions in full.- The
The Cabinet decided on the 6th November last that even in war cases where a service pension is drawn the disability pension should be based on n rate of 33s. (i.e. excluding the latest cost of living increase of 7s. recommended by the Select Committee on Pensions.)The problem before the Committee as regards post war cases is therefore to fix the service element, the disability element and the rank element and to ley down a method for oombining these in a joint pension. 4 *   Service Element *The Committee again recommend the scale laid down for non-attributable present war oases.     Thi may be regarded as a scale which recognises the basic rate of 1-J-dU a day but in a general way provides., as is only proper, that a man who leaves the service some yea. before Completing his contract is not entitled to the full proportionate pension based on his actual years of service.It is recommended therefore that the service &quot;element&quot; in -service cum disability oases should be&apos; the same as the service pension where no disability pension is drawn i.e. the rates set out in Appendix 1. 5*    Disability Element *The Committee regard it as obvious that the exceptional features of the Tar Pensions system (e.g, alternative pension e&apos;t&amp;) are not to be oontinued for the post war professional Navy and Army.     Nor do they consider it practical to make any distinctionbetween
between-en narrie-d,.and- unmarried nen,     l?o definite information is before the pomitt-^v,..     to- tfh-e--. ^nrtlrmrcru^^ .....or no n- co nt inunn ce o f separat ion al 1 owan ce ,The 7orkm.en&apos; s Compenflat ion Act. makes no such distinction and the analogy with war pensions is weak, as a concession that was necessary under con-script ion is not necessarily required when the Navy and Amy have ag&amp;a become professions.The war rate of disability pension is 40s, a week.     This however is subject to revision with cost of living after 3 years,     The maximum Tore-war rate for a private,  it may be noted, was 17. 6d,     The present Workmen*s Compensation Rate is half wages subject to a maximum, in oases of total disability only of 35s. and,&apos; in oases of less disability 20s.. a week.     After careful&apos; consideration the Committee have decided to&apos;recommend(a) For the lowest grades, seamen, private, airman, et o., a ma.xira.um. pension for disability attributable to service, of 32s. 6d. for total disablement, less depress of disablement carrying proportionately reduoed rates.     In special cases of total disablement, the department concerned should have power to increasethe rate to 40s.(b) l\To distinction should be made as to the nature of the disability or the circumstances in which it was contracted, provided it was due to x Service apart from questions of negligenoe or misconduct.     The rate of pension should depend on degree of- disablement only. Climatic disease should be included.&apos; these the Committee do not feel able to make any definite recommendation on -tha subject of disability &quot;a .(?ravated by&quot; Service pending, the report of the liedical Disability Committee of the Kin istry of Pensions.
These axe therefore the rates recommended for dis-ability pension., in oases where no service pension is drawn and also the disability &quot;element&quot; of service own disability pensions 6.   Ran]^; Elemen/s^ *The Admiralty War Office and Air Ministry will make the usual additions for rank etc, ad in the new service scale. 7&apos;   M5Lth o d^of^.c^mJ^Aning service clement, disability element.Thare is no difficulty about the rank element;   it should be added (once only) in every case.As already stated, the Committee are agreed that the servioe element and the disability element, where both are drawn cannot be paid in full.     A disability pension is g v^n in order to enable the invalided man to live, and it cannot be deni ed that the service pension helps .     In fixing the amount of weekly payment under the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act, regard is had to any payment or benefit which the workman receives iSrom his employer during his incapacity.     If the disability pension is enough, it is in theory at least enough for the man who has earned a pension as well.On the other hand, it i3 not practicable to revert entirely to prs-war conditions when only sftall and arbitrary additions were i..n.ie to disability p&amp;cislon in respeat of service.     Similarly, if two men are entitled to service pension, and&apos; one is disabled and the other perfectly fit there is reason for giving something extra to the disabled man.The. Commit3 recommend that where a man is eligible for both servioa element and disability element he should receive whichever of these is the larger ( in his particular oase) in full plus one half of the other.A table showing what on this basis would be the total pension in respect of servioe ranging from 10 to 22 years and disability from 20$ to 100$ is attached.    It contains ne special feature to which attention need be drawn,     While itwould
would be possible to construct by purely arbitrary nethods a table which would bo &quot;smoother&quot; in appearance, the Committee definitely do not reoommend the construction of such an arbitrary table, as they consider that it will be easier to state and defend the adoption of the simple general rule recommended above.It may happen in a few isolated cases that the present recommendations of the Committee, are slightly more generous than those made in their first report for present war cases. If this occurs, the man discharged during the war or on account of disability due to the war must of course be allowed the more favourable of the two alternatives.The representative of the Ministry of Pensions disagrees because,(1) he considers that it would not be possible to defend a rate of 3&amp;/6d. a week as the minimum pension, for a totally disabled man of the lowest rank without service pension in view of the present cost of living and the fact that the minimum war disability for disablement is 40/- a week as representing the lowest amount for the maintenance of the single man who can-not camcfS) Under the proposed scheme the men in the lower degrees of disablement receive proportionately much more generoustreatment than those in the higher degrees.He prefers therefore a scheme for a rate of disablementpension common to all of 40/- a week, to be reduced as in the.case of war pensions as the cost of living falls, together withfixed additions in respecting^Ot of service, as under the scheme approved for service cum disability war pensioners.The Committee have carefully considered these objections, but adhere to their recommendations above.     Thoyagree with the Ministry of /Pensions representative in thinking that, if a 40/- rate were adopted, it would be necessary to reconsider the amount of their service element as set out above, : Service
Service less than 14 years, Jor 10 years Colour Service ;;oro tern)Hen discharged for non-attributable disability with less than 14 years1 Service (10 years1 Colour Service pro ten) should, it is recommended, by the majority of the Committee be allowed in respect of each completed year of service a gratuity of not less than    with an additional 10s. for each step (i.e. extra 10$) of disability in excess of 30$.     llo addition would be made for rank in such a case,,The Viar Office representative would prefer to leave the award in Army cases to the discretion of the Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital, within a maximum of  50, the predominant consideration being the degree of the disability.     The majority of the Committee are unable to concur in special arrangements for the Army.Hen discharged for attributable disability with less Service,than 14 years1/ (or 10 years1 Colour Service pro tern) should,it is recommended, receive in addition to disability pension agratuity not exceeding  2 for each year of service.Gratuities paid in the Army and Air Force under thisparagraph should not be treated as additional to the gratuitynow paid to soldiers and airmen on discharge i.e. the soldieror airman may receive the gratuity paid under existing warrantsnotor that now recommended but/both.     The method of paying gratuities &apos;Xi,e. in one sum or by weekly or monthly instalments) awarded under this and the succeeding paragraph, should be within the discretion of the DepartmentcThe Committee recommend that a boy under the age of 18 should, if his discharge is caused by an attributable disability, be eligible for disability pension or disability gratuity but have no other claim under-the scheme.
?,     Attributable Disability of lass than 80ft.If discharge is due to slight permanent Injury on duty or disability due to service of less than 20$ a gratuity appropriate to the degree of disability, but not exceeding a maximum of  100, may&apos; be awarded an respect of the injury or disability fin addition to service pension, if applicable).In cases where a man has less that 14 years&apos; service for ten years1 colour service pro tern) and. an attributable disability of less than 20$, he may receive-a gratuity for disability under this paragraph as well as a gratuity, not exceeding  2 for each year of service, under paragraph 8 above,    i^o addition for rank would be made in such a case.10.        The committee recommend that the scales now approved for post-war Disability pensioners shall be applied also to pre-war life Disability pensioners under the same conditions and. as from the same date as the increases in long-service pensions have been applied to long-service pensioners subject, however, so far as the Disability element is concerned, to medical survey to determine the present degree of Disability.
(Signed).......Stanley Baldwin ,0hairman.(     &quot;   ).......Jc(J Ashley, ,1-rr Office,(except as regards Service Pension, on which dissentient report is annexed)%(     &quot;   ).......T.D. &quot;lames,Admiralty,f &quot; )-William SanderMinistry of Pensions..F.Phillips,Treasury.(     &quot;   ).......J. A. Smith,Air Ministry.2, ffhiteGardens, SVflJl.26th April, 1920.
APPENDTI   I.Table,Non-Attributable Scale.10 years . l/- a14     &quot; 1/616     &quot; 1/918     &quot; 2/-on     n 2/6      &quot;    (up to 21 years for ArmyV)(up to 22 years  pi La- andi Ail l?i rc-fci&apos; iSg     n -2/9      &quot;   (up to 24 years for i;ir Force.)UOTE.      On completion of contract (i.e*.Aa&apos;my 21 years Bayy 22 years, and Air Force 24 yoars), the pension becomes the full rate of per day for each year ofpensionable service.
tableservice aintd disability scale.Navy 5c Air   Air        Air For co        Force    EorceDisebilit y	Servi pe	(xTavy only (    7/-(Years 10 to 13.	10/6 14.	10/6 15-	12/3 16.	12/3 1.7.	14/-18,	14A 19,	17/6 20.	only. 17/6 21.	only. 19/3 22.	only, 19/3 23.20%	6/6	10/3	13/9	13/9	15/6	15/6	17/3	17/3	20/9	20/9	22/6	22/6	9/9	13/3	i5A*		17/1*	17/li	18/10*	18/10*	22/4*	22/4*	24/1*	24/1*40;5	13/-	16/6	18/3	18/3	19/li	19A-I-	20/6	20/6	24/-	24/-	25/9	25/950%	16/3	19/9	21/6	21/6	22/4*	22/4*	23/3	23/3	25/7*	25/7*	27/4*	27/4*6Q%	19/6	23/-	24-/9	24/9	25/7*	25/7*	26/6	26/6	28/3	28/3	29/1*	29/1*70%	22/9	26/3	23/-	28/-	28/ie^-	28/lO*	29/9	29/9	31/6	31/6	32/4*	32/4*80%	26/-	29/6	31/3	31/3	32/l-i-	32/li	33A	33/-	34/9	34/9	35/7*	35/7*	29/3	32/9	34/6	34/6	35/4*	35A*	36/3	36/3	38A	38A	38/10*	38/ia*100?,	32/6	36/-	37/9	37/9	38/7*	38/7*	39/6	39/6	41/3	41/3	42/1*	42/1*co
Dissentient rer ort^ as l9...^ Ol?::-.-Il5.li5^--.^ 2l.H.J!Z the ..ar Oific(  lepresentative.1.     The service scewld vvhich the majority of the Committee wish to adopt ioi post war c^scs was strongly supported by thern when we were consider trig oiu first report; and as it was to be applied only to a ejooiel class ci&apos; cases and administered by the Ministry oi ir one ions, 1 agreed to it, but   must confess that I did not then anticipate that the scale would be recommended for the post war scheme or that it might be inconvenient for that purrose.2,     There is a fundamental difference in pension matters between the army end the navy.     The army Is predominantly short-service; the navy long service.     In tiiu army reserve service counts as service for pension^ find a man with Zl years s rvice can claim a full pension (if he has a minimum of 10 years colour service&quot;).&quot;&quot;   The rate of pension is based, on the colour   , service.     A re-engaged man with 18 years service allowed to t-aice his discharge may be given a pension calculated in the usual vvay, less 10J1.3.     Whatover may be done for future entrants we cannot take away these rights from soldiers now serving.   A soldier with 14 or even 10 $ears pensionable service may, in the army, be, as regards total service, a 21 years man, an 18 years mm or a 14 years men,, and these are three distinct classes; but in the Havy service is generally identical with qualifying service.It is impossible, to bring the two services into uniformity on this point, end it- would therefore almost bo a convenience if the &quot;service pension&apos;-&apos; in the army -.vore fixed in a different way from the Envy.,4.     The proposed scale has the disadvantage of being a new one, and it seems to me clearly an advantage to have a scale which is definitely based on the lku basic service rate,   Ifiy proposal (with which Che leea agrees) is that, for the army, the service scale shall be *for 21 yr. men l^d. a day for each year of colourservice.,for men with .18 and less than 21, the same less 10^..for men with 14 and less than 18 the same less 20/^..The following table -shows the scheme in detail;-(a)  or the 21 years man, who is entitled to his full service -pension based on.colour service..(b) tfor the- man with 18 and less than 21 years, who is now-entitled to his service pension less lOJo if he is allowed to take his discharge voluntarily. If he goes for medical unfitness, he could hardly be given less.(c) The man with 14- and less than 18 years service, has a vested right und, r the Pay &apos;.arrant to a service pension less such deduction as the Treasury may prescribe.   He has at present no rights to the new scale of pension.Table
- 1.3 -Table showing service pension in pence a day of soldier under (a) and (b), uiku r (c) assuming a 20$ deduction from 1-^d. scale, and (d) under majority proposal, which would take the place of tb) and (c).Colour service.	(a)	(b)	(c)		(d)21	31.5		-		31.20	30	27.	VMM		30.19	28.5	25.65	*&quot;*		2418	27	24.3	(Ml	i	2417	25.5	22.95	80.40		2116	24	21.6	19.2		2115	22.5	20.25	18.		1814	81	18.9	16.8 v		1813	19.5	17.55	15.6		1212	18	16.2	14.4		1211	16.5	14.85	13.2		1210	15	13. 5	12.		12(Figures would of course be rounded off, into weekly rates,)6.    As a &quot;eerviaa pension&quot; ihe &quot;war scale&quot; would probably not have a long life.     It would soon be discovered that it was not really the service scale, and that (for example) the man with 17 years service was not getting any more than the man with 16.    We should not have any convincing answer, and \ e might be forced to introduce the full service scale without deduction.Even if we could then introduce the modified service pensitn I naw suggest, we should leave behind a residuum of vested rights as shorn by r in paragraph 5, It would &apos;be bad to introduce a regulation which Is almost certain to have such a result.7.     We now have a clean slate, and if, for the army, &apos;-e begin by giving the service scale with a deduction of lOfo off the 18 year-man, and 20$ off the 14 year man we shall not be introducing a new scale, but merely carrying on the principle ox deductions from the full service scale already in force for the 18 year man&apos; who is pensioned for service only; and our position will be much sounder.(bd. ) J..G.. ASHI.EY,26th April, 1920,

</content>
</cab>
