<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/104/0 images: 553-557</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.HOUSING- FINANCE.11.16.j^itemorandum by the Minister of Health.I find it necessary to bring to the notice of mycolleagues the serious position of the financial, provision forthe Government Housing Scheme.     The situation to-day is that plans for 185,000 houses have been approved and tenders for approximatly 100.000 houses have been received by the Localauthorities, submitted to the Ministry of Health and finally approved.     Work on these houses has either begun or should beginat once if the Local Authority were in a position to sign the contract.     The season of the year suitable for building opera-tions has arrived.Progress may in any case be hampered to an embarrassingextent by shortage of labour and materials.     I have in handvarious measures for dealing with these difficulties so far asa Government department can deal with them, and further pro-posals in regard to materials may be submitted.But the most pressing problem is that of financing theLocal Authorities&apos; housing schemes.    Before contractorsworking for Local. Authorities can begin to operate, the Authori-ties must have the necessary funds available or clearly in view,and I regret to say that in many instances, affecting in theaggregate thousands of houses, serious difficulty in providing the requisite capital has arisen.In so far as Local Authorities have a rateable valueunder  200,000 per annum they may now borrow from the Publiclorks Loan Commissioners to the extent to which they cannot raisefunds otherwise.     In all such cases I am exerting the maximumfundspressure on the Authorities to obtain/by the issue of bonds and in other additional ways to get forward with the building. Difficulty,however, remains as regards Authorities with a
rateable value of over  200,000, and unless funds can be provided quickly for work in the areas of these Authorities all over the Country, the provision of houses must inevitably fall far short of the number contemplated, for this year, which number is itself far short of meeting the full and pressing needs of the country.finding the money both for their own schemes and for those of the metropolitan Borough Councils.    The building programme for this year is for approximately 14,000 houses, cost about  14,000,000,  8,000,000 for the County Council itself and  6,000,000 for the Borough Councils.    The Council expect to have available this year  6,500,000 in all for housing, of which they do not feel able to allot more than  1,000,000 to Borough   Councils, i.e. there is a shortage of  2,500,000 for Council building and of  5,000,000 for Borough building.     I am arranging for a Housing Bonds campaign to begin early next 7/eek in London, and I trust that this may to some extent relieve the situation. -   At this time however many authorities in the Metropolitan area are practi-cally at a standstill for lack of funds.In the outer areas of London the scheme for the year as regards Local Authorities with a rateable value of over  200,000 comprises 11,000 houses, approximate cost  11,000,000..     Under the present Cabinet decisions funds for these houses require to be found by the Local Authorities and under the Housing (Additional Powers) Act, 1919, the County Councils in which the areas con-cerned are situated have powers to. borrow money to lend to the Authorities primarily responsible.In London itself the County Council are responsible forThe County Councils concerned are -MiddlesexHertfordshireEssexKentSurrey5,000 houses.1,000 1,500 1,000
The &quot;balance of 2,000 houses is for the County Boroughs of Croydon, East Ham, and lest Ham..Of the County Councils Hertfordshire have already issued stock and will he able to finance the Authorities in their area. Surrey do not prooose to raise money, considering that the Local Authorities can themselves raise it.    Middlesex,, Essex and Kent are prepared to issue stock and lend to their Authorities, but Middlesex are not prepared to raise more than  2,000,000 out of the  5,000,000 required^     The present difficulty In raising money by the ordinary method of issue of stock will be apparent from the recent experience of the London County Council,90 per cent of whose issue of  7,000,000 Was left with the underwriters. I feel bound to point out that these issues are being made at our request and after much pressure and difficult negotiation, in pursuance of the policy required by the Treasury of inducing the greater local authorities to raise the money for themselves. The issue of L0C3Ce stock at about 6% was only open for a few days; and during the morning of the first day of issue, Treasury Bills were put up to 6-g$ with the Immediate result (so I have been informed by the Chairman of the LtCeC* Finance Committee) that applications ceased*      I have no material on which to form a judgment as to the necessity for the action of the Treasury &apos; on the particular day selected: but it is clear that no action could have been taken more calculated to defeat&apos; the policy they have dictated and which we are laboriously and honestly trying to carry out.   The result of this unfortunate event is that the other three counties will not be able to make issues for 6 or 7 weeks, I am arranging for co-ordination of their negotiations, and I am pressing the Local Authorities to enter into contracts up to the limit of what they,expect to borrow from their County Council, obtaining temporary accommodation during the Intervening period, but they have lost confidence, and hesitate to commit themselves to more than a trivial part of what they want to do and what has already been approved.
As regards Groyclcn, Cast Ham and West Ham. these Authorities being County Borough Councils cannot look to the County Councils fcr financial assistance.   Croydon will probably sooner or later be able to finance itself by stock issue or otherwise. n^here is, however, practically no prospect of East Ham and West Ham being able to secure funds - 500 houses are contemplated this year for these two County Boroughs cThe ato/e analysis will show how difficult the situation is in London and in the outer area cf London.As regards the Midlands and North, I hope that as a rule the housing bonds, campaign, joined to stock issues and other expedient, may be successL&apos;ui in securing the funds required for this year0There will, however,  be areas such as London and the surrounding district and generally the South of England in which the money required cannot be raised by the Local Authorities either by housing toads or in any other way    Further action is therefore clearly necessary unless the Government is to face a heavy reduc-tion in the programmeI woajd acocrcMnglj urge in^the first place as a partial remedy that the arrangement under which only Local Authorities under  200,000 rateable value may have recourse to, the Local Loans Fund be relaxed in cases in which the Ministry of Health Is satisfied that the Local Authority does not possess the necessary credit or local resources to raise the sums necessary to carry out its programme,    I make this suggestion the more readily at the present time because so many of the Local Authorities under  200,000 rateable value are starting campaigns to satisfy their loan requirements locally.    -I am fully aware of the objections to any further extension of Government loans, but it is my duty to point out to the Cabinet that in certain cases the only alternative to Government assistance in the provision of capital , will be a reduction in the Housing programme *In the sec&amp;nd place I think it is clear that in certain cases it will be necessary to Increase the/-4-
rate of Interest payable on Housing Bonds under the Housing (Additional Powers)Aot.   The race of interest on Local Bonds Is to be fixed from time to time by the Treasury and the rate at present fixed is a maximum rate of 6 per cent.     Some of the larger municipalities especially in the North of England, will, I believe be able to raise the money they require at 6 per cent but this is not the case with many local authorities in the South.     I think, therefore, that each case will have to be considered on its merits and that local authorities who cannot raise the necessary capital by the issue of Housing Bends at 6 per cent must be permitted to offer 6-g per cent or even 7 per cent.Ir^the^third J^ape^nd^for similar reasons I think that the rate of interest on mortgage loans must also be increased where necessary*    At present local authorities are empowered under the Housing (Assisted Scheme) Regulations to raise money at the rate of interest for the time being charged by the Public Works Loan Commissioners without my approval.     If they propose to offer a higher rate of interest they require my approval.     I have already in some instances approved of a rate of 6-1 per cent and I shall feel obliged to approve of even higher rates of interest if the local.authorities cannot raise tho money otherwise.I hope my colleagues will recognise that the position is really serious, and that the Government2s pledges cannot be fulfilled without 3ome such measures as I have indicated.     In particular I wish to emphasize the point that the financial difficulties to which I have referred are a source of grave embarrassment to the Government in their dealings with recalcitrant or backward Local Authorities and with Labour.    So long as there remains any reason-able grounds for supposing that the necessary capital may not after all be forthcoming, Local Authorities will plead this as an excuse for Inactivity or delay, labour find3 a ready argument for resisting the demand for increased production, and Public Opinion will be un-convinced that the Government are in earnest in their determination to grapple with the Housing shortage.Ministry of Health C. ADDISON.29. 4, 20.

</content>
</cab>
