<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/32/36 images: 300-303</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRTCAMIO MAJESTY*S C^verification^ffiNTSECRET .   . -    COPY NO.v7.P*(42)6Q623rd December, 1942--TilAR CABINETColonial policy memorandum by the minister of lAbaijr and National Servloolm     I am concerned at the suggestion made by the Secretary of Statefor India in his memorandum (17.P.(42)575) that India ought not to be directlyrepresented on any Regional Commission that may be set up for the Far Eastor South Eastern Asia following the proposals made in T/.p.(42)544.2.     In our instructions to H.M* Ambassador in Y/ashington for the purposeof his private talks with Mr. Hull, it has already been indicated that the regional Commissions should &quot;be composed not only of representatives of&quot;parent-States&quot; but also of nations having a major defence or economic interest in the regions concerned.     India is not, at present, in the first of these categories, though it scorns highly important to me that we do nothing now which would prejudice the possibility of her becoming a parent-State after the war or would bear the interpretation that wo are excludingthat possibility.     I am, however, unable to understand on what ground itcould bo said that India is not in the second category as a nation having a major defence or economic interest, comparable for example to China&apos;s.3.     The. Secretary of State for India suggests that it would be sufficient for Indian interests to bo looked after by His Majesty1 s Government1 representative on the Commission, but I cannot believe that this would be acceptable to India, or that Lord Halifax would have an easy task in convincingMr. Hull that it conf orns to the spirit of the Joint Declaration.     In thisconnection it cannot be overlooked that India is not only a member, in her own right, of the League of Nations and the International Labour Office, butthat she has held from the beginning of the latter body one of the eightseats on its Governing Body permanently allocated to the eight countries of chief industrial importance.     It is not suggested that the same criteria apply in determining representation on the Regional Commissions, but we surelycannot neglect the status which India has secured on existing international organisations in considering what her position should be in relation to thepresent proposals.E. B *H-Q.760-70 L.L




</content>
</cab>
