<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/63/33 images: 448-461</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET. Copy No. [W.P. (45) 178.19th March, 1945.WAR CABINET.LOCAL GOVERNMENT REFORM.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.1. I &quot;attach a draft Bill to give effect to the proposals in the White paper on Local Government during the Period of Reconstruction. This Paper was discussed at a meeting of the War Cabinet on the 20th December last andwas approved, subject to certain amendments which were subsequentlyincorporated (W.M. (44) 172nd Conclusions, Minute 3).2. The Paper was debated in the House of Commons on the 15th february and a motion welcoming its proposals was carried without dissent, Members fromall quarters of the House expressing approval of the idea of a Local GovernmentBoundary Commission.3. The Bill establishes a Local Government Boundary Commission (Clause 1and First Schedule), and empowers it to make orders adjusting Local government areas (Clause 2). The powers conferred on the Commission take the place of those contained in the Local Government Act, 1933. The Minister of Health is empowered to make regulations laying down principles for the guidance of theCommission and regulating their procedure and these regulations require an affirmative resolution of each House. Orders affecting counties or county boroughs are expressed in the Bill to be &quot; provisional &quot; (Clause 3 (7) ), but theintention is that if the proposed Statutory Orders (Special Procedure) Billbecomes lav/, they shall be subject to the procedure laid down in that Bill. TheMinister is also empowered to give directions as to the priority in which theCommission are to deal with cases (Clause 3 (4)). When an area has beenconsidered by the Commission, a period of ten years must normally elapse before any further alteration can be made (Clause 3 (6)).4. I am anxious, if possible, to publish the Bill early in the Easter recess,and I seek authority to present it before Parliament rises, subject to any draftingadjustments which may be recommended by the Legislation Committee, to whichit will, if approved, be submitted on the 27th March,H. U. W.Ministry of Health, Whitehall. S.W.1,19th March, 1945.[29462]

CONFIDENTIALLocal Government (boundary commission) bill arrangement OF CLAUSES.ClauseI.   Establishment of Local Government Boundary Commission.Power of Commission to alter areas.Exercise of powers of Commission.Supplementary provisions as to orders.Annual report of Commission.Saving for royal prerogative.Short title, citation and repeals.Schedules:First Schedule. Constitution and Proceedings of LocalGovernment Boundary Commission.Second Schedule. Repeal of certain Provisions of LocalGovernment Act, 1933.749 3

5 &amp; 9 Geo. 6.DRAFTOF    AB   I   L   LT OProvide for the establishment of a Local Government   a.d. 1945.Sp    Boundary Commission ; to make further provision for      -the alteration of local government areas in Englandand Wales exclusive of London ; and for purposesconnected with the matters aforesaid.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled,and by the authority of the same, as follows : k   1.-(1) There   shall   be   established   a   Local   Government EstablishmentI Boundary Commission (in this Act referred to as &quot; the Com- of local mission &quot;) which shall be charged with the duty of reviewing the government circumstances of the areas into which England and Wales commission&apos;I (exclusive of the administrative county of London) are dividedifo for the purposes of local government, and exercising, where itll appears to the Commission expedient so to do, the powers ofI altering those areas conferred by the following provisions of thisI Act.(2) The provisions of the First Schedule to this Act shall have15 effect as to the constitution and proceedings of the Commission.I (3) The Minister of Health (in this Act referred to as &quot; theI Minister &quot;) may make regulations prescribing general principlesD by which the Commission are to be guided in the exercise ofi their functions under this Act, but such regulations shall be of3 no effect until approved by resolution of each House ofParliament.2.-(1) The Commission shall have power  Power of, . Commission to[a) to alter or define the boundaries of a county, county ajter areas.borough or county district ;49 A 2
a.d. 1945. (b) to unite a county with another county, or a county-- borough with another county borough,  or to unitea non-county borough with another non-county borough,or an urban or rural district with another district,whether urban or rural, or to include an urban or rural gdistrict in a borough ;(c) to divide  a county   into, between or among two ormore counties or an urban or rural district into,between or among two or more districts (whether urbanor rural) ; 10(d) to constitute a borough (either by itself or together withthe whole or any part of another county district) a county borough ;(e) to direct that a county borough shall become a non-countyborough and specify the county in which it is to be 15included ;(/) to constitute a new urban or rural district, or to converta rural district into an urban district or an urban districtinto a rural district ;(g) so far as appears to the Commission to be requisite in 20connection with any exercise of their powers under the miforegoing paragraphs, to alter the boundary between a parish and another parish, to unite a parish with an-other parish, to divide a parish into, between or amongtwo or more parishes, or to constitute a new parish: 25Provided that no part of the administrative county of Middlesexshall be constituted a county borough.(2) For the avoidance of doubt it is hereby declared that nothing in this Act affects the power of His Majesty to grant a commission of the peace and a court of quarter sessions to any 30borough, whether constituted in pursuance of this section orotherwise.Exercise of 3. (1) Where the Minister directs the Commission to take intoPowers of consideration the question whether any alterations ought, to beCommission, made under the last foregoing section in respect of any areas 35of local government, or where the Commission without any suchdirection consider it expedient so to do, then, subject to theprovisions of this section, they shall take that question intoconsideration.(2) If application in that behalf is made to the Commission 40with respect to (a) the area of a county or county borough, by the councilthereof;  or
8 &amp; 9 Geo- 6-3(b) the area of a county district, by the council of the county   a.D. 1945.in which the district is situated, -the Commission shall take into consideration the questi on whetheror not alterations under the last foregoing section a?e requisite5 with respect to the area.(3) If application in that behalf is made to the commission by the council of any borough with a population of one hundred thousand or upwards (determined in accordance with section two hundred and ninety-six of the Local Government Act, 1933)10 the Commission shall take into consideration the questionwhether or not it is requisite to exercise in relation to the borough the power of constituting it a county borough conferred by the last foregoing section.(4) The Commission shall comply with any direction of the15 Minister that for the purposes of this section they are to give priority to any area or areas, or class of areas, specified in thedirection.(5) Where the Commission determine that any alteration of areas is requisite, or that no such alteration is requisite, they20 shall embody their determination in an order.(6) Where an order made under this section determiningthat an alteration of any area is requisite, or that no alterationof an area is requisite, has come into operation, then, notwith-standing anything in the foregoing provisions of this section,25 the Commission shall not, within ten years after the order came into operation, take into consideration the question of alteringthat area unless they are satisfied that by reason of a substantial change in the distribution of population or other exceptional circumstances it is requisite so to do.jo (7) An order under subsection (5) of this section relating toa county or a county borough (including an order constituting a county borough or directing that a county borough shall become a non-county borough or an order embodying a determinationthat it is not requisite to constitute a county borough or to direct35 that a county borough shall become a non-county borough)shall be provisional only and shall be of no effect until confirmed by Parliament.(8) The procedure in connection with the exercise by theCommission of their functions under this section shall be such as40 may be prescribed by regulations made by the Minister and approved by resolution of each House of Parliament, and such regulations (a) shall make provision for opportunities for objection by persons likely to be affected by any order proposed to be45 made under this section, and for securing that where49 A 3
48 &amp; 9 Geo. 6.A.D. 1945. objections are made by the council of any area likely to- be so affected or in such other circumstances as may be specified in the regulations and are not withdrawn alocal inquiry shall be held before an order is made ;(b) may empower the holding of local inquiries generally for 5the purposes of this section, and make provision as tothe conduct of local inquiries held in pursuance of theregulations and in particular for limiting the evidence to be called and the manner in which persons may berepresented thereat, l0and subsections (2) to (5) of section two hundred and ninety ofthe Local Government Act, 1933 (which relate to the giving ofevidence on, and defraying the costs of, local inquiries) shallapply to local inquiries held as aforesaid as they apply to thelocal inquiries mentioned in subsection (1) of the said section 15two hundred and ninety.(9) As soon as may be after the Commission have made such anorder as is mentioned in subsection (7) of this section, they shallprepare and transmit to the Minister a statement describingshortly the proceedings leading to the making of the order, 20summarising any representations made for or against the order,and setting out the considerations which led the Commission tomake the order, and the Minister shall lay the statement beforeParliament.Supple-mentaryprovisions asto orders.annual report of commission.4. (1) The supplementary provisions set out in sections one 25hundred and forty-eight to one hundred and fifty-four of theLocal Government Act, 1933, shall apply in relation to orders under this Act altering an area of local government as if this Actwere included in Part VI of that Act (which provides for the alteration of such areas), and as if references in those provisions 30to the making of an order by the Minister included references tothe making of an order by the Commission.(2) Any such order as aforesaid shall provide that for thepurposes of the said section oik; hundred and fifty a former officerof a local authority who at the date when the order came into 35operation was engaged in war service (as defined by the LocalGovernment Staffs (War Service) Act, 1939), having ceased to bean officer of the authority in order to be so engaged, shall betreated in like manner as a person who at the said date was anofficer of the authority. 405. As soon as may be after the end of the year nineteenhundred and forty-six and each subsequent year the commission shall prepare and transmit to the Minister a report of theirproceedings for the year in question, and the Minister shall laythe report before Parliament. 45
8 &amp; 9 Geo. 6.56. The powers conferred by this Act shall be in addition to,   a.d. 1945.and not in derogation from, the powers exercisable by His Majesty       -bv virtue of his royal orerogative. Saving for-     A       &amp; royal prerogative.7. (1) This Act may be cited as the Local Government Short title,5 (Boundary Commission) Act, 1945, and the Local Government citation and act, 1933, and this Act may be cited together as the Local rePeals-Government Acts, 1933 and 1945.(2) The provisions of the Local Government Act, 1933, specifiedin the first column of the Second Schedule to this Act, which10 relate to the matters specified in the second column of that schedule, are hereby repealed to the extent specified in the thirdcolumn of that Schedule.
FIRST SCHEDULE.Constitution and Proceedings of Local GovernmentBoundary Commission.Constitution. 51. The Commission shall be a body corporate by the name of theLocal Government Boundary Commission, and shall consist of a chairman, a deputy chairman and three other members.2. (1) The members of the Commission shall be appointed byHis Majest\r, and shall hold and vacate office in accordance with the 10terms of their respective appointments.(2) A person who has ceased to be a member of the commission shall be eligible for re-appointment.3. A person shall be disqualified from being appointed to or being a member of the Commission so long as he is a member of the Commons 15House of Parliament.4. There shall be paid to a member of the Commission suchsalary or fees and allowances as may be determined by theTreasury at the time of his appointment.5. The Commission   shall   have a common seal, which shall be 20authenticated by the signature of a member of the Commission or ofany other person authorised in that behalf by the Commission.Capacity and proceedings.6. The Commission shall have power to act notwithstanding a vacancy among the members thereof, and at any meeting of the 25Commission two, or such greater number as the Commission may determine, shall be the quorum.7. All acts done at a meeting of the Commission shall, notwithstanding that it is afterwards discovered that there was a defect in the appoint-ment of a person purporting to be a member thereof, be as valid as if 30the defect had not existed.8. Subject to the foregoing provisions of this Schedule, and to any regulations made under this Act or directions given by the minister under section three of this Act, the procedure of the Commission shallbe such as the Commission may from time to time determine. 35Officers and servants, and remuneration and expenses.9. The Commission may appoint a secretary and such number ofofficers and servants as may be determined by the Commission afterconsultation with the Minister and with the consent of the Treasury,SCHEDULES.
SECOND SCHEDULE.Repeal of certain Provisions of Local Government Act, 1933.20Provision repealed.	Subject matter of provision.	Extent of repeal.s. 140 s. 141 s. 143 s. 146	Alteration of boundaries of counties, boroughs, etc. Alteration  of   urban  or rural    districts    and parishes, etc. Adjustment of boundaries of counties and county boroughs. Review of county districts by county councils.	The whole section. In subsection (1). In paragraphs (a) and (6) respectively the words &quot; of an urban or rural district or.&quot; In paragraphs (c) and (d) respectively, the words from the beginning to the third &quot; or.&quot; Paragraph (e). In paragraph (/), the words &quot; urban or rural district or.&quot; The whole section. The whole section.and there shall be paid to the secretary, officers and servants of the   A.D. 1945.Commission such salaries, fees and allowances as may be so determined.        -1st Sch.10. The expenses of the Commission, and the salaries, fees and      _cont.allowances of the members of the Commission and their secretary,5 officers and servants, shall be defrayed out of moneys provided byParliament.Proof of documents.11. (1) Every document purporting to be an instrument made orissued by the Commission and to be duly sealed with the seal of theCommission or to be signed by the secretary, or any person authorised10 to act in that behalf, shall be received in evidence, and shall, unlessthe contrary is proved, be deemed to be an instrument made or issuedby the Commission.(2) Prima facie evidence of any such instrument may in any legal proceedings be given by the production of a document purporting to15 be certified to be a true copy of the instrument by or on behalf of thesecretary.
Local Government(Boundary Commission).DRAFTo f aBILLTo provide for the establishment of aLocal Government Boundary Corn-mission ; to make further provisionfor the alteration of local government areas in England and Wales exclusive of London ; and for purposes connectedwith the matters aforesaid.CCVI-F. (3).xgth March, 1945.49-3(p.2964)



</content>
</cab>
