<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/33 images: 282-287</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;room, House of Commons, S.W.1, on Wednesday, March&apos;11, 1942, at12-30p.m.Copy No. 44Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.Petroleum. The Lord President of the Council reported to the War CabinetAbolition of that, at a Meeting of his Committee on Monday, the 9th March, itBasic Eation. had been decided that the basic petrol ration for private cars shouldbe abolished as from the 1st July next; that an early announcement should be made to this effect; and that the 50 per cent, cut already announced in the basic ration for April would be continued during may and June.It was pointed out that although the saving resulting from theabolition of the basic ration was not in itself large, abolition would assist in checking illegitimate uses of petrol.The War Cabinet-Endorsed the decision summarised above.[23572]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  March 1942.SECRET.W.M. (42)33rd Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK.AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 33 (42).

IISSECRET. &quot; MO CIRCULATION.W.M. (42) 33rd CONCLUSIONS.11th March, 1942.Arising out of the discussion on   the abolitionof the petrol ration, there was a discussion on the needfor further restriction of civil consumption and curtail-ment of activities not essential to the war effort.The view was generally expressed that the restric-tions to be imposed should be those which would savetonnage or man-power, and that, so far as possible,further Regulations and the multiplication of new offencesshould b e avoi de 5.THE PRIME MINISTER referred, in this connection, tohis Minute 79/2 on L.Po(42) 51.Reference was also roade to   the fact that it was now a punishable offence to drop a cigarette carton inthe street.   The Secretary was told to look into thispoint.There was also some discussion on the Press, inthe course of which it was emphasised, that there were three points which required to be dealt with:-(a) An effective censorship of material leavingthis country:(b) Provision whereby, in suitable cases,publication in this  country could be prevented of messages containing matter which had already been published overseas:(c) Steps to prevent the publication of materialgravely prejudicial to the   national morale.It was for consideration whether (c) could be dealtwith by   a determined use of existing powers, rather thanby an extension of the powers of censorship.THE PRIME MINISTER informed the War Cabinet that hehad instructed the Secretary to send a strong letter toSir Roger Keyes calling for the immediate return of theofficial Papers in his possession.11th March, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
