<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/167/3 images: 66-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
iTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(73) ? COPY NO k ^16 January 1973CABINETSTATEMENT ON THE DEFENCE ESTIMATES 1973Memorandum by the Secretary of State for defence i attach a draft of the 1973 Defence White Paper in tb.s form inwhich, subject to the amendments listed at Annex, it has been approvedby the Defence and Oversea policy  Committee.    Paragraph 14 of chapter I, paragraph 6(b) of Chapter II, and paragraph 34 of Chapter V,all dealing with Malta, may need to be revised if events so warrant beforethe White Paper goes to the printer.2.       I propose to publish the White Paper on Wednesday, 21 February;but I should like to have the approval of my colleagues to its text before i leave on 21 January for visits to Kenya, Australia, New Zealand, Fiji,the Far East, and the United States.    I shall assume approval unless any objections are notified to the Secretary of the Cabinet by close of business on Thursday, 18 January.c ministry of Defence16 January 1973
ANNEXSTATEMENT ON THE DEFENCE ESTIMATES1973AMENDMENTS AGREED BY THE DEFENCE AND overseas policy COMMITTEEChapter I, paragraph 4 (page 2)Amend the last sentence to read:-&quot;The Soviet Union now has some 1, 500 ICBMs, some 700 medium and intermediate range ballistic missiles, about 60 operationalballistic missile firing submarines, and some 300 other attack and cruise missile submarines&quot;.Chapter Ij paragraph 19 (page 11)Amend the last sentence to read:-&quot;Throughout this period the Army displayed the utmost forbearance,impartiality and tact&quot;.Chapter I, paragraph 30 (page ILi)In the penultimate sentence delete the words &quot;and the introductionof value added tax&quot;.Chapter V, paragraph 20 (page 56)At the end of the paragraph add the words &quot;... with the objective of introducing trading funds in due course&quot;.
rANNEXDRAFT statement on THE defence estimates 1973i
contents chapter I.    policy the Challenge of 1973     ............Britain&apos;s Contribution   ............Northern Ireland   ...............Manpower       ..................Defence Organisation       ............Defence Budget       ...............CHAPTER II.    COMBAT FORCES, DEPLOYMENT,  operations and EXERCISESCOMBAT FORCES AND DEPLOYMENTNuclear Strategic Force ............Royal Navy General Purpose Combat Forces   ...European Theatre Ground Forces ......Other Army Combat Forces .........Royal Air Force General Purpose Combat ForcesAir Mobility Forces ............OPERATIONS AND EXERCISESNorthern Ireland...........,      ...The NATO Area............      ...The Rest of the World     ............CHAPTER III.    RESERVE AND AUXILIARY FORCESArmy Reserves        ............Royal Navy and Royal Marines Reserve forces royal Air Force Reserve Forces ...Cadet Forces .............iiCONFIDENTIAL
PageCHAPTER IV.    MANPOWER AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICERecruitment and Re-engagement during 1972-73       ... 38Engagements           ......     ...     ...      ...      ... 1+5Pay and. Pensions.................. hSConditions of Service     ............... hiCHAPTER V.    SUPPORTHigher Defence Training and Studies......... usInitial and Specialist Training        ......... 50Flying Training     .................. 53Commonwealth and Foreign Training     ......... 53Adventurous Training       ............... 5UProduction, Repair and Supply Organisation in theUnited Kingdom   .................. 55Computer Bureaux   .................. 58Lands            ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 58Works Services.................. 59Hirings        ..................... 60Movements     ...      ...............      ... 60Meteorology            .................. 61SsTGS                        m m-m           ***           * * *           m * *           * * *           * * *            * * * 6*2Cost and Manpower............... 62CHAPTER VI.    RESEARCH AND development cost of Research and Development       ......... 63Research..................... 63International Collaboration     ............ 6UDevelopment Programmes 1973-7U          ......... 65Operational Analysis       ............... 70illCONFIDENTIAL
IPOLICYTHE CHALLENGE OP 19731.     For the Western Alliance 1973 will he a year of test and opportunity.    The pace of change has quickened as the politicalalignments of the post-war world have become less rigid;    this development and the period of collective negotiations ahead willbe a test of the solidarity of the Alliance.   At the same time there will be a fresh opportunity to find ways of diminishingthe causes of instability and tension in Europe; and increasedscope for developing closer European defence co-operation withinthe framework of the Alliance.2.     Britain will play a full part in these endeavours.   Her contribution to Western security has been strengthened by all that hasnow been done to achieve the broad objectives set out in the supplementary Statement on Defence Policy 1 970 (Cmnd. h521) .    :.&apos;.ean-while the task of assisting the civil power in Northern Irelandremains a major commitment for the Army.East/V.&apos;est Tepiotiations3.     The multilateral phase of East/West discussions, which has nowbegun, follows a year of substantial achievement in international legislation.   During 1972 the first major agreements emerged fromthe Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) between the United 3tar.eand the Soviet Union and the second phase of the talks now under- &apos;1 - I ;&apos;CONFIDENTIAL
way is expected to lead to further constraints.   Chancellor Brandt&apos;sOstpolitik has been carried forward by the ratification of the treaties between the Federal Republic of Germany and the soviet union and Poland and the signature of the basic treaty concerningrelations between East and West Germany,   The multilateral prepara-tions for the Conference on Security and Co-operation in Europe (CGCE^have been complete^and the Conference is expected to start in/&quot;&quot;June this year/.     Exploratory talks on Mutual andBalanced Force Reductions (MBFR)   /&quot;are now in progress J,with a prospect of substantive negotiations beginningin the autumn.      In the general field of arms control, theBacteriological (Biological) Weapons Convention, opened for signatureir. April in London, Moscow and Washington and which has attractedover  &quot;-\QO^y   signatures,  banned a potential new category of .varfaro.Developments in the Threatu.     There is no sign that the Soviet Union is anticipa-ting the outcome of negotiations by a slackening of its defenceefforts.    The Soviet Union&apos;s defence expenditures, v/hich absorba much higher proportion of national resources than those of most of the NATO countries, continue to rise each year in real terms.The build-up of her strategic capabilities has continued over thelasLt year, with 90 new silos under construction for intercontinentalballistic missiles (ICBM) and the completion of six new ballisticmissile firing submarines.    The Soviet Union now has so::.a 1,500IC3f.iS, some 700 medium and intermediate range ballistic missiles,and about 60 operational ballistic missile firing submarines.
Conventional forces of all the services have received large suppliesof new weapons and equipment of high quality.   Despite the substantial and still increasing military strength deployed on the border with china, there has been no decrease in Soviet forces facing NATO.There are at present some 9U Russian and other Warsaw Pact divisions in Eastern Europe and another 129 divisions elsewhere in the soviet union.   The Soviet Union now has some 11 ,600 military aircraft v/idelydeployed and a large air transport fleet.   Its naval forces, equipped with the most advanced weapons systems, have been deployed in increas-ing numbers throughout the world.   Russian long-range aircraft areactive over all the sea areas around the coasts of Europe and far out over the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans:    on occasions they have alsobeen seen over some areas of the Caribbean Sea and the Indian Ocean.Western Objectives5.     Her Majesty&apos;s Government continues to make a constructive contribu-tion to current efforts to bring about a further relaxation of tensionand a more lasting peace in Europe   and to promote agreement onrealistic measures for arms control and disarmament.   However, the steady increase in the military capability of the Soviet Union under-lines the importance for the West of clearly identifying and keeping in view its own policy objectives.    In the CSCE, the prime aims shouldbe to bring about closer, more open, and freer relationships between all people in Europe, to stimulate a wider flow of information and tobuild up confidence in the peaceful intentions of the participating countries towards each other.    In MBFR, an outcome which preservedthe present balance of security at a lower level of forces would bea valuable prize;   but this will not be easy to achieve in view ofthe disparities in the forces confronting each other in Central europe and the additional advantages of speedier reinforcement conferred onthe Warsaw Pact by geography.   Only negotiation from strength is
likely to produce equitable agreements.    There must, therefore, beno unilateral reduction in defence capabilities in the West.European Defence Co-operation6.     The desire for closer co-operation in defence among the european countries has already been given practical expression in bilateralstaff talks, in collaborative equipment projects and in the multi-lateral forum of the Eurogroup.   Britain is playing a full part inall these activities and is ready to explore with her allies newpossibilities of collaboration wherever they can be expected tocontribute to the cohesion and effectiveness of European defence.Bilateral staff talks already take place between Britain and seven of her European allies.   Britain is collaborating with other european countries in a number of equipment projects:    in addition to theMulti-Role Combat Aircraft (MRCA) with the Federal Republic ofGermany and Italy, these include the Jaguar aircraft, the Lynx andGazelle helicopters and an air-to-surface guided missile (Martel)with France, a combat reconnaissance vehicle with Belgium, and towedand self-propelled versions of a 155mm howitzer with Germany andItaly.    In 1972, Britain joined the multilateral organisationFINABEL, in which Army Chiefs of Staff of seven Western european countries meet to discuss possibilities for harmonising tactics,logistics and training.7.     The Eurogroup.   This informal group of the Defence ministers and NATO Permanent Representatives of ten European countries provides a forum for the exploration and promotion of measures designed toimprove the European contribution to collective defence and to achieve a more effective collective result from the available resources;    and for an exchange of views on current issues in the- k -CONFIDENTIAL
defence field, including national plans for the development and modernisation of force structures.    Its main achievement has beenthe three-part European Defence Improvement Programme (EDIP) consistingof a special five-year contribution to NATO infrastructure funds, a programme for improvements to national forces not previously planned,and mutual assistance in the provision of transport aircraft to turkey by Germany.   The momentum established by the Programme isbeing maintained:    in 1973 the planned defence budgets of member countries are in total one and a half billion dollars higher thanin 1972.8.     Specialised sub-groups of the Eurogroup have been set up to explore and promote closer European collaboration in arms procurement,logistics, communications, training and medical facilities.   TheEurogroup Ministers have paid special attention to co-operation inequipment procurement and at their meeting in Brussels in December1972 signed a joint declaration to confirm and emphasise their national commitment to the principles of collaboration and to guide the activities of the European national armaments directors.   these principles provide for a thorough exchange of information on futureintentions,  joint review of possibilities and a joint effort to devise common procurement plans before national decisions are fixed.The Eurogroup Ministers have also defined project areas as a basis for special effort;    these include the main battle tank of thefuture, howitzers, aircraft approach and landing systems, and tacticalcommunications systems.9.     Thus in parallel with the enlargement of the European economic community, a number of European countries will be developing and
extending their practical co-operation in defence.   That processshould he facilitated by the opportunities that will arise in theCommunity for the removal of fiscal, legal and technical barriersto trade and to the free operation of enterprises throughout theCommunity.BRITAIN&apos;S CONTRIBUTION10.   Major force improvements made or planned for all three services will enable Britain to continue to make a powerful contribution tothe preservation of peace and stability in Europe and else wherein the world.   These improvements include:Royal Navy.   In 1973 one nuclear-propelled submarinewill replace a conventional type;    the converted air-craft carrier HMS Hermes will enter service as acommando ship;    two cruisers will have been converted to carry Sea King helicopters;    and the last Leanderclass frigate will have entered service.   A furtherfour nuclear attack submarines, six guided-missiledestroyers and eight frigates, now under constructionor being ordered,are programmed to enter service bythe end of 1977, when the cruiser programme is expectedto be well advanced.Army.   Armoured reconnaissance units began to receivethe Scorpion combat reconnaissance vehicle late in197?.   By the middle of 1973,all armoured regiments willhave been re-equipped with Chieftain tanks and will have- 6 -CONFIDENTIAL
receivedSwingfire anti-tank missiles.Mechanised &quot;battalions will &quot;begin to receive this missile system in 1973* and issues to the air-portable battalionswill begin in 1975.   The extra Territorial and ArmyVolunteer Reserve armoured reconnaissance regiment willby May 1973 become fully operational and ready fordeployment to SACEUR in an emergency.   Negotiations arenow in progress between certain Eurogroup countries,including Britain, and the United States authoritiesabout the terms of a possible purchase of the Lancetactical nuclear weapon system to replace the presentHonest John equipment.Royal Air Force.   The modernisation of front-linesquadrons with Phantom PGR 2 and Harrier V/STOL air-craft has been completed.   The Buccaneer and Nimrodforces will be increased in size.   Additional Jaguaraircraft will be deployed in Germany.    In the longterm the most important re-equipment programme will bethe introduction of the Multi-Role Combat Aircraft.A thorough survey of Royal Air Force support functionsis continuing with the aim of maximising resources available for improvements to the front line.NATO11.   Virtually the whole of the Royal Navy, most of the combat unitsof the Army and the majority of the combat aircraft of the RoyalAir Force are committed to NATO.    The Royal Navy&apos;s Polaris forcecontributes to the strategic nuclear deterrent and British forces
also provide tactical nuclear weapons.    In addition to the 3ritishArmy of the Rhine and Royal Air Force Germany, Britain contributesland and air elements to the Allied Command Europe Mobile force which is available to be deployed anywhere in tiie NATO area.   TheRoyal Navy contributes to NATO&apos;s Standing Naval Force atlantic and Naval On Call Force Mediterranean.   Details of the forcesBritain makes available to NATO are given in Chapter II.12.   British forces provided a large contingent to the successfulNATO exercise STRONG EXPRESS which took place during September 1972.The purpose of the exercise, which was the largest combined land,sea and air exercise ever undertaken by NATO, was to test and developNATO&apos;s capability for rapid reaction and reinforcement in time ofemergency.13.   Nuclear Planning; Group.   Britain was the host at a meeting of nato&apos;s Nuclear Planning Group which took place in Lancaster house in October 1972.   This was the twelfth of the regular half-yearlymeetings of the Group, which has the general responsibility for developing political guidance on nuclear defence matters for adoption by the Alliance.   The first phase of a major work programme which began in 19&amp;9 and consists of a number of studies on the defensivetactical use of nuclear weapons has now reached an advanced stage.Britain has played a leading role in several of these studies.- 8 -
Malta/Th.   Following discussions with the Maltese Government during thelatter part of 1971 and early 1972, Britain, on behalf of NATO,negotiated the Military Facilities Agreement, signed on 26 March1972 (Cmnd, U9U-3), which gives Britain the right in peace and war to station forces and use facilities in Malta for the defence purposes of the United Kingdom and of the North Atlantic treaty organisation.   The facilities include port and harbour facilities,naval and air headquarters, barrack accommodation and the use ofthe airfield at Luqa.   Units of all three Services have now returned to the Island.   There are a number of matters relatingto the operation of the Agreement which are at present under discus-sion between the British and Maltese Governments.^Outside Europe15.   Although Britain&apos;s basic security depends on the strength ofthe North Atlantic Alliance and it is to NATO that by far thegreater part of Britain&apos;s military forces is committed, Britaincontinues to play her part, within her resources, in counteringthreats to stability outside Europe.   For without that stabilityBritain&apos;s world-wide political and trading interests cannot flourish.Britain supports CENTO and SEATO and contributes forces to the FivePower arrangements for defence in Malaysia and Singapore inauguratedin November 1971.   Garrisons and other forces are deployed in HongKong, Gibraltar, the Caribbean and elsewhere for the protection ofBritish territories overseas and of those to whom Britain owes aspecial duty by treaty or otherwise.   A British maritime presence- 9 -
in the Indian Ocean helps to maintain vigilance in that area.British forces visit the Gulf and provide military training andother assistance in Africa, Asia and the Middle East.   3ritain alsocontributes an Army contingent with Royal Air Force helicoptersupport to the United Nations peace-keeping force in Cyprus, andenforces the United Nations embargo on the importation of oil to rhodesia through Beira.16.   Details of britain&apos;s commitments and deployments outside Europeare given in Chapter II.NORTHERN IRELAND17.   The task of assisting the civil power in Northern Ireland touphold law and order and to combat terrorism has remained a heavycommitment for the Armed Forces throughout 1972.   During the year the number of major units engaged in the infantry role in NorthernIreland (including armoured, artillery, engineer, Royal Marines and royal Air Force Regiment units) rose from 17 in January 1972 to a peak of 27 for Operation MOTORMAN at the end of July,    It was reducedto 18 in December 1972, of which seven were redeployed from BAOR.The Royal Navy has increased its patrols off the Northern Irelandcoast and provides accommodation ships;    HMS Fearless and HMS Intrepidgave support to the land forces during Operation MOTORMAN.   TheRoyal Air Force has provided air transport support, includinghelicopters, photographic reconnaissance and survey, a marine craftto assist in coastal patrols, and Royal Air Force police to supplement the Royal Military Police.- 10 -
18.   The role of the troops was perhaps even more difficult and dangerous than in the previous two years.    In 197? 126 soldiers(including 25 members of the Ulster Defence Regiment) and2 Royal Marines died in action in Northern Ireland:    the totalnumber killed since the beginning of the present disturbances is &quot;MhJJ soldiers and Royal Marines.19.   Following the assumption by the United Kingdom Government of direct responsibility for the internal affairs of the Province atthe end of March, a sustained effort was made to win the confidence of all sections of the community and to persuade them to repudiatethe extremists in their midst, so that the political initiativetowards a peaceful settlement should not be jeopardised.   The Arraydisplayed the utmost forbearance, impartiality and tact and it wasthrough no fault on its part that the initiative was only partiallysuccessful during its early months.20.   In July the Provisional IRA, after calling off their short-livedceasefire on a flimsy pretext, mounted a fresh wave of explosiveattacks, causing death,  injury and damage to property on a horrifyingscale.    It became clear that their grip on the community had notyet loosened sufficiently to be removed by political measures alone;and that some Protestant elements were becoming increasingly militant.Operation MOTORMAN, mounted at the end of July, successfully re-established the security forces&apos;  freedom to move in all areas of theProvince and paved the way for vigorous action to undermine thestrength of the extremists in parallel with the political programme.Since MOTORMAN there has been a marked improvement in the availability of intelligence;    impressive quantities, of arms, ammunition and explosives have been uncovered;    and new legal measures have made it
easier to deal effectively with suspected terrorists.   Improvedsources of intelligence enable the Army to base its operations onaccurate information and thus to achieve results with the minimum of disturbance to innocent parties.21,   The Armed Forces can be proud of the contribution they aremaking in Northern Ireland.   The skill and courage with which theyare discharging their difficult task there has earned them the respect and gratitude of the nation.   They will continue to serve the cause of peace in Northern Ireland for so long as they arerequired.MANPOWERThe Services22,   Although recruitment of Servicemen - expected to reach  &quot;y$, 1OC-J^ln1972-73 -   is running lower than the record level of L6,500 achieved in 1971-72,the Services&apos; manpower requirements are being met apartfrom shortages in some trades and specialisations.   There will,however, be difficulties in the future to be overcome as a resultmainly of the raising of the school-leaving age and of a reductionin the size of the pool of available manpower.23.   The pay structure of the Armed Forces has been placed on a sound basis.   The rates introduced in April 1972ifollowing the first report of the Armed Forces Pay Review Body, have been welcomed bythe Services.   The new engagement arrangements, which offer a flexiblechoice in length of service, are working well.2k.  Further details about manpower are given in Chapter IV,
Civilian Staff25.     The total number of civilian staff employed by the Ministryof Defence on  1    April 1973 is expected to be about  &quot;325,000J.This takes account of the transfer to the Ministry of Defence ofsome  bjiooj staff, ^&quot;&quot;mainly, subject to legislation now beforeParliament, from the UK Atomic Energy Authority,J7 and the transferof some  &quot;2,500J7 staff to other Departments.   Allowing for theseadjustments, this total represents a reduction of approximately^&quot;1,600J civilian staff between   1    April 1972 and  1    April 1973.DEFENCE ORGANISATIONProcurement Executive26.     After the successful launching of the Procurement Executivebased on his recommendations, Sir Derek Rayner, the first chief executive (PE), returned in October 1972 to the service of Marksand Spencer Ltd.   He remains a part-time member of the ManagementBoard of the Procurement Executive, with special duties in the fields of improvements to project management and relations with industry.   He has been succeeded as Chief Executive by Sir MichaelCary, formerly Secretary of the Procurement Executive.27.     In the light of its first year&apos;s operations, some changes havebeen made or are contemplated in the structure of the ProcurementExecutive.    These include the abolition of the post of Controller of personnel, whose responsibilities have been assumed by the Secretary,  and the planned absorption beginning in early 1973 of the duties ofthe Controllerate of Guided Weapons and Electronics by the otherControllerates.^28.     Continued attention is being given to the strengthening of the links between the Ministry of Defence and its suppliers in industry.In addition to use of the facilities of the National Defence Industries- 13 -CONFIDENTIAL
Council and other existing consultative machinery, the ManagementBoard of the Procurement Executive has &quot;begun a series of Board-to-Board meetings with each of the main suppliers when general policyquestions are discussed./29.   The first batch of studies into the scope for rationalisationwithin Ministry of Defence Research and Development Establishmentshas now been completed.   It has been decided that over the next three to five years a number of moves will be made which will achieve a tauter organization, save manpower, and enable the Department&apos;s land holdings to be reduced.   The Signals Research and DevelopmentEstablishment at Christchurch and the Services Electronics research laboratory at Baldock will be closed and their work concentrated atthe Royal Radar Establishment, Malvern.   At about the same timearrangements will be made for some of that establishments work,which entailed the retention of the airfield at Pershore, to becarried out at the Royal Aircraft Establishment, Farnborough, enabling the airfield at Pershore to be given up.   As a further rationalisation-tion measure the Royal Armament Research and Development Establish-ment&apos;s outstation at Langhurst, Sussex, will be closed and its worktransferred to the main establishment at Fort Halstead, Kent.These moves constitute the first stage of the rationalisation plan,which is designed to be completed in two overlapping stages.   plans for the second stage, to be prepared during the coming months, willtake into account the impending transfer, subject to the passageof the legislation now before Parliament, of the Atomic WeaponsResearch Establishment from the Atomic Energy Authority to theMinistry of Defence^
DEFENCE BUDGET30.   The Defence Budget Estimates for 1973-7U total  /&quot;&quot;3,365j7m. *and represent approximately   per cent of the gross national product.   A Defence Budget target for 1973-7U was contained in theWhite Paper on Public Expenditure to 1976-77 (Cmnd. 5178), which also gave  a detailed account of the changes affecting the target for this year since Cmnd, ii-829.   The Estimates as now presentedare in line with that target as adjusted for the factors set outin Annex B, Table 2.   The Estimates are also  /&quot;51&quot;lJ7m. higherthan the Estimates for 1972-73.   Of this  ^/&quot;&quot;3h.8j7m. is accountedfor by pay and price changes and the introduction of value added tax.   The balance of  /&quot;&quot;l63-7m. represents a real increase of/&quot;5.7j7 per cent over the 1972-73 level, the main elements ofwhich are also set out in Annex B, Table 2.- 15 -CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALIICOMBAT FORCES,DEPLOYMENT, operations and EXERCISESCOMBAT FORCES AND DEPLOYMENT1.     The Combat Forces consist of:a. The Nuclear Strategic Force;b. Royal Navy General Purpose Combat Forces;c. European Theatre Ground Forces;d. Other Army Combat Forces;e. Royal Air Force General Purpose Combat Forces;f. Air Mobility Forces.2. The cost and Service and civilian manpower strengths of these forces are shown at Annex /     J.3. An illustrative outline deployment of the Combat Forces earlyin 1973 is given in the map at Annex  &quot;   J*NUCLEAR STRATEGIC FORCEh. The Polaris submarines Resolution. Repulse, Renown and Revengprovide a continuous patrol as the United Kingdom&apos;s contribution tthe .7estern strategic deterrent.- 16 -
ROYAL NAVY GENERAL PURPOSE COMBAT FORCES5.     All major ships and the amphibious forces are earmarked forassignment in war to NATO;    in peacetime they are deployed world-wide as NATO, other allied, or national interests require.6.     Naval forces are deployed overseas as follows:a. Far East and Indian Ocean.   The guardship at HongKong was previously provided on a rotational basisfrom ships deployed to the Far East;    it will infuture he permanently stationed there.    Other tasksin the area are met &quot;by destroyers and frigates ona rotational basis:    they include a contribution tothe Five Power defence arrangements and the ANZUKForce,    visits to the Gulf, the 3eira Patrol and,with other ships on passage between tasks, apresence in the Indian Ocean and the seas of SouthEast Asia.   Patrol vessels for maritime policingduties are stationed at Hong Kong and Royal FleetAuxiliaries are deployed in the Far East.   A sub-marine is serving with the Royal Australian Navy, and plans have been made for occasional visits by ships of higher capability;    the first will take place in1973 and will include co-operation with ships from commonwealth and allied countries.b. Mediterranean.    A guided-missile destroyer and twofrigates earmarked for assignment to SACEUR are stationed in the Mediterranean, backed from time to
time by larger units such as HMS Ark Royal andamphibious ships with Royal Marines Commandosembarked.   Other destroyers, frigates, submarines and Royal Fleet Auxiliaries also deploy periodicallyto the Mediterranean.   The Royal Navy contributesto NATO&apos;s Naval On Call Force Mediterranean.   one ship is kept in the vicinity of Gibraltar   and a royal Marines Commando Group is deployed in Malta^.c. West Indies.   Two helicopter-carrying frigates, each with a detachment of Royal Marines, are stationed inthe West Indies, augmented occasionally by otherunits for exercises and trials.d. South Atlantic.   The Ice Patrol ship HMS Endurancehas deployed to the Antarctic with a detachment of royal Marines for the summer season in support of theBritish Antarctic Survey and for hydrographic surveys.A Royal Marines detachment is based on the falkland islands.Other deployments7.     The Royal Navy&apos;s fishery protection patrols in the north atlantic and home areas have been intensified by the addition of extra mine countermeasures vessels and a fast patrol craft.   Afrigate or destroyer is allocated full-time as Britain&apos;s contribution to the NATO Standing Naval Force Atlantic.   One Royal MarineCommando Group stationed in Scotland is specially trained and equipped for mountain and arctic warfare to fit it for servicon the northern flank of I&apos;ATO.- 18 -
SHIPS AND EQUIPMENT8.     A table showing the strength of the Fleet in 1973-7U is at annex  &quot;   J,   The following programmes are in train or likelyto be put in train during the year:a.     New Construction(1)   New DesignsWork continues on the design of improvedclasses of submarine.(2)   CruisersSubject to satisfactory negotiations the contract with Messrs. Vickers for the first of a new class of cruiser will be placedshortly.(3)    Nuclear-Powered Fleet SubmarinesThe seventh and eighth are to be accepted into service.    The ninth and tenth are under construetion.   The eleventh is being ordered.(h)   Destroyers and FrigatesSix Type h.2 destroyers are under construction.HMS Amazon, the first of the Type 21 frigateclass, is to be accepted into service.   Anotherseven of this class are under construction. A contract has been let with Messrs. Yarrowfor full shipbuilder involvement on the first
of a new class of general purpose frigates(the Type 22) with a view to ordering thefirst ship during the year.^(5)    fMine Countermeasures VesselsA shipbuilder involvement contract has beenlet with Messrs. Vooper Thornycroft on a newclass of glass-reinforced plastic mine counter-measures vessel.JJ(6)    Other ShipsA minehunter constructed in glass-reinforcedplastic will shortly be accepted into service.A survey ship, two small fleet tankers and twosalvage vessels are to be accepted into service.Two fleet replenishment ships, one experimentalship and four patrol craft are under construction.Conversions and New Equipment(1)    Major UnitsThe conversion of HMS Hermes to the commandoship role will be completed.(2)    FrigatesThe special refits of more Leander Class frigatesto carry Ikara will be completed.HelicoptersSea King, //asp and vVessex helicopters are widelydeployed at sea.Equipment(1)    The Mark 2U submarine-launched anti-submarine torpedo- 20 -
is in production and will enter service shortly.(2)   Deliveries of the US Mark i-j.6 light-weight torpedowill begin shortly.(3)   The first deliveries of Sxocet 3hip equipments have beenmade. The.first missiles are due for delivery this year,and the system is expected to be in service in i97U.(U)   The Anglo-French Martel air-to-surface anti-shipguided-weapon is being introduced into the Buccaneersquadron on HMS Ark Royal.EUROPEAN THEATRE GROUND FORCESBritish Army of the Rhine (3A0R)9.     3A0R remains a key element in the United Kingdom&apos;s contributionto NATO.    Its peacetime strength could be more than doubled on mobilisation.The Berlin Brigade10.   The Berlin Independent Brigade fulfils Britain&apos;s commitment to the security of the Western Sector of Berlin.Forces in the United Kingdom11.    Headauarters United Kingdom Land Forces was formed on 1 April1972.    3y 1 April 1973 all units and District Headquarters in theUnited Kingdom with the exception of Northern Ireland will be under its command and four Command Headquarters and three DistrictHeadquarters will have closed.   Under the new organisation therewill be ten District Headquarters (including Northern Ireland)within the United Kingdom.12.   The following forces have primary roles in support of NATO:- 21  -
a. the land elements of the United Kingdom MobileForce;b. the United Kingdom Joint Airborne Task Force;c. the British contribution to the Allied Command EuropeMobile Force (Land).13.    A Gurkha battalion is at present stationed in the UnitedKingdom.OTHER ARMY COMBAT FORCES1U, This category comprises land forces stationed abroad to meCommonwealth and treaty commitments as follows:a. The Far East.   3ritain&apos;s contribution to the armycomponent of the forces set up under the FivePower defence arrangements comprises a battaliongroup,with appropriate staff and logistic elements,stationed in Singapore.    The Hong Kong Garrisonconsists of five (including three Gurkha)  infantry battalions, an artillery regiment, an armoured carsquadron and supporting units.    A Gurkha battalionis stationed in Brunei.b. The Mediterranean.   Britain contributes an infantry battalion, an armoured reconnaissance squadron andlogistic support to the United Nations force in cyprus.   An armoured car squadron and an infantry battalion are stationed in the Sovereign Base Areas.The Gibraltar garrison includes an infantry battalionc. The Caribbean.   The small garrison in British
Honduras provides a force for the external defenceof the territory and, when required, assistance tothe civil authorities in the maintenance of lav/and order. The garrison currently consists of a battalionheadquarters, two infantry companies and supporting arms.EQUIPMENT15.   The following improvements in Army equipment are planned totake place in the coming year:Q*     Armoured ForcesAll armoured regiments will complete conversion toChieftain.    Issues of Sv/ingfire long range anti-tankguided-weapons to armoured regiments, and of theScorpion tracked reconnaissance vehicle to armouredreconnaissance units will be completed.b. ArtilleryFirst issues of the Rapier low-level air defenceguided-weapon system to operational units will bemade.    An initial production order has been placed for the Blowpipe very-low-level air defence guided-missile.   A new mortar-locating radar, Cymbeline,will enter service.c. InfantryMechanised battalions in BAOR will start to receivethe swing fire system.- 23 -
d.     CommunicationsInitial issues of the new Clansman range of combatnet radio will be made.ROYAL AIR FORCE GENERAL PURPOSE COMBAT FORCESCOMPOSITION AND DEPLOYMENT16.   The general purpose combat forces of the Royal Air Forcecomprise all front-line formations and units, although the transport and tanker forces are formally designated as Air Mobility Forces.They are organised in three Commands:    Strike Command (the singleoperational command for both combat and Air Mobility Forces in theUnited Kingdom), RAF Germany and Near East Air Force.   As from1 April 1973 the last will include Gan and Gibraltar, and, for thepurpose of administrative control, Hong Kong and Singapore.   Thecombat forces consist of:a.     Strike/AttackReconnaissanceClose Support andTacticalReconnaissanceAir Defence- Vulcans in Strike Command and near East Air Force;    Buccaneersand Phantom figures in Strike command and RAF Germany.- Victors and Canberras in strike command;    Canberras in Near EastAir Force;   Phantom PGR2s in strike command and RAF Germany.- Harriers in Strike Command andRAF Germany.- Phantom FG1s in Strike Command;Lightnings in Strike Command, RAFGermany and Near East Air Force;31oodhound surface-to-air missiles- 2k -CONFIDENTIAL
in RAF G-ermany and Near East AirForce;    a Royal Air Force RegimentTiger Cat squadron in Strike command and light anti-aircraft gun squadron in Strike Command, RAF Germany and near East Air Force;    Shackletonsfor Airborne Early Warning in strike command.e.     Maritime Patrol        -   Nimrods in Strike Command and near and Anti-submarine warfare v     East Air Force and detached to singapore for AKZUK duties.- *     Royal Air Force        -   Based in the United Kingdom butRegiment FieldSquadrons available for detachment overseasas required.Of these aircraft all those in RAF Germany, most of those in strike command and some of the Canberras and Nimrods in Near East AirForce are assigned to or earmarked for NATO.    In Near East AirForce the Vulcan aircraft, some of the Canberra reconnaissance aircraand some of the Nimrods are declared to CENTO.    In the Far East theRoyal Air Force contributes a detachment of Nirnrod maritime patrolaircraft, as well as Wessex helicopters, to the Five Power defence arrangements.   A squadron of Wessex helicopters is based in HongKong.    Frequent overseas visits are made by combat aircraft based in the United Kingdom.- 25 -CONFIDENTIAL
AIR MOBILITY FORCESCOMPOSITION AND DEPLOYMENT17.   Air mobility for the Services is provided by the transport andtanker forces.   The strategic transport force consists of VC1Os,Comets, Belfasts and Britannias;   the tactical force of Hercules(which also have a strategic capability), Andovers and Wessex andPuma helicopters.   The bulk of these forces, previously in air support Command, are now in Strike Command but there are Herculesin the Near East and Wessex helicopters in RAP Germany and the far east.   The tanker force in Strike Command is equipped with VictorMark 1 aircraft.EQUIPMENT18.   Major equipment changes are as follows:a,     JaguarsFirst deliveries of the Jaguar to the Royal Air force will take place during the year.   The introductionof the Jaguar into the strike/attack and reconnaissanceroles will enable the Phantom FGR2 to be transferredgradually to air defence0be     BuccaneersFurther Buccaneers have been deployed to RAF Germany.Additional aircraft are on order.c,     NimrodsThe build-up of the initial Nimrod force is complete.Additional aircraft are on order.
d. HarriersThe &quot;build-up of the Harrier force is complete.   Theprogramme for improving the aircraft&apos;s capabilityincluding the progressive re-equipment with more powerful marks of Pegasus engine is continuing.e. ShackletonsThe build-up of Shackletons converted to provideAirborne Early Warning is almost complete.f. PumasThe build-up of the Puma helicopter force is complete.WessexIn the Far East Wessex helicopters have now replacedthe Whirlwinds.h. Victor Mark 2sWork on conversion of Victor Mark 2 aircraft to the tankerrole is continuing.i. MartelFirst deliveries of the Anglo-French Martel air-to-surface guided-weapon are expected to reach RoyalAir Force squadrons during the year,j.     RapierThe Rapier low-level surface-to-air missile willbe delivered to the Royal Air Force Regiment inthe course of the year.- 27 -
OPERATIONS AND EXERCISESNORTHERN IRELAND19.    An account of operations by the security forces in NorthernIreland in 1972 is given in Chapter I, paragraphs 17-21 .THE NATO AREAOPERATIONSSurveillance and Interception20.    Ships of the Fleet and Nimrod long-range maritime patrolaircraft, assisted by Victor strategic radar reconnaissance aircraft, monitor the movements of Russian naval forces operating in the North Atlantic and in the Mediterranean.    Phantoms andLightnings of Strike Command have made many interceptions of approaching Russian aircraft at long ranges from Britain.Iceland21.    In addition to normal patrols to distant water fishing grounds,frigates of the Fleet have been available since September 1972 toprotect and assist trawlers close to the disputed fishing groundsoff Iceland.Norway22.    In November 1972 at the request of the Norwegian Government,Royal Navy helicopters helped in the search for a suspectedunidentified submarine in Sognefjord.Other Tasks23.    Survey vessels of the Royal Navy continue their surveyingand charting programmes.
MILITARY AID TO THE CIVIL COMMUNITY2h.    Ships and. aircraft of the Royal Navy and Royal Air Forcecarried out numerous search, rescue and disaster relief operations,including the rescue of the crew of a burning Icelandic fishingvessel in September 1972.    In July the Royal Navy won the HenriDurant International Search and Rescue Trophy for the second year in succession.25.    A small team of Army and Royal Marines bomb disposal expertsdropped by parachute from a Hercules aircraft into the mid-Atlanticto search for a bomb suspected to be on board the liner queen elizabeth 2.26. The Royal Navy has assisted in a survey of shipping in theDover Straits and in spotting and destroying drums of dangerouschemicals off south-west England.27.    The Royal Air Force contributed towards the National PhysicalLaboratory&apos;8 studies on traffic density of shipping in the english channel, by providing radar photography obtained by Victor aircraft on routine training flights.28.    In August 1972 the Royal Air Force flew relief sorties tothe Shetland, Orkney and Hebrides Islands during the dock strike.EXERCISES29.    The most important live exercise of the year was STRONG EXPRESS,in which all three Services demonstrated their ability to givesupport to the northern flank of NATO.    The Royal Navy conducted
fleet and amphibious operations.    The Royal Air Force conductedmaritime reconnaissance and air defence operations and alsodeployed the Army and air components of Britain&apos;s contributionto the Allied Command Europe Mobile Force.    Royal Naval andamphibious forces and aircraft of the Royal Air Force also took part in three major NATO maritime exercises.30.    A full programme of national exercises included aircraft carrier, amphibious force and anti-submarine operations.    TheRoyal Naval Reserves participated in seagoing mine countermeasuresoperations and contributed to the manning of shore headquarters.The Royal Navy continued to provide a substantial proportion ofthe submarine contribution to NATO exercises, and NATO forces from several nations have benefited by participation in jointmaritime courses and training at Portland.    Ships of the royal navy have joined the United States Navy on exercise, and bilateralexercises have been arranged with the French Navy.    An agreement has been concluded with the Netherlands for up to two submarinesof the Royal Netherlands Navy to operate with the Third SubmarineSquadron at Faslane.31.    Training for BAOR units continued in Germany and in othercountries including Canada (at the Suffield training area).    Armyunits assigned to the Allied Command Europe Mobile Force and RoyalAir Force aircraft practised their winter warfare roles in trainingperiods and exercises in Norway.    A major exercise,  SKY WARRIOR,was conducted by units of the United Kingdom Land Forces supportedby Royal Navy and Royal Air Force helicopters, to explore theproblems of air mobile operations in Europe.
32.    Royal Air Force aircraft of Strike Command, Near East AirForce and RAF Germany continued to play their full part in national and NATO exercises and competitions throughout the year.    TheUnited Kingdom Joint Airborne Task Force was deployed to Denmarkby the Tactical Air Transport squadrons of Strike Command toexercise with Danish forces, and aircraft of RAF Germany partici-pated in a major battlefield exercise in the Central Region of NATO.Bilateral exercises were held with the French Air Force.    Royal AirForce aircraft were successful in international weapons and recon-naissance competitions: in particular they won the Allied ForcesNorthern Europe Tactical Reconnaissance Competition, BIG CLICK 1972,and formed part of the winning team in the Allied Forces central europe Tactical Weapons meet.REST OF THE WORLDOPERATIONSThe Caribbean33.    Ships of the Royal Navy with detachments of Royal Marinescarried out the Bahamas Patrol against intruders.Oman34.    The Sultan of Oman*s armed forces, which include loan personnel from the Royal Marines, the British Army and the Royal Air Force,were engaged in operations in the Dhofar, the south-west province of Oman.    Army and Royal Air Force Regiment personnel were deployedto assist the Royal Air Force detachment at Salalah in defence ofthe airfield against rebel attacks.South America35.    A Royal Navy squadron visited Brazil and Argentina in the- 31 -CONFIDENTIAL
spring of 1972.Beira Patrol36.    The patrol off Beira to enforce the United Nations&apos; resolution was maintained.The Gulf37.    HM Ships and aircraft of the Royal Air Force made regular visits to the Gulf area throughout the year.Hydrographic and Aerial Surveys38.    Survey ships of the Royal Navy carried out surveys in the solomon Islands, Hong Kong, the Gulf and the Seychelles, andphotographic reconnaissance aircraft of the Royal Air Force carriedout aerial surveys in Kenya, the New Hebrides,  the Barbados islands and Kuwait.Hong Kong39.    The garrison, supported by Royal Air Force helicopters, was available to assist the civil authorities in assuring the securityof the Colony.   A detachment of the Royal Air Force Regiment was maintained at Kai Tak, and HM Ships carried out guardship and patrolduties throughout the year,AntarcticakO.    Hercules aircraft of the Royal Air Force operating fromShristchurch, New Zealand, assisted the United States Antarcticresearch programme by flying supplies to and from McMurdo base inAntarctica.MILITARY AID TO THE CIVIL COMMUNITY,    At the request of the Mauritian Government, HMS Hydra and
RFA Tidespring helped Rodriguez Island to recover from CycloneFabienne.   HlviS Lincoln gave assistance to the Philippines after a flood disaster.   Military units stationed in Hong Hong assistedthe civil authorities when heavy rainfall caused severe floodingand landslides in June 1972.   A small team of Royal Engineersassisted with the repair of communications in Bangladesh following the Indo-Pakistan war, including the construction of 13 Baileybridges provided by Her Majesty&apos;s Government.   Development tasks havebeen undertaken in other countries, including road and bridgeconstruction projects in Kong Kong, Kenya, Ethiopia and Malawi andsurvey work in the United Arab Emirates.       Many Royal Air Forceflights were made during the year to provide assistance to distressed areas, including flights to Saigon carrying relief supplies forrefugees, relief missions to Nicaragua, Fiji and the Philippines, andan evacuation flight by a YC10 from Addis Ababa for seriously injuredpassengers from a civil air crash.EXERCISES1*2.    During the year British forces took part in annual CENTO andSEATO exercises, and in those mounted by the Commander of theIntegrated Air Defence System and the Commander of the ANZUK force under the Five Power defence arrangements.1+3.    Army units too!: part in exercises in Australia, Brunei, Canada,Cyprus, Fiji, Hong Kong, Jamaica, Kenya, Malaysia, rJew Zealand andthe United Arab Emirates.       Aircraft from Strike Command practiseddeployments to the Far East.   HM Ships on visits abroad exercised- 33 -CONFIDENTIAL
with the navies of host coxmtries.   Royal iarines Commandos trained in Canada and the Caribbean.   The Red Arrows team gave highly successful performances at major Canadian and American air displaysand in Austria, among other European countries.- 3h -
IIIRESERVE AND AUXILIARYFORCES1.     The Reserve and Auxiliary Forces are an integral part ofthe Armed Services.    Some of their members have a reserve liabilityfollowing a period of full-term service with the colours; others are volunteer men and women who devote their spare time to training for the roles they would undertake in war.2.      The current strengths of the Reserve and Cadet Forces and the ulster Defence Regiment are shown in Annex  &quot; J, Table      J&apos;.Their estimated cost is shown in Annex   J,ARMY RESERVES3.     The Army Reserves comprise the regular Reserves, the ArmyGeneral Reserve consisting of certain ex-National Servicemen, andthe Territorial and Army Volunteer Reserve (TAVR).k.     Following the expansion of the TAVR establishment in April 1971there was a rapid build-up in strength, which has continued.    Thestrength of the TAVR rose from 56,300 in December 1971 to   Jon 1 January 1973.5.      Units of the TAVR with an overseas role train abroad once inevery three years.    In 1973 about 23,000 men will train in Europe,Cyprus and Gibraltar.
THE ULSTER DEFENCE REGIMENT6.     The Ulster Defence Regiment has established itself as animportant element of the security forces in Northern Ireland.The strength of the Regiment rose from 6,700 on 1 January 1972to 9,000 on 1 January 1973.   An additional battalion, 11 UDR,was formed in parts of County Armagh and County Down.7.     The Regiment performs the vital role of supporting theRegular Army in Northern Ireland by carrying out such tasks asguarding key points, conducting patrols and manning road checks.Since it was formed in 1970 the Regiment has suffered  &quot;^Oj killed,25 during 1972*   The whole Regiment was called out for extendedservice at the time of Operation MOTORMAN.ROYAL NAVY AND ROYAL MARINES RESERVE FORCES8.     The Royal Navy and Royal Marines Reserve Forces consist oftwo elements, the regular Reserves and the volunteer Reserves.The regular Reserves are ex-regular Royal Navy and Royal Marinesofficers and men,  including some 5,000 ratings in the Royal FleetReserve, who have had recent experience of active service.    Thevolunteer Reserves are the Royal Naval Reserve,  the Royal MarinesReserve and the Women&apos;s Royal Naval Reserve totalling some 3,000officers and h,h00 ratings.9.     Members of the regular Reserves are not required to undertakeperiodic training but those in the volunteer Reserves normallyundergo evening instruction and carry out fourteen days&apos; annualtraining.    The Royal Naval Reserve Divisions man eleven minesweepers- 36 -CONFIDENTIAL
and support maritime and other headquarters on communications,naval control of shipping and other tasks.    The Royal MarinesReserve&apos;s primary task is to reinforce the regular Corps and inparticular the Royal Marines Commandos.    Its strength is to be built up eventually to 1,350.ROYAL AIR FORCE RESERVE FORCES10.    The Royal Air Force Reserve consists of the Regular andVolunteer Reserves and the Royal Auxiliary Air Force.    Under are-allocation of the duties of the Royal Auxiliary Air Force,additional support will be provided to Strike Command.CADET FORCES11.    The total strength of the Cadet Forces at 1 January 1973 was &quot;      J,   The Sea Cadet Corps, the Army Cadet Force, the air training Corps and the Combined Cadet Force make a significant contribution to recruitment to the Regular Forces.- 37 -
IVMANPOWER AND CONDITIONSOF service.     Over the next few years the Services will have a number of problems to overcome in achieving the high rates of recruitment and prolongation of service required to meet manpower needs.   the raising of the school-leaving age, which will produce a sharpreduction in the number of school-leavers, will create special difficulties in 1973-7U.   In the longer term, it is expected thatthe size of the pool from which the recruits can be drawn willcontinue to diminish, as increasing numbers of potential recruitscontinue in full time education.RECRUITMENT AND RE-ENGAGEMENT DURING 1972-73Male Officers2.    The numbers of recruits during the nine months ended31 December 1972 are shown in Annex  &quot;    Jf, Table  &quot;   J.    Themain developments in that period are set out below.3.    Royal Navy and Royal Marines.    Officer entries into theSeaman, Engineering and Supply branches of the Royal Navy showed- 38 -
a further improvement;       Z&quot;&quot;220J recruits undertook full careercommissions compared with  177 the previous year, an increaseof /&quot;nearly 25 per centJ7.   This figure represents  &quot;Sh per cent^of the target, the best achievement since 1966-67.   The numbersof graduates and undergraduates undertaking full and short servicecareers increased substantially.    Specialist officer recruitment to the Royal Navy during the period was satisfactory but shortages of doctors still cause concern.h.    The number of full career entrants into the Royal Marinesincreased but there is still a shortage.    Many officers on short service Commissions are however transferring to Full CareerCommissions.5. The numbers of Royal Navy and Royal Marines officers recruited from civilian life are given in the table below.	1 April-31 December (9 months)		Percentage difference 1972 over 1971	1971	1972	C+ or -)Officer Cadets	256		University Cadets	56		Direct Graduate Entry Scheme	k5		Other Schemes	57		Total			6.    Army.    It has been another disappointing year for the entry toSandhurst for permanent regular and special regular commissions, and
	1 April-31 December (9 months)		Percentage difference 1972 over 1971	1971	1972	C+ or -)Officer Cadets	U03		University Cadets	88		Direct Graduate Entry Scheme	37		Other Schemes	67		Total	595		7.     The improvement in recruitment of qualified doctors for theArmy has been maintained,but the full annual requirement is still not being met.   There has been a slight reduction in the recruitment of medical cadets.    Cadetships will in future be open to female aswell as to male medical students.8,     The Army&apos;s Short Service Limited Commission scheme, which enables young men to serve for several months in the Army without commitment before going to university, has proved successful andhas now been established permanently.9.   Royal Air Force,   There has been no shortage of applicants forcommissions and with few exceptions the entry targets for bothflying and ground branches will be met.    In future some 30 per cent of all officer entrants to the Service are expected to be graduates,and graduate and university cadet recruitment continue to be- hO -there has been a fall in the entry for short service officerscompared with last year.   The university entry, on the other hand,has continued to grow.   The numbers embarking on cadet training orcommissioned direct from civilian life are given in the table below.
satisfactory.   A Pre-University Officer Cadetship Scheme has nowheen introduced to enable young men to gain some experience of theRoyal Air Force, without any commitment to subsequent service, beforegoing to university.   The numbers of officers and cadets recruited from civilian life are given in the table below.	1 April-31 December (9 months)		Percentage difference 1972 over 1971	1971	1972	C+ or -)Officer Cadets	263		University Cadets	19U		Direct Graduate Entry Scheme	130*		Other Schemes	179		Total	766		* Includes 60 graduate recruits shown in Cmnd. i+891 under &quot;other schemes&quot;.Servicemen10. The Services&apos; recruiting achievement during the nine month sending 31 December 1972 is set out in the Table on page kk.Fuller details and certain definitions are given in Annex  &quot; J/,Table     J.11, Royal Navy and Royal Marines.   Recruitment to both the royal navy and Royal Marines has been maintained at the high level set in 1971-72.    In the nine months April to December 1972 the royal navy recruited ^&quot;&quot;6,280J/ and the Royal Marines ^f&quot;l,180j7, comparedwith 6,123 and 1,030 respectively in the corresponding periodof the previous year.   Despite this satisfactory general picture,there are still shortages in some branches of the Royal Navy.
12.   The most welcome feature of Royal Navy and Royal Marinesrecruiting patterns during the past year has been the large numberof entrants between the ages of 16 and 17^.   During the period april to December 1972 the number of entrants in this category was/&quot;2,6iqJ7 and  &quot;ty&amp;JJ respectively compared with 2,381 and  &quot;hl)ljin the corresponding months of 1971,   This is particularly encouraging-ing in the light of the situation following the raising of theschool-leaving age.13.    Prolongation rates in the Royal Navy and Royal Marines have maintained an upward trend and at the nine-year point now standat 51 per cent for the Royal Navy and 1+7 per cent for the royal marines.1U.    Army. Adult recruitment has declined from the exceptionally high level achieved during 1971-72.   The reduction has to someextent been offset by a further increase in junior recruiting,which has surpassed last year&apos;s record achievement.   The juniorintake in September was again so large that the training organisa-tion had to take special measures to cope with it.1 5.   The first large intakes of soldiers recruited on the three-yearengagement, which was made generally available in April 1969, passed the three-year point during the last year.    Between April and september 1972 5k per cent of these soldiers prolonged their service, mostly to the nine-year point.   At the six and nine-yearpoints the rates of prolongation have improved; at the twelve-yearpoint the rate remains high.   There are some signs of improvement inthe wastage rate of trained soldiers, but the rate for recruitscontinues to give concern.   The underlying reasons for this wastageare being investigated.
16.   Royal Air Force.   All the Royal Air Force&apos;s present require-ments are &quot;being met.   The rate of prolongation to non-pensionableengagements continues to be entirely satisfactory; the number ofpensionable engagements is subject to control to meet long-termmanpower requirements.17.   In view of the raising of the school-leaving age and satis-factory adult recruitment, the Royal Air Force will discontinueapprentice schemes, with the exception of technician apprentices,from the summer of 1973.   After that, recruits will be enlistedfor most trades from the age of 16  and will be given shorterperiods of training to the same technical standards.   Currentregulations regarding the employment and treatment of young airmenwill continue to apply, and those enlisting below the age of 17^will retain the right to opt for the notice engagement on reaching the age of 18.- 43 -
RECRUITMENT OP SERVICEMEN PROM CIVIL LIFEService and Method of Entry	1 April to 31 December (9 months)		Percentage Difference 1972 over 1971 or -)	1971	1972	Royal Navy and Royal Marines Adult3 Juniors Artificer Apprentices Total	2,058 4,853 262			7,173		Army Adults Young Soldiers Apprentices Other Juniors Total	12,425 3,352 1,231 6,626			23,634		Royal Air Force Adults Young Airmen Apprentices Total	3,638 .631 1,362			5,631		All Services Adults Others Total	18,121 18,317			36,438		- kh -CONFIDENTIAL
Women&apos;s Services18. Recruitment to both commissioned and non-commissioned service in the Women&apos;s Services and the Nursing Services has been generally-satisfactory, but there are still some shortages in the QueenAlexandra&apos;s Royal Army Nursing Corps,ENGAGEMENTS19.   Both the engagement structure for boys introduced in early1971 in the light of the recommendations of the Donaldson Report(Cmnd. U509), and the notice engagement for adult Servicemen havebeen working well.    All three Services now have flexible engagementstructures which give the individual Serviceman and Servicewomana wide freedom of choice on the length and terms of their service.The &quot;Donaldson Option&quot;20.   The proportion of those boy entrants to the Services who were entitled to shorten their engagements to three years (about  &quot;     Jin the last nine months of 1972) and who actually did so is shownin the following table.Service	1 April to 31 December   (9 months)		1971	1972Royal Navy Royal Marines Army Royal Air Force	Percentage 27 26 3k 10	PercentageAll Services	25	- k5 -CONFIDENTIAL		
These figures are generally encouraging and show that / the greatmajority^ of hoys who join the Services remain content with theirchoice after they mature from hoy service.The Notice Engagement21.   For the period /&quot;May to DecemberJ 1972 the proportion of recruits eligible to enlist on three-year notice engagements who did so was:-PercentageRoyal Navy and Royal MarinesArmyRoyal Air ForceAll services the first Servicemen who joined on notice engagements will notbe entitled to exercise their option to give 18 months&apos; noticeof their intention to leave until the autumn of 1973,  18 monthsafter their enlistment.PAY AND PENSIONS22.    The Review Body on Armed Forces Pay made its first report in1972.    It recommended increased rates of military salaries, andnew rates designed to reflect the increases in civilian earningsthat   had taken place since the previous biennial pay review in1970, were introduced with effect from 1 April 1972.    The pay of
*Servicewomen was increased from 87 to 90 per cent of the rate formen.   Increased charges for food and accommodation were introducedfrom 1 April 1.972, pending further studies by the Review Body.23.   The Armed Forces Pay Review Body will keep Service pay underreview and, while retaining the existing system of biennialreviews, will make recommendations on particular aspects of service pay at other times.  2U.   The Armed Forces   Pensions Scheme is being reviewed.    Thefirst phase of the review, completed in April 1972, resulted insignificant improvements in pensions and retired pay.    The second phase is concerned with improving other benefits, taking accountof recent improvements in Civil Service pension arrangements andthe Governments pensions policy as embodied in the Social SecurityBill at present before Parliament.    The main changes affect pensionsand other benefits for widows and children and for injuryand death during a Service career.    They also include the intro-duction of deferred pensions for those who serve for a qualifyingperiod but who leave the Services before pensionable age.^/CONDITIONS OF SERVICEDiscipline25.   The Armed Forces Act 1971 came into force on 1 July 1972.The provisions bring the disciplinary codes of the three Servicesmore into line with each other.    There have been no difficultiesin carrying out the Act.- kl -CONFIDENTIAL
Family Welfare26.    Unaccompanied service separates families and gives rise toa number of welfare problems.    In the United Kingdom a great dealof assistance is given both by local authorities and by such bodies as the Soldiers&apos;, Sailors&apos; and Airmen&apos;s Families Association.Ways of improving the services available are continually underreview.    The report of the Naval Welfare Committee under Lord Seebohmis   expected shortly.Visits by Schoolchildren to Parents Serving Overseas27.    Service families abroad with children under 18 attendingboarding schools in Britain are now entitled to a third visit every year at public expense so that families can be together during theschool holidays.   Parents are required to contribute towards thefare of the first child.Improvement of Conditions for Troops in Northern Ireland28.    Measures designed to ease the problems of men and their families arising from service in Northern Ireland include extensions of leave, leave travel concessions, increased provision for cheaptelephone calls to Great Britain and British Forces Germany, and additional amenities and recreational facilities.Single Accommodation29.   New standards have now been adopted for new building andconversions based on the &quot;barrack flat&quot;: a group of single orfour-person bedrooms with sitting room, bathroom facilities andutility area.
VSUPPORTHIGHER DEFENCE TRAINING AND STUDIES1.     The National Defence College completed its first course inJuly 1972;    the second course is now under way.   The 1972 course at the Royal College of Defence Studies was attended by studentsfrom 15 nations.2S     The Ministry of Defence enjoys a close association with theacademic v/orld through the Defence Lecturers,  the Defence Fellows,and a joint programme of study conferences and seminars.    SevenDefence Lecturers, whose costs are borne on Defence Votes, arealready in post.     Four serving officers hold Defence Fellowshipsfor the current academic year at the Universities of Edinburgh,London (Imperial College of Science and Technology), Loughborough,and Oxford (Balliol).   The Ministry of Defence sponsored studyconferences at Southampton in May 1972 on the Indian Ocean andat the National Defence College in September 1972 on the Defenceof Western Europe.    Serving officers and civilian officialsmaintained a wide range of other contacts and discussions withthe academic world.- US -
INITIAL AND SPECIALIST training royal NAVY AND ROYAL MARINESTraining for RN Short Career Officers3.     A full academic term at Dartmouth has been introduced for thefirst time for short career Seaman Officers.   This will providea better basis for some of the technical aspects of their specialisttraining later.   Qualified entrants for a short career as NavalEngineers have in the past started Engineering Application Coursesimmediately after a very short introductory course at the DivisionalSchool at Portsmouth;    in future they will undergo a full term ofGeneral Naval Training at Dartmouth followed by a term at sea withthe Fleet before going to reconstituted Application Courses.Staff Trainingk.     For some time too few Royal Naval officers have had theopportunity of staff training as Lieutenant Commanders at the royal naval Staff Course.   The course is now being halved to about 5i months in order to increase the numbers attending.   A period of one monthwill be allocated for extensive reading before the beginning of thecourse and the syllabus has been revised to provide a concentratedand demanding period of study.Ratings5.     Good progress is being made towards securing the award ofnationally recognised qualifications to ratings after successful
completion of naval training.   Twelve established naval courses ofvarious specializations are now accepted as meeting particularcivilian requirements with only minimal change;    negotiations arenearing completion for a further three courses.ARMYTraining at Sandhurst6.     All Army officer cadets now train at the Royal Military Academy,Sandhurst.   The first courses on a new pattern of training started in September 1972.   There is a course of 25 weeks initial militarytraining for the whole entry.   Those who have chosen to become regular officers stay on for a further course of five months academic andmilitary studies.   Those short service officers who wish to convertto regular commissions at a later date return to Sandhurst to attendthis course.   There are also courses lasting up to one year for regular officers wishing to improve their qualifications for a degreeplace at either a university or the Royal Military College of science.   Courses of four to five months are now held for young officers entering through university before taking up regimentalduties; the length of each course depends on the amount of militarytraining already undertaken.Degree Training7.      60 serving officers began degree courses at the Royal MilitaryCollege of Science, and 23 at universities during the last nine months of 1972.Officer Training Review8.     A comprehensive review of officer training from first-51 -CONFIDENTIAL
commissioning to promotion to Lieutenant Colonel is being undertaken.This review will build on the foundation of the new courses at theRoyal Military Academy, Sandhurst and will examine the need for changes in the training pattern later in an officers career.Training of Juniors9.     The raising of the school-leaving age to 16 reduces the period during which a boy can join the Army as a junior, and brings himcloser to the age (17) at which he can enlist as a Young Soldier,eligible for training in the adult training organisation.   Thelength of junior training, other than for apprentices, will as aresult need to be shortened.Organisation of Individual Training in the United KingdomICr.   From 1 April 1973, the Commander-in-Chief, United Kingdom land forces will become responsible for implementing training policythroughout the United Kingdom, and District Commanders will exercisegreater control over training establishments.   The Director of ArmyTraining will remain responsible for promulgating Army Boardtraining policy but the Directors of Arms and Services, while retaining their role as advisers on specialist training to the ArmyBoard, will become responsible to the Commander-in-Chief, UnitedKingdom Land Forces for training matters relating to their Corps.ROYAL AIR FORCEOfficer Training11.    Following the introduction of the graduate entry scheme, thenew form   of general service training is operating satisfactorily.
Planning for the re-deployment, announced last year, of units tothe Royal Air Force College, Cranwell is going ahead.12.   A revised and shortened programme of command and staff training for officers is being introduced in stages, beginning in March 1973.After initial training and command and leadership training, basicstaff training will be given by a combination of correspondence and residential courses; selected officers will later attend the RoyalAir Force Staff College, Bracknell, where the course will be shorterthan hitherto.   Advanced specialist training in air warfare willsubsequently be given to selected officers required to fillappointments directly concerned with the planning and executionof air operations.FLYING training royal AIR FORCE AND ROYAL NAVY13.   The Jetstream aircraft will start to replace the Varsity inthe multi-engine pilot role this year and the Bulldog to replace theChipmunk in the University Air Squadrons.   The first Jaguar pilotswill be undergoing conversion training in October.    All Buccaneerand Phantom training, including that for the Royal Navy,  is nowcarried out within the Royal Air Force; under a new scheme selectedRoyal Naval helicopter aircrew are transferred on temporary loan tothe Royal Air Force for training and experience in fixed-wing flyingoperations.   Rotary wing flying training has begun at the royal naval Air Station, Yeovilton.COMMONWEALTH AND FOREIGN TRAINING1k.    The Services assisted other nations last year by receivingmore than 5,000 officers and men from overseas on training courseswithin the United Kingdom, by seconding officers to the staffs of colleges overseas, and by providing personnel on loan and in- 53 -CONFIDENTIAL
Planning for the re-deployment, announced last year, of units tothe Royal Air Force College, Cranwell is going ahead.12.    A revised and shortened programme of command and staff training for officers is being introduced in stages, beginning in March 1973.After initial training and command and leadership training, basicstaff training will be given by a combination of correspondence and residential courses; selected officers will later attend the RoyalAir Force Staff College, Bracknell, where the course will be shorterthan hitherto.   Advanced specialist training in air warfare willsubsequently be given to selected officers required to fillappointments directly concerned with the planning and executionof air operations.FLYING training royal AIR FORCE AND ROYAL NAVY13.   The Jetstream aircraft will start to replace the Varsity inthe multi-engine pilot role this year and the Bulldog to replace theChipmunk in the University Air Squadrons.    The first Jaguar pilotswill be undergoing conversion training in October.   All Buccaneerand Phantom training, including that for the Royal Navy, is nowcarried out within the Royal Air Force; under a new scheme selectedRoyal Naval helicopter aircrew are transferred on temporary loan tothe Royal Air Force for training and experience in fixed-wing flyingoperations.   Rotary wing flying training has begun at the royal naval Air Station, Yeovilton.COMMONWEALTH AND FOREIGN TRAINING1h.    The Services assisted other nations last year by receivingmore than 5,000 officers and men from overseas on training courseswithin the United Kingdom, by seconding officers to the staffs of colleges overseas, and by providing personnel on loan and in- 53 -CONFIDENTIAL
training teams to help with local training.       For example there areloan personnel in Malaysia and in the Union Defence Force in theUnited Arab Emirates,     a Special Air Service training team in Oman,and joint-Service training teams in Kuwait and Kenya.15.   Following the withdrawal of British Forces from the Gulf, aMilitary Advisory Team has been established at Sharjah to assistunits visiting the area on training exercises, and to advise and assist local forces.16.   The Army has started using the training area at Suffield,Alberta, under the agreement on the increased use of military training facilities reached with the Canadian Government in 1971.   The 1972orogramme was a complete success and in 1973 increased numbers ofall arms will undergo the particularly effective training that thearea provides.17.    Facilities have been provided for jungle warfare training inMalaysia and Brunei.   Minor exercises were carried out in 1972.ADVENTUROUS TRAINING18.    A start has been made to the tri-Service adventurous training programme.    Mountain training, free-fall parachuting, sub-aauadiving and skiing   courses have been held.    Most of the requiredtraining centres will be established by the end of the current financial year.
PRODUCTION, REPAIR AND SUPPLY organisation in THE UNITED KINGDOMHM DOCKYARDS AND THE ROYAL NAVAL SUPPLYORGANISATIONProgramme of Work19.   The Royal Dockyards will he heavily loaded during the financialyear 1973-74.   The programme for Portsmouth includes the normalrefit of the assault ship HMS Intrepid, one long refit and two normalrefits of guided-missile destroyers, three refits of frigates andthe three-stream refitting of conventional submarines.   Devonportwill complete the conversion of HMS Hermes to the commando ship roleand undertake   the normal refits of the aircraft carrierHMS Ark Royal and the assault ship HMS Fearless, eight refits offrigates and the routine docking of nuclear submarines.   Both Chathamand Rosyth will refit and refuel nuclear submarines.   The programme for Chatham also includes the refits of a conventional submarine and five frigates and the normal refit of the fleet maintenance shipHMS Triumph;   Rosyth will undertake the refits of frigates and aconventional submarine.   All dockyards will also undertake work on other vessels and craft.20.   The effects of the industrial unrest which all dockyardsexperienced in 1972 will be felt throughout the financial year1973-74 in the backlog of work outstanding from 1972-73.   Measuresplanned to reduce the additional load in 1973-74 include a reductionof the work content of some refits, the cancellation of some dockingperiods and the repair of some ships by contract.   Further
improvements to management systems include the extended applica-tion of operating accounts, and the extension and streamliningof a project management and reporting system in all yards.Royal Naval Supply Organisation21.   Planning of the move of the Royal Naval Stores Depot atCopenacre to Hartlehury is going ahead.   As announced in theHouse of Commons on 10 May 1972, the Depot at Eaglescliffe willnot now he moved.   The savings in capital and running costs,while lower than under the original plan, will nevertheless hesignificant.ROYAL ORDNANCE FACTORIESOrganisation and Operation22.   The restructured Royal Ordnance Factories (ROF) Board, whichwas set up last year under the chairmanship of the parliamentary under-Secretary of State for Defence for the Army, has beenreviewing ROF policy in the context of the organisations morecommercial role.   A trading fund will be brought into operation on a notional basis from the beginning of 1973-7U.Output23.   The output from ROFs in 1973-7U is expected to be  82m. excluding the value ( 15m.) of components supplied to the factories for incorporation into their products.   The Ministry of Defence is the- 56 -CONFIDENTIAL
major customer for ROF production but a third in 1973-74 willbe for export.Investment2k.    Capital investment in new machine tools and plant remains at the level necessary to ensure that the factories are ableto deal with future programmes of work and to continue to Improveproductivity.ROYAL AIR FORCE ADMINISTRATION and supply ORGANISATIONEconomy in Support Costs25.    A major review of Royal Air Force manpower and supportrequirements is under way.   This should lead to a reduction ofsome 6,000 posts without detriment to the front line.   At thesame time, the role of Maintenance Command within the UnitedKingdom, the organisation within the Ministry of Defence forengineering and supply support of the Royal Air Force and theorganisation of flying and trade training are under examination.This is expected to lead to Improved efficiency and co-ordination and to yield further economies in support costs.Logistic Support Arrangements26.    Comprehensive studies are in progress on the support of aircraft and equipment in service.   They are aimed at improving the efficiency and economy of the system with particular emphasis- 57 -CONFIDENTIAL
on computer methods of assessing requirements, determining the quantity and timing of orders and controlling provisioningand distribution.COMPUTER BUREAUX27.    The use of large computing bureaux offers the maximum potentialfor cost-effectiveness in meeting the rapid growth expected over thenext decade in data-processing requirements in the administrativefield.   Following a tri-Service project study, led by the management services organisation, the equipment for a first large bureau willbe ordered shortly for delivery in 1974-75.28.    The development of the Departments Automatic Data Processingsystems, including the use of large bureaux, and work in the Manage-ment Services area generally are supervised by the Management ServicesSteering O-roup which is chaired by the Permanent Under-Secretary ofState and on which the three Services and the Procurement Executiveare represented.LANDSProperty Services Agency29.    From 1 September 1972 the Property Services Agency of theDepartment of the Environment became responsible for the professional
services required Tor property and estate management for the Ministryof Defence, which were formerly provided by the Defence Landsorganisation.   The Ministry of Defence will continue to own and tobe responsible for the financial and administrative control of itsland holdings.Defence Lands Committee30.    The Defence Lands Committee under the chairmanship of LordNugent of Guildford has now reached the final stage of its reviewof defence land holdings in the United Kingdom and is expected toreport soon.WORKS SERVICES31.   Within the Department of the Environment works services arenow the responsibility of the Property Services Agency.32.    In the coming year about  9m. will be spent on the continuingredevelopment of the Naval Bases at Devonport, Portsmouth andRosyth:    individual projects to be started include a frigaterefitting complex at Devonport.       A further  3.5m. will be spenton the redevelopment of HMS Raleigh, the major new-entry trainingestablishment near Plymouth, and the rebuilding of accommodation at Culdrose.   The standards of emergency accommodation for thetroops in Northern Ireland have been improved and expenditure on further improvements and on general amenities will continue at ahigh level.    Implementation of the new standards of accommodation for single Servicemen and Servicewomen will- 59 -
begin in the United Kingdom and Germany during 1973-74: about 3,000new married quarters will be built, and older married quarters willbe refurbished.HIRINGS33.    The cost of hiring married accommodation for all the Services-in 1973-74 will amount to about  21.7m.,  km. in the United Kingdomand  17.7m. overseas.   The number of hirings in Germany is expectedto reach 22,300 by the end of 1973-7k compared with 16,500 at the start of 1972-73.MOVEMENTSMalta3k.   The return to Malta of 6,600 Service personnel and their dependants was completed by 23 October 1972, mainly by Servicemeans.   In restoring the base to an operational state about 50,000shipping tons of stores and other essential equipment were movedusing both Service and civil resources.   The withdrawal and return of the British force was a considerable feat of organisation and administration by the Services Movements and Logistics staff, andby the Headquarters British Forces Malta.Northern Ireland35.    About k6,000 personnel have been moved to and from NorthernIreland by sea and air during the year.   In July 1972, over a periodof 72 hours the Services moved some k,500 troops to Northern ireland for operation MOTORMAN.Training in Canada36.    Equipment and vehicles for use in the new training area at- 60 -CONFIDENTIAL
Suffield in Canada were moved &quot;by sea in Landing Ships Logistic ofthe Royal Fleet Auxiliary.   Units are carried by Royal Air Forceaircraft between Germany and Canada for training.Gurkha Trooping37.    With the agreement and co-operation of the Indian and NepaleseGovernments, Gurkha soldiers and their families, who were previouslymoved with some difficulty between Hong Kong and Nepal by civil aircraft and rail, are now being carried direct by the Royal AirForce.METEOROLOGY38.    The Richardson Wing at the Meteorological Office Headquarterswas officially opened in October 1S72.   It houses the new CentralForecasting Office, modernised telecommunications facilities andthe IBM 360/195 computer which has been producing operationalforecasts for the northern hemisphere since August 1972.39.   Considerable international interest has been shown in the DeeWeather Radar project, jointly sponsored by the meteorological office, the Water Resources Board and Plessey Radar Ltd., to investigate the use of weather radar as a means of measuring rainfall.h0*   The Meteorological Office is engaged in the project definitionphase of a temperature measuring instrument for incorporation inthe US Tiros N series of meteorological satellites to be launchedby the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in 1976-77.U1.      The Office is co-operating with other European MeteorologicalServices in the planning of a geostationary meteorological satellite- 61 -CONFIDENTIAL
Stiffield in Canada were moved by sea in Landing Ships Logistic ofthe Royal Fleet Auxiliary.   Units are carried by Royal Air Forceaircraft between Germany and Canada for training.Gurkha Trooping37.    With the agreement and co-operation of the Indian and NepaleseGovernments, Gurkha soldiers and their families, who were previouslymoved with some difficulty between Hong Kong and Nepal by civil aircraft and rail, are now being carried direct by the Royal AirForce.METEOROLOGY38.    The Richardson Wing at the Meteorological Office Headquartersv/as officially opened in October 1972.    It houses the new CentralForecasting Office, modernised telecommunications facilities andthe IBM 360/195 computer which has been producing operationalforecasts for the northern hemisphere since August 1972.39.   Considerable international interest has been shown in the DeeWeather Radar project, jointly sponsored by the meteorological office, the Water Resources Board and Plessey Radar Ltd., to investigate the use of weather radar as a means of measuring rainfall.hO,   The Meteorological Office is engaged in the project definitionphase of a temperature measuring instrument for incorporation inthe US Tiros N series of meteorological satellites to be launchedby the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in 1976-77.U1.      The Office is co-operating with other European MeteorologicalServices in the planning of a geostationary meteorological satellite
to be built and launched by the European Space Research Organisation.SALESU2.    The Defence Sales Organisation provides support, assistance and advice to British industry, including the Royal OrdnanceFactories, in promoting the sales of defence equipment overseas.Exports are expected to reach a value of  350m. in 1973-71+.COST AND MANPOWERU3.    The cost of and Service and civilian manpower strengths insupport functions are shown at Annex  &quot;   J.- 62 -
VIRESEARCH AND development cost OF RESEARCH AND development .     In 1973-74 the total cost of research and development on afunctional basis is expected to be  /&quot;440^/m., including an allowance for value added tax.   An analysis of the expenditure is shown at annex  &quot; J,   At the same price level but with minor differences inthe basis of calculation, the forecast out-turns of expenditure for1971-72 and 1972-73 are  /&quot;&quot;315j7m. and &amp;fjh5.J^* respectively.   Thisupward trend reflects a build-up in effort as the programme proceedsand is also an indicator of the increasing development costs of advanced equipment.RESEARCH2.     The research programme is the responsibility of the controller of Research and Development Establishments and Research, who isprovided with guidelines on operational requirements and advice on broad policy issues by the Defence Research Committee.    Researchexpenditure covers work which is not tied to specific projects andwhich is carried out in support of the development programme,either within the Government*s Research and Development Establishments(intra-mural effort) or outside (extra-mural effort).    The latter is mainly undertaken by industry.3.     The results of current research are likely to be reflected infeatures of new defence equipment some years hence.    For example,the Multi-Role Combat Aircraft project depends on recent research into aerodynamic wing design and air inlet design.    Similarly, the105 mm light gun, which has a greater range and rate of fire than- 63 -
any other in its class, owes its performance to extensive research into steels for gun barrels and carriages and to new concepts of design.4.     A significant part of the research work of the Ministry ofDefence is directed towards civil objectives.    In many cases jointcivil/military programmes are arranged in order to use resourcesmost effectively.   The estimated receipts on civil account in1973-74 are    -\6m._J.    Most of this sum relates to civil aerospaceresearch.    The programmes aimed at defence objectives are in two main areas: general technological research, and applied researchrelated to specific development fields.   The expected expenditurein 1973-74 is on general research and  &quot; kbi&amp;*J onapplied research.INTERNATIONAL COLLABORATION5.      Special attention is paid in consultation with NATO allies to improving the machinery for identifying potential areas for future collaboration.     One aim of the principles of collaboration agreed between the Eurogroup nations isto avoid duplication of expenditure on research and develop-ment (see Chapter I, paragraph 8) particularly on projectslikely to absorb major resources.    The NATO Conference of NationalArmaments Directors (CNAD) has decided to recommend theadoption of similar principles by all NATO nations.    Both in the- 64 -
Kurogroup and in CNAD a number of specific project areas havebeen identified as priority targets for co-operation.DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMMES 1973-7*4-6.     The management of the development programmes is the responsibility-responsibility of the appropriate systems Controller in the ProcurementExecutive.   The principal projects now in progress are:a.     Aircraft(1)   The Multi-Role Combat Aircraft.    The MRCA, which isbeing developed in collaboration with the federal republic of Germany and Italy, continues to receivehigh priority in the aircraft programme.    Since thebeginning of the first phase of full developmentwas authorised in July 1970, good progress has beenmade with all aspects of the design of the aircraftsystem.    Substantial resources are now engaged onthis project, although the scheduled flight of thefirst prototype is still some way ahead.   the closest attention is being given to management andcontrol of cost.(2)   Anglo-French Projects.   With deliveries to the Royal AirForce starting this year, development of the Jaguar isnearing completion.    The Gazelle also is in produc-tion and development of the Lynx is well advanced.(3)   Trainers.   During 1972 the HS 1182 was selected for development as the new jet trainer for the Royal- 65 -CONFIDENTIAL
Air Force, and the Jetstream as the multi-enginedpilot trainer,(h)   Future Prelects.   A project definition study todetermine whether the Harrier can he adapted atan acceptable cost for a maritime role isnearing completion.   A project definition studyto examine the conversion of the Argosy toreplace the Varsity in the rear crew trainingrole is also under way.    Studies are in hand toconsider the progressive modernisation of the equipment installed in the Nimrod maritime patrolaircraft and the eventual replacement of theShackleton in the Airborne Early Warning Role.G-uided-WeaponsFive important guided-weapons projects have now reachedan advanced stage of development:(1)    Sea Dart (medium-range surface-to-air guided-weapon system for ships);(2)    Sea Wolf (short-range surface-to-air guided-weapon system for ships);(3)   Rapier (air defence system, including the all-weather version using the DN 181 tracking radar);(h)    swing fire (anti-tank weapon already developed for mounting on armoured personnel carriers andFerret scout cars, and currently under further development for mounting on several other vehicles);(5)   Blowpipe (air defence system).- 66 -
During 1972, project definition studies were initiatedon an underwater-launched air-flight anti-shipguided-missile system for the nuclear submarine fleet;a short-range air-to-air missile; and a helicopter-borne anti-ship missile.   A feasibility study has been initiated on a new British homing head and fuze forthe United States Sparrow medium-range air-to-airmissile already in service with the Royal Air Force.Wherever practical the requirements of the different services are harmonized (for example, the Rapier system is being developed for both the Army and the Royal AirForce) and as far as possible common components andtechniques are employed throughout families of weapons and also in different systems.   Training requirements,for example the desirability of using simulation tech-techniques, are carefully considered at the design stage of a project,c.     ElectronicsThere are many projects in the electronics field, and much of the work is associated with the aircraft programme.There are requirements for radars, navigation attacksystems, flight simulators, flight control systems andother avionic systems both for aircraft projects underdevelopment, notably for the MRCA, and for improvements to existing aircraft, for example the Nimrod. Radars and sonarsare being developed for naval use, and other areas ofimportance are electronic countermeasures and- 67 -
communications systems for all three Services. Currentprojects include:(1)     a naval integrated communications system;(2)     Defence Communications Satellites (the firstreplenishment satellite is to he launchedduring 1973);(3)     Ptarmigan   (tactical trunk communications system);(U)     search radars for Nimrod and Lynx;(5)     a laser ranger/target detector for the Jaguarand the Harrier;(6)     a laser target marker for forward aircontrollers;(7)     electronic warfare equipment for the RoyalAir Force;(8)      an infantry company radar;(9)     night vision aids for ground forces.Ships and EquipmentBy the end of the 1970s the surface fleet will be builtround the new cruiser, the Type 1+2 destroyers and the Type 21 and Type 22 frigates.    All these ships will be powered by gas-turbine engines developed from aircraft engines.   Further development of these enginesis in progress.   Development of the special non-magneticmachinery and equipment required for the new class of mine counterraeasures   vessel^Xsee Chapter II,.paragraph8a(5))J^is now well advanced.    In the submarine fieldwork continues on an improved version of the present- 68 -
Swiftsure class of nuclear submarines and on nuclear propulsion for later submarines.   Work is also in hand onjji new light-weight torpedo and onj improvements to theMk 2k heavy-weight torpedo.Ordnance and Other Army EquipmentDevelopment of two major artillery systems, the 155 mmtowed and self-propelled howitzers, is being carriedout in collaboration with the Federal Republic of Germanyand Italy and the towed version is now well advanced.Collaborative   studies   are also in progress with thesecountries on an artillery free-flight rocket system.During the past year project definition studies have started on a new mechanised infantry combat vehicle toreplace the FVU30 series.   Concept studies on a futuremain battle tank, intended to lead to a programme ofcollaborative development, are in hand with the federal republic of Germany.   The first examples of both thetracked and wheeled versions of the air-portablearmoured reconnaissance vehicle (Scorpion and Fox)are now in production and development of specialistvariants continues.   Other projects in the development programme include:(1)     the combat engineer tractor for which the firstproduction orders have been placed;(2)     improvements, including an improved fire-control system, for Chieftain;(3)     a new range of logistic vehicles for battlefieldsupport.
OPERATIONAL ANALYSIS7.     Operational analysis studies are essentially concerned withobjective choice between alternative options.   They have become increasingly applied to questions of defence strategy and to the major policy decisions which face NATO.   They continue to help in solving problems of resource allocation within the Defence Budget,particularly in the equipment field.8.     Studies are carried out at various locations including severalResearch and Development establishments, but particularly at theDefence Operational Analysis Establishment (DOAE), a unit of some120 professional civilian and military officers whose authority and expertise are now well recognised.   DOAE is one of the mostimportant such units in NATO, and has developed close links withthose in other allied nations.- 70 -


</content>
</cab>
