<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/52/3 images: 28-42</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECiPA4IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm(73) 25thConclusionsCOPY NO59CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting cf the cabinet held at 20 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 3 MAY 1973at 11. 00 am present the Rt Hon Edward Heath mp prime minister the Rt Hon Sir Alec Douglas-Home mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs  (Items 1-6)The Rt Hon William Whitelaw mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Robert Carr mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon Anthony Barber mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Lord carrington secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Prior mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Geoffrey Rippon QC mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Gordon Campbell mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Peter Walker m.p the Rt Hon John Davies mp secretary of State for Trade and Industry     Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon The Earl jellicoe lord Privy seal the Rt Hon Maurice Macmillan mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Peter Thomas QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Joseph Godber mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QCMP ;Minister for Trade and Consumer Affairs(Items 3-7)
ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Francis Pym mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat the Rt Hon Sir Burke trend  J J B hunt mr P benner mr A P hockaday mr I T lawman mr D EvansDr M J HarteCONTENTSItem Subject page 1. PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSSocial Security Bill 1Subsidised Butter 12. OVERSEA AFFAIRSUnited States of America 3French Nuclear Tests 3The Lebanon 3Rhodesia 3Icelandic Fisheries Dispute 43. EUROPEAN COMMUNITY AFFAIRS 54. NORTHERN IRELAND 65. INDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSNational Day of Protest 7Shortage of Labour in Industry 8Discussions with TUC and CBI on Counter- 9Inflation policy. GOVERNMENT DISPERSALThe Hardman Report 107. DISCRIMINATION AGAINST WOMEN 13iiSECRET
PARLIAMENTARY   1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the affairs House of Commons during the following week.Social The Cabinet were informed that there might be difficulty during theSecurity Bill Report Stage of the Social Security Bill in securing the reversal ofan amendment made in Committee giving tax relief on employeesTcontributions to the reserve pension scheme.    It was important thatthe Bill should be restored to its original form in view of theGovernments policy of enhancing the attractiveness of occupational pension schemes by comparison with the reserve pension scheme.Every effort should therefore be made to ensure that the maximum number of Government supporters voted for the relevant amendment.Subsidised The Cabinet were informed that it was envisaged that there shouldButter be an early announcement of the Governments decision to takeadvantage of the European Economic Community (e.c.) Regulationenabling butter to be supplied at reduced prices to recipients of social assistance.    The original intention had been to make astatement later that day.    But some details of the administrative arrangements for operating the scheme still had to be settled;and, despite the public interest in the subject, it might be preferable to postpone the announcement until 7 May, when it couldbe made in the course of the Supply Debate on prices duringStage 2 of the Governments counter-inflationary policies.    Itshould be possible by then to resolve most of the points whichwere at present not settled.    In particular, it was to be hoped thatarrangements could be made for introducing the scheme within amuch shorter period than the three months at present contemplated.Moreover, it would be possible to secure the presentationaladvantage of announcing at the same time that the general buttersubsidy recently agreed by the e.c. would be coming into effecton 14 May, the earliest permissible date under the relevant EECdecision.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that the announcement of both butter subsidies should be made by the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry inthe course of his speech during the forthcoming debate on prices.In the meantime, the Lord President of the Council, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for Social Services, the Minister ofAgriculture,  Fisheries and Food and other Ministers concerned,should ensure that the main outstanding points in connection withthe administrative arrangements for providing subsidies butter forthe recipients of social assistance were resolved without delay.
In particular, the scheme should, if possible, be brought intoeffect within a much shorter period than three months.    The termsof the announcement by the Secretary of State for Trade and industry should reflect, as appropriate, the decisions reached on the detailsof the scheme.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.
VERSEA 2. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH secretary affairs informed the Cabinet that,  in the view of HM Ambassador in washington, the repercussions of the &quot;Watergate&quot; scandal in theUnited States were unlikely to inflict permanent damage on theUnited States        standing of the Presidency or the personal prestige of Presidentof America Nixon, unless it was established that he had had some knowledgebefore March, 1973, of the implication in the affair of members ofthe Administration or of his own staff.   Meanwhile, we shouldcontinue to refrain from any public comment on the affair;  and wecould hope that the foreign policy of the United States would continue to follow the confident course exemplified by the speech of Dr Henry Kissinger at the Associated Press Annual Luncheonon 23 April and by President Nixon&apos;s robust reaction to the possibleresumption of an offensive against South Vietnam by north vietnamese forces.French THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the nuclear Tests     Australian and New Zealand Governments continued to criticise us for not protesting more vigorously against the intention of theFrench Government to hold atmospheric nuclear tests in the PacificOcean later in the year.    In the House of Commons on the previous day he had reiterated the Governments view that the tests shouldnot be held and had made it clear that the French Government were well aware of this view.    But no useful purpose would be served byany more formal protest, particularly in view of the PrimeMinister^ forthcoming visit to Paris.The Lebanon        THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that therehad been an outbreak of fighting between the Lebanese Army andPalestinian guerrillas after the Army had surrounded a refugee campi to demand the release of two soldiers who had been kidnapped byguerrillas.    Fighting continued; but it was understood that the army were regaining control of the situation.     Some 120 children hadbeen isolated in the British community school in an area wherefighting was taking place; but HM Ambassador had succeeded inevacuating them.Rhodesia THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatMr Peter Niesewand, the journalist who had been convicted in salisbury on charges under the Rhodesian Official Secrets Act,had successfully appealed against the conviction but was still kept in custody under a detention order.    The Rhodesian authorities,however, were reconsidering the matter;  and they had been informedthat, if they agreed to deport Mr Niesewand from Rhodesia withoutdelay, we would admit him to the United Kingdom.
ftThe Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the statements bythe Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary.IcelandicFisheriesDisputePreviousReference:CM(73) 19thConclusions,Minute 2THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY informed theCabinet that the Minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs and the Minister of State, Ministry of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food, were renewing discussions with IcelandicMinisters in Reykjavik that day.    On the main issue of the limitation to be placed on the annual catch by British fishermen they had been instructed to open negotiations on the basis that the catch should beof the order of 155, 000 tonnes and to make a determined effort tosacure at least 140, 000 tonnes.    If agreement seemed to be within reach on the other points at issue (which might include acceptanceof the Icelandic desire to exclude freezer trawlers from waterswithin 50 miles of the coast), it would be for consideration whethera limitation of the annual catch to 130, 000 tonnes should be conceded.But this should be avoided, if possible.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOODconcurred.    He had made it clear to the fishing industry that somelimitation of catch would have to be conceded;  and, withoutdiscussing specific quantities he had gained the impression that,while a limitation of tha catch to 140,000 tonnes, perhaps coupled with the exclusion of freezer trawlers, would probably be tolerable,any lower limit would provoke serious dissatisfaction.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that concessions in respect of catch limitationshould be restricted to the minimum;  and the issues involved would need to be considered further if we were required to entertain limitation to an annual figure lower than 140, 000 ton&amp;es.The Cabinet -2. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister^ summing up of their discussion.4J
EUROPEAN 3. THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE FISHERIES AND FOODCOMMUNITY informed the Cabinet that the negotiations on prices under the affairs Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) for 1973-74 had finallyended on 1 May.    The principal factors in securing a resultwhich we could accept had been our efforts to ensure that theCommission understood our position to work closely with themthereafter and to prevent the French and German representatives from reaching an agreement at the expense of ourselves andthe rest of the Community.    This had called for some carefultactical management during the long negotiations.    Butagreement had finally been achieved when he had made it clearthat the United Kingdom would refuse to accept the further increase in the price of beef, which the French were trying to persuade the Germans to accept.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Cabinet would wish to congratulate the Minister and the Chief Secretary, Treasury,on their success in securing so favourable an outcome for theUnited Kingdom.5
northern ireland previous reference:CM (7 3) 24thConclusions,Minute 44. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN ireland said that the publication of the Governments White Paper on northern Ireland Constitutional Proposals (Cmnd 5259) hadstimulated vigorous political activity in Northern Ireland andhad produced significant changes in the traditional pattern of party politics in the Province.    A wide range of canaidatesappeared likely to come forward for the Local government elections; and we must hope that this would be repeated in the subsequent elections for the Assembly.    It did not necessarily follow, however, that all those who might be prepared to standas candidates would, if they were elected, be equally preparedto operate the system of government in a responsible manner.The leader of the Unionist Party, Mr Faulkner, hadreiterated his intention of co-operating in the elaboration ofnew constitutional arrangements on the lines;proposed in theWhite Paper;  and he had accepted that, if satisfactory new arrangements were not in operation by March, 1974, thecoiitinued willingness of British public opinion to acceptpolitical and military involvement in the affairs of NorthernIreland could not necessarily be assumed.Meanwhile, the security situation within the Province had greatly improved, apart from a campaign of &quot;retaliation&quot;against individual members of the security forces by snipersof the &quot;Official11 wing of the Irish Republican Army.    propaganda against the Parachute Regiment, however, was continuing.But they had been extremely effective in discovering arms and explosives and in reducing the number of serious incidents inthe Ardoyne area of Belfast; and there should be no suggestionthat they did not command the Governments full confidence.The Government would also continue to be criticised following a decision by the Courts (with whom alone the decision rested)to grant an order for the extradition to the Irish Republic ofa man accused of an offence of murder which the Court had decided was not a &quot;political&quot; crime.    Here, too, we should beready to deal firmly with any demonstrations by members ofthe Ulster Defence Association on this issue.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatthe Foreign Minister of the Irish Republic, Dr Fitzgerald, had given very short notice of his recent private visit to belfast and had refused to accept protection from the security forceswithin Northern Ireland.    Apart from the repercussions whichwould follow an attempt on his life, any intervention of this kindwas unwise in the present sensitive political climate in NorthernIreland; and HM Ambassador in Dublin would be instructed to seek to persuade Dr Fitzgerald to refrain from private visits tothe Province, at least until after the elections to the assembly on 28 June.
The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the statements bythe Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary andthe Secretary of State for Northern Ireland.INDUSTRIALAFFAIRSNational Day ofProtestPreviousReference:CM(73) 24thConclusions,Minute 55. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT saidthat, despite the efforts of militant elements, only about .1. 6 million workers had taken strike action on 1 May, the dayof protest and stoppage sponsored by the Trade Union Congress(TUC).    They were principally in the engineering industry, inthe docks, on the railways and in the more militant coal-mining areas.    The pay negotiations in the motor industry were stillproving difficult; and the disputes at the British steel corporation&apos;^ Scunthorpe works and at Harland and Wolff in belfast, both of which had caused substantial numbers of men tobe laid off, were having serious economic consequences.    Ingeneral, however, industry might now be relatively free frommajor industrial action for at least some months; and the risk ofnational one-day stoppages in future had probably been reduced.In discussion the following main points were made -a. The information about the national day of protestwhich had been broadcast by the British broadcasting corporation (BBC) had been inaccurate in severalrespects.    Provided that these could be substantiatedin detail, appropriate representations should be made tothe Corporation.b. There were some indications that the series ofindustrial disputes in the motor industry, which had ledto a substantial loss of production and exports, mightreflect a concerted plan to disrupt the economy.    It was for consideration how far it would be wise to expose the tactics being employed for this purpose.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up this part of the discussion,said that the Home Secretary should consider whether it would be advantageous to make an approach to the BBC in order to representto them the need for a better balance in their presentation of theeffects of industrial disputes.    The Home Secretary should also consider whether it would be helpful to seek to promote public discussion of the possible motivation of industrial disputes.
The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister and invited the Home Secretary to be guided accordingly.In further discussion it was noted that, although there had been avery substantial increase in production since the end of 1972, therewere increasing complaints from industrialists, which the recentIndustrial Trends Survey by the Confederation of British Industry(CBI) tended to confirm, that output during the coming months was likely to be constrained by shortages of labour.    Although therewas no evidence to show that there was in fact any general shortageof labour in industry, the reduction in unemployment during recent months did not appear to have been caused by the recruitment ofadditional labour by manufacturing industry.    In any event it was amatter for concern that general shortages of labour should now bea matter of discussion;  and it was increasingly unreasonable thatunemployed workers should be able to.define so narrowly the typeand location ox work which they were willing to accept that they couldreject without penalty employment which would be within theircapacities and would not involve any excessive daily journey.    Itwas for consideration, therefore, whether further steps should betaken to ensure that those who refused, without good cause, to accept any reasonable employment offered to them would be disqualifiedthereafter from receiving unemployment benefit.    The CBI mightbe correspondingly invited to persuade employers to be more precise in stating the reasons why they had rejected applicants for employment submitted to them by the Department of Employment.The entitlement of unemployed students to unemployment and supplementary benefit should also be reviewed.The Cabinet -f2f     Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for theCabinet to be informed of the outcome of theconsideration already in hand by the Home and social affairs Committee of the possibility of introducing more stringent rules governing the receipt of unemploymentbenefit.\ $3)$    Invited the Secretary of State for Employment toarrange for the Confederation of British Industry to be consulted about a more precise definition by employers of their reasons for rejecting applicants for employment.
ft IJj4jt    Invited the Secretary of State for Social services to circulate a Note describing the entitlement ofunemployed students to unemployment and supplementary benefit.Discussions withTUG and CBI onCounter-Inflation PolicyPreviousReference:CM(72) 4?thConclusionsTHE PRIME MINISTER said that, since the interruption of theearlier exchanges with the TUC and the CBI on counter-inflationpolicy there had been only informal contacts with these organisations.    It had become apparent, however, that, once thenational day of protest had taken place, the TUC would be preparedto resume discussion of the policy to be followed during Stage 3.Although there might not be much scope for progress until the outcome of the Pay Board&apos;s study of the anomalies arising fromthe Stage 2 pay policy was known, an initial meeting with the TUCmight take place before the end of the month, primarily in orderto ascertain the topics which they would be mainly concerned toconsider.    Productivity and threshold agreements would almost certainly need to be examined at some stage;  and these and other questions which might form part of the Stage 3 policy were already under study.    Reports that the Government were contemplatingintroducing substantial food subsidies, however, were not correct;indeed, a number of the union leaders would probably prefer the tuc not to press for such subsidies.The Cabinet -5. Took note, with approval, of the statement by the Prime Minister.9
ftGOVERNMENT 6. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the dispersal Lord Privy Seal (CP(73) 57) and the Secretary of State for trade and Industry (CP(73) 59) discussing the oeope forfurther dispersal of Government Departments from London.The HardmanReport THE PRIME MINISTER said that the report of an inquiry bySir Henry Hardman &quot;A Review of the possibility of dispersingmore Government work from London&quot; had identified some30, 000 posts which could be moved from the capital.    Theseproposals, however, would create administrative problems for some Departments;  and they would also fall short of the expectations entertained by the regions in this context.    Itwould therefore be desirable that as the next step the report should be published as a basis for discussion and consultationbefore the Government came to any final conclusions.Publication during the season of the annual Staff AssociationConferences   might be inexpedient;  and this implied that for practical purposes it must wait until after the WhitsuntideRecess at the end of May.    The subsequent process of consultation would necessarily take time;  and it was unlikelytherefore that decisions could be announced before the autumn.In discussion there was general agreement with, fc&amp;o procedure proposed by the Prime Minister.     The report should be released to National and Departmental Staff Sides shortly before publication;  and it should be accompanied by a notesetting it in its historical context and making it clear that itwas being published as a basis for discussion.    But subsequentconsultations should be based on certain general principlesindicated in paragraph 7 of CP(73) 57 and designed to ensurethat, without rejecting at this stage any of the possible courses of action proposed in the report, the Government would notnecessarily be committed to regarding all of them as equallyacceptable.In further discussion the following main points were made:-a.    Certain Departments, particularly the foreign and Commonwealth Office, the Home Office and theMinistry of Defence, would be liable to suffersignificant damage in terms of efficiency if theywere required to accept any further substantial measure of dispersal of senior policy-making staff.The same considerations might apply to the newManpower Services Agency.    It was for considerationhow far it might be possible, in these cases, to
dispense with detailed discussion of the proposals with the relevant St&amp;M Sida* by reaching prioragreement in principle that operational efficiencyrequired the staffs concerned to remain in or near london.b. In the case of the Ministry of Defence it was alsoarguable that the proposal to move a very largenumber of staff to Milton Keynes might adversely affect the nodal development of a relatively smallNew Town.    The alternative suggestion that the staffof the Ministry of Defence might be dispersed to scotland would, however, be open to even more serious objections on grounds of operational efficiency.c. On the other hand, the Government might be unwise to appear to make exceptions from therecommendations in the Hardman report, in a few cases, before the process of consultation had begun,since this would merely encourage expectations thatthe remainder of the report&apos;s proposals would beaccepted as they stood.    It might be preferabletherefore that all thm Governments final decisions should purport to result from the forthcomingprocess of discussion and consultation.d. Moreover, considerations of operational efficiency must be weighed against the regionalbenefits of dispersal which were discussed inC?(73) 59.    Even without further modification theproposals in the report would be liable to be regarded by the regions as disappointing;  and it was arguable,particularly in view of the continuing improvement inthe ease of travel and communication,that the numbers to be moved to the assisted areas should beJuacreasedrather than reduced.    Unless tha- Government wereprepared to set an example in this respect they could not expect private industry to be willing to disperse staff to the regions.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed, in principle, that the report should bepublished as a basis for public discussion and consultation withStaff Sides.    But the Lord Privy Seal should give furtherconsideration, in consultation with the Ministers, concerned,to the manner in which the proposals should be presented in ordeto take account of the points which had been made during the cabinets discussion.    It would be necessary to reconsider11
from the same point of view the draft statement, at annex to CP(73) 57, which it was suggested should accompanypublication of the report.    In the meantime the science research Council and the Natural Environment research council might reasonably proceed with their plans fordispersal to Swindon.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^summing up of their discussion and invited theLord Privy Seal, in consultation with theMinisters concerned, to proceed accordingly.12
DISCRIMINATION       7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theAGAINST Secretary of State for the Home Department (CP(73) 58)WOMEN discussing the Governments attitude towards two PrivateMember1 s Bills, in the House of Lords and the House ofCommons respectively, seeking to prevent discrimination against women.THE HOME SECRETARY said that the Bill which had recentlybeen published by a Select Committee of the House of Lords was open to criticism in a number of respects; and the Bill whichwas likely to emerge from the corresponding Select Committeein the House of Commons would probably suffer from similardeficiencies.    It was unlikely that the Government couldprevent the former Bill from completing all its stages in theUpper House.    But the Home and Social Affairs Committeehad concluded that it would be right to decline to grantexceptional facilities to assist either Bill to make progressin the House of Commons, with the result that neither would reach the Statute Book in the current Session.    It would not bepossible, however, for the Government to adopt this attitudeunless they undertook to introduce anti-discrimination legislation of their own in the following Session;  and the Committee had recommended that arrangements should now be made for thepreparation of proposals for this purpose.    It would also benecessary for the Government to indicate their intentions ingeneral terms in the House of Lords;  and the opportunity fora corresponding statement in the House of Commons would beprovided by the fact that the Select Committee of that House had invited the Secretary of State for Education and Science, theSecretary of State for Employment and himself to give evidence before them.    It would be preferable that this evidence should follow, rather than precede, the debate in the House of lords on 14 May; but, if this proved not to be convenient, theGovernments intentions would have to be initially disclosed tothe House of Commons Select Committee rather than during the debate in the House of Lords.In the course of a brief discussion there was general agreementwith these proposals.The Cabinet -Approved CP(73) 58,Cabinet Office3 May 1973 13

</content>
</cab>
