<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/146/0 images: 120-138</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION  OF  THE  ATTACHED   WESTERN  AND  GENERALREPORT No. II.South A. erica.The -reluctance of the Government of the South African Union to sanction the raising of natives lor combatant purposes illustrates the extreme sensitiveness of the South African white population on the question of the status of the native.Portuguese East Africa.The native rising in the Barue country may be serious in so far as it is symptomatic of a general restlessness of the natives under a regime which, is both feeble and oppressive. Stories of the headlong flight of Portuguese troops before German-led Askaris are, no doubt, spreading with due exaggeration all through Mozambique, and trouble on a large scale is not impossible, especially if remnants of the German forces make their way across the border.Greece.The Revolution in. Russia, the intervention of America, and the occupation of Zante have, no doubt, strengthened M. Veni/,elos&apos;s position. The latest pruuounce-ment of the aims of the Russian Government may, indeed, create a current in favour of the Entente, in Royalist as -well as in Venizelist circles, as the fear of Russians securing Constantinople, has boon one of the strongest motives influencing Greek feeling against the Allies. The situation, indeed, contains the possibilities of a real improvement in Greek affairs, if only the French can be kept quiet.Bulgaria.The factors referred to above are all bound to have a favourable effect on Bulgaria as well. But until the military predominance of the Central Powers begins to break down in the Balkan Peninsula itself, it is idle to imagine that Bulgaria will seriously contemplate a separate peace.The Jugoslav Question.The Appendix on the Jugoslav Question is a document worth studying carefully. The possibility of the Central Powers being enlightened enough to offer to satisfy the ideal of Jugoslav national unity within their own orbit cannot be wholly ignored. Their action in. Poland, though falling a long way short of satisfying Polish aspirations, has already shown a decided move away from the cruder Prussian ideals of direct conquest and suppression towards the more tolerant conception of a Middle Europe of diverse nationalities whose general military and economic policy is to be dominated by Germany.
German Internal Conditions.The German Emperor&apos;s promises of constitutional reform should be taken seriously as something more than a simple case of &quot; the devil was sick,&quot; or, as Bismarck put it, &quot; paying blackmail.&quot; The Imperial Government has for a long time past been tired of being alternately patronised and bullied by Prussian Junkerdom. The present war, though it lias justified the agrarian policy of (he Junkers, without which Germany would long ago have been starved out, has largely disposed of their claim to be alone capable of conducting 1&apos;rtissia&apos;s wars. J unkerdom was in fact defeated at the Marrie, and Germany&apos;s successes since have been the triumphs of the great industrial and engineering middle class, which has also supplied the overwhelming bulk of the officers of Germany&apos;s new armies. Hence the Emperor may have been quite content with the opportunity afforded by the Russian revolution and. President Wilsoids speech for shaking himself free of the Junker incubus. Aioreover, it is in the true German tradition that the initiative for political., as in a former generation for social, reforms should come &quot; from above,&quot; and that even the Social Democrats should accept that as the proper line of progress.Sweden.The evident anxiety of the new Government, known to be of very definitely pro-German views, to conclude with us the agreement left unsettled by their predecessors is, no doubt, mainly due to real apprehension as to the shortage of cereals. But it is not unreasonable to suspect a certain amount of manoeuvring with an eye to the opposition in Parliament, so that, if the negotiations break down, the Government may be able to claim that it did all it could lo come to terms with us, ami thus secure more support for an actively pro-German policy hereafter.Central America.The President of Guatemala is apparently thirsting to make use of the war in order to settle old scores with San Salvador. The Mexicans, too, seem spoiling Eor a fight, and the United States may soon have a hotter Balkans on their hands.L. S. A.12th April 1917.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]Printed for the War Cabinet. SECRET. For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.No. 11.   Week ending 11th April (night).Contents.Part I. British Empire- and Africa. Imperial Conference.Texts of Resolutions on Demobilisation, Military Equipment, Ordnance Personnel, and Trade Commissioners. Canada.Subscriptions to War Loan.   Provision of further troops for oversea.   Construction of motor boats. Australian Commonwealth.Nominations for Federal elections.   Naval escort for New Zealand transports.   Offer from Women&apos;s Service Corps. South Africa.Governments objection  to employment of natives as combatants.    Restrictions on exportation to Katanga.   Crisis in wool industry. Portuguese East Africa.Native revolt in Barue region.   Recruiting of carriers. German East AfricaFinancial estimates of occupied territory for 1917-18.    Delimitation of spheres of Protestant Missions.   Co-operation of Belgium in East African campaign. Gold Coast.Demands for timber.Part II. Foreign Affairs. France.Lack of co-operation in regard to tonnage difficulties. Italy.Report of impending German offensive. Belgium.Re-organisation of Relief Commission work. Greece.Independence Day ; no incidents.   The Allied Ministers and King Constantine.   The Allied controls.   General Sarrail and the currency.   M. Venizelos and his followers. Mount Athos.   The embroglio at Zante.   Movements of Italian troops. Bulgaria.Report from Washington concerning. Switzerland.Negotiations at Paris and Berne. German Internal Conditions.Wireless news and extracts from German Press. Holland.Grain ships for Holland to be released at Halifax.   Dutch Governments Note in regard to armed merchantmen.   Relations with Germany. Sweden.The Anglo-Swedish&apos; agreement.   The British ships in the Baltic.   Internal situation ; Socialist activities. Denmark.Relations with the United States, and with Germany. Spain.The iron ore regulations. Portugal.Relations with Great Britain.-. China.No immediate prospect of declaration of war.   Japanese Government inclined to hedge. A Salt Gabelle question..Japan.Desires to acquire enemy ships in China. Argentina.The embargo on wheat. Brazil.Requests guarantee for payment of debt owing by Germany to the State of Sao Paulo. Mexico.Signs of unrest and German intrigues. Central American Republics (Cuba, Panama, Costa Rica, San Domingo).Declarations of war ; and of neutrality. Guatemala.President fears attack by Mexico. United States.   Preparations for co-operation with the Allies. German Submarine Campaign. Peace Discussions. General.(33)2842-2   Pk 80-4/17 A
PART I. BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA.IMPERIAL CONFERENCE.In pursuance of the arrangement that the Secretary of. State should telegraph to the Australian Government the text of the Resolutions passed at the Imperial War Conference, the following Resolution dealing with the demobilisation of Dominion troops at the conclusion of the war has been communicated to the Commonwealth, viz. : .It was agreed that all Dominion Contingents in France with their equipment should start from a French or Belgian port as soon as possible, but arrangements will be made to give furlough for the purpose of visiting this country to individual soldiers desiring to do so.The Secretary of State has also telegraphed to Australia that the Imperial War Conference considered at two meetings a Memorandum by the Quartermaster-General dealing (inter alia) with Equipment and Orduance Stores, and the following Resolutions were passed, viz. : First. That this Conference, recognising the importance of assimilating as far as possible the military stores and equipment of the Imperial forces throughout the Empire, recommends that an expert Committee representative of the Military Authorities of the United Kingdom, the Dominions and India, be appointed as early as possible to consider the various patterns in use with a view to selecting standard patterns for general adoption as far as the special circumstances of each country admit.Second. This Conference is of opinion that it is desirable that the ordnance personnel of the military organisations of the Empire should as far as possible be trained on the same methods and according to the same principles, and that to secure this end selected officers of the ordnance service from all parts of the Empire should be attached for adequate periods to the Imperial Ordnance Department.The Prime Minister of the Commonwealth has further received intimation that on 4-th.April the following Resolution was passed : That the Imperial War Conference welcomes the proposed increase of the Board of Trade service of Trade Commissioners and its extension throughout the British. Empire in accordance with the recommendations of the Dominions Royal Commission, and recommends that the Governments concerned should co-operate so as to make that service as useful as possible to the Empire as a whole, especially for the promotion of inter-Imperial trade.CANADA.The total subscriptions to the War Loan amount, according to announcements in the Press, to 53,34-9,600Z., being about 23,000,000Z. in excess of the sum asked for.With regard to the provision of further troops for oversea service, the Dominion Government have intimated that the necessities connected with the supply of reinforcements and the demands of labour make it almost impossible to raise additional units. In order, however, to release men. who are at present training for the Expeditionary Force, it has been decided to enlist 50,000 men for home defence.In response to the Admiralty inquiry on the subject, the Dominion Government have telegraphed that 30 anti-submarine motor boats can be built for the Italian Government without causing delay in the completion, of the drifters now under construction. It is, however, pointed out that it would be necessary to obtain the motors and auxiliary machinery in the United. States.AUSTRALIAN COMMON WEALTH.The nomination of candidates for the forthcoming Federal Elections closed on 7th April, according to a Press telegram. It is also stated that seven Ministerialists, including Sir John Forrest, the Treasurer, and three supporters of the Opposition, have been returned unopposed.
The Australian naval authorities have been requested to - send H.M.A.S. &apos;&quot; Encounter &quot; to New Zealand, in order to escort transports of that Dominion to Sydney. On reaching that port, the Australian warship will then convoy hoth Australian and New Zealand transports to Fre mantle, where two separate convoys will be formed in order to proceed respectively via Colombo and the Cape.The Women&apos;s Service Corps have telegraphed from Sydney to Mr. Lloyd George offering the services of 500 efficient women to replace men for Army duties. The Prime Minister has sent a telegram expressing appreciation of this patriotic offer, but pointing out that it cannot be accepted as women in Great Britain have volunteered for the purpose in larger numbers than can be employed. He adds a suggestion that the women who have offered their services might take the place of fit men in Australia who could thus be freed for oversea service.SOUTH AFRICA.With reference to the wish of the Army Council to enlist natives of South Africa for service in the Artillery as combatants, the Union Government have replied that they consider this to be impracticable, and that they therefore regret they cannot agree to the suggestion. In the first place, Ministers consider that natives would not be prepared for Avarfare under European conditions without a much longer period of training and discipline than could be afforded. Again, an attempt to enlist natives for the fighting line would adversely affect recruiting for the Labour Contingent. Amongst the practical objections raised, from a South African standpoint, to the employment of natives in the manner suggested are (1) that they would not be under officers who were experienced in controlling them; (2) that it would be impossible to keep them iu closed compounds ; (3) that it would be dangerous to let them associate side by side with British soldiers wdio did not understand them. &apos;The Union Ministers point out that a motion condemning the employment of natives in any war capacity is a subject of debate in the House of Assembly. Those opposed even to the present arrangements relating to non-combatant service argue that military necessities may interfere with the control exercised by the officers appointed by the Union Government, and also with the system of housing and discipline, with the result that the natives may be open to the bad influences arising from free intercourse with Europeans. The reply Ministers have hitherto given has been based on the necessities of the Empire and the wish of the natives themselves to help, but the Union Government feel that they would be placed in a very difficult situation if they agreed to recruit natives for active service, as it would be impossible to maintain the safeguards that are at present imposed with regard to the Labour Contingent.The authorities of the Belgian Congo have made representations that the industrial work of Katanga has been jeopardised by the restrictions upon exportation of machines and spare parts from the Union. As the Ministry of Munitions are most anxious to secure the transport of Katanga copper, the Secretary of State has conve37ed the representations to the Union Government, and has asked to be informed regarding the refusal of export licences for Katanga railway plant.The Union Minister of Finance (Mr. Burton) has pointed out that a serious crisis is threatened in the wool industry. As the wool buyers received no intimation that shipping was to be stopped, they continued to carry out orders from England. There is now at the ports 2,500,OOOL worth of wool awaiting shipment in accordance with orders, and if the delay in transport should cause a sale at low prices the banks and the buyers will be severely hit. The Governor-General has therefore inquired wdiether more maize is required, as, if not, it is suggested that wool could be carried in those portions of the ships which are now allocated to maize.PORTUGUESE  EAST AFRICA.With regard to the native rising in the Barue region (between the Zambesi and the Southern Rhodesian frontier) the British Consul at Lorenzo Marques reports that three columns are being sent to operate from Tete, Sena, and Gorogoza, but that there is much difficulty in obtaining carriers. Native reports indicate that the revolt may spread, as much unrest prevails in Gaza and Maputo districts owing to the commandeering of natives by the Portuguese as soldiers and carriers.As to the recruiting of carriers, the British Consul asks that the Witwatersrand Native Labour Association should be used as a British recruiting agency north of latitude 220 south.
PART II.-FOREIGN AFFAIRS.FRANCE.Lord Bertie has been instructed to draw the attention of the French Government to the fact that the great shipping difficulties which beset the operations of the-Allies are aggravated by the French. Governments lack of co-operation, both in the use of tonnage and in their independent measures for purchasing and chartering neutral ships. The effect of these measures is being seriously felt in several directions, and notably in the reduction of the number of Spanish ships available for the carriage of iron ore to the United Kingdom. His Majesty&apos;s Government therefore desire that the whole shipping problem should be reconsidered as a matter of urgency, and particularly the Clementel agreement of December last. It is pro-posed that the question shordd be fully discussed by the Shipping Controller with M. Clementel and M. Guernier as soon as possible.ITALY.According to confidential information from Polish sources, forwarded through Berne, the Germans are. preparing for a vigorous offensive against Italy. It is-reported that Mackensen has left the Roumanian front for this purpose ; also that the main object of the submarine campaign is to isolate Italy.* Similar telegrams have been despatched to the Governors of the Gambia and Sierra Leone and the Governor-General of NigeriaGERMAN EAST AFRICA.The Administrator of the occupied territory states that the estimated revenue for 1917-18 amounts to 371,000L, which includes the surplus of assets for-1916-17,. amounting to 45,000Z.The main items which go to make up the above figure are :   Customs (including Dar-es-Salaam) 150,000Taxes      - - - - - - -   128,000Railway   ------ -     33,000The estimated expenditure amounts to 215,000Z.The Administrator further reports that the following delimitation of spheres has been arranged tentatively after consultation with the Protestant Missions, viz. : Church Missionary Society - -  Kilimanjaro and neighbourhood, and also-area of Central Railway from Kiliman-tinde to Dar-es-Salaam. Universities Mission        - - -   Wilhelmstal and Tanga area.United Free Church Mission (from Nyasa-  District to north-west, north and north-land), and perhaps Church of Scotland      east of Lake Nyasa. Mission.&apos;London Missionary Society - -  Bismarckburg district.The concurrence of the Secretary of State is sought in respect of the above-scheme.Owing to the critical stage reached in the campaign in East Africa, the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs has urgently requested that Belgian representatives-should he sent to London at once to discuss the future co-operation of Belgium.GOLD COAST-*.The Secretary of State has informed the Governor that the demands for timber from England should be reduced to the utmost limit. He has asked for information; as to the possibility of using local timber.
BELGIUM.With a view to the reorganisation of the Relief Commission&apos;s executive, necessitated by the withdrawal of the American delegates, Sir W. Townley has been instructed to make certain suggestions to the Spanish Minister at Brussels and to the Netherland Government. It is proposed that the existing Commission for relief in Belgium, managed by its present American directors, should continue to be responsible for the delivery of supplies to the various terminals in Belgium and- Northern. France, handing them over to the Comite National and the Comite Francais respectively. The American organisation would maintain their shipping and accounting office at Brussels, and anticipate no difficulty in continuing their Belgium staff there. For the purposes of protecting the relief work of the Commission and discharging its international functions, it is proposed that a new Committee be established, under the patronage of the King of Spain and the Queen of Holland, whose respective diplomatic representatives at Brussels, London, Paris and Berlin would jointly discharge the duties of that patronage. It is suggested that this Committee should be directed as to its executive by two chairmen, one Spanish and one Dutch, who would select their staff of local, representatives from both nationalities. By this arrangement the neutral governments -would be relieved of heavy financial responsibilities towards the Allied Governments.With reference to the torpedoeing of the Relief Ship &quot;Trevier &quot; off Scheveningen, at a distance of 20 miles from the Dutch coast, a German official wireless of the 9th instant asserts that the vessel was sunk within the barred zone, and adds that if &quot; Cax^tains will not avoid that zone, it matters not for whose service or for what purpose they may be running.&quot;GREECE.Independence Day at Athens was celebrated without disturbance of the.peace. Acting under instructions, His Majesty&apos;s Minister had solemnly warned the Prime Minister that the members of the Government would be held personally responsible for any renewed attacks upon Venizelists ; a communique was published by the Govern]))ent on the 6th giving strict orders for the maintenance of law and order. The official Te Deum ceremony (at which the Allied representatives were not present) passed off without incident. Reuters&apos; telegram recording the event was only passed by the Censor on condition that it described, the Xing as having been &quot; enthusiastically acclaimed.&quot;   Sir F. Elliot has no reason to apprehend further trouble.In view of the unconstitutional behaviour of King Constant!ne and to prevent his position being enhanced in the eyes of his people, the French Government have proposed that each of the Allied Ministers at Athens should be instructed not to visit the King without reference to his Government, who would then consult the Allied Governments. Without going so far, His Majesty&apos;s Government directed . Sir F. Elliot to restrict as much as possible his personal interviews with King Constantino. In reply, Sir F. Elliot observed that (with the &quot;exception of one visit by the Italian Minister on 13th December), none of the Allied Ministers had seen the King since the beginning of December. It subsequently transpired that the French Governments communication referred to visits which took place last autumn.As the chief part of the Military Control Commissioits duties will be concluded, and the demands of the Allies satisfied, -when the surrendered rifles in Morea have been counted, Sir F. Elliot with, the concurrence of his Russian and Italian colleagues now suggests the re-establishment of the Allied. Controls, together with the formation of their joint Board, under the conditions which have been approved by all. except the French Government (vide Report No. 6).The National Banlts offer to supply- Salonika with, notes to the amount of 50 million drachmas remains in abeyance, as General Sarrail declines to give the necessary guarantee for their safe custody. In the meanwhile he has drafted a Decree, fixing the local exchange rate for French paper at the same rate as that prevailing between Paris and New York, intimating that any bank- which offers a lower rate will be closed, and that, if any difficulties arise, French army payments will be made by vouchers redeemable at the end of the war. The French Minister has undertaken to endeavour to persuade General Sarrail to make the rate of exchange-more elastic.The Allied Governments have agreed, to the appointment of a delegate of the Provisional Government to prepare statements of claims on behalf&apos; of parties having no direct representative on the Indemnities Commission.28-12- 2 b
In a recent conversation with Lord Granville, M. Venizelos stated that his adherents are becoming more and more imbued with Republican sentiments, which he himself seems disposed to encourage. A section of his followers, he said, might accept the abdication of King Constantino in favour of the Crown Prince ; but the whole country, even the strongest Republicans, would joyfully accept an English Prince as their King.... The Salonika Press published on 7th April the text of a resolution, said to have &quot;been passed on 25th March by Venizelist monks and laymen at Mount Atlios, announcing their adherence to the Provisional Government and the deposition of King Cons tan tine. Lord Granville connects their action with the activities of the Russian Lieutenant mentioned in last week&apos;s Report; his French colleague maintains, however, that General Sarrail is determined not to permit any political changes during the military occupation.Zante is once more under the administration of Venizelists, the French authorities having now reinstated, the representatives of the Provisional Government who were suppressed by Admiral Gauchet on the 25th March. At the same time they effected the arrest of the local Royalist authorities, police force, and a number of reservists. His Majesty&apos;s Vice-Consul at Zante, reporting the facts on the 5th instant, stated that perfect tranquillity prevailed. On the 8th, Lord Granville was informed that M. Arenizelos had ordered the Greek gunboat &quot; Thetis &quot; to escort members of the Provisional Government and Police to take over Zaute &quot;and. other islands.&quot; Lord Granville enquired whether His Majesty&apos;s Government would authorise the expedition and received, a reply in the affirmative (10th April). M. Venizelos explained that he had ordered it in the first instance without reference to the Allied Ministers at Salonika because he understood from his representatives in London and. Paris that the Allied Governments would not object, though they might prefer not to be consulted in advance. He has reason to anticipate similar risings in Ithaca and Cephalonia, partly because shipowners of the islands desire to escape the new tax imposed by the Greek Government on shipping. Since the decision taken by the Powers in regard to Zante, lie no longer discourages such risings, but rather encourages them, stipulating at the same time that he can do nothing to assist them. Subsequently (on the 9th). Sir F. Elliot telegraphed asking for instructions as to the reply which he should make to a protest which, the Greek Government were preparing on the subject ; incidentally he observed that in dispossessing the Royalist Authorities at Zante for the second time, the French Naval Authorities would, appear to have gone too far, just as they did before in re-establishing them. The Greek Governments formal protest was received, on the 10th.The Venizelist agent in London has officially requested His Majesty&apos;s Government to support the endeavours being made by the Venizelist Mission in the United States to secure recognition, at Washington for the Provisional Government. His Majesty&apos;s Government are inclined to support this request ; it has been, referred for the opinion of the French Government and of His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington.His Majesty\s Vice-Consul at Janina reports that the movements of Italian troops appear to indicate an intention to occupy the Calamas line, and that the local population are genuinely perturbed at the prospect. Sir F. Elliot states, on the other hand, that the Italian Minister at Athens is opposed, to this military advance, and believes that he has been able to prevent it. (The Calamas line runs from the neighbourhood of Konitza in a south-westerly direction to a point on the coast opposite Corfu.)BULGARIA.The Bulgarian Minister at Washington has informed the Secretary of State that he has hopes of being able to persuade his Government not to break off relations with the United States. The Secretary of State has great confidence in the influence for good of the pupils of Robert College&apos;5&quot;; he is making every effort to induce the Bulgarian Government to withdraw from the war and has hopes also that the Turks may be persuaded to throw off the German yoke.* The American College on the Bosporus, where so many of Balgarias leading men of the oldergeneration were educated.
SWITZERLAND.The Rationing Commission has concluded its sittings at Paris and the Swiss delegates have returned home. Subject to the approval of the Federal Government, they have accepted the various modifications of rations recommended by the -Commission.   The cattle question is reserved for further discussion.With reference to M. Denys CoohhPs impending negotiations at Berne (vide fast Report), His Majesty&apos;s Government have expressed the hope that the Italian Government may be willing to postpone the conclusion of their separate arrangements in regard to supply of Swiss timber until after Al. CqchirPs visit, and suggest that it might assist him if the Italian delegate at Berne were authorised to negotiate this question in consultation with him.GERMAN  INTERNAL CONDITIONS.A &quot;German official wireless of nth. April, states that &quot;Mr. Wilson&apos;.s address to &quot;Congress is generally interpreted to mean that the President attaches more importance to the question of &quot;freeing the German people &quot; than to the submarine campaign. The Berlin correspondent of the Hearst Press observes that &quot; there is no indication &quot;that the President has driven a wedge between the people and the Government. &quot; Tlie immediately observable effect of his speech has been on the one hand to give &quot; an impetus to the proposed liberalising reform and on the other to shake the people &quot;&quot; out of their complacent fatalism, and galvanise them into renewed determination.&quot; The same correspondent in another message states that, in placing the German Government, institutions and people on the same level, as those of Russia, the President has aroused the deepest indignation.The &quot; Vorwarts &quot; of the 5th observes : &quot; We must remember that at some time, &quot;and it may be earl)-, a Peace Conference will assemble on which we shall desire &quot; America to sit with our adversaries. On the whole, it is a situation to be met with &quot; quietness ami presence of mind.&quot;The &quot; Kolnische Zeituug&quot; announces that the Bill for Prussian electoral, reform will probably be introduced immediately after Easter. An official wireless&apos;of the 9th instant says that the Cabinet has been directed to draft this Bill, for submission to the Emperor, upon lines which shall, recognise His Majesty&apos;s firm belief that, &quot; after the gigantic work performed by the whole people during this terrible war, there is no more place in Prussia for a class franchise.&quot; The Emperor endorses the principles of political reform enunciated by the Chancellor and authorises all necessary preparations to be made, in order that constitutional reform may bo carried out so soon as the soldiers return from the field. Nevertheless there are many indications in the Press of scepticism and of a desire for more immediate action, and signs of unrest among the Socialists. Concerning the latter, His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington states that the United. States Government hope that the war may eventually be concluded as the result of a Socialist revolt against the Prussian regime.HOLLAND.With reference to the political situation and to Sir W. Townley&apos;s views thereon as stated in last week&apos;s Report, His Majesty s Government have decided, as &quot;an indication of their good will and of their desire for friendly relations -with Holland, to clear the Dutch foodships at Halifax for Dutch ports, without requiring them to call at Kirkwall, as has already been done in the case of their vessels carrying fertilisers and fodder. In return for this spontaneous concession, Sir W. Townley has been instructed to request the Netherlands Government to publish a communique stating definitely that, in their communique of 29th March, it was not their intention to suggest that the British Government are primarily responsible for the shortage of food in Holland. His majesty&apos;s Government also expect that the Netherlands Government should take all possible steps to re-establish the freedom of the seas by encouraging their mercantile marine to resume trading.The Dutch Governmenfs Note, maintaining their refusal to admit armed merchant-men to their ports, disclaims any unfriendly feelings towards Great Britain and. insists that their policy of exclusion is based on fundamental, principles of neutrality. The rule .adopted in this matter by the Netherland Government in August 1914- was nbtihed to all belligerents, and to modify it at the request of any one of them would not only be an act of partiality, but would be ojrposed to the procedure advocated by
1 he British delegates at the Second Peace Conference at the Hague, who insisted that; a neutral Government can only modify it rules of neutrality during a war in order to-make them more rigorous.The Dutch -Governments Note to Germany, declining to release the interned. German submarines, was presented on 2nd April.   The Minister for Foreign Affairs,, though anxious as to the nature of the impending reply, does not anticipate an ultimatum.   He informed His  Majesty&apos;s Minister on the 7th that, in  any events-Holland will not yield the point and is prepared for all eventualities.SWEDEN.- Referring to the instructions recently conveyed to him by His - Majesty&apos;s-Government on the subject of the Anglo-Swedish draft, agreement, Sir E. Howard submits his opinion that, in view of the importance of seeming the release of British shipping from the Baltic, it is inadvisable to take any steps which might lead the Swedish Government to abandon their present amenable attitude. In any case, he holds that it would, be best to allow them to state their wishes with regard to modification of the draft agreement. As regards the transit trade to Russia, he suggests that the ideal solution, of this question would be for the United States to declare that no export of commodities to Sweden will be allowed unless the Swedish Government allow this transit trade to be operated at its full capacity.&apos; . -The Minister for Foreign Affairs has communicated to Sir E. Howard a memo-random of the terms which the Swedish Government are willing to make with regard to the questions outstanding with Great Britain. They are prepared to allow the passage through the Kogrund Channel of a &quot;considerable number&quot; of the ships now lying in the, Baltic under certain conditions, e.g., they would be required to leave at stated intervals and in ballast. In return for this arrangement, they would expect facilities for a specified number of Swedish grain ships. As to the resumption of general traffic between Sweden and the United Kingdom, the Government regard the matter as dependent upon the initiative of shipowners and beyond their competence. Sir E. Howard is of opinion that the shortage of cereals is sufficiently acute to compel the Swedish authorities to come to some amicable arrangement.- The German Minister at Stockholm, who until lately was wont to say that his Government would never consent, to the passage of British and Allied vessels through the Kogrund Channel, has apparently been persuaded by the King of Sweden to agree to it, as the only possible means of averting a very serious situation. His Majesty&apos;s Government concur in Sir E. Howarcfs opinion that the present attitude of the Swedish Government affords a basis for negotiations, on condition that all the vessels detained in the Baltic are released, and that they be allowed to carry cargoes of timber. At the same time the Swedish Government must be given to understand that, in the present general shortage of food supplies, it is not possible to guarantee to them any fixed quantity of: cereals within a given time.Discussing the effect on Sweden of the United. States&apos; entry into the Avar, His Majesty&apos;s Minister considers that although the present Ministry is in sentiment more pro-German than the last, there is less danger than before of a rupture with Russia. The main concern of the Government is to secure a regular supply of foodstuffs and raw materials, for which they are dependent on America. There is much discontent throughout the country, and any attempt to make common cause with Germany would-mean, civil war. The activities of the Socialists at Stockholm are also giving the Government cause for uneasiness. Revolutionary placards have been posted in one industrial quarter of the city ; strikes are increasing, and there are other s,ymptoms of social and economic unrest. Sir E. Howard reports that the large meeting held under the presidency of the Mayor on 6th. April, ostensibly to celebrate the Russian xevolution, was to a very great extent directed against, the present regime in Sweden.DENMARK,According to a German wireless message, America&apos;s decision to enter into the Avar has thrown a gloom over Denmark-. The Danes are represented as oppressed by the fear that a great tightening of the blockade of Scandinavia is impending. &quot; Some say that no Scandinavian will risk the sending of ships if America enters the Avar. Many perceive, however, that &quot;under such conditions Scandinavia may be &quot; forced, to increase her trading with Germany, and become a valuable source of &quot; supplies for that country.   A. similar state of affairs is likely to be produced in
&quot; Holland. The prospect of America&apos;s participation in the war lias not created as &quot; ranch joy in Allied circles as might have been expected.&quot; The propagandist in this instance is evidently endeavouring to discount the fact, already becoming as apparent in Denmark as it is in Sweden, that the amount of pressure which, the Allies, including America, can &quot;bring to bear by the restriction of necessary imports must compel, the Scandinavian countries, whatever their sentiments, to pay less heed to the German point of view. Sir R. Paget, dismissing the possibility of a German invasion of Denmark, does not consider it more probable now than at: any other:: period of the war. lie points out, however, that the continued supply of fertilisers and fodder to Denmark must, naturally make -Jutland more desirable in German eyes than would otherwise be the case. in. another despatch, he suggests that, should it be found necessary for the Allies to apply further pressure to prevent the export of Danish produce to Germany, a threat by America to cut oft supplies of absolute necessaries (such as oil) might prove effective.SPAIN.The negotiations in. London between His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Marquis de Cortina proceeded satisfactorily until the 11th April, and a draft agreement was then concluded for signature covering the various trading questions at issue, and especially those which refer to the traffic in coal and iron ore. His Majesty&apos;.s Govern-meht propose to license and transport 150,000 tons of coal per month to Spain, in return for the unrestricted export of iron, ore, a free hand in the matter of time-chartering Spanish shipping, and. other facilities. The agreement deals also with the trade in potatoes, oranges, wines, and other commodities. On the 11th, however, the Marquis de Cortina announced that he would not be able to sign, as arranged, instructions having been given, him to return to Madrid for further consultation. His Majesty&apos;s representative at Madrid has been instructed to express the extreme surprise of His Majesty&apos;s Government at this sudden change of front and the hope that the Marquis de Cortina may be instructed to sign the agreement. The Spanish Press reports that a Governmental crisis is imminent.Meanwhile, despite these negotiations and the assurances given that the new regulation concerning iron ore shipments would not be applied to vessels which had left England, before the 24th of March, a considerable number of such ships have been vexatiously held up in Spanish ports. After ceaseless representations His Majesty&apos;s representative at Madrid, was able to report on the 8th that all the ships in question had finally7 been allowed to load except four at Almeria for which permission was expected. He attributes the action of the Spanish authorities to the persistently unreasonable attitude of the Minister of Finance, who exercises great influence, over the Minister for Foreign Affairs.PORTUGAL.Oh the 5th instant the President of the Republic took occasion to express to His Majesty&apos;s Minister at considerable length his views on the present relations between Great Britain and Portugal. While, recognising the fact that repeated appeals for money had been made to the British Government in a manner derogatory to the dignity of his country, he laid stress on the military and other burdens which Portugal has accepted as her contribution, to the cause of the Allies. He suggested that EnglancPs loan of 2,000,0007. last year could hardly be regarded as adequate recognition of the hardships and sacrifices which the Portuguese people are enduring and must continue to endure, or that it fulfils the new assurances of goodwill between the two countries given by Great Britain when Portugal threw in her lot with the Allies. He referred also to the misunderstandings that had arisen in regard to the use of the enemy ships, originally designated for employment in the Portuguese shipping trade but eventually diverted therefrom by the exigencies of the military situation and the submarine campaign.. Portugal, he concluded, asks for financial aid from England, not as a beggar but as a friend and an Ally.The Portuguese government have requested Pfis Majesty&apos;s&apos; Government&apos;:s reconsideration of the recent decision of His Majesty&apos;s Secretary of State for War, to the effect that, owing to the lack of transports, it is not possible to arrange for the carrying of additional Portuguese troops to France. The Portuguese Minister for War has pointed out that his proposal to convert the Expeditionary Force into an Army Corps had been fully discussed with General Barnardiston, and that to suspend2S42-2 C
the operation now would create material losses and a bad moral effect. The additional transport required involves only two extra voyages of the ships now employed.CHINA.Mr. Alston telegraphed on 4th April that the Premier had suggested to the Japanese Minister that it would greatly strengthen his hands in pressing the President and Cabinet to declare war against Germany, if the Allies would convey their proposals to China in the form of a definite offer. His Majesty&apos;s Government,&apos; being of the same opinion, and believing the Japanese Government to be in general agreement with them as to the nature of the offer to be made, instructed Sir C. Greene to enquire whether they would join in representations to the French, Russian, and Italian Governments so as to secure united action, based on a disinterested and generous recognition of China&apos;s needs and difficulties. On the 0th instant, however, Sir G. Greene was informed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs at Tokio that the Japanese Government (while concurring in the proposal to address the Russian, French, and Italian Governments in the sense desired), had come to the conclusion that it is no longer advisable to force the Premier&apos;s hand by pressing him to declare war. They advise marking time for the present, so as to give the Premier an opportunity of strengthening his position, and of allowing America&apos;s declaration of war to produce its effect in China. Certain information conveyed by the special Envoy from China (Wang Ta-hsieh) has led the Japanese Government to the conclusion that the internal political situation in iChina is more difficult than was supposed. Thus, Mr. Alston observes, the question of China&apos;s participation in the Avar remains primarily a matter of internal politics. These, in their turn, are greatly influenced by financial considerations, in which the Foreign Powers are all more or less involved.Discussing the Japanese Governments proposal to mark time, and their professed -anxiety for the. premier&apos;s difficult position, Mr. Alston expresses the belief that their change of policy is to some extent due to the fact that the Japanese Government have committed themselves to certain arrangements with the Premier and his party, with a-view to the maintenance of Japanese predominance, and that the entrance of the United States into the war may have led them to doubt the ultimate benefits of these arrangements and even their feasibility.Anticipating the probable dismissal, of the German Deputy Director-General of the Salt Gabelle, and understanding that the Chinese Government propose to abolish, the post, the French. Minister at Peking has informed Mr. Alston that he intends to claim, it for the French official, next in rank to the German Deputy Director-General in the administration. Both Mr. Alston and Sir R. Dane (the Director-General.) take strong objection to this proposal, for reasons stated, and support the Chinese in their desire to abolish the post. As a consequence of the generally unreasonable attitude displayed by the French Minister, a leading article in the &quot;Peking Gazette&quot; of 6th April announced that the Chinese Government had informed the French Government that he is no longer persona grata. For the publication of this article the Minister for Foreign Affairs apologised in writing to the French Minister on- the following day.JAPAN.Sir C. Greene has received a note from the Japanese Government (10th April) stating that certain Japanese shipping firms have long, wished to purchase the enemy vessels lying in Eastern ports ; the ex post facto announcement that His Majesty&apos;s Government have made an offer to China for the purchase of these vessels has therefore come as an unpleasant surprise. The Japanese Government, notiug the expressed intention of the British Government to reconsider the allocation of the ships in question after purchase, intimate that they expect to be consulted in regard thereto.ARGENTINA.Upon the representations of His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Buenos Aires, the President has ordered, a fresh investigation of the present stock and rate of consumption of wheat in the Republic, and Sir R. Tower believes that the Argentine Government, being well disposed, will endeavour so to modify their embargo on. export as to meet Great Britain&apos;,? requirements. It is expected that the Governments enquiries will be completed in the course of a few days. Sir R. Tower does not think that any financial inducements by enemy firms have, influenced the Government in prohibiting
&quot;the export of wheat, but admits the possibility of: enemy inspiration in. regard to erroneous and pessimistic returns of shortage. He has been directed, to request the Argentine Government to give permission, as a &apos;matter of great urgency, for the export to the Allies of at least 190,000 tons, for which freight is coming forward, the -amount to be replaced, if necessary, in the autumn by Australian-wheat.BRAZIL.The Minister for Foreign Affairs informed Sir A. Feel on the 7th instant that if the Brazilian Government were assured that Great Britain would guarantee the amount owing to the State of Sao Paulo fry the German Government (between six and. seven millions sterling),,a rupture/of relations with German)&apos;would follow. He asked for an immediate answer, as on. it the Brazilian Governments decision would depend. In reply, Sir A. Peel was directed (9th April) to inquire whether, in the event of the German ships in Brazilian ports being serviceable, the Brazilian Government would, hand them over to us at a fair valuation, to be paid for in cash, and tire amount deducted from the German debt to Sao Baulo, on the understanding that His Majesty&apos;s Government would guarantee the payment of the remainder of the debt at the end of the war.Late on the 9th, Sir A. heel was informed by a member of the Chamber of Deputies that although the President was very anxious not to sever relations with Germany, public opinion was too strong for him and he would be compelled to hand the German Minister his passports. The President was also strongly opposed to the -seizure of the German ships.The Brazilian Government have decided to requisition a number of privately-owned Brazilian, ships, and Sir A. Beel understands that they propose to resume the service to Europe by Government-owned vessels.MEXICO1.Information received by the Admiralty confirms the reports of German attempts to -establish a powerful wireless station in Mexico. Tbey are at present busy with, the receiving station and will, probably be able before long to receive messages from Xauen. Apparatus for the sending of messages is being sent to Mexico from the United States ; it is hoped that it may be intercepted, there.Air. Thurstan reports that the latest sub-divisions and activities of political factions in Mexico have produced a situation full of uncertainty and danger, very favourable to German intrigues. Carra-nza finds himself confronted, by the truculent independence of General. Ohregoii, who has arrested and declines to release the proprietor of the newspaper &quot; Universal,&quot; one Palavicini, a protege and adviser of the President. It is doubtful which side Gonzalez will take. Under these conditions, Mr. Thurstan regards it as probable that the Germans may create grave internal, trouble. Any declaration of neutrality by President Carranza would be open to suspicion.In another despatch, His Majesty&apos;s Minister states that Sen or Carranza is now completely in the hands of the military party and the great majority of the new Congress are not only military but irresponsible extremists. The Legation has received information that the military party are planning to seize the Tehuantepec Railway and the Eagle Oil Company&apos;s refineries.CUBA.On the 7th April the President of the Republic signed the resolution unanimously approved by both houses of Congress, declaring the existence of a state of war between. Cuba and Germany. Mr. Leech suggests the advisability of His Majesty&apos;s Government sending an expression of their warm appreciation of the strategical and political importance of this step.PANAMA.The proclamation issued by the President on the Sth declares that in a conflict between the United States and Germany, it is impossible for Panama to remain neutral. The Government of the Republic oiler energetic co-operation in defence of the Panama Canal.Censorship over the cable offices at Panama and Colon has been established by the United States Government.
COSTA RICA,The Government have declared that they will observe benevolent neutrality: towards the Allies, and will keep watch, in their interests, over the coast.SAN DOMING 0.Mr. Fisher reports that the entry of the United States into the war will not modify the attitude of neutrality hitherto maintained by the Government of San Domingo.GUATEMALA.The President of the Republic informed the United States Minister on the Sth instant that, the Guatemalan Government had decided to sever relations with Germany so soon as they had received official information, of the United States&apos; declaration of war. In that event, they would ask for material support against the hostile action which they believe Mexico is about to take, assisted possibly by San Salvador. The President asserts that the Mexicans intend to attack British Honduras as well as Guatemala; one of his spies has reported that they have a force of 180 men on the frontier in readiness to co-operate with a body of Germans in a coupmclemai&apos;n on British Honduras. Mr. Young finds it difficult to believe that a rupture of relations between Guatemala and Germany would be the signal for an attack on the Republic by its neighbours, and suggests that the Presidents chief object is to make sure of military assistance from the United States, and also from Great Britain, against Mexico. To render his measures of surveillance more effective, he is about to declare a state of siege, which will mean the arrest of many-Mexicans, and may precipitate trouble. In the opinion of the authorities at Washington, founded on. recent inform a-lion, there is no immediate probability of an attack by Mexico on her neighbours.On 11th April Mr. Young reported that the Presidents courage had failed hint and that he would consult the United. States Government before severing relations with Germany.UNITED  STATES.The war Resolution passed by Congress was signed by the President on the afternoon of 7th April. On the previous day, the United States authorities had. seized all German ships in American ports, including Hawaii and the Philippines, and had removed their crews.   The Austrian ships were seized on the Oth.German translations of the Presidents message to Congress have been sent to the front for distribution by aeroplane over the German trenches and in Germany.Since the entry of the United States into the war, the attention of His Majesty&apos;s Government has been closely directed towards establishing immediate and active co-operation between America and the Allies, for the restriction of enemy trade, the tightening of the blockade against the Central Powers, and the alleviation of the tonnage difficulties produced by Germany&apos;s submarine warfare. His Majesty&apos;s Government are of opinion that by means of such co-operation, and by the exercise of legitimate and reasonable pressure, it should now be possible to force neutral bankers both in America and Europe, wherever desirable, to desist from operations advantageous to the enemy ; Sir G. Spring Pice has accordingly been instructed to sound the American authorities and banks as to their readiness to consult as to the principle of this line of action. In the meantime, suggestions have been made (Oth April) to the United States -Embassy in London as to the steps immediately desirable in reference to banking transactions in America, eg , strict censorship of. all. financial operations conducted by cable, wireless, or post, restriction of dealings in enemy securities, Ac.As a matter arising out of the whole question of America&apos;s co-operation in blockade matters, His Majesty&apos;s Government have drawn the attention of the British Ministers in Scandinavia and Holland to the fact that such action as it has hitherto been possible to take in restricting oil supplies to &quot;objectionable &quot; industries has been weakened in neutral countries by the consideration that these supplies were chiefly of neutral origin. This consideration becomes greatly modified, by America^ participation in the war and His Majesty&apos;s Government therefore are of opinion that it should be possible, especially in Scandinavia, to exercise in the matter of oil a form of pressure similar to that applied in regard to coal, thus securing a further restriction of exports to enemy countries and additional supplies for the Allies. His Majesty&apos;s Ministers have been called upon to express their views on this subject and on the probable local results of the pressure proposed.
In. compliance with the urgent representations of the United States Ambassador in London, a verbal assurance was given by Lord Robert Cecil on 3rd April, that the British Governments Statutory List for the United States would be withdrawn so soon as the United States Government had declared war. In a confirmatory letter addressed to Mr. Rage after the declaration of war, His Majesty&apos;s Government state that they were content to rely upon the enforcement of the laws of the United States against trading with the enemy. At the same time the hope was expressed that before making any public announcement of the withdrawal of the Statutory List, the American Government would put in force certain specified measures of a precautionary nature.A despatch from. Sir C. Spring Rice on IOth April reports that the State Department are fully alive to the. gravity of the situation, in Mexico ; they have lost all confidence in Carrauza, but are prepared, to back another revolutionary movement before resorting to intervention. They recognise that the dangers with which German activities are threatening the oil-fields are increased by the fact that American men-of-war as belligerents have no longer a legal, right to remain in Mexican ports.Various arrangements and negotiations between Great Britain and the United States in regard to shipping matters are dealt with under the next heading.GERMAN SUBMARINE CA.MPAIGN.The total tonnage of vessels laid, up in the Baltic is 210,000 tons. None of the vessels are of too deep a draught to prevent them from passing out within the limits of territorial waters.Sir M. Eindlay telegraphs (7th April) that the Norwegian Government are evidently nervous as to the possible restriction of imports from the United States, especially as regards oil, cereals, meat, and copper. In his opinion, if it be decided, by means of such pressure, to stop alJ further supplies passing from Norway to Germany, America would be morally bound to guarantee Norway against attack -from the sea and air, and to establish a naval base in Norway for that purpose.As a concession to the Norwegian G-overnment and shipowners, His Majesty&apos;s Government have authorised. Sir M. Find lay to state that Norwegian tonnage requisitioned (or time-chartered) by the British authorities will not be employed in the Anglo-Norwegian trade, but will be replaced in that trade by bond fide British ships ; also, that Norwegian owners may place contracts in Great Britain for ships (to be delivered after the war) wherewith to -replace vessels destroyed while under reqtusition.For the general guidance of shipowners in Scandinavia and Holland, His Majesty&apos;s representatives in these countries have been notified (9th April) that His Majesty&apos;s Government do not propose to grant facilities for vessels to carry cargoes for destinations other than, that of the country to which, the vessel belongs. - This regulation has been made with particular reference to the trade of Denmark and Sweden in Norwegian bottoms.Danish shipowners, referring to their losses of tonnage on the Bergen route, point out that all the vessels recently torpedoed have been lost on the voyage jrom the United Kingdom, and they complain that their captains receive no sailing directions when leaving England.Anticipating the United. States&apos; formal declaration of war, His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment instructed Sir C. Spring Rice on the 4th instant to lay before the State Department the urgency of the tonnage. question and to express the hope that the United States Government might devote their greatest energies to rendering-immediate assistance in the provision of vessels, required for England, France, Italy and Russia. To facilitate concerted action in this, the most vital problem of the war, the services of Mr. Sparks, New York Manager of the Cunard Company, have been placed at the disposal of His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington and of the United States authorities. At the same time (5th April) the Foreign Oflice have communicated to the American. Ambassador in London a memorandum, setting forth the most urgent needs of the Allies and &quot;suggestions as to the measures by which the United States can most effectively contribute to lighten their difficulties. These suggestions include (1) the seizure of enemy ships and their employment at the -earliest moment on the important trade routes ; (2) the charter of neutral shipping, which might be transferred from the European trade to safer waters ; (3) the release of shipping from coastal or lake trade to work on the main lines of communication ; and, most important
of all (4) the rapid increase of shipbuilding to the extreme limits of possible production, not only during the present year, but also during next year.It has also been suggested to the American Government that they should assume control of the export and supply of American coal, on a system similar to that which has been applied in the case of British coal. Sir C. Spring Bice has been instructed to state that if some such system of control is adopted and effectively enforced, His Majest.y&apos;s Government will be quite prepared, having regard to the views expressed hy the United States Shipping Board, to consider favourably the suspension of bunkering conditions, as now applied to United States ships trading with South America. The direction ami supervision of American Marine Insurance are under discussion, together with, the possible regulation of the supplies of cereals and foodstuffs to neutral countries, and legislation on these subjects is impending.The policy of the United States Shipping Board appears to be inspired in certain directions by concern, for the protection and development of purely American interests rather than for the common cause of the Allies. His Majesty&apos;s Government have expressed their earnest hopes that the United States Government may suspend and reconsider their proposed amendment to the United States Shipping Act of 19.16, which would inevitably&apos; prevent the free employment of American tonnage to the best advantage. (By this amendment it is intended that no ship now building for foreign .account in the United States can be launched during the war, unless she be owned by an American Corporation and registered as American ; also, that if engaged on foreign trade, such vessels must be officered according to American laws and trade to or from an American port). In. this connection it is of interest to note that Mr. Denman,. President of the United States Shipping Board, has taken exception to the Ounard Company&apos;s purchase of wooden ships now building in. United States yards. On the ground that the United States Government are contemplating the purchase of all wooden ships available, he suggests that the Ounard Company- should refrain from competing in this market. Sir C. Spring-Rice observes that wooden ships are a hobby with Mr. Denman and that it might conduce to more amicable relations with the Shipping Board if the held were left free for him. He has authority- to spend a considerable amount of money- in buying wooden vessels and apparently is chagrined at being forestalled by the action of Mr. Sparks.PEACE DISCUSSIONS.Information has been received from a trustworthy- source that certain Swiss Socialists, headed by Hen- Grimm, are endeavouring to obtain from the German Government safe-conducts through Germany for a number of Russian socialists and anarchists resident in Switzerland. It is proposed that these men, advocates of international ism and of immediate peace with Germany, should, go to Russia, probably accompanied by spies and agents provocateurs of the German Government, and there start a peace campaign amongst the working classes and the troops at the front.On 6th April. Sir A&quot;. Townley reported that the Dutch Press had reproduced that-morning a statement published by the &quot; Yossische Zedong &quot; to the effect that peace negotiations were being opened through Austria-Hungary, not from the German but from the British side.    He was instructed to publish an official denial.GENERAL.On 6th April His Majesty&apos;s Minister at The Hague received through the Dutch authorities a vote verbalc of the German Foreign Office, together with a memorandum dealing with the alleged misuse of hospital ships by the Allies, and announcing- the German Governments intention to adopt measures of increased ruthlessness in the destruction of these vessels in the Mediterranean. The German Government assert, and. bring what they describe as evidence to prove, that the Allies&apos; military traffic is carried on to a great extent by means of hospital ships. Such vessels will, therefore, very7 shortly (vie) be treated as belligerents in Mediterranean waters, including the channel of approach left for Greece. The memorandum states, however, that hospital ships may- continue to use this channel, for the removal of sick and wounded from Salonika, under certain specified conditions. By these conditions, the port of embarkation would be at Kalatnata, in Morea (i.e., the wounded would have to be brought thither by railway from Salonika) ; the name of each vessel, with the time of its arrival at and departure from Kalamata and Gibraltar respectively,  must  be
APPENDIX.The JUgoslav Question in the Enemy Press.Iferr E. V. Zenker, a member of the independent Party in the Vienna Reichsrat, published in the &quot; Vossische Zeitung &quot; of 19th March an article entitled The Southern&apos;: Slavs : A Question for Mitteleuropa.This is the translation of the article : &quot; In the diplomatic notes and. in. the statements which have recently been&apos;made on . the occasion of the peace offer by the Central. Empires we hear precious little about the Jugoslav question,   in the answer given by the Entente Powers to President A\ilson&apos;s note reference is made, it is true, to the restoration of Serbia and Monte-negro, to the evacuation of these countries and to the reparations due to them ; but . not one word is said as to the idea being formed regarding the new situation in the -Balkans as it shoxdd be established among these variegated peoples who have their&apos; replica in the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy.   In his last speech President Wilson reserved the place of honour to the Polish question, without finding a single word to say about the Jugoslav question.&quot; This is a peculiarity one cannot help noticing, inasmuch as the Jugoslav question, in its restricted meaning, and this is the Serbo-Croatian question, was the pretext for the world war, and. to this day the Serbo-Croatian territories remain in the possession of the Central Empires and their Allies. One cannot suppose that on the enemy side it iras intended to omit this question or that it -was in fact omitted, and neither can one suppose that the Entente Powers merely desire the unqualified re-establishment of the statu quo ante helium in the Balkans.&quot; The Treaty of Bucharest, to wit, is one of those which are the object of President Wilsons severest condemnation when, alluding to arrangements between victors and vanquished, which arrangements, if serving the peculiar interests and provisional aims of certain States, cannot, nevertheless, constitute the basis of a lasting peace. I will not argue as to why the Entente Bowers and America (where new maps of the woidd are being drawn with great love) seem to care so little for the Jugoslav-question. I must, however, express my astonishment thereat, considering that toe too feel a shiver of passion when roe approach this question, although we, if anyone, as the actual possessors of the whole of the Serbo-Croatian territories, should be given the priority in these debates.&quot; The solution of the Jugoslav question is at one time very easy and very difficult. Originally the problem icas stated with clearness and simplicity ; through its historical. . development in the course of the last century it became extraordinarily complicated, and now it is really and truly another Gordian knot.    We have to deal with a people2S-12-2 1)announced at least six weeks in advance. . Li tins connection, it is of interest to note, that the French Government have decided, as reprisals for the sinking of hospital ships,,,. henceforward to embark enemy prisoners on this class of vessel.Anticipating that Germany&apos;s barbarous methods of warfare will compel us to keep N our wounded in certain theatres of operations instead of evacuating them to England,-. His Majesty&apos;s Government have directed Sir G. Spring Rice to enquire whether the., great demand for doctors and nurses thus created can be met to some extent by assistance from, the United States. The American Red Cross have replied (Sth April) , that they can supply at once as many nurses as may he required. The question of , doctors is under examination.Sir M. Findlay (christiania) reports that there are now several hundred. Belgian ,, and Italian reservists in Norway, and that, as the cost of their maintenance is. , considerable, the Belgian and Italian Ministers are urging that His Majesty&apos;s Govern-.. merit should take steps to facilitate their being sent to the United. Kingdom.The German Government have now agreed to grant safe passage for the vessel chartered by the Rockefeller organisation to carry stores for prisoners of war from America (vide Report, No. 4). The conditions attached to this safe conduct have been officially communicated to the Crown. Princess of Sweden, under whose patronage atuh supervision the work of dividing the supplies will be carried out.
who spank a common tongue, some - nine or ten niillion strong, whose compact masses inhabit the north-western part of -the Balkan Peninsula, but whose advance posts are still to be found as far west as the Adriatic:sea-bddrd on one side, and as far away east as the vast expanse of the &quot;Hungarian, plains on the other. The most irresistible aspirations urge this people on towards its political union. These aspirations were horn at the beginning oil the nineteenth century ; in 1848-49 they led to political struggles which as yet were not hostile to Austria, but which, in these latter years, assumed a character decidedly more dangerous every day and threatened the very existence of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy.&quot;Juridically, more than one half of these nine or ten millions of Serbo-Croatian belong to the A astro-Hungarian Monarchy ; the other half finds itself divided into two independent States. This people, therefore, before the war was living under various forms of government, and so we find &quot; (1) The Serbs of the Kingdom of Serbia ; &quot; (2) The Serbs of Montenegro ;(3) The Serbs of Southern Hungaria who were mere Hungarian citizens ; &quot;(4) The Serbs and. Croats of Croatia and Slavonia who,While embodied in the hungarian State, were to a certain extent enjoying autonomy ; &quot; (5) The Serbs and Croats of Dalmatia who belong de jure to Croatia and ,Slavonia, and therefore to Hungary, although they belong de facto toAn stria ;&quot; (6) The Croats of Tstria, wdio were and still are Austrian subjects ; and last, &quot; (7) The Serbs and Croats of Bosnia-Herzegovina, who belong to the  Dual Monarchy, and not merely to one of the two States which constitute Austria-Hungary ; and these latter have enjoyed peculiar and let us add, quite special auto no in y.&quot;It must be confessed that these connections, which at first sight appear to run against the laws of nature, were not the result of a capricious dynastic policy but the perfectly natural produce of historical creations and the entanglement of all the political forces of the various States who made their influence felt on these regions which, are the postern of the Balkans. Yet, on the other hand, it should not be deducted therefrom that lite situation as it now presents itself is, so to say, the last word spoken by Nature, and thai it should be considered as the best that can be in a loorld rendered as perfect as possible.&quot;I will not state here what happened on the eve of the Avar. I none the less believe that the great majority of German public opinion has for one of its duties to ascertain where it stands, and wJiether Peace, in so far as the Jugoslav question is concerned, will be satisfied with merely re-establishing the statu quo&apos;, or whether diplomatists -trill limit their task to the -re-adjustment of frontiers on certain points, deciding, at the same time, the fate of the very honourable dynasties of the Petrovitch, Niegushs and Karageorgevitchs.&quot; Granted that the principle of nationalities be legitimate, wherever found in the world, it is all the more so as regards the Jugoslav question. The aspirations towards re-union of a people scattered about far and wide, and lying under the yoke of the most monstrous jurisdictions, should be considered independently of the Panslavist propaganda which has during these last few decades been carried by fiery proceedings and Avitbout too many moral scruples. Whoever studies with an open mind the genesis of tile question must needs recognize, that a Jugoslav solution can, only be attained, through the re-union of these kindred races. We have to that end hut one choice either this solution will be reached with the help of the Austro-Eungarian Monarchy, and within her pale, or it -will be reached without her and against her.&quot; There was a time when this idea represented the essential policy of the Kingdom of Serbia, Pashitch himself always acknowledged the accuracy of this axiom, although, he Avas in favour of those who Avould have it that this pobcy could only take effect if directed against the Austro-Huugarian Monarchy. Therefore, despite an extraordinary political agitation on the part of the Serbian elements ever since the days of King Milan, it would still be quite feasible in Serbia and Montenegro to induce the ancient foes of Austria to listen to.reason if, by giving its solution to the Jugoslav question within the pale of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, it were at the same time possible to enable the dream of the Southern Slavs to become a reality in their political re-union.&quot; From, the geographical point of view, and also-from the point of view, of political, economics the Jugoslav countries -undoubtedly  belong  to  the Austro-Hungarian
Monarchy. The whole of Serbia is a mountainous region which, surrounded east and west by continuous ridges of high mountains, descends towards the Danube through a succession of slopes less and less steep until the waterway is reached ; its main river, the artery winch, so to say, forms the active centre of the country, the Morava, belong to the Danube watershed. In spite of all the artificial attempts which have been made these last few years Serbia has not been, and will not be able to, satisfy her needs of industrial produces so easily and. satisfactorily as in Austria ; and again, in regard to her agricultural produces she can nowhere find better and readier markets than in Austria. If the phrase &quot; State system &quot; has any meaning, it has its full meaning in this instance; Serbia belongs to the system of States which form the Austro-IIungarian Monarchy-. By this averment I am far from pleading the cause of a policy of conquest. Nevertheless things are not otherwise, and an isolated Serbia is not and, cannot be economically independent, and her desperate struggle to reach her maritime route, from which it ioas debarred by Austria, goes to -prove it. There is for Serbia but one means to get an outlet on the sea, either she must be made a, part of Austria or else she must conejuer parts of the Danubian Monarch,]). And thus the question is again brought back to its starting point : with Austria or against Austria: within the pale of the, Dual Monarchy or outside it. There is no question which affects the vital nerve of Austria-Hungary as deeply as this.&quot;And. this Jugoslav question is very intimately connected with the vital interests of the German Empire and with the free passage which the Mitteleuropa, must have towards the, East. In Germany, when face to face with similar difficulties which, of course, are only in appearance essentially Austrian questions, the tendency7 has been to give us to understand that to us, and to us alone, does it become to surmount them.&quot; But this is a peculiar case, and. such method does not apply. We must say in this instance : et rostra res agitur. It must not be forgotten that the Serbo-Croatian region extends from Quarnero to the Iron Gates, and from the Drava and the Danube to Macedonia, and that therefore this region constitutes a, barrier lying across the whole of the Balkan Peninsula. In this region are all the trade outlets of Mitteleuropa ; and across this self-same region run all. the railways that lead to Constantinople. The Morava and Vardar watershed is the natural commercial route of Mitteleuropa towards Salonica; the Sandjak of Novi-Bazar scheme, which, again, can only become practicable through Serbian territory, is very difficult, and. would also be very costly ; and as such it has already been, given up by the Austrian Government. Something far better can be undertaken elsewhere. Indeed, all the Adriatic ports of the Dual Monarchy, with, [he sole exception of Trieste, are situate in the, Jugoslav region. The Bocche cli Oattaro, the most magnificent and commodious natural, harbour in the world, is inhabited by a Croatian population.&quot; If arrived at against Austria, tlie solution of the -Jugoslav problem i could, ipso facto, hit at the same time Germany&apos;s vital interests and would in any case render Utopian the great scheme of an economic Mitteleuropa. It is but a secondary question to know what the juridical structure of Austria-Hungary would be if Serbia and Montenegro were to be incorporated. For Austria this incorporation is a vital question to which all the veUeiti.es of the various races of the Dual Monarchy are subordinate ; for Germany this implies the question of her military plans being given effect to, and by this we mean the constitution of Mitteleuropa. Be it as it may, it is necessary for us to ascertain where we now stand in regard to this question.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
