<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/17/33 images: 320-341</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET Copy No.W.P. (41) 160(Also Paper No. C.O.S. (41) 421) /July 10, 1941 /TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care ma^/oe taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 97)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 12 noon July 3rd, to12 noon July 10th,1941[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.Our shipping losses have been very light, while heavy losses have beeninflicted on the enemy by our submarines and aircraft.An Italian cruiser and U-boat have been sunk.American naval forces have arrived in Iceland (C).Home Waters.2. On the 5th the transport Anselm (5,954 tons) with 1,200 Army andR.A.F. personnel for the Middle East was torpedoed, and sunk about 300 miles north of the Azores. 1,210 survivors were picked up by H.M. ships in company.On the same day H.M. Aircraft Carrier Furious was unsuccessfully attacked by  Focke-Wulf aircraft to the westward of Cape St. Vincent.On the night of the 5th/6th H.M. Destroyer Holderness was damaged by mine off Flamborough Head.In attacks by enemy aircraft on coastal convoys off Cromer, one was shot down by British s.s. Tetela (5,389 tons) and a Ju. 88 was destroyed by a convoy.H.M. Trawler Tartan obtained a direct hit by gunfire which probably destroyed an aircraft off the Humber, and in the course of minelaying in the thames Estuary one enemy aircraft was shot dfowii by our patrol craft, and several were seen to be hit.An air raid on Aberdeen during the night the 8th /9th caused some damage to the dock machinery and to Admiralty offices. On the same night fires inPlymouth Dockyard, caused by incendiaries, were quickly extinguished.Our aircraft have sunk or damaged 66,900 tons of enemy shipping off the coasts and in various harbours from Ushant up to and including the coast of norway.   Details are given in the Air Section of this Resume.Two of H.M. Auxiliary vessels were sunk by mine and two were sunk and3 damaged by air attack.   Details are given in Appendix V.Atlantic.3. Two battleships, two cruisers and ten destroyers of the United states navy have arrived at Hvalf jorcl, Reykjavik. The U.S. Admiral is flying his flagat Reykjavik.On the 8th July ships in harbour at Freetown were hit by machine-gun fire and cannon shells in an attack by a single aircraft.Mediterranean.4. Reports received during the week of our submarine operations in theCentral Mediterranean are as follows : On the 23rd June Utmost sank a merchant ship of 6,000 tons off the North coast of Sicily, and on the next clay landed a party which blew up the railway lineon the West Calabrian coast. On the 28th Severn sank a merchant vessel of 1,592 tons in the Tyrrhenian Sea and one of 8,000 tons off the east coast ofSardinia. On the 29th Urge sank an 8-inch cruiser and torpedoed an armed merchant cruiser south of Messina. She also landed a demolition party,which wrecked a train in a tunnel north of Taormina. While returning frompatrol in the Gulf of Genoa, the Dutch Submarine O. 23 sank a fully laden tanker.On the 3rd July Upholder sank a merchant vessel of about 5,500 tons, north-east of Catania (Sicily).In an air attack on Palermo Harbour on the 6th, serious damage was caused to enemy shipping, and it is estimated that 35,000 tons of shipping were hit.On the 4th the Vichy French s.s. Saint Didier (2,778 tons) was located by aircraft in Turkish territorial waters off Cape Khelodinia (to north-west of cyprus). After two unsuccessful attacks by Swordfish aircraft she was torpedoed and sunk by 4 Albacores in ^A^alja^piaxbour (Southern Turkey).Naval forces, including two Yugoslavian torpedo boats, continue to co-operate with the Army on the Syrian coast and on the 7th effective support was given inthe advance on Damour.During the week 6 French ships (15,000 tons) have passed Gibraltarwestbound, and 8 (21,000 tons) have passed eastbouncl.
Anti-Submarine Operations.5. An Italian U-boat was sunk by H.M. Submarine Tigris 140 miles west of Bordeaux. An aircraft claimed to have obtained hits with bombs in an attackto the westward of Ushant. There were 8 other attacks during the week, 5by aircraft and 3 by surface craft, without conclusive results.Enemy Intelligence.German.6. There have been no changes in the positions of the larger surface unitsduring the week. The two battle-cruisers and the 8-inch cruiser Prinz Eugenare still at Brest. The latter was probably damaged in an air attack on the1st/2nd July.Italian.7. Air reconnaissance on the 7th showed 1 Cavour class and 2 Littorioclass battleships in Taranto with 5 destroyers and 4 torpedo boats. The cruisers and destroyers present in Palermo at the time of the air attack on the 6th Julyhad left by the following day.U-Boats.8. The disposition of U-boats has remained substantially unaltered. Duringthe week 20 or more Germans have been in the North Atlantic. Photographicrecconnaissance confirms the presence of up to 12 U-boats in Trondheim.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.9. According to the information at present available, shipping casualties during the week under review have been exceptionally light. No ships in convoyhave been reported lost. Two British ships (one of which was the transportreferred to in paragraph 2) were torpedoed, one to the westward of the CanaryIslands and the other north of the Azores. One ship was mined at the entranceof Alexandria. Although there has been a considerable amount of bombingaround the coast, especially at night, only two small ships have been sunk and five ships have been damaged.The tonnage sunk by the German Air Force has progressively decreased since february. In May and June it is estimated that the losses were less than 50 percent, of those for February and March, despite an increase in the number of aircraft employed.Details of shipping losses for the month of June will be included next week.Protection of Seaborne Trade.10. During the week ending the 9th July, 779 ships, including 117 allied and 9 neutral, were convoyed. Ten armed merchant cruisers, five anti-aircraftships, seventy-one destroyers and eighty-nine sloops, Fleet minesweepers and corvettes were employed on escort duties.Imports into Great Britain by ships in convoy during the week ending the5th July totalled 652,597 tons, compared with 953,270 tons during the previous seven days. Oil imports, in 27 tankers, amounted to 290,125 tons; mineral imports were 76,544 tons, of which 55,945 tons were steel, pig iron, scrap iron and iron ore. Timber imports were 9,553 tons and cereals 183,977 tons. Other food imports totalled 66,167 tons, the principal commodities being: tinned andrefrigerated meats, bacon and hams 20,420 tons, sugar 8,717 tons, fruit 6,807 tons(2,875 tons of lemons), cocoa 2,530 tons, eggs 1,894&quot;tons, tea 1,083 tons. Importsof ammunition and war stores were again satisfactory.British Minelaying.11. During the night 3rd/4th H.M.S. Plover laid mines in the East coast barrier, and on the 9th July 1,500 miles were laid in the Faroes-Iceland (C)Channel by H.M. Ships Agamemnon, Menestheus and Port Quebec. Minelayingon a small scale has been carried out by aircraft on the north German coast andoff the French Biscay ports.
Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.Home Waters.12. With the exception of one night, that of 3rd/4th July, enemy aircraft have laid mines every night this week. The area from the Thames Estuary tothe Humber, inclusive, has received most attention, particularly the former.Milford Haven has been visited three times, and minelaying was suspected inthe Spithead, Solent and Southampton Water area, off the Farne Islands,from Beachy Head to Selsey, and in Cardigan Bay.During the period under review three small ships were mined and sunk inthe Thames Estuary. The British Lunan (363 tons) was sunk in the bristol channel, and three other ships were damaged by mines but reached harboursafely. Thirty-four acoustic and 11 magnetic mines have been detonated duringthe week. The mine totals to date are: Acoustic, 855; magnetic, 1,270;contact, 911.Foreign Waters.13. Mines were dropped both inside and outside Alexandria Harbourduring an air raid on the night of the 6th/7th. Mines were also laid in the harbour at Haifa on the night of the 7th/8th and the port was closed, but wasreopened on the 9th.The port of Takoradi, which had been closed on account of mining, wasreopened on the 4th.Enemy Merchant Shipping.14. The Havenstein (7.974 tons) and the Ursula Rickmers (5,050 tons) arebeing manned by Chinese crews at Dairen. They are reported to be about to sailunder the Japanese flag with cargoes consigned to Germany.MILITARY SITUATION.Russo-German Campaign.(An outline map showing the operations in Russia is enclosed in this resume as an inset.)15. By the end of the second week of the campaign the Germans have driventhe Russians out of almost the entire area occupied by them in 1939. The mainthrusts appear to be north-west towards Leningrad, east towards Smolensk and moscow and, further south, east towards Kiev. The rate of advance has been most rapid in the Baltic States, where mobile German units had, up to the endof the second week, covered distances of approximately 35 to 40 miles a day. Inthe White Russian sector the advance was considerably slower during the second week, and now that the Germans have reached the main lines of russian resistance their progress may be further slowed down.Finland.16. German-Finnish forces have at various points driven wedges intoRussian territory. Details are scanty, but the principal thrusts so far appear tobe directed against Murmansk and Kandalaksha. There has also been somefighting in Central Finland and in the Karelian Isthmus opposite Leningrad.Little progress appears to have been made to date.Baltic States.17. German troops advancing in the general direction of Leningrad fromthe south-west are now attacking across the Estonian and Latvian frontiers inthe direction of Ostrov and Pskov. The Russians are counter-attacking strongly in this sector.White Russia.18. During the past week the German forces have been driving eastwardsfrom Minsk with the object of securing the line of the rivers Dvina and Dnieper.Two main thrusts are developing, one to the north-east in the direction of
Polotsk and Vitebsk, the second to the east towards the Dnieper at Rogachev.North-west of Polotsk the Germans have reached the northern bank of the Dvinain the region of Dzisna. The Russians claim that all attacks on the line of the dnieper have been held.19. The left wing of the German force advancing in the general directionZhitomir-Kiev is encountering strenuous Russian resistance in the Novograd-Volynsk area. A parallel thrust appears to be developing further south onBerdichev. It is probable that an enveloping movement directed on Kiev is contemplated.20. Tarnopol was captured on the 4th July and a subsequent advance inthis area may be intended to swing south-east and turn the Dniester fortifications.Hungarian troops are co-operating with the Germans in this area and are believed to have reached a line Stanislavov-Kolomja.Chernowitz was occupied by German and Roumanian troops on the 5th July.Bessarabia.21. German-Roumanian forces, having taken Balti, are driving north-easttowards the Dniester.Operations.Libya and Egypt.22. The Tobruk garrison has continued to carry out offensive patrollingoperations. There has been some shelling of the town and harbour by enemyartillery and counter-battery action has been taken.In the frontier area operations have been confined to patrol activity and23. The chief events of the last week were the suri-ender of Debra Tabor andof the entire Galla Sidamo province south of the Blue Nile.With the surrender of the garrison of Debra Tabor on the 3rd July enemy troops numbering some 3,000 have come into our hands and one of the remainingcentres of resistance has lost a strong natural fortress and approximately one-quarter of the total garrison.   Gondar is still holding out.24. On the 4th July representatives of General Gazzera, Commander-in-Chief, Southern Command, met Belgian forces operating in the area of DembiDollo and negotiated the surrender of the whole of the command, which included the Galla Sidamo province south of the Blue Nile and was, in fact, the mainpocket of resistance remaining in Southern Abyssinia. It is not known how manyprisoners have been taken, but in Dembi Dollo they include 10 generals, 1,200Italians and 2,000 natives. The total forces affected by the capitulation are probably of the order of 6,000 white and 9,000 native troops.25. In the north-east a column from Northern Iraq has reached the Turkishfrontier at Kamechli and a further column has moved up the road Abu Kemal-Aleppo as far as Raqqa. At Palmyra our troops, having captured the town,have sent patrols along the Horns road as far as Furqlus (30 miles from Horns).They are also in touch with Free French Forces from Damascus at Qaryatein.26. In the Damascus sector the Free French have beaten off a counter-attack at Nebk and have advanced to Deir Aatiye. Our forces advancing along the Beirut road are held up by strong Vichy French forces 15 miles west of damascus.27. After the capture of Merjayoun our troops advanced on Hasbaye, whichhas been evacuated by the Vichy French, though they are still south of the town.Forces from this area are also in the Lebanon range (20 miles north of Merjayoun).In the coastal sector Damour was captured by our troops on the 9th July,Ukraine.exchanges of artillery fire.A abyssinia.Syria.
28. On the 8th July the Vichy High Commissioner, General Dentz,proposed on behalf of his Government that there should be an immediatesuspension of hostilities in Syria and that negotiations should be opened for an armistice.Intelligence.Italy.29. An Italian Expeditionary Force is being sent to join in the campaign against Russia; it is believed that it will be employed on the Hungarian front.Forces already detailed are two lorry-borne divisions, the total strength of whichwith corps troops, services, &amp;c, may be 30-40,000. There is no indicationwhether further forces will be sent.It is rumoured that a Spanish Legion is to be associated with this Force.Libya.30. There have been a number of reports indicating that an Axis attack onTobruk is possible in the fairly near future. It is certainly true that an Italiandivision has moved eastwards from Derna, but there is no evidence that substantialGerman reinforcements have arrived in Cyrenaica.31.   Present Italian dispositions in Libya are believed to be : Frontier area ... 55 (Savona) Division.Tobruk area ...      ...   27 (Brescia) Division.17 (Pavia) Division.102 (Trento) Motorised Division.Barce area   ...       ...    25 (Bologna) Division.132 (Ariete) Armoured Division (reorganising).Tripolitania ...       ...   60 (Sabrata) Division.Miscellaneous forces equivalent to 1-2 divisions.Many of these formations are probably still under strength.AIR SITUATION.General Review.32. The number of aircraft engaged in bombing attacks on enemy targets in Germany and Occupied Territory was the second highest since the outbreakof war, and the tonnage of bombs released was the largest.Successful attacks were made on enemy shipping in the North Sea and inthe Channel, and Bomber Command aircraft have attacked Bremen andWilhelmshaven in daylight, besides many objectives in France. Fortress I&apos;s havebeen in action.The German long-range bomber effort over this country has decreased by day but increased by night. Bombers from Malta have carried out a highly successful attack on Italian shipping in Palermo harbour and have attackedNaples.Germany and Occupied Territory,Day.33. Bomber Command aircraft, often escorted by fighters, continued theiroffensive operations against objectives in North-Eastern France and Germany,166 daylight sorties being flown during the week. In Germany, the objectives were the docks at Bremen, the seaplane base at Norderney, and the naval base willhelmshaven, and in France, the railway centres at Hazebrouck, St. Omer andAbbeville, and the industrial centres of Chocques, Lille, Mazinbarge and Albert.34. Objectives in Germany were of course attacked without fighter escort.On the 4th July, eight Blenheims attacked Bremen at a height of fifty feet,ignoring the balloon barrage which was flying at about 500 feet; one aircraft flew under an electric cable and another collected some telegraph wires. A largefactory was hit and the resultant explosion threw debris to about a height of500 feet.   A railway junction north-west of the city was attacked and the goods
yard was hit several times. Intense light A.A. fire was encountered but no enemy aircraft were seen. Four Blenheims were lost; one was seen to be hit by A.A. fire and to crash into a factory, causing a large explosion. The same clay a largebuilding, believed to be an hotel, was destroyed in Norderney.35. On the 8th, American Fortress I&apos;s were in action for the first time.Two of these aircraft attacked the Naval Barracks at Wilhelmshaven from about30,000 feet, dropping six heavy blast bombs which were seen to explode directlyon the targets, which lie in a thickly populated part of the town. No opposition was encountered over the target, but two Me. 109&apos;s were seen over Terschelling andwere apparently unable to engage.36. A total of 156 fighter squadrons provided escort for Bomber CommandBlenheims and Stirlings engaged in daylight attacks on North-Western France.The steel works at Lille, the chemical works at Chocques -and the Potez airf ramefactory near Albert were each hit several times. Most successful attacks were also made against shipping in Cherbourg and Havre, and are reported under&quot; Coastal Operations.&quot; In the course of combats over France and the Channel,76 enemy fighters were destroyed, 37 probably destroyed and 47 damaged. Welost 4 bombers and 44 fighters, but 10 fighter pilots are safe.37. German fighters on the Western Front are being strengthened by theuse of single-engined and twin-engined operational training units on operationalduties, giving an estimated additional strength of about 90 single-engined and60 twin-engined fighters. This use of O.T.Us. is believed to be only temporary.There is no evidence that they are to lose their training status or become apermanent part of &quot;the first-line strength. About 600 fighter sorties were madeon the 7th, mainly over the Channel area. The daily average for the week was approximately 380 sorties, as compared with 290 in the previous week.Night.38. There was a considerable increase in the weight of our attacks onobjectives in Germany and Occupied Territory during the week, 1,338 bombersbeing employed, as compared with 748 in the previous week, and over 1,345 tonsof H.E. bombs released (the largest on record), compared with 767 tons.39. Targets in Germany included the industrial and railway centres atEssen, Munster, Osnabruck, Dortmund, Cologne, Hamm, Aachen and Bielefeld,the shipyards at Bremen and the large synthetic oil plant at Merseburg, nearLeipzig. Munster was heavily attacked on four nights of the week, Osnabruckon three and Bielefeld on two.In Occupied France, the principal targets were the naval units in Brest,which were attacked on two nights, and the submarine base at Lorient.40. In most instances, a large proportion of bombs fell in the target areas and numerous fires, many of them large, were started. Some of the attacks were particularly effective. At Munster, considerable damage was caused to therailway and industrial centres; aircraft attacked from 1,500 feet and reportedthat the whole town was ablaze. The Krupp works at Essen and the synthetic oil plant at Merseburg were hit several times.At Brest, bursts were seen near the German warships, fires were started near the seaplane base and a liner of 10,000 tons lying in the Roads received adirect hit.41. From all these operations, forty-two Bomber Command aircraft are missing. Defensive enemy fighter activity at night is increasing. An increased number of twin-engined fighters were known to be operating on most nights overHolland and North-west Germany.42. Attention is drawn to the Raid Assessment Reports summarised inAppendix VII, which are this week of particular interest.United Kingdom.   ,43. Fighter Command hew 1,119 patrols, involving 4.513 sorties,-&apos;by day,and 691 patrols, involving 912 sorties, by night. The latter total includes duskand dawn patrols.   The bulk of our fighter effort by day is accounted for by
offensive sweeps and bomber escorts over Northern France, and by shippingprotection patrols. Details of these operations are reported in the appropriatesections.44. The German effort by day was again very small and only fivereconnaissance aircraft were plotted inland, though on two days a few fighterscrossed the coast. Shipping and weather reconnaissance flights were at the samelow level as last week. Of the week&apos;s German Air Force casualties, only twooccurred over this country a Ju. 88 which crashed from an unknown cause inCornwall and an Me. 109 which our fighters destroyed off the Isle of Wight.45. At night, about 340 long-range bombers and bomber-reconnaissance aircraft operated, compared with 195 last week. On the nights of the 4th/5thand 8th/9th, the Midlands appeared to be the principal objective and, on othernights, small concentrations attacked Plymouth, Southampton and Yarmouth.On four nights, the main activity was armed reconnaissance of shipping. Aboutsixty aircraft are suspected of minelaying, and night fighters operated on five nights over our eastern aerodromes, but without success. Fighters accounted foreighteen of the 21 German aircraft destroyed at night during the week.Coastal Operations.46. Coastal Command flew 259 patrols (340 sorties) and provided escortsfor 78 convoys (200 additional sorties). Shipping protection patrols carried outby Fighter Command totalled 881 (1,675 sorties).47. Several successful attacks on enemy shipping were made during theweek by aircraft of Bomber and Coastal Commands. On the 7th July, elevenBlenheims of Bomber Command attacked a convoy of eight merchant vessels and four flakships off the Hague, sinking six vessels, totalling 18,000 tons. On the10th, 24 Blenheims of the same Command attacked shipping at Cherbourg andHavre. Six ships, with a total tonnage of about 34,000 tons, were hit by bombs,and it is considered that each of the vessels is a total loss. Earlier in the week,a flakship of 3,000 tons was sunk off the mouth of the Scheldt, five reportingvessels of about 120 tons each were sunk off Heligoland, and an &quot; E &quot; Boat was sunk off Gravelines. Other enemy casualties include the following which receiveddirect hits : A merchant vessel of about 2,000 tons, off Gravelines.A merchant vessel of 4,000 tons, off Dunkirk.Two merchant vessels of 3,000 tons and 800 tons respectively, off theAlsboen Light.A merchant vessel of about 1,500 tons, off Ushant.Several other vessels were attacked, but results could not be observedaccurately. In an attack on shipping at Haugesund, South Norway, a Beaufortscored hits on the quay, probably damaging a merchant vessel of 6,000 tonsalongside, and on a warehouse, which was set on fire.48. A total of 29 aircraft laid mines off the Frisian Islands, off the South-West Coast of Norway and off the North-West Coast of France.49. Enemy attacks on shipping continue by both day and night, but, as reported in the Naval Situation, in spite of the increase in the number of aircraftengaged in these operations, losses are now progressively decreasing.Central Mediterranean.50. On the 6th July, six Blenheims from Malta carried out a most successfulsurprise attack on shipping in Palermo harbour. A ship of 10,000 tons was hittwice, her back apparently breaking; three hits on another ship of the sametonnage caused a fire, explosions and dense columns of smoke; two bombs hit a ship of 8,000 tons, and two other ships of 5,000 and 2,000 tons were also hit.Our aircraft machine-gunned cruisers and destroyers. Divisional Headquarters,warehouses, dry dock buildings and the power station. An explosion, probablycaused by incendiaries, was observed near the dry dock, and complete confusionwas caused in the harbour and outside.   On the 4th, six Blenheims attacked a
troop convoy of about 130 vehicles, west of Sirte, destroying a number of themby bombs and others by machine-gun fire and inflicting heavy casualties on troops.One of the Blenheims attacked and hit the barracks at Tamet.51. On the night of the 9th/10th, six Wellingtons dropped six tons of bombs on Naples. The Central Railway Station and marshalling yards were hitmany times, in addition to warehouses and an aircraft factory.52. On three nights, a force of six Wellingtons bombed the harbour, enginesheds and sidings at Tripoli (L), causing many fires and explosions. Swordfishalso bombed the Spanish Mole and laid mines outside the harbour. Hurricanesmade a low flying attack on the seaplane base at Syracuse, destroying three aircraft and damaging five others, and causing casualties among the crews on theslipway. Reconnaissance aircraft have maintained a close watch on enemy shipping off the Tunisian Coast and in the Ionian Sea, and have photographedTaranto and the Sicilian ports.53. Enemy activity over Malta has been negligible by clay, and the onlyreconnaissance aircraft which approached the Island was driven off by hurricanes, which destroyed one or more of the escorting fighters. Night attacks have been on a heavier scale, but the damage inflicted was negligible, except onthe night of the 8th/9th, when a Wellington was destroyed and a floatplanedamaged.  On this night, our fighters destroyed one bomber and damaged another.Egypt and Cyrenaica.54. Heavier attacks were made on Benghazi by Wellingtons this week, and considerable damage must have resulted from the fires and explosions which followed. At least one ship is believed to have been hit. Our fighters main-tained shipping patrols, and also attacked aerodromes and landing-grounds inthe Western Desert, ships in Menelao Bay and the port of Derna. On the 7th,Hurricanes destroyed six enemy aircraft on the ground at Gambut, while coveringfighters shot down an Italian fighter and damaged others. Five Hurricanes are missing from these operations.55. The enemy have made one daylight attack on Tobruk, where theycaused little damage and lost four bombers. Fifteen Me. 110&apos;s attacked ourcoastal column and aerodrome at Sidi Barrani and the landing ground at MaatenBagush, destroying two Blenheims and a Tomahawk. Night attacks were madeon Alexandria, the Suez Canal area and on our aerodromes at Fuka and Amriya,but no important damage was caused, though there were some civilian casualties in Alexandria.Syria and Palestine.56. Wellingtons from Egypt have made nightly attacks on Beirut andAleppo. Many hits were observed on hangars, and at least seven aircraft were destroyed on the ground at Aleppo, where the station was also hit and a largefire broke out in the railway depot. At Beirut, the barracks were hit and a firevisible.from 80 miles broke out among the fuel cisterns. One Wellington was lostduring these operations, and another crashed in Egypt after an engagementduring which it destroyed an enemy fighter, probably destroyed a second and damaged a third.57. Blenheims have flown many day sorties against enemy harbours,shipping and aerodromes, in addition to giving close support to our troops.Two enemy bombers were destroyed and hangars damaged at Hama, and severalhits were made on Vichy headquarters at Beit ed Dine.58. Our fighters maintained patrols over our naval units off the Syriancoasts, but encountered very little enemy opposition. In the course of low flying-attacks on landing grounds, Hurricanes set fire to a fuel store and destroyed atleast two, and damaged twenty-two, enemy aircraft. Tomahawks successfully attacked enemy troops and motor transport and Beaufighters attacked aeroplanesin Tripoli (S) Harbour.59. Hostile aircraft made two night attacks on Haifa. The station,camp and refinery were hit, and mines were dropped in the harbour.   One Vichy
Glenn-Martin was destroyed by A.A. lire. By day, Vichy aircraft became increasingly inactive, though oil two occasions bombers and fighters attackedour troops in the Deir ez Zor area. Up to the 6th July, 78 Vichy aircraft havebeen destroyed, 8 probably destroyed and^.damaged.Cyprus.60. German and Italian aircraft have made a number of bombing attacks on Cyprus during the week. On the 4th Nicosia and the harbour at Famagustawere the objectives, and the customs house and a wharf were hit at the latter,though no casualties resulted. On the 7th, thirteen Ju. 88&apos;s bombed the aerodrome at Nicosia, destroying&quot; two petrol dumps and damaging four of our aircraft. AVichy Glenn-Martin carried out an ineffective raid on Nicosia and Famagusta onthe 5th.East Africa.61. Attacks against objectives in south-west Abyssinia were continued bythe South African Air Force until the capitulation of General Gazzera on the4th July. Efforts were subsequently made by pamphlet dropping and other means to inform the Patriots still operating in the Galla Sidamo Province that hostilities in that area had ceased. In the north Wellesleys and Free French Blenheims have continued their attacks on Gondar.Aden Protectorate.62. Punitive bombing started on the 5th July against the occupants ofDar-el-Beidha, who have been giving trouble since the latter part of last year. Bythe 7th the Dar, which had been evacuated, was completely destroyed.West Africa.63. A single aircraft attacked and hit shipping in Freetown Harbour with machine-gun and cannon fire on the morning of the 8th.Russia.64. There is evidence that attacks by the Soviet Air Force are not onlycausing casualties, but are definitely impeding communications and hinderingthe German advance, which is noticeably slackening. It is reported that theGermans have been obliged to concentrate their A.A. defences in forward.areas.65. Strong opposition from the Russian land and air forces has been,encountered, particularly on the line of the Dvipa and the Dnieper, in the northernsector. In this area, two German operational air Commands have been mainlyengaged in the support of some 30 divisions attempting to force the crossingof these rivers towards Tobolsk and Polotsk. Reports have been received ofRussian attacks on Lovisa and Kotka, in the Gulf of Finland, the lattertown having suffered severely. On the 3rd, Russian fighters.attacked the Helsinkiairport with small bombs, damaging a Ju. 88, and destroying a neighbouringchemical works. Two more Ju. 88&apos;s were destroyed whilst attacking Hango. the finns have bombed Baltiski and the Germans have attacked the Stalin Canal.66. In the central battle area, Russian attacks from the air on Germanoperational landing grounds have compelled the maintenance of constant fighterpatrols. In the southern sector, German air operations have generally consisted of attacks on Russian road and railway communications and moving columnsbehind the front.67. Reports have been received about Russian bombing attacks onRoumanian targets, and it seems certain that the raids on Constanza didconsiderable damage. The railway station is said to have been destroyed and twoempty tankers in the port are believed to have been sunk or severely damaged.The bombs dropped in Bucharest did little damage, but Jassy is said to be in ruins..
68. Five German operational air Commands have now been identified onthe Eastern Front, one having been previously, operating in the Greek campaign and three of the others having been withdrawn from the Western Front.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.By Day.69. The only daylight incident of the week occurred at Land&apos;s End, on 3rd July, when an enemy aircraft dropped bombs which failed to explode. this aircraft then crashed.By Night.70. Enemy bombing was somewhat heavier than in previous weeks and included a sharp attack on Southampton (7th/8th July) and two short attacks on Great Yarmouth (6th/7th and 8th/9th July).71. No bombs were dropped on the night of the 3rd/4th. On other nights of the week a few bombs fell in Birmingham, Coventry, Bristol, Plymouth,Aberdeen and several places in East Anglia, without causing serious damage ormany casualties.Damage.Southampton (7th/8th July).72.   Although 75 fires were started, 5 of which were serious, damage was.caused principally to private property; 106 houses were demolished and 277damaged beyond repair.73. The utility services were not affected, with the exception of gas. Twoholders of the Southampton Gas Works were damaged and all suppliestemporarily cut off.74. Temporary interference with transport was caused by the closing ofthree important roads, and the blocking by debris of the Southern Railway lineat Central Station.  No material damage was done to the docks.Great Yarmouth (6th/7th and 8th/9th July).75. Although some damage was done to utility services and to the railway,these raids chiefly affected private property, 120 houses being demolished.Casualties.76. Casualties for the week ending 0600, 9th July, are estimated at 78 killed and 67 seriously, injured.
APPENDICES I, II and iii will be published monthly.APPENDIX IY.Merchant Ships (all sizes) lost by the Enemy up to 8th July, 1941.	German.		Italian.		Together.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.Captured or seized Scuttled or sunk   ... Unidentified ships reported as sunk or destroyed by S/M, A/C, &amp;c, (tonnage estimated)	61 116 235	274,000 62S,000 940,000	42 88 147	201,000 &apos; 451,000 808,000	103 204 382	475,000 1,079,000 1,748,000	412	1,842,000	277	1,460,000	689	3,302,000In addition, 49 ships of 89,000 gross tons under enemy control or useful to the enemy havebeen sunk.Also some 53 ships, totalling 320,000 gross tons, have been placed under protective custody in United States and South American ports to prevent sabotage by their crews. Some of this tonnage has been taken over and put into service by the United States and some South american republics.Note. A survey was recently carried out to determine the average tonnage of unindentifiedships being sunk; this showed that the general average of 5,000 hitherto adopted was rather too high for German ships, but not high enough for Italian ships. A closer approximation will begiven by adopting 4,000 tons as the average for German and 5,500 for Italian ships. Thisestimated tonnage of unindentified ships in the table above has been brought into conformitywith the new averages accordingly.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.The following casualties have occurred to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels during theperiod under review : July 3. Boom drifter Receptive mined and sunk in the Thames Estuary.Four survivors.July 4. M/S Trawler Akranes bombed and sunk in Bridlington Bay.July 5. Paddle M/S Snaefell bombed and sunk off Sunderland.   Threekilled and nine wounded.July 6. A/P  Trawler Jennifer damaged by bombs off  Skegness.Subsequently beached.July 7. A/P Trawler Louis Botha damaged by bombs off Plumber.July 7. A/P Trawler Lord St. Vincent mined and sunk in thames estuary.July 8. M/S Trawler Heroine damaged by bombs in Thames Estuary.No casualties.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : Killed 15, missing 1, wounded 11.Ratings : Killed 66, missing 47, wounded 13.
Operational Aircraft Battle Casualties.0600 hours, Thursday, 3rd July, 1941, to 0600 hours, Thursday, 10th July, 1941.Royal Air Force.Bombers ...Fighters.....CoastalTotalMetropolitan Area.In the Air........... 5445.......... 310210 fighter pilots are known to be safe.On the Ground,nil german.bombers fighters miscellaneous total destroyed,17831101ProbablyDestroyed^437243Damaged.454159No account is taken of aircraft destroyed on the ground.Of the above totals, 1 &quot;miscellaneous &quot; aircraft was destroyed by A.A; firesRoyal Air Fdtfce.Bombers...Fighters ...Coastal  .;,       li\total german.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousItalian.Bombers ...Fighters lt.MiscellaneousTotalMiddle East.In the Air....... 1...... 10Destroyed.&quot;664111ProbablyDestroyed.NilOn the Ground.21Damaged.112Totali
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week from air reconnaissance and Intelligence sources : Germany.Cologne. Photographs taken of the Gremberg Marshalling Yard (situateon the East side of the River and to the South of the city) on the 17th June. 1941,have been examined by a railway expert.   He states that : (i) One stick of bombs has straddled the northbound departure line,(ii) The office of the Permanent Way Inspector, which is a small building to the south of the frump and of great importance, has received adirect hit.(iii) At the north-east end of the yard (a) a direct hit has severed one of the main connections to the militaryloading station in that area, and(b) the through fast lines for traffic avoiding the yard have been hit.(iv) The items above would result not only in the yard itself being blockedbut also the main lines avoiding the yard.(v) Generally, the bombs could not have been better placed and the damageappears to be as great as could be hoped for in the case of a nightraid on a yard. The capacity of the yard is 6,000 waggons a day ormore, yet no sorting is in progress and the southbound receptionsidings are so congested that no further trains can enter. It isimpossible to calculate the far-reaching nature of the disorganisation,but the yard, with its cabin-controlled braking system, must have beenput out of service for some time, perhaps for weeks. In short, themain artery for traffic south from Cologne on the East bank of the rhine was cut.In the raid on the 23rd/24th June one wing of the main station was badly-damaged.Duisberg. The Thyssen steel works received six direct hits shortly aftermidnight on the night of the 16th /17th June. An oil tank in the coal liquefyingplant was set on fire. The damage was such that 3,000 of the workers becameunemployed.General. Recent reports tell of the increased effectiveness of raids in thelast fortnight of June. One states that &quot; the scale and weight of the attacks in.Germany during June has shaken the morale of the civil population concerned-All sorts of stories are being circulated about the terrific results obtained byBritish heavy-type bombs, which are stated to weigh 2,000 kilog. On the night of the 17th/18th June, in Cologne one bomb destroyed twenty-five houses.Groups of Belgian gendarmes have been placed along the new Belgian-german frontier to prevent the entry into Belgium of Germans from bombed areas. Alarge number of men are working at full pressure on the protection of gasometersand gas mains in Essen.France,Brest. Three independent and reliable reports have been received which show that in the raid of the 1st/2nd July the Prinz Eugen received one hit on thestern and that a second bomb fell down the funnel, causing serious internaldamage. Of the personnel on board, over fifty were killed. It was also statedthat the Gneisenau still has two of her lengths of shafting in Germany, and itis thought that she will be out of action for several more months.    The
Scharnhorsfs boiler tubes are now repaired and she has fired up at least one ofher boilers.Camines. Photographs taken during a daylight attack on the power stationshow direct hits on the boiler-house, the pump-house and the water-circulatingpipes. Several near misses must almost certainly have caused damage to theturbine-house and other buildings. A report has now been received thatthe power station will be out of action for a considerable period, it may be asmuch as a year.Pont-d-Verdon. Photographs taken during a daylight attack on the power station on the 30th June show bursts between two of four large chimneys. they also show bursts among buildings to the west of these chimneys, being direct hitson the turbine- and boiler-houses, and probably the offices and switching-house.Merville. Photographs taken during the daylight attack on the aerodromeon the 2nd July show approximately twelve bombs bursting on a hangar and ataxi-track leading to a dispersal area at the south side of the aerodrome.Norway.Bergen. -In the attack on the 8th June one ship was hit and sunk, another in shallow water was hit and is now resting on the bottom, and direct hits were obtained, on a wharf.
i Q o2 0 0LEGENDApproximate^Hnes reached by axis forces.Pockets of Soviet resistance.(Dates denote when resistanceTBelieved to have ended.)Main t;hrusts of Axis Forces.Mote-- Though lines are shown givingthe extent of advances byAx i s Forces,  it must itfeunderstood that  thes% are) only approximate.AXIS   operations against U.S.S.R.-sxh owing approximateadvances.MOSCOWG.5 O.R. 5462western   u-s-s-r-SECRETfnternationdl BoundaryRailwaysreference
SECRETG.5 O.R. 5462&apos;western   u-s-s-r-SCALE :l/4M OR 63 MILES TO 1 INCHryanskreferenceInternational BoundaryRailwaysAXIS   operations against USjSRsjiowirig approximateaclv^nces.legend approximate A/nes reached byr Axis forces.Pockets of Soviet resistance.fJDates denote when resistanceoe/ieved to have ended.)Main thrusts of Axis Forces.Mote-- Though lines are shown giv\ingthe extent of advances by I4*Forces,  it must itieunderstood that  thes$ areonly approximate.
Approximate^l/nes reached by axis forces.Pockets of Soviet resistance.(Dates denote when resistanceBelieved to have ended.)Main thrusts of Axis Forces.Note-- Though lines are shown givingthe extent of advances byjAxis Forces,  it must fieunderstood that  these areonly approximate.
legend approximate Ai nes reached by axis forces.Pockets of Soviet resistance.(Pates denote when resistanceBelieved to have ended.)Main thrusts of Axis Forces.flfobe:- Though lines are shown givjngthe extent of advances by axis Forces, it must (be understood that  these areonly approximate.




</content>
</cab>
