<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/48/28 images: 407-426</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTSECRET Copy No.   3 0W.P. (44) 178(Also O.O.S. (44) 57)30th March, 1944WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 239)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 23rd March, to0700 30th March,1944[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT1G2SECRET Copy No.   3 GW.P. (44) 178(Also O.O.S. (44) 57)30th March, 1944WAR cabinet weekly RESUME .(No. 239)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 23rd March, to0700 30th March,1944[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room.
General Review.NAVAL SITUATION.1. Coastal forces have attacked enemy shipping and light craft off theFrench and Dutch coasts.No attacks on Allied shipping are reported to have been made during theweek.Home Waters.2. On the night of the 23rd/24th a large ship, believed to be the Atlanta(4,404 tons), was attacked by Albacores and M.T.Bs. off Calais. Two of theescorting R-boats were severely damaged and set on fire and one of them probably sank. Early on the morning of the 24th the ship entered Dunkirk. An M.T.B.fired a torpedo at her in the harbour entrance, but she was photographed on the28th at Rotterdam, apparently undamaged.On the night of the 25th/26th, E-boats operating off the East Coast were driven off by H.M. ships Mackay (destroyer) and Sheldrake (corvette) : at least one E-boat was damaged.M.T.Bs. have throughout the week made night attacks on enemy trawlersoff the Dutch coast, damaging six ships. On the night of the 28th/29th sixM.T.Bs. engaged enemy coastal craft off the French coast. One R-boat was probably sunk and others were severely damaged. In this engagement, in which enemy coastal batteries joined, five of the M.T.Bs. were damaged and sustainedcasualties of 12 killed and 33 wounded.Norwegian Waters.3. H.M. S/M Satyr, on the 24th, probably sank a 2,000-ton tanker offStadtlandet.Mediterranean.4. During the week ending the 28th, 38,340 tons of supplies were unloadedat Anzio. Shelling has been intermittent and air raids on two successive dayscaused only slight damage to landing craft.Early on the morning of the 30th H.M.S. Laforey (destroyer) was sunk by -boat north of Sicily. The U-boat was later sunk by gunfire from H.M.destroyers Tumult, Blencathra and Hambledon.Allied destroyers on the 23rd, 24th and 28th bombarded German strong pointsnear Anzio, and in the same area H.M.S. Grenville (destroyer) on the 24thrammed and sank an E-boat and took prisoner five Italians and two Germans.On the night of the 27th/28th, coastal forces sank a convoy of six lighterssouth of Leghorn and drove off the escort. On the 21st an M.T.B. sank a smallboat from Sardinia and captured 11 fugitives who were trying to reach German-occupied Italy.5. In the Adriatic on the 19th a Commando force, including Royal Marines,raided Solta Island (south of Split) and captured or killed the entire Germangarrison of 106, of which 78 were taken prisoner.On the night of the 22nd/23rd, R.M. commandos and partisans landed onHvar Island and re-embarked on the night of the 24th/25th with 80 Germanand 20 Italian prisoners, leaving a partisan garrison. The Marines suffered46 casualties. On the following night commandos landed on Brae Island. Onthe 22nd an ML. was damaged during an enemy air raid on Lissa Island.6. In the iEgean on the night of the 18th/.19th an M.L. captured a caiquecarrying plate-glass. On the night of the 25th/26th M.Ls. intercepted fourschooners and four armed caiques south of Mitylene and captured one schoonerand one caique.HM. S/M Unswerving sank an armed caique on the 20th, and on the 26thprobably torpedoed the German s.s. Gerda Toft (1,960 tons) . On the 28th,HM. S/M Sportsman torpedoed the German m.v. M.T. 3 in Monemvasia harbour(S. Greece).7. The Allied submarine base at Beirut was recently closed. It had been used by British flotillas which formerly operated from H.M.S. Medway at alexandria, and by Greek and Polish submarines. Including their successeswhen based on Alexandria, the results achieved by these flotillas were estimated to be as follows : 1,436,400 tons of shipping sunk, 431,932 tons damaged; and thirty bombardments carried out.
Black Sea.8. During the week ending the 24th, Russian aircraft off the mouth of theBug and the west coast of the Crimea sank two Siebel ferries and 14 small craft,and damaged 2 Siebel ferries and 7 small craft. Thirteen enemy aircraft were destroyed.On the 17th the German s.s. Charlotte (1,591 tons) was sunk by mine offSevastopol.On the 22nd a L7-boat shelled a train and a station south-east of Novorossisk.Bast Indies.9. H.M. S/M Taurus bombarded Government House, Ross Island (PortBlair, Andamans) on the 13th.Pacific.Philippines.10. On the 24th a convoy comprising three heavy and four light cruisers, a destroyer and two large tankers, was observed on a south-easterly course in theBasilan Strait (S.W. coast of Mindanao).*Carolines.On the 27th a Liberator sighted some 300,000 tons of shipping in MalakalHarbour (Palau Islands, 500 miles east of Mindanao).New Guinea.An amphibious Allied patrol landed at Bogadjim plantation, south-east ofBogadjim, but found no prepared positions and withdrew after making contact with the enemy.Bismarck A rchipelago.On the 20th two Allied M.T.Bs. raided Loniu, on the south coast ofLos Negros Island. They destroyed 30 laden barges and set fire to 25 buildingscontaining stores and ammunition. On the following day a destroyer bombarded,the enemy positions remaining in the area. On the 23rd destroyers bombardedMussau Island and destroyed a fuel store. On the 24th and again on the 26ththey bombarded Eloae and Pityilu Islands, destroying ships and buildings.Thirty-five Japanese were killed and four captured when M.T.Bs. sank a bargenorth of New Britain. On the 25th three Allied destroyers bombarded villageson Los Negros Island.Solomons.On the night of the 20th/21st an Allied destroyer bombarded enemy positions on the shores of Empress Augusta Bay (Bougainville Island), wherethere has also been further enemy shelling.    &apos;Anti-Submarine Operations.   (To the 29th March.)11. During the week one U-boat was probably sunk and, three possibly sunk.Seventeen attacks have been reported, of which six were carried out by shore-based aircraft, five by carrier-borne aircraft, five by warships and one by a cargo ship.   One of the attacks Avas made in the Mediterranean.Mosquitoes probably sank a U-boat off St. Nazaire on the 27th in a low-levelattack, using 6-pdr. shell. Aircraft from the U.S.S. Block Island (escort carrier)possibly sank two U-boats north of the Canaries, one of them on the 23rd andthe other,-in co-operation with the US: destroyer Bronstein, on the 19th. Onthe 10th a U-boat was possibly sunk by H.M.S. Mull (trawler) off Bizerta.Enemy Intelligence.12. The repairs to the Tirpitz have evidently been completed, as the repairship Monte Rosa left Altenf jord on the 24th on a southerly course. The battleshipcontinues to undergo daily trials.Fifty of the drifters built in Sweden last year to German order were reported on the 15th to be in use at Swinemunde as minesweepers.[27176]   .     &apos; i b
Photographic reconnaissance of the Piraeus indicates that the Germans arenow assembling 60-ft. launches there, 15 of which were seen on the 19th. Theyare preparing to use Volo, in Thessaly, as a naval base.U-boats.13. No important change has taken place in the disposition of the maingroup of U-boats, although there are indications that half-a-dozen or more have moved from the North Atlantic towards the U.S. coast. Two or three have alsoprobably succeeded in passing through the Strait of Gibraltar during the last ten days, raising the Mediterranean force to approximately twenty.Enemy Attack on Shipping.14 No attacks by U-boats during the week under review have been reported.Belated reports state that two ships, one a tanker, were sunk in the Arabian sea on the 19th and 21st.Protection of Seaborne Trade.15, During the week ending the 26th, 1,002 ships in convoy arrived at their destinations. Of these, 320 were in ocean convoys and 682 in British coastal convoys. Two escort carriers, one anti-aircraft ship, 62 destroyers (including18 U.S. destroyers), and 97 sloops, cutters, frigates and corvettes, were employedon escort duties.Four homebound convoys, consisting of 168 ships, and four outward convoys,consisting of 152 ships, arrived at their destinations. One U.S. ship in an inwardconvoy was sunk by U-boat.Allied Minelaying.16. Surface craft have laid mines off the Dutch coast, the Belgian coast andthe Channel Islands. Aircraft laid mines off the Frisian Jslahds, the dutch coast, the north coast of France, and in the Bay of Biscay. British and Alliedsubmarines laid mines in the Bay of Biscay and in the Malacca Strait.Enemy Minelaying, Allied Minesweeping.17. No minelaying by enemy aircraft was suspected. E-boats were active offthe coast on three occasions, but there has been no confirmation of minelaying.Five ground and three moored mines have been destroyed during the week. -The mine totals are : 4,714 ground and 4,369 moored.On the 23rd mines were laid in the Anzio anchorage, and two were destroyed the following day.Enemy Merchant Shipping.18. During the period the 16th to 29th February nine enemy ships totalling22,945 tons were sunk or captured and two ships totalling 6,000 tons were seriously damaged.. Of the ships sunk, seven of 16,995 tons were in theMediterranean. This makes a total during February of 27 ships (62,784 tons)sunk or captured, 12 of them (29,130 tons) in the Mediterranean, and six(18,318 tons) seriously damaged.Four of the larger ships engaged in the ore trade are reported to havearrived at Bilbao during the week.An unidentified Spanish ship, reported as the s.s. Carmen Freiocas, leftSagunto (north of Valencia) on the 22nd with a cargo of iron ore destined for germany. /Russian Intelligence.19. The port of Nikolaev, which was recaptured by the Russians on the29th, was in peace time the main shipbuilding and repair dockyard of the black Sea fleet. It. is unsuitable, and was not used, as a base for large ships, butit can be used for M.T.Bs. and submarines. It is probable, however, that it willbe found to have been extensively damaged by the retreating Germans, who,during their occupation, had at first attempted to put the port into working order.The Russian fleet will have to remain based in the south-eastern corner&apos;of the black Sea until Sevastopol has been recaptured.
MILITARY SITUATION.Russo-German Campaign.   (An outline map is included as an inset.)Northern and Central Sectors.20. There has been only local fighting, although the Germans report Russianattacks in some strength astride the Krichev-Mogilev railway.Kowel Sector:21... The Germans still hold Kowel, but the Russians appear to have pushed forward N.W of the town.Tarnopol-Ribnitsa Sector.22. Although the Russians have not yet claimed Tarnopol, which has changed hands, several times, they have isolated the town by advances north andsouth of it. At the same time they started a new thrust southwards from theline Tarnopol-Proskurov, which is the area where the Germans had made their most determined counter-attacks in recent weeks and had regained a small amountof ground. This Russian advance made rapid progress; in four days theyadvanced 60 miles, reaching the Dniester on a 50-mile front and crossing it to approach Cernauti.Farther east the Russians have quickly extended their bridgehead over theDniester in the Yampol area, reaching the River Pruth on a wide front and push-ing southwards towards Jassy. This was achieved in spite of the fact that theGermans in their withdrawal destroyed the railway bridge at Mogilev-Podolski.Above Jassy, the Pruth is only about 100 yards wide.As a result of these advances the Russians have now captured two of thefour railway crossings over the middle and lower Dniester and have cut therailway leading into Bessarabia from a third. This leaves a German pocketnorth of the Dniester west of Mogilev-Podolski with no bridge for evacuation,while the German forces east of the lower Dniester have only the railway and road bridges at Tiraspol and the ferry at Ovidopol (which has no great capacity)for the evacuation of their remaining men and equipment. A certain amountmight, of course, be evacuated by sea from Odessa, but it seems probable that thebulk of German shipping in the Black Sea is already fully employed in supplying the Crimea, which the Germans still show no signs of evacuating.Lower Bug Sector.23. On the 22nd, the Russians took Pervomaisk; since then they have madeprogress west and S.E. of the town, eliminating the German bridgehead acrossthe Bug at Voznesensk, and later forcing the river on a 30-mile front betweenPervomaisk and Voznesensk. In the extreme south they have captured Nikolaev,which had been stubbornly defended by the Germans.General.24.   The outstanding achievements of the Russians this week have been : (a) Their success in driving to and across the Dniester from the areaTarnopol-Proskurov, where the Germans had offered very strongresistance and launched repeated counter-attacks.&apos;   (6) Their ability to develop so rapidly their original small bridgehead overthe Dniester and push on to the Pruth, thus threatening the line ofretreat of the remaining German forces east of the Dniester.Italy. o25. On the night of the 24th/25th, both the Indian troops on Hangman&apos;sHill and some New Zealanders holding another isolated point immediately tothe S.W. of Cassino, were withdrawn under cover of a diversionary operation from Castle Hill. Our forward line now runs roughly from Castle Hill, N.W. ofthe town, to the railway station in the S.E. We hold the majority of the townitself, in its northern and eastern quarters, but the suburbs, including theContinental Hotel, are still in the hands of the enemy. The attack has thus cometo a halt for the time being,, and reliefs have been taking place.26. In the Adriatic sector there has been more activity than of late,Canadian troops have made numerous patrols in the Tollo sector and further tothe south in the Orsogna area Indian troops have had several clashes with theenemy. , . . .[27176] * &apos; b 2 &quot;
27. In the bridgehead the enemy has shown greater spirit, and on the 23rd,the 27th, and again on the 29th, he carried out small probing raids against theBritish-held sector of the front to the west of the Anzio-Campoleone road.Further regrouping and reinforcement of our forces has proceeded, includingthe arrival of a U.S. formation which had been resting and refitting in reservewith the main Fifth Army. While the enemy&apos;s general attitude in this sector still continues to be defensive, there has been a marked decrease in his medium artillery fire. At the same time there are fairly strong gun areas on both flanks,although there appear to be relatively few in the centre. This decrease is accounted for by the withdrawal of some of his forces, some of them into reserve and some destined for other theatres.Yugoslavia.28. Fighting continues to be&apos;on an increased scale and has spread to many areas throughout Yugoslavia.In Montenegro the Partisans have strengthened their control over com-munications by the capture of Grahovo (25 miles S.E. of Dubrovnik).The fighting in East Bosnia has turned in favour of the Partisans who have begun to counter attack.On the 20th a German column advancing N.E. through Virovitica inSlavonia was attacked by Partisans who inflicted 156 casualties on the enemy.Allied Commandos and Partisan troops have carried out successful raidsin the Dalmatian Islands. (See &quot;Naval Situation.&quot;)Greece.. 29. On the 20th, E.L.A.S. forces engaged an enemy column which wasadvancing into the mountains N.E. of Volo.Burma.  (An outline map showing enemy dispositions is included as an inset.)A arakan.30. Fierce local fighting has continued near the Maungdaw-Buthidaungroad where our troops are slowly gaining possession of the tunnels on the roadwhere it crosses the highest part of the Mayu Ridge. A force of about 500Japanese who infiltrated to the Sinzweya area (seven miles N.W. of Buthidaung)is being mopped up.Chin Hills and Qhindwin.31. Our troops have made some progress both from the north and the southin clearing the road 25 miles north of Tiddim, which was cut recently by japanese forces from the south.In the Tamu area our troops have withdrawn into perimeters protecting thetown as a result of Japanese pressure northwards in the Kabaw Valley andwestwards from the Chindwin.N.E. of Imphal Japanese. attacks have made some progress towards thetown; fierce fighting has taken place in the area.Further to the N.E. in the Somra Tract, the Japanese are reported some20 miles S.E. of Kohima; contact was made on the 28th.Upper Burma.32. Long-range penetration groups operating behind the Japanese line shave inflicted further casualties on the Japanese in encounters in the Mawluarea (on the Katha-Mogaung railway). A Japanese attack on Mawlu.itselfhas been repulsed with heavy casualties.Hukawng Valley.33. Chinese and U.S. troops are now closing in on Shaduzup, 30 miles southof Maingkwan.N.E. Burma.34. Our troops have captured Sumprabum and are in contact with theenemy 20 miles further south.
AIR SITUATION.General Review.35. Activity by home-based squadrons was maintained at a high degree pfintensity both by day and at night. Essen, Berlin, Brunswick and Ijmuidenwere heavily bombed and strong formations of aircraft attacked railway yards,airfields, aircraft assembly plants and military objectives in France.Two night attacks, each by approximately 120 enemy aircraft, were madeon this country.In Italy, heavy attacks were made on enemy rail communications.Transport aircraft operated effectively in Burma.United Kingdom.36. Two night attacks were made, each by about 120 enemy aircraft. In thefirst, approximately 60 aircraft operated over Greater London and a fair-concen-tration was achieved, particularly in the S.E. suburbs. The second raid was veryscattered over the whole of Southern England from Weston-Super-Mare toHastings and nowhere was any degree of concentration attained. On another .night a harassing attack over S.E. England was carried out by 17 enemy aircraft. *A total of 21 enemy aircraft was shot down, including one by Intruders and sixby AA. guns.Home Waters.37. Thirty-three aircraft of Bomber Command iaid, 156 sea-mines in enemy waters.Beaufighters (one missing) of Coastal Command, with fighter cover, attackedan escorted 16-ship convoy off the Frisians; a torpedo-hit was made on a 3,500-ton ship and four other ships and a minesweeper were damaged by cannon fire.&quot; Beaufighters damaged a 3,000-ton ship off the Norwegian coast.Germany and Occupied Territory.38. A total of 15,850 tons of bombs was dropped during a sustained day and night offensive. R.A.F. and U.S.A.A.F. bombers of all types flew, with theirsupporting fighters, approximately 13,050 sorties on these operations, fromwhich 192 aircraft did not return. The enemy lost 116 aircraft in combat and71 were destroyed, on the ground; 20 more were probably destroyed and over 100were damaged.Day.39. On the 23rd, U.S. heavy bombers dropped 1,538 tons on targets inGermany; a heavy attack was made on Brunswick and substantial tonnages were released at Hamm, munster, Ahlen and osnabruck. On the following day,Frankfurt (340 tons) and Schweinfurt (115 tons) were bombed. On the 29th,Fortresses carried out a second attack on Brunswick (358 tons).On the 26th, the base for naval light craft at Ijmuiden was the target forstrong formations of Marauders, Mitchells.and Bostons; 657 tons of bombs were released.Marauders, other medium bombers and bomb-carrying Mustangs droppedover 400 tons on railway yards at Creil, N.E. of Paris. Marauders also bombed the wagon and locomotive works at Haine St. Pierre, 10 miles east of Mons, andthe railway centre of Hirson, 70 miles east of Amiens. Each of the latterobjectives received 240 tons of bombs.On the. 26th, 1,200 tons were released by U.S. heavy bombers on military objectives in Northern France and, during other days, similar targets wereraided by medium and fighter-bombers, which dropped an additional 268 tons.Other activity included attacks by Fortresses and Liberators on 15 airfields,&apos;repair works and assembly plants, the heaviest bombing taking place at st.. Dizier,* Bordeaux/Merignac,^ Chateaudun, Cazaux,* Tours* and Chartres^;the landing-ground at Biarritz, 12 miles from the Spanish frontier, was amongthe targets attacked.* Marauders raided Beaumont-le-Roger and Thunderboltsbombed Bernay-St. Martin. In all, 3,030 tons of bombs were dropped on thisseries of operations,, including 414 tons at St. Dizier and 260 tons at bothBordeaux/Merignac and Chateaudun.-* Vide Appendix VII for assessment of results.
Fighter reaction by the G.A.F. was only slight to moderate during&apos;the heavy attacks on Frankfurt and Schweinfurt. In the Brunswick area, on the 23rd and29th, however, strong opposition was encountered.Night.40. On the night 26th/27 th, aircraft of Bomber Command attackedEssen; 2,765 tons were released. Cloud prevented visual assessment of results.*All but nine of the 705 aircraft despatched on this mission returned safely. Onthe night 24th/25th, 2,322 tons were dropped at Berlin and other targets in thevicinity. Well-grouped fires were seen through drifting cloud; 72 bombers are missing from this operation and three crashed out of the total of 810 aircraft dispatched.Railway yards at Aulnoye, on the Franco-Belgian border,* Vaires, nearParis, and at Laon* and Courtrai* were bombed by Halifaxes and Lancasters.The totals of tons dropped on these targets were, respectively, 807, 306, 472and 298.  Three Halifaxes were lost.Lancasters of No. 5 Group carried out three attacks on aero-engine works at. Lyons; a total of 145 tons of bombs was dropped.Mosquitoes flew about 200 sorties in raids over Germany and on &quot; intruder &quot;operations, from which three aircraft are missing. Kiel, Hanover, Dortmundand 12 other cities were among the objectives attacked.Opposition by enemy night-fighters was strong during the attack on Berlinbut, at Essen, it was relatively ineffective.Italy.41. The Mediterranean Allied Air Force flew a total of 8,529 sorties;32 Allied aircraft are missing and 39 enemy aircraft were destroyed.The main bombing effect was directed against railway communications.The heaviest raid was made on Verona railway centre, in which over200 heavy bombers dropped 500 tons of bombs. The attack was well concentratedand many craters cut all the through tracks and the majority of the siding&apos;stracks; in addition, considerable damage to repair shops and other buildingswas caused and at least 150 units of rolling-stock were derailed or destroyed.At Mestre (6 miles N. of Venice) 424 tons were.released and damage comparable to that at Verona, resulted. Other centres heavily bombed by Fortresses andLiberators were Milan (300 tons), Turin (272 tons), Bolzano (366 tons) andRimini (250 tons). The Allied casualties in these operations were eight bombers* and two fighters.Good concentrations were obtained on Campo Di Marte, the railway centre of Florence, by 72 Marauders and on Padua and Vicenza at night by similarforces of Wellingtons. Other railway centres that were bombed were Perugia,Poggibonsi, Rimini and Sulmona. The ports of Fiume and Leghorn were also attacked.In conjunction with the attacks on railway centres, bridges and viaducts were successfully bombed and damaged at Orvieto, Arezzo, Tarquinia, Marsciano,Antrodoco (16 miles W.N.W. Aquila), Falconara (7 miles W. of Ancona), Rignano(21 miles N. of Rome), Corchiano and Fabro.In the battle area fighter-bombers and light bombers were active against gun positions, dumps and other military objectives. Rimini and Forli airfields were attacked by 23 Kittyhawks and 11 enemy aircraft were destroyed on the ground and hangars were set on fire. Enemy casualties as a result of combat in the battle area were 21 destroyed and Allied fighter casualties were 11.Yugoslavia and Albania.42. Over 190 sorties were flown by fighter-bombers against enemy coastal shipping. One 200-ft. landing craft was set on fire, and two Siebel ferries, fourE-boats and six small craft were destroyed; over 23 other small vessels were seriously damaged.In the Split area M.T. vehicles were attacked and damaged and buildings and warehouses were hit. At Kavaji (20 miles S.S.E. Durazzo) barracks and stores were bombed, and eight M.T. vehicles destroyed.iEgean.43. Operations were curtailed by unfavourable weather. Six caiques were destroyed or seriously damaged.* Vide Appendix VII for assessment of results.
Russia.44. The weather remained bad throughout the week. Details of russian air operations are very limited.There has been little activity for some weeks by the German long-range bombers in South Russia and, it is likely that with increasing difficulties of communications and the constant isolation of army units, these aircraft areparticipating to a greater extent in supply duties.Burma.45. Between the 21st and the 28th a total of 1,897 offensive sorties was flown.In the Chin Hills and Upper Chindwin areas enemy troop concentrations,positions, villages and communication targets were attacked in considerablestrength principally by Vengeances and Hurricanes. Ten Lightnings inter-cepted 35 enemy aircraft about to land at Anisakan (20 miles E. of Mandalay)airfield, seven of which were shot down and two others were destroyed on theground for the loss of two Lightnings.Enemy stores and dumps were the main targets in the Myitkyina area, thoughenemy positions were also attacked; fighter-bombers successfully attackedbridges. In the Katha area enemy troops and camps were attacked withfragmentation bombs.Beaufighters and Hurricanes were mainly responsible for successful attacks on river-craft on the Mayu and Kaladan rivers in the Arakan; enemy positionswere also bombed.Attacks on communication were widespread and effective; a total of at least261 river-craft were destroyed or damaged, also 47 M.T. vehicles, 12 locos.,2 trains, 49 units of rolling stock and 6 warehouses. In the Arakan threebridges were damaged; in the Upper Chindwin and Chin Hills area three hits were obtained on a bridge near Kalemyo, and a bridge over the Manipur Riverwas rendered unserviceable; near Myitkyina the approach to one bridge was destroyed, the approach to three others damaged and a road and railway bridgewas seriously damaged; near Bangkok and Moulmein, two bridges were destroyed,five probably destroyed and two damaged.A total of 744 transport aircraft operated in different areas of Burma.A total of 1,951 tons of stores and equipment was delivered, at least 2,274 troops and 100 mules were landed and 1,500 casualties were evacuated.Enemy activity was on a comparatively small scale; a total of 35 enemy aircraft was shot down for the loss of 14 Allied aircraft. An attack was madeon Digboi (N. Assam) by 18 enemy bombers, escorted by 20 fighters; U.S. fighterssuccessfully intercepted the raid and destroyed 11 bombers and 13 fighters;three Mustangs are missing. A small scale raid was made on our troops in theTamu area and two enemy aircraft were destroyed by Spitfires.Pacific Zone.New Guinea.46. On the 21st, about 200 Allied bombers, operating in the Wewak area,dropped 142 tons of bombs on the float-plane base and barge repair depot atKairiru Island and destroyed stores at the main supply depot at Brandi Plantationand at Murik Lagoon.With the exception of, two days when operations were held up by weather,targets in the Wewak/Boram district were subjected to daily attacks the objectives included A.A. gun emplacements, enemy personnel and shipping.Approximately 450 tons were dropped and good results were reported.Liberators and Mitchells released 150 tons at Hansa Bay, Mitchells effectivelyattacked Dagua airfield and a camp area at Alexishafen and a formation of medium bombers sank numerous small craft near Aitape. Several enemy aircraft were destroyed on Tadji airfield.Neiv Britain.47. Between the 20th and 26th, heavy, medium and naval aircraft kept up the daily offensive without pause except when, on the 23rd, adverse weatherintervened. At Rabaul, about 450 tons were dropped on the four nearby airfields,naval aircraft bombed the docks and several attacks were made on gun emplace-ments round the town.   Ammunition dumps at Tawui Point, a fuel dump at
Keravia Bay and a supply base at Rataval (Talele Bay) were bombed withsatisfactory results and a radar station was destroyed at Adler Bay (GazellePeninsula).Solomon Islands.48. During the six days ended the 25th, a total of 204 aircraft operatedagainst gun sites and installations in the Torokina and Kahili areas (Bougain-ville).   Supply dumps and the airfields at Kara and Kahili were also attacked.A dmiralty Islands.49. On the 26th, in support of Allied troops, a force of Bostons bombed and machine-gunned Japanese strong-points on the western point of ManusIs] and.Marshall and Caroline Islands.50. Approximately 250 sorties were flown by Liberators and light bombersin raids on targets on enemy-occupied atolls in the Marshall group. Liberatorsbombed Ponape, Kusaie and Japutik in the Carolines.Wake Island.51. On the 18th, hits were made on storage depots and barracks when theimportant enemy anchorage was attacked by Liberators; 48 tons were dropped.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.52. Bombs were dropped on three nights. On the night 23rd/24th a fewbombs were dropped in Kent, Surrey and Sussex and in the London Region, atCoulsdon and Croydon. On the following night bombs were dropped overa wide area in the same three counties, and in 28 London. boroughs mostlysouth of the river, causing some large fires. One bomb was also dropped inBuckinghamshire, at Beaconsfield. On the 27th/28th bombs were scattered overa wide area in Devon, Dorset and Somerset with one at Goldcliff, Monmouthshire.In Kent and Sussex bombs were also dropped at a number of places near thecoast. The official German broadcast described this as &quot; a heavy raid on Bristol &quot;and a sharp attack on London &quot; highly concentrated in point of time.&quot; In factno bombs fell on either of these places.Damage.53.   On the 23rd/24th bomb damage affected production at GreshamTransformers, Ltd., Feltham.On the 24th/25th, there was a 70-pump fire in West Norwood, a 56-pumpfire in the Fleet Street area and a 28-pump fire in Croydon. There were 81 fires inCroydon and 60 in Beckenham. All were under control in a few hours. At Brixtonhouse damage was extensive, and in the City the Temple Church was damaged.Railway traffic was temporarily blocked between East and South Croydon, nearBeckenham Junction and at Maiden Road; also between Horsham and Warnhamin Sussex where normal working was resumed on the 29th. Elsewhere, outside london, there was little damage. Civilian casualties for the night totalled39 killed and 118 serious, of which 14 killed and 43 serious were in Croydon.On the 27th/28th, very little damage was caused. Railway traffic was .suspended for about 12 hours between Exeter and Bristol both on the direct linenear Weston-Super-Mare and on the alternative loop. Rather more damage was caused at Weston than elsewhere and there were a few casualties. At an R.O.factory at Cardiff casualties, 9 killed and 14 serious, were caused by an A/Ashell.Casualties.54.   Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 hours on the29th were 54 killed and 141 seriously injured..
Appendices I, II, III (C), and YI will be published periodically.OSAPPENDIX III (A)Non-Tankers under British Control.Analysis by availability.1,600 g.t. and over.(Thousand gross tons).End of month.Vessels not engaged in or available for carrying cargoes to or from overseas countries (including all troopships).Troopships^).Other vessels wholly on fighting service^-).immobilised by damage or repair.Engaged in coasting or Inter-coastal trade.New vessels not yet allocated, &amp;c.employment information incomplete.,  Total.Vessels carrying or availablefor carrying overseas civil or military cargoes.Total.1943-March   .april may june july august .SeptemberOctober ...NovemberDecember1944-January...February2,1032,0982,0982,1272,1202,1532,1802,2092,2082,2172,3312,3131,3981,3811,3821,3661,3381,2871,2511,2591,2631,2711,1881,3261,7731,6451,3971,1771,0061,9351,0411,1761,2221,4451,2761,2701,1661,1431,1641,2731,2651,5031,6731,5971,7081,6801,7001,608196656583670853158105734520161410131463336,4796,3486,1126,357(2)5,7776,060(2)6,235   &apos;6,2756,4626,7216,5706,5697,7427,7258,0347,8898,4506,3928,4498,5668,6178,6078,8989,01314,22214,07314,14614,24614,22714,45314,68514,84115,07915,32815,46815,582(l) Including those under repair.(2) Including vessels temporarily allocated for operations.C5
APPENDIX III (B)Tankers under British Control.Analysis by availability.1,600 g.t. and over.(Thousand gross tons.)End of Month.	Tankers not engaged in or available for carrying cargoes to or from overseas countries.						Tankers carrying or available for carrying overseas civil or Service cargoes.	Total.	Engaged in Fleet attendance.^)	Immobilised by damage or repair.	Engaged in coasting or inter-coastal trade.	Employed as depot ships.	Employment information incomplete.	Total.		1943-March......... April      ..........., May       ...... June      ...... July     ........-August September        .........	360 337 895 395 409    1	909 917 863 734 769	260 . i 234 262 246 285 261 283	41 41 33 33 39 39 47	3	1,570 1,529 1,553 1,408   . 1,502 1,427 1,439 1,620 1,553 1,540 1,522 1,455	2,004 2,128 2,102 2,212 2,133 2,206 2,206 2,019    . 2,108 2,172 2,240 2,322	3,574 3,657 3,655 3,620 3,o35 3,633 3,645	447 424	680 685 779 780 765 730 678						October   ......      ...... November        ......... December............ 1944-J anuary............ February ...	456 425 442 455 452		338 294 279 295 271	47 54 54 42 51				3,639 . 3,661 3,712 3,762 8,777(l) For August 1943, and succeeding months, includes those under repair.Appendix III (2) will in future be called Appendix III (C) and will be inserted in a subsequent Resume.
i3 16 8APPENDIX IV.Enemy Merchant Ship Losses assessed to 29th February, 1945.Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously Damaged.		Damaged.		Total........ ,\y\                   -*&apos;-&apos;)-		v;;!vBB;&apos;i&apos; No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross . Tons.	No.	-:- Gross Tons.German  ...       ...       ... Italian    ... Other enemy ships and ships useful to the enemy Total   ......	614 955 489	2,460,973 3,297,064 948,914	210 175 43	514,632 708,607 108,973	413 269 75	1,049,748 1,042,644 304,742	1,237 1,399 607	4,025,353 5,048,315 1,362,359	2,058	6,706,951	428	1,332,212 1 757 1		2,396,864	3,243	10,436,027Amlhe !?b!f d0GS n0- include casualties inflicted on the enemy bv on   Pn   iAllies, which are estimated at about 2 016 00ft o-r^00 wJ i7      -Russian.or about 2,856,600 gross tons estimated to number 618 ships sunk,36,000 gross tons of German sbippingsoTd to S&amp;t^f      ^APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. and Allied Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.24th March. H.S.L. 2706 sunk by aircraft off Orfordness.21th March.-M.T.Bs.  699, 698, 361  and 354 damaged by gunfire offGravelines.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 7 killed; 6 missing; 3 wounded (including 2 W.R.N.S.).Ratings : 16 killed; 47 missing.; 4 wounded.APPENDIX YII.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.France.Airfields (General). Ground reports in increasing degree bear witness tothe severe damage done to aircraft on the ground and in hangars in many of therecent heavy airfield attacks. For example, during the U.S.A.A.F. attack onVillacoublay, on the 25th February, more than two dozen fighters and transportaireaft on the landing-ground, and a large number in hangars, were destroyed. Onthe same day, in the American attack on Chateau Roux-Le Martinerie, some 30aircraft were destroyed or damaged on the ground, and an equal number inhangar, and repair shops. In this latter attack, one aircraft was in such a hurryto get away that it crashed into the doors of its hangar which were not wide enough open, and left both its wings behind. -:[27176] d
An immediate interpretation of photographs taken after the numerousattacks on airfields on the 27th March shows the following results :  iBordeaux-Merignac Airfield. Heavy damage has been caused to the airfield buildings and, while this is most severe on the southern boundary, instal-lations in practically every part of the airfield have suffered. Several largehangars and many workshops as well as other buildings have been destroyed or damaged in varying degree. The aircraft assembly plant of S.N.C.A. du Sud-Guest has also been affected and the main building has received a direct hit.There are large concentrations of craters on the north and S.E. of the landing-ground with at least 20 on the runways.Chartres Airfield. On the west and N.W. side of the airfield, one largedouble hangar has been completely destroyed and another half destroyed, whiletwo workshops, one large and the other small, have also suffered partial destruc-tion. Several other buildings have been damaged more or less severely. There is a heavy concentration of craters on the west side of the airfield and about five onthe extreme W.S.W. end of the runway.La Rochelle / La Leu Airfield. Damage is confined to the western boundary of the airfield, where a large hangar has been severely damaged and three smallerhangars less severely. Three small workshops have been completely destroyed and a large five-bay workshop severely damaged. In the hutted camp, out of atotal of 15 huts, six have been destroyed and six damaged and there are severaldirect hits among stores in the stores dump. Eight small unidentified, buildings have also been destroyed or damaged.Pau/Pontlong Airfield. The hangar, barracks and landing area of the southlanding-ground have suffered heavily. Many hangars, several of them large, havebeen completely destroyed and many more have been damaged, some of themseverely. Other buildings have been gutted and a large number of barrackbuildings destroyed and damaged. There are at least 85 craters on the landing-ground.St. Jean d&apos;A ngely A airfield.-Widespread damage has been caused among themain buildings, both in the west and S.E. of the airfield, and heavy damage hasbeen done to the hangars, all of which have now been severely affected by thisraid and the attack of the 31st December. In addition, heavy damage has been caused to barrack buildings in the west dispersal area, where a large number ofhuts have been destroyed and severely damaged. A water-tower has been destroyed. In the S.E. dispersal area, three open aircraft shelters have been damaged. Craters are spread throughout the dispersal areas and on the landing-ground and tarmac in front of the hangars.T ours j Par cay Me slay Airfield. The weight of the attack has fallen in and around the main station buildings and several workshops and store buildings havebeen destroyed. Two double hangars have suffered severely and a single hangar,damaged in the previous raid., has now been almost completely destroyed. Twobarrack huts have been badly burnt. There are a large number of fresh craters on the landing-ground, with 18 on the N.W./S.E. runway and nine on theN.E./S.W. runway.Biarritz A airfield.-*Photographs taken on the 27th March after theTJ.S.A.A.F. attack earlier in the day, show that 10 buildings in the living quartersarea and two buildings in the ammunition storage area at the E. end of the airfield have been destroyed. The hangar and two workshops at the N.E. cornerhave been damaged.Cazaux Airfield. An immediate interpretation of photographs (some ofwhich are obscured by the smoke of fires still burning) taken about 2\ hours afterthe U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 27th March, shows heavy damage to buildings andto the landing ground. Many hangars and aircraft shelters on the Northern,Western and Eastern sides of the airfield have been destroyed or damaged, while at least 15 buildings in a hutted camp to the W. of the airfield have sufferedsimilarly. Six aircraft, and probably many more, on the landing ground and inthe dispersal areas have been destroyed or damaged, and there are heavyconcentrations of craters on the landing ground.Tows.-Photographs, taken after the attack on the 27th Maren, show that damage is concentrated in the southern half of the Usine Liotard AircraftRepair Works.  A multi-bay workshop and a long rectangular building adjacent
to it have been partially destroyed, while another small building adjoining hasbeen demolished. There is also some damage in the central area of the works,though this is not so severe.St. Dizier I Robinson Airfield.-Photographs, taken on the 26th March, showthat, as a result of the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 24th March, severe damage hasbeen caused in the S.E. dispersal area where three hangars have been destroyed and a fourth damaged, and to the administrative buildings in the N.E. corner-ofthe airfield. In this area, four barrack-type buildings have been gutted and a fifth almost gutted, while three more buildings have been destroyed and five havebeen damaged. A barrack-type building in the S.W. dispersal area has alsobeen gutted. Craters which were made on the Southern edge of the landing ground (with two oh E/W runway) have already been filled in, and this fact isan indication of the importance the Germans attach to this airfield.Courtrai Marshalling Farefe-Photographs, taken after the attack on the.26th/27th March, show heavy damage in the reception, forwarding andmarshalling sidings. In the reception sidings, the engine sheds have been severely damaged, the turntable cut by a direct hit, railway tracks cut in atleast 20 places and several wagons damaged. In the marshalling sidings, thelong narrow shed has been severely damaged, tracks cut in at least 30 places and,again, many wagons damaged. In the forwarding sidings, further wagons havebeen damaged and tracks have been cut in about ten places. There is further damage of a similar nature in the passenger, stock and market sidings, while thetracks between the goods depot and the main station have been cut in about sevenplaces and main-line tracks in about 20 places.Laon Marshalling Yards: An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the 26th March shows that, as a result of the R.A.F. attack on the23rd/24th March, there are two concentrations of craters in the marshalling yards. One is in the centre, across the converging lines at the exit from thesorting sidings, and the other is in the N.W. part of the yards on the tracksserving the locomotive repair shop which has itself been damaged. Many shedsand small buildings in various parts of the yards have been destroyed or damaged.Aulnoye Marshalling Yard.-An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the 26th March after the. U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 15th March and theR.A.F. attack on the 25th/26th March, shows that the central portion of one ofthe carriage and wagon repair shops has been destroyed and three adjoiningbuildings damaged. The other carriage and wagon repair shop has sustainedsome damage and two small railway buildings have been severely damaged. Manydirect hits have cut the railway tracks and damaged and derailed rolling stock.South of the marshalling yard, the locomotive shed has been half destroyed andtracks in this area have also been cut.Germany.Essen. An immediate interpretation of photographs of poor quality showsthat, as a result of the attack on the.26th/27th March, fresh damage has oeencaused in many parts of the town and several workshops of Krupps have againsuffered severely. The main passenger station.has also received damage, whileone or two fires were still burning in the town more than 36 hours after the attack.Frankfurt. An immediate interpretation of photographs marred.by cloud and smoke shows that, as a result of the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 20th March andthe R.A.F. attacks on the 18th/19th and 22nd/23rd March, two very important industrial targets have suffered severely. The works of Alfred Teves (aircraftcrankshafts, Priority 1 + ) has been very heavily damaged, and 19 out of 24buildings, including a large hew machine shop, have been destroyed or severely damaged, while a branch of the same firm to the north-west has also sufferedpartial destruction, and, in this instance, 13 out of 20 buildings have been destroyed or severely damaged (including the main machine shop). AdlerwerkeA.G. (A.F.V.&apos;s-Priority 1) had also been heavily damaged, and GriesheimElectron-Chemical Works (Priority 1) has received moderate damage.      -Rebstock airfield, west of the city, and the adjoining marshalling yard, havebeen very heavily damaged; at the airfield, nearly every building has been damaged or destroyed. -The railway station and warehouses in the east harbour, and the Grossmarkand Importhalle in the same, area, have been severely affected, and the Autobahn
bridge over the river on the west side of the town has received a direct hit. Inaddition, considerable damage has been caused to business and residential property in the town, and many fires were still burning some 12 hours after the attack.Photographs of rather small scale taken on the 25th March show that, asresult of the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 24th March, further heavy damage was caused to business and residential property in the heart of the city and manyfires were still burning in this area more than 30 hours after the attack. Inaddition, the works of Hartmann and Braun (fuses and firing apparatus forsubmarine mines Priority 1) suffered severely and extensive fresh damage was caused in and near the railway marshalling and goods yards.Augsburg.- Further photographs, taken on the 3rd and 16th March, permit,of a final intepretation of damage caused by the U.S.A.A.F.- attack on the 25thFebruary, and the R.A.F. attack on the 25th-26th February. These confirm andamplify the damage previously reported, and show that the greater part of theold city has been devastated. Apart from the industrial area which has beenravaged, by fire, nearly 60 per cent, of the fully built-up area, and about 14 percent, of the 50/70 per cent, built-up area has been destroyed or severely damaged.In all, the area of devastation amounts to almost 450 acres.The two chief industrial targets in the town have suffered heavily. TheM.A.N. Works the largest producers of Diesel engines in Germany is the worst affected, and practically the entire plant has been destroyed or severely damaged, some of the largest shops being completely gutted. The MesserschmittWorks have received important damage in nearly all parts of the factory; manybuildings have been destroyed and others damaged.The important firm of Martin Schmittner (making aircraft components) hasalso been damaged severely.East of the city, the majority of the factories are engaged in the textile industry and nearly all of them have been destroyed or severely damaged.Altogether 26 factories in the town have been damaged or destroyed.Many public and civic buildings were destroyed by the fire which ragedthrough the heart of the city, and these include the Rathaus, the Stock Exchange,.the Law Courts, and the local Government Offices.   A transformer station andtwo tramway depots were among public utility buildings severely damaged.Austria.Steyr. Photographs of rather small scale taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attacks on the 23rd and 24th February from Italian bases, show that damage in theSteyr-Daimler Puch Works was widespread and heavy. The largest machineshop covering eight acres was destroyed over -an area of three acres, and a large;part of the machine and assembly shop was also destroyed. Many other buildings were severely damaged and these include the M/T and A/C assembly plant, thefoundry, the power plant, the small-arms plant and the timber workshops. the extensive offices have also suffered heavily, while many other buildings have been damaged less severely.The Steyrwaffen works were hit in the first attack, and the large ball-bearingand cage factory and the offices sustained slight damage.
O.R.5942WEST RUSSIAAND THEBALTIC STATES



</content>
</cab>
