<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/122/0 images: 21-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCTO.CTT IS THE PROPERTY OF T!IS BRITANNIC MAJEffTYT3 aggglgggSOTtSE0H8T. COPY HO,&apos; 0 A B I II J] T.Relative&quot;hankey or officers of the Navy, Amy and Air Foroe. ADMIRALTY. tTeob^arifliui for the Cabinet.Tha present position in regard to relative rank of Officers of the Navy, Amv, and Air Force is very anomalous and unsatisfactory. 2. This is due to two facts:-(a)    That the rules as to relative rank between the navy and the Array differ in important respects fran the corresponding rules in practically all other countries: (h)    mbat the Air Force in recently adopting new titles of rank have appropriated certain naval titles but have claimed to retain a higher relative rank than the titles nomally oarry0 3,       In practically all foreign countries the following relative rank applies as between the Naval and Military Officers mentionedl)    Captain (Navy) ................. Colonel (Array).2)    Commander,Oa&quot;Ditaine de ^negate.. Lieut.Colonel Oaeitano di Fregata etc,(Navy) (Array)4.       ^his countrv of course insists that British Naval Officers must rank, equally with Foreign Naval Officers, jae. the British Captain, Roll., ranks strictly with the United States, French, or Italian Naval Captain, and the British Commander R.N., with the United States Commander, tbe French ^anitaine do Fregate, the Italian Oaoitano di Fregata, etc.5*       But the rules as to relative rank as between British Naval and Military Officers introduce a serious complication, being as below:-(l)    Captain over 3 years (Navy)...,. Colonel (Army) (2)     Captain under 3 years (Navy),... Lieut,Col.(Array)(3)    Commander (Navy).,............... Lieutenant Col,(Army) but junior of that rank.6.       The British Ocranander R.N.,, therefore ranks after the Britisb Lieutenant Colonelv but with the United States&quot; Commander who in his turn ranks with&quot;the United States Lieutenant Colonel.7.      It follows that on any occasion when British and Foreign Naval and Military Officers are assembled together, difficulties arise owing to the want of uniformity in the rules as to relative rank.8. ,     there is also constant pressure on the part of foreign Naval authorities to get the relative rank of their Naval Officers raised in relation to ours, on the ground that their relative ra^nk in relation to the Army is higher.9.       A further complication has now been introduced by the Air Force.    The Air Force originally adopted Military titles: and the Colonel RoA^F,, and Lieutenant--Colonel R*A.F^ necessarily.had the same relative rank as the Army Colonel and Lieutenant-Colonel.10. The Air Foroe Ibs now substituted sem-Naval Titles, vis: Croup Captain and Wlng-Oomroander, but claims to retain the relative rank associated with the Military ^itleso    ^his would have the effect of making the ftooup Captain rank with a Naval Captain of ovor 3 years seniority and the V/ing . Corridor vlth a Captain R.N* of under 3 years instead of a norland or R.N.
Hp      The similarity of mitie and.general approximation of duties makes this differentiation in relative rank most unfair from the point of view of the Navy.    As soon as.it &quot;becomes known abroad, it is &quot;bound to reopen in an acute form the foreign contention that British Naval Captains and Commanders are not entitled to rank strictly with Foreign Naval Captains and Commanders,12,      I suggest that the Cabinet should appoint an impartial Arbitrator?of Cabinet rank^to consider -the whole question, and that his report f; if apoVove-d by the Cabinet * should be submitted to the K^ng.(initialled)L. of- F*6, 4t. 21,

</content>
</cab>
