<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/122/0 images: 95-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
III-v   ft, fritfsAxMsPjs      - - .      &apos; &quot;(THIS DOCUKSiTT IS THB PROPERTY OP HIS ERITA^IC MAJESTY&quot;! S GOV-^i&amp;IiiT.)%COifiTIDSHTIAL.CABINET. ^C.J,, 2818.THE KIBBRS&apos; STRIKE,Notes of Conferences held &quot;between the Government and Representatives of the Railwaymen and Transport Workers on Saturday, 9th April, 1921.The following were presentThe Prime Minister,The Rt. Hon. Austen Chamberlain, M.P.,The Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Horne, G.B.D.,K.C.,M.P.,The Rt. Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,The Rt, Hon. T. J. Maonamara, H. K,The Rt. Hon. Sir 3ric Geddes, G.C.B.,G.B.E.,M.P.,The Rt. Hon. VT. C. Bridgeman, M.P,,Sir M,P.A.Hanl:ey, G.C.B., Mr, T, Jones,Representatives cf the NATIONAL UNION OP RAILWAYMEN,The Rt. Hon. J. H. Thomas, M,P.,Mr. C T. Cramp,Mr. Abraham,Mr, D. Thomas,Mr. J, C. Allkn,Mr. W, Bobbie,Representatives of the TRANSPORT TORKEHS1 FSKjRATIOU.Mr, H, Gosling, Mr, R, \7illiams, Mr, E, Bevin, Mr. J, Sexton, M.P,, Mr. Ben. Smith, Mr. 3&quot;. Cotter.
10.a.m. FIRST CONFERENCE.

A statement of the proceedings of this Conference as made by the Prime Minister is summarised in the Minutes of the Conference of Ministers held on Saturday, April 9th at 12 noon and has been already circulated.

2.30 p.m. SECOND CONFERENCE.

In the course of this Conference, of which at the request of the Deputation, no notes were taken, further discussion took place on the question of preserving the mines, the Deputation urging that the subject should be taken up but not necessarily disposed of at a Conference of miners and owners with the Prime Minister in the Chair. The Government, on the other hand, pressed for an undertaking before the resumption of negotiations, that there should be no interference with the pumping arrangements made by or at the request of the Government, nothing which would necessitate the use of force by the Government.

The Deputation left to consult the Miners&apos; Executive and returned at 7.15 p.m.

7.15p.m. THIRD CONFERENCE

The miners returned with the following formula which the Miners&apos; Executive were prepared to accept:-

"The Federation desire it to be conveyed to the Government that learning that negotiations are to be opened unconditionally we propose to advise our members to refrain from doing anything which would necessitate the use of force in any district, and to ask the Government to fix the Conference for tomorrow morning (Sunday) and further to ask the Triple Alliance to keep in session until the Federation can report progress to it, and we await the return of our colleagues to ? the time of the meeting."

The representatives of the Government adjourned to conside this formula and to draft an alternative.
On mooting tho deputation a.sain agreement wasreached to the following(1) The Government shall suiomon a Conference of the representatives of the Joiners1 federation and the coal owners to meet at tho Board of Trade, on Monday, April 11th at 11 a.m, to discuss all questions in Oisoute between the parties.(2) The. . inors1 federation shall tonidit issue notices to the Branches of the federation lire; in 2 their menbers to abstain from all action which will interfere with the measures necessary for securing the safety of the mines or will necessitate the use of foroe &quot;by the Government.The Deputation withdrew at 0,20 p.m, in order to submit -tiifrir formula to the Minors&apos; Executive whom the;/ were due to meet at 9 p,ra.At 10,30 p.m, a mossago was reoeived announcing the aooeptanco of the formula by the Miners1 Executive.2 Whitehall Gardens, riiwi April 9th, 1921*

</content>
</cab>
