<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/122/0 images: 281-286</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]    215Printed for the Cabinet. April 1921.SECRET.CP. 2850.mm       ooCABINET.SPECIAL WEEKLY REPORT ONUNEMPLOYMENT.No. 25.WEEK ENDED APRIL 15, 1921.T. J. MACNAMARA,Ministry of Labour.
I. NOTE ON UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION IN UNITED KINGDOM ONAPRIL 15, 1921.1. The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent.The average for the ten years prior to the war, according to Trade Union unem-ployment figures, was 4-7 per cent. It was as high as 7-8 per cent, in 1908 and 7-7 per cent, in 1909.Throughout 1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent, in September and 3-2 per cent, in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.The figures for 1920 are :- Per cent.To the end of January   ...        ...        ... ...        ...        ...     2-9February ... March April May June July August SeptemberOctober    ...     .   . November December ...The figures for 1921 are:-To the end of-January   ... February  ... March1-6 11 0-9 11 1-2 1-4 16 2-9 5-3 3-7 606-9 8-5 1002. Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges.1920.				1921.				Aug. 27.		i nov. 12.1  dec. 3.		jan. 7.	feb. 4.	feb. 11.	feb. 18.	feb. 25men  civilians ex-service   .. boys women girls totals  ..	86,1,76 142,600 17,608 58,982 17,430	134,868 239,816 21^872 97,964 22,237	137,222 263,553 21,379 119,886 23,663	250,365 312,147 35,704 215,869 41,441	357.701 362,866 48,507 286,821 55,419	372,012 375,809 51,167 295,528 54,367	397,181 379,175 51,115 300,408 55,254	420,471 381,952 51,143 310,222 54,430	318,096	516,757	565,703	855,526	1,111,314	1,148,883	1,183,133	1,218,2181921.	mar. 4.	mar. 11.	mar. 18.	mar. 24.	april 1.	april 8.	april 15.f	men  civilians ex-service  .. boys women girls	450,651 379,184 51,571 319,394 &apos; 53,877	492,097 382,196 53,594 335,696 54,531	534,075 378,866 55,923 -354,683 54,731	j 936,298* 57,478 365,096 54,884	1,002,913* 62,655 382,573 57,939	1,092,358* 67,893 394,388 60,968	1,143,200* 71,200 409,000 65,000	totals ..	1,254,677	1,318,114	1,378,278	1,413,751	1,506,080	1,615,607	1,686,900	* separate figures not yet available. . f advanced figures.in addition to the above figures, which represent persons wholly unemployed, approximately 844,000 adults are in receipt of unemployment benefit or out-of-work donation under systematic short-time schemes.
216GENERAL.3. While the coal dispute has caused increased unemployment, the present position, as shown by figures of unemployment, is perhaps not so alarming as was anticipated. The iron and steel trade is the industry at present most affected by the coal stoppage, and unemployment is rapidly increasing in the North of England and Scotland among employees at the blast furnaces and steel works. The position in the shipbuilding industry has not appreciably altered, and the coal shortage will probably not affect this industry for several weeks The uncertain outlook caused by the coal stoppage has had an unfortunate effect on the cotton trade, which, as mentioned in the last report, showed some signs of recovery. Although most of the mills have several weeks&apos; supply of coal on hand, the general uncertainty of the position prevents development of trade. No further improvement can be expected in either the textile or the boot and shoe trades until the coal dispute is settled. Some pottery works have been obliged to close down on account of shortage of coal, and at St. Helens, Lancashire, Messrs. Pilkington, Glass Manufacturers, have placed the whole of their 10,000 employees on day-to-day notices as a precautionary measure. In the London area no considerable discharge of workpeople is at present reported.II. EMERGENCY WORK.On the 19th October, the Prime Minister made a statement in the House of Commons on the proposals of the Government to provide against unemployment. A further statement was made in the House by the Minister of Labour on the 21st December.1. The schemes of work then outlined (which have been more fully described in Report No. 22 for the week ended the 18th March, 1921, and earlier reports to the Cabinet) included the following : (a.) Arterial Roads.The anticipating of a four years&apos; programme for arterial roads in London and in the Provinces.(b.) Road Maintenance.Pressing forward with the Ministry of Transport programme of road classifica-tion and maintenance grants.(c.) Housing.The acceleration of the lay-out of roads and sewers on approved housing schemes work brought forward as additional to the main programme.(d.) Unemployment Grants Committee.The distribution by the Unemployment Grants Committee, under the Chairmanship of Viscount St. Davids, of a sum of  3,000,000 for the purpose of assisting Local Authorities on relief schemes other than house-building work and certain kinds of road work.(e.) Unemployment Insurance.The amendment of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, in order to enable benefit to be paid to workpeople who had been unemployed since the Act came into operation and could not therefore qualify for benefit.2. More recently the following additional measures have been devised by the Government, viz. : (a.) The Unemployment Insurance Act, 1921.Under this Act, which became law on Jdie 3rd March, the rate of benefit was raised from 15s. to 20s. for men and from 12 , to 16s. for women, and it was provided[6120] B 2
that benefit might be drawn tor sixteen weeks in each of two periods running from the 3rd March, 1921, to the 2nd November, 1921, and from the 3rd November, 1921, to the 2nd July, 1922; after the last date benefit to be drawn to the extent of twenty-six weeks in each insurance year.(b.) Alternative Work.Alternative work has been arranged by the War Office at five national factories. This includes waggon-repairing, manufacture of medals, coin blanks, locomotives and new waggons and miscellaneous articles for the Post Office and for private firms.Alternative Avork has also been adopted at His Majesty&apos;s Dockyards and other Admiralty Industrial Establishments, but fresh entries for this work ceased on the 19th March. 1921.(c.) Short-time in Government Establishments.This policy was introduced on the 24th January, 1921, in His Majesty&apos;s Dockyards and other Admiralty Establishments and in the Royal Ordnance Factories. Woolwich Arsenal and other National Factories administered bv the War Office.It was also introduced, where practicable, in the remaining War Departments, Industrial and Semi-Industrial Departments and Factories from the 7th February. No further entries in Admiralty Establishments have been made since the 19th March. 1921.(d.) 6: oe of Works Emergency Pro. amme.Ti Is includes a considerable ami .nt of decorating and repair work in Govern-ment Ii apartments with a view to the ibsorption of unemployed painters and similar workpeople. The entire programme is expected to be completed by the middle of May and the numbers of men employed are being gradually reduced.3. Other Public Work. In addition, various Local Authorities throughout the country are employing labour on schemes of relief work which have not been assisted by Government grants.4. Housing : Additional Proaress on actual Housing Operations since october 19, 1920.On the 1st April there were 63,230 skilled men employed on housing schemes in England and Wales, as against 54,479 at the end of February, 48,053 at the end of January, 40,270 at the end of December, 37.024 at the end of November, and 32,974 at the end of October. As regards unskilled men, there were 56,151 employed on the 1st April, as against 53,689 at the end of February, 48,710 at the end of January, 41.093 at the end of December, 39,197 at the end of November, and 36.414 at the end of OctoberAt the 1st April the additional labour still required for housing schemes was 9.690 skilled men (including 4,284 bricklayers, 1.433 carpenters, 2,663 plasterers) and 484 unskilled men.5. Summary of Labowr engaged on Relief Schemes.(Including those for whom part-time employment is being provided.)Returns are received weekly from the Government Departments responsible and from the Local Authorities in regard to all the schemes of works indicated above, and the latest returns show that the number of men for whom emergency work has been found in this way is as follows : 
217(a.) Schemes assisted by Government Grants: Arterial Roads (a.) London           ...        ...        ...        ... 2,370(b.) Provinces        ...        ...        ...        ... 17,972Expediting of lay-outs on housing schemes (a.) London&apos;          ...        ...        ...        ... 631(b.) Provinces        ...        ... -      ...        ... 3,682Other Public Works assisted by the Unemployment Grants Committee (a.) London           ...        ...        ...        ... 6,119(6.) Provinces        ............ 23,229Alternative work at War Office and Admiralty Estab-lishments............... 8.776*Adoption of short-time in War Office and AdmiraltyEstablishments       ...        ...        ...         ... 9 734*Additional  labour  engaged   by   Office  of  Works(Emergency Programme)       ...        ...        ... 555(b.) Public,  Works put in hand by Local Authoritieswithout Government Grants ...        ...        ... 12,563Grand Total85,631As reports for the week ended the 15th April have been received from only 312 Local Authorities out of 367 who were asked to supply information, it is probable that the Relief Schemes which have been inaugurated by the Government and by Local Authorities are finding employment for a number of&apos;men in excess of 86,000.(The Ministry of Transport estimate that employment has also been provided for some 20.000 men on road maintenance and repair work over and above those ordinarily so employed.)6. Government Scheme for the Employment of 50,000 ex-Service Men to be trained in the Building &quot;industry.Arrangements for carrying out the above scheme, in conjunction with the employers&apos; organisations in Great Britain, have now been completed, and posters announcing the scheme were displayed in all Employment Exchanges on Monday, the 18th April. *The Employment Exchanges will be responsible for certifying that a candidate for employment is eligible as an ex-Service man, &amp;c, and employers will be responsible for selecting and determining the number of men to be engaged, subject to a maximum for the whole country of 50,000. Employers will enter into two years&apos; agreement with accepted candidates, and the rates of pay under the agreement will be :-1st six months2nd six months3rd six months 4th six months50 per cent, of the district rate for skilledworkmen plus Government grant of10^. per wreek. 65 per cent, of the district rate for skilledworkmen plus Government grant of5s. per week. 80 per cent, of the district rate for skilledworkmen.90 per cent, of the district rate for skilled workmen.[ Progress Reports will be furnished weekly.&quot;* No figures are at present available in respect of Admiralty Establishments later than for the 19th March.&apos; It is known, however, that some hundreds of men have been discharged since that date.
III.  PAYMENT OF UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT AND OUT-OF-WORKDONATION.1. The following statement represents the position as shown by the Exchange registers on the 8th April: 0	Men.	Women.	Total.Numbers wholly unemployed .. N           Numbers on short time* Total......	1,092,358 402,000	394,388 442,000	1,486,746 844,000	1,494,358	836,388	2,330,7462. Number in receipt of Unemployment Insurance or Out-of-work Donation : 			 	Men.	Women.	Total.Wholly unemployed (estimated) On short tlme* Total	991,000 402,000	365,500 442,000	1,356.500 844,000	1,393,000	807,500	2,200,500-N.B. The abov*; are advance figures in all cases.* There is no record of the number of workpeople on short time, who are not eligible to receive Unemployment Insurance or Out-of-work Donation, those who are employed in such a way that they are unable to comply with the rules as to continuity of unemployment.o

</content>
</cab>
