<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/122/0 images: 376-385</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS LOCUfclKT IS THE PROPERTY OX EIS BBI3PAIMC i^JLoTY^ government.;H1        )CREI,e A E I M S Ii-- 856^RSIrORT BY TEE GMHUL OFFICER COiuUUDIUG-XU-CIil 1^ OU TH2 SISUAffXOE W IRBiUJD FOB WSSK ENDING 16thiuPIL, 19 1.(Circulated,07 the Secretary of State for War.)Ir- SEi!LR,xL MILITARY SITUATION.The comparative freedom from outrages on a large scele,&apos;and tho inactivity of :.ebel Inlying volumne noted in my last report have continued during the past week.   The principal incidents have beenIn Lublin, (a), a. bomb attack on the&apos;London Ilorth   estern Hotel, Korth ..all, which is occupied by auxiliaries.   Very little damage was done.(b) attacks on Horse transport in the streets and the shooting of horses and mules.((?) The seizure of arms and explosives, amounting to some twenty revolvers and fifty bombs.In the Country.(a) The burning of Derry House, Roscarberry, Co. Cork by rebels. i&apos;his was apparently the beginning of an intended destruction of the village the inhabitants oi which had given assistance to the E.I.C. when the Ros*arb.erry Polioe 2arraoks was. burned.   The further destruction Of the village was prevented by the in-habitants, who headed by a Priest drove the rebels out of the place.(b) attacks on police Barracks at Kallinavat, Co. Kilkenny and Eedamcre, Co. Limerick.   Beither of these attacks was successful.(cj   The murder of Sir Arthur Viaars.(d) The murder of Major liackinnon of 5th government.. Auxiliaries on the Go^f Links at Tralee.Details of the above and other outrages will be found in appendix I.The rebels appear to be concentrating thoir eftorts just, now on three forms of activity(l) The attack on and destruction of Government -transport.    his has been considerably on the increase, and a new phase- is marked by the shooting of horses and mules in the streets in Lublin.   I do not think that this form of outrage will find favour evon with the Sinn Peiners.
(2) Attacks on irost Offices, Banks and olvil servants who exe known to bo in possession of public monies.There is no doubt that funds are urgently neede^ay the Republicans, and these raids are certainly carried out at the instigation of ieadpuarters.(3) The oold-blooded murder of loyal civilians.   2he number of such murders has increased very largely recently,   they  are probably due to the desire of the X,$aAt to counteract by intimidation the growing discontent of local inhabitants, who in many districts are reported.to be getting tired of Sinn lein methods.i&quot;he cutting and blocking of roads has not been so prevalent lately, and in some districts the local inhabitants have turned out and filled in the trenches on their own initiative.   In one Brigade ,-.rea the experiment of allowing fairs to take piece in spite of the cutting of roads, has been tried.   ^ military Order was published to the effect that the difficulty ex. erienced by farmers in getting their goods to market was caused by the action of the I.B.A. and that the Crown forces were pre;; red, .ith the oo-operation of the inhabitants, to overcome the difficulty,   ihe road-cutting in this ..rea hss shown a marked decrease since the publi cation of this - Order.An increase in rebel activity must be expected in the Porth before long,   xhere ere indications that H. .1.1;.... are exerting their energies towards stirring up trouble in bister, and intend to increase their intimidation there, probably in vie  of the coming elections.The relations between the troops .-;nd the police aic&apos; the co-operation between tho two continue to be most satisfactory.Information is coming in showing that rebels in Hying Columns are boooming discontented.   !The cold weather and snow showers experienced recently have no doubt been very dispiriting to men who have of late been unable to set off any market successes against their discomfort end the ruin of their businesses during their absence.   Captured documents clso prove that the Rebel leaders have nov/ been forced to recognise , thst civilians are grumbling at being forced to house and feed members of ilying Columns ..?nd rebels on the run.The seizure of arm:, end explosives,. es; eoially in Dublin., has for the lest two or three weeks&quot;shown ah increase over seizures during previous periods.   &apos;fhe discover?;- of a bomb factory in Devlin rlaoe, and the seizure of  0 rev elvers and E&apos;5 bombs near Dolphin&apos;s Barn were the result of good military intelligence vcrk.The boycott of Belfast Goods is being intensified, and instructions have been issued by  ebel xieadquarters to extend the boycott so as to inolude certain agricultural implements and other goods from England.It is -still not passible to state definitely the reason tor the present comparative-inactivity&quot;on the pert of the rebels.   I am of opinion that there are several contributary causes, such as the coming elections, the growing feeling amongst inhabitants of dissatisfaction at rebel methods which effect trade eiiC farming, and the discontent of men who have been for some months on the run or with H&apos;lying uolumns.   ihe willingness with which many men now go to internment, and the openly expressed relief of their relatives are indications that the power of 3iru, Irein is, at any rate, not increasing.   On the ,other hand it is rulte possible thatthe
the elections may he the occasion ior a great effort on the part oi the Republicans ;.to turn ^ublic opinion-more completely in their favour, .nd 1 am not at present prepared to say what methods the rebels will employ for this end..  ;  -Although great interest was tcken in the labour situation in England during the post-. v&amp;ek,there was no indication of an intention to eo-cpera^e either on the part of the Irish  ranches of the 1I.U.K, or the. Irish transport ..or hers Union.     l-o untoward event marked the transfer oi 4 Iiattalions to rjaglanc nor was advantage taken anywhere by the rebels of the conse..uent shortage of troops in certain districts.(3gd.) C,3P.H. MCH3ADY....Commanding-in-Chief, IRjSLAED.QtWk, Ireland..   19th ^pril, 3,921,
APPENDIX I.OPERi^IOKS &amp; OUTKAGSS.gubllPo Keer Valieymount a Military despatch rider wes lired at during the morning by 2 armed civilians but escaped unhurfe.In Camden street a kilitary l^rry v/as attached with bombs and rifle fire at 19,SO hours.   The lorry v/as halted end fire was opened on the assailants with the result that 2 civilians were wounded,   Shore were no casualties to troops,Ballybofey. uo, Donegal..    *t about 83.00 hrs. 0 shots ware fired at s mixed patrvl oi troops epd police, wounding a civilian in the knee,   The assailant escaped,Timoleague, oOrCork,   The Bridge on the Bandon lioac? was destroyed at night &quot;by rebels^   The post Office was raided also, where telephones, correspondence &amp;  12 were seized by armed men.lildorrery, Col Cork,   2 Constables were shot deaefby armed men in the evening.Hoscarberry, Co, Pork.     Derry House was burnt down and the , village was looted, presumably by rebels, as the town had been threatened by them.Grlendowan, Letterkenny, (jo. Donegal^   A search revealed 2 rifles, 1 carbine, 1 shot gun &amp; 115 rounds ammunition.   Pour arrests were made.Dublin,     At about 08.00 hrs. about 10 bombs were thrown into the windows of the L cc HV . Railway Hotel, Korth   all, which is ticcupied by Auxiliary H.I.C.   dhots were ..Iso fired at the windows.   Fire v/as returned and one rebel was killed.     Thero were no casualties in the hotel.. exfprd.   rebels attempted to bum two military cars at South V/exferd itati&amp;n.     One was slightly damaged and. the other extensively sc.Baylin, Athlone. a Protestant farmer v/as shot dead by I.K.A. Pour arrests have been made.Oastlebar, Co,, kayo. 4 unknown civilians raided the offices of 5 solicitors &amp; removed bill processes for hearing at the Quarter Sessions there on 16th.Cork,   At 10,00 hrs. a bomb v/as thrown at 2 police vehicles in ,ashington Street.   The bomb wounded 4 civilians.   Revolver shots were also fired at the police who returned the fire.   The assailants retired rapidly.   Eo police were hit.   The same evening a constable was fired on by 3 men and wounded in 2 places.kullinavatv Co. Kilkenny.   The R.InQ, Barracks were attacked just after midnight&quot;&apos;of 11th April by about 100 armed rebels.   ,;jn attempt was made to blow up the barracks with an infernal machine.     The attack lasted two hoars.   Thero were no crown casualties.though 3ome rebels were believed shot.Dublin. Two attacks were made on Army transport.   At 1;..S0 hrs. 2 RASC ,/wagons in karket Street were stopped by 2 armed civilians who fired a shot over the unarmed drivers head and ordered them to dismount.   aII 4 horses were then shot, Z killed and
and 2 badly wounded. At 14.00 hrs. a limber in charge of 2 unarmed soldiers was held up by armed men in Cork Street. One soldier was ordered away and the other forced to drive the mules down a lane where he was ordered to leave them. The mules were subsequently found walking unattended, badly wounded in the temple.

Cork. At 21.30 hrs. a demonstration was made outside Cork Male Prison. 14 shots were fired, wounding an R.I.C. No arrests were made.

Clonakilty, Co.Cork. 4 civilian motor lorries occasionally commandeered by troops were destroyed by rebels at ?3.00 hrs.

Dublin. A party of troops was fired at across the Grand Canal near Blackhorse Bridge. ? N.C.O. was wounded. No assailants could be found.

?/4/21 Killarney, Co. Kerry. The Killarney-Killerglin Mail Car was held up by 7 or 8 masked and armed men at 11.00 hrs. The mails were taken and the driver told to proceed.

Co. Kilkenny. At 18.00 hrs. a mixed party of troops &amp; police proceeding in 2 tenders from Callan to Kullinahono were fired on by about 20 rebels near ?ilbride cross roads. Fire was returned with unknown results. 1 R.I.C. Sergeant was wounded.

Kilkenny. Four rebels fired at and wounded an R.F.A. sentry posted over horses outside Kilkenny Barracks. Fire was returned with unknown results.

Dungarvan, Co. Waterford. At 23.00 hrs. 3 Auxiliary Police were attacked with bombs and fired at. Local troops and police then engaged the rebels who numbered about 20. ?here were no known casualties on either side.

Fedamore, Co. Limerick. 5 R.I.C carrying water some 300 yards from barracks were attacked and one was murdered, 2 wounded and 2 escaped. Soon afterwards the barracks was attacked by 50 rebels without however inflicting any further loss on the R.I.C Rebel casualties are unknown.

Letterkenny, Co. Donegal. On the night of 13/14th. raiders stole 9 bicycles in the district.

Dublin. Rebel bomb workshop located 9 Devlin Place. Two men arrested actually assembling bombs. ?5 bombs, 46 detonators, fuzes and a number of spare bomb parts and tools seized.

?4/21 Listowel, Co. Kerry. Near Listowel, armed men shot Sir Arthur Vicars at 10.15 hrs.

Dungarvan, co. Waterford. 3 constables walking out bombed. Police and Military reinforcements also fired upon. No casualties either side.

Ballinfair near Sligo. Thomas ?alker, Civil Bills Officer shot.
?4/21 Dublin. Rebel dump discovered at Dolphin&apos;s Barn included ? revolvers, 1 Very Pistol, 2 bombs 65 rounds revolver ammunition, 1 Government bicycle, 2 Field Telephones, 1 pair of climbers and small number of tools.

Dublin. 3 grenades thrown at Military lorry in Aunger St. No casualties. Five returned with unknown results.

Dublin. 2 Military cars attacked by bombs and revolver fire at Canal Bridge, Phibsboro. The driver of one car was wounded. No fire returned as attackers could not be observed.

Tralee, Co. Kerry. Major Mackinnon, O.C. 5th Coy. Auxiliaries murdered on Golf links about 16.00 hrs.

?/21 Ballina to Belmullet, Co. Mayo. Motor Mail Van attacked at Knockanellann by 7 armed men and money from registered letters, postal orders and stamps stolen.

Castleporta, Co. Limerick. Houses of Patrick Casey of Cahivelly Nicholas O&apos;Dwyer of Raheen and Tom Harrington, Castleporta, destroyed as military operation in view of murder of Constable Rogers at Fedamore.

Dublin. Seizure of rebel literature at 5 Chelmsford Terrace.

Dublin. At 28.50 hrs. bomb thrown in yard in area of National Bank Smithfield. Only windows damaged.

Waterford, Co. Waterford. The G.P.?. at 12 hrs. raided by armed men and £13 and mails taken.

Fermoy, Co. Cork. 40 rounds from Hotchkiss Gun fired at aerodrome 0315 hrs. No casualties.

Davidstown, Co. ?exford. Michael Kennedy, farmer shot dead by 2 armed unmasked men at 22.00 hrs.

?/21 Charleville, Co. Cork at 18.40 hrs. Attempted ambush on Crown Forces. Enemy driven off. No casualties.

Ennis, Co. Clare. At 22.45 hrs. armed civilians threw hand grenade into Shaughnessy&apos;s public house and killed Sergt. Rees, Royal Scots, wounded a police constable and two females.

Derrybeg, Co. Donegal. Armed men cut off hair of Mary Gallagher aged 56 apparently because she reported neighbour to Military for poisoning her dog. Also shot and wounded in leg Morris Coll result of agrarian dispute.

Dublin. Bomb thrown at Auxiliary RIC. on Eden Quay. No damage done.

Fermoy Area. At 18.00 hrs. Crown Solicitor&apos;s Clerk wounded in the arm by 3 armed men.

?21 Dublin. At Dolphin&apos;s Barn seizure by Military 20 revolvers between 20 and 30 bombs &amp; quantity of ammunition. 4 arrests.

Ballybrody, Co. Limerick. Police constable wounded when cycling in plain clothes by 3 armed men.
APPENDIX II.RAH&quot;8AY SITUATIOU.Ballywillan. Co. Longford. At 2?*.15 hrs. the train Cavan-Mulllngarwas raid&amp;d and a* quantity of Belfast broach for local traders was taken out and thrown away,^allycullano^ OpVTe^terford*  he Corfc-Rosslare train was hold up at 23.16 Ers. tc searched.   3 mail bags for Swansea, Cardiff., and Newport respectively, wero removed,!l^iMS5U. Co* Kildare. At 00.30 hrs. 3 train was ha*d up &amp; searched. A number of mail bags were opened.Blarney, Co.. Cork. The Corh-Dublih train was raided by armed men at SC.1? hrs.   3omo mail bags wore taken.ggQftJtetone, .Dublin. IS armed men raided the locomotive &apos;7orks and removed&apos; rope&quot;ladders, picks and shovels.81   Sligc, Guard of Goods train tiod up by armed men at 0300 hrs.Bray, Op. 1 Jioklcw.   Wight 10/11, armed men hold up Looomotive 11   Staff and burnt 2 motor ambulances belonging to Ministry of Pensions.   Flooring of two Railway trucks burned.81liffey Junction, Co. Dublin. The signal Box and a milosman^s hut WoW oroJion into by raTdors who removed a number of p&amp;sfcs, shovels and hammers from the latter.Kilfreov Co.Sligo..- At about &quot;01.30 hrs. a train to Ballaghadereod from Cavan was raided at the Junction by armed men., 2 wagon loads of potatoes consigned to local traders woro destroyed.Kingstown. Soon after midday armed men entered the Goods Store ana remanded 18 rolls of felt and some stationery sent from Belfast for local traders.Newpestle^Opl Limerlok. Wires were out between Beweastie and Sa&apos;th eale end Sewoastle and Barnagh causing considerable delay to trains.El   Ballywillan. Co. Longford,,   Armed men raid3? the 81.15 hrs. train &apos; lirom (TavaS toTtu^lingar lor the second time within 4 days. It is not known if anything was removed.Br ay. C p, WloklowA Motor tyres consigned from Foxrock to Manchester were burned at*&quot;33..00 hrs.Rathkoale to Newcastle)Newcastle &amp; Barnagh    )Co.Iimorick.   Telephone k telegraph wires out,Clara, gjng&apos;s County, Goods station raided by armed men.   1 keg of spirits for Military Canteen destroyed.^  j1! n t own t Go. pone gal. Train ex-Stranorlar to Fintown hoi? up and Mail bags removed by disguised men.Telegraph &amp; Telephone wires cut also on morning of 15th.C1 ara,..king Connty. Overhead Railway Bridge between Clara and Ithlona^c^magel by explosives.   No injury to permanent way.Falcarragh, Co,Donegal. 10.15 hrs. Goods train Londonderry to Burtonport boarded by armed men.   SkVofcrapti &amp; telephone linos cu&apos;% Train ordered to proceed and lato mail searched, some being removed.
%aterrora -tation, Oo, Tatorford,- At 20.00 hrs. party of Military examined&quot;all Mails arriving on the 1745 hrs. train from Maryborough for 3osslare.Qarristwohill, Co.. Oor-r. About 05.45 hrs. armed and masked men Held up train Cork to Youghal and removed 16 bags of mail.wm* *mm
appendix III.l  I -111   .    I IIQIVTLIAHS TP;ED BY COUNTS MAKTIAL.55 civilians have been tried by Courts Martial of whom 48 wars convioted and sentenced as under :-^Jr attacks on Qgown forces.1 ,to 5 yoars P.S.2 to 2 year3 Imp. H.L.(b)   Assaultsmon Civilians.2 to 4 yoars P..3. 3 to 3 year3 P.S.1 to 1 day3 Imp. (3&quot; jaon&amp;hs in confinement awaiting trial).(G) 191 fraias in -poosossion of arms, ammunition, or explosives.1 to 7 years P.S. 1 to 5 years 2.3. 1 to 3 years P.3. 1 to 2 years Irnp.H.L. 4 to 1 years Imp.H.l. 1 to 6 months lmp.H.L. 1 to 1 days Imp, 7 -fined.(3) ^or boinp; in possession of seditious literature.1 to 2 yoars Imp.H.L* 3 to 13 months imp,H.L. 3 to 1 years ImpcE9L. 1 to 9 -months Imp,H.L. 3 to 6 months Imp-H.I.(a) Mi3-3Qllane,oca^1 to 4 yoars 1 to 2 yoars Imp,H.L. i 1 to 15 months tap..33*it. 1 to 5 months ImnVKJD. 1 to 3 months Imp*H.I.
APP.i2sDI2 IV.Internment of J-fonbvrs of I.R.A.Tho following number - of members of I.K.A. bava boon recommended for internment15th Infantry Brigade 233Londonderry Brigade 7613th Infantry Brigade Uthlomj) 28414th Infantry Brigade (Curragh) 213Galway Brigade 27416th Infantry Brigade (Fcrmoy) 26817th Infantry Brigado (Cork) 34518th Infantry Brigada (Limsriok) 150Kerry Brigado 71Dublin District 95588691st Division 3098th Division 7716th Division 834Dublin District 9552869Members of recommended for Internment by Hanks.Brigado Commandants 17Brigade Staff 44Battalion Commandants 71Battalion Staff 161Company Officers 1153Other ranks and Hanks unknown 14232869 2869m.      IQ      m*

</content>
</cab>
