<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/122/0 images: 471-478</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCirOT IS THE PWETITY OP 3K V.X*Am?XG :!/..7E\TYfS (W^JR^WT,)C.P.2867.C A B I V E T .SURVEY OP THE STATE OP IHELAKDFv  Week ended 18th April, 1921* (Circulated by the Chief Secretary for Ireland,)I submit for the consideration of the Cabinet my survey for the week ended tho 18th instant. QgTOAL STATE OF THE COUNTRY. Statistics of Outrages.The outrage figures for the week present no special feature.   The total is slightly higher than that of the previous week but a comparison of the two weeks1 figures gives no indication of a change in the general state of the country.Attacks on the Crown forces fell from 34 to 29 but the casualties sustained in these attacks rose from 26 to 30. The attacks included four unsuccessful attempts to capture occupied Police Barraoks, (Mdllinavat, Oo.Kilkenny, Fedamore, Co.Limerick, Plenties, CcDonegal, and Bagenalstown, Co.Carlow). Except in the case of Glonties in which a Head Constable and a Constable were slightly wounded, no casualties were suffered by the defending garrisons in any of these attacks, but the attempt on Pedamore Barrack was Immediately preceded by an ambush about 300 yards distant in which one Constable was killed and two wounded.   Other ambushes in which police casualties were sustained took place at Cullyhanna, Co.Armagh, Kllbride Wood; CoKilkenny, Loughaderry, Midleton District^ CcCtork, Oallan, Co.Kilkenny and Tralee.Co.Kerry.    On the
15th instant. m]ov KoKinnon, the Officer Commnding IT. Company of the Auxiliary Pi^iUon, of the Hoyal Irish Con-st-^bulnry was fired at and nortally woundod while playing golf at Trnleo.   He ins in tho act of putting when fired at and killed by men concealed about 30 yards distant.The number of Sinn Fein murders r i civilians fedl from 9 to 6, but the number cf attempted -lurders rose from 7 to 9, Among the civilian vie ins was Sir Arthur Vicars, K.O.V.O., formerly Ulster King at Arris, who was murdered in his house nt Kilmome, Listowel District, Ct.Kerry, b/ a party of about thirty men armed Tith rifles, shotguns and r^olv*rs* From a label bearing the words &apos;Spyt Informers beware1 it would appear that tho motttra.of his murder was suspicion that he had ^iven information * concerning the movements of men of the I.R.A. to the police.   This suspicion, I understand was entirely ^groundless, although Sir Arthur was always on the most friendly nrK1 cordial terms with the police and did much to relieve the strain and tension of their present trying conditions by supply-ing them with paries and literature for their amusement *   The late Sir Arthur Vicars was a half brother of the O^lahony.   His house was burned to the ground by the murdarara.   It contained priceless articles connected with the history of Ireland and the ancestors of the OfIlahony who served in foreign countries.    Another &apos;spyf murder during the week was that of a woman, named ritty Carrell, aged 40, who  &quot;as bound and dragged from her hom* at Aughnameena, Co.*&quot;onaghan, on the 10th. instant, and shot on the public road about half a mile a^ay.*IInor outrages for the week Included 50 raids on mails and 5 raids on the offices of rate collectors in which sums of money amounting to a total of  16,537.. 9. 10 were seized.   The recent Increase in the number of raids on nails, which had steadily declined ovor a period of several weeks,, is perhaps explained bythe
following passage *hich appears in *AN T-OGLAC&quot; (the official organof the Irish Republican Army) of the 1st instant?-&quot;Take for example the raiding of :inemy Despatches. In several creas the enemy is still able to use the ordinary post for his official correspondence.    Ihercver this is so it is essential to raid the mails systematically * a Post Office, a rail Train, a Postman, even a Pillar Box -in all these there may be information.    The enemy strength, co mands, and even intention may be ascertained in this way. Information&apos; of a brotd importance should be forwarded to General Head quarters.    For example, a letter may be address-ed to a G.O.C. such and such a Brigade at such a place; this irmediately puts G.H.Q, in possession of the knowledge of such and such an hnemy Brigade Headquarters.    Similarly for smaller units.    Every scrap of information about the enemy is useful therefore the mails must be raided at frequent intervals, both to seoure information and to make the enemy uneasy about his communication&quot;.Similar instructions for harassing the &apos;enemy&apos; by cutting telegraphwires, sniping at police barracks and conducting other ^Snor&apos;operations1 appear in the flame captured document and give some indication of th* many ramifications of the very formidableconspiracy with which the Irish Government are contending.Arrests for outrages and political offences numbered 60for the week.Trials of Civilians by Court ?artlal.Sixty-five trials of civilians by Court Martial were con-oluded during the week resulting in forty-nine convictions andsixteen acquittals.    The following sentence:; were imposed inthe oases in which convictions were obtained;10 Sentences of Tenal Servitude    (3 years to 7 yoars)20     n        n   Imprisonment with (2 months to 2 years)hard labour.11     n        n   Imprisonment with-(l day to 2 years)out hard labour 7 Fines ( 1. to  20). 1 sentence remitted tal     WSSSMBIncluded in the convictions were the cases of three Special Constables one of whom was sentenced to two years Imprisonment and the other two to three months imprisonment with hard labour for looting in  Nawry.    Three other special constables/
-   347******Constables who core tried on the same occasion were acquitted. Two Constables of the regular Constabulary were sentenced to terms of six months imprisonemnt with hard labour for looting and two to 1wo months&apos; imprisonment *ith nard labour for assault.    Sentence of seven years1 penal servitude was imposed in one case for the offence of soliciting a soldier to   sell revolvers, and sentence of five years1 penal servitude for an attack on a Police barrack,    Penrl servitude for four ye-rs in t*ro cases and for three years in three cases was imposed on five men convicted of assaulting and imprison-ing two girls with the intent of intimidating    them into leaving the country^*Internment Orders,1   126 Orders for internment were made during the week bringing the total number of persons hot interned to 2,679, In addition there   are 68 orders at present awaiting completion and 7 in abeyance pending the arrest of the persons against whom they are made,    The number of persons who have been released from internment is   124, STATE OF THK POLICE FORCES,The recruiting figures for the permanent force of the Royal Irish Constabulary are slightly lower than last week, but those for the Auxiliary Divisions have improved.    The net increase in the strength of the Regular Force is 61 and in the strength of the Auxiliary Division 3,    The following are the usual particulars for the week;
,.e ulai&apos; i: orce.Strength on 10th Aoril, 1921..................   13,771De:.ths during the week. ..t.....70lietirements,...................9,,iiesiv;n, tions.................,25.Dismissals cr Disahe:rg6E0.....Total wastage 82Recruits.Ireland.........8.Gt,Lritain.....125 133Het Increase...............................51Strength on 17th April, IS21....................13,0*2auxiliary Diy 1sion.Strength on l&amp;ch April, 1921.................... 1,478Recruits.................... .2.16Dische-rged (medioally unfit)..4Resigned......................8Dismissed.....................113llet increase,........................... _____3(Strength cn 17th April, 1931............,.....1,481The corresponding figures for the Ifublin Metropolitan Police are as follows ;Strength of force on 9th April, 3.521,........... 1,131Resignations............... ,2Recruits (Ireland)..........1Ilet decrease..........................____1Strength on 16th April, 1921...................   1,130BOYCOTT Cg BgMVugg GOODS a gOUTHMg IHBLJKD.Prcm reports received there would a^ear to he no doubt that the Boycott of Belfast goods in Southern Ireland is making an appreciable inrcad into the trade of the Northern Capital and at the recent meeting of the Belfast- $ -
Wholesale Merchants" Association the question of Instituting a counter-boycott was seriously discussed. The boycott is particularly active in Dublin where the sale of all classes of elfast goods is for the present almost at a standstill. Even such articles as tobacco manufactured by ?. Callagher &amp; Co., and Messrs Murrary &amp; Co., which for many years have maintained a strong hold in the Dublin retail trade have been practically driven from the market, and wholesale buyers of woollens, linens, soap, candles, etc. have directed their travellers not to execute any more orders with Belfast firms while the present situation continues. An order to boycott certain English articles has also been issued by Lail Bireann. I attach a copy of the Order recently issued by the Republican Trade Department on this subject. That such a policy would meet strong opposition from Irish manufacturers and workmen themselves is evident from a letter addressed to the Press by Messrs. Jacob &amp; Co., the well-known Dublin biscuit makers, who point out that two-thirds of their trade depends upon the British and foreign markets and that a grave danger of widespread unemployment in Dublin and other parts of Southern Ireland would result from any interference with the trade relations with the two countries.

(Intd) W.G.

Chief Secretary&apos;s Office,

Dublin Castle.

April 22nd, 1921.
			WP1EK	ENDED			Totals toHAT UBS OP OUTRAGE.	Totals frem 1st January, 1919 t* 12th Maroh, 1921.	19th Mardri^th Karch,2nd April, 9th April, 16th April, 1921.          1921.          1921             1921               1921.					l6th Aprilt 1921.Courthouses destroyed	72	2	-	-	-	-	74R. I.C.Vacated Barracks destroyed	512	-	-	mm	-	1	513R.I.Cm Vacated Barracks damaged	120	-	-	-	-	-	120E.1.0.Occupied Barracks destroyed	24	-	-	1	-	-	R.I.C.Occupied Barracks damaged	106	4	3	7	6	4	ijpRaids on Mails	1,3 37	29	31	3i	40	&apos;    To	1,Raids on Coastguard Stations &amp; Lighthouses.     54		1	1		-	-	&amp;Raids for Anas.	3T074		10		9	1	3.111Raids on Offices of Rate Collectors and Petty Sessions Clerks.                                     51				45			101Policemen Killed	S4?*	10	...    JC	8	3	6^	2U1&quot;&apos;Policemen Wounded Policemen 3?required  at^ etc.	not recorded	3	14-9 &quot;	14 &quot; *   12	6   ----	^19_______ 10	Soldiers Killed	74	11	13		1	1	100Bcidiers Wounded	177	t?	14	4			^219Soldiers fired at, etc.	not recorded		.....&quot; &quot;T&quot; &quot;	7		**	XHCivilians Killed	77	4	________8m:	11	^    -9.......	0	........ -r^:::-Civilians Wounded	124	3	7		7	 	1^3TOTALS.	_______6^434________	10&quot;$	life	i J-T	&apos;1C7	&quot;* 120	g.971 ____Arrests for Outrages &amp; Political C	)ffences&quot;   -	40	&apos;&quot;    48&quot;   &apos;		25		Weekly totals to week ended l6th April, 1921 and Totals at that date.X   These figures do not include casualties in Ulster Riots during period June-September, 1920: 20 Civilian deaths occurred in Londonderry riots and 62 in Belfast riots during that period:f.B. The above particulars do not include outrages of a kind which are not now being committed e.g. 119 raids on Revenue Offices which occurred during months of April and Kay, 1920, and resulted in the destruction of many official documents and much other public property.     Minor forms of outrages (e.g. intimidation cattle-driving etc.) are also not included.&amp;     These figures in each case include two Special Constables.Ofi-     This figure includes 3 Special Constables.
The following Order has been issued :-PAIL EIREaNN.TR.J)B lS3E*m&amp;WT* April 14th, 1921.IMPOSMIOH J3D B..LL Of BRITI3H GOODS Jfc-RGFJBMIOB ORDER Mo.2.In accordance with the powers conferred on the Ministryby Dail Eireann at its session in karch, 1921, it is herebyordered that on and after May 14th, 1921, the importation and sale of BRITISH makes of the following articles is prohibited:-BISCUITS BPCT POLISHEvery loyal oitizen of the Republic is erpeoted to give active support to the Government in making this Order absolute.Signed:- E4ENAJJ DB BLAGHD.Minister of Trade.Order No.l. prohibited the importation of British-made bindersT mowing machines, horse rakes, swathe turners, hay trolleys (Rick shifters), ploughs, harrows, oora drills, root cutters, as from 31st March, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
