<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/210/1 images: 5-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(80) 515 August 1980COPY NO81CABINETCOMPENSATION AND PRIVATISATION OF SHIPBUILDINGMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Industry1* I was invited to submit a further memorandum in consultation with theSecretary of State for the Environment and others concerned on the option ofimmediate privatisation at compensation value (CC(80) 31st Conclusions,Minute 6).    Under this option the former owners of the war shipbuilding yardswould be asked to choose between accepting their yards back at compensationvalue or accepting compensation on the basis of the present compensationprovisions of the nationalisation Act.    A variant of this is not to change thepresent compensation terms but to introduce legislation for privatisation andoffer back at market value which in the most critical cases may not be far offthe likely compensation price.    The main alternative is a deferment ofprivatisation and no change in present compensation provisions.CASE FOR IMMEDIATE OFFER AT COMPENSATION VALUE2. The arguments in favour run as follows:i. The terms of nationalisation are an outrage representing, in thecase of Vosper, one year&apos;s purchase of 1977 profits. Adversefinancial consequences should be accepted to right such an injustice.ii. There should be no adjustment for any change in assets ormarket value under British Shipbuilders (BS).    Equally, no assurancesshould be given to the former owners about future orders. Theobject is to offer the opportunity of restoring the position to what it wasbefore the nationalisation Act.iii. Comparable treatment cannot be offered to Lord Weinstock inrespect of the British Aircraft Corporation because the aircraftindustry has become too integrated since nationalisation.    This is notsufficient reason for refusing to deal with the grievances of the war-shipbuilders where action is still possible.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALiv. The offer should not be diluted by any retention of aGovernment shareholding to prevent foreign takeovers. Thecompanies remained satisfactorily in private hands beforenationalisation.    In any event, reserve powers to prevent a foreigntakeover exist under the Industry Act 1975.v. British Shipbuilders&apos; contention that privatisation should waituntil BS is viable is a recipe for indefinite procrastincation. Thereis no sign that BS would be attractive to any private investor in theforeseeable future, and if we wait there is every risk that the war-shipbuilders will be infected with the same malaise as the merchantshipbuilders.    Only restoration to private enterprise will make thecompanies competitive again in export markets, and this is all themore important because of the Ministry of Defence (Navy)&apos;s reducedrequirement for surface warships.vi. If we hold our hand because of fears of disruption, it will beimpossible to roll back the frontiers of socialism.    The acceptance bythe unions of the sale of British Rail&apos;s hotels shows what can be donein the present new climate.THE CASE AGAINST IMMEDIATE PRIVATISATION AT COMPENSATIONVALUE3. The difficulties and disruption of immediate privatisation whether atcompensation value or market value are set out in paragraph 8 but there arespecial difficulties attaching to offering back the yards at compensation value.i. It ignores our duty to the taxpayer to realise the best price, andis no consolation to the thousands who sold shares in the companiesconcerned in the knowledge of the terms of compensation.ii. It is an arbitrary valuation ignoring any changes in financialcircumstances eg capital investment since the reference period.This will further encourage the Opposition to threaten torenationalise at an arbitrary and penal valuation which could put injeopardy the flotation of British Aerospace and our generalprivatisation programme.iii. It will compound the problems of dealing with the former ownersof the British Aircraft Corporation who will see themselvesdeliberately discriminated against and with both the Burmah OilCompany and its shareholders who may draw comparisons with theGovernment&apos;s position on the ex-Burmah British Petroleum share-holding.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL4. While the concept of handing back the yards at &quot;compensation value&quot;appears at first sign an attractive solution, implementation through thelegislation required poses formidable problems.    The nationalisation Actvested shares and the debentures of the companies with BS.    The assetsunderlying the shares have changed.    The taxpayer through BS have, forexample, invested  30 million in the war shipbuilders, and the position underthe debentures and long-term liabilities of the companies will also havechanged.    The situation cannot be restored to what it was beforenationali sation.5. If privatisation were to be at market value, the price would adjust forchanges in the assets and liabilities since the reference period six years ago.However, if the sale were to be done at &quot;compensation value&quot;, which will berepresented by the Opposition as being substantially below market value, itappears essential to cover in the legislation what assets and liabilities arebeing disposed of.    Even though no great difficulty should arise on thephysical assets, the warship owners and Parliament would need to know suchthings as whether the tax allowances would remain with the companies or betaken by BS for Group Relief, the treatment of loans to and from BS, theapportionment of surpluses and liabilities under pension funds, the permittedlevel of dividends prior to sale, etc.    It would be necessary for the Bill tohave safeguarding provisions to prevent BS stripping the companies prior tosale.    General powers would also need to be taken to recover payments onaccount on compensation together with provision for interest.6. If the Bill were to be confined to the specialist war shipbuilders, HallRussell and Brooke Marine, the risk of the Bill being declared hybrid would begreat.    If the Bill, to avoid hybridity, were to apply to all the shipbuilding andshiprepair companies of BS then the safeguarding provisions at least initiallywould have to apply to most of BS&apos;s operations.    The warship owners and any-one else interested in having some or all of their assets back on such termswould need to know precisely what they were taking on before they took theirdecision on taking back the yards and implementation by an order subject tonegative resolution directing BS to sell at a stated price.7. A long and complex Bill would be needed, and it probably could not beready for introduction much bafore Christmas.    The warship owners and anyother former owner interested would need time to study the provisions of theBill and discuss them with the Department before making up their minds.There would thus be a long period of uncertainty and controversy for both theshipbuilding and shiprepair industries.IMMEDIATE PRIVATISATION?8. These considerations would appear to point strongly to anyprivatisation being based on market value which, in some cases, may be nearcompensation value particularly when the prospects for surface warshipsbecome public knowledge.    However in my view, we should not proceed now3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALon privatisation against the advice of the Chairman of BS and the equipmentsuppliers, against the background of a prospect of further substantialcontraction both on naval shipbuilding and on merchant shipbuilding in areas ofvery severe unemployment, with substantial effects also on the Public SectorBorrowing Requirement.    Our immediate task is to handle the fvrthercontraction and cut BS&apos;s losses and cash requirements.    The co-operationof the workforce, which the Confederation of Shipbuilding and EngineeringUnions, supported by the middle management, would withdraw in the event ofprivatisation, will be essential.NEED FOR STATEMENT9. An announcement of Government policy before the Recess is essentialon political and industrial grounds to end uncertainty.    No statement could bemade on a change in compensation provisions since it would take some monthsto work out the details of an agreed new formula for compensation and apremature announcement would fuel speculation.    Similarly a statement thatthe Government would introduce legislation to hand back yards at compensationvalue would involve speculation and questions which we could not answer atthis stage, and if colleagues should decide on this option a holding statementas at Annex A seems desirable.    Draft statements on the other options areattached.10. Colleagues are invited to decide between the following options on thebasis that no change would be made in the compensation provisions under anyoption.a. Immediate privatisation of shipbuilding at compensation valuegiving first option to former owners of nationalised assets.b. Immediate privatisation at market value with first option for theformer owners but with the question of a Government equity holding ofa minimum 25 per cent subject to negotiation and further consideration.c. Deferment of immediate privatisation.K JDepartment of Industry5 August 19804CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALNO COMPENSATION CHANGE - PRIVATISATION AT COMPENSATION VALUEAs the House will know, the Government has been considering whetherto introduce private capital into the nationalised shipbuilding andshiprepair industries.   We have consulted widely with those concernedand we have concluded that it would be in the best long term interestsof these industries and the taxpayer to bring proposals before the House in the autumn to facilitate the introduction of private capitalin accordance with   our Manifesto commitment.2 We recognise that in practice private buyers        will only beinterested immediately in the profitable warshipbuilders and possibly[one or two shiprepair companies but in our view the restoration[of private enterprise and the reintroduction of competition offer-thebest prospect of reinvigorating these sectors particularly in export[markets, and the most hopeful outlook for employment.3 Former owners will be given first option to purchase.   We stronglycriticised the   compensation provisions of the 1977 Act and rightlyso, and it is therefore proper that these owners should be givenfirst option on the assets removed from them by nationalisation.4-      The Government has received representations from some formerowners of yards that the terms of purchase should not be very differentfrom the terms of compensation.   The Government accepts that thismight represent the most equitable solution and will be consideringthis point further.   As a first step further   merchant bank advicewill be sought as to possible market values &apos;   i which in somecases could be at or near the compensation price.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALANNEX BNO CHANGE IN COMPENSATION PROVISIONS - PRIVATISATION AT MARKET VALUEIAs the House will know, the Government has been considering whetherto introduce private capital into the nationalised shipbuilding andshiprepair industries.   We have consulted widely with those concernedand we have concluded that it would be in the best long term interestsof these industries and the taxpayer to bring proposals before theHouse in the autumn to facilitate the introduction of private capitalin accordance with our Manifesto commitment.2      We recognise that in practice private buyers        will only be[interested immediately in the profitable warshipbuilders and possibly one or two shiprepair companies but in our view      , the restorationI of private enterprise and the reintroduction of competition offer the&gt;est I prospect of reinvigorat^np: these sectors particularly in export;markets^ and the most hopeful^outlook for employment.I3      Former owners will be given first option to purchase on the basis of negotiations at market value.   It is right that they should|i have first option on the assets removed from by nationalisation. We shall be seeking further merchant bank advice on market value.&quot;* 14      I have received many representations about the yards from the  previous owners on the unfairness of the compensation terms laid down in the 1977 nationalisation Act.   While in opposition we strongly criticised these provisions and rightly so.   However, the introductionof amending legislation would create new difficulties and fresh| unfairness for the shareholders who sold on the basis of the present terms.   In the light of these difficulties and after the most careful and sympathetic consideration of the representations made to me, I have with reluctance concluded that we cannot change the present compensation provisions but the former owners will have first optionto buy back their assets.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALANNEXTO CHANGE BT COJffiENSATION PBDVISIONS - DEFEEMEITO OP PRIVATISATIONThe House will know that the Government has been considering whethernow is the appropriate,time to announce proposals to introduceprivate sector capital into shiphulding and shiprepair.   This reviev;was begun when there were some signs of recovery in the market andthere was still a reasonable expectation that BS would be able toget on course for their financial limits this year without the needfor substantial&apos;corrective action.   As I told the House last week these hopes have been disappointed.   There are still considerableluncertainties surrounding the industry and the Chairman has advisedus that to introduce private capital at the present time would makesubstantially more difficult his task in making the Corporationriable and inevitably delay the time when viability is achieved.We have accordingly decided to defer proceeding at this stage.Generally the only part of BS which could have attracted private capital at the present time are the specialist warshipbuilders. Ihave received many representations about the yards from the previousfcwners on the unfairness of the compensation terms laid down in theIn977 Nationalisation Act.   While in Opposition, we strongly criticisedfchese provisions and rightly so.   However, the introduction, of mending legislation would create new difficulties and fresh unfair-ness for the shareholders who sold on the basis of the present terms.In the light of these difficulties and after the most careful andsympathetic consideration of the representations made to me, I have ith reluctance concluded that&apos; we cannot change the present compen-sation provisions.CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
