<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/30/23 images: 196-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MA.JESTXrS*GrOVERNMENT) .MOSTSECRETJtiS re(jue-stl!li care may be taken to SSESJP&apos;SisiS--     ensure the secrecy of this document.WiM ^o) rygrm nnrcnLUSIONS, MINUTER% nonfidential AnnexoMIBDLE^ST^atpovaftReinforcements.Diversion ofSpitfiresDestined for Australia.(previous references.M.(42) 65thConclusions,Minute 1. )(22nd June, 1942 - 5,30 p6mc)The War Cabinet were informed that the Chiefsof Staff had considered means of sending reinforcementsof fighter aircraft urgently to the Middle Bast.    Thequickest and most effective way would be.to borrow forthe Middle East 42 Spitfires now about to be sent toAustralia in pursuance of the War Cabinet1 s decision tosend three Spitfire squadrons from this country toAustralia (W.M.(42) 65th Conclusions,, Minute 1),    Ifthis course were taken, the personnel of the threesquadrons destined for Australia would sail in accordancewith plan, and aircraft to take the place of the 42diverted to the Middle East would be despatchedsubsequently and would arrive in Australia one month after the personnels,    The aircraft so diverted could reach the Middle East in about three weeks&apos; time - one month ahead of the time by which reinforcements couldbe obtained by any other means.    In view of the critical situation in the Middle East, the Chiefs of Staffconsidered that the balance of advantage was in favourof diverting these aircraft to the Middle East0    they therefore suggested that the Australian Government shouldbe informed of the position and invited to agree tothe course proposed,MR. BRUCE said that the first reaction ofthe Australian Government was not likely to be favourable.Circumstances had changed, however, since the decision was taken to send these Spitfire squadrons to Australia;and the Australian Government might be ready to acceptthe delay involved if the urgent need for fighterreinforcements in the. Middle East were explained to therm,It was essential however that they should be given a clear picture of our difficulties in the Middle East, andof our proposals for dealing with the situation.    Itshould also be brought out that the personnel of the squadrons would proceed to Australia in accordance withplan and an assurance should be given that the aircraft would follow one month later0The War CabinetsInvited the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs to explain the position to the australian government, on the lines suggested,and to invite their concurrence in the course proposed by theChiefs of StaffomGreat George Street, SsWale




</content>
</cab>
