<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/45/0 images: 70-88</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S..S C RE T.Hi mi- -.: &apos;&apos; - WAR CABIEET .I circulate herewith a memorandum which has been prepared in the Foreign Office, and which furnishes a synopsis of our engagements to our Alli* and others.(Initialled) . A, J. B.-14th March, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government,]Printed for the War Cabinet.   February 1918.SECRET.G.T-3917.Synopsis of our Obligations to our Alliesand Others.(This Synopsis deals only with pledges given by us to foreign Powers or Nationalities, and not with any obligations into which we may have entered with our Dominions or with British commercial firms or companies.)TO FRANCEWe are bound I. By the Pact of London (5th September, 1914), whereby we undertook not to make peace separately nor to formulate peace terms without the consent of the other signatory Powers.2. By the Anglo-French Agreements of April-May, 1916 (incorrectly called the Sykes-Picot Agreement), under which we agreed, &quot; provided the Arabs fulfil the conditions, and that they obtain the towns of Hons, Hama, Damascus, and Aleppo &quot; (N.B. This reservation is to some extent invalidated by our recent assurance to the French that we had no intention of departing from the Agreement), that (i.) France should have priority of enterprise and local loans, and supply advisers and public functionaries in the zone marked &quot;A&quot; on Map I in return for similar privileges being accorded to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the zone marked &quot; B.&quot;    Both the zones were in theorv to be- - .... - . Jincluded within the territory of the future Arab State, (ii.) France should establish such administration or control asshe should desire to arrange with the Arabs in the bluearea on Map I in return for similar privileges to HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the red area, (iii) The brown area to be internationalised under a regime tobe decided on after subsequent discussion, (iv.) We undertook not to cede Cyprus to a third Powerwithout the consent of France, (v.) Haina, which is attributed to England, to be a free port,and French goods to have free transit through the redarea   in   return   for   similar   assurances   as  regardsAlexandretta and transit of British goods through theblue area.(vi.) We also undertook not to acquire, or to consent to a third party acquiring, any possessions in the Arabian Peninsula and not to cede to any but the Arab State our rights in the red area in return for a similar assurance on the part of France.(vii.) We undertook not to push the Bagdad Railway in area &quot; B &quot; north of Samarra until the completion of a railway from Bagdad to Aleppo, and then only with the con-currence of France. In return France promised on similar conditions not to extend the railway in area &quot;A&quot; south of Mosul.(viii.) The existing Turkish customs tariff was to remain in force throughout the red and blue areas for a period of twenty years.[238] &quot; * B
3. By the Decision of the Paris Economic Conference (17th June, 1917), whereby we undertook (i.) To prohibit all trading with the enemy during the war. (ii.) To refuse most-favoured-nation treatment to the enemyand to subject his commerce to a special regime duringa period to be fixed, (iii.) To reserve for Allies essential raw materials, (iv.) Generally to develop Inter-Allied trade to the detriment ofthe enemy.4. By the resolutions of the Conference (Paris, October 1917), whereby the so-called policy of the bloc was decided upon, i.e., enemy private property and interests in Allied or occupied territory at the end of the war is to be held as a pledge for Allied private propertjr in enemy or enemy-occupied territory.5. Apart from the above contractual obligations, we have marie several official statements pledging ourselves to the evacuation of Northern France and the cession of Alsace-Lorraine, e.g., Lord R. Cecil in the House of Commons, 15tli November, 1917 : &quot;The restitution of Alsace-Lorraine was a well-understood war aim- from the moment we entered the war &quot; (and cf. Prime Minister to Trades Unions Delegates, 5th January, 1918).6. In addition to the above, there are two agreements at present under negotiation with France which may shortly be completed : (a.) A Supplementary Agreement is being negotiated whereby we would recognise that the Holy Places of Arabia and their immediate vicinity are open to foreign enterprise, the French recognising in return our predominant interests in the rest of Arabia.(&amp;.) Discussions are proceeding for a mutual agreement by which in substance France will recognise for us a free hand in Egypt, and we for them a free hand in Morocco.TO ITALYWe are bound  1. By the Pact of London (see under France (i)).2. By the Italian Agreement of the 26th April, 1915, whereby we pledged ourselves, subject to Italy employing the totality of her forces against all our enemies (a condition which has technically not been observed), that (i.) Italy should obtain the territory in the Trentino and on the Adriatic as marked blue on Map II. (The portion marked red to be neutralised, and those marked yellow to go to Serbia, Montenegro, and Croatia.)(N.B. This does not entail a contractual obligation towards the last three.)(ii.) Italy should have sovereignty over Vallona and the Island of Sasseno with sufficient territory to secure their defence.(iii.) Italy may undertake the charge of the foreign relations of the future State of Albania (i.e., establish a practical Protectorate);(iv.) And annex the Dodecanese ;(v.) And abolish the rights retained by the Sultan of Turkey over Tripoli and Cyrenaica (i.e., complete annexation).(vi.) That &quot; in a general way&quot; we recognise the interest of Italy in the maintenance of the balance of power in the Mediterranean, and that, in the event of the p-irtition or partial partition of the Ottoman Empire, or even the redistribution of zones of interest in Turkey, Italy should obtain an &quot; equitable share &quot; in the region of Adalia.
(vii.) That if we or France obtained an increase in our colonial possessions in Africa, Italy might in principle claim equitable compensation, particularly in the shape of a favourable settlement of questions affecting the frontiers between Erythrea, Somaliland. -and Tripoli and the adjacent British and French Colonies;(viii.) And share in any war indemnity.(ix.) We also promised to support the objections of Italy to any proposal for papal representation at the Peace Conference or anv similar negotiations.3. Under the Agreement with Italy respecting Asia Minor (8th August, 1917), we pledged ourselves, ^subject to the consent of Poissia&quot; (which has not been obtained), that (i.) Italy might administer the zone coloured green on Map I, and appoint functionaries, &amp;c, in the zone marked &quot;C&quot; on the same terms -as France and Great Britain were allowed to administer or appoint functionaries in the blue and red zones and the zones &quot; A &quot; and &quot; B &quot; under the Sykes-Picot Agreement.(ii.) Italy to enjoy reciprocal commercial privileges in the Allied zones.(iii.) If, as a result of the war, it were found impossible to partition the Ottoman Empire to the full extent contemplated in the above agreements, then the principle of the balance of power in the Mediterranean will be observed in any distribution which takes place.4. By the decisions of the Paris Economic -Conference (see France (iii) ), which, however, the Italian Government signed but have not yet ratified.5. By the Senoussi Agreement (July 1916), under which we agreed not to conclude an arrangement with the Senoussi without a previous understanding with the Italians.TO RUSSIAWe are bound (if bound at all)  1. By the Pact of London.i&apos;. By the Constantinople Agreement (March 1915) under which we pledged ourselves &quot;subject to the war being brought to a successful conclusion and to the desiderata of France and Great Britain in the Ottoman Empire and elsewhere being realised &quot; To agree to the incorporation in the Russian Empire of the city of Constantinople and the dependent territory as shown in yellow on Map I.3. By the Sj^kes-Picot Agreement under which we agreed that (i.) Russia might annex the portion of Asia Mino1: colouredyellow on Map I. (ii.) That Powers annexing portions of the Ottoman Empireshould assume a proportionate charge of the OttomanPublic Debt.4. N.B. The Russian Government refused to ratify the decisions of the Paris Economic Conference ( [1916]. See under France (iii)), except on certain terms, and no reply has been received to alterna-tive proposals which were put before the Russian Government last year by the British and French Governments.
TO ROUMANIAWe are bound (if bound at all)  1. By the Roumanian Agreement (17th August, 1916), by which we undertook-(i.) To guarantee the territorial integrity of Roumania. (ii.) Not to make a separate peace.(iii.) To secure in the final peace settlement the annexation to Roumania of the Austro-ITungarian territories as marked on Map III.2. By public statements and assurances to the effect that the liberation of Roumania and the Roumanians consti&amp;ute an essential war aim (e.g., inclusion of Roumania in Mr. Asquith&apos;s &quot;We shall not sheathe the sword&quot; statement and in our reply to President Wilsons peace note. Liberation of Roumanian territory restated in Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s War Aims Speech of the 5th January, 1918).TO THE KING OF THE HEDJAZWe are bound -1. By the Anglo-French Agreements of 1916, which have been communicated to the Kino-.2. By various written assurances given to the King by the High Commissioner in Egypt, namely: (a.) (17th December, 1917) that &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government had no intention of concluding any peace in the terms of which tho freedom of the Arab people from German and Turkish domination did not form an essential condition.&quot;(b.) That His Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared to &quot; recognise and support the in iependence of the Arabs within territories bounded on the west by the Red Sea, on the south by the Indian Ocean, on the east by the Persian Gulf and the Turco-Persian frontier. The northern and north-western to be left for subsequent discussion. As regards Mesopotamia the King was warned that &quot; The established interests of Great Britain would necessitate special measures of administrative control.&quot;(c.) That Great Britain would guarantee the Holy Places against external ao-pression.We are also bound by subsidiary treaties to Ibn Saud and the Iclrissi Saiyid, but these obligations are of a local rather than an international character.TO JAPANWe are bound 1. By the Pact of London.2. By the Assurance of the 14th February, 1917. By which we undertook that His Majesty&apos;s Government would support at the Peace Conference Japans claims in regard to the disposal (i) of Germ.any&apos;s rights in Shantung (Kiaochow), (ii) of the German possessions in the Pacific Islands north of the Equator. In return for which Japan will support the claims of Great Britain to the German Islands south of the Equator.3. By the Paris Economic Conference (1916) (see under France (iii)). In ratifying the resolutions of the Conference the Japanese Government reserved considerable liberty of action, and His Majesty&apos;s Government made similar reservations vis-d-vis of the Japanese Government.
TO CHINA.1. At the time when we were obtaining Chinese coolies for work in France we gave the Chinese Government an assurance (30th December, 1916) to the effect that &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment would protect China against any aggressive action taken by an enemy Power on the ground of a supposed breach of neutrality arising out of the engagement of these coolies.&apos;&apos;2. On the occasion of China&apos;s entry into the war we agreed (a.) To the raising of the Tariff to an effective 5 per cent. (6.) To the postponement of the Boxer indemnity for a period of five years.TO BELGIUM.1. Declaration of the 14th February, 1916, by which we assured the Belgian Government that &quot;Belgium will be invited to take part in the Peace Conference, and the guaranteeing Powers will not cease hostilities unless Belgium is reinstated in her political and economic indenendence and largely indemnified for wrongs suffered.&quot; The guaranteeing Powers at the same time undertook to lend Belgium their assistance to secure her commercial and financial recovery.2. By the Assurance of the 9th April, 1916, we promised the Belgian Government that we would support them at the Peace Conference with a view to maintaining the present territorial limits of the Belgian Congo and to securing fir that colony a special indemnity for losses suffered during the war.3. Lord Grey, in May 1916, indicated to the Belgian Minister for Foreign Affairs that if the Netherlands Government after the war desire to enter into any general agreement with us, His Majesty&apos;s Government might be prepared to use their good offices to secure a solution of the Scheldt question in a sense favourable to Belgium. The above intimation, however, can scarcely be regarded as a promise.4. The Belgian Foreign Minister endeavoured subsequently to elicit from Lord Grey an assurance that His Majesty&apos;s Government would support the claim of Belgium for a customs union with Luxern-bourg, Lord Grey merely replied that this was a question that concerned France more than us, but that &quot;if the Allies won the war the)r ought to secure the independence and integrity of Luxembourg.&quot;5. We are also bound to Belgium under the decisions of the Paris Economic Conference.   (See under France (3).)6. By the resolutions of the Conference (Paris, October 1917), whereby the so-called policy of the bloc was decided upon, i.e., enemy private property and interests in Allied or occupied territory at the end of the war is to be held as a pledge for Allied private property and interests in enemy or enemy-occupied territory. (See under France (4).)7. Assurances have been given that we will do our utmost to help in the industrial reconstruction of Belgium, and an Inter-Allied Commission has been formed in London to consider ways and means.TO SERBIAWe are bound 1. By the decisions of the Paris Economic Conference. (See France (3).)f. By several public statements regarding restitution and reparation, and by the references to Serbia in the Allies&apos; reply to President Wilson&quot;s Peace Note.N.B. In August 1915 we guaranteed to Serbia Bosnia, Herzegovina, Slavonia, and Syrmia, with portions of the Dalmatian[238] &apos; &apos; C
and Albanian coast, on condition that Serbia offered Bulgaria the uncontested zone. This condition was not fulfilled, so that our guarantee is not contractually valid. At the same time, the fact that the guarantee was offered, even though conditionally, should be borne in mind. It should also be noted that Sir E. Grey informed the Serbian Minister verbally on the 6th May, 1915, that &quot;the victory of the Allies would secure for Serbia, Bosnia, and Herzegovina wide access to the Adriatic, to say nothing of what Montenegro and Croatia would have.&quot;TO PORTUGALWe are bound 1. By the re-affirmation in 1899 of our ancient treaties, notably that of 1661, under which we undertook &quot; to defend and protect all conquests or colonies belonging to Portugal.&quot; The fact that the entry of Portugal into the war is based on this Treaty of Alliance renders these obligations more binding&quot; than when the alliance had not been appealed to as an effective instrument.2. By the decisions of the Paris Economic Conference. (See France (3).)3. By the fact that during the war we have allowed the Portuguese to administer the portion of German East Africa which lies south of the River Rovuma, thus implicitly recognising the Portuguese claim to this district.TO GREECEWe are bound only ]. By the Treaty of 1863, which re-affirmed our position as a Power guaranteeing Greece as an independent and Constitutional Monarchy.&apos;1. Our moral obligations towards M. Venizelos are naturally of a very binding nature, although the previous offer of Cyprus has, of course, lapsed.   Moreover, under the Sykes-Picot Agreement we are bound not to cede Cyprus to any third Power without French consent.TO SWEDEN.Under the Convention of 1856, to which, however, Sweden is not a party, we agreed that the Aland Islands should not be fortified by Russia. In 1915 the Germans attacked one of these islands, and the Russians then decided on placing the islands in a state of defence. They therefore assured the Swedish Government that the measures taken were defensive only, and for the period of the war. As signatories of the 1856 Convention, His Majesty&apos;s Government have officially associated themselves with this assurance.TO HOLLANDWe are bound 1. By the official assurance, given at the beginning of the war, that if Holland maintained her neutrality we would not violate her territory.2. By public statements (eg., Lord Robert Cecil, Plouse of Commons, 13th December, 1917) : &quot; There is not now, and never has been, any intention to interfere in any way with the independence or integrity of Holland or her possessions.&quot;TO SWITZERLANDWe are bound By the assurance of the 17th December, 1917, to the effect that we would respect the integrity and neutralitv of Switzerland so long as such neutrality was observed by the Swiss Government themselves and by our enemies.
TO THE POLESWe are not. of course, bound by any contractual obligation, although we have officially associated ourselves with the Russian declaration of March 1917 in the following terms: &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government are happ)r to give their complete adherence to the principle of an independent and united Poland &quot; (0/, the Asquith-Briand telegram of the 16th November, 1916. Reaffirmed in Mr. Lloyd Georges War Aims speech, 5th January, 1918).TO THE JEWSWe are bound only by the limited assurances given to Lord Rothschild in Mr. Balfour&apos;s letter.TO THE JUGO-SLAVSW e are bound by public statements and by the reference made to their aspirations in the Allied reply to President Wilson&apos;s Peace Note.It should be noted also that on the 30th August, 1915, Sir E. Grey assured M. Supilo that &quot; after the war Bosnia, Her-zegovina, Southern Dalmatia, Slavonia, and Croatia shall be free. The]? can decide their own fate.&quot;TO THE CZECHO-SLOVAKSWe have committed ourselves only by a vague reference in the Allies&apos; reply to President Wilsons Peace Note.TO THE ALBANIANSWe are bound only by vague assurances of sympathy. Our obligations to Albania, incurred bv the decisions of the Ambassadors&apos; Conference of 1913, and by the Florence Protocol, being of an inter-national character, are presumably regarded as having lapsed with the outbreak of war, and they have in any case been superseded by our commitments under the Italian Treaty of 1915.We have been very careful to incur no obligations whatsoever towards Essad Pasha.TO THE ARMENIANSWe are not bound by any valid contractual obligations, although we are morallv committed to the Armenians not only by article 61 of the Berlin Treaty of 1878, but &quot;also by the many public statements made on their behalf.   (See Appendix, section 8.)TO PERSIAWe are not as )ret bound by any definite agreements. His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Tehran has, however, just been authorised to intimate to the Persian Government that His Majestj-&apos;s Government would be prepared, in certain circumstances, to regard the Anglo-Russian Convention of 1907 as being in suspense.We have also concluded (16th February, 1916) a local arrange-ment with the Bakhtiari Khans.In connection with Persia it should be borne in mind that our responsibilities towards the Anglo-Persian Oil Company amount almost to an obligation.TO AFGHANISTAN.The Ameer was assured in the summer of 1916 that 1. No proposal affecting the interests of Afghanistan will bemade or agreed to at the Peace Conference. 2. That if, as a sequel to the Peace Conference, any suchquestion should arise, nothing will be decided withoutthe Ameer being consulted.H. G. N.February 6, 1918.
8&apos; - - WAR   AIMS.the points tabulated below are those   distinguished   by president. wilson as being at, issue.    the  list formed the basis of counts hertling and cxeriiin&apos;s replies, and is there-tore the must convenient avail-able, though not, of course, necessarily exhaustive.	AMERICAN TERMS. Source. president wilson&apos;s speech of january 8, 191S, as reported in the &quot; times &quot; of january 9 (unless other source stated).	BRITISH TERMS. Source. mr. lloyd george&apos;s speech of january 5, IMS, as reported in the &quot;times&quot; of january 7 (unless other source stated).	FRENCH TERMS. Source. m. piehoivs speech of   december   2S,   1917,   as reported in the &quot;times&quot; of december  29  (unless  other source stated).	ITALIAN TEEMS.1. belgium..	Complete restoration, with sovereign rights unimpaired.	Complete restoration. Reparation for damage done.	Deliverance of territory. Reparation.	1 12. occupied france.	Evacuation of occu-pied territory.	Evacuation of occu-pied territory.	As above.	3. alsace-lorraine.	Wrong doneby Prussia iu 1871 to be righted.	Reconsideration of the great wrong of 1871.	Restitution  of terri-tories torn away by force and,  consequently,  re-tui-u of Alsace-Lorraine to France.	i4. italian frontier.	Readjustment along clearly recognisable lines of nationality.	Evacuation of occu-pied territory. Italians must obtain union with those of their own race and tongue.	(See point 1.)	5. russia. 5a. poland.	Evacuation of occu-pied Russia, and friendly aid of sister democracies towards self-develop-ment of Russia. An independent Po-land.	Russia, if bent on a separate peace, must negotiate it without the Allies&apos; aid. An independent Po-land, comprising all Poles who wish to join it.	If Russia deserts her Allies they cannot help her. As   regards   Poland, principle   applies   that peoples must be free to choose their own des-tiuies.	6. balkan states. 6a. boumania. 6b. serbia. 6c. montenegro.	Relations of Ralkan States to be settled on lines of allegiance and nationality. Serbia to be given access to the sea.	Restoration of Rou-mania. Justice to be done to men of Rou-manian blood and speech. Restoration of Serbia and Montenegro.	(See point 1.) Principle  laid  down in 5a mentioned as ap-plying to Serbia also.	
WAR  AIMS.9				RUSSIAN TEEMS.	AUSTRIAN TERMS.	GERMAN TERMS.	TURKISH TERMS.	DEGREESource. Statement of Rus-siau    Delegates   at    Brest-Litovsk, December 22, 1917, as reported ill the &quot;Times&quot; of December 28, and Mr. Liml-lcy&apos;s  telegram  So. 210K - of December 2o (unless  other source stated).	Source. Count     Czernin&apos;s speech of January 24, 1918, as reported in the &quot;Times&quot; of January   26   (unless   other sjuree stated).   [Regard has been had to the inaccuracies in   the   &quot;Times&quot;   version, pointed out by &quot; Daily News,&quot; February 5.]	Source. Count    Hertling&apos;s speech of January 24, 1918, as reported in the &quot;Times&quot; of January   26   (unless   other source stated).		of AGKEEMENT.No forcible annexa-tions of territories con-quered during the war. Political independence of peoples conquered during the war to be fully restored. No public indemnities: but losses of private persons to be met from special fund to which all belligerents shall contribute proportion-ately.	Point not developed.	Forcible annexation of Belgium no part of German programme; but question cannot be discussed until Entente bave themselves openly admitted principle of integrity of territories of Central Powers.		Partial agreement as to evacuation; point of reparation not developed.(See point 1.)	Point not developed.	Forcible annexation no part of German policy.		Partial agreement.National groups not independent before the war shall decide their own destiny by referen-dum. For the latter purpose there must be independent voting for the whole population, including emigrants and refugees. (See a&apos;so point 8.)	Austria is bound to de-fend the pre-war posses-sions of her allies as she would her own.	There was no wrong of 1871, greater part of Alsace-Lorraine being historical^ German. Germany will never permit herself to be robbed of Alsaee-Lor-raine.		Acute disagreement.(See points 1 and 8.)	Can make no state-ment which, by coni-mitting the monarchy beforehand, would give the Entente advantage of being able to drag on the war relatively with-out risk.	Answer on this point must be left to the Austrian Minister for Foreign Affairs to make.		Point not developed : depends on attitude of Austria.(See points 1 and 3.)	Austria does not de-mand a square metre of Russian soil. t Independent Polish State to include all peoples indisputably Polish, with freedom to settle its own destiny.	Question concerns Russia and the Central Powers alone. Settlement of Poland exclusively concerns Germany, Austria-Hun-gary, and Poland. [N.B. Count Czernin, January 24, in referring to what he calls &quot; The divergence of view between our German ally and the Russian Government&quot; (as to the mode in which Russian peoples are to vote their own destinies), states that &quot; Germany has no intention of making any territorial conquest by violence at the expense of Russia.&quot;]	-	Question dependent upon result of Brest-Litovsk negotiations.(See point 1.)	Same attitude as in point 4.	Same attitude as in point 4.		Point not developed ; depends on attitude of Austria.[238]    - D
10 WAR AIMS.The points tabulated below are  those   distinguished   by President Wilson as being at iteue.    The list formed the iinsis of Counts Hertling and CV.eniin&apos;s leplies, and is there-fore the most- convenient avail-able, though not, of course, necessarily exhaustive.	AMERICAN TERMS. Source. President Wilsons speech of January S. 1918, as reported in the &quot; Times &apos;&apos; of Jauuarj- 9 (unless other source stated).	BRITISH TERMS. Source. Mr. Lloyd G eorge&apos;s speech of January 6, 1918, as reported in the &quot;Times&quot; of January 7 (unless other source stated).	FRENCH TERMS. -Source. M. Pic.hon&apos;s speech of   Deeembrr  2-!,   1917,  as reported in the &quot;Times&quot; of December  29  (unless  other source stated).	ITALIAN TERMS.7. Austria-Hun gury.	Peoples of Austria-Hungary to be given an opportunity of auto-nomous self-develop-ment.	Peoples must be given genuine self-government on democratic principles. No desire to dismember the Empire, but provisos made as to peoples of Italian and lioumanian blood. (See points 4 and 6a.)		8. Turkey. (Armenia, Syria, &amp;c.)	Non-Turkish nation-alities of Ottoman Ern-pire to be assured auto-nomous development. Dardanelles to be per-maiiently free to all ships.	Arabia, Armenia, Syria, Mesopotamia, and Palestine entitled to recognition of their separate nationalities. Black Sea to bs opened to all ships.	Armenia   and   Syria named   as   places   to which    principle    laid down in 5a applies.	9. -German Colonies.	Impartial adjustment of colonial claims; in-terests of natives to have equal weight, with claims of Governments asserting such.	Natives to be placed under an administra-tion acceptable to them-selves.		-10. league of Nations.	An Association of Na-tions affording guaran-tees of political and territorial independence for all States.	International organi-sation must be set up to establish law instead of war as the means of settling international controversy.		11. Freedom of Seas.	Complete freedom of navigation outside terri-torial waters both in peace and war, except when seas closed by international action.			13. Economic Kig-hts.	Eemoval as far as possible of all economic barriers.			13. Diplomacy.	No secret diplomacy.			14. Armaments,	Adequate guarantees for the reduction of armaments.	Armaments to be limited by international organisation.						Bern arks.				Foreign Office,February 6, 1918.
JSECRET.MAP TO ILLUSTRATE THE AGREEMENTS OF 1916 IN REG24;52036*eJx  .iullj , .lonasia   ^;&apos;V   TSlif!-jr.7/n*7&quot;i7uRi-6-1Urfa. IlakfciBeyrooigiigiAkka 0I&apos;^^^^^^A MAP OF^ ffiSTf V&apos;/.,.,,,sniailia ;Marcolis   &quot;^-S&apos;)&apos;&quot;&quot;&quot;^&apos;TURKEY in ASIAMrmphiAk1  Svl pSCALE OF   ENGLISH STATUTE MILES 50 40 30 20 10 0 50 100.V;(bhit Vafa or Jaffa/x//-/:&apos;....1 ^mils iirllimis in:-i.i/u;;i.uiiy/&apos;l- v,w7.      S . v^Pamascus v ; ,jri?     .f.flaui;aii^kMtiih ArniiwiTMil So a or HahivLootUead b**a or ikiiuu. ftephaltiies like r1)    s-; eX&quot;.1 \^ A-W-^VEl.Lim^itxide EhsI   280 of Greeuwich360^6&quot;^?. I//SS938) fiOJ38.FRENCH SPHERE. BRITISH SPHERE. ITALIAN SPHERE. INTERNATIONAL SPHERE.London : Etlw;ti-tl Stanford. 12,13 fV- It. Lone AerieC = Italian sphere of influence. RUSSIAN SPHERE.
ieAgreements of 1916 in regard to Asia Minor. Mesopotamia,&amp;.c.36&quot;40&quot;&apos;44&quot;48&quot;KE3r, p &apos; ri/--......*.KaleImY;   :,. V&apos;       . ,. / .......      ^&apos;1*UirajmnTtlymvliSWOTTripoli1- /;.i.f f.&quot; Aleppo;iiakkiiIBs/iW,?,i...-Xi.&apos;w.-/i ^-. 7 .7,i/) Ctlmnfyn&quot;l/,i/.-.vi,n/l) esj)amascus feW/i: \   _  V-,Jea(l S*ea or UahrLoot C&quot;! gVspialtiics Like ;fejvV-V&apos;    f. .0Suit;&quot;1lAnabsite/&quot;(VlOH&quot;&quot;   \tj/fit.(M.ln(/.-Jebcl) H   AAkabii\ 1    B.I/.m/t/   Slhullirh;ibiu uflvSulx^ilwfl&apos;,l.l&apos;1 EarniBaitU&quot;L1/.v/.1J.W .1/.&quot;&quot;i?ane\ v &quot;to-44&apos;48A &amp; B   r INDEPENDENT ARAB   STATE,A being in the French,and B in the British) sphere of influence.
sard to Asia Minor. Mesopotamia,&amp;cMAP 1rrV ,i&quot;;.......-       a^jr ito-44&quot;48Ja &amp; b   s INDEPENDENT ARAB   STATE,/4 iie//?  in the French, and B in the British^ sphere of influence.Stan/onis Geixf. fcsiah*London,
Blue ^ ItalyYellow ^ Croatia,Serbia, Montenegro. Red outline = Neutralised Coast.
MAP-2\    A^&quot; ^ 46Q&apos;Vttocfbltczo4     *TO    \\ X   X      ^ BaUahusIUmtcliTcchtmi&quot;- Tjrmrht^Biigaiyno6 .(i^T.Jjr ^*s ASLicoiiaGran oi-iuj  enihex iT /.. Pchujosa-3 ere-si.XRcrani j6fec,*  mate off   -42Gargaao JProtoonlarv roano /WS-Jhgeio-Jani&apos;rcdonia Gulf of MsuafVedoma\41Diu-azzoi\2hnopoli3riadisi-Ml-allipolj tf;Ac East 14 of Greeirwioh16&quot;61
48.\   \ IvaschauA&apos;m   */-&apos;;--...........v s........ -ifWiildla^1\5&quot;JBoi^sd&apos;,1SH7f.N/&apos;&quot;Ms,KJmoR.r/^-o-.^..If /),.,,/,J )uvi^t,f-1 * 54s- hiu-an.&apos; v.,FOCSMII.-iUivtiix 1&quot;H/sHf5*J Kiiiijiol&apos;i&quot;21    i/:^-- ,&apos;(lnni(Y.tiKiuinilcl&apos;   - if&quot;&quot;&apos;/    &quot;&quot;V !&apos;nilf.ili &apos;?     11,!liilaiH44aeuieudt-ih; *r&quot; ^-v-sa .....ljoiii-liily-ii \ &apos; I [l&apos;ilt&apos;SU- ^iHtlifvo/?&apos;    rT^-^j   - Plane&quot; -&quot;T^fVc &quot;^&quot;&quot;F^ IMo.^-    f&quot;(Slatiua&apos;. - i V. &apos;:     /I&quot;    ,,.     ,,   siT..tj..v:i A 1     &apos;\itjttnc Xlnif if20Longitude. East 22&quot; of GreejiwichB      U 24c L       G      A      R
MAP 328&quot;   RUQOl\)rtol/iiliilli8Scale of AlileseoR    I     A464430&quot;
WAS  AIMS. 11RUSSIAN TERMS. Source. Statement, of Ttus-sian    Delegates    at.    Erest-itovsk, December 22. 1917, as reported in the &quot;Times&quot; oi December 28, and Mr. I.isid-&apos;ey&apos;* telegram  Xo.  210S  of December  25  (unles-;  other source stated).	A USTRIAN TF.RMS Source. -Count. 1    Casern in &apos;s speech of January 21. !P!8, as reported in the &quot;Times&quot; of January   in   ;un]e-s   other source stated).   [Regard has heed had to the inaccuracies in   the    &quot;Times&apos;    version, pointed out hy &quot; Daily News,&quot; Februarys.]	GERMAN TERMS. Source. Count.    ITertling&apos;s speech of January 24, 1918, as reported in the &quot;&quot;Times&quot; of January    38   ,&apos;unt ss   other source stated).	TURKISH TERMS. ,	DEGREE OF AGREEMENT.(See points 3 and 8.)	No more democratic ParirtroeEt than the Austrian Parliament in the world. Austria-Hunoary can-not accept advice as to how to manage her do-mestic affairs.	Same as in point 4.		Agreement as far as developed; depends on attitude of Austiia.In regard to territory of mixed nationality the right of the  minority shall be protected by a special   law giving  it independence of national culture, and, if practic-able,   self - administr a-tion.	Same attitude as in point 3.	Cannot forestall the altitude of Turkish statesmen.		Not developed ; de-pends on attitude of Turkey.Colonial questions to to be settled in accord-ance with the principles laid down in points 1 and S.	(See point 3.)	Scheme outlined by President Wilson is im-practicable. Question can only be discussed in connection of general question of reconstruo-tion of world&apos;s c lonial possessions, which Ger-many unconditionally demands.		Disagreement.	No opposition to Pre-sictent Wilson&apos;s sugges-tion.	German Government in sympathy with idea ; will investigate possi-bility of it.		Agreement.No sea blockade which does not pursue a direct war aim.	Entire support of Pre-dent WilsoiVs formula.	General agreement with President Wil*on ; exception mentioned by him is, however, incont-prehensible, and must be struck out.		Agreement in principle, acute disagreement in practice.No economic boycotts.	In agreement with President Wilson.	Complete agreement with President Wilson.		Agreement, except in so far as Paris economic decisions may be said to stand.	No objection to sup-pression of secret dip-lornacy, but some doubt whether open diplomacy is very practical.	In agreement with President Wilson.		Agreement.-   -[ -,-:-	Armaments to be limited as suggested by President Wilson.	Matter suitable for discussion ; satisfactory settlement should be possible.		Agreement.I				I		1		

</content>
</cab>
