<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/45/0 images: 263-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIvS DOCUMENTISTHE PROPERTYOFS  g G  g  B  TeG.T*-3952. WAR     C A B I 1DISPOSAL CP PU :S7Aff QQOTrt QKOERKD AGAIK3TCopy of letter from Sir E. W;;ldboro Spit-Ii to Secretary, War Cabinet aCommission Internationale de Ravitaillement,India House,Kingsway, W.O.15 th March, 1918,Dear Colonel Hankey,With reference to 2ir* Crosby1b letter to the Prime Minister of the 8th March (G*T*3BB7) suggesting that a clearing house should be established under the Versailles Council to arrange for the dis-posal of goods ordered on Russian account out of Credits provided by the British, American and French  overaments, it is not clear whether Mre Crosby&apos;s suggestion is /(1)     That all such warlike stores should bs referred to theproposed clearing house, or ( )    That only the residue remaining after each CreditorGovernment has disposed of what it can, Should bego referred.If (1) is the suggestion, I may point out that it is now impracticable so far as  pods ordered on British Credits are eon-cerned,    These are rapidly,being disposed, of under a ^r-oo-edure formulated and promulgated by the treasury, whereby the Controlling Departments of H*LU Government, acting in conjunction with this Commission, take over any goods required for British purposes, and divert for the fulfilment of Allied demands, as far as is possible, v.any&quot; not so required.If (E) is the suggestion, I fully concur, since when every-thing possible has been done under the procedure outlined above, there will presumably still remain a residue consisting of such goods as arms and ammunition of Russian calibre, and manufactured articles of Russian specification.     The use to which such stores might best be applied should doubtless be decided on grounds of military or other policy by some central body of Inter-Allied Authority, such as the Versailles Council.     To this end I v;ould propose, if so directed, to have lists compiled of goods not required by the British or Allied Governments, which have been bought on British Credits,     These lists could be furnished periodically, or when completed, and I cresume that the American and French Governments would supply similar lists of goods bought on thsir credits, if the  p*e&amp;e&amp;mre was agreed upon.Other cases which might with advantage be referred for decision to the Supreme War Council are cases where the Creditor Government does not require any particular goods, wbioh are however required by two or more of the other Allied Governments, and the predominating consideration in the decision as to priority of claim is one of military policy.     Such cases are not likely to be numer-0u8, but machinery is required for dealing with them when they do arise.Yours sincerely,(Signed) EEfcOTD WYLDBORS SMITE.

</content>
</cab>
