<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/45/0 images: 416-417</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy No, 19^  SECRET.Genoral Headquarters,British Armies in Franco. No.. O.A.B,/145*. 19th March, 1918..Sir,I have the honour to forward herewith a reportreceived from the G,O.C, R.F.C., on tho bombing raidcarried out by the Ochoy Squadrons on the 16th March, 1918,I havo tho honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant, (Signed)   K. Wigram.B.G.for   Field-Marshal, Commanding-in-Chicf, British Armies in France.The Secretary, War Office,London, S.W.Lionel yea)&quot;-&apos;
Copy, SECRET.DETAILED REPORT ON BOMB RAID CARRIED OUT ONZWEIBRUCKEN    &apos; 16th March 1918.Ten machines of No. 55 Squadron left the ground at 11.0 a;mi to bomb the Badische-Aniline and Soda-Fabrik at Ludwigshafen.   One machine was forced to return with a leaky petrol pipe at 11-40 a,mi and one with engine trouble at 12-25 p.m.   The remaining machines crossed the lines at 10,000 feot and proceeded to their objective via Sarregu e mine s .Over Diouze four enemy aircraft attacked the formation at long rango and another of our machines was forced to return owing to the petrol tank being shot through.   The enemy aircraft eventually broke off the engagement after about 950 rounds had been fired by our machines.The remainder of the formation proceeded to Zweibrucken and as the country to the North of this town was covered with thick clouds,, they bombed the barracks and railway junction from 12,500 feot.Bombs were dropped as under ;-14   112-lb. 4    40-lb. (phosphorus) 6     25-lb,TOTAL   1,878-lbs.Bursts were observed in the railway station and in and around the barracks.   Only four plates were exposed owing to a plate breaking in the camera and jamming It.Anti-aircraft fire was very slight.All our machines returned to their aerodrome at 1-50 p.m. The weather was clear at first but clouded up very rapidly towards midday,(Signed)   R. PROUT, Captain, Brigade-Major, for Brigadier-General. In the Field. G.O.C., 8th Brigade,Royal Flying Corps.

</content>
</cab>
