<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 57-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   (Distributed to the Council,  to the Members of the league and to the Delegates at the Assembly.)A 6- (a) 1922.Geneva,  August 28th, 1922.LEAGUE OF  NATIONSSupplementary  Report  to  the Third  Assembly  on  the  Work  of  the  Council   and  on  the  Measures  taken  to execute  the  Decisions of  the Assembly (July-August  1922).
CONTENTS. i.  LEGAL QUESTIONS:                                                           page.         I.  Committee on Amendments to the Covenant.............      3        II.  Procedure of Conciliation......................      3 2.  THE ECONOMIC WEAPON OF THE LEAGUE........  .  ..........      3 3.  PERMANENT COURT OF INTERNATIONAL JUSTICE.................      4 4.  FINANCIAL  ADMINISTRATION OF THE LEAGUE  ................. .      5 5.  LIAISON OFFICE WITH LATIN AMERICA....................      5 6.  REDUCTION OF ARMAMENTS........................&apos; .      6 7.  POLITICAL  QUESTIONS :           I.   Incursions into the Frontier Districts of the States bordering on Bulgaria .     8        II..  The Frontier between Austria and Hungary..............     9        III.  The Frontier between Hungary and the  Serb-Croat-Slovene State.  ...     10 .-8..  TERRITORY OF THE SAAR  BASIN.......................     10 9.  MANDATES...................................     1210.  THE WORK OF THE TECHNICAL  ORGANISATIONS:           I.  The Provisional Economic and Financial Committee..........     15         II.  Communications and Transit Organisations .  .  .  . .  .  .  .  . . .  ....     15        III.  Health Organisation ......................- .  -     1611.  THE  GENOA CONFERENCE  AND  THE  LEAGUE OF  NATIONS...........     1812.  SOCIAL  QUESTIONS:           I.  Traffic in Opium and other dangerous Drugs.............     19         II.  Traffic in Women and Children....................     19        III.  Deportation of Women and Children in Turkey and neighbouring Countries    19 13.   RELIEF OF RUSSIAN REFUGEES.......................     19 14.   FAMINE IN RUSSIA...............................     20 15.   COMMITTEE ON INTELLECTUAL CO-OPERATION.................     21
LEGAL QUESTIONSI. THE AMENDMENTS COMMITTEE.    The Council decided, on July 18th, to leave it to the discretion of the Chairman of the Com-mittee on Amendments to the Covenant (General Report, page 12) to fix the date on which theCommittee should, if necessary, come together.    The Council, on July 18th, approved the report of the Committee entrusted with the enquiry into a procedure of conciliation (GeneralReport, page 13).         .&apos; .    The Council, at its meeting on January 10th, decided to ask the Members of the League foxtheir observations on the proposed rules for guidance in the application of the economic weaponof the League laid down in the resolutions adopted by the Assembly on October 4th, 1921.  Upto the present replies have been received from the following Governments:    These replies have been circulated to the Members of the Council and to the Members of theLeague for their information.  Most of the Governments state that they are willing to acceptthe recommendations of the Assembly, but some of them point out that it will be necessary tointroduce legislation in  order to enable these rules to be  applied when the necessity arises, and attention is drawn by certain Governments to constitutional or other difficulties with which theyare confronted.II. REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ENTRUSTED WITH THE ENQUIRY            INTO A PROCEDURE OF CONCILIATION.THE ECONOMIC WEAPON OF THE  LEAGUEAustriaBulgariaGreat BritainItalyJapanSiamSwedenSwitzerlandCzechoslovakia
PERMANENT COURT OF. INTERNATIONAL JUSTICE    The  Court opened its first ordinary session on July 15th,  1922.    The public business before the Court was the consideration of three requests for an advisoryopinion made  to it by the Council,  under Article 14 of the Covenant.    The  first two questions referred to  the Court were:Question  I:                                  .     .            &quot; Was the Workers&apos; delegate for the Netherlands at the third session of the Inter-        national Labour Conference nominated in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 3        of Article&apos; 389 of  the Treaty  of Versailles ?&quot;&apos;    -Question II:            &quot;Does the competence  of the International Labour  Organisation extend to interna-        tional regulations of the conditions of labour of persons employed in agriculture?&quot;    On July 18th, the Council, on the proposal of the French representative, resolved to address to the Court  the following additional  question:Question  III :            &quot;Does the examination of  proposals for the organisation and development of me-        thods of agricultural production, and of other questions of a like character, fall within        the competence of  the  International  Labour Organisation ?&quot;    The  Council has received the opinion of the Court upon each of the above questions.  TheCourt answers  the first question in the affirmative, stating in its judgement that, since the Nether-lands Workers&apos; delegate to the third  session of the International Labour Conference.was admitted by the Conference, the Court is of opinion that the sole object of the question submitted to it isto obtain an interpretation of paragraph 3 of Article 389 of the Treaty of Versailles.    The  Court answers the second  question in  the affirmative,  two of the judges dissenting.    The  third  question was answered in the  negative.S-special Chambers provided jot in the Statute of. the  Court.    The  Special Chamber for  Labour questions will,  for the period ending on  December .31st1924, be composed as follows:.    Members: Lord FINLAY (President),  MM. de BUSTAMENTE, ALTAMIRA, ANZILOTTI and HUBEK    Substitutes: MM. NYHOLM-and MOORE.    The  Special  Chamber  for Transit and  Communications  will be composed  as follows:.    Members:  MM.  WEISS  (President), BARBOZA, NYHOLM,  MOORE and  ODA.    Substitutes: MM. ANZILOTTI and HUBER.  - The  Court also elected  the members of its  Chamber for  Summary Procedure for the year1923; this Chamber willbe composed as follows :   ^Members:  MM.  LODER  (President), WEISS, MOORE.    Substitutes: Lord FINLAY,  M.   ALTAMIRA.    This Chamber, for the period ending December 31st of the present year, will  be composed asfollows:    Members:  M. LODER (President), MM. WEISS and HUBER.    Substitutes: Lord FINLAY and M.  ALTAMIRA.
THE  FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION  OF THE LEAGUEBudget  and Audited Accounts.    The Council, on July 17th, considered a report on the budget for the fifth fiscal period (1923),on the audited accounts for the third fiscal period (1921), and on the first report of the Commissionof Control  (General  Report,  page 17),    The Council decided, in view of the  short time at its disposal before the expiry of the delaywithin which the budget as approved by the Council  must be circulated to the Members of theLeague, not to examine the budget for  the fifth fiscal period during that session.    The Council, in taking this decision, reasserted the right of its  Members which it had reservedat the previous session  (General Report, page 17) for its  representatives to discuss  or proposeamendments  to the budget in their capacity  as Members of the  Assembly.    The Council, in adopting the audited accounts for the third fiscal period, directed the Secre-tary General to thank the Netherlands Government for having put officials from its audit depart-ment at the disposal of the League, and to thank the auditor and the members of the Commissionof Control  for their  work.The Allocations Committee.    The Committee on the Allocation of Expenses was,  on January 14th, 1922, invited by theCouncil to continue its work in accordance with the recommendation  of the Second Assembly.    The Committee met in Paris for a session which lasted from June 28th to July 1st, 1922.It was composed as follows: M. J. REVEILLAUD (France), Chairman, M. Barboza CARNEIRO (Brazil),M. JANCOVICI (Roumania), M. SOLERI (Italy), and Sir Henry STRAKOSCH (South Africa).    The Committee presented its report to the Council in July,  and the Council, on July 17th,authorised the Secretary-General to circulate this report to the Members of the League for their consideration prior to  the meeting  of  the  Assembly.                                   5APPOINTMENT OF  A LIAISON  OFFICE WITH THE STATES                       OF LATIN AMERICA.     The Second Assembly, at its meeting held on October 1st, 1921, decided, in approving the report of the 4th Committee, to establish a liaison office between the League of Nations and the States of  Latin America.   It  was understood that the Secretary-General would place definite proposals before the Council for its approval.  A sum of 97,715 francs was set aside in the budget for the establshment of the office.                                              ,     The Secretary-General, accordingly,  submitted a  memorandum to the Council,, which was approved on May nth, 1922.  He pointed out that  the results of the journey undertaken in 1921 by two members of tho Secretariat in Latin America did not enable him to make a definite recommendation, as to the seat of the office.  He represented, however, that it was essential to give effect as soon as possible to  the spirit of the Assembly&apos;s decision by making an effort toimprove the liaison between the  central  organisations of the League and  the  States  of  Latin^America.   He  therefore proposed to set up a small office immediately in Geneva, the members of which would be chosen by the Secretary-General from among nationals of the States of Latin America.   The appointments would  have  a provisional character, and would terminate at the expiry of one year, so that the Third Assembly would remain free finally  to fix the seat of the office.                                                                                 .
    The Council approved these proposals and a correspondence followed between the Secretary-General and the representatives of  a certain number of States of Latin America.   The corres-pondence showed that,  though there was the greatest sympathy for the  scheme, there  was ageneral desire that the  appointment of the members of the office should  not be hastily  made,and that care should be taken to appoint a staff which should be really capable  of fulfilling the delicate task entrusted  to it to the full satisfaction of the interested States.  The Secretary-General decided, in accordance with the wishes which had been expressed,  to wait for the ThirdAssembly in order that the representatives of all the States of Latin America might be consulted on amiatter in which they were so nearly concerned.                  6REDUCTION  OF  ARMAMENTS.     The Temporary  Mixed. Commission met  in.  Paris  from  July 3rd  to 7th,  1922,  and M. Viviani, as Chairman of the Commission, presented a report to the Council in London on July 20th.                      GENERAL SCHEME FOR A REDUCTION  OF ARMAMENTS. (a) Limitation of Land Armaments.     The proposals submitted by Lord Esher to the Temporary Commission in  February 1922 were considered during the  July session.     Lord EsAer&apos;s scheme for a proportionate reduction on the lines of the Washington agreements for naval reduction was referred by the Commission to a sub-committee of six members, and the Commission decided to request the Council  to invite the technical opinion of the Permanent Armaments Commission on  its merits.     The Commission  further considered proposals presented on July 3rd by Lord Robert Cecil, defining the principles which he considered might serve as the basis of a scheme for the general reduction of armaments.  Lord Robert Cecil&apos;s proposals were  based on the assumption that no disarmament  was possible unless it was universal  and simultaneous with a treaty of mutual guarantee.  The Commission referred Lord Robert Cecil&apos;s proposals to the sub-committee appoint- ed to consider the proposals of Lord Esher.     The Council, on July 20th, requested the Permanent Advisory Commission to consider Lord Esher&apos;s plan from a technical point of view  and to forward its conclusions as early as possible to the Temporary Mixed Commission. (b) Limitation  of Naval Armaments.     Three schemes were before the Temporary Commission during its July session for the exten- sion of the principles  which inspire the Naval Treaty of Washington to the naval armaments of Powers which were not parties to the Treaty.     The Commission  decided to ask the Council to  refer  these schemes to the Naval Sub-Com- mission of the Permanent Advisory Commission.     The Council, on July 20th, requested the Naval Sub-Commission  to present its report as soon as possible,  and to forward it directly to the Second  Sub-Committee of the Temporary &quot;Mixed Commission.   The  Council  further decided to  inform the Governments concerned that they would  be called upon at the next  session  of  the Assembly to consider the advisability of convening an international conference for the purpose  of extending to non-signatory Powers the principles which  inspire the Treaty of Washington. -    The Naval Sub-Commission met at Geneva on July 24th and  forwarded  its report to the Temporary Mixed Commission on July 27th. (c) Statement of Governments on their National Requirements.    The Temporary Mixed Commission, during its July session, noted that  the object of the in vitation to the Governments to make a statement on  their military  requirements for  national securitywas to obtain positive information which would place the problem of the reduction of armamentsin direct relation with existing political, geographical and  strategical  facts  (General Report,page 19).  It was obvious to the Commission that no scheme for a reduction  of armaments wouldhave any chance of acceptance unless it  took account of the factors mentioned in Article 8 of
the Covenant, that is to say the national security, international obligations, geographical situation,and special conditions of each of the countries concerned.     The Council, on July 20th, decided that its  President should request the Governments whohad not yet forwarded a statement to reply as  soon as possible, in order that the commission might have material for the report which it was  bound to. present to the Assembly in September.The Council authorised the Secretary-General to communicate the replies of the Governmentsatd the members of the Commission.  Twenty replies have been received, i.e., those of albania                Esthonia              Haiti                PolandAustria                Finland               Italy                South AfricaBelgium                France               Japan               Switzerland.Bulgaria                Great Britain          Latvia               S.C.S. StateCzechoslovakia         Greece               Lithuania            Siam     All these  replies have been duly communicated to the members of the Temporary. mixed commission.                                        ARMS TRAFFICDistribution of Surplus Stocks of Munitions.          .                                     .     The Temporary Mixed Commission, during its July session, noted the report of the PermanentArmaments Commission  on surplus stocks of munitions  (General  Report,  page  22) and on themeasures taken by the various States for the liquidation of these stocks.   The Commission was of the opinion that this question had now been settled in accordance with the wishes of the second Assembly.                               THE CONVENTION OF ST-GERMAIN.     The Temporary Mixed Commission, at its July session, requested the Council again to approach the Governments  in order to secure an early ratification of the Convention of St. Germain.     The Council, on July 20th, decided to request all the Members of the League, who had not yet ratified the Convention,  to make  all  the necessary preparations to ratify, in order that formal ratifications might be deposited as soon as the principal signatory Powers, including the United States of America,  were  ready to  do so1.                                             ,  .,.     The necessary steps for the carrying out of the decision of the Council have been taken.by the Secretariat.                                        ,                     .                                       POISONOUS GASES.    The Temporary Mixed Commission, considered a proposal that Members of the League shouldbe urged to adhere to the Washington Treaty concerning the use of asphyxiating and poiosnousgases in time of war (General Report, page 22).  The  Commission decided not  to take action until  it was informed  that  the Washington Treaty had been forwarded to the non-signatoryStates after ratification by the signatory Powers.   &apos; The Commission further decided to ask the Committee on Intellectual Co-operation,  whichwas to meet in August, for its advice as to  the  methods by which  the co-operation of scientificmen might be  secured in order to  carry out  the resolution of.the  Second Assembly.  It was provided  in the Assembly  resolution  that scientific men  should  be invited  to publish theirdiscoveries  on poisonous gas  and  similar  subjects, so  as to  minimise the likelihood of their employment. (General Report, page 22).                                 ...  .  .    The Council, on July 20th, expressed the hope that the Committee on Intellectual. Co-operation would be able to present a report on the subject to the Temporary Mixed Commission before theend of August.  The Committee on  Intellectual Co-operation after careful consideration adopted a resolution on August 5th, 1922, regretting its inability to suggest any methods by which scienti-fic men could be induced to publish their discoveries.                               ;    1 A despatch has since been received by the Secretary-General from the Department of State at Washington, dated july 28th. The despatch, while pointing out that Congress has already enacted legislation making it unlawful in certaincircumstances to export arms and munitions from the United  States except under such limitations  and exceptions asthe President may prescribe, contains the following explicit statement in regard to the ratification of the Convention of st. Germain :    i! In reply to the inquiry made by the Secretary-General : whether the Government of the United States of america is prepared to ratify the Convention of St. Germain, the Secretary of State begs to state that the terms of the proposed convention have been carefully examined and that, while the Government of the United States is in  cordial sympathy with efforts to restrict traffic in arms and munitions of war, it finds itself unable to approve the provisions of the Con-vention and to give any assurance of its ratification, n
                      PRIVATE MANUFACTURE OF AND TRADE  IN ARMS.    The Council was requested by the Second Assembly to invite the Members of the League andother interested States to take part in an international conference on the trade in arms to meeton a date to be fixed by the Council.    The Temporary Commission was entrusted with the task of  preparing the programme of theconference and of submitting a draft convention (General Report, page 20).    The Council  decided, on  March 25th, that a conference could not  be  summoned until theTemporary Mixed Commission had completed its examination of the question.    The Council,  on July 20th, was informed of the progress made by the Temporary Commissionin its preliminary work.    A preliminary legal study of the problems arising out of the application of Article 8 of theCovenant has been made by the Secretariat, and technical studies of the administrative, industrial and military problems involved have  been  prepared by General Marietti and  Colonel Carnegie,members of the Tempc rary Commission.    The Permanent Advisory Commission has prepared a report defining the technical terms usedin this connection, such as &quot;arms  and munitions&quot; and &quot;private manufacture&quot;.  These  defini-tions have been accepted by the Temporary Commission.  The Temporary  Commission is consi-dering a draft convention, under which licences would be required.for the private manufacture ofmunitions.    M. Viviani informed the Council on July 20th that the results of this preliminary work wouldbe submitted  to the Council  at the session to be held in September.  He said that the council would then be in a better position to judge whether the moment had come for convening an inter-national conference.                         BUDGETARY LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.   . The Temporary Mixed Commission, during its session in July, noted with satisfaction reduc-tions in the military budgets of various States, and adopted a resolution, subsequently approvedby the Council on July 20th, under which the Governments which had not replied in 1922 to the inquiries which the Council had addressed to them were invited to do so, if possible before August15th of the current year (General Report, page 22).  The Council also approved a resolution of theTemporary Mixed Commission according to which the actual military expenditure of the Membersof the League will be the subject of a comparative statistical study to be presented to the Assemblysince many countries, though unable to engage themselves beforehand to a limitation of  expen-diture, have in practise carried out the policy recommended by the Assembly.7POLITICAL  QUESTIONS. I. INCURSIONS OF ARMED BANDS IN THE FRONTIERS DISTRICTS OF THE STATES BORDERING ON                                         BULGARIA.    The Governments of Greece, Roumania and the Serb-Croat-Slovene State on June 14th 1922addressed a collective note to the Bulgarian Government protesting  against the incursions of armed bands in the frontier districts of their respective territories.    There are estimated to be about 500,000 refugees in Bulgaria drawn from territories whichwere in; the  occupation  of Bulgaria before the late war and also before the Balkan wars which preceded it.   Some of these have formed  themselves into  small bands which continually passacross, the frontiers, provoking . disorder and giving rise to protests on the part of neighbouringStates.    There had previously been  negotiations  on the subject  with the Bulgarian Government,arising out of  complaints which  had been made by the Serb-Croat-Slovene Government in the spring of 1921-.:  The-Bulgarian Government had then replied  that it would welcome an investi-gation into the facts, and had asked the  Serb-Croat-Slovene Government to  choose between theprocedure of a mixed commission and an international inquiry..
      The Bulgarian Government  considered that the note presented by the  three Governments  on June 14th was of a.threatening character, and that it was unjustifiably blamed for responsibility  in the formation of the armed bands and for their incursions over the frontiers of its neighbours.  The Bulgarian Government accordingly  appealed to the Council of the League under Article n  of the Covenant.  The appeal was made on June 17th, T922, and the note of the. three Govern-i merits was represented by Bulgaria to be a circumstance likely to affect international relations underIphe conditions presupposed in that Article.      The Council heard the representatives of the four Governments concerned at a public meeting  held in London on July 18th,  1922.   The Bulgarian representative came to the  Council  with a  proposal that a commission of inquiry should be appointed.      The representatives of Roumania, Greece, and the Serb-Croat-Slovene State submitted that the  note of June 14th could not be regarded as.a circumstance affecting the friendly relations of the  parties, and denied that the note was of a threatening character.  It was true  that  the Serb-  Croat-Slovene Government had not agreed to the suggestion made by the Bulgarian Government  for a mixed commission; but the Bulgarian Government had  made  further proposals, namely,  that the military and administrative authorities on the frontiers should arrange between them-  selves a common plan of action against  the bands,  and the Serb-Croat-Slovene Government had  accepted these proposals in principle.   Moreover, negotiations were even then proceeding between  the parties, and the Roumanian  representative announced that as  a result of these negotiations  the Serb-Croat-Slovene Legation at Sofia had been instructed to accept proposals put forward by.  the Bulgarian Government on June 19th.      The Council noted the declaration made by the representatives of the three States  bordering  on Bulgaria that the step which they had taken in addressing a collective communication to the  Bulgarian  Government on June  14th was in no way unfriendly.   It further noted that direct  conversations were proceeding between the interested Governments, and that the Governments  were ready,  if these  negotiations were unfavourable, and if the terms of the Covenant  should  become applicable,  to bring the question  again before the Council.   It expressed the hope that the  efforts of the Governments to settle the question by direct agreement might be brought to a satis-  factory conclusion and requested the Governments to inform the Council at its next session of the  results of the negotiations. Finally, it placed itself at the disposal  of the Governments,  should  its intervention be  again required to avoid all possibility of conflict.II.  THE FRONTIER BETWEEN AUSTRIA AND HUNGARY.       The Conference of Ambassadors on  July 22nd,  1920, and  again  on June 3rd, 1921, issued  instructions to the Delimitation Commissions  which had been entrusted with the definition of the  frontiers of Hungary.   It was stated in  these instructions that the Commissions might make  modifications in the frontiers, as defined in the Treaty of Trianon, provided  they were of small  importance and were unanimously approved by the Commissions.   The Commissions were fur-  ther instructed, if in certain districts they thought it necessary  to make modifications which  from their nature and importance went beyond  their normal competence, to address a report  on the subject to the Council of the League of  Nations.  It was understood that the Commissions  might not in any case alter materially the territorial basis of  the Treaty.   Austria, under the  Protocol of Venice, undertook, in the event of her wishing to lodge an appeal against the decisions  of the Delimitation Commission for the Austro-Hungarian frontier, to accept as final the decision  of the Council of the League.       The Delimitation  Commission for the frontier between Austria and Hungary decided on  March 28th by 5 votes to 1 to present a report to the Council of the League on certain proposed  modifications of the  frontier between these two States.   This report was forwarded by the Confe-  rence of Ambassadors to the Council of the  League,  which was invited under the Protocol ofi  Venice to decide whether the suggested modifications of the frontier should be carried out.       The Council discussed this question in the presence of the interested parties on July 19th.3  1922 and it decided  to assume the responsibilities defined in the Protocol of Venice.       The representative of Austria explained that the  question at issue was whether the frontier  of the Burgenland should remain as fixed  by the treaties,  or whether it should be modified.  He1  represented that Austria had already consented to a considerable sacrifice in signing the ProtocolI  of Venice,  and thereby losing the capital of the Burgenland and the adjoining districts, and thatI  the modifications of the frontier now proposed would seriously compromise her economic future.1  Austria asked for an application of the treaties as they stood.       The representative of Hungary said that the decisions of the Delimitation Commission hadI  been accepted unanimously by  the Commission, with the exception of the Austrian member.  HeI  stated that the decisions taken  by the Commission affected only a small number of villages in the1  Burgenland,  where the population was mixed, and  that the transfer Of the districts in questionjfcxwould not be economically detrimental to Austria.       It was agreed that the Secretariat, under the direction of M. Hymans, the rapporteur, should  study the question with the assistance of the technical representatives of the two countries concern-I  ed, and the rapporteur undertook to  present a report  on  the basis of  which  the subject would  again be considered  at the next session of the  Council.
III.  THE FRONTIER BETWEEN HUNGARY AND THE  SERB-CROAT-SLOVENE  STATE.    The Council decided, on July 19th, to have a similar preliminary study and report made inregard to modifications which had been proposed by the Delimitation Commission for the frontier between Hungary and the Serb-Croat-Slovene State.  The Council had received the report of the delimitation Commission from  the-Conference of Ambassadors and a request from the hungarian government.  It was asked to  use its good offices in the matter, and  the limits within which itsgood offices might be employed were defined  in a letter addressed to the Hungarian Governmenton May 6th, 1920.  In this letter the President of the Conference of Ambassadors stated that the delimitation Commission was competent to propose modifications in the frontier, it being understoodthat the Council of the League might,  at the request of one of the interested Governments,  offerits good offices with a view to arriving  at a settlement by friendly agreement between the parties.This arrangement had been  accepted by the Roumanian, Serb-Croat-Slovene,  and CzechoslovakGovernments in a  reply which they had subsequently addressed to the letter of the Presidentof the Conference of Ambassadors.  It was contemplated in the Presidents letter that the council would  mediate only in regard to those portions of the frontier in which modifications had  been proposed by the Delimitation Commission, such alterations to the treaty line being possible  only with the consent of the two Powers concerned.    The representatives, of Hungary and of the Serb-Croat-Slovene  State made statements tothe Council on  July 19th  and July 20th, 1922.    The Council decided to request M. Hymans, in consultation with the interested parties andwith the assistance of  the Secretariat of the League, to present to the Council  at its next sessiona statement on the controversial points involved and the possibilities of agreement between theparties. The Council would then decide at its next session whether it could usefully offer to mediate.... As stated in the main report on the work of the Council which explained at some length theestablishment of the Advisory Council of the Saar (pages 35/38), the elections for this Counciltook place on June 25th, 1922. Full reports with regard to these elections and the first sessionof the Council which was held from July 19th to 261th, 1922, have been sent in by the GoverningCommission,  The information which is given below with regard to these matters is taken fromthese reports which have also  been circulated in full to the Members of the League.    Nine  political parties or economic groups sent in lists of  candidates who carried on a very active campaign during the weeks immediately preceding the elections.  The Governing Commis-sion forwarded  with its  report a collection of manifestes of these parties or groups and pointedout that in a certain number of them, a. desire might be noted to make the Advisory Council not an organ of collaboration on the part of the population with the Governing Commission, but anorgan of systematic opposition intended to render the task  of the Commission  more  difficult,and to compel it to relinquish in favour of the Advisory council the powers and functions heldby  the Commission  under the terms  of the Treaty of. Peace, which the Council of the League ofNations stated  on  March 26th that  it would not allow the Commission  to abandon.    Of the 356,141  electors entered on the rolls,  over 193,000 cast valid ballots.  In accordancewith the results, the 30 seats in the Council were distributed among six groups as follows:STHE  TERRITORY OF  THE  SAAR  BASIN.THE ADVISORY COUNCIL OF THE SAAR.Centre Party .  .   .  .  .  ;  .  .  .  .Social  Democratic Party   .......Liberal People&apos;s Party........Union  of Landowners and Agriculture .Communist  Party........  .  .German Democratic Party .  .  .  .  .  &apos;.16 seats 5   * 4   &quot;2   M2   M-1   K
                                    - IT -One woman was elected to the Council, whose Members as regards occupation are.dividedas follows:                Secretaries of Trade Unions.........    6                Lawyers..................    4                Artisans..................    3-x               Farmers..................    3                Manufacturers...............    2                Journalists................    2                Office employees..............    2                Workmen.................    2                Clergyman.................    1                State school-teacher.............    1                Business man...............    1                Commercial agent   .......:......    1                Architect  ....  .  ________ ...._____  .  .  .... ...    1                Without profession.............    1    The Advisory Council was convened for its first meeting  on July  19th,  1922.   At  theopening  of the  meeting, the  Chairman  of  the  Council, Mr. Kossmann, read a message fromthe Governing  Commission which had  been prepared with the unanimous approval  of  theCommission.  This message, after reminding the Advisory Council of the basis on which it was established and the necessary limitation of its powers, expressed the confidence which the Corn-mission felt in the Advisory Council and the liberal programme for collaboration which the Corn-mission would adopt in its relations with that body.. The representatives of the six political partiesthen read their political programmes.  These will be found printed in full in document No. C. 543M. 328, 1922, I.    At its second meeting on  July 26th, the Advisory Council considered a  report from one ofits Committees concerning the draft rules of procedure for the Council, which had been submittedto that body by the Governing Commission.  The Advisory Council expressed their views uponthe matter and the Governing Commission will promulgate the rules after considering these views.The Commission  has already accepted the proposal of the Advisory Council that its members should receive a monthly salary of 10,000 marks with 500 marks extra for each meeting of a Com-mittee and a fine of 500 marks for each absence  from a full meeting of the Council.                OTHER SAAR QUESTIONS SUBMITTED TO  THE COUNCIL.(1)   The Adhesion of the Saar Territory to the Berne International Railway  Convention.    This question which was the subject of a dispute between the Governing Commission and theGerman Government was again considered in correspondence forwarded to the Secretary-Generalduring the summer by the Chairman of the Governing Commission.  The Governing commission has now laid the matter before the League of Nations in virtue of paragraph 22 of the Saar annex to the Treaty of VersaiUes and of Article 376 of the Ports, Waterways and Railways, part of thesame Treaty, in order that the procedure with regard to conciliation and the settlement of disputeslaid down by the resolution of the Assembly dated December 9th, 1920, may be put into effect.The Secretary-General has sent a copy of all this correspondence to the Advisory and technical committee on Communications and  Transit. (2)  Settlement of Pre-war Debts.     Negotiations on this question were carried on in Berlin at the end of July between repre- sentatives of the Governing Commission and the German Government, but it was found,impos- sible at that  time  to  come to an agreement with regard to a method of applying the German legislation on this subject to German nationals in the Saar. (3)  The intention of the Governing Commission to put certain Officials at the disposal of the German              Government.     The German Government, in a letter dated July 23rd, 1922, forwarded copies of correspondence between the Governing Commission and the German Government with regard  to the intention of the Governing Commission, on grounds of economy, to place a considerable number of officials at the disposal of the German Government.  The German Government claims that the Governing Commission has no right to  do this and has requested the intervention of the League  of Nations in order that an understanding may be reached between  the  Governing Commission  and the German Government.     The Governing Commission has also set forth its position on the question,  and both parties have in fact expressed their willingness to carry on direct negotiations in  order, if possible, to-arrive at  a settlement.                THE ECONOMIC SITUATION AND THE BUDGET OF THE TERRITORY.    The 12th periodical report of the Governing Commission contained a survey of the economicsituation in the  territory and the administrative work of the Governing Commission during thesecond  quarter of 1922.
    It was stated that the economic situation had undergone notable improvement during thatperiod, as indicated by the fact that the number of unemployed had been reduced from 3,000during the first quarter of 1922 to less than 2,000 during the second quarter.  The nett productionof coal reached 865,000 tons in June, cast-iron and  wrought-iron were sold in Germany on favour-able terms, the building industry has been active and certain new industries have been established in the Basin.                                                                             II    The budget estimates  for 1922-1923 show that both ordinary  and extraordinary expenditureW-should be fully covered by normal receipts and that the estimated deficit for the railway, postaltelegraph and telephone services, which amounted to 16,000,000  francs for 1921-1922, has beenreduced to 5,500,000 francs for 1922-1923. The revenue from the coal tax for 1922-1923 has been estimated at 40,000,000 francs and that from, the customs at 10,000,000 francs. The total expensesfor  the year are expected to amount to about 68,000,000  francs and 328,000,000 marks.                                      IKDUTIES INCUMBENT ON THE  LEAGUE OF NATIONS BY VIRTUE         OF ARTICLE 22 OF  THE COVENANT  (MANDATES).                             DECISIONS OF THE COUNCIL.    Following the decision taken during its session held in May 1922 (General Report, page 51),the Council undertook the examination of the draft B and A mandates at an extraordinary sessionheld in London in July 1922. The Council at the first meeting of the session held on July 17th,noted with regret the resignation of the Spanish member of the Permanent Mandates Commission,M. Raymond Pina, and expressed its gratitude for the services which he had rendered.  The Councilappointed to succeed  him his compatriot, the Count de Ballobar.    The  following draft B mandates were before  the Council:           :  (1) The  British mandate for East Africa.             (2) The  British mandate for Togo.             (3): The  British mandate for the Cameroons.   v  .       (4) The  French mandate for Togo.             (5) The  French mandate for the Cameroons.             (6)&apos; The  Belgian mandate for East Africa.    These drafts were not distinguished in any important particulars from those on which, inFebruary 1921, the Japanese representative  on the Council, acting as rapporteur, for the B man-dates, had presented a long report.  The Council therefore confined itself  to noting on this occasion the new  observations of  the rapporteur contained in two supplementary reports.    In these reports; the Japanese representative proposed  certain amendments in the draftB mandates.  The object of these amendments was  to clear up certain obscurities, to correctinconsistencies between the British and French texts which appeared to be contrary to the inten-tions of those who had drafted them, and finally to bring the provisions  of those drafts into agree-ment with the corresponding provisions of the C mandates approved by  the Council in December1920.    The Council  was informed that negotiations  between the Principal Allied Powers  and theUnited  States had  resulted  in an agreement concerning certain amendments  which had  been incorporated into the drafts.&apos;    The  Council, at its meeting on July  18th, approved the texts  of the mandates in principle,subject to formal amendments, the insertion of which was  entrusted to.a drafting committee under the direction of the Japanese representative.    The Council; at the same meeting on July 18th, adopted a resolution on the dangers of alcoholismin the territories under the mandates. The Council, in this resolution, drew the  special attentionof the mandatory Powers to the devastating effects of alcoholism upon the primitive populations ofEquatorial Africa.  It begged the Permanent Mandates Commission to study with close attention^the measures taken  in order  to ensure a strict control of the trade in alcohol, and communicate to the Council any  observations  of fact to which  the application of these  measures might giverise.    The  final text of the B mandates, with the amendments proposed by the Drafting Committee,were recognised as in conformity with the spirit and letter of Article 22 of the Covenant, and were
 confirmed by the Council on July 20th in accordance with the conclusions of the report presented by the Japanese representative.   .  Of the draft A mandates, only those for Palestine and for Syria and Lebanon were submitted for examination by  the Council.     In the  discussions which  took place at the meetings of the Council, emphasis was laid on the  desirability of simultaneously  approving these two draft mandates.)    As the  negotiations which were then proceeding between the Governments of France and Italy in regard to Syria and the Lebanon had not yet been  brought to a conclusion satisfactory to both parties, it was decided, on July 24th, .1922, to  define the terms of the mandates under reserve of the following declaration:             In view  of the declarations  which have just been made,  and  of  the agreement         reached by all the Members of the Council, the articles of the  mandates for Palestine         and Syria are approved.  The mandates will enter  into  force, automatically and at the         same time,  as soon as the Governments of France and Italy have notified the President         of the Council of the League of Nations that they have reached an agreement on certain         particular points in regard to the latter of these  mandates.     A drafting committee appointed by the Council was instructed to introduce certain amend- ments into  the  draft mandates especially in order to bring the texts  into agreement  with the corresponding provisions of the B mandates, which had already  been approved by the  Council.     Particular attention was given by the Council to the question of the Holy Places.  In Article 14 of the draft mandate for Palestine, a special Commission was contemplated for the study of this question.  Different  views were put forward during the discussions as to the method of appoint- ment, composition, and the duties of this Commission, and  the Council reserved its decision on these matters for  its next session.     The Council, for this reason, decided  that Article 14 of the  mandate for Palestine should be as follows:             A special Commission shall  be appointed by the mandatory to  study, define and         determine the rights and claims in connection with the  Holy Places and the rights and         claims relating to the different religious communities in Palestine.  The method of nominate-         ation, the composition and the functions of this Commission shall be submitted to the         Council of the League for its approval, and the Commission shall not be appointed or         enter upon  its functions without the  approval of  the Council.     The President of  the Council, when this article was approved,  declared on behalf of the  Spanish Government  that  the  latter would consider indispensable the presence of a Spanish member among the  members  of the  Commission  for the Holy  Places.  The  representatives of France, Italy and Belgium made the same declarations on behalf of their respective Governments.                           PERMANENT MANDATES COMMISSION.    The  Permanent Mandates Commission held its second, session according to Article 1 of itsrules of procedure, at the seat of the League of Nations  from August 1st to nth, 1922.  TheCommission held  seventeen meetings, of which two were in public.    The Commission, at its first meeting, re-elected  the Marquis Theodoli as Chairman andM. vanRees as Vice-Chairman.    The  Commission,  during its  session, examined the following questions:      NATIONAL STATUS OF THE INHABITANTS OF TERRITORIES UNDER B AND C MANDATES.    On this question, concerning which the Commission had been consulted by the  Council ofthe League of Nations, the Commission presented  a  report with the following conclusions:            1. It is important, in order that the principles laid down in Article 22 of the Covenant        may be respected and subject  to the provisions in Resolution 3 below, that  the native        inhabitants of B and C mandated territories should be granted a national status wholly        distinct from  that of the  nationals of the  mandatory Power.            2.  A  special  law of the  mandatory Power should  determine the status of these        native inhabitants, who might be given a  designation such as &quot;administered persons        under mandate&quot; or &quot;protected persons under mandate&quot;  of the mandatory Power.            3.  It  is open to mandatory Powers to which B and C  mandated territories  have        been  entrusted to make arrangements in conformity with their own laws  for the indi-        vidual and purely  voluntary  acquisition of  their  nationality by inhabitants of these        territories.      EXAMINATION OF THE ANNUAL  REPORTS  ON  TERRITORIES  UNDER A C  MANDATE.    The terms of the C mandates  were fixed  by the Council on  December 17th,  1920.    TheCommission, was therefore  called upon during its session to  study for the first time the annual reports relating to the administration of the territories under this regime.  The territories  were as follows:
             South-West Africa.             Samoa,             New Guinea,             Nauru,             The Pacific Islands under Japanese  mandate.     The Commission studied the reports relating, to these territories.  It discused them separately in the presence of the accredited representatives of the Powers which had presented them, exceptin the case of the report concerning South-West Africa.  The mandatory Power for South-WestAfrica, namely, the Union  of South Africa, did not send a representative to attend the sessionof the Commission.     The  Commission,  after having  discussions  in  the presence  of  the  representatives ofthe  mandatory Powers,  held  a  public  plenary meeting.   The Chairman,  at  this  meeting,presented a general report  on the administration of the territories  under the C mandates  andon certain questions connected with them.  The Commission noted in this report that the manda-tory Powers had, in general, administered the territories entrusted to  them in conformity with the guarantees contained in the Covenant and in the mandates at the cost of financial sacrifices whichwere often considerable.     The Commission drew the particular attention of the Council to the following points:     The first arose -from the presence in all the Pacific Islands administered under a mandateof workers imported from various countries from oversea, and especially from China. The intro-duction of these foreign workers, which was necessary for economic reasons, presented difficultiesof a social character.  The  Commission confined it. elf for the moment to drawing the attentionof the Council tc the position and to expressing a wish that the mandatory Powers should intheir future reports give all necessary information on the subject.     The second question which  had particularly engaged the attention of the Commission wasone which arose from the administration of the Island of Nauru. The discussions of the Commissionrecalled the fact that His Britannic Majesty, who was the mandatory, according to the  decisionof the Supreme Council on  May 7th, 1919, had delegated the duty of administering the island in his behalf to Great Britain, Australia  and New Zealand, and that these Governments hadreserved to  themselves the exclusive rights previously vested in a  private monopoly in regardto the exploitation of  the phosphate deposits which were the sole natural source of wealth of the island.     As a result of an  agreement between the three Governments, Australia was for the momentsolely responsible for the government of this territory.  The rights of exploitation of the mineral resources of the island were, on the other hand, exercised by three phosphate commissioners,whose powers appeared to  be unlimited  so far as concerned  the enterprise of which they  weremanagers. The Commission felt it its duty to draw attention  to. the pre-occupations which arose from this situation.      EXAMINATION OF  THE REPORTS RELATING TO TERRITORIES  UNDER B MANDATES.    In accordance with the declarations  made by the English, French and Belgian delegates onSeptember 20th,  1921, to the Sixth Committee of the Assembly, the British, French and belgian governments presented to the Permanent Mandates Commission the reports  which had  beenprepared for their respective Parliaments on their administration  during 1921 of the variousterritories under the B and A. mandates. Reports were received relating to the following territories:             Tanganyika (British),             Ruanda-Urundi (Belgium),             The Cameroons (French),             The Cameroons (British),             Togo (French),             Togo (British),             Syria and Lebanon (French).    These reports were examined  in the  light of the questionnaires prepared by the permanent mandates Commission  at its first  session.  The Commission paid  special attention  to severalquestions, such as land tenure, preventive measures against tropical diseases, the economic and customs regime, the partition of Ruanda, the trade in alcohol, and the taking into considerationof the conventions  or  recommendations  of the international labour conferences.                      .  PREPARATION OF THE QUESTIONNAIRES.    The Commission noted that the Powers had  followed the indications given in the  question-naires which had been drafted for their guidance in presenting the annual reports which it was their duty to present to the Council.  The Commission thought.it desirable to draft questionnairesfor the  two A mandates, the British mandate for Palestine and the French mandate  for Syriaand Lebanon, which the Council had approved at  its last session.
ADMINISTRATIVE QUESTIONS.       The Commission finally examined several administrative  questions.   It  decided  to make   certain additions to the B and C questionnaires.  It insisted strongly on the importance of receiving!(&apos; ;.n good time a sufficient number of copies of the annual reports of the mandatory  Powers andis   complementary texts of their legislative and administrative measures.  It  fixed the date of itsj   next ordinary session  for July  20th,  1923,  and settled the procedure whereby it  would  deal.-I   internally  with  petitions.                              IOTHE  WORK OF THE TECHNICAL ORGANISATIONS.                    I.  PROVISIONAL ECONOMIC AND FINANCIAL COMMITTEE.       The activities of the Provisional Economic and Financial Committee were noted in the general   report (pages 52 to 55) from the end of the Second Assembly up to, and including, the sessionsI  of the Economic Committee and the Financial Committee held in Geneva at the beginning ofI  June.       Pending the forthcoming sessions of the two Committees to be held in  September, thereII  remains nothing further to report beyond the decisions taken by the Council in July.mif  Economic Committee.I       The Council approved the measures taken by the Economic Committee for the  examination1  of the questions submitted to it, and invited it to continue its work, particularly as regards theJ  application of the resolutions of the Economic Commission of the Genoa Conference.1I  Financial Committee.       The Council adopted a series of resolutions in approval of the decisions taken by the FinancialI  Committee during its June session.   It invited  the  Committee to consider  the methods bestI  suited to foster monetary stability and to make it possible to avoid the consequences  caused;I  by too abrupt  changes in the  values of  currencies.   It  invited  the  Secretariat to  collectjB  information concerning the evasion  of taxes, and to ascertain the views of  the Governmentsj  concerning the extension of any international conventions on the subject at present in existence.I  It approved the transfer to Geneva of the International Credits Department and the administrationI  of this department  by the Secretariat.  It thanked the Committee for its unceasing efforts onI  behalf of Austria;  and, noting that the Committee had been remarkably successful in its  efforts to&apos;M  obtain the suspension of liens upon Austria, pointed out that the matters in which the CommitteeI  had been unsuccessful were those in which no other body had achieved results.   It approved the1  measures taken by the Financial Committee  in dealing with a number of particular questions,I  such as the recent investigation into the finances of the  Free City of Danzig, and the steps takeni  by the  Financial  Committee to  assist Albania, to which country it had sent an expert  to report   upon, the general financial situation.       In connection with the loan to the  Czechoslovak Government by Messrs. Baring Brothers,1  the Council accepted the recommendation of the  Financial Committee, and undertook to acceptt  the  invitation to  nominate  persons who  should  be empowered to make  arrangements in theI  interests of the bondholders in the event of the  Czechoslovak  Government and Messrs. Baringgj  Brothers not being able to  arrive at an arrangement satisfactory to both parties.  The CouncilU  also agreed to nominate arbitrators in the event of certain disputes arising under the agreementM  for this loan.                    II.   COMMUNICATIONS  AND TRANSIT ORGANISATION.    Since the publication of the general report to the Third Assembly on the work of the Council,there been the following developments as regards the ratifications of the Barcelona Conventions:    Albania, Bulgaria, The United Kingdom, India, New Zealand and Italy have ratified the
Convention  on  Freedom of Transit  and the Convention  on the Regime of Navigable Water-ways  of International Concern.    The  entry into  force of the Conventions,  which takes place as soon as five States  havedeposited their ratifications, will occur on October 31st, 1922.    The Health Committee held its fourth session at Geneva from August 14th to August 21st,1922.   It  adopted a  number  of resolutions, which  will be  presented to  the  Council  for examination.Epidemic-logical  Intelligence  and  the Interchange of Public  Health Officials  between  Various    References have  already been made to the  organisation within the Health Section of theLeague of a service of epidemiological intelligence, and  to a plan for an interchange of publichealth officials between the health  services  of various Governments (General Report, page 60).    The  Medical Director was  able to inform the Health Committee during its August sessionthat the  International Health Board of the  Rockefeller Foundation, which had previously shown itself  interested  in the work  of the Health  Organisation of the League, had offered an annualgrant for three years  of 32,840 dollars for the organisation of a service of epidemiological intel-Intelligence, and 60,080 dollars for the interchange of public health officials.  The Committee was asked by the Council of the  League to  consider  in detail the  appointment  and administrationof the funds thus placed at its disposal.    Contracts relating to each  of the above services, drafted by the Secretariat, were submitted for  the approval of the Health Committee.    The  Committee carefully considered the nature and  scope  of the work to be undertaken bythe new  service  of epidemiological intelligence, and drafted a  scheme which will be  inserted inthe contract to be submitted  for approval to the Rockefeller Foundation.  The Committee simul-taneously considered  plans for an interchange of sanitary officials between various countries.    Both the draft contracts will be submitted to the  Council in September.    It is provided in  the draft  contracts that the Rockefeller funds shall be kept apart from the funds provided by the Members of the League and shall be devoted to distinct and specific services.The Committee, in defining these services, kept in view  the necessity of distinguishing betweenwork which would naturally be financed by the Members of the League as falling clearly withinthe obligations of the Covenant,  and work  which might be appropriately assisted by  a private.international organisation.    Arrangements have already been made to carry out a preliminary experiment for an inter-change among certain countries of sanitary  officials.   The experiment will be opened at Brusselsin October of the present year,  arid will include a course  of instruction to be given by M. Velghe,the director of the Belgian Health Services.  It is an essential part of the scheme that a study of the health legislation and health administration of  a particular country should be followed bya period  of practical  instruction  in the health services of the  country itself.Epidemic Commission.    The Health Committee, during its August session, as a recult of a careful examination of thelatest information available, considered that there was no reason to modify the estimate whichit presented to the Council in May of the gravity of the situation in Eastern Europe in regard tothe spread of typhus,  relapsing fever, cholera, and  other  epidemic diseases.    Dr. Norman White, the Chief Epidemic Commissioner, reported that the danger of massinfection from the continual movement of repatriated persons and refugees was likely to continue and that a serious situation would thereby be created for Latvia and Lithuania, as well as forPoland, unless great vigilance were exercised.    The Health Committee decided that, if a lack of funds made if necessary during the coming  jwinter to concentrate international effort upon a particular zone of operations, the zone withinwhich this effort was to be made should, in addition to the territory bordering the western frontier  jof Soviet Russia and the Ukraine, include Russian and Ukrainian territory as far eastward as  jVelikeluki, Smolensk and the River Dnieper.    The Committee, in taking this decision, noted  that the British Government was  preparedto contribute funds for carrying out  the limited programme which  alone appeared to be possible  jin the circumstances, provided other  Members  of the League also contributed.   This programme gshould include preventive work on either side of the western frontier,of Russia and in the Black %Sea ports.                                                                                   j    The Chief Epidemic Commissioner, in his  report to the Committee in August, described the  Ihelp which had been given to the border States by the Commission.  He indicated the  improve-  appointments  which had been made in the hospitals  for infectious diseases, in  the internment camps,  and in the camps established for repatriated persons and refugees.III.  THE HEALTH ORGANISATION.Government.
Revision of the International Sanitary Convention of 1912.    The Health  Committee, during its  May session, drew the attention of the Council to the greatimportance of the earliest possible revision of the International Sanitary Convention of 1912. TheCouncil duly noted this resolution  on July 20th, and  decided to draw the  attention of theMembers  of the League to the  very  great importance  of the Conference to be  convened  bythe French Government in October, at which this question  will be considered.    The &quot; Office international d&apos;Hygiene publique&quot; has already revised a draft text for Part I of theConvention.  Action taken in connection with the revision of Parts II and III of the Convention,which deal specifically with Near Eastern questions, was noted in the first general  report of theCouncil to the Third Assembly (page  61).    The Council, on July 20th, decided to forward for consideration to the &quot; Office internationald&apos;Hygiene publique&quot;  the preliminary work  of  the Health  Committee on Parts  II and III  ofthe Convention,  and authorised the Secretary General to place the technical services of the Leagueof Nations at the disposal of the French Government and of the Conference.The Study of Tropical Diseases.    The Health Committee, during its August session, appointed a sub-committee, to which two questions were referred:            &apos; (1) What reply should be given to the Mandates Commission, which had requested         the co-operation of the Health Committee in drafting the health section of the question-         naire to be addressed to the mandatory Governments which are administering territories         in Equatorial Africa ?             (2) What steps were necessary to give effect to the decisions taken by the Committee         in May in regard to sleeping sickness (General Report, page 63) ?    The sub-committee, in drafting  the health section of the questionnaire  of the mandates commission,  laid particular emphasis on the desirability of  obtaining information in regard tothe practical health administration of the mandated territories.    It decided, in regard to the study of sleeping sickness, that a British, a French and a Belgianexpert should be appointed to collect material.  Epidemics in the Far East.       On August 9th, Dr. Miyajima, the Japanese member of the Health Committee, presented&quot;a  report on the epidemiological situation in the Far East, and asked that a mission of inquiry should  be despatched similar to the inquiry which had recently visited the Near East.   He emphasised  the importance of stimulating public  interest in oriental countries in questions of hygiene, and  represented that the researches of a mission of inquiry would facilitate the conclusion of a sanitary(  ^convention between the Far Eastern countries, the urgency of  which had long  been recognised.  The League,  moreover, would be giving a concrete proof that its work was not limited to European  affairs, as, unfortunately, the peoples of the East seemed more and more inclined to suspect.       It was finally decided to recommend in principle the despatch of a small Commission and that  a sub-committee of three members should  define the details of the inquiry to be undertaken, and  consider how the preliminary negotiations should be conducted  with the interested Governments     The Health Committee noted that the administrative expenses of the Epidemic Commission represented a charge of only 5.7 per cent, of the total sums expended, and recorded its appreciation of the fact that the funds contributed by the League represented only a small fraction of the money which had been expended on preventive measures by the border States themselves.  The Com- mittee considered that the Epidemic Commission had been able to achieve results in the campaign against epidemics out of  all proportion to its expenditure.  It had furnished expert advice and^)o-ordinated the action required in the different countries.  It had supported and strengthened the health services of the various countries, including that of Soviet Russia, and had been able to  point at critical times to the weak places in the local organisations, and to strengthen them by the judicious distribution of essential medical material, which could not otherwise have been obtained.     The Health Committee  decided to call the attention of the Council to the need for at once renewing the special fund of the Epidemic Commission.  It pointed out that the field for success- ful international effort in combating disease  was limited only  by the question of the  money and material which could be secured, and that so far  the invaluable work of the Commission had cost only  200,000- a sum which now was practically exhausted.     The Committee noted in this connection that certain duties of the Commission, for example the sending of missions  to infected areas to obtain information as to the prevalence of epidemic diseases,  as well as the work of co-ordinating preventive measures, fell within the normal duties of the Health Organisation, as defined by the Covenant,  and that in their opinion the expenditure in such duties should be  defrayed from the funds of the League.
and authorities.   The sub-committee would also make recommendations to the Chairman of the health Committee concerning the appointment of the Commissioners.  It was decided, as a matterof principle, that the  Commission should concentrate upon collecting information regarding the incidence of epidemic diseases, especially those of international importance, in important ports,and regarding the measures taken to prevent the transmission of these diseases to other ports.The Opium Sub-Committee of the Health Committee.    The Health  Committee approved a suggestion received from the Advisory Committee on the traffic in Opium that a mixed  committee on opium should be appointed, consisting of three members of the Opium Advisory Committee and three members of the Health Committee.  It wasnoted that the Advisory  Opium Committee had  occasionally to deal with medical questions arising out of the traffic in opium and other dangerous drugs, and it was recognised that the appoint-ment  of a mixed committee would enable the two Committees to avoid any confusion or over-lapping in their work.    The three members appointed by the Health Committee were Dr. Miyajima, Dr. Santoliquido,and Dr. Carriere.Procedure and Organisation of the Health Committee.  .    The Health Committee, during its August session, adopted rules for its procedure and internalorganisation. The Committee, in these rules, carefully defines  the relations of the Medical Directorwith the Committee and with the Council  of the League, and describes the powers and responsi-bilities of the Medical Director and of the Chairman of the Committee between its sessions.  they include a provision for the appointment of sub-committees  by the Chairman for any questionsrequiring either decisions of principle or. general instructions which cannot be settled by the MedicalDirector according to directions already received.    The Committee acted upon a resolution adopted by the Council in July, inviting it to appoint a member of German nationality.The Standardisation of Sera and Serological Tests.    The Chairman reported to the Committee on the progress made with the standardisation ofsera and serological tests (General Report, page 62).    The Chairman was authorised to convene any small technical conference that  he might judgeto be necessary and to obtain the collaboration of institutes and specialists other than those so farengaged in the work.   He announced that a considerable advance had been achieved in respect ofthe anti-tetanus and  anti-diphteria sera, and that there would be a conference of experts in Sep-tember  to compare results.    The investigations in regard to the other sera were not so far advanced.  There had been some interesting experiments in the sero-diagnosis of syphilis, but the laboratories engaged inthese researches had  announced remarkably different results.   It would be necessary to conductfurther investigations and to discover the causes of the differences which had been noted.1 1THE   GENOA  CONFERENCE  AND  THE   LEAGUE   OF  NATIONS.    The Italian representative, on July 22nd, 1922, presented a report to the Council of the Leagueon the Genoa Conference and.the League of Nations (General Report, page 63).  He noted with satisfaction that the Genoa Conference&apos; had given a fresh proof of the confidence of the Govern -ments in the League of Nations, and, on behalf of his colleagues, thanked the Secretariat for theassistance it had rendered at the Conference.    It was noted that the resolution of the Genoa Conference imposed a considerable amount ofadditional work on the various organisations of the League and on the Secretariat.    .
- ig -50           12SOCIAL OUESTIONS.                   I. TRAFFIC IN OPIUM AND&apos;  OTHER DANGEROUS DRUGS.    The Council, on July 2ist, decided that it would again refer back to the Advisory Committeeon Opium for its further consideration those passages of its report upon the revision of which theCommittee had been unable to agree, and which the Council at its last session had invited it to reconsider (General Report, page 72).  The Council asked the Committee to deal with the question before the report came up for discussion at the Assembly.  The Committee will meet on September1st, 1922.    The passage in question refers to the cultivation of the poppy in China.                          II. TRAFFIC  IN WOMEN AND CHILDREN.    The Council, on July 17th, considered and approved the report on the work of the AdvisoryCommittee on Traffic in Women and Children accomplished during the session held at Geneva from june 28th to July 1st, 1922 (General Report, page 73).  III.  DEPORTATION OF WOMEN AND CHILDREN IN TURKEY AND THE NEIGHBOURING COUNTRIES.    The Secretary-General informed the Council on July 17th that the Commission of Enquiry atConstantinople had definitely accepted the duty of reclaiming deported persons (General Report,page 75)-                                             .    The Commission of Enquiry has thus,  in accordance with the resolution passed by the Councilon May 12th, undertaken the duties of the Chief Commissioner pending his appointment, and the funds allocated to the use of the Chief Commissioner have been made available for the work.                    13RELIEF   OF  RUSSIAN  REFUGEES.     The Council, on July 20th, heard a further report from Dr. Nansen on the relief of Russian refugees. The Russian Refugees in Constantinople &apos;.     Dr. Nansen informed the Council that only a part of the   30,000 required for the evacuation of the refugees in Constantinople had been promised by Members of the League in response to the appeal addressed to them by the Council during its previous session (General Report, page 78). Belgium,  Brazil, China, -Czechoslovakia, Great Britain,  Japan and Switzerland had promised between them approximately   17,000.*  He reminded the Council that the American Relief Admi- administration  had promised to feed the refugees for four months  pending  their evacuation, and to^contribute 25,000 dollars towards evacuation expenses, provided the    30,000 could be secured. He was glad to say that the American Red Cross had offered to guarantee the balance of the   . 1  Line 47, page 78, of the English text of the Report to the Third Assembly shouldmissioner informed the Council that the offer of the A. R. A.  etc.&quot;-ead &quot;The High Com-
  30,000 required, but he hoped that the Members of the League would be able to contribute thewhole sum, and that the American Red Gross contribution might be held in reserve as a margin of safety.    Since the establishment of the High Commissariat, no fewer than 9,000 refugees have been evacuated from Constantinople, whilst 1,000 have secured permanent employment in the vicinity.About one-third of the work of evacuation has thus been accomplished,  18,000 refugees still re-maining.    The High Commissioner has appointed a special committee in Constantinople  to deal withthe administration of the   30,000, consisting of his delegates, Colonel Procter and M. Burnier,Mr. Ringland, of the American Relief Administration, and Major Davis, of the American Red Cross,Admiral Bristol, the U. S. High Commissioner in Constantinople, has also consented to serve onthis Committee.    Arrangements are being made with the Bulgarian Government and  the Russian Red Crossin Bulgaria for, the transfer of about  1,000 invalids with their families, some 2,500 refugees in all,from Constantinople to Bulgaria.  This category of refugees constitutes one of the most difficult problems with which the High Commissariat has to deal.    Negotiations are also in progress for the evacuation of about 1,000 Siberians to Vladivostockand upwards of 600 Jewish Russian refugees to Palestine.Egypt, Cyprus and the Serb-Croat-Slovene State.    Dr. Nansen was able to report that the refugees camps in Egypt and  Cyprus had been closed,and that the work of evacuation was practically finished.    The necessary arrangements had been carried out by agreement with the British  Government,from whom the High Commissioner had taken over about 4,600 refugees in Egypt, Cyprus and theSerb-Croat-Slovene State, in return for the sum of   150,000.    The refugees from the camps in  Egypt and Cyprus were mostly  evacuated to Bulgaria,, andarrangements had been made  to deal  with the major portion of them.   Negotiations were in  pro-gress with the Government of the Serb-Croat-Slovene State, as a result of which it was expectedthat the Government would assume the responsibility for the remaining 1,500 Lemnos refugees inits territory.Identity Certificates and Visas  for Refugees.    The Council further considered the recommendations of the Advisory Committee of PrivateOrganisations which had met on May  29th and 30th (General Report, page 78).    In accordance With a recommendation of this Committee, Dr. Nansen had convened a corifer-ence of Government representatives to consider the question of identity papers and visas for Russianrefugees.  The Conference met in Geneva from July 3rd to July 5th under the chairmanship of dr. van Hamel, chief of the Legal Section of the Secretariat.   Sixteen  countries were represented,namely, Austria, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia,  Finland,  France,  Germany,  Great Britain,  Greece,Hungary, Japan, Poland, Roumania, the Serb-Croat-Slovene State, Spain, Sweden and Switzerland.    The Conference adopted unanimously a simplified form of identity certificate.    The Council decided, on July 20th, to recommend all the Members of the League and the Govern-ments of all countries interested in the problem of Russian refugees to adopt this form of identitycertificate, and to notify the  Secretary-General as early as possible  of  their agreement to thisarrangement.               14THE  FAMINE  IN  RUSSIA.    The Council, on May 16th, 1922, considered a proposal of the Norwegian Government that aCommission of Enquiry should be appointed to investigate the facts  of the situation in Russia(General Report, page 79).    The Council referred this proposal to the Genoa Conference,  which was then  in progress.The Genoa Conference was unable for lack of time to consider it, and referred it back to the Councilof the League.    Dr. Nansen again presented the proposal to the Council on July 20th, 1922.  He  said that, inthe opinion of the Norwegian Government, the need for a Commission of Inquiry was not less acutethan when the proposal had first been made.  He emphasised the economic importance of thequestion, and said it was the conviction of the Norwegian Government that trade in Europe couldnot be restored to its normal activity until Russia was again in a position to export her products and to open her markets.  .
      Nothing-had occurred to encourage any reasonable hope that the problems of famine and  disease would be less acute during the coming year.  Two million people had died in the famine  region of starvation alone, and at least twenty million had. suffered in their productive capacity  from the privations to which they had been submitted.   At  the most sanguine computation, the  harvest for 1922 would be 50 %, or 33 million&apos;tons, below that of 1916.  Less than half the normal  yield was expected in the Ukraine.(   )   Dr Nansen laid particular  emphasis  upon  the necessity of re-establishing  agriculture in&quot;&quot;Russia, and for this purpose insisted on the need of providing Russian peasants with animals  and seed.  The  problem of draught animals, of which from 55 % to 95 % had perished,  would  have to be faced immediately, as, without assistance, it would be very difficult to reap the harvest  or to plough for the coming year.  The seed problem would have to be faced in the early spring.  Unless assistance were afforded, famine conditions might be prolonged into 1924.      The Norwegian Government considered that, in order to awaken  public opinion as  to the  actual position  in. Russia, the  proposed  Commission of  Enquiry was  essential.   There existed  a large mass of information in  the possession  of the  Governments and  of  the  various relief  organisations. It was necessary that this information should be studied and compared, and that  an authentic and authoritative statement should be issued by  an impartial body, which might  command the confidence both  of the Governments and  of the public.      The Council, on July 20th,  decided that the Secretariat of the League should be authorised  to collect, arrange and tabulate all the information obtainable from the  various Governments  and relief organisations and other agencies  working in Russia, and to complete it whenever pos-  sible from other sources.  The object of this work was to  present to the Council as complete and  accurate a picture as possible of the actual famine situation in Russia, and to render this informa-  tion accessible to the public. It was understood that a commission of experts might be  appointed  to make  use of the material thus obtained and to examine what conclusions might  be  drawn  from it, provided the results of the work of the Secretariat, when finished, appeared to  justify  further action.                            15.COMMITTEE ON  INTELLECTUAL CO-OPERATION    In conformity with the decision taken by the Council on May 15th, 1922, the Committeeentrusted with the duty of examining international problems connected with intellectual co-ope-ration, held its first  session at  Geneva from August  1st to -5th,  1922.    All those who had been appointed by the Council to sit on this Committee were present,with the exception of Professor Einstein who was prevented at the last moment from coming to geneva, having been summoned to Japan on a scientific mission. Professor Einstein had assured the Committee that he would participate in its work upon his return. The Committee was composed as&apos; follows:                           Professor  of  Political   Economy  at Calcutta  University.                           Honorary Professor of Philosophy at the College de France, Member                               of  the&apos; French Academy,  Member of the Academy of Moral                               and  Political  Science.                           Professor of Zoology at Christiania University,  Delegate to the                               Assembly  of  the League  of  Nations.                    .                           Director of the Faculty  of Medicine at Rio de Janeiro University.                           Professor of Physics at  the Paris  University,  Hon.. Professor at                               Warsaw University, Member of the Warsaw Scientific Society.                           Formerly Minister for Sciences and Fine Arts, Member of the Belgian                               Academy  of   French  Language  and  Literature.                           Director of the Mount Wilson Observatory, Member of the Inter-                               national Council for Research, Hon. President of the National                               Council  for Research of the United  States.M. D.  N. BANERJEE,M. H.  BERGSON,Mile  BONNEVIE,M. A.  DE CASTRO,Mme CURIE-SKLODOWSKA,MA.. J. DESTREE, Prof. G. E.&apos;HALE,
Prof.  G. A. MURRAY,       Professor  of Greek Philosophy  at  Oxford  University,  Member                               of the Council  of  the British Academy,  Delegate  for  South                               Africa to  the Assembly of the  League  of Nations.M.  G. DE REYNOLD,        Professor  of French  Literature  at  Berne University.M.  F. RUFFINI,             Professor of Ecclesiastical Law at Turin University, formerly Minister,.                               for Education, President of the Union of the League of Nation. J                               Associations, President of the Royal Academy of Turin.M. L. de TORRES-QUEVEDO,  Director  of  the Madrid Electro-Mechanical  Laboratory,  Member                               of the Commission for the Extension of Scientific Study (Junta                               Para Ampliation de Estudios), Member of the Madrid Academy                               of  Science.Prof.  R. A. MILLIKAN,    &apos;  Director  of  the  Norman Bridge Laboratory of  Physics  at the                               Californian  Technological  Institute,  Vice-President   of  the                               National Research Council of the United States,  Member of the                               International Council for Research (Substitute for Dr. Hale,                               who  was prevented from being present  at all of the  meetings).M.  BERGSON,  was  elected  President;Prof.  MURRAY, Vice-President,  andM.  DE REYNOLD,  Rapporteur.    In view of the length of  its agenda and the limited time at its disposal, the Committee started by  deciding on its method  of work and  defining the limits of its activity.   It  suggested thatthe Council should at once  institute  an  enquiry into the condition of  intellectual work in thevarious countries, and drew  the Council &apos;s attention of the desparate conditionsof  intellectual life in certain European countries and  to the urgent necessity of taking action. It asked M. de Rey-nold and Mme. Curie-Sklodowska to prepare  as soon as possible a report, to serve as a model, uponthe conditions of intellectual life in Austria and in Poland  respectively.    It set up  a  sub-committee, comprising Mme. Curie-Sklodowska and  M.  Destree,  with M.Bergson in the Chair.  This sub-committee might co-opt from three to five experts from the classof intellectual workers  whose collaboration  appeared to be  required,  i.e., bibliographers andscientists  with special knowledge.   It would be the duty of this commission  to study questionsconcerned with bibliography and particularly any  means by  which an  improvement might bemade in the branch of bibliography  known  as  &quot;periodical&quot;.    It drew the Council&apos;s attention to the Brussels Conventions of March 15th, 1886, dealing withthe international exchange of publications and to the desirability of improving these conventions and providing for their more extensive  application.    It laid down the principle that intellectual co-operation in scientific research was the concern of the scientific societies themselves. The committee, however, was desirous, in practice, to affordthem all possible support, and it accordingly retained the question of co-operation among menof science on  the agenda of its next session.    It decided to study at once the question of constituting an international fund for providingloans  and credits  for  assisting  scientific  research.    It entrusted one of its  members  with  the duty of investigating means for regulating inter-nationally the preservation  and the alienation  of ^archaeological monuments by  compiling a listof archaeological treasures brought  to  light, by  drawing  up a general plan of research,  and bydetermining the procedure  and methods to  be applied  to these  researches.    The Committee considered that some effort in the direction of co-operation between the uni-universities was one of the pressing needs of modern civilisation.  Accordingly, it instructed a sub-committee comprising M. de Castro,  M.  Millikan, M. Murray, M. Destree and M. de&apos;Reynold,with M. Bergson in the  Chair, to undertake the  preparation of an international congress of suchuniversities  as it  might decide to convene as soon as circumstances permitted.   The principalpoints to be  dealt with  would be as follows:  Exchange of professors, exchange of students,standardisation of studies and  university degrees, the institution of international scholarships,international holiday courses artd a central  office for university information. The  sub-committeewill work  in co-operation with the various Universities and will encourage them to  organise among themselves either  national  congresses or congresses  of  groups of nations.    The Committee entrusted a sub-committee comprising  M. Destree,  M. Millikan,  M. Ruffiniand M. de Torres-Quevedo  with the duty of studying by what means intellectual proprietaryrights and scientific proprietary rights in particular may receive adequate protection.    The Committee considered a resolution taken by the Assembly on October 1st, 1922, and referred to it by the Temporary Mixed Commission for the Reduction of Armaments.  The Com-mittee was asked to suggest  methods by which scientists throughout the world might be induced to publish their discoveries in respect  of poison gas and chemical warfare.  The Committee decla-red its inability to suggest  any method  for giving effect to the proposal.


</content>
</cab>
