<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 81-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
t     1   /     DOCUMENT IS THE -.PRGEERTY  OF HIS.. BTtllAjfllC liiiJ[ESTY^ K^n^JaMT^J   ............................................................S E 0 B E T.                         G A B I g E T.CP. 4211.                                                     V ...                                                             ^1                    THE TURQO-gREKg SITUATION.              W&apos;                 00-OPERATTOH  Oi1 THE LOklfilOflS.            Further Telegrams  between  the  Secretary of state            for the Colonies and Governors General  of Canada,            Australia and Jsiew  Zealand  and  the  Union of South                            Africa.(Circulated by the Secretary of State for the Colonies)         (Previous Paper: C.P. 4200)                        I.Paraphrase telegram from the  Secretary  of State  for theColonies to the Governors General  of  Canada, Australia,New Zealand and the Union of  South Africa.Dated 20th September.     Following message for your  Prime  Minister.   I amorganising a special staff from  tomorrow to  iceep youcontinuously informed of military  and  political  develop-ments.   JPlease arrange to have  adequate deciphering atyour end.                       CHURCHILL.                         II.Paraphrase telegram from the  Secretary of State  for theColonies to the Governors General  of Canada,  Commonwealth ofAustralia, Hew Zealand and the Union of South Africa.              (Sent 7.10 p.m. 21st  September,  1922)21st September.     Following message is for your  Prime Minister.   -Begins:I should be glad if you would inform me by  telegraph of yourwishes as regards communication to  representatives  of your government now at Geneva of the recent and  any  subsequenttelegrams exchanged between us as to the Bear East  crisis &apos;(including messages to and from yourself and Prime  Ministerhere ) ends.                          CHURCHILL.
Paraphrase telegram from the  governor  General  of Canada tothe Secretary of  State for the Colonies.            Dated  EOth September.(Received Colonial Office 6.20 a.m.  21st  September, 1922)/                  &apos;                          (V  iSecret,  following for your Prime minister from Prime Ministerbegins.  I have just received your telegram 19th September.Government is gratified to learn that  under present circum-stancos there is no necessity of summoning Parliament.Canadian public opinion confirms the belief expressed: in our previous message that Parliament must  determine such action as Canada should take with respect to  the situation which has arisen in the Hear i*ast.  We have not  thought  it necessaryto re-assert the loyalty of Canada to  the British empire.Your may rest assured that should the  summoning of Parliamentbecome necessary Canada by decision  of its Parliament will act in such a v;ay  that the full duty of Canadian people willbe carried out.  ends.                           BYE Gn                        IV.Paraphrase telegram from the  Governor  General  of theCommonwealth of Australia to  the Secretary of  State for theColonies.            Dated  21st September, 1922.(Received Colonial Office 12.52 p.m, 21st September, 1922 )     Special arrangements for deciphering have been made.Above refers to your telegram of 21st  September,
%                                    v.. Paraphrase   The Governor General of the Commonwealth of Australia to Telegram.             the Secretary of State for the Colonies;                           Dated 22nd September.             (Received,  Colonial Office, 8,55* ,*s*s.. , SSnd September, 1928)                  following from my Prime Minister: -Begins,  As the             number of these telegrams will be very great, some being             very lengthy as may be my replies thereto and. all highly             confidential, I leave the question of keeping High             Commissioner informed to your discretion,  -Binds.  Above             refers to your telegram of 21st September.                                      ffORSIERo                         VI.Telegram:  from the Governor General of flew Zealand to theSecretary of State for the Colonies.(Received Colonial Office 8.40 a,m. 21st September 1922).     Urgent Prime Minister would be glad to know whether any assurance can be given by His iviajesty&apos;s Government regardingsafety of -English women who were in Constantinople orGallipoli when the present trouble commenced and who perhapsmay be still there.  Prime Minister has been approached by several Hew Zealand citizens who have relatives in constantinople and who are naturally anxious to know whethersafety of their kinsfolS: has been ensured early reply will be appreciated.                           JBL1IGQ&amp;.
Paraphrase telegram.,   he Governor General of Mew zealand to the secretary of State for the Colonies.               Dated: Elst September.(Received, Colonial Offioe, 10.53 a.m., 21st September, 1922)     As I held all cyphers I will arrange for adequatedecyphering facilities.     Above refers to your telegram of 20th September.                           JfiLIICOEo                      VIII.Paraphrase Telegram from the Governor General of Bets zealand to the Secretary of otate for the Colonies.             Dated 22nd September, 19 22.(Received Colonial Office 11.3 a.m. 22nd September, 1922 ).     As suggested in your telegram of the 21st Septemberpreparations are being made for the immediate despatch of one battalion and the formation of a brigade.  Pending anncunoe-ment by my Prime Minister please postpone publication.                           JELLICOk,                       IX.Paraphrase telegram.  The Governor General of Hew Zealand tothe Secretary of State for the Colonies,,                     Dated: 22nd September.(Receiyed, Colonial Office, 11.37 a0m., 22nd September. 1922)     It is necessary for my Government to icnow as soon aspossible in the event of troops being required from fiew Zealandproposed ports of disembarkation and whether horses can besupplied by His Majesty rs Government.     Please reply as soon as possible by telegraph,                           JELLICOli
 O           Telegram.  The Governor General of  lew Zealand to the secretary           of State for the Colonies.                         Dated: 22nd September.           (Received, Colonial office, 11,4? a,m.,  22nd September,  1922)                as evidence of the Imperial spirit of New Zealand I may                that           mention/although no call for volunteers has been issued over           12,000 officers and other ranks and 300 nurses had volunteered           for servioe up to night of 21st ^pteenber.  It is estimated           that about one third of that number are returned soldiers.                                 JEL1IC0E.                                   XL.47134/1922 Telegram from thb Secretary of State for the Colonies to the           Governor General of isew Zealand.                     (Sent 7.40 p.m. 21st September,  1922)           Urgent.                Your telegram 21st September please inform your Prime           Iv-inister that no British oivilian families evacuated from           Constantinople or Gallipoli. His kajesty&apos;s High Commissioner           at Constentinople and British naval and military authorities           may be  relied  on make all arrangements they consider           desirable for safety of British community though so far they           have not suggested evacuation.  Secretary of State for           Foreign Affairs is informing High Commissioner at Constant!^           nople of your Prime Minister&apos;s enquiry *
Paraphrase of telegram from the Secretary of State for theColonies to the Governor General of ^ew Zealand.       (Sent. 8.20 p0m. 21st September, 1922. )21st September,     following message for your Prime iwlnister begins.  &apos;Vithreference to your cypher telegram of the 19th iieptember.  Weare clear that to despatch immediately one battalion (one thousand men) and to form a brigade to be held in readinesswould not only be of material assistance but produce greatmoral effect in emphasizing solidarity of British imperial interests in Gallipoli peninsula and Dardanelles.   All orders should be open If situation clears to cancellation at a mount&apos;s notice.  Ends.                             CHURCHILL.                         III.Paraphrase.  Mr. Londonr (Geneva).                                    September 19th,  1922.           D.11.20 a^m. September 20th, 1922.           E. 2.0.p.m. September 20th, 1982.No.40,     following from Lord half our for Secretary of State for colonies.     Mr. fisher has seen fielding who had already telegraphedto Canada urging a strong declaration in the sense indicatedin your telegram.  He did not disguise,, however, that there maybe difficulties as Canada is very averse to fresh military commitments.Australian
      Australian High GommifcSioner said to-night that although his government had agreed they felt they were entitled bofuller explanation than had hitherto been given to them of allelements in situation.     Above refers to your unnumbered telegram of 18thSeptember.2,  Whitehall Gardens.  -j.Vul.,       23rd September,  1922.- 7 -

</content>
</cab>
