<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 226-227</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,^t^0r   DRAFT OF INVITATION TO ANGORA GOVERNMENT.CREX.     British,  and French Foreign Ministers  andItalian Ambassador in Paris have the  honour onbehalf of their governments to  invite mustapha kemal to come himself or the Grand National Assemblyof Angora to send a representative with  full powersto a meeting at Venice or elsewhere to which willalso be invited plenipotentiary representatives  ofFrance, Great Britain, Italy, Japan,  Yugoslavia,Roumania and Greece.   The meeting will  be  held as soon as the necessary arrangements can be madeby Italian government and the other governments  con-cerned.  Its object will be to  negotiate and draw up the final treaty of peace between  the alliedpowers and Turkey and thus among other things to mediate a settlement of the outstanding  points in dispute between Greece and Turkey.     The British, French and Italian  governmentsdesire at the same time to take this  opportunity ofrecording that they view with sympathy and  are readyto examine with benevolence at  the coming conference the desire of the government of Angora to secure thereturn of the greater part of Thrace  to  &quot;Turkishsovereignty.  They hope it will be found possible after taking into account at the conference all  the vital interests of the countries concerned  to  give such
such satisfaction to Turkish aspiration in thisdirection as can be reconciled with the provisionnot only of those guarantees for the permanentmaintenance of the freedom of the waters between the black Sea and the Mediterranean which the alliedpowers are united in regarding as indispensable,but also of that protection of racial and religiousminorities under the aegis of the League of nations which the government of Angora have already declared their willingness in principle to accord.  Theallied governments solemnly reaffirm the assuranceswhich they gave in March last to withdraw their troops from Constantinople upon the entering intoforce of the treaty of peace.     As a pledge of their good faith&quot;&amp;e alliedpowers are prepared, while the arrangements forthe Venice conference are being male, to use all their influence to secure the withdrawal of theCreek forces to such a line in Eastern Thrace asmay be agreed upon between the Turkish and Greekmilitary authorities and the allied commander-in-chief at Constantinople and his allied colleagues,provided always that the government of Angora firstdeclare their readiness, pending and during thepeace conference, not to enter the neutral zonesor cross the Sea of Marmora,,     For the above purpose a meeting could bearranged between the allied generals and mustapha kemal at Mudania or Isold,

</content>
</cab>
