<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 234-264</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SITUATION IN THE NEAR EAST,Stenographic Report of a Deputation to the PrimeMinister from the General Council  of the TradesUnion Congress on Thursday,  September 21st, 1922,                     at 11a 0 a ontoPRESENT!The Prime Minister;The RtoHeno Ao Chamberlain,  M.P*The RtcHonP R:So Home,  G.B.E.,K.C.,M*P.The RtaHon. Sir Le Worthington-Evans,          . Barts,G*g b e .,M0PcSir Edward Grigg, K,&apos;C.WOi-,CaM.G.Sir M. P. Ac Hankey, G.O,B.THE DEPUTATION, which numbered  thirty,  included the Rt.hon JaH, Thomas, M,P.Iviro Wili Thorna, Mi P.Mr, :0,Wi Bowerman, M0P..Mro&apos; A o Hayday, M* P*Mr* Robert Smillie.Mr. JoBo Williams  (Chairman  of  the  Council)eMr, Ben TillettcMr, John Turner*Mro Ben Turner?Mr? John Beard0Mr, Aa Connolly*Miss BsndfieldaWhitehall Gardens, S0W*, 23rd September, 1922,
           J.-m.,W.IXLlAMS:   Mr.J?rxme MijajLrter^ TayoUrty &quot;to-day is a vary light one.  I have only tb present in their irtrm -three-- speakers appointed by the general Council of the Congress to express organised Labour 1s voice on the question of war generally,--and- on the Hear Bast position -in -particular,,. Summed up,  Labour*s strong voice is, there is nothing in. the. l?ear East position to warrant this country throwing Over the League of nations which was established to proajote peace in the world and to substitute&apos; for armed force a policy of reason and arbitration-  The late war  we were told was to end war and we believe in expressing  our views to you dn regard to the -  ear East we are not  only carrying out the-express directions, of-our various Congresses  but are expressing the views of the British.people as a whole.  The three speakers will elaborate on tho brief outline-I have just made-and I call on Mr -Tillett to address you  first,          MR. B53H TtLLETT:   Mr.Pr ime Minister .- . The duty. devolving upon me though important is a simple one. &apos; ?/e are not here to dictate; we are not here to&apos;-advise; we are not&apos; here to suggest. the  manner  of your conduct&apos; of this... international difficulty of the  moment; we are,not unmindful of the difficulties imposed by this world tangle and we are not unmindful.-of the cross purposes end the varying national jealousies which operate to prevent any sort of understanding. /We are cognisant of the vested  interests and the cross purposes of the vested interests and  we  realise the gravity of the pbsition and your responsibility. We are  here to indicate the working class opinion, the Trade&quot;Union,  &quot;the  industrial opinion as being one absolutely antagonist tic  to  war.  Whether we like  it or not our own forces demand from us organised opposition to war.  The feeling of antagonism is so pointed and so definite that whatever plausible excuse  or even, what may be, reason for taking action, we feel -
assured the opposition will be of such a .ho--stiXe. ..char-acter that whatever opinions might be express-ssed - and we are not criirj^o-dsing&apos;for the moment; we shall criticise in another place *- but whatever observations might be made in support of any attempt at war - and we are not alleging there is now a feeling on thepart of our Cabinet for war; we hope they are not so ridiculous^so mad or stupid, but things may drift as other wars havedrifted; the world is in such a oompleta tangle at the momentbecause of lack of control and apparently the lack of anintelligent view towards humanity itself and the lack offorethought in :         realising that there must be somesettlement of the things at present so involved or they willbecome more tangled and more involved.  Some of us are of theopinion, not that we are on. the edge of bankruptcy but that weare already insolvent.  The condition of unemployment; theconditions arising out of the last war and the disasters which followed to our trade are of such a character as. to awaken-considerable resentment, loss ox trust and even a. lack ofoptimism in any particular form so far as the country isconcerned,  Eow you may or may not be to blame but we should notbe doing our cuty and we should be acting the part of cowards ifwe were to tell you there is any support,  We are of opinionwe should have to organise, hostility; we should have to organiseevery  form of hostility to any act of war.  We are hoping we shallhear from you something this morning that will clear the air.The press has a confused view of the position as it stands butwe&apos;are  here to say, and say quite definitely, we stand forthe Freedom of the  Straits  or the freedom of navigation in anypart of the world.,  That is the catholic  attitude we adopt towardstrade.  We have no  quarrel with the  Turks; we have no  quarrelwith the  Greeks.  We  are iaindful of  our  relations to Mahommedans                                                          in
     MR J.B. WILLIAMS:   I will ask Miss Lhndfield  to  speak.     MISS&apos; BOiOJffLEJD:  Mr. Prime Minister.  My task is to associate with the expression of opinion already given thegreat volume of voajeinT s  c\ in ion in the country.  In thismatter the men and women in the labour movement are absolutelyunited but if there is a difference  in the degree  of  oppositionto war,  I think it is probable that  the women feel the question more strongly still.  I ?,ant to say, kr. Prime Minister,  -and I have had some opportunity of meeting conferences duringthis -week-end - that the impression  which the Cabinet callto the Colonies have made has been one of horror on the partof the women to discover the perpetuation of the war  mind.They feel that p-gyehsingle ally there has been no change in theattitude of those in control ox the  fiffairs of  state, and they want to state in the clearest possible way that they  regardwar as a scourge and that in no way  at all can v* ar be regardedas a means of settling religious or  economic questions.  They                                                      and thatrealise the experience that they have passed through  &apos; ./  thisscourge of war can only  be destroyed by psychological changeof mind by those who control.  We are- unable to accept theterms that are freely bandied about by the papers to-day suchas a holy war and such as the sanctity of Gfallipoli,  We say a nev, war would be the beating of the dead., because they diedto prevent any more war.    The idea that in the twentiethcentury - and I mention  this not because the Cabinet  is responsible but because  the organs of the pre;bs&apos; are usingcatch phrases without realising the  amount of emotion thatit stirs up - the idea that in the twentieth century  it ispossible to talk about a holy war strikes on the minds of  most                                   blasxhemywomen of to-day as nothing short of          .  There can  beno holy isar and    any who profess to believe the  6hr stianphilosophy to say that the Cross should conquer the Crescentby force sounds to us simply  the ore converting to  the paganism
 of the early church.  Surely we have  learnt  that lesson in all these centuries  of  suffering and wrong.   Surely it is time and  surely the  people  of England  have the  right to expect that  in this  new attitudg of mind  in  regard to the settlement  of war questions our Government  Can  be expected to take the lead.   -e ask  in the  name  of suffering  humanity that there should be a  very definite  and clear  lead given by our Government against  war.     MR. J.B. WILLIAMS:  I will Call upon Mr.  J.H.  Thomas to address you.     I R. J.H. THOMAS:   Mr. Prime  iiinister.   Both my colleagues have put before you in  general terras the feeling of the working classes of this country towards war and I will  be frenk by saying that they have net  expressed their general condemnation                                                             n of war and all  its horrors in more graphic terms than you yourself have described it on many occasions.    Your   last speaeh to the Ifoncomformists  of  this  country pointed out every thing that my colleagues have pointed  out this  morning and  there fore it would be idle to waste very much time oil the  general denunciation of war, except in eofaras we have  got  to be mind- ful that in this country to-day out people are  feeling the  worsteffects of it (hear hear).  Every home  is paving its  price  in suffering,  and the workers through unemployment  and&apos;misery  arepaying a price in that  connection.   Therefore  we make no apology as beihg specially representative of the working classes in saving to you - with all the knowledge of the misery and suffering - to bring to you immediately  what Our  people feel.     But what Is more germane to the point in that  connection is this,  that there was and is perhaps I hope - if  we can judge by the press things  look somewhat  easier  than when we                                           torae&amp;  yesterday,-  but when we read your  call/the Colonies,  acall that could not be  other than interpreted as a  danger ofwar,  a call which we have no hesitation  in saying that was  notonly unwise  but humiliating and. dangerous, .pe*i&amp;i&amp;&amp;e$$L 
it had reached such a stage of daiger as was portrayed inthat call the first and paramount duty, we maintain, of theCabinet would be to have summoned Parliament at once so thatthe peoplers representatives could have had a voice in it.But when we are spooking of labour, kir, we want to make itperfectly clear to you that if a war was inevitably forced upon us, the last war proved that no matter how united theCabinet may be end how determined you were, the opposition  -active, strong-and determined opposition - of the labour movement in this cou atry would make it disastrous1 &quot;from thepoint of view of the Empire.  And we make no apelogy insaying to ysu now clearly and definitely- and it is far better that you should understand it - we make no apology in  sayingto you ^hat sofaras this General Council is eonoeraed,  -Kithall the knowledge at eur disposal and with all the knowledgeof our people in the country, ue would fsel i.  incumbejK&amp;iupon us not enly te support the war but strongly to use all our influence to persuade our people not to support the war.How that is the deliberate decision arrived at by our  pee pie andit is as well that you know that right away0     Now having said that in a general way I want to put toyou our views on the immediate difficulty as we understand  It,and if I may say so I am going to submit that our attitude ha^sheen perfectly consistent   on the immediate difficulty,.You yourself in a speech delivered in February 1918 at a jointconference that we had with you on our own war aims gavegeneral approval to tixaai; whilst you qualified  it incertain respect;.-you did place it on record that,, speakingbroadly and generally, you thought it was a good and wisecontribution to the ultimate settlement that ought to  takeplaoea  I have not the exiraot of your spseoh at the moment, butspeaking generaly I am sure--     THE PRIMS MIBflSTBPv:  What did you say about the freedom.of the Straits?
                                                  -    151  i    I                                            B.4.     &apos;&quot;&apos; &quot;     MR. THOMAS:  I am coming to that, but  in the X5-oni&apos;e&quot;reJice&apos;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;which took place with us, you yourself gave  general applica-tion to our war aims and on- the particular  point this isthe phrase we used and which we had  sent to  you in advance -you had an advance copy of it.  This  is in  February 1918:-          &quot;It is further suggested that the  peace  of the           world requires that the Lhfdanelles should           be permanently and effectively neutralised           and open like all the main lines  of marine           communication under the control  of the  League           of Uations free to all nations without           hindranoe or customs duty&quot;,     THE PRIME LIUISTEL:  That is our policy to-day,     MH. THOMAS:  nait a moment.  I  am going to show it is our policy as well and we are going  to show that we agreedirectly.  How that was in 1918.     ME. CEAMBERlAlfl:  Permanently and effectively neutralised   junder the League of Nations ?                                                    i     ME, THOMAS;  Exactly.  That is  the phrase I used andprefaced my remark by saying that the Prime  Minister had notjoined issue on it.     THE PRIME MINISTER:  I accept that.     MR, THOMAS:  That was followed  by our  next international conference at Lausanne In 1919 - the  following year - andfollowing the peace.  -*gain we applied oui selves to this situation and if you will allow me to say so this  is the clearest anticipation of the danger  that has now arisen,because on this same question we say:-        *The Conference protests against the policy         of the Entente in j*sra Minor  and especially         against the military occupation by troops         of the Greek J-overnment in  the pay  of the         Entente of the town and village of omyrna         where the Turkish population Is five times         greater than the Greek&quot;.     THE PRIME MINISTER:  It was not  then.   It may now beten times greater.     MR. THCk&amp;S:  .*nd if it goes on  much longer it willprobably be exclusive, but here at least I  am drawing attentionto the fact that our policy as a Labour Party was  not onlyconsistent but there is no denying but we there saw  in
                                                      B..5.the circumstances the very danger iihat has happened now.I merely draw attention to that because that :&apos;.e  -----     3!HEi PRUnB MINISTER:  la there anything about  the Straitsthere ?     MR, THOMAS:  (handing in a document)  I want  to say toyou that our policy on this matter has been consistentright throughout.  How in connection with the decision ofthe Straits you yourself have indicated that you adhere to thefirst statement I read out.     (THE PRIME MINISTER:  Yes.     MR. THQkAS:  And the phrase and the meaningi  but wecannot reconcile that with your last speech in the Rouse onthe subject^ beoause in ysur speech of April 29th  last year, when you were giiring the general report of the Conference that had just previously been held you said -           &apos;*We have to guard the btraits - that  is           -our charge - Palestine and Mesopotamia.&quot;Now then, I -want to pui to you thei if the &quot;We&quot;  In thatspeech is  We&apos;  - Great Britain&quot; - it is absolutely eontradio-tory of an international control linder the League  of -Wations,and our interpretation of that speeuh to which you gaveutterance and in which we join issue is that whilst therewas common agreement as to the necessity of the  ctraits beingopen that was a common obligation a-nd not ours in  particular.
                                                    B.6.I has many other quotations, hut I have brought those threehome with the two-fold object of showing that we have not ---     THE PRIME MINISTER:  let me look at that.     ME. THOMAS:  (handing in a doaiment)  I have brought thosehome with a view of illustrating two points.  The first one is--     THE prime MINISTER; What is the date?     MR, 3JH0M&amp;S*  It was 19S1.  It was following the SanBemo Conference.  I am bringing these points home with the ideaof Illustrating two points on behalf of the General Council.The first is that we have not been ^mindful of theobligations of the Empire, that we.Jaave not &quot;&quot;bsenv.TinmInd.fiXi.of the necessity of the Straits being open, and  that wehave always believed and still believe&apos;., that ths support you,as a Government, gave to the Greeks has  been the direct causeof aggregating the situation.  In this matter we are neitherpro-Turk nor anti-Greek.  As far as we are oonoerned we arenot unmindful ef the things that have happened under bothsBut we are mindful of the fact that if we are involved in another war, it is our people who will have to pay the price,Therefore I sum up by submitting to you first our right -   which I am sure you will not challenge -as representativeof the British Trade Union movement in having in the ni&amp;atconstitutional way come to you as the responsible BritishGovernment to put our views before you;  secondly,, thatour attitude on this question is well known and well defined and which we stick to; and thirdly that it could be accomplishedwithout the unfortunate threats whitfh you yourself have foundnasMS^aary to uttera
                                                   0.1.It has been your special privilege as well as  your pleasureto lecture us on many occasions about threats.  I havehad to sit here and in other places and to hear  some  verynice homilies from you as to how much better we  could get our way without threats.  We believe that  of allthe things which have contributed towards this diffi-culty, the chief has been your own attitude, and Iwould conclude&apos; by saying that when we talk about theinterests of the Straits, we do not mean the exclusion of either Germany or Russia.  When we talk 0f  a  Leagueof Nations, we want it to be a League of Nations, thatis to say, a League of all nations.     THE PRIMS MINISTER:  That is to say, if they want to join it.  Up to the present they have both  refusedto join.     MR. THOMAS:  Here again, if we were going; into thefacts in connection with Germany there would be  anotherside to the question as to whether they have refused  tojoin and there would be very much to say.     THS PRIME MINISTER:  They (Germany) know  perfectly well that if they apply we will support them.  We willgive them support not merely in the sense that theyshould be a member of the League, but that they  shouldbe on its Council.  As for Russia, I know what. Chicherin says about the League of Nations,.     MR. THOMAS:  But it is not sufficient for you, Sir,to say  in the House of Commons &quot;Speaking for  myself&quot;,and then to have M. poincare or someone else disavowing it.We believe the League of Nations to be an instrument  for good, an instrument that ought to render the danger ofwar considerably less, but we equally believe  thatthere is a graver danger by big States                                            remaining/
                                                       C .2.remaining outside.       THE PRiM HMffiKHH:    I Quito  agree with you, and Iwould include  America.          MR.THOMAS:   And so would wo.  We think that Americawho contributed to the Versailles Treaty and its difficultieshas no right to run away from its obligations.  I have only to add that we appreciate the very prompt manner in which you metus, which is tho clearest indication  that you are not unmindfulof the dangers, and wo submit for your consideration the factswe have brought to your attention.          2.13*- OEAMSERLAIH:         In the Memorandum which you have presented you refer to a discussion in the House ofCommons, but there was no discussion  onthat subject recorded inHansard on the date you mention.          MR.THOMAS:   It may be tho wrong date, but I know the -speech;  I have it well in my mind.          MB.CHAMFIRLMIH:   May I say one ward about tho message-I got from Mr. -Howorman yesterday and the answer that was returnsI think there was some little misunderstanding either on thepart of my Private Secretary or Mr, 3owormm  or whoever took the message for him which has led to a mis-statement in the press&apos;.          MR.B0&apos;t3RM-If:   Speaking for myself, I do not think therwas any mistake on our side.          MR.GHAMBiHLAlI?:   I do not know how it came about, butthere is a suggestion in the press that the i?ri :e minister wasonly returning this morning and that  therefore the interview was fixed for today.  What happened was that Mr.Jowerman tried toget in touch with the ?rime Minister  who happened at that time tobe out of town for a few hours.  Ho therefore communicated with me.  I felt that this was a matter of such great consequencethat I ought not to handle it in the  temper ary absence of the                                                   Prime
Prime Minister from town.  He could not fix the time last night,and in view of other Cabinet consultations it could not have beenheld oarlior.          MR.THOMAS:   There is not one of us, Sir, who does not feel that you met us very promptly.        (At this point the Prime Ministor left the rcom to               consult with his colleagues^.,           On the Prime Minister *s rsturn, MRB THOMAS said:We find that the date was misquoted in the Memorandum wesubmitted to you.  It was given as 1921 instead of 1920*  the extract itself was perfectly in order.      THE PRIME ^MINISTER:   Well, Gentlemen, I am very glad of theopportunity you have afforded the Government of explaining tothe r epresentatives of so many millions of our f ellow-countrymenths, attitude and the policy of His Ma jestyrs&apos;Government in thesecritical . days,  Wo are not pursuing a policy of war.  Uo every                             beensentence in my speech which has/referred to by Mr,J0H0Thomas 1adhere, but in that speech I warned the public - in fact it was myobject when I made that speoeh to draw the attention of the public to the perils which existed and which might precipitate inter-national conflict unless they were averted.  If we havetahenstrong measures in the course of the last few days it has beenbecause we are firmly convinced that the measures will have theeffect of averting that conflict.  But if we had drifted alongtrusting merely to verbal protests, you might have had a conditionof things that would have made war inevitable, that would have carried the torch of war, pillage, outrage, and nurdor from Asiainto Europe.
                                                 Dole      It is to avert that - War in its most horrible form -we have taken the steps which re have taken, and&apos; which,subject to the overriding view of the democracy of thiscountry, we propose to continueo   I agree so fully  witheverything that Miss Bondfield has said that we mustpreserve suffering humanity from the terrors and torturesof war, that I want to read today what General Maurice says:-&quot;Nervousness amongst the Christian population, already considerable, has been much increased^ and an exodus  is taking place.   I cannot too strongly represent that inthe present temper of the Mohammedans the evacuation ofIsmid or Chanak at this juncture might have a sequel whichwould make the fires of Smyrna pale&quot;.   I recommend  thatto those who put forward the interests ef humanity.      MISS BONDFIELD; There have been considerablesufferings already.      THE PRIME MINISTER: That may be the case, but  that isno reason why the sufferings should be increased.      MISS BONDFIELD: Exactly.      THE&apos; PRIME MINISTER: Very  well; and therefore  I wantthat borne In mind.   That Is from a gentleman who  is  certain!no supporter of the Government, who is a systematic  criticof the Government, and has been ever since he quitted  office in 1918,   Now, that is the position.   We are anxious toavoid a war.   We are doing our best to avoid a war: weare taking,  In my judgment, the only method that will  avertwar, the only method that will prevent war from spreading,and that Is by saying &quot;Well, Asia Minor is out of our  controlcWe cannot engage in enterprises in Asia Minor ourselves; wedo not propose to support enterprises in Asia Minor, and havenever done so  but we are going to prevent the conflagration                                           from spreading/
spreading into Europe, and we can do so.   That is all wesay; because, if it spreads into Europe, the lesson of 1914shows that you cannot guarantee that you can stop thisprairie fire that once catches in the dry wood of Europe.That is all we are doing - we are preventing it fromspreading.      Something was said about our having paid the Greeks.We never paid sixpence to the Greeks; we never gave themsupport either in money or in arms.   The Greeks came here,as everybody comes, to try and negotiate a loan in the City,hut they failed.   With a Government guarantee they could have had it*   And let me point this out; when the Greekswent to Smyrna we said &quot; You go there at your own expense;we  cannot suooort you; you take the responsibility&apos;.! -  Just                                           Adalia, the French as  the Italians had at that moment gone to/      - the americans were hopeful that they might  get a mandate forAr^enia-j - the Greeks went to Smyrna.   It was part of thegeneral policy which  the Trades Unions  themselves supportedat  that moment, which  I  shall prove by  an  extract from what mr. J.H. Thomas  said  on  the subject.    Let me point out whatthe position  is.   We  gave , no thing  to the&apos;&quot;Greeks, but  thisis  not a question of  Greek; this  is not a  question ofArmenian -  it is  a -question of preventing  war  spreading  into europe.   Everything  that has been  said about  the League  ofNations we  all know.   We wired Lord  Balfour two or three days                /ago,  to  give our  support  to  every proposal                                        League  ofwhich  would involve  the  intervention of the/Nations.       MR.  J.K.  THOMAS:   To  the  extent of  settling the politicquestion as distinct from war?       THE PRIME MINISTER:  It  is  the League of  Nations whichsettles  this or other questions  ----       MR.  .T.I-I.  THOMAS:  Yes, but----       THE ^RIME MINISTER:  Do let  me finish.   The refusal to                                           other  Governments. refer to the League of Nations  came from the/&apos;&apos;   - &apos; - .    We                                               offered/
offered it in March of this year?  we were in favour then                                                     Governments ;of            referring to the League of Nations; otha&quot;/  &apos; &quot;refused.                    It is a new idea of ours            j                                                                :1referring to the League of Nations-.   The occupation of theStraits by the League of Nations we would welcone, and always would welcome, provided there is an adequate forcethere planted by the League of Nations to see that theStraits are kept neutralised and free.   You cannot defend the Straits and keep them, free by flauding a covenant                                force  them.in the way of those who try to/                      Itis no use pretending that you can; and therefore we ha73been ih favour of the League of nations undertaking theprotection of the Straits, provided it is really done.      Now I come to the question of the present position.It is now purely a question of maintaining the freedom  ofthe Straits,   There is no guarantee given by the Kemalist                                                   aGovernment that they will do anything beyond giving /verbalguarantee for the freedom, of the Straits.                    In 1914, when it was vital for thiscountry, when we had no reason to believe that we had anyquarrel whatever - nor had we - two or three TurkishMinisters in the pay of Gerriany overrode the rest,, andclosed the Straits in our teeth, and the War was undoubtedlyprolonged by two or three years.   Roumania was destroyed,Russia was destroyed - both those countries were destroyedbecause the Straits were closed, and nobody could go there.But can this country, which is a maritime country -  afterfour and a half years of war with Turkey because the Straitswere closed - can we possibly take steps that will putTurkey ih the same position as  she was before the War -to close the Straits against us, whatever happens, and.enable Roumania and Russia to be strangled, and closes  thewhole  commerce of the Black Sea?   Miss Bondfield did not                                             contend/
                                                   D.4.contend that that should he our policy.   She,  in factquoted a very clear extract from the Trades Unions docu-ment of 1918 which she says represents the policy of theLabour Party at  this hour - as it certainly represents ours;and T do not mind reading it a second time: -      &quot;It is further suggested that the peace of the world       requires that the Dardanelles should he  completely       and effectively neutralised and opened like all the       main lines of marine communication under the control       of the League Of Nations - not of Turkey - freely       to all Nations without hindrance or Customs Duties.&quot;That is the policy , but that is under the control of theLeague of Nations - not under the control of Turkey.      Well now, what I want to put is this:  The Turks  demandcontrol of the Straits,       e.s essential for  national security  and success,      MR. .T.H. THOMAS: You are quoting from  some document?                                     0             PACT      THE PRTT1H  MINISTER:  Yes, the TURKISH  NATIML/whichsubstantially demands that they should have  the power  to close the Straits.   They say it is essential to the securityof Constantinople, but they g\zarantee  that they will keepthe Straits open.   That was exactly $he position  in 1914,but that  is not  the  dsmmd  of the Labour Party either  in                Labour  Party1918 or now.   The/ say that the Straits should be -under thecontrol of the League of Nations.   If the Kemalists demand that the  Straits  should be under the control  of the  Turks,and that  we  should defend merely sckAx  on verbal guaranteesthat those Straits will be kept open,  I  should  like  to know                                                whether        utiat  is  the  view of  the Labour Party -  /    you  would accept that position   Without putting  * up - .. any fight for the freedom  of the Straits. I.f  that  is the  case, wellthen, that  is not our position.    Our  position  is  that we propose to hold  the  Straits  until  the  Conference;  we proposeto do our best  to prevent  the fire  from  crossing the                                             Bosphorus/
                                                       D.5.Bosphorus or the Dardanelles.    Then when we come to theConference we propose with all Cur power to press thepolicy by which every Nation will gain, and that is thatthe key  of the Straits should be in the pocket of theLeague of Nations.   That is our policy.   I would pointout to Mr. Thomas that in the paragraph which he has quotedhe has left out some very vital poihts.      MR. J,H, THOMAS: Not deliberately;  I quoted extractsWhich were applicable.      THE PRIME MINISTER: Quite so, but believe me theyare not without significance when youcome to criticiseour attitude with regard to Anatolia.   I will just show you in what respect your policy and ours has been identical.  Mr.Thomas says that in 1918 I adopted the policy of the LabourParty in the  declaration I made.   I did not adopt it.   Itwas our policy too*   We both took the sane view.   Mr. Thomashas abandoned it; that is the only difference.   I will justread what that declaratibn was:      &quot;The Conference condemns handing back to the       systematically violent domination of the Turkish       Government any subject people^   that, whatever       may he proposed with regard to Armenia, Mesopotamia       and Arabia,  they cannot be restored to the tyrranies       of the Sultan.   ,The Conference condemns the aims       of those who would make these territories subject       to  any such  domination.    If the peoples of these        territories do not feel  themselves able to settle       their  o*wn destinies, the Conference insists that,       conformably  with the policy of  lno annexations1       they  should  be placed for  administration under a       Commission acting with super-national  authority       sf the League  of Nations.   That is, you  should  take       them from the Turks and put  them under  the       authority  of somebody that  will guarantee that       these subject  populations  will  be governed  fairly.&quot;That was our  policy,      MR. J.H. THOMAS:  No, not    Your policy has  been  four powers, not the Leagiie  of Nations.
India.  All these things count with us, but wo axe of theopinion that so fax as we axe concerned,  you will not get anyresponse of any sort or degree or character that wouia warrantyour assumption that wo are enthusiastic or desirous of taking part in any war.  The state of unemployment would mean thatsome men would join, particularly the young men, if any callwere made upon them. Some of them might be glad of it, but sofar as the intelligent organised opinion of Labour is concerned,you would find all of us would throw all our ardour intopreventing another war happening to us.  As ,1 say we are nothero to criticise; we are not hero to be involved in an argument.All we are here for is to tell you tho ilain GrOd*s truth -* weshould be opposed to war and would organise opposition against.any form of war.
                                                 P.6.      TRT ?Rl:&quot;E MINISTER:  Somebody had to -occupy  it,   Xthink I know what our policy was.   Our pea 103 was to havethe sovereignty vested in the League of Nations-.,   You had of course to give a mandate to some particular  au I horityvPor instance, in Armenia, the proposal was thar.  -;,he nx.ndateshould be given to America, which would have  prcr.eo.1 elthose poor people; bht at any rate what I  want  to  pomx, outis this; our view was identical  withyours  at  that  moment,that you could not leave these subject populations inAnatolia under the control of the Turks0   I  am sorry tosay that; for reasons over which the Labour Party and our-selves have no control, that policy has become  impossible,                                          for Armeniafirst of all because America would not cone in/would hothave it; it has become impossible in the second place be-                                               in CiJxciacause the French  could not undertake the Mandated  it hasbecome impossible in the thirrt place because  the Italianscould not undertake the mandate  for Southern  Anatolia;and it has become Impossible in  the fourth place because,       fallby the/&apos;      of Venezelos and the transmission  ofpowers to a thoroughly incompetent regime  that  last partWPS impossible.   We agree that  at the present  moment you cannot enforce that.
 The consequences have, been very disastrous in the massacre of thousands and scores of thousands of Armenians and Anatolians.   But all we can do is to prevent that spreading into Europe.   Hr. Thomas made a. reference about using                                               or threats.   Iviy only recollection is that upon one/two occasiohs when I was trying to settle labour disputes I suggested that the decisidn should be/Some to by an impartial tribunal,, and I quoted the case of the League of Nations as a proof of the advisability of disputes being settled rather by reason than toy war.   That is exactly our policy to-day   We are quite willing that the League of Nations should settle this dispute.   We are quite willing to be controlled toy the decision of the League of Nations, but of course we must get an agreement from theTurks also to abide by the decision of the League of Nations, otherwise it is cf no more use to make a proposal of that kind than It was to the .purposo in labour disputes when one  iide    or both of then refused it.   We could,not -onfcprco in that case and we cannot in this case,    All we can do is to try and induce peace.   Meanwhile, we stand by the declaration made net  merely by us but, as Mr. Thomas points out, male by the Labour Siriy that the freedom of the Straits must be ensured uuder the control of some inter- national authority whom you can trust and not    under the&apos; control of the Turk who, in 1914, closed the Straits to - us and might be tempted in the future - perhaps not the present Government but ssme other Government conceivably that you might have in Constantinople -* night be tempted by some other Power to close the straits against us and by&apos; tha^means bring c new struggle upon Europe*       I finally call attention to the fact that the Labour Rarty proposed this polioy In 1918 in the interests of the peace of the world.   They did not regard it as -a war policy                                                      /then.
1S4                                                    Ea2.then.   The war policy in their judgment was handing theDardanelles over to anybody except an International author! tycThey further suggested that the peace of the world requires that the Dardanelles should be handed over to the control ofthe League of Nations9   That Is our peace policye   our peace policy is the peace policy of the Labour Party.   Itis in the interests of peace that we are proposing it,exactly as they proposed it in 1918 in the interests of peacecWe are all for peace, but we think we are pursuing the only possible method for ensuring it, and there are many people who believe that if this method had been adopted in 1914,before it was too late, there would have been no war     MR, BEN TILLETT:   I have followed you very closely.I would like to get your definition of what you term &quot;freedomof the Straits&quot;.     THE PRIME MINISTER:   The freedom of the Straits Is  this -that it should be just like any other in&quot;ernational waterway,that it should be free to the vessels of.&quot; any nation to pass to and fro to the Black Sea without any interference, and thatyou should have a guarantee not merely on the word of the turk, but of the control of the League of Nations in orderto ensure free passagoc     MR. BEN TILLETT:   Does that mean fortifications In thehands of an international body?     THE PRIME MINISTER:   That they would have to decidejif they thought it necessary to fortify in order to guaranteefreedom, the Leaguo of Nations would decide that *   That  isnot for us to decide0     MR. CHAH3ERL&amp;IN:   Whatever is necessary to make thecontrol of the League of Nations effective,,
      MR.  BEN TILLETT :    In 6ase--of^mr^tJtor^LJL^-t-o......be.&apos; no - lnts rrVr-enceJB&amp;fla that -neutral! ty ?      THE  PRIME MINISTER:   No.      MR.  BEN TILLETT:    By any nation?      THE  PRIME MINISTER;    No  - by  any  nation.;  by  cursor by any  other nation.  .  Otherwise  that is  not  i nternaii on-alisation  of the Straits.      MR.  J.H. THOMAS:    Let me say  that I an  quite  sure^that when  I  said there. Was-no- apology--ne-ces-aary  f or  us beinghere  e v * ... c      THE  PRIME MINISTER:    I  beg your pardon..   I  am  so  sorry.There is one thing it Is  essential I should say;  I  had quiteforgotten  about that -  that Is.,- that we  treated  the  Greeksexactly  In the same way as we   are treating the  Turks  now aboutthe neutral zone.   We  went to the neutral zone  at  the requestof  our Allies and in agreement with  the  Turks,   It   .vas  partof  the Armistice with the Turks that we  entered  this neutral zone,-    We occupied one part,  the French occupied another,but  it was an agreement between the  Allies,and the  Turksagreed  to  It in an armistice which is still in existence *    - SIR  L. WORTHINGTON-EVANS:  And the Italians.       THE  PRIME MINISTER:   The Italians, yes,   The Greeks     threatened to advance to this  zone because they said thatTurkish bandits were gathering together under the protection of  the  British   flag to attack them, and they earnest her e; that  is  Chanak.   They  came there  but we turned them out. We           tt      said,we are holding this on behalf of the Allies  and we cannot  allow either Greek or Turk!1   They then,  quite  recently, threatened to advance upon-Constantinople, and it must beremembered that they were at? *--ar v.: th the Turksc   If  we  had-not  beer, there, it would have been a  perfectly legitimate  operation 1
 for thera &quot;to have marched on the Turkish capital just as the Turks were margining upon Smyrnae   We said to them, we will not allow you to cross the neutral zone.   Vie actually put British troops there to stop them, and if they had advanced we should have fired upon them,,       MR. CHAMBERLAIN:   French troops were mainly holding that front, and on this strip we immediately put English troops to support the French and forbid the Greeks to violate the neutral zone as we now forbid the Turks,       THE PRIME MINISTER:   We received no protest/from the Labour party,and all we are doing now is to treat the Turks as the Greeks..  Until there is peace we can allow neither to enter the neutral zone which we are holding      for our Allies.   We are perfectly impartial, and as a matter of fact our first action Was against the Greeks and not the Turks; and at the time the Greeks could have delivered a most effective counter-blow against the Turks - a most effecive counter-blow *- because their ships could have prevented the Turks crossing the Dardanelles because they had a better navy than the Turks and they could have easily stopped It.   I think it very important that we should make it clear that we hold the balance quite fairly between both parties and that our first action was against the Greeks and at present our only action.       ME. BEN TILLSTT:   What would be very helpful would be to have your opinion as to the kind of international control. that is, Would the Ecu -anlans, would the Russians, would the Turks, would those directly affected by the Dardanelleshave some voice i some lot j in that ceunGijl?       THE PRIME MINISTER:  Certainly we have been strongly in favour of the Rouinanians coming there because they are interested^   As for the Russians, that is a matter for the Conference which is.to take place later on between the parties, and I should say it would probably be handed to the League                                                       /of
 of Nations and it would probably be for the League  of Nations to consider bow the guard Is to be composed,      MR. BEN TILLETT:   Would you be prepared to favour the Russians?      MR, CHAMBERLAIN:   I think that is an embarrassing question, to put to a Government which has got to conduct negotiations with a great many Powers.   I do not think we ought to be asked to pledge ourselves or to go too  much into details at this moment.   The assurance we are giving in perfect good faith is that we must have effective international control no more favourable to us than to other Powers, securing by international authority that freedom of the Straits which is as much your policy as ours 4      THE PRIME MINISTER:   And I need hardly point  out thatcompared with all the other great Powers In the world our attitude towards Russia is not the least friendly.      MR. J.H. THOMAS;   Our presence has given you  a very necessary opportunity of declaring what is your policy and you have not unfairly, if I may say so, with the usual  skill that we always expect from you, clearly indicated what brothers we are in this matter and that really you are only discharging our policy.    With the greatest respect..........      THE PRIME MINISTER:   I do not call it your policy; it is no more yours than ours.      MR. J.H. THOMAS:   Our joint policy,      THE PRIME MINISTER:   That is it.   It. is a policy which I  declared in. 1918 and to which you assented, to which you agreed.      MR. J.H. THOMAS:   If that is so, I think it is better to immediately draw attention to the fact that we rather disagree                                                    / wi th
                                             E,6a with the methods in giving effect to this policy, and we do not think your method has had the best effects For instance, -you have clearly indicated this morning  - and I presume the intimation to us is meant to be  to the world at large as welL....       THE PRIME MINISTER;  I do not know.   That depends entirely on what we agree.   I understood this was a private-interview and that was the view taken by Mr. Wiliiansj and that Is why we are talking very  freely: so that at the moment I am not talking to the world at large but to the representatives of tie great Trade unions in the countrys       MR. J.H. THOMAS:   In this sense - that it is the policy that you have indicated you Intend to stick to!                           known and therefore it will beeone/at some time to the world.       THE PRIME MINISTER:   It is known already, I hope,       MR, iffH, THOMAS:   You have intimated that you have acquainted Lord half our within the past few days  of. your agreement to the matter being raised at the League, Well now, I put it to you, Sir, that it would have been better if that had been your consistent policy, if that step had&quot;been taken before this immediate crisis,  because       THE PRIME MINISTER:   I think you have forgotten, Mr. Thomas, that I said we proposed it in March other Powo refused it.   That is rather before the present crisis,       MR. J.H, THOMAS:   I will come to that in a  moment, but I presume - and I only want to be quite clear  so that we know exactly what the policy is - I presume that in answer to your appeal to the Colonies one intimation at least was that they had instructed their representatives to raise the issue there; and do I gather that you have acquiesced in that       course by your instruction to                                                /Lord
                                                E.70Lord Balfour?  Is that what I understand?      THE PRIME MINISTER:   That is what I said5      MR. J.H. THOMAS:  It is rather different.      MR. CHAMBERLAIN:   Mr. Thomas understates it when he says we acquiesced.  We gladly concurred in it and Lord Balfourvrill support it.      THE PRIME MINISTER:   It is not a belated policy ofours  because It is what we proposed in March before  thiscrisis arose.      MR. J.H. THOMAS:   But In the second place you also made a very significant statement which I presume you attachconsiderable importance to and expect us to, namely,  thatthe only issue now was the question of the Straits,
      THE PRIMS MINISTER:  I ,do net know what you mean by  theonly issue.      MR. THOMAS:  The only object as far as  our troops  areconcerned was and can be taken -      THE PRIME MINISTER:  Yes.      MR. THOMAS:,:  I want to krow, does that mean that  sofar as the Borders question * so far as the remainder of  the differences on this matter are concerned, they  are  all matters of adjustment, for negotiation *i      THE PRIME MINISTER:  ^es.      MR. THOMAS:  That is very important.      THE PRIME MINISTER:  Eor instance I mean  - protectionof Minorities, the Boundaries of Thrace - those are questions for discussion.  The one question upon which  we cannot  give way is the Freedom of the Straits.  Upon that we stand  andwe cannot - I want to be quite clear - we cannot until  theConference comes to an agreement, we cannot permit  the  zone of the Straits to be occupied and the war to  be carried into Europe and trouble to begin in this Continent  again?You must remember it was from the Balkans the war of 1914began,  I want you to bear that in mind.  It  is always the place where the trouble begins.  We do not  want any  moretrouble.  This is a peace policy and I am sure  it is inthe interests of peace to prevent these people  coming over.If they cone over and start massacring - they are in thatmood at present; it makes no difference who provoked it;it is the fact they are in that mood - if they  cross overin that mood and you have massacres, and you  have troublesIn Thrace, the Ydiole infernal trouble would begin again.I am using the word infernal1 not as an expletive butas a fair descriptive adjective.  Ours is a policy of peace.
i 11          MR. THOMAS:  Por  the aonont  I an  only trying to ascertain so  tli-it there nay be no misapprehension afterwards when wo come to  oonsider this question, what exactly is meant by the different phrases you use.   &apos;e do not want to have any misundorstanding about that and I am still  going to put raw point again, namely is  it the position at this moment that the British Government&apos;s policy is to agree that any International Commissions, which includes the League of nations, are to be the people responsible for hooping the Straits open?      T3E PRIME MINISTER:   Yos.           MR.THOMAS:  That is point ono; and that, that having been settled cither by the League of Nations or some International Commission, the second point is, the existing Treaties which define the borders are all shall wo say to be scrapped or you enter into a discussion of those da novo.  Do I mi dorstand that to be the position?      THE miM JOTISTSEH:   I do not use the word Scrapped1. Butwo are quite open to discuss the question of boundaries.  We are not using our troops on any question of boundaries at all.Wo are using our troops purely to safeguard the Freedom of the Straits and to prevent the extension of the war to Europe. Those are the two purposes.          MR.CHAM3;5RT.a.IF:  Would it help at this point to remind Mr.Thomas that our policy has all along been to restore Constant- inople to the Turks.          HR.THOMAS:  That has boon your private policy.       THE PRIMS MINISTER:  I beg your pardon, Mr.Thomas.  It is  in the Treaty of Sevres; it is in the Paris Treaty and the declaration which has been so criticised which wo mado on Saturday again repeated that.  We have never swerved from that policy and as you know very well wo wore attacked in the House                                                        of
of Commons because We were restoring -Constantinople to theTurks.  There was a big debate and I am not aware I got very-muchsupport on that occasion when I made a speech in favour of restoring Constantinople to the Turks.          MR.THOMAS:  It is not for us here to go into what partysupports you in the House except to say that in all your foreignpolicy latterly the only people who have supported you have boonour people and nobody knows that better that you. At all eventswe do not want to get into a controversy here.          MR.CHAMBERLAIN:  Mr.Thomas will know that neither thePrimo Minister nor ayself have acted with a view to provokingtrouble.  It was with a view of clearing the air and it has beenour publicly declared policy to restore Constantinople to theTurks as soon as peace was made and it is our policy to discussthe situation with an open mind with those who are immediatelyinterested with the object of finding a settlement which does notmerely lead to war the day after.          MR. TIL LETT:  Would it be possible for t he Prime Ministerto give us some statement as to the attitude of the Allies onthis matter?       THE PRIMS MINISTER:&quot;  On the matter of the &quot;Jree^om of theStraits?          MR. TILIETT:  Yes.       THE       KUJIST3EE:   I an not aware  that any Ally has goneback on the question of the Ereedom of the  Straits.          MB. WILLIAMS:  On behalf of the Council I wish to thankyou for giving us so much of your time on this question and forthe clear statement you have given us.  As.to what the opinion of.tho Council is in regard to your reply I cannot  say until  we discuss it.        TES PRIMS MINISTER:  I think wo must have an agreement aboutthe report because  I fio not want any charge in regard  to breach                                                             of
of  faith  in 3?ogard  to  it.          MR.TILL?T3?:   I much prefer an open report being  given.       TE3 PEJME MIEIS0)ER:   I certainly have no  objection.          MR. CHii-MB:3HL.aIK:  It is a very serious  matter  what  wepublish.  Opinions  provisionally expressed in conversation maybe modified, misconceptions  which the Conference nay  haveremoved,  to publish those nav defeat the object  enmmon  to  usboth which is to avoid,  war.          MR; SMIIIJXQ:   I think it would be bettor  that  this  join-meeting should now  decide that we should simply  issue a baia six-line st at onion t totho press which we agree now, stating  thatMrcThomas, Miss Bondfleld and MrVTillett placed  the views  ofthe Council before  the  Prime Minister and the Prime Ministerreplied.          MR,, CH.il/I3MB la IP:  I think that is very wise, Mr,Smillie.I foel a  deep sense of  responsibility.  It is quite clear  thatat the proper moment we must render an account to the House  andto-the country of all that has happened but I do fool that publication at this moment of our conversation might havedisastrous results  and  I think MruBmillio1s proposal  is a  verywise one.          MR.THOMAS:  If you are going to do it  in that my, whynot immediately  got one of your men with one of cur men toput in a  few sentences  before wo leave the proposals we made and the answer made by  the Prime. Minister.          SIR ROBERT BORES:  The Prime ministers reply was obviously a very long one,          MR. THOMAS:  You must put all your -cards clearly  onthe table..    v     MR.WILLIAMS:  1 think the general feeling on  this  sideof the table  is that a  bald  statement as to the  proposals  wo                                                         made
 made and the reply that was given would be sufficient.        !PMB PJ&amp;UB lOTISfllEi   I am thinking of the effect of publication abroad.   If we  stated under no conditions would you resist  and Mustapha Kemal sees it.  if you give that Impression abroad,  believe me,  it is very bad-.   The one chance of  stopping the  war  is for Mustapha Kemal to know that we are not going to be turned  out,of the  Straits.   3f he  knows that he won*t go there. There was  a little incident about a yoar or t?;o --go at  Ismid. Ho boat  -uhe  Greeks and marched albng  and fired upon some of our troops who fired basic   I beliefre that he is going to do it again and  we aro going to stop him naturally.   If he believes that the nation is  divided  on  tho subjoct and  that he is getting encourage- ment to  go on,  he  will be very likely to pursue a warlike policy. We are not eut for war;  we  are out for peace.         MRfiSHJMBBRlAlH:   What I think would be helpful would be-to refer to  the ISIS  Resolution and say that that represented the policy today.         _MR.WtlI.IiJ/iS:   There  Is no one on this side of the table who  wants  to say anything that will encourage war.        TEB ESjtSltE MmiSTJEU   Bor on this side of it either.           MR.WlILIAuS:   I think that  a bare statement should go out  to  the press.  .  .           MR.THOMAS:   And tho shorthand notes will go. to Mr. Bowerman as a private documant*.

</content>
</cab>
