<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 276-276</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   DOCTOEHT IS THE PRO Pn&apos;Rfjy. OF. HIS BRTTA-MTSft0 MAJESTY&quot;&apos; S GQVEWHEHT ),: 1 8 6iflgET.,.-                    lv.P.. 4225.                          &apos; G - A, B I 3M E T .                          ML0AH   TO   AUSTRIA&quot;pecypher,    Mr, London (Geneva),                            24th September, 1922,       D,&apos;    1.00-a-emV 25th September, 1922.       R,    10-SO a-,m,25th September., &apos; 1922.,  -lumber  53.                 Following from Lord Balfour for Cabinet.                 Your telegram.Number 39                 I hope when Prime Minister and Chancellor of the            Exchequer are considering subject of Austrian guarantees,            they will keep following points in mind.              1.  That plan on which sub-commit tee. is engaged seems            to offer real prospect of extracting Austria, from          .  apparently hopeless position.   If she is not extricated            economic and political consequences will undoubtedly            be serious and may be very grave..                  British trade will directly suffer and Indirectly            recovery of Europe will be greatly delayed&quot;,              2c  Blackett will have explained nature of guaranteeo            France, Italy and Czechoslovakia are each prepared to            guarantee 20% of loan.   I hope Great Britain will guarantee         .   another 20%a    Securities are ample,, no money will be            advanced to Austria unless and until she is committed to            work of reform and if scheme succeeds Britain will be            repaid loan she has already made to Austria, in the course            of this year  which is over  2,000,000.                 Het new  liability would thus be little more than             2,500,000 but of  5,000,000 ample security which it. is            proposed to guarantee-.   If Britain stands out I fear whole            plan will fail and Great Britain however unfairly will be            regarded as -responsible for failure0Whitehall Gardens,&quot;                   -------25th  September,  1922:.                     .

</content>
</cab>
