<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 291-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                         G A3 I H S T.                       vj &apos;I.P. 4228.                -&apos;--           OOIJFBRBBCE Oil inter-ALLIED DSBTS MJD REPARATIONS.                     Hote by the Secretary.         With reference to the Memorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State   for Foreign, Affairs on the proposed Conference on Inter-ill Led.    Debts and Reparations (CP.4194), I circulate herewith to the   Cabinet a Sfote received from the Under Secretary of Stats for   Foreign Affairs, covering  en amendment proposed &quot;by the Treasury   to the penultimate sentence of Paragraph 8 of Lord CurzonEs   draft despatch to Lord Hardiaage.                                        (Signed) M.P.A.HANEEYWh it ehal 1 Gar den s . - S. W.ih September. 1922.
X ... &apos;202 &quot;f 7795/2618/50).               The Under Secretary of $tat e for Foreign Affairs presents      his compliments to the Secretary to the Cabinet,  and is directed      by the Marquess Curzon of Kedleston to transmit herewith the      text of an amendment which the Treasury suggest should be inserted      in the draft reply to Monsieur Poincare*s note on tho subject of      Inter-Allied indebtedness..            2. In view of the Secretary of State7 s re commendation to      the Cabinet that no answer should be sent to the French note at      present, it would seem unnecessary for the moment to consider the      adoption of this amendment which Sir M. Hen key will, doubtless,      bring before the Cabinet when they resume their discussions on      t his que st ion.                 Proposed Amendment to the penultimate sentence                   of paragraph 8 of Lord CuraonTs despatch                   to Lord Hardinge regarding inter-allied                                    debts. &quot;So far as concerns the method of computation &quot;used in fixing the French debt to Great  Britain &quot;no export duties were  charged on supplies &quot;furnished by the War Office and the  charges  for &quot;all materials &quot;which were at the time accepted &quot;and paid by the French authorities did not&quot;exceed the actual cost  to the British taxpayer.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
