<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 343-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is  the  property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.                                II     31SECRET.CP.  4340.     .THE CABINET.THE   SITUATION  IN  THE  NEAR  EAST.      MEMORANDUM  BY  THE SECRETARY  OF STATE FOR WAR.    I circulate     A. An appreciation of the  position at  Chanak Constantinople,  prepared  by the           Chief of the  Naval Staff, the Chief of the Imperial  General  Staff and the           Chief of the Air Staff;  .    B. An appreciation of the situation in Gallipoli and Chanak during  October, 1922,           prepared by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff.                                                                       L. W.-E.THE WAR  OFFICE,    28lh September, 1922.A.-APPRECIATION  BY  THE  COMBINED  STAFFS  OF  THE  POSITION                      AT  CHANAK CONSTANTINOPLE.    The Conference had  under discussion the question of holding Chanak and Gallipoliand the statement that the evacuation of Constantinople would be necessary, vide general harington&apos;s telegram of 27th September,  1922.    It was pointed out that General Harington had never doubted his capability to holdChanak.    It was agreed that Chanak  could be held for 3 or 4 weeks after the  evacuation ofConstantinople with the present forces available.    It was pointed out, in this connexion, by the Chief of the Air Staff that Air Forcesin conjunction with counter-battery work should  make it impossible for the  enemy tobring up and maintain large guns on Bairak  Tepe and Sirt Tepe, which two  positionscommand Chanak.    The Chief of the Naval  Staff also  stated that the Navy could  lend material  help,and that the Commander-in-Chief, Mediterranean, had reported  that  Naval Forces couldbe stationed to support the defence with gun-fire, and that the ground lent itself to such operations.    From  purely military  considerations, therefore, there is no  reason for evacuatingChanak.    It was pointed out, however, that the.  Turks  must not be permitted to bring  gunsinto the  neutral zone.  The present  policy had  been to avoid  incidents, and Turkishcavalry had entered the zone ; artillery, however, was far more important..    It was agreed that the  reply to General  Harington  should indicate  again  that, ifnecessary, he was to evacuate Constantinople in order to hold Chanak.    It should be emphasized to him that the policy to hold Gallipoli and Chanak remains the same.    It was then agreed that, if  the policy is to hold Chanak and Gallipoli permanently,the Cabinet must decide to reinforce with sufficient force as soon as  Kemal attacked, andthat General Harington should be so informed.    Two divisions would be mobilized as reinforcements  and, assuming 2nd October asthe date of mobilization, there would be a gap of  8 days, between 15th and 23rd October,between the arrival of the  last  troops now on their way  and  the first of the  troops of.those  mobilized.    It is the opinion of the General  Staff that the first serious  attacks by the Turks onChanak will  be  repulsed.  The  question whether or  not the Expeditionary Force landson  Gallipoli first of  all,  or  directly at Chanak,  will  depend on the  perimeter held at chanak.    It is possible that the first attack  by the Turks would  be repulsed with heavy losses to them, that is, be so decisive as to permit of the perimeter being extended  to includethe two hills, Bairak Tepe and Sirt Tepe.    (B22/251)  100 9/22  W.O.P.  377
     To sum up :      The force now at Chanak is inadequate to stave off a prolonged attack, which would necessitate the immediate evacuation of Constantinople to render it safe until the situation was  improved  by the arrival of reinforcements from  England,  namely two  divisions,which would commence to arrive 21 days after mobilization.     It was emphasized that  these  forces, including the two divisions mobilized, couldonly hold Chanak and Gallipoli, and could not clear the Neutral Zone.     27th  September, 1922. B. APPRECIATION  BY THE GENERAL  STAFF  OF  THE  SITUATION  IN              GALLIPOLI AND  CHANAK  DURING OCTOBER,  1922.                                   1. ASSUMPTIONS.      The  General Staff  have been asked to  appreciate the situation which may develop during October, 1922, on the following assumptions         (a)  That  the  Turks  attack   the  British  forces  at   Chanak  on  or  about             30th September,  with  such forces as they can bring up by that date ;      (b)  That  the  Turks are repulsed and  then take  up  a  position  within striking             distance of the British forces to await reinforcements ;      (c)  That  orders are given in  England  on 2nd  October for the  mobilization  o              the Interim  Expeditionary  Force of two divisions and  a cavalry  brigade             and their despatch  to the Dardanelles for the  purpose of driving back the             Turks and re-establishing the control of  the neutral zone.                                2. SPECIAL PROBLEMS.      The special problems to  be dealt with on the above assumption are :       (a)  What would  be the situation  and  prospects  of the  British Force  during the             period  between  the  arrival   on  15 th October  of  the last  reinforcements             now under orders and  the arrival of the Interim Expeditionary Force ?      (b)  What  prospect  is  there that  the  British  force reinforced  by the  Interim             Expeditionary Force will  be able to carry out the task of driving the Turks             out of the neutral zone and holding it ?      In considering these questions, the assumption that we can repulse a Turkish attack on Chanak has  been accepted ; but the General Staff consider  that Kemal has sufficient force at hand to make a prolonged resistance impossible.                    3. STRENGTH  AND SITUATION OF OUR FOECES.      By  30th  September, on  the  assumption  that  General  Harington  still holds Constantinople  with           4 Battalions,          2 Field batteries,          1 Squadron cavalry, which is  the minimum he  can be satisfied  with so  long as he remains there (vide his telegram        of  22nd  September),  his  force at  Chanak  and  Gallipoli  will be  as follows :           1 Cavalry regiment (less 1 squadron).          5 Field artillery batteries.          2 Pack batteries.        *4 Medium batteries (on Gallipoli Peninsula or at Chanak).       i  ffl Battalions.          1 Squadron and 1  Flight (arrives 30th  September  or 1st  October and  first.             machine in action  1. day later).      By  7th October, 5 more  battalions will  have  arrived,  and  by  15th  October a further  reinforcement of 2 pack  batteries, a medium  artillery brigade, a heavy brigade,. Royal Garrison Artillery, with three more Royal Air Force squadrons and  drafts.Including 1 battery arriving on this date.
     After this  date,  there will be a gap  till 23rd October,  when the infantry of thefirst reinforcing&apos; division  from  England could  begin to arrive.   The  whole of  thedismounted personnel of the 1st Division could arrive by 30th  October and the balance ofits mounted troops, including horses, would reach the Dardanelles by 3rd November.     The arrival of the  dismounted personnel of the second  reinforcing division could being on 30th or 31st October, being completed  by 4th November, and its horses could arrive by 7th November.     The line which  General Harington is  now holding is approximately a perimeter of4 miles  round Chanak.   Its  actual garrison now is 6  battalions.  The position is wellprepared and wired and reconnaissance  has  been  made  with  a view to  its extension asreinforcements arrive.  But the force which he will have by 30th September (see above)will not suffice to enable him to extend his position sufficiently to give him possession ofthe  heights  Bairak  Tepe  and Sirt Tepe overlooking  Chanak and the Narrows, whichit would seem essential to  hold in order to cover  the assembly of the Expeditionary Force.     We must assume, therefore, that if attacked  by 30th  September, General Haringtonwill hold only the position he has now  prepared  with possibly  a hastily prepared outpostzone in front  of it.  (A description   of  the country round Chanak is  contained inAppendix I.)                  4.  SITUATION  AND STRENGTH OF  TURKISH  FORCES.     The Nationalist forces in the western portion of Asia are grouped in 3 armies.   The 3rd Army of 3 divisions (about 11,000 rifles and  24 guns)  is in the neighbourhood of Ismid and may be expected to remain there to watch, or, if necessary, to advance against Constantinople.     The  2nd  Turkish Army  (36,000 men and 112 guns)  has been  concentrating northward into the area Ak Hissar-Balikesri-Panclerma Edremid, and is now believed to  be continuing its move  northwards.   With  this army, or part of it,  an  attack on Chanak might he delivered at any  time  after 28th September.     Under  the assumption  made  in  section 1,  it is  this army which will have been repulsed on  30th  September.     The 1st Turkish Army  (available strength, after deducting proportion for Lines of Communication troops,  18,000 rifles and sabres and 79 guns) is in  the neighbourhood of Smyrna but is reported to be moving northward.  There are,  however, only three  roads leading into  the  Dardanelles neutral  zone, namely,  those passing through Panderma, Balia Bazar Koi and Edremid.   The first is suitable for horsed and possibly mechanical transport, the second for  pack transport and the third for  horsed transport. It  will, therefore, not be easy for the Turks to  move horsed guns,  ammunition and supplies into the area immediately around  Chanak, and the concentration for attack of any force larger than the 2nd Turkish Army will present  great  difficulties.   We  have,  however,  seen many instances during the past seven years of the Turks overcoming similar difficulties, and we must admit that it is possible they may do so again.    On  the  whole, it appears most probable that the 1st Turkish Army would  not  be launched  into the  neutral zone until  some date considerably later than 2nd October,  and that  if it is it will be short of  guns, ammunition and  essential supplies.     In the opinion of the General Staff, it is unlikely that  the Turks will  be able to increase their rifle strength or their artillery to  any  appreciable strength once they have concentrated the three armies referred to in this  paragraph.                        5. SITUATION  AFTER 30TH SEPTEMBER.  ,     Assuming that  the first  attack by the  Turks has been defeated, it  may be supposed that they will not attack again until they have  received considerable reinforcements, and, having regard to the conditions  stated in section 4,  it appears unlikely that a  second serious attack on a larger  scale  than  the initial attack could be  delivered much before 15th October.      Between 7th and 15th October,  General  Harington will  have  received -reinforce- ments  amounting to 5 battalions, 4  medium   batteries,  2 pack  batteries and 4  heavy batteries, Royal Garrison  Artillery, and 3 squadrons,  Rojal  Air Force, though some of the guns will hardly be in action quite  so soon.   He will also, if the situation  at Chanak becomes dangerous, jDresumably have withdrawn altogether from  the Constantinople area. Thus  by 15th October, at  latest, his total force may be taken at 15 battalions, with x4^field and mountain g-uns and howitzers  and  at least 16 medium guns and howitzers
actually ready and 16 medium howitzers and 16 heavy howitzers which can be expected.to be ready very quickly.     His force  will thus have been  approximately doubled  in numbers and will have-received a great accession of gap power.  It must also  be remembered  that  our troops-based  on the sea should be  able  to lire 10 rounds  per gun  for every round  fired bythe Turks.     There will  be a gap in  the programme of reinforcements  of 8 days between 15thand 23rd October when  the  first  echelons  of the  mobilized divisions begin to  arrive.During this gap of 8  days, the Turks may attack  again ; and it  is unlikely  in thesituation now being visualised  that the  Chanak  force will be  able during that time toextend its position to the extent necessary to  cover the assembly of the whole InterimExpeditionary Force.  The Expeditionary Force, or a large proportion of it,  might there-fore have to land on Gallipoli, in which  case as  soon as  enough troops were available a preliminary operation  would  have  to be prepared  to capture  the  hill positions  BairakTepe Sirt  Tepe.     The above is a forecast of the course which the General  Staff consider events might take  if the  first Turkish defeat is  not very severe  and if they  continue to exercisepressure  on  our  troops.     It is cpiite possible,  however, that their first repulse might be so decisive as to enableGeneral Harington  to  use his earlier reinforcements  arriving  after 30th  September to enlarge his  position sufficiently to cover the assembly of an Expeditionary Force.  Inthis event the Expeditionary  Force could land at  Chanak, provided of course the passageof the  Straits can be used, and the next stage of: the operations would be accelerated.     6. FUTURE PROSPECTS  OE DRIVING THE TURKS OUT OP THE  NEUTRAL  ZONE                                  AND  HOLDING IT.     The second problem set to the General Staff is to appreciate the prospects of drivingthe Turkish forces back from the Chanak  position and re-establishing control  of theneutral zone when the  Expeditionary Force of 2  divisions  and a cavalry brigade has arrived.     It appears to the General  Staff that  this task would prove one of  extreme difficultyif the  Turks put up the obstinate resistance which experience teaches is to be  expected from them.    As already indicated, the roads in the ai*ea are few and  singularly bad, and areliable to become almost impassable during the rains which begin at the end  of  October.We shall have to rely very largely on pack transport, a form of  transport to which unitstrained in Great Britain are not accustomed, and which will deprive us of all our medium and heavy  artillery.    This  season  of  the year  will   be most unpropitious  for fieldoperations, and the hardships  to which the troops will be  subjected will be much moretrying to the British than to the Turks who are more or  less  inured to them.  They willalso probably resort after a time to guerilla tactics.    Taking into consideration all these disadvantages of season, topography and tactics,the General  Staff do not feel confident that a reinforcement of 2 divisions and a cavalrybrigade  would  suffice to  clear  the  neutral  zone of the  presence of Turkish troops.Even if they were successful, it would be necessary  to maintain a force  for an indefinite period along the line Ezine Baramich Bigha Kara Bigha, at a distance of some 30 miles-from their base,  to which they would be connected by roads and  tracks which would often be impassable.   The task of  guarding  this line  against the Turkish  Army would be beyond the power of three recently engaged divisions.     The  alternative  would  be  to come  back to some position approximating  to theoriginal  starting line, when  the Straits would again become  partly  exposed,  and the clearing process have to be clone all over again.     On the other hand, it is quite possible that the  Turks would not  consider  it worthwhile to defend their positions desperately against an advance in (orce, in which  case ifwe wanted to clear  the area temporarily  we could do so, but the task of guarding theEzine Bairamich Bh/ha Kara Bigha line in order to  keep the Straits secure againstincursions by the Turkish Army would still be too much for our forces.     The combined  Staff opinion on  what could be done by two divisions is containedin A. above.     7. The question of water for our forces on Gallipoli, which will probably be used asa subsidiary base&apos; and  for gun positions, is  not  a determining factor, as, from  enquiriesmade,  it is probable that it will be found  possible to station  the troops  in  places wherewater is obtainable, with the exception possibly of certain batteries., for which,  howevers
                                     APPENDIX  I.                              THE CHANAK  POSITION.                            (Reference Slap, Gallipoli 1/250,000.)      1.  GENERAL DESCRIPTION OF THE COUNTRY ON THE ASIATIC SHORE OF THE STRAITS.       From the low-lying country on the iEgean shore, and at the mouth of the Menderes   Chai, the ground rises gradually in  wooded slopes to Erenkeui  (10  miles  S.S.W.  of   Chanak).   The hills running  along  the shore of Erenkeui  Bay afford covered positions   for batteries shelling Helles and  the Straits.   Between Erenkeui and Masakeui (7  miles   north-east of Chanak) the country is cut up into  a series of ridges running generally   north-west  and south-east, varying in height from 120 to 350 feet.  Between these ridges   are  broad cultivated valleys down which run  river courses, most of which are dry in   summer.       Further east of Chanak and  Lapsaki, and from 8 to 12 miles distant, runs a range of   hills from 2,000  to 3,000 feet high, which dominate the  surrounding  country and from   which almost the whole of the  Straits is visible.       From  Masakeui to the Sea  of Marmora  the country is very hilly and enclosed, and   communications are difficult except by the coast road through Lapsaki.                                  2. THE CHANAK AREA.       Chanak is overlooked by the  surrounding hills, which form roughly  two  semi-   circles        (a)  The inner range consists of the low hills  forming the lower basin of the Koja              Chai, and this river divides the  area into two  portions.   In the  northern              portion Sirt Tepe is  the main feature, while Bairak Tepe (4 miles south-east              of Chanak) dominates the southern  sector.       (6)  The outer range is formed by the higher hills mentioned in paragraph 1 above.       North-east of Chanak the country is extremely broken and difficult.  Large  spurs   run down towards the Straits from the  hills  south and south-east of Bergaz, making it   almost impossible  to secure  a good  defensive  position between the Sirt Tepe and the   Tr upaldak river.   Beyond these  spurs  is the pronounced ridge running east and west   between the Yupaldak river and  Bergaz Chai,  and north of which  runs the Elleskeui     Subashkeui ridge.   These two ridges are more  open and contain larger features than the   spurs between Sirt Tepe and the Yupaldak river.                      3. EFFECT  OF  TOPOGRAPHY ON THE  DEFENCE.       From  the above description it will be evideiit that the selection of a defensive position   of reasonable length round Chanak is a  matter of extreme difficulty.       In order to protect the Narrows from the fire  of hostile field guns the possession of   the inner semi-circle of hills (vide 2 (a)) should  be denied to the enemy.  This  semi-   circle, shown in  red on the map,*  has a perimeter of  about 17 miles.   It must not be   assumed, however, that this is the line General Harington intends to hold.   We do not as\   yet know his plans.I                                      * Not attached.(377)Bspecial arrangements can be made.  The existing water  supply in  the  Chanak area willrequire improvement to make it adequate, but so far as enquiries have  gone there is noreason to think it will be impossible to make it fit and adequate for the forces which maybe sent there.     Owing to the limited wharf accommodation and cramped  nature of the position at chanak, it will certainly be necessary to establish a base on Gallipoli or at some placesuch as Mudros to accommodate drafts, ammunition and stores.     8. The unlikely  contingency of  the  Turks being  simultaneously in  a position to threaten Gallipoli from Thrace as well as Chanak on the  southern side of the Dardanelleshas not been considered in this  paper.     27th  September, 1922.
     Owing to the proximity o   Bairak Tepe to the Narrows, the southern flank of this-semi-circle should be extended to include  the high ground north-west of Kosakeui.  Afurther  extension  to  the Erenkeui  ridge  would  be more satisfactory, but would very greatly  increase the  defensive perimeter.   On  the  northern flank it  will probably  be advisable  to withdraw to the  neighbourhood  of Masakeui and Y^paldak, owing to the difficult nature of the country between Sirt Tepe and Y^paldak.     The main lines of advance on Chanak are by the five roads leading to the town fromErenkeui, Bairamich, Eski  Kirezeli, Baljilar  and  Lapsaki.   Of these,  the Erenkeui andLapsaki roads run along the coast and would  be exposed to direct fire  from the gallipoli peninsula and ships in the Straits.     The  defending force will be at a disadvantage as  regards gun positions, since thedefence is overlooked from all sides.   On the other hand, the conformation of the groundenables the attackers  to place their  guns in well  concealed  positions close up to thedefenders,  with excellent observation. And, owing to the steepness of the slopes, itwould be difficult  for the defence to deal with enemy batteries except with plunging fire from  howitzers  and attack  from the air.   For  this  reason it is unlikely that our  Navalguns, with their fiat trajectory, will be able to render great assistance in attacking hostileguns, but would be of considerable value  in firing on the plain which  surrounds Chanakin event of serious enemy attack, and in firing on the roads  by which  heavy guns  mightbe brought up.

</content>
</cab>
