<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 376-381</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
4S46 war BOOK (HEAR EAST) SUB-COMMITTEE.                SUB-CQMMITTEE ON CENSORSHIP.     The attached Draft Report of the above Sub-Committeeon the scale of censorship to be introduced in the&apos;eventof hostilities with the Turkish Nationalists  is circulated with, reference to Paper Number CP. -4244,                        (Signed)  M*P.A. HAHKEY,                           Secretary to the Cabinetsi2,  Whitehall Gardens, SoW0   30th September, 1922*document is THE PROPTY his BRITANNIC MAJ3STYfS GOVERNMENT
 CCMHIIESa  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCEcWar 3oo(Near East) Sub g Committee^  Sub^Oommitteo^on Censorship,OHAIHMMi      Etc. Oolo So Jo  Eowe^ DoSo0o,  O.B,E,,  War Office-,MEMBERS:       I-to Col, A, P.-. el..  Q,M*&amp;b,  Admiralty,               Wing Commander A4E0 Wynn.  Air Ministry*               Mr0 Sc  Gaselee, CcBoE,,  Foreign Qfficec               Mr, JoWo Hose, CoS,I0,  India Office0               Mr0 CoDe Oarew Rohinson,  Home Officer,               Mr0 J^EoH, Green,  Colonial Offices               Mr, J,-,  Flood,  Colonial  Office-,               Mr, MoEc Antrobus, Colonial Off 3.0 8 o               Mr. Jdo de Wardt, OJ,S,, General Post Office,               Mr,. WcEcG, Gabey,  General Post Office,               Mrc E,  Simon,  General Post Offices               Mro Po  Greenfield. General post Office0                   THE FOLLOWING  ALSO  ATTENDED i -               Colonel Sir Y0GoWo&apos; Eell,  ;C,B*Eo s CeB,               Colonel Lord Arthur Browno,  EoE0EoSecretaryCaptain WoH*W0 Smith, Me0.,,        War Officen
 ommend-ISLl-.     The Sub-Committee composed as shove met at p.m. on the 29th September, 1922,, at the War-&apos;Off ice&quot;&apos;toconsider to what extent if        nsorship would, berequired in tho United Kingdom, Overseas Possessions,Mandated Territories etc, in the event of hostilitiesw i t h the Turkish N? t i on Nationalists.     The deliberations of the Sub-Committee were limited to the consideration of what, would, be  necessary and possible in - the event: of orders, being given for themobilization of two divisions for operations in the near east,     The following questions were . examined, in  the : ordernamed              A. Cable Censorship              B. Radio Censorship              C, Postal Censorship              D. Press CensorshipA. CARLS CENSORSHIP.              -     The object of any cable censorship would  appear  to be  :.-      (l) to conceal troop movements,      (2) to isolate Turkey&apos;in Asia from West -and  North.      (3) to check -Pan-Islamic and. pro Turkish  propaganda.     With regard to (l) and  (2). which it is convenient to consider together, It -was decided that no measure  of cablecensorship would be effective as regards  leakage  of  informa-ti on regarding  troop movements unless such censorship &apos;&apos;wsspractically world wide, and  comprised a complete  system ofall round, censorship, including port  control.     The Colonial Office representative was moreover ofthe opinion that the Dominions would  object very  strongly toany complete  censorship which  would lpso-facto involveprohibition  of  tho use of  commercial  codes.     The Sub-Committee recommend therefore that no  cableCensorship should bo instituted in the United  Kingdom, but                           a power  should  hc^taken undor/Homo Secretary&apos;s Warrant                          -2-
-to stop selected messages-, for example messages  man a- tingfrom., or addressed -to- suspected persons,, or any messagesthat may he .dangerous to the  security of -the  State,          With regard to the  Mediterranean and the near east itself, the Admiralty representative was strongly of the opinion that a cable -censorship ,should be  set upin the Mediterranean and  the  Rod&apos; Sea in order thatmovements of troops by  sea dn this  area should be  concealedas far as possible.          The  Sub-Committee  examined this  question&apos;andre commend ^t hat t cable -oensorshlli^shoul^ be -instituted.....in gibraltar,;!.MalyaiVi Egypt.,and  Aden.           In  order to make  this-csble  censorship  as effective  as  possible,  it will be necessary.to cut Turkeyoff  from, cable  communications west and north, which willgive the additional advantage of driving her to an extended use  of wireloss: telegraphy,  which can beintercepted.           There are three means of.-carrying this  out   t-         (a)  to trust- the C-rook censorship......      (b)  to establish Britisli censorship  stations             on Greek territory at Lemnos and Syra,             and to cut  the Rhodes Cable.         (c)  to cut all  cables which land in Turkey, in             Asia, of these (a)  is out of the question;   (b)- is the most desirable from the Admiralty and War--Office  points of view but. the -Sub- Commit too understand that. the. Foreign Office have objections of a -political nature to this procedure, and are in favour of-procedure  (c).           &apos;The Sub-Committee feel - they  are unable to. come- to a - definite conclusion-on this point, which they recommend should be &quot;referred- for Cabinet, decision.
      The Subcommittee were of the opinion  thatthe Black Sea cables landing in - Coristan^inoT^^ti-ho^lxrbe out at the same time as a ction is taken in  regardto the Asia Miner cables; it being recognised  thatit will be -necessary to approach Roumania with regard^ tothe C o n s t a na - - C o n s t a n t i n o p1 e Cable . . &apos;      With; regard to (5) &quot;Propaganda&quot;, the IndiaOffice and Colonial Office  Representatives were strongly of the opinion that some measures would  have to be  takenin regard to possible Moslem unrest ih India and  EastAfrica,               -              , &apos; ,    &apos; &apos;. / .&apos;      -  ..&apos;      The Sub-Committee recommend that cable censor-ship should be instituted in India  and Zanzibar;B. RADIO CENSORSHIP.      The Sub - - G omm111 ee re c omm. e nd that&apos; measuressimilar to those of cables,  should &quot;be put intoforce in the case of Radio  telc/rraohy:   that is bo  say;that there should be wireless censorship at  Gibraltar;Malta , Egypt ^, Ad en, India and Zanz Mb a r &apos;.-      The Home Secretary!s  Warrant  iss\ie \  for  thepurpose of stopping selected cable messages  in theUnited Kingdom, will cover  messages of a similar  naturefor transmission by wireless.C* POSTAL CENSQRSHIP.      The Sub-&apos;committee are of  the  opinion that any measure of postal censorship is quite impracticable-,and recommend that none  should  be instituted except such control of mails for Asia Minor as may be  possible  in constantinople,-      The India Office. Representative considered thatexamination of selected  correspondence in India will  benecessary&apos;.&quot;&apos; &apos; Nosuch examination  is  considered necessary at Zanzibar,,
                      If postal and telegraphic  communication, is  to               be stopped with Turkey the General  Post  Office will               require s definition -of  the area affected.,.               D. PRESS -&apos;-CENSORSHIP.                      The Sub--Commit tee  consider the  best  way of               ensuring that no  undesirable.matter is published  .               in the press in Great Britain,,  is to  set up a special               press  Committee composed of representatives of the               -Admiralty, War Office and Air Ministry which could               maintain close relations with the press,.                      It is recommended.that the &quot;Admiralty, War  Office               and  Press Committee&quot;  should meet at.once in order               to ascertain the  views of the press on  this proposal.commendation       .    The Sub-Committee  re commend that  this special  77      7               7 77        1              .....               Press  , Commit tee  should ho set up&apos; with as little^ delay               as possible^ and  should  commence to function even before               any  mobilisation  orders  are  issued..                                  (-Signed), W.H.W. &apos; Smith,                                            Captain                                            Secretary.

</content>
</cab>
