<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 382-384</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AjW-this DOCUMENT  IB THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT&apos;&apos;)0.P- 424.7,              CAB I N E To            THE__GREEK.  ARMY,NOTE BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR,        I circulate a note en the Greek Army prepared bythe General Staff.(Initialled) LnWmE.1 War  Office,-    30th  September,  1922.      Note on the Greek Army,  3.0th September 1922*   2i&apos;f A note was written  on  the  Greek Army an the 27thSeptember.   Since then,;  telegrams dealing with this subjecthave been received from the:General Off!cer Commanding-in-Chief. Constantinople,, and from  the Military Attache j  Athena:-it therefore becomes necessary to  review  the&quot; situation in-the light of these telegrams.-   2C The arrangement given  below  deals.separately with eachGreek formation that existed prior to the recent operabionsin Anatolia.   The following information  has been received&apos; i-(a), G,H.3QoThe original :G&apos;..H.Q,.,&apos; was evacuated- to Athens ,but it is understood that  a new G*H*Q,formed at Rodostov,ng(b)  3rd. Corps.(3rd Division of 3 regiments&apos;..(10th Division, of 3 Regiments n(Remnants of 11th Division and of 4        Independent Regiments..4th Corps.  (Adrianople Division of  3 Regiments-&apos;,DivisionRegime: b,s                 (6th Division of  3 Regime&apos;nts                -(also 2  Independent Regiments r.      These two  corps occupy the  front  Silivri-Cherkess&apos;Keui-Midia, in addition  to watching the Bulgarian  frontier andperforming police duties in Eastern Thrace, east of  the maritza.      As regards guns., the 4th Corps has always had.  68,, and none -of these would have, been lost in the  recent operations.&apos;The Military Attache, Athens, reports 3 batteries  of 6;?howitzers and. 6 batteries of field artillery, making a  totalof 36 pieces and-i pending the receipt of further information,it must be assumed, that  this,is all&quot;that remains in  the 3rd -Corps o   The total number ,of guns and. howitzers with the3rd and. 4th Corps would  therefore appear to be I04t,
    The Military Attache, Athens, reports that  the&quot;ration,strength of these two Corps is about 50,000,  their riflestrength being about 20,0000   These figures  are con-firmed by G,H..Qa, Constantinople-,     The Greek General Staff admit that the morale of thesetwo corps fell after the collapse in Anatolia,  but believethat there has now been some improvementa  The Britishliaison officer with the 3rd Corps reports, however, thatthe troops &quot;are incapable of offering organised resistance-tance at present, but should improve u   Colonel Condllis,the Venizclist organiser in Constantinopler is  reportedto have stated, on his return from a visit to the troopsthat &quot;if the Turks reached Thrace, nothing would stop the Greeks running hut the Gulf of Corinth&quot;e(c)    The Independent DLvi. sionjof 3 regiments *       This Division became separated from the  2nd GreekCorps in the neighbourhood of Uskak, and after  severalengagements reached Aivali. whence it was shipped to salonika, practically intact0   The Military Attache,Athens, reports that it amounts to a ration strengthof 8/Mc.Kenna .and that the Greeks report its morale  good.Our secret service reports&apos;., on the other hand,  that  itis discontented;- and Is gradually breaking up0    It  isreported to have 12&quot; - 6  Skoda gunse(d)    2nd Division and remnants jof 1st, 5th. 7th Divisions^-       The 2nd Division appears to be more or less corapleteaIt was not heavily engaged during the operations^ and hasrecently been brought from the islands to support therevolution at Athens,   There are also 2 regiments of cavalry and 8 guns in Athenso   Little is know of the remnants of the other three divisions^,.,, but it is unlikelythat they will be of further use ex^?/m supplying draftsto Thracec   The Military Attache reports that  the morale of the 2nd Division and artillery seems good, but that thatof the remainder is low, though likely to conform to thatof the 2nd. Division^(e)    The &quot;Alpha&quot; 4th, 9th, .12 and 15th Divisions.       The Alpha Division was sent as a reinforcement toSmyrna from Thrace early in the month, but on arrival.there the troops refused to disembark, although they hadnot been near the fighting0.   They were finally shippedto tho island of Tha-sos &quot;as a disciplinary measure&quot;.       The 4th and 9th Divisions reached Smyrna In dis-.order,, with heavy losses of guns and personnel, and wereshipped to Ehios and other islandso      The 12th and 13th Divisions were almost destroyed during the fighting in the Murad Dagh, only remnants reachedthe coast,-whence they were shipped to the islands.5      The Military Attache., Athens, estimates the totalof Greeks troops in the islands at about 15,000, and addsthat their morale Is unreliable, but dependent upon thesuccess of tho Revolution at Athens..
     3.  The following measures have already been taken forthe re-organization of the army :-(a)      They are. demobilizing all but 4 animal classes:&apos;(b)      They have called up the new (.1923) class.         The new Revolutionary Government propose to confirm(b),.&apos; and to recall two or more of the younger classes which areat present being demobilized.  .-           .         The Greek General Staff propose to complete theIndependent Division and to form two or more new divisions fromthe other remnants, and. to send them to Eastern Thrace.   Thiswould raise, the Greek rifle strength in Thrace to 36,GOOrifles.         It seems probable that they will encounter much difficulty in carrying out these proposals, and G.H.Q,Constantinople, estimate that it will take 3 months for th&amp;i toproduce an efficient force in Thrace on these lines.   The 1923class is at present totally untrained.     4.-  As regards artillery, it Is believed that enoughmountain and field guns exist for 3 Army Corps (on the normalscale for Greek units), but there is a great shortage of medium artillery.   The Military Attache,- Athens, reports that1,000 rounds a gun for this artillery is Immediately available.         The.Greek General Staff believe that a sufficiency oftransport exists.     5*  Colonel Hoaro Nai-rne sums up the situation as follows         irMy own impression is that at the present moment.-everything is fluid and nothing certain Can be predicted abeutmorale.   Original idea of revolution was to. strengthen; -Thracian front but it is not  certain that this- idea will      -continue to predominate.   Nevertheless I still consider thata  serious Greek army would be available if fighting for definiteobject, and fully-supported by Great Britain.-1&apos;         Lieut en-ant-General Sir Charles Harington sums It -upas follows .:-               ...         &quot;I am afraid I have no more faith,in greek army and I think/to1 pin.co any reliance whatever in it  wouldbe most unwise.&quot;         Elth these opinions  before them, the General Staffconsider it certain that, even if the. morale of the army andnation is to some  extent regenerated by the call  of Thracethe  formation of an efficient Greek army must be  a matter ofsome months..-3r-General Staff.     30th September, .1922.

</content>
</cab>
