<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 654-687</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS Britannic MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)QNFIDEHTIAL.P. 4275,   CABINET..LEAGUE  OP  NATIONS.REDUCTION OP ARMAMENTS.1,    Report of the Third Committee to the Third Assembly,2.    Resolutions adopted by the Assembly at its meeting      on Wednesday, September 27th, 1922a(Circulated with reference to C*Pc4212)Whitehall Gardens, S.W.   12th October, 1922,
  [Communique au Conseil, aux Membres de la Societeet aux Delegues a 1&apos;Assemblee.]A. 124.1922. IX. [A. III. 17. 1922.]                                    Geneve,                                       le 22 septembre 1922.               Societe des NationsREDUCTION   DES   ARMEMENTS                 RAPPORTDE LA TROISIEME COMMISSION A LA TROISIEME ASSEMBLEE           Rapporteur : Lord Robert CECIL               League of NationsREDUCTION   OF   ARMAMENTS               REPORTOF THE THIRD COMMITTEE TO THE THIRD ASSEMBLY         Rapporteur : Lord Robert CECIL
TABLE DES MATlERES                                                                                 page introduction . . . . .  ...  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  ... .  .................     3I.  DIVERS:         1. Limitation des defenses nationales en armements .............     4         2. Enquete statistique.......................  .  .     4         3. Excedents de stocks de munitions...................     5         4. Fabrication privee des armes.....................     5         5. Trafic des armes...........................     6         6. Guerre chimique................... ........     7         7. Exposes des gouvernements sur les exigences de leur securite  nationale ...     8         8. Echange de renseignements......................     9         9. Conference de Washington.......................     9        10. Conference pan-americaine de Santiago................. .     9II.   REDUCTION DES  ARMEMENTS NAVALS...................v.     10III.  REDUCTION DES ARMEMENTS TERRESTRES ET AERIENS..............     10IV.  TRAITE DE GARANTIE MUTUELLE.......................     11V.  ACCORDS REGIONAUX POUR LA REDUCTION DES ARMEMENTSVI. CONCLUSIONS GENERALES...............1313
SOGIETE DES  NATIONSREDUCTION   DES  ARMEMENTSRapport de la troisieme Commission  a la troisieme Assemblee.                   Rapporteur: Lord Robert CECIL.INTRODUCTION.     La troisieme Commission de l&apos;Asscmblee a tenuneuf seances toutes consacrees a la discussion de la reduction des armements. Los deliberations de la Commission se sont fondees sur les conclu- sions qui lui ont ete fournies par le rapport dela Commission temporaire mixte nommee par le Conseil sur la proposition de la premiere Assemblee afin de k preparer pour soumission au Conseil... toutes etudes et propositions sur la question de la reduction des armements n. Conformement a la  resolution  adoptee par 1&apos;Assemblee  1&apos;annee derniere, le  Conseil a renforce la Commission temporaire mixte en mars 1922, en lui adjoignant sept membres supplementaires specialement qualifies pour cette tache. Depuis la derniere Assemblee, la Commission temporaire mixte a tenu trois sessions et a realise des progres considerables dans 1&apos;etude des questions dont elle s&apos;cst occupee. Sur certains points, elle a abouti a  des conclusions precises qu&apos;elle recommande a 1&apos;Assemblee de bien  vouloir adopter. Sur certains autres, elle a pose des principes generaux et suivi des directives d&apos;apres lesquelles elle espere  etre  bientot en mesure de presenter au Conseil et a  1&apos;Assemblee un plan concret.     Les progres realises dans cette  voie ont amene la troisieme Commission a penser qu&apos;il y aurait tout  avantage a ce que le Conseil prorogeat d&apos;une annee les fonctions dela Commission temporaire mixte.  Elle  voudrait, d&apos;autre  part, insister  sur  la necessite pour la  Commission temporaire mixte de  presenter ses propositions en temps utile et  permettre ainsi a la prochaine Assemblee de deliberer avec  profit sur  ce probleme complexe et particuiierement important.  En meme temps, la troisi me Commission desire suggerer qu&apos;il conviendrait que la Commission temporaire mixte fut tenue davantage au courant des vues des gouvernements Membres de la Societc4. Elle ne suggere pas 1&apos;adjonction a la Commission de representants des gouvernements, mais elle estime qu&apos;il y aurait avantage a ce que le Conseil invitat les Membres de la Societe des Nations a assurer a la Commission temporaire mixte 1&apos;aide et la cooperation la plus etroite de la part de  leurs depar-. tements militaires arm  que des renseignements, des opinions et meme  des critiques  autorisees viennent faciiiter son travail.  La troisieme Commission estime qu&apos;il importe tout specialement que les gouvernements soient invites a soumettre toutes les observations qu&apos;ils jugeraient oppor- tunes, et notamment a presenter des suggestions sur les principes de la reduction des armements terrestres  enonces par la Commission ainsi que sur le projet de traite de gaiantie mutuelle dont  il est question ci-apres. Pour ces motifs, la troisieme Commission recommande a 1&apos;Assemblee 1&apos;adop- tion de la resolution suivante:              II est desirable que la Commission temporaire mixte soit invitee a poursuivre, pen-         dan t une annee encore, les travaux qu&apos;elle a entrepris, et qu&apos;elle presente  son rapport.         en temps utile avant la prochaine  Assemblee. L&apos;Assemblee charge en outre le Conseil         d&apos;inviter  les Membres de la Societe a  prefer tout leur appui a la Commission dans sa         tache  difficile et a lui donner  avis et assistance en ce qui concerne les projets de desar-         mement terrestre et le traite de garantie mutuelle.)         - :.:^La troisieme Commission tient a signaler la valeur particuliere qu&apos;elle  attache a la          collaboration qui a toujours existe entre la Commission temporaire mixte et la Commission          permanente consultative et a exprimer le vceu que  cette collaboration se poursuive et          devienne, si  possible, plus etroite encore. Elle estime que la competence technique de          la Commission permanente consultative  est  indispensable a 1&apos;etude du point de vue          technique militaire,  naval et  aerien, des questions dont s&apos;occupe la G. T.  A.    S. d. N. 150+150+2100 A. 9/23. Imp. Kumlig^
I. DIVERSi.  LIMITATION DES DEPENSES NATIONALES RELATIVES AUX AKMEMENTS.    A sa deuxieme  session, 1&apos;Assembled a adopte la resolution suivante:             Sous reserve des conditions y enoncees, la recommandation de la premiere Assem-         blee, tendant a ce que les Membres de la Societe sdngagent a ne pas depasser, au  cours         des  deux prochaines annees financieres, la somme totale  de leurs depenses militaires,         navales et aeriennes prevues au budget de la presente anned, sera de nouveau transmise         a tous les Menibres de la Societe, ainsi qu&apos;un releve des reponses a cette recommanda-         tion  qui sont deja  parvenues.    Le Conseil ayant fait sienne cette resolution, le Secretaire general ecrivit a tous les membres de la  Societe,  le 17 Janvier 1922, en leur envoyant une copie de la recommandation et un relevedes reponses revues a cette date par le Secretariat. Comme suite a cette communication, un grandnombre de gouvernements ont envoye de nouvelles reponses. En vue d&apos;une meilleure utilisationdes precieux  renseignements  contenus  dans ces reponses,  la  Commission  temporaire niixte  adresse des tableaux  speciaux qui permettent de se rendre un compte plus exact  des conclusionsgenerales que Ton peut. en tirer. Apies avoir mis ces renseignements sous forme de tableaux, etapres les avoir attentivement examines, la Commission temporaire mixte a abouti aux conclu-sions  suivantes:              a) Dans 1&apos;ensemble, les previsions budgetaires pour la defense nationale, pour 1&apos;anned         financiere 1922 (ou 1922-1923)  accusent une reduction par rapport aux depenses effec-         tives des deux annees financieres prededentes.              b)  Toutefois, il y a lieu, pour r appreciation de cette reduction, de tenir  compte du         fait que depuis Tanned 1920 il s&apos;est produit,  dans beaucoup de pays interesses, une reduc-         tion  des  charges de  guerre resultant  des operations  de demobilisation et d&apos;une baisse         sensible du prix des matieres.    La troisieme Commission est en complet accord avec la Commission temporaire  mixte surcette  question, et  elle a decide de faire  siennes les conclusions citeds ci-dessus. Toutefois, elle aestime qu&apos;il etait possible, pour 1&apos;Assemblee, de s&apos;engager, dans cette direction,  plus avant qu&apos;ellene 1&apos;avait fait en 1921. En consequence,  sur la motion de M. de Jouvenel, delegue de la France,et sans diminuer  en rien la  ported cles vceux precedents  sur  cette  question  elle propose  a1&apos;Assemblee la resolution suivante:             L&apos;Assemblee  emet le  voeu que,  pour  commencer,  les  Etats europedns  existant         avant la guerre de  1914 sous leur denomination actuelle, dont cette guerre n&apos;a pas modi-         fie le statut juridique et  qui ne se trouvent pas,  a 1&apos;lieure actuelle, engages dans des         operations  militaires qui justifient leurs armements,  soient invites a ramener le  total         de leurs depenses militaires, navales et aeriennes aux chiffres de 1913 calcules sur la base         des  prix  d&apos;avant-guerre, suivant  la mcthode employee par la Commission  temporaire         mixte.                                  2. ENQUETE STATISTIQUE.    La Commission  croit qu&apos;il est de son devoir cTexprimer  toute sa gratitude a la Sous-Commis-sion de statistique de la Commission temporaire uiixte, ainsi qu&apos;au  Secretariat  de la Societe pour la facon dont  la Sous-Commission et le Secretariat ont rnene a bien les enquetes statistiques deci-dees par P Assembled lors de ses sessions anterieures. Les resultats obtenus jusqu&apos;ici dans cettevoie presentent une  valeur considerable et rceuvre de centralisation et de coordination des statis-artistiques a ete accomplie avec beaucoup cFingeniosite et de soin.    Le programme primitif  de ldnquete semblait impliquer  une comparaison entre 1913  et 1921.Certaines de ces investigations ont done ete effectuees sur la  base hypothetique d&apos;une Europe tellequdlle aurait  ete constituee  si ses frontieres geographiques actuelles avaient existe avant la guerre.Une evaluation  de cette nature ne  peut  naturellement pas avoir de valeur pratique pour les tra-vaux  ulterieurs de la Commission temporaire mixte.  La Commission suggere done que les recher-ches statistiques soient poursuivies sur la base des chiffres  bruts relatifs aux conditions  existantactuellement,  quitte a decider pour Tavenir les methodes  a suivre pour leur mise en valeur.    II ressort du rapport de la Commission temporaire rnixte  quelle a maintenant besoin de sevoir indiquer  par 1&apos;Assemblee les directives qui doivent guider ses futurs travaux. Ces directives,la Commission croit  qudn peut les trouver dans la pensed  qui a inspire, des le debut, ldnquetestatistique.                                                                               I    II s&apos;agit, en somme, d&apos;une etude preliminaire appelee a contribuer a la preparation d&apos;un plan-general de reduction des armements. Ce plan lui-meme doit s&apos;inspirer de 1&apos;article 8 du Pacte, lequelreconnait 1&apos;importance primordiale  que presente en cette matiere la sedurite nationale. Ainsi qu&apos;ilressort des exposes recus des differents Etats, la securite nationale de chaque pays depend en grandepartie de la puissance militaire integrale ddutres pays.  cest done  cette puissance militaire inte-grale  qui devrait faire Tobjet de ldnquete statistique. Elle  comprend deux  elements:
     i0 La puissance militaire actuelle qui se reftete dans les armements du temps de paix et dans les depenses relatives a la defense nationale;     2&quot; La puissance militaire potentielle oil entre pour  une grande part le pouvoir industriel et economique de chaque Etat, dont la derniere guerre a prouve l&apos;importance au point de vue militaire.     A cet egard done, les additions suggerees par la Commission temporaire mixte  au programmeV/e la partie economique de sonenquete, semblent pleinement justiftees. II est douteux, cependant, que le moment soit venu de se livrer a cette derniere partie de 1&apos;enquete, et, tout en reconnaissant qu&apos;il serait peut-etre utile d&apos;envisager pour 1&apos;avenir rextension des etudes statistiques dans ce sens, la Commission estime devoir limiter, pour le moment, ienquete statistique aux deux ele- merits principaux qui expriment la puissance militaire du temps de  paix, c&apos;est-a-dire: les  arme- ments et les budgets.     La  Commission se permet done de soumettre a 1&apos;approbation de  1&apos;Assemblee les propositions suivantes:              La Commission  exprime sa satisfaction  pour 1&apos;effort  remarquable  accompli  dans         la reunion et  1&apos;elaboration des donnees statistiques clans un domaine tout nouveau et         particulierement  difficile.              Tenant compte du travail accompli et reservant la question de savoir quelle por-         tee il pourrait etre necessaire de donner plus tard a 1&apos;etude statistique, la  Commission         desire fixer, pour 1&apos;annee a venir, le programme  qui  lui parait immediatement utile et         pratiquement realisable.  Elle  propose done que le  programme soit  limite aux deux         points suivants:              1.  Armement du temps de paix.              2.  Depenses d&apos;armements.              II serait desirable que le Conseil priat la Commission permanente consultative de         bicn vouloir apporter a la Commission temporaire  mixte sa collaboration pour la partie         technique militaire, navale et aerienne de cette enquete.                                  3. STOCKS EN EXCEDENT.      Le Conseil avait invite la Commission permanente consultative a examiner la question  de la destruction  eventuelle des surplus de stocks de munitions, en raison du caractere technique de cette question.      Apres un examen approfondi, la Commission  permanente consultative concluait ainsi son rapport:              K En resume, la Commission constate que la question a deja ete resolue par les divers          pays interesses,  et que les stocks en surplus qui, sans doute, existaient a la fin  de la          guerre mondiale, ont ete, durant  les trois annees et  demie qui se sont  coulees depuis,          detruits,  ou liquides, ou sont en cours de liquidation n.      Et la Commission temporaire apres avoir pris connaissance dudit rapport, presentait les conclu- sions suivantes adoptees par le Conseil le 20 juillet 1922 :              a La  Commission temporaire  a pris acte du  rapport cle la Commission permanente          consultative et note les mesures satisfaisantes prises par les differents Etats en vue de la          liquidation de ces stocks. Cette question se trouve, en fait, reglee conformement aux ctesirs          cle  la deuxieme Assemblee a,      Toutcfois, il faut observer que la Commission permanente consultative avait tres justement note que le danger que pourraient presenter des stocks de munitions ou de materiel de guerre, s&apos;il en existait encore,  proviendrait non pas de leur existence meme entre les mains de gouvernements responsables, mais de la circulation sans controle de ce materiel dans le monde. D&apos;ou  1&apos;interet cVaboutir a  un controle du trafic des armes.      La troisieme  Commission recommande done 1&apos;adoption de la resolution suivante:              L&apos;Assemblee, apres avoir  examine  le rapport de la Commission temporaire mixte          estime que la seule mesure pratique qu&apos;il y a lieu de prendre au sujet des stocks d&apos;armes          et  de munitions  en excedent consiste a etablir un controle du trafic international  des          armes.                                   4. FABRICATION PRIVEE.      Lors de sa session de 1921, 1&apos;Assemblee fut saisie d&apos;un rapport detaille prepare par  les soins de la Commission temporaire mixte, sur la question de la fabrication privee des armes. Ce rapportfpxposait les facheux effets resultant de la fabrication privee des armes, et presentait certaines suggestions&apos;d&apos;un cara.ctere general sur la facon de remedier a ces  consequences fatbeuses. A cette date, la Commission temporaire mixte n&apos;a prcsente aucune conclusion generale sur le point, cle savoir s&apos;il est possible ou opportun cVinterdire d&apos;une facon absolne la fabrication privee. Toutefois; elle faisait ressortir la grande difficulte que presente 1&apos;interdiction absolue et suggerait qu&apos;il serait peut-etre  plus pratique d&apos;arriver a controler strictement la fabrication privee, sans avoir recours
a. 1&apos;interdiction absolue.  La Commission  temporaire  mixte proposait egalement la  convocationd&apos;une conference destinee a elaborer une convention internationale sur la question, et offrait de secharger elle-meme de la preparation d&apos;un projet de convention qui pourrait etre examine a cetteconference.  Pour assurer le succes cle cette conference, elle  ajoutait qu&apos;il etait necessaire  d&apos;yinviter tous les Etats qui ne sont pas Membres de la Societe.    La Commission temporaire mixte sigjiala.it, en outre, que quelles que soient les  mesures  qugfcl&apos;on pourrait prendre relativement a  1 &quot;interdiction ou au controle de la fabrication privee, Feta&quot;blissement d&apos;un controle strict  du trafic. international des armes et Pobligation absolue de clonnera ces: transactions la plus grande publicite, contribueraient en une  large mesure a  abolir  d&apos;unefacon effective les facheux effets resultant de la fabrication privee. La Commission rccommandaitdone instamment la mise en vigueur, a la date la plus prcche possible, de la Convention de Saint-Germain sur le trafic des armes.    Toutefois, depuis la derniere Assemblee, la Convention de Saint-Germain n&apos;a pas  encore etemise en vigueur. En outre, la Commission temporaire mixte a rencontre, a Felaboration d&apos;un projetde convention, des difficultes plus considerables qu&apos;elle ne Pavait prevu; aussi le Conseil n&apos;a-t-ilpas convoque la  Conference internationale proposee.    Cette annee, a sa derniere session, la Commission temporaire mixte a adopte une propositionprecise, en vue de placer sous controle les societes privees qui s&apos;occupent de la fabrication des armes,et elle a suggere que cette proposition pourrait servir de base aux travaux de la Conference pro-posee. La troisieme Commission partage Popinion de la Commission  temporaire mixte et proposeque cette derniere  soit  charged de developper  la proposition qu&apos;elle a adoptee, sous forme d&apos;unprojet de convention, et qu&apos;au  moment propice le Conseil convoque une conference internationalepour  examiner ce projet. Toutefois, comme il est a souhaiter que cette Conference s&apos;occupe ausside la question du trafic des armes, il est evident qu&apos;elle ne peut etre convoquee tant qu&apos;il n&apos;aurapas ete convenu  d&apos;un programme precis de mesures a prendre relativement au trafic des armes. L&apos;Assemblee ne peut done que se bonier a inviter le Conseil a convoquer la Conference, au momentqu&apos;iljugera opportun. En consequence, la troisieme Commission propose la resolution suivante:             L&apos;Assemblee ayant pris acte de la proposition de  la Commission  temporaire  mixte         relative a un accord international sur  le controle de la fabrication privee, prie le Conseil         d&apos;examiner s&apos;il est opportun de convoquer a une date rapproched une conference des         Membres de la Societe des Nations pour donner a cet accord la forme  d&apos;une convention.         L&apos;Assemblee estime d&apos;autre part que les Etats qui ne sont pas Membres de la Societe         des Nations devraient etre invites a prendre part a cette Conference et a collaborer  a la         politique qu&apos;elle pourrait adopter.                                   5. TRAFIC DES  ARMES.    1. Le trafic international des armes fait depuis longtemps 1&apos;objet d&apos;un examen de la. partdes gouvernements. Des 1887, un certain nombre de Puissances ont conclu une convention rela-tive a la question. Le sujet fut de nouveau traite a la Conference de la Paix, a Paris, et une nouvelleconvention destinee a remplacer celle de  1887 fut rediged et signee  par les Etats qui participerenta&apos;la Conference.    Depuis cette epoque,  la question a ete examinee par la Commission permanente consultativeet par la Commission temporaire mixte aux deux premieres sessions de F Assembled de la Societeet a plusieurs sessions du Conseil. II a ete reconnu chaque fois qu&apos;il est du plus grand interet pour la civilisation que le trafic international  des armes soit soumis a un controle  par un accord inter-national.    II est inutile de developper les raisons de cette opinion. Tous les membres de 1&apos;Assemblee ontconscience des scandales honteux auxquels a  donne lieu le trafic des armes.    2. La Convention sur le trafic des armes signee a Saint-Germain en septembre 1919, repondaitaux deux objets suivants:    a): Elle avait pour but ddmpecher Fimportation des armes, sauf sous le controle le plus strictpossible, dans certaines regions definies, habitees par des peuples arrieres. L&apos;objet de cette sectiondu Traite est evident. La  tache cPeviter  les effusions de sang dans de vastes  regions  de 1&apos;Afriqueet. dans les  pays qui  bordent la Mer Rouge sera rendue  beaucoup plus difficile si les habitantspeuvent se procurer des armes et des munitions en quantites illimiteds. On jugea qu&apos;il importaitavant tout de mettre immediatement en vigueur cette partie de la Convention, afin ddmpecherque les excedents de stocks restant  de la guerre ne sdparpillent dans ces regions du monde.    b) La Convention avait pour second objet cFassurer par un systeme de licences, une publicitegenerale au ti-afic internationale des armes. Lessignatairesdela Convention s&apos;engageaient a nduto-riser Pexportation des armes hors de leurs territoires que sous reserve d&apos;une licence  clelivree parles autorites gouvernementales, oil seraient  indiquees les quantites autorisees pour F exportationet le pays de destination.  .    La Convention stipulait en outre que copies  de ces  licences  devraient etre immediatementcommuniqueds a un office central, qui serait etabli sous les auspices de la Societe, et qudlles seraientpublieds. On estime qu&apos;en donnant ainsi une publicite complete au trafic des armes, on pourrait %au moins arriver a supprimer quelques-uns des facheux effets qui  en resultent.    La Convention de Saint-Germain a  ete redigee dans Fided qu&apos;elle serait accepted universelle-ment par les gouvernements de tous les pays. Sans doute,  il  importe avant tout cle s&apos;assurer lacooperation des pays qui  fabriquent des arrnes et des munitions, mais il n&apos;en est pas moins clcsi-rable de voir tous les pays, qu&apos;ils fabriquent ou non ces armes, adherer a cette Convention.
                                    6.  GUERRE CHIMIQUE.     Lors de sa derniere session, 1&apos;Assemblee avait propose que la Commission temporaire mixte, instituat une enquete en vue de savoir s&apos;il y aurait quelque utilite pratique a inviter les savants des diverses nations du monde a publier leurs decouvertes dans le domaine de la chimie appliquee a la guerre. On estimait que cette proposition, s&apos;il pouvait y etre donne suite, serait de nature a reduire le danger d&apos;une utilisation des decouvertes dans un but degression militaire.     La  Commission  temporaire mixte, cependant, apres avoir etudie attentivement la question, est arrivee a la conclusion qu&apos;une telle invitation ne pourrait avoir aucun resultat utile. La Corn- mission est&quot; egalement tombee d&apos;accord pour estimer que des conventions interdisant 1&apos;emploi des gaz en temps de guerre peuvent avoir une grande valeur morale, mais que les stipulations d&apos;un traite, quel qu&apos;il soit, ne peuvent  empecher avec certitude la preparation secrete de la guerre chi- mique. II n&apos;y a que trop de raisons de craindre, apres l&apos;experience de la derniere guerre, qu&apos;un pays qui combat pour son existence ne fasse usage de toutes les armes qu il lui sera possible d&apos;employerI utilement.  II est done necessaire, quelque regrettable que cela puisse etre, de prevoir que,  dans le cas oil une nouvelle guerre eclaterait, les armes chimiques seront employees.     La Commission  est profondement impressionnee par la nature terrible des resultats de l&apos;em- ploi de  telles armes. Depuis la fin des hostilites, de tres grands progres ont ete realises au point de vue des decouvertes chimiques susceptibles d&apos;etre appliquees a la guerre.     Le  progres dans  la fabrication des bombes  d&apos;aeroplanes n&apos;a pas ete moins remarquable. Les effets des bombes les plus puissantes employees pendant la derniere guerre seraient conside- rablement depasses  par ceux que Ton obtiendrait aujourd&apos;hui.                                          - 7 -    3. Lorsque  fut  signee la Convention de Saint-Germain, les  principales parties au Traitesignerent egalement un protocole supplementaire, par lequel elles s&apos;engageaient a mettre ses dis-positions immediatement en application, sans en attendre la ratification omcielle. Malheureuse-pent, ce protocole ne fut pas suivi d&apos;effet, sauf chez quelques-uns des principaux signataires, et:eulement dans les regions arrierees mentionnees plus haut. Depuis lors, de grands efforts ont etefaits en vue de mettre la Convention en vigueur. Lors des deux sessions anterieures de 1&apos;Assembleede la Societe, des resolutions tres energiques ont ete votees demandant selon les cas, aux gouverne-ments des Membres de la Societe et des Etats hors de la Societe, soit de ratifier la convention, soit d&apos;yadherer. Le Conseil de la Societe a adresse un certain nombre de lettres aux gouvernements pour les inviter a mettre a effet la resolution de 1&apos;Assemblee. En reponse a ces communications, trente-quatre gouvernements ont jusqu&apos;a  present exprime leurs vues sur la question. Parmieux,  onze onteffectivement ratifie  la Convention et quatre autres ont exprime leur intention d&apos;y  adherer. Lereste, y compris toutes les principales Puissances signataires,  sauf les Etats-Unis  d&apos;Amerique,ainsi que les autres Etats  qui fabriquent des armes et  des munitions,  ont exprime leur intentionde ratifier la Convention lorsque tous les autres Etats fabriquant des armes seraient disposes ale faire. Quant a 1&apos;Allemagne et a 1&apos;Autriche, pays jadis grands producteurs d&apos;armes, ils se  trouventmaintenant lies, conformement  aux dispositions des Traites de Paix, par la Convention de Saint-Germain.    II semblait done qu&apos;apres  trois ans d&apos;efforts continus, le Conseil et 1&apos;Assemblee pouvaientraisonnablement esperer que la Convention de Saint-Germain allait etre mise a effet  d&apos;une fagongeherale et sans retaixl appreciable. Le 28 juillet 1922,  cependant, le Departement d&apos;Etat  des etats-Unis adressait  au Secretaire general une communication dans laquelle il 1&apos;informait que leGouvernement  des Etats-Unis se trouvait dans 1&apos;impossibilite d&apos;approuver les dispositions de la convention ou de donner aucune  assurance au sujet de sa ratification. Cette reponse mit fin a1&apos;espoir que la Convention de Saint-Germain, sous sa forme actuelle, serait acceptee  d&apos;une fagongenerale.    4. Comme nous 1&apos;avons deja dit, il importe au plus haut point qu&apos;une convention soit univer-sellement acceptee, en vue du controle du trafic international des armes, et que tous les pays civi-lises cooperent aux memes mesures de reglementation.    Ceci depend cependant de 1&apos;attitude des Etats-Unis d&apos;Amerique.  II importe done que les membres de la Societe s&apos;efforcent de toutes les facons possibles, de donner satisfaction a  1&apos;opijriondu Gouvernement des Etats-Unis et de s&apos;assurer sa cooperation dans une action commune. dans la lettre qu&apos;il adressait, le 28 juillet, au Secretaire general, le Departement d&apos;Etat des Etats-Unisdeclarait que a le Gouvernement des Etats-Unis est en cordiale sympathie avec les efforts accomplispour limiter le trafic  des armes et des munitions de guerre... )) et qu&apos;il K etait desireux de coopereraux efforts faits pour controler effectivement le trafic a; nous avons done de bonnes  raisons d&apos;es-perer qu&apos;il est  encore possible  d&apos;arriver a quelque accord pour une  action commune,  entre les membres de la Societe et les Etats-Unis.    En consequence, la Commission propose que 1&apos;Assemblee vote les resolutions suivantes :             1. II est  hautement desirable que  le  Gouvernement des Etats-Unis  exprime les        objections qu&apos;il a a formuler contre les dispositions de la Convention de Saint-Germain,        ainsi que les propositions  qu&apos;il pourrait desirer faire sur la fagon dont il serait possible        de lever ces objections.             2.  La Commission temporaire mixte  devrait etre chargee d&apos;elaborer  un  nouveau         pro jet de controle du trafic international des armes. Ce projet pourrait etre  examine         par la meme conference que celle qui doit traiter de la fabrication privee des armes.             3.  L&apos;Assemblee prie le Conseil de prendre telles mesures qu&apos;il jugera oppcrtunes         pour atteindre les buts vises ci-dessus.
    La Commission estime qn&apos;il est d&apos;une importance vitale pour les peuples du monde entier debien comprendre le probleme  qui se pose devant eux et, dans ce but, la Commission Temporairemixte a decide de nommer une sous-commission pour etudier le developpement de la guerre chimiqueet preparer un rapport sur ses effets probables  au cours d&apos;une guerre future. La Commission estd&apos;avis  que la Commission temporaire mixte a agi tres sagement en prenant cette decision et eljAestime que le rapport de la Sous-Commission, lorsqu&apos;il sera termine, doit recevoir la plus grandr1publicite possible. La Commission propose, en consequence, la resolution suivante :             L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine le rapport de  la Commission temporaire mixte  sur         le developpement de la guerre  chimique, approuve la  Commission d&apos;avoir charge une         sous-commission speciale de presenter un rapport  sur les effets probables des decouvertes         chimiques dans les prochaines guerres; elle prie le Conseil et la  Commission temporaire         mixte d&apos;assurer, par tous les moyens possibles, la publicite la plus complete du rapport         de  cette Sous-Commission.    La troisieme Commission a pris egalement  en consideration deux propositions visant le con-trole de 1&apos;emploi des gaz toxiques en temps de guerre. La  premiere proposition, presentee par M.Urrutia (delegue de la Colombie), tend a ce que la Commission temporaire  mixte soit priee deconsiderer 1&apos;opportunite de rediger un traite,  qui serait presente a la signature des Membres de laSociete lors  de la quatrieme Assemblee, en vue  de faire adopter par toutes les Puissances les  dis-positions du traite concernant 1&apos;emploi des gaz dans la guerre, qui a ete conclu a la Conference deWashington.    La deuxieme proposition, presentee par  sir Mark Sheldon (delegue de PAustralie), tend a ceque 1&apos;Assemblee adopte une resolution pressant les gouvernements d&apos;adherer a la Convention deWashington sur 1&apos;emploi des gaz toxiques et  des sous-marins en temps de guerre.    M. Urrutia, desireux d&apos;aboutir a un resultat positif,  ayant  consenti a retirer  sa propositionen faveur de celle de sir Mark Sheldon, la troisieme Commission a adopte la resolution suivante:             L&apos;Assemblee prie le Conseil de recommander aux Membres de la Societe des Nations         et  aux autres nations de donner leur adhesion au  Traite conclu a Washington le 6 fe-         vrier 1922, sur 1&apos;emploi des gaz asphyxiants  et des sous-marins en temps de guerre et         autres  questions similaires.7.  EXPOSES DES GOUVERNEMENTS SUR  LES EXIGENCES DE LEUR SECURITE NATIONALE.    L&apos;article 8 du Pacte prevoit que: K Le Conseil tenant compte de la situation geographique et des circonstances speciales de chaque Etat, prepare les plans de cette reduction (des  armements)en vue de 1&apos;examen et de la decision des divers gouvernements. a    Ann de pouvoir tenir compte de la situation geographique et des circonstances speciales queles  Membres de la Societe desireraient signaler comme important a leur securite nationale, le conseil, sur la proposition de la Commission temporaire mixte, a adresse une demande aux Mem-bres de la Societe pour les inviter a fournir une expose sur les considerations qu&apos;ils desiraient fairevaloir a  ce sujet.  Le but de cette enquete  etait  de decouvrir non seulement les  considerationsgeographiques qui affectent la defense de divers pays, mais aussi les dangers politiques dont les gouvernements doivent tenir compte, la mesure dans  laquelle les forces armees qu&apos;ils entre-tiennent sont necessaires, d&apos;une part pour le maintien de la paix  a 1&apos;interieur et d&apos;autre part pour la. protection contre les agressions venant de 1&apos;exterieur.  Le Conseil estimait que les exposes four-nis  par les gouvernements en reponse a son  questionnaire constitueraient une documentationd&apos;apres  laquelle la Commission temporaire mixte pourrait preparer des plans de reduction  desarmements.    La Commission temporaire mixte a recu  jusqu&apos;ici et a pris en  consideration  des  exposesfournis par les gouvernements de vingt-six Membres de la Societe, y compris toutes les  grandesPuissances militaires.  Le rapport de la  Commission temporaire mixte montre  que ces exposesseront de la plus grande valeur pour son ceuvre future. Les exposes ont, pour la plupart, traite d&apos;unefacon suffisante toutes  les considerations enumerees a 1&apos;article 8 du Pacte. II montre que les forcesentretenues par les divers gouvernements pour le maintien de 1&apos;ordre a 1&apos;interieur sont relative-ment faibles, qu&apos;en consequence Feffort  militaire fourni par les divers pays est presque entiere-ment destine a la defense contre une agression exterieure et que  les  dangers de ces agressionsresultent de situations politiques vis-a-vis desquelles on espere que P action de la Societe desNationspourra s&apos;exercer utilement.    II est evidemment a souhaiter que les autres Membres de la Societe qui ne se sont pas encoretrouves en mesure d&apos;envoyer un expose en reponse  au questionnaire du Conseil,  puissent le fairesans delai.    La troisieme Commission recommande,  en consequence, a 1&apos;Assemblee d&apos;adopter la  resolu-tion suivante:             L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine les reponses des gouvernements de vingt-six Membres&apos;         de la Societe des Nations a Penquetequi leur a ete adresseepar le Conseil sur les exigences         de leur securite nationale, tient a declarer qu&apos;elle attache un grand prix a  ces reponses         qui fournissent une base  aux  deliberations ulterieures de la  Commission temporaire         mixte et  exprime le vceu que le Conseil invite a nouveau des Membres  de la.Societe des         Nations qui n&apos;ont pas encore envoye leur reponse a le faire sans delai. ))
t8.  ECHANGE DE RENSEIGNEMENTS.*&apos;  La Commission  temporaire  mixte, dans son rapport, fait remarquer que les exposes fournispar les divers  gouvernements  en reponse au questionnaire du  Conseil constituent en realiteun echange de  renseignements assez semblable a  celui que  les Membres de la Societe  se sontengages a effectuer conformement au dernier paragraphe de 1&apos;article 8 du Pacte.   Le Conseil avait ete saisi de la question  par la Commission permanente consultative il y adeux  ans.  La troisieme Commission  ne peut  que souhaiter la realisation de 1&apos;echange de rensei-gnements vise  a 1&apos;article 8  du Pacte; elle recommande, par consequent, d&apos;adopter la resolutionsuivante:            L&apos;Assemblee approuve le vceu de la Commission temporaire mixte tendant a ce        que le Conseil considere si le moment n&apos;est pas venu d&apos;etudier 1&apos;application de 1&apos;alinea du        paragraphe 8 du Pacte  relatif a 1&apos;echange de renseignements militaires entre les Etats        Membres de la Societe des Nations.9.  CONFERENCE  DE WASHINGTON.   Le rapport de la Commission temporaire  mixte  fait  justement remarquer que  malgreles graves difficultes d&apos;ordre politique dont le monde souffre actuellement, 1&apos;esprit de cooperationInternationale vers des buts de paix  qui anime la Societe des Nations se  manifeste  aussi parlilleurs. La Commission  temporaire mixte voit deux exemples de cet esprit dans la Conferencepi a eu lieu a Washington 1&apos;automne dernier et dans la  Conference  pan-americaine qui doit sereunir a Santiago pendant le printemps prochain.   Sur  la proposition de la  Commission  temporaire mixte, la deuxieme Assemblee,  en  se ral-liant  aux suggestions de  la Commission temporaire mixte, avait exprime 1&apos;avis que H Ton ne peutmettre a  execution aucun plan complet de reduction des armements  sans  la collaboration des etats-Unis, de 1&apos;Allemagne et de la Russie; en particulier, la puissance riavale de la premiere deces nations rend tout projet de reduction des armements navals impossible, sans son appui, et c&apos;estpour  cette raison, entre autres,  qu&apos;elle  saluait chaleureusement la prochaine Conference deWashington et esperait qu&apos;elle pourrait avoir comme resultat d&apos;assurer, dans une large mesure,la reduction des armements *.   Dans son rapport au  Conseil,  la Commission temporaire mixte exprime a la satisfactionqu&apos;elle a eprouve de 1&apos;ceuvre accomplie a Washington dans le domaine de la reduction  des arme-ments navals 9. La troisieme Commission est sure que 1&apos;Assemblee s&apos;associera de tout coeur a lasatisfaction exprimete par la Commission temporaire mixte du succes de la Conference de Washing-ton dans un terrain qui 1&apos;interesse a un si haut point.10.  CONFERENCE PAN-AMERICAINE DE SANTIAGO.     Le fait  que la  question de la reduction des armements allait etre soumise a la prochaine Conference pan-americaine de Santiago a  ete communique a  la Commission temporaire  mixte par son membre chili en,  M. Rivas-Vicuna.     Dans son rapport general, la Commission a exprime naturellement 1&apos;interet  que lui inspire cette question sur laquelle elle a adopte la resolution suivante:              La  Commission temporaire mixte prend note des declarations faites par M. Rivas-         Vicufia, au nom  du Gouvernement chilien, en sa quatrieme session.  Elle accueille avec         interet 1&apos;initiative du Gouvernement chilien  tendant a soumettre la  question du desar-         mement au Congres pan-americain qui doit avoir lieu  a Santiago au mois de mars 1923.              La Commission exprime 1&apos;espoir que le Congres aboutisse a des solutions pratiques,         susceptibles de rentrer dans le cadre plus general du desarmement qui fait 1&apos;objet de ses         propres travaux.     Ce sujet a ete souleve pendant les debats de la troisieme Commission a propos de 1&apos;extensionlies principes du Traite de Washington aux Puissances non signataires, et  M. Rivas-Vicuna a exprime 1&apos;avis que a la cooperation des organismes techniques de la Societe des Nations et de ceux qui collaborerent a la Conference de  Washington  serait d&apos;une  inappreciable valeur pour les; travaux de la Conference de Santiago it.     La troisieme Commission a decide de faire sienne la resolution de la  Commission  temporaire: mixte reproduite ci-dessus.
II.  REDUCTION DES ARMEMENTS NAVALS    La troisieme Commission a examine les recommandations faites par la Commission temporairemixte en vue de 1&apos;extension aux autres Puissances des principes du Traite de Washington sur ledesarmement naval conclu par les Etats-Unis, l&apos;empire britannique, la France, lTtalie et le Japon.Cette partie du rapport de la Commission  temporaire mixte a procure  une satisfaction particu-liere aux membres de la troisieme Commission parce qu&apos;il contient une recommandation ferme en vue des mesures pratiques qui pourront, nous Pesperons, etre realisees sans grand delai.    La Commission temporaire mixte a transmis au Conseil et a 1&apos;Assemblee un projet de traitesur ce sujet qui a ete prepare par la Sous-Commission navale de la Commission permanente con-consultative. Ce projet est semblable a celui  qui a ete conclu par la Conference de Washingtonet prevoit la limitation du tonnage total des navires de ligne et des navires porte-aeronefs que lesdiverses Puissances pourront  entretenir, ainsi que la limitation des dimensions et de Parmementdes navires cle ligne et autres bailments. Tel qu&apos;il est propose dans le rapport de la sous-Commissionnavale qui  accompagne ce projet, il assurerait  des  a vacances navales a de io ans. La Coin-mission temporaire mixte  propose qu&apos;une conference soit convoquee a  une  date rapprocheepour rediger un traite definitif et elle suggereque ce projet pourrait servir de base aux delibe-rations de cette conference. La Commission propose egalement  qne tous les Etats, qu&apos;ils soient ounon Membres de la Societe, soient invites a participer  a cette Conference.    La troisieme Commission est entierement d&apos;accord  avec la  Commission temporaire  des arme-ments pour  estimer qu&apos;il est souhaitable qu&apos;une conference soit convoquee a une date rapprocheeet que tous les Etats, qu&apos;ils  soient ou non Membres de la Societe, soient invites a y participer. Elleconsidere cependant qu&apos;une certaine elasticity, en ce qui concerne le programme cle cette  Confe-rence,  doit etre prevue et qu&apos;il doit etre specifie egalement que la Conference ne sera aucunementliee par le projet de traite, mais, au  contraire, qu&apos;elle sera libre cle prendre en consideration lescirconstances speciales des divers pays et,  en particulier, les conditions speciales dans lesquellesse trouvent  les nouveaux Etats  qui  n&apos;ont  pas  encore de marine. Tout en etant d&apos;accord sur cepoint de vue, la troisieme  Commission, cependant, est fermement persuadee qu&apos;il est hautementdesirable cPassurer la limitation immediate des forces  navales entretenues  par  tous les pays afinque les peuples du monde entier puissent etre soulages de la charge economique qui peserait sureux par Paccroissement du tonnage total ou des dimensions des navires de guerre entretenus parleurs gouvernements.    La troisieme Commission recommande, en consequence, que F Assemblee adopte la resolutionsuivante:             a) Que le Conseil convoque aussitot que possible une conference internationale a         laquelle seront pries d&apos;assister tous les Etats,  qu&apos;ils soient ou non Membres de la Societe         des Nations, en vue de considerer Pextension des principes du Traite de Washington sur         la limitation des armements  navals a tous les  Etats non signataires dudit traite. II  reste         entendu que  tous les cas particuliers, y compris ceux des Etats nouvellement formes,         seront specialement examines a cette  Conference.             b) Elle emet  le voeu que le rapport de la Commission temporaire mixte, ainsi qne         le rapport et le projet de convention prepares par la Commission permanente consulta-         tive et le texte du Traite  de Washington,  soient soumis sans  delai a  l&apos;examen des         differents gouvernements.III. REDUCTION DES ARMEMENTS TERRESTRES ET AERIENS.    Dans son etude d&apos;un projet de reduction des armements terrestres, la Commission temporairemixte a pris  pour base de ses deliberations les resolutions qui lui avaient ete soumises par lordEsher. Ces resolutions qui comprenaient une proposition d&apos;une echelle de reduction precise pour les effectifs de  paix, a adopter par les divers  gouvernements cPEurope, ont  ete tres soigneuse-ment etudiees par la Commission temporaire mixte et par la Sous-Commission  qu&apos;elle a designee,ainsi que par  la Commission permanente  consultative,  a  la  demande  du Conseil.  La Sous-Commission,  et la Commission elle-meme, sont arrivees a cette conclusion, qui etait egalement cellede la Commission permanente consultative, que dans la forme oh elles ont ete presentees, on nepouvait recommander les propositions  cle lord Esher.  En les etudiant, la Commission temporairemixte  a abouti a certains  principes  generaux concernant la  reduction des  armements sur labase desquels elle estime que Ton pourrait etablir un projet satisfaisant.    La troisieme Commission a  examine les  principes expose.-;  par la  Commission  temporairejmixte et leur a donne son approbation generale sans entrer clans 1&apos;examen detaille de la facofldont il serait possible de  les utiliser  pour F elaboration  definitive d&apos;un  traite comportant la Ireduction des armements. A ce sujet, des appreciations quelque peu divergentes ont ete ernises parquelques membres de la Commission.  Elle est d&apos;avis, cependant, que  ces principes  constituentun premier pas tres  important vers la preparation d&apos;un traite cle ce genre,  et elle estime que la commission temporaire mixte doit etre invitee a pousser sans delai son etude cle la question. Elle jestime que la Commission temporaire mixte doit etablir ces principes d&apos;une maniere plus detaillee, j
determiner la methode par laquelle  on pourra les appliquer a F elaboration d&apos;un accord pour lareduction des armements et formuler alors, d&apos;une fagon aussi precise que possible, un projet fondesur ces principes. Ainsi qu&apos;il a ete declare ci-dessus, la collaboration des Ministeres de la Guerredes divers  Membres de la Societe pourra etre particulierement importante pour cette partie de1&apos;ceuvre de la Commission temporaire mixte et la troisieme Commission est certaine que les Mem-Ares de la Societe preteront a cet egard leur concours plein et entier.P   La Commission recommande a 1&apos;Assemblee 1&apos;adoption de la resolution suivante:             L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine  le rapport de  la  Commission  temporaire  mixte sur         les principes generaux du desarmement terrestre  et  aerien,  charge la Commission  de         poursuivre ses investigations sur la base de ces principes, a F effet de  preparer  un plan         precis de  reduction  generale des  armements  terrestres qui  pourra etre  soumis  a         1&apos;examen de la  prochaine Assemblee .IV. TRAITE DE GARANTIE  MUTUELLE     La Commission temporaire mixte a emis 1&apos;opinion, dans son rapport, que pour rendre possible la reduction des armements terrestres, il etait necessaire que certaines conditions politiques fussent remplies.  De 1&apos;avis de la Commission temporaire mixte, la premiere de ces conditions consiste a susciter par un traite de garantie mutuelle, cette confiance et ce sentiment de securite sans les- quels la plupart des gouvernements ne pourront prendre la responsabilite de reduire leurs moyens de defense. La Commission  temporaire mixte a adopte cette conclusion sous forme de quatre resolutions, procedant du principe que  la reduction des armements doit etre generale pour pou- voir etre couronnee d&apos;un plein succes. La troisieme Commission approuve, dans ]&quot;ensemble, ce prin- cipe, bien qiFelle n&apos;exclue pas, comme 1&apos;indique la cinquieme partie de ce rapport, la possibilite que, dans quelques parties du monde, la situation geographique de certains groupes d&apos;Etats leur permette de s&apos;entendre entre eux, par un accord regional distinct, pour la reduction des armements.&apos;     La Commission temporaire mixte, apres avoir enonce le principe de la necessite d&apos;une reduction generale des armements, passe ensuite a une deuxieme conclusion: De nombreux gouvernements ne peuvent,  dans Fetat actuel du monde, prendre la responsabilite de  reduire leurs moyens de defense, s&apos;ils ne regoivent pas, en echange, une garantie de securite contre une attaque venant du dehors. A moins de garantie de ce genre, les gouvernements sont tenus de  considerer commc de leur devoir fondamental de consacrer tout  F effort national  a  la preparation de la  defense du  terri- toire. La Commission temporaire mixte insiste sur le fait  que si  les gouvernements doivent etre amenes a ne pas deployer cet effort national tout entier, ils doivent recevoir une assurance quel- quelconque,  garantissant leur peuple contre Faccroissement ainsi encouru  du danger d&apos;invasion.     La  Commission  temporaire mixte  emet  Favis  qu&apos;une assurance de ce genre pourrait etre  donnee  aux  Gouvernements  par  un  traite  de garantie  defensive  mutuelle.  Chaque signataire  s&apos;engagerait, aux termes de ce traite, a porter secours, par des mesures economiques et militaires, a  tous les  autres  signataires  qui  seraient victimes  d&apos;une attaque exterieure. La Commission fait,  remarquer,  dans son rapport, que l&apos;objet essentiel d&apos;un traite de  defense mutuelle de ce genre serait  de  donner  a tout Etat qui reduirait ses  armements,  une securite au moins  aussi grande  que  celle  dont  il pourrait beneficier au cas  ou il  ne  reduirait pas ses armements en faisant appel a toutes ses ressources propres. Mais la Commission  fait egalement observer qu&apos;un traite de defense mutuelle de ce genre,  s&apos;il etait etabli et generalement accepte, aurait, en  fait, pour resultat presque certain d&apos;enlever toute  chance de victoire a un Etat agres- seur; cet Etat ne pourrait mettre, en effet, la Societe en presence d&apos;un fait accompli obtenu par la violence; il est tres probable qu&apos;il succomberait immediatement sous  les forces reunies  que les Etats garants emploieraient contre lui.     La troisieme Commission approuve  les opinions ainsi exposes s par la Commission temporaire mixte. Elle considere, elle aussi, que le traite de garantie mutuelle, pour etre efficace, doit etre accessible  a tous les Etats du monde. Elle considere qu&apos;un traite de ce genre ne peut exister utile- ment tant  qu&apos;un nombre considerable d&apos;Etats ne Fa pas ratine; elle estime extremement souhaitable que ces  Etats participants comptent parmi eux presque  toutes,  sinon  toutes,  les  grandes Puis- sances militaires et croit probable que toute tentative d&apos;etablir un traite de ce genre, sauf aux conditions indiquees,  pourrait determiner la reapparition du. systeme de groupes d&apos;alliance existant avant la guerre. Toutefois,  la Commission  est egalement &apos;d&apos;avis  qu&apos;il  n&apos;est pas necessaire que, pour entrer en vigueur, le traite soit accepte universellemeht;  elle propose done que  la Commission temporaire mixte soit chargee d&apos;etudier cet  aspect de la question et de formuler des avis sur les conditions auxquelles xm traite de ce genre pourrait etre utilement applique&quot;.     Un  traite de garantie mutuelle a simplement pour objet de rendre possible la reduction des armements;  il est done  evident que son l&apos;efficacite depend en grande mesure du nombre  d&apos;Etatsliqui y participent. Plus le nombre de ces Etats sera grand,  plus la garantie sera effective et plus la&quot;reduction  des armements pourra etre etendue. Mais, ici encore, la Commission estime qu&apos;il  ne lui est pas possible de formuler une opinion definitive sur  les etapes qu&apos;il y a lieu de parcourir effectively- movement pour aboutir alia reduction des armements.  Elle propose done que cette question deli- cate, et celle&quot;de la mise  en vigueur du Pacte de garantie mutuelle, soit renvoyee a Fexamen de la Commission temporaire mixte qui serait chargee de deposer un rapport sur ces points.
    La Commission s&apos;est sentie toutefois  en mesure  rTaccepter les  grands principes generauxqui veulent que le  Pacte de garantie et la reduction des armements constituent d&apos;une  part lesdeux elements  essentiels d&apos;une politique unique, et doivent, autant  que possible, d&apos;autre part,entrer en vigueur en meme temps.    La reduction des armements doit dependre de la garantie comme la garantie doit dependrede la reduction des  armements. Cest a la lumiere de ces principes que la Commission temporalmixte est priee d&apos;etudier la methode et les moyens permettant d&apos;appliquer simultanement ces deuxmesures.    La troisieme Commission estime qu&apos;il importe beaucoup, pour que la Commission tempo-raire mixte puisse poursuivre Petude de ces questions difficiles, qu&apos;elle beneficie des avis des gouver-nements Membres de la Societe. Aussi,  tout  en proposant que la Commission  temporaire  mixtesoit chargee de rediger ces propositions  sous la forme concrete d&apos;un projet de traite, la troisiemeCommission recommande egalement que les gouvernements soient invites a transmettre au Conseilles observations qu&apos;ils auraient a formuler.    Ici encore, comme pour Pelaboration d&apos;un  projet de reduction  des armements terrestres,il est evident que les gouvernements Membres de la Societe ont Poccasion  de  rendre au Conseilet a la Commission temporaire mixte un service signale. Mais,  en  attendant, la Commissiontemporaire mixte a deja accompli une tache remarquable en procedant a une enquete prehminairesur les  mesures pratiques, permettant  de  rendre efficace un traite de garantie mutuelle et enenoncant dans son rapport les principes generaux qui  doivent presider, selon elle, a la redactiond&apos;un pacte de ce genre.    Elle s&apos;est propose, a juste titre, pour  objet de montrer qu&apos;une garantie comme la garantieproposee pourrait constituer une aide immediate pour tout Etat attaque. Elle fait ressortir, pourcette raison, qu&apos;il est essentiel de trouver une methode permettant de resoudre les deux problemesprincipaux suivants:    i0  Lorsqu&apos;une  guerre a eclate, determiner dans le plus court delai possible lequel des Etatsest Pagresseur.    20  Prevoir les moyens d&apos;assurer une aide militaire mutuelle, tout en evitant un delai qui pour-rait etre fatal pour PEtat  attaque.    La Commission temporaire mixte propose pour le premier de ces  problemes que le Conseil dela Societe decide, le cas echeant, par une majorite des trois quarts, quel est 1&apos;Etat agresseur et soitoblige  de prendre cette decision dans un delai de quatre jours au plus. Elle propose Papplicationd&apos;un criterium, a son avis, simple et efficace qui consisterait a declarer que PEtat agresseur estcelui qui a deliberement viole le territoire de Pautre Etat. En vue de determiner quel est cet Etatle Conseil pourrait envoyer une Commission d&apos;expefts sur les lieux pour faire une enquete sur lesfaits. Cependant, il est possible que des recherches ulterieures montrent la possibilite de trouveiun meilleur criterium de Pacte degression.    Quant au second but  que Pon se propose, a savoir de veiller a ce que le secours militaireapporte arrive  sans des delaii qui pourraient devenir fatals, la Commission temporaire  mixte a fait d&apos;autres propositions relativement aux conditions dans lesquelles  pourrait s&apos;effectuer la colla-boration militaire entre  PEtat attaque et  les autres Etats garants. La Commission temporairemixte  fait remarquer aussi qu&apos;outre les diverses formes de pression  economique prevues par lePacte et qui peuvent etre facilement appliquees, certaines armes telles que les avions et les naviresde guerre sont rapidement disponibles et que leur action semble devoir etre efficace dans les debutsd&apos;une guerre.    La troisieme Commission n&apos;a pas  juge  possible d&apos;examiner ces  propositions en detail; parsuite, elle ne peut pas exprimer de jugement decisif a leur sujet. Mais elle croit bon de dire d&apos;unefacon generate combien elle apprecie la valeur de Poeuvre accomplie par la Commission temporairemixte  et  des suggestions qu&apos;elle a presentees. La Commission  invite  egalement la  Commissiontemporaire mixte a continuer ses  travaux  pour presenter a la prochaine Assemblee un plan  pludetaille en vue de l&apos;application des principes qutelle a emis.    La troisieme Commission a Pespoir que si un projet de pacte de garantie mutuelle,  tel que celuiqui est propose, peut etre realise avec succes, il contribuera beaucoup a faire naitre ce sentimentde securite qui permettra d&apos;operer la reduction des armements. Tel est l&apos;objet des propositions faitepar la Commission temporaire mixte.  Mais la troisieme Commission estime necessaire de faireremarquer, en y insistant fortement, qu&apos;accepter ces principes c&apos;est  reconnaitre que pour s&apos;assurerle benefice d&apos;une  reduction generate des armements, les gouvernements doivent etre prets, en casde necessite, a s&apos;y  conformer. La  troisieme Commission croit que les gouvernements des EtatsMembres de la Societe des Nations sont prets a le faire, pourvu qu&apos;ils soient certains qu&apos;en agissant ainsi, ils realiseront la grande fin qu&apos;ils poursuivent.    Aussi propose-t-elle a F Assemblee  d&apos;adopter les resolutions suivantes:    L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine le rapport  de la  Commission temporaire mixte sur la  questiond&apos;un traite general de garantie mutuelle, estimant d&apos;une part, que ce rapport  ne saurait affecteien rien la complete validite de tous les traites de paix ou autres accords existants et connus entrles Etats, et que, d&apos;autre part, ce rapport renferme  des suggestions precieuses quant a la  methodepropre a rendre effectif le traite de garantie mutuelle. approuve les resolutions suivantes:             i. Aucun plan de reduction des armements, dans le sens de Particle 8 du Pacte, ne         peut pleinement aboutir que s&apos;il est general.             2. Dans 1&apos;etat actuel du monde, un grand nombre de Gouvernements ne pourraient         assumer la responsabilite d&apos;une serieuse reduction des armements a  moins de recevoir         en echange une garantie satisfaisante pour la securite de leur pays.
les.rtV. ACCORDS REGIONAUX EN VUE DE LA REDUCTION DES ARMEMENTS.    Dans les parties precedentes de ce rapport, la troisieme Commission &quot;a examine le probleme delareduction des armements en tant qu&apos;il doit etre resolu au moyen de conventions generates concluespar tous les Etats qui sont Membres de la Sbciete et traitant, en premier lieu, des armements navals,et, en second lieu, des armements terrestres et aerie ns.  La Commission estime toutefois  que, dans certaines parties du monde, la situation geographiqueet politique est telle que les Etats situes dans ces regions pourraient, a leur avantage, et sans sacrifierleur securite, alter plus avant dans la voie de la reduction des armements terrestres ou maritimes quecela n&apos;est possible pour d&apos;autres  Etats moins favorises par leur situation. Pour cette raison, la Corn-mission  pense que la Commission temporaire mixte doit etre invitee a rechercher les progres realises-sables a cet egard, et elle recommande a 1&apos;Assemblee 1&apos;adoption de la resolution suivante:             a L;Assemblee de la Societe des Nations,             a Tout en affirmant que la reduction des armements visee par 1&apos;article 8 du Pacte ne        peut porter tous ses effets pour la paix du monde que si elle est generale,             K Tient  a souligner 1&apos;importance que peuvent avoir des  accords regionaux tendant a        une reduction des armements, et qui, le cas echeant, pourront meme depasser les mesures        fixees pour la reduction generale,             a Et prie le Conseil de demander a la  Commission temporaire mixte  d&apos;envisager,  au        cours de ses travaux ulterieurs, la possibilite de recommander la conclusion de semblables        accords aux Etats qui pourraient y etre interesses. *VI. CONCLUSIONS GENERALES.    La Commission temporaire mixte a explique tout au long dans son rapport les dimcultes qu&apos;elle a rencontrees pour la preparation  d&apos;un projet pratique de reduction des armements.  Elle a aussi ndique les lignes generates suivant lesquelles il serait possible d&apos;esperer trouver une solution de ce probleme.    La troisieme Commission, cependant, estime que malgre la pression economique qui  pese sur tous les gouvernements et qui milite en faveur d&apos;une reduction des armements, la situation politique et economique de l&apos;Europe est si precaire, qu&apos;aucun plan general tendant a reduire les moyens de defense ne serait actuellement accepte. Les gouvernements d&apos;un grand nombre de pays sont preoc--cupes par 1&apos;imminence de grandes catastrophes dont les consequences peuvent etre incalculables. Outre ces dangers menacants, la situation economique generate est telle que le monde est tenu dans un etat de suspicion et de nervosite incompatible avec une paix reelle.  Sans la paix,  sans le desar- mement moral, les projets de reduction des armements materiels sont vains.    En consequence, quiconque cherche a reduire les armements doit se poser la question suivante: Quelles sont les causes qui entravent le mecanisme du commerce international  et des changes et qui            3. Une telle garantie peut etre fournie par un accord defensif, accessible a tous les        pays, qui engagerait les Parties a porter assistance effective et immediate et suivant un        plan pre-etabli au cas ou Tune dtelles serait attaquee, pourvu que 1&apos;obligation de venir en        aide a un pays attaque soit limitee en principe aux pays situes dans la meme partie du        globe. Cependant, dans des cas ou pour  des raisons historiques, geographiques ou autres,        un pays court tout particulierement risque dtetre attaque, des mesures speciales devront        etre prises pour sa defense, en execution du plan precedent.            4. La reduction generale des armements etant le but des resolutions qui precedent        et le traite de garantie mutuelle le moyen de realisation, il va de soi que le consentement        prealable a cette reduction est la premiere condition de ce traite.            Cette reduction peut steperer soit sous la forme, qui serait la plus souhaitable, d&apos;un        traite general, soit sous la forme de traites particuliers, mais destines a s&apos;elargir et demeu-        rant accessibles a tous les pays.            Dans le premier cas, le traite entraine la reduction generale  des armements.            Dans le second cas,  la reduction  devra  etre proportionnee aux securites que le        traite de garantie  apportera.            Le  Conseil de la Societe des Nations, apres avoir pris 1&apos;avis de la Commission tempo-        raire mixte, qui  etudiera les  conditions dans lesquelles pourront etre appliques 1&apos;un et        1&apos;autre de ces systemes, etablira ulterieurement, pour la soumettre a 1&apos;appreciation et a        la decision souveraine des Gouvernements,  le  plan  du mecanisme, a la fois politique        et militaire, charge d&apos;en preparer et d&apos;en assurer avec precision la realisation.    L&apos;Assemblee prie le Conseil de demander aux divers Gouvernements leur avis sur les propo-sitions ci-dessus; elle demande a la Commission temporaire  mixte de poursuivre ses travauxet, afrn de donner toutes precisions aux resolutions ci-dessus, de preparer un projet de traitebase sur les principes envisages dans ces resolutions.
aboutissent a un malaise economique et politique ? La reponse est simple. II est hors de doute qu&apos;ilfaut chercher la cause preponderante de cette situation dans les dettes  intergouvemementales  quipesent sur tous les grands Etats d&apos;Europe.     Ces dettes intergouvernementales, qu&apos;elles prennent la forme d&apos;obligations de reparations, decredits de secours, ou de dettes contractees entre allies durant la grande guerre, constituent un obstaclequ&apos;il faut ecarter avant que la vie economique de 1&apos;Europe puisse etre retablie. Tant que des mesuresn&apos;auront pas ete prises a cet effet, on ne saurait arreter la chute des changes et retablir le commerilinternational. On pourrait citer a cet egard 1&apos;opinion du Comite financier de la Societe des  Nations:K Nous avons la ferme conviction qu&apos;il est vain d&apos;esperer retablir la situation economique du mondetant que le probleme des dettes intergouvernementales n&apos;aura pas ete resolu d&apos;une fagon raisonnableet  pratique, M  La troisieme Commission  croit qu&apos;il est generalement reconnu  que le  mecanismed&apos;cchange des produits au moyen duquel ont toujours vecu les pays d&apos;Europe ne peut etre restaureavant que ce probleme n&apos;ait ete resolu d&apos;une maniere satisfaisante.     La troisieme Commission  est d&apos;avis qu&apos;il y a lieu d&apos;agir aussitot en cette matiere dans le plusbref delai. II est possible qu&apos;on ne puisse arriver a une solution integrale de cette question sans lesecours des Etats-Unis. Mais ce n&apos;est pas une raison  pour ne rien faire jusqu&apos;a ce que ce secoursarrive. On peut deja faire beaucoup avec la collaboration des gouvernements europeens et de ceuxqui sont en dehors de 1&apos;Europe et qui, nous sommes heureux de le savoir, sont prets a venir en aide.Et s&apos;il en est ainsi, il n&apos;y a aucune raison pour ne pas agir de suite, car tous les observateurs compe-tents sont d&apos;accord pour declarer que 1&apos;Europe dispose de bien peu de temps pour trouver son salutfinancier et  ecarter ainsi les desastres qui la menacent.     La Commission ne croit pas qu&apos;il lui appartienne de preciser davantage  les mesures qui sontnecessaires ou la part que la Societe des Nations peut etre utilement appelee a prendre en vue detrouver une solution. Elle croit de son devoir de rappeler a 1&apos;Assemblee la necessite d&apos;une  actionimmediate et de repeter que tant que les difficultes financieres de 1&apos;Europe ne seront pas reglees,on ne saurait esperer pouvoir retrouver la stabilite et la confiance politique, elements sans lesquelsil est impossible de realiser le desarmement moral dont depend le succes de tout projet de reductiondes armements materiels.     En consequence, la Commission soumet  a 1&apos;approbation de 1&apos;Assemblee la resolution suivante:            (( L&apos;Assemblee, considerant que le desarmement materiel exige d&apos;abord le desarme-        ment moral, que celui-ci ne peut etre realise que dans une atmosphere de securite et de        confiance mutuelle;            ((Constate que cette confiance sera impossible tant que se perpetueront le desequi-        libre des changes,  le chaos economique et le chomage dont souffre le monde, et que seule        la cessation de 1&apos; incertitude qui regne sur les moyens par lesquels peuvent etre restaurees        les  regions devastees et  sur  le reglement  des dettes  interalliees  permettra de porter        remede a ces maux;            H Emet le vceu que, dans la mesure oh des questions peuvent etre reglees par le senl        concours des nations europeennes,  les gouvernements signataires des  traites et accords        internationaux dont  ces questions sont 1&apos;objet, et dans  le cadre desquelles elles doivent        etre envisagees, aboutissent le plus tot possible a une solution  d&apos;ensemble du probleme        des reparations et du probleme  des dettes interalliees;            (( Emet le vceu que le Conseil donne a tous les efforts faits dans ce sens par les gouver-        nements interesses une attention constante, etant  entendu qu&apos;il ne peut apporter a la        solution de ces problemes  une contribution utile sans que  ces gouvernements  lui en        fassent la  demande. s
esiINDEX.                                                                                page introduction  .   ...   ........-......  .   .   .   .      3I. VARIOUS :         1. The Limitation of National Expenditure on Armaments......      4         2. Statistical Enquiry.................      4         3. Surplus Stocks of Munitions..............      5         4. Private Manufacture................      5         5. Arms  Traffic...................      6         6. Chemical Warfare.................      7         7. Statements of Governments on the Requirements of their National -Security     8         8. Exchange of Information................      8         9. Washington Conference...............      9        10. Pan-American Conference at Santiago...........      9II.  REDUCTION OF NAVAL ARMAMENTS..............      9III. REDUCTION OF LAND AND AIR ARMAMENTS............     10IV. TREATY OF MUTUAL GUARANTEE...............     10V.  REGIONAL AGREEMENTS  FOR THE REDUCTION OF ARMAMENTS........     12VI. GENERAL CONCLUSIONS..................     13
LEAGUE OF NATIONS.REDUCTION  OF  ARMAMENTS.Report of the  Third Committee to the  Third Assembly.Rapporteur : Lord Robert CECIL.INTRODUCTION.    The Third Committee cf the Assembly has held nine meetings, all of which have been devotedto the discussion of the reduction of armaments.  The deliberations of the Committee have been based upon the  conclusions presented to it in the Report of the Tempoiary Mixed  commission appointed by the Council at the suggestion of the First Assembly in order to prepare for submission to the Council reports and proposals for the reduction of armaments.  In accordance with theresolution adopted by the Assembly last year, the Council, in March  1922,  strengthened theTemporary Mixed Commission by appointing seven additional members with special qualifications for its work.  Since the last Assembly, the Temporary Mixed Commission has held three meetings,and on all the matters with which it has dealt, considerable progress has been made.   On some ofthem definite conclusions have been reached and are recommended for adoption by the Assembly.On others,general principles have been laid down and the lines indicated on which the Commissionhopes that it may be able, in a not too-distant future, to present concrete plans for the considera-tion  of the Council and the Assembly.    The progress in  its task has brought the Third Committee to the opinion that it is&apos; most desirable that the Council should reappoint the Temporary Mixed Commission for another year.The Committee, moreover, is of opinion that it is imperative that the proposals of the TemporaryMixed  Commission should be  submitted at  a  date previous to that of the next  Assemblysufficiently early to enable it to discuss with  profit so complex and important a problem.  Inmaking this proposal, the Third Committee wishes  also to suggest that it is desirable that the Corn-mission should be brought into closer touch with the views of the Governments of the Members ofthe League. It  does not suggest that Government representatives should be added  to the Corn-mission, but it considers  that the  Council  might usefully invite the  Members of the League toensure  the closest  co-operation  between their military departments  and the Temporary  mixed commission in order that authoritative information, opinions and even criticism may facilitateits work.    The Third Committee considers that it is particularly  important that  the Governments  shouldbe asked to submit observations which they might desire to urge, and in particular to put forwardany suggestions which they may have to offer with regard to the  principles of the  reduction ofland armaments formulated by the Commission,  and  with regard to the scheme for a Treaty of mutual  Guarantee, which is discussed hereafter.    The Third Committee therefore recommends the following resolution  for adoption by theAssembly  :             It. is desirable that the Temporary Mixed Commission should be asked  to continue        for another year the work which  it has  begun and that its report be submitted at an       &apos; early  date previous to that of the  next Assembly.  The  Assembly further requests        the Council to invite the Members of the League to lend their  assistance  to the Corn-        mission in its difficult task, and  to  give their  assistance and  advice  with regard to        proposals for reduction of land armaments and  a Treaty of Mutual Guarantee.            The  Third  Committee desires  to  express  its sense  of  the  great value  of  the        collaboration  that has existed between the Temporary  Mixed Commission and the        Permanent Advisory Committee,  and it trusts  that it will continue and, if possible,        increase. It is of opinion that the great technical competence of the Permanent Advisory        Commission cannot but be of essential service in the questions in which the Temporary        Mixed Commission has been engaged.
I.  VARIOUSi.   THE LIMITATION OF NATIONAL EXPENDITURE ON ARMAMENTS.    At its second session the Assembly adopted the following resolution:             &quot;Subject to the conditions set out in the recommendations of the First Assembly,        the recommendation that Members of the League should undertake not to exceed, for        the next two financial years following the present year, the sum total of expenditure on        military, naval and air forces provided for in the budget of that year, be again forwarded        to the Members of the League, together with a statement  showing the replies already        received to this recommendation.&quot;    The Council endorsed this Resolution and the Secretary-General forwarded on January 17th,1922, to the Members of the League a copy of the recommendation and a statement of the replieswhich had  been received.  In response to this communication, a large number of governments have sent further answers.  In order to make of greater use the valuable information containedin these replies, the Temporary Mixed Commission drew up special tables in which the general conclusions which resulted from them could be more easily reviewed.  When it had tabulated theinformation thus received and had given it due consideration, the Temporary Mixed Commissionarrived at the following conclusions:              (a)  On the whole  the estimated defence expenditure for the  financial year 1922        (or 1922-23) shows a reduction as compared with the actual expenditure incurred in the        two previous financial years.             (b)  In appreciating the  significance of this reduction, due consideration must be        given, however, to the fact that,  since the year 1920, in many of the countries concerned,        there has been a  falling-off  in war charges, owing  to the operations connected with        demobilisation, and also to the fact that in many countries there has been a considerable        decrease in the prices of raw materials.    The Third Committee  is in  complete agreement with the  T. M. C. on this matter and hasdecided to  adopt as  its own the  above conclusions.  It has thought  it possible, however,for the Assembly to  take a further step in this same direction beyond that which it took in 1921,and accordingly,  on  the motion  of M. de Jouvenel, delegate for France, and without in any wayrestricting the scope of the previous recommendations on this subject, it proposes to the Assem-bly the following Resolution:            Furthermore,  the Assembly recommends that, as  a preliminary step, the European        States existing before the war in 1914,  under their present description, whose juridical        status has not been modified by the war, and which are not, at the moment, engaged in        military operations which justify their armaments, be invited to reduce the total of their        military, naval and  air expenditure to  the figures for 1913, calculated on the basis of        pre-war prices according to the method employed by the Temporary Mixed Commission.                                 2.  STATISTICAL ENQUIRY.    The Third Committee feels it its duty to express its gratitude to the Statistical Sub-Committeeof the T. M. C. and to the Secretariat  of the League for the manner in which they have carried outthe statistical enquiries decided upon by the Assembly at its previous sessions.  The results achieved in this direction up to the present time are of great value, and the task of collecting and co-ordi-nating statistics has been carried through with great ingenuity and care.    As  the original programme  of the  enquiry  was thought  to imply a  comparison between1913 and 1921, some of these investigations had to be executed on the hypothetical basis of europe as it would have been had its present geographical frontiers existed before the war.  Such investi-gations  would naturally be of no practical value to the further work of the T. M. C.  The ThirdCommittee therefore suggests that the statistical investigations of the T. M. C.  be continued onthe basis of original figures relating to actual conditions as they exist and leaving for the future the question of the method for their elaboration.    It appears from the Report of the T. M. C. that what it now requires is an instruction from theAssembly as to the lines upon which its further work shall be carried out.    The Third Committee believes that these general lines can be found in the original principles on which the statistical enquiry was based.    What  is required is an investigation carried out as a first  step towards the  preparation of ageneral  plan for the  reduction of armaments.  This plan should be based upon Article 8 of theCovenant, which recognises the primary importance of national security in this matter.   As maybe clearly seen from the statements received from the different countries, the national security
                                                                                       *   J                                         - 5 -                                          1of each depends very largely  on the full military strength of other countries.  The subject of the  Istatistical enquiry should therefore be this full  military strength.   It  consists of two factors:-             i.   The actual  military strength,  which is expressed in the peace-time armaments         and the  expenditure on national defence;             2.   The potential military strength, in which an important element is the industrial^         and economic power of each State, the military importance of which was proved in the*i         last war.    In this respect, therefore, the additions suggested by the T.M.C. to the programme of the econo-  !mic part of its enquiry would seem to be entirely justified.  It is doubtful, however, whether thetime has yet come to deal with this latter part  of the enquiry, and the Committee, while recog-recognising  that  it would perhaps be desirable to contemplate  a  future extension  of the statisticalinvestigations in  this direction, considers that  the statistical  enquiry  should be limited for thepresent  to the two principal factors by which   peace-time military strength is expressed, is.,armaments and budgets.    The Committee ventures to submit the following proposals for the approval of the Assembly:             The Committee expresses its satisfaction at the remarkable work  accomplished         in collecting and drawing up statistical data in an entirely new and peculiarly difficult         province.             Taking into account the work  accomplished, and reserving the question of the scope         it might be necessary to give to a statistical enquiry at a later date,  the Committee desires         to determine for the coming year the programme which appears to it at the same time         immediately useful and practicable.  It therefore  proposes that this programme should         be limited to the two following points:                   (i)   Peace-time armaments;                                               I                 (2)   Expenditure on armaments.             It would be desirable  that the Council should request  the Permanent Advisory I         Commission to collaborate with the Temporary Mixed Commission in that part of the I         work which deals with technical military, naval and air questions.                            3.   SURPLUS  STOCKS OF MUNITIONS.    The Council had invited the Permanent Advisory Commission  to examine the question of the  destruction of surplus stocks of munitions on account, of the technical character of this question.    After a detailed  examination of the matter, the Permanent Advisory Commission arrivedat the following conclusion :              &quot;To sum up, the  Committee notes that the question has already been settled by         the various countries concerned and that the surplus stocks which undoubtedly existed         at the close of the world-war have, during the three and a-half years which have elapsed      -   since that date, been destroyed or liquidated, or are in process of liquidation.&quot;And the Temporary Mixed Commission, having taken cognizance of the said Report, submittedto the Council the following conclusions, which were  approved by it on July 20th, 1922 :              &quot;The  Temporary Mixed  Commission  took  note  of the report of the Permanent         Advisory Commission and of the satisfactory measures taken by  the various States for         the liquidation of these  stocks. This first question has been settled in accordance with         the desire  of the Second Assembly.&quot;    Nevertheless, it should be observed that the Permanent Advisory Commission had rightlypointed out that the danger which might arise from  the possible existence of stocks of munitions and war material would be really due  not  so  much  to the fact that this material existed in thehands of responsible  Governments as  to its circulation without control  in the world at large.Hence the necessity of arriving  at some measure of control of the traffic in arms.  Owing tothese considerations,  the  Third Committee recommends  to the  Assembly the adoption of thefollowing resolution :              The Assembly, having considered the Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission,         is of opinion that there is no  step which could  usefully be taken in connection with         surplus stocks of arms and munitions except by means of the control of the international         traffic in arms.                                 4. PRIVATE MANUFACTURE.    The Assembly, at its  session in 1921,  took into  consideration an elaborate  report on thesubject of private manufacture of armaments prepared by the Temporary Mixed Commission.This report  set out the evils alleged to result from the private manufacture of armaments and
 I V,X&apos;E jiade certain suggestions of a general nature as to how these evils might be dealt with. The Tem- jporary Mixed Commission did not at that time put forward any general conclusion as to the desi- ability or possibility of prohibiting altogether private manufacture.  They pointed out, however, the  great difficulties of absolute prohibition,  and suggested that it might be more practicable to secure a strict, control of private manufacture without proceeding  to absolute abolition.  The temporary Mixed Commission also proposed that a conference should be called  to draw up an nternational convention on the subject and that it should, itself be charged with the duty of prepar- ng  a draft convention for the consideration  of this conference. They added that the conference, to be successful, must necessarily include States  not Members of the League.    The Temporary Mixed Commission further pointed out that, whatever might be done regarding the  prohibition or control of private manufacture, an important step in securing the effective abolition of the evils resulting from private manufacture lay in establishing a strict control over, and securing strict publicity for, the international traffic in arms.  They therefore urged that the Arms Traffic Convention of St. Germain should be brought  into effect at the earliest  possible moment.    Since  the last Assembly, however, the St. Germain Convention has not been brought  into force. Moreover, the Temporary Mixed Commission found more difficulty in working out. a draft Convention than had been anticipated.  The Council, therefore, did not summon the international conference which had been suggested.    At its last session, this year, the Temporary Mixed Commission adopted a definite proposal for the control of private companies engaged in the manufacture of arms and suggested that this proposal might serve as the basis for the labours of the conference which had been proposed.  The Third Committee shares the view of the Temporary Mixed Commission and suggests that the Tem- porary Mixed Commission should elaborate  the proposal which it has adopted in the form of a draft, convention, and that at the appropriate moment the Council  should summon an intema- tional conference for its consideration.  Since, however, it is desirable that this  conference should also deal with the subject of the arms traffic, it is evident that it cannot be summoned until a definite programme of action in connection with the arms traffic has been agreed upon..  The Asseni- bly, therefore, can do no more than invite the Council to  summon the conference at the moment that it  shall judge  opportune; and the Third  Committee  accordingly proposes the following Resolution:             The Assembly,  having noted the  proposal of  the Temporary Mixed Commission        for an international agreement for the control of the manufacture of arms by private        companies, urges on the Council to consider  the advisability of summoning at an appro-        priate  moment a conference of the Members of the League to  embody  this agreement        in the form of a convention.  The Assembly is further of the view  that States not Members        of the  League should be invited to participate in this conference and to co-operate in        the policy on which it may agree.                                   5. ARMS TRAFFIC.    1. The international traffic in arms has long been the subject of consideration by Govern-ments. As long ago as 1887,  a treaty on the matter  was agreed to by a number  of Powers. Thesubject, was discussed at the Peace Conference in Paris and a new treaty to replace that of 1887was di-awn up and signed by the Powers who took part in the Conference.    Since then it has been the subject of consideration by the Permanent Advisory Commission andthe  Temporary Mixed Commission, as well  as by the  Assembly of the League at both its pre-vious meetings and  on a number of occasions by the Council. On all those occasions it has beenagreed that it is pre-eminently in the interest of civilisation that the international ti-affic in armsshould be subjected to control by international action.    It is unnecessary to elaborate the reasons for this opinion.  Every Member of the assembly is doubtless aware of the grave and sordid scandals connected with the trade in arms.    2. The Arms Traffic Convention which  was signed at St.. Germain  in September 1919 was intended to fulfil the two following purposes:     (a)  To prevent the importation of arms, except under the strictest possible control, to certaindefined areas inhabited by backward peoples.  The purpose of this part of the  Treaty is evident.The task of preventing bloodshed in great parts of Africa and in the countries which border theRed Sea is rendered  far more difficult  if the inhabitants have access to unlimited quantitiesof arms and  munitions.  It  was felt to be especially desirable  to bring this part of the Treatyquickly  into  effect in order to prevent dissemination to these parts of the world of the surplusstocks left over from the war.     (b)  To secure by a  system of licensing  full publicity for all  international traffic in arms.The parties to the Convention undertook not to allow the export of arms from  their territoriesexcept with a licence from the Government  authorities, which should indicate the quantities theexport of  which was allowed, and the destination to which the\r were sent.     The Treaty further provided that copies of these licences should immediately be forwarded to a central office to be established under the League, and that they should be  published.  It was believed that, by securing in  this way the fullest publicity for traffic in  arms, something at  leastwould be done to get rid of the evils attendant upon it.     The Convention of St. Germain was drafted on the assumption that it would be universallyaccepted by the Governments of all countries. While, of course,it is essential to secure the co-opera-tion of countries which produce arms and munitions, it is nevertheless desirable that every country,whether it produces arms or not, should be a party to such a Convention.
    3 - When the St. Germain Convention was signed, the principal parties to it also agreed to a supple-mentary protocol to the effect that they would bring its provisions into immediate effect  without waiting  for formal ratification. This protocol, unfortunately, was not acted upon, except by a few of the principal signatories and in respect only of the defined backward areas mentioned above.Since then, great efforts have been made to bring into force the Convention. At both meetingsof the Assembly  of the League very strong resolutions were agreed to urging the Governmentsof Members of the League and of States outside the League to ratify the Convention or to adhere toit as the case might be. The Council of the League has addressed a number of letters to the  Govern-ments inviting them to act in accordance with these Assembly Resolutions. In reply to these letters, thirty-four Governments have, up to the present, expressed their views  on the -subject.Of these, eleven Governments  have actually ratified the Convention and four others have expressed their willingness  to adhere to it.  The remainder, including all the principal signatories, except the United States of America, and also the other States which produce arms and munitions, haveexpressed their willingness to ratify the Convention when all the other producing States are readyto do so.  Germany and Austria, which used, to be great producers  of arms, are bound under theprovisions of the Peace Treaty by the St. Germain Convention.     It therefore appeared that, as the result of three years of continuous effort,  the Council andthe Assembly of the League might have had reason to hope that the Convention of St. Germainwould be  generally brought into effect without undue delay.  On July 28th, 1922, however, theDepartment of State of the United States Government addressed a communication to the Secretary-General in which it informed him that the United States  Government found itself unable to approve the provisions  of the Convention or to give any assurance of its ratification.  This replyput  an  end to the hopes that the Convention of St. Germain in its present form would receivegeneral acceptance.     4.  As has already been said, it is most desirable that some treaty should be universally accepted for the control of the international trade in arms, and that all civilised countries should co-operate in a common policy  of regulation.     Whether that can be done, however, depends on the attitude of the United States of America.It is important,  therefore, that the Members of the League should endeavour in every way tomeet the  views of the United States Government and to secure their co-operation in a common policy.  Since, in the letter addressed to the Secretary-General on  July 28th, the Department ofState says that &quot;The Government of the United States is in cordial sympathy with efforts to restricttraffic in  arms and munitions of war.....&quot;  and that  &quot;It  is desirous to co-operate for the purposeof suitably controlling the traffic&quot;, there is good ground for hoping that some arrangement for com-mon action on the part of the  Members of the League and of the United States may yet be arrived at.     The Committee therefore proposes that the Assembly should pass  the following resolutions:             1. That it is highly desirable that the Government of the United States should express         the objections which it has to formulate against the provisions of the Convention of St.         Germain, and any proposals  which it may care to make as to the way in which these         objections can be overcome.             2.  That the Temporary  Mixed Commission should be instructed to prepare a plan         for the control of the international trade in arms, which can be considered by the Confer-         ence which is  to deal with private manufacture of  arms.             3. That the Assembly requests the Council to take such steps as it thinks advisable         to carry out the purposes above indicated.6.  CHEMICAL WARFARE.    The Assembly, at its last session, suggested that the Temporary Mixed Commission should make enquiries as to whether any useful purpose could be served by inviting the scientists of the world to publish their discoveries in the realm of chemical warfare.  It was believed that this proposal,if carried out, might minimise the danger that chemical discoveries would be utilised for aggres-sive attack.    The Temporary Mixed Commission, however, after careful enquiry, came to the conclusionthat such an invitation as had been suggested could serve no useful purpose.  They also agreed that,although conventions forbidding the use of gas in time of war might have  great moral value, yet no treaty stipulation could certainly prevent secret preparation for chemical warfare.  There isonly too much reason to fear, after the experience of the late war, that any country fighting forits life will avail itself of whatever weapon it may find it possible to use effectively. It is therefore necessary, however unfortunate it may be, to anticipate that if another war breaks out chemicalweapons will be used.    The Committee  is  deeply impressed with  the terrible  nature of the results which would follow from such use. Great development has already occurred since the termination of hostilities in chemical discoveries for use in war. The progress in the manufacture of bombs for use in air-craft has been no less remarkable. The largest bomb used in the war was insignificant in its effectcompared with bombs which could and would be used in any war which  might now break out.    The Committee  considers that it is vital that the peoples of the whole world should under-stand the issue which they have to  face, and with this object the Temporary Mixed Commissionagreed to appoint a small committee to study  the development  of chemical warfare  and to
 !  * 7.  STATEMENTS  OF GOVERNMENTS ON THE  REQUIREMENTS  OF THEIR NATIONAL  SECURITY.    Article 8  of the Covenant provides that  &quot;The Council, taking account of the geographicalsituation and  circumstances of each State, shall formulate plans for the reduction [of armaments]for the consideration and action of the several Governments.&quot;    In order  that they might be able to take into account the  geographical  situation and anyspecial circumstances which the Members of the League might  wish to put  forward as important to their national security, the Council,  on the proposal of the Temporary Mixed Commission,addressed an enquiry to  the Members of the League inviting them to make statements as to the considerations which they wished to urge in this connection. The purpose of this enquiry was to discover, not  only the  geographical considerations which affect the defence of various countries,but also the  political dangers which the Governments have to take into account, the extent towhich the  forces they maintain are required for internal purposes and to  what extent they arerequired for defence against the  danger of aggression from without.  It  was believed that the statements made by the Governments in reply to the Council&apos;s enquiry would provide materialwith which the Temporary Mixed Commission could prepare  plans for the reduction of armaments.    Up to the present time  the Temporary Mixed Commission has received and has taken intoconsideration statements made by the Governments of twenty-six Members of the League, including all the greater military Powers.  The Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission shows that these statements will be of great value in  its future work.  The statements, for the most part, have dealtadequately with all the considerations enumerated in Article 8  of  the Covenant.  They show thatthe forces maintained by the various Governments for the purpose of the maintenance of internal order are relatively very small; that,  in consequence, the military effort made by the various countries is  almost exclusively intended as defence against aggression from without; and that the dangers of such aggression result from political situations in which it may be hoped that the action of theLeague will be of value.    It is evidently desirable that the other Members of the  League which have not as yet found it possible to send in statements in reply to the enquiries made by the Council should do so withoutdelay.    The Third Committee accordingly recommends the following Resolution for adoption by theAssembly:             The  Assembly, having  considered the  answers  which have been  made  by the        Governments of twenty-six Members of the League to the enquiry as to the requirements        of national security issued  to them by the Council, desires to express its opinion of the        high  value of those replies as affording a basis for the further deliberations of the Tempo-        rary Mixed Commission, and recommends to the Council that it should once again urge        the Members of the League which have not yet sent  in their  replies to  do so without        delay.                              8. EXCHANGE  OF INFORMATION.    The Temporary Mixed Commission,  in its report, points out that the statements made bythe various Governments in reply to the enquiry of the Council constitute, in fact, an interchange irepare a report upon its probable effects in any future war. The Committee is of opinion that the Temporary Mixed Commission were well advised in taking this action, and  it considers that the Report of the Committee when  it is completed should receive  the greatest possible publicity. It therefore recommends the following Resolution:            The Assembly, having considered the Report of the Temporary Mixed  Commission        on the subject of the development of chemical warfare, approves its  action in establishing        a special Sub-Committee to report on its probable effects in any future war, and urges        upon the Council and the Temporary Mixed Commission that every measure should be        taken to secure the  fullest publicity for its report.    The Third Committee also took into consideration two proposals put forward for the control oi the use of poison gas in time of war.  The first proposal, by M. Urrutia, delegate of Colombia, was to the effect that the Temporary Mixed Commission should be asked to consider the advisability- bility of drawing up a treaty for signature by the Members of the League at the Fourth Assembly for the extension to all Powers of the treaty concerning the use of gas in warfare agreed upon at the Washington  Conference.    The second proposal, by Sir Mark Sheldon,  delegate for Australia, was to the effect that the Assembly should adopt a resolution urging the Governments to adhere to the Washington Conven-tion concerning the use of poison gas and submarines in war.    M. Urrutia, being desirous of obtaining a definite decision, agreed to withdraw his own pro-posal in favour of that of Sir Mark Sheldon, and the Third Committee adopted the followingResolution:            The Assembly requests the Council to recommend the Members of the League and        other nations to give their adhesion to the Treaty of Washington (February 6th, 1922) in        relation to the use of asphyxiating gas and submarines in war and other similar matters.
                              9.  WASHINGTON  CONFERENCE.    The Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission rightly points out that, despite the great political  difficulties from which the world  is at  present  suffering, the spirit of international co--operation aiming at peace which inspires the  League of Nations  can also be observed at work-in other places.  The T.M.C, sees two  examples  of this spirit in the Conference which took place at Washington during last autumn, and the Pan-American Congress which will take place inSantiago during the  coming spring.    At the suggestion of theT.M.C.,the Second Assembly had declared that &quot;no complete schemeof reduction of armaments can be carried out without the co-operation of the United States, Germanyand Russia. In particular, the naval strength of the first-named Power makes any scheme of naval disarmament impossible without her support, and it is for that reason, among others,  that theCommittee warmly welcomes the forthcoming Conference at Washington, and trusts  that it maybe fruitful  in securing a large measure of reduction of armaments.&quot;    In its Report to the Council, the T.M.G. expresses &quot;its satisfaction at the work accomplishedat Washington in connection with the reduction  of naval armaments.&quot;  The Third Committeeis sure that the Assembly will heartily endorse the satisfaction of the Temporary Mixed commission at the success achieved in Washington in a problem in which it takes so deep an interest.                       io. PAN-AMERICAN CONFERENCE AT SANTIAGO.    The fact that the question of the reduction of armaments was to be submitted to the coiningPan-American Conference at Santiago was communicated to the T.M.G. by its Chilian Member,M. Rivas-Vicuna.    In its general Report, the  Commission  naturally expressed its  interest in this question, onwhich it adopted the following resolution:             &quot;The Temporary Mixed Commission notes the declarations made at its fourth Session        by M. Rivas-Vicuna, on behalf of the Chilian Government, and welcomes  with interest        the Chilian Governments intention of submitting the question of disarmament to the        Pan-American Congress which is to meet at Santiago in March 1923.             &quot;The Commission expresses the hope that the Congress may arrive at practical        solutions capable of being fitted into  the more general scheme of disarmament which is        the subject of the Commission^ own labours.&quot;    This subject was raised during the debates of the Third Committee in  connection with theproposed extension of the principles of  the Washington Treaty to the non-signatory Powers,and  M. Rivas-Vicuna  expressed the opinion  that  &quot;the co-operation  of the technical organi-sations of the League of Nations and of those which contributed  to the Washington conference would be of inestimable value for the work  of the Santiago Conference.&quot;    The Third Committee decided to adopt as its own the above resolution taken on the matter by the  Temporary Mixed Commission.                      II.  REDUCTION  OF NAVAL ARMAMENTS.    Tbe Third Committee has considered the recommendations made by the Temporary Mixed&apos;Commission for the extension to other Powers of the principles of the Washington Treaty for thelimitation naval armaments agreed to by  the United States,  the British Empire, France, Italyand Japan.  This part of the Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission has given peculiar saris-faction to the members of the Third Committee, because it contains a definite recommendation for practical action, which the Committee trusts may be realised without great delay.    The Temporary Mixed- Commission forwarded to the Council and the Assembly a draft treaty on the  subject,  which had been  drawn  up by  the  Naval Sub-Commission of the PermanentAdvisory Commission.  This treaty is modelled very closely on that agreed to by the Washington&apos;Conference and provides for the limitation  of the total  tonnage in capital ships and  aircraft car-riers to  be maintained by the various Powers, and also for the limitation of the size and armamentof capital ships and other  craft.  As proposed in the report of the Naval Sub-Commission which accompanied  the  draft treaty, it would provide a &quot;naval holiday&quot; for ten years.  The  Tern-of information not unlike that which the Members of the League undertook to carry out in accor-dance with the last paragraph of Article 8 of the Covenant.    The question was submitted to the Council by the Permanent Advisory Commission two yearsago.   In the opinion of the Third Committee, it is most desirable that the complete interchange of information contemplated by Article 8 of the Covenant should take place, and it therefore!recommends for adoption the following resolution:            The Assembly approves  the recommendation of the Temporary Mixed Commission         that the Council should consider whether the time has not come to discuss the applica-         tion of the paragraph of Article 8 of the Covenant relating to the exchange of military         information between States Members of the League.
  t                III.   REDUCTION  OF LAND AND  AIR ARMAMENTS.   In its  consideration of a plan for the reduction of land armaments, the Temporary mixed commission began its deliberations on the basis of resolutions laid before it by Lord Eshcr. Theseesolutions, which included a proposal for a definite scale of reduction of peace effectives to beid opted by the various Governments of Europe, was subjected to very careful examination byhe Temporary  Mixed Commission and by a  sub-committee which  they appointed, as well asiy the Permanent Advisory Commission at the  request of the Council. The sub-committee andlie Commission itself came to  the conclusion, which was also that of the Permanent advisory commission, that, in the  actual form in which  they were put forward, Lord Esher&apos;s proposalsould not be recommended for adoption. In their study of them, however, the Temporary mixed commission arrived at certain general principles with regard to the reduction of land armaments,m the basis of which they believe that a satisfactory plan could be worked out.   The Third  Committee has considered the  principles laid  down by  the Temporary mixed commission and has given then! its general approval, without entering  into  a detailed exami-lation of how they can be utilised in the framing of a definite  treaty of reduction, a point on whichthere were different  opinions  within the  Commission.   It  is,  however,  of opinion  that thesemnciples  constitute a considerable beginning towards the task of preparing such a treaty,  andt considers  that the  Temporary  Mixed Commission should be  instructed to press  forwardrithout delay its investigations on this subject.  It believes that the  Temporary Mixed Commis-iion should.work out its principles in more detail, should elaborate the  method by  which they;an be applied  in the framing of an agreement for reduction, and  should  then  formulate as defi-litely as possible a scheme founded on these principles.  As has been said above, the co-operation)f the Ministries of War of the various Members of the League may be of particular  importancen this part of the work of the Temporary Mixed Commission, and the Third Committee is confident that the Members of the League will lend their full assistance in this  respect.   It recommends for  the adoption of the Assembly the following Resolution:            The Assembly, having examined the Report of the Temporary Mixed  Commission       on the general principles of land and air disarmament, instructs the Commission to       continue its investigations on the basis  of these principles, with a view to preparing for       the consideration of the next Assembly a definite scheme for the general reduction of       land armaments.                      IV.  TREATY  OF  MUTUAL GUARANTEE.    The Temporary Mixed Commission, in its Report, set forth the view that, to render possiblethe reduction of land armaments, certain political conditions must be fulfilled.   In the opinionof  the Temporary  Mixed  Commission the first  of these conditions  is  the  provision by aTreaty of Mutual Guarantee of that confidence and sense of security without  which  manyGovernments will not take the responsibility of reducing their means of defence.  This conclusionirary Mixed Commission proposes that a conference should  be summoned  at an  early date toaw up a definite treaty and suggests that this draft  might serve as a basis for the delibera-ons of  this Conference.  It also proposes that all States,  whether  Members of the League or it, should be invited to participate in this Conference.   The Third  Committee  is entirely in agreement with the Temporary Mixed Commission inlinking it desirable that a  Conference should be summoned  at an early date and that all States,hether Members of the League or not, should be invited to  take part.   It  considers, however,lat a certain elasticity with regard to the programme for this Conference should be allowed, andlat it should be made quite clear that the Conference  would not be in any way bound by theraft treaty but that, on the contrary,  it should be free to  take into consideration the  specialrcumstances in any country, and, in particular, the special circumstances of new States which a set have no navies. While agreeing to this view, however,  the Third Committee  feels stronglyle great desirability of securing immediate limitation of the naval forces maintained by all coun-ies, in  order that the peoples of the world may be spared  the economic burden which woulde laid upon  them by increases in the total tonnage or in the size of warships maintained byieir Governments. The Third Committee therefore recommends for the adoption of the Assemblyle following  Resolution:           (a)  That  an International Conference  should be summoned by the Council as soon       as possible, to which all States, whether Members cf the League or not, should be invited,       with a view to considering the extension of the principles of the Washington Treaty for       the limitation of naval armaments to all non-signatory States, it being understood  that       any special cases, including that of the new States,  shall be  given  due consideration at       the Conference;           (b) That the Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission, together with the Report       and  the Draft Convention prepared by the Permanent Advisory  Commission, as well       as the text of the Washington Treaty, should be forwarded immediately to the various       Governments  for consideration.
the Temporary  Mixed Commission put forward in four resolutions  which it adopted.  Theseresolutions are founded on the principle that the reduction of armaments, to be fully successful,must be general. With this principle the Third Committee is in general agreement, although, as appears from Part V of this Report, it does not exclude the possibility that, in some parts  of theworld, the geographical situation of certain groups of Powers might enable them to agree amongithemselves to a separate regional  arrangement for reduction.                                *     From the principle that the reduction of armaments must be general, the Temporary  mixed commission passed to a second conclusion -  that  many Governments cannot, in the present condition of the world, take the responsibility of reducing their means of  defence unless they receive in exchange some guarantee of security against attack from without.  Unless they receivesuch a guarantee, the Governments will consider it their essential duty to put forth their maximumnational effort in preparation for the defence of their territory. The Temporary Mixed Commissionurges that, if the Governments are to be induced to make less than their maximum national effort,they must be given some assurance that their people will not thereby incur a greater danger of invasion.     The T. M.  C. suggests that  such  an  assurance could be given to the Governments by aTreaty of Mutual Defensive Guarantee.  Under such a Treaty every signatory would undertake toassist by economic and military action any other signatory that might be the victim of aggressiveattack. The Commission in its report  point out that the essential  object of such a Treaty of mutual Defence would  be to give every State that reduced  its armaments at least as great a security as it  could have by its own unaided efforts  if its armaments were not reduced. But it also points out that, if it came into being and were generally accepted, such a Treaty of Mutual ,Defence would in fact almost certainly ensure that  an aggressor State could have no chance of victory; that it would not be able to present the League with a fait accompli achieved by violence,and that in all probability it would be immediately  overwhelmed by the united forces  brought against it by  the guarantor States.    The Third Committee is in agreement with the views thus put  forward by the TemporaryMixed Commission.  It further  agrees that  such a Treaty of Mutual Guarantee, to be effective,must be open to every State in the world. It considers that  such a Treaty cannot usefully comeinto being juntil a  considerable number of States have ratified it.  It thinks it highly desirablethat these ratifying States should include nearly all, if not all, the greater military Powers, andit considers it probable that any attempt to bring such a Treaty into being except on these con-ditions might result in a re-creation of the pre-war system of group alliances.  It also holds theview, however, that the Treaty need not be universally accepted before it can come into effect,and it therefore  proposes that the Temporary Mixed Commission should be  instructed to studythis aspect of the matter and to formulate  views as to the conditions upon which such a Treatycan usefully be brought into force.    The purpose of such a Treaty of Mutual Guarantee is, however, merely to render  possiblethe reduction of armaments, and in this connection its efficacy will evidently depend in a great measure on  the  number of States that participate in the Treaty. It is evident that the greater the number of States that participate the more effective will  be  the guarantee and the greater the reduction of armaments which will be rendered possible. But on this point again the Committeefeels that it is not possible for it to formulate any definite views as to  the actual stages by meansof which the reduction of armaments can be brought about. It therefore proposes that this intricatematter, together with that of the bringing into force of the Treaty of Mutual Guarantee, shouldbe referred to the Temporary Mixed Commission for its investigation and report.    The Committee, however, has felt able to accept the broad general principle  that the Treatyof Guarantee and the Reduction of Armaments are the two essential parts of one policy, and thatas far as is possible they must be brought into effect  at the same time.  The Reduction of Arma-ments, in that line of thought, must depend on the  Guarantee, and the Guarantee must equallydepend upon the Reduction of Armaments.  On  this basis the Temporary Mixed Commission is asked  to work out the  process and machinery by means of which the two measures can comeinto force together.    The Third Committee felt  that it is of great importance that, in carrying out this further work  on these difficult questions, the Temporary Mixed Commission  should have the advantageof knowing the views of the Governments of the Members of the League.  While proposing there-fore that the Commission should be instructed to draw up its proposal in the concrete form ofa draft treaty, the Third Committee also recommends that the  Governments should be invited to transmit to the Council their observations on the subject.  Here again, as in connection with the ela-boration of a scheme for reduction of land armaments, it is evident that the  Governments of theMembers of the League can render the Council and the Temporary Mixed Commission great service.    In the meantime, however, the Temporary  Mixed Commission  has already done admirablework in a preliminary investigation of the practical steps by means of which such a Treatylof mutual guarantee can be made  effective,  and in its report  it has laid  down general   principles uponwhich it believes such a Treaty must be drawn up.  In doing this, its puipose has rightly  been to show that such a guarantee as is proposed could be made of immediate military assistance toany State that was attacked.  To this end it has pointed out that it is  essential to find a method (of solving the two main problems:    P rrst, when an outbreak of war has occurred, to determine with the briefest possible delaywhich  State is the aggressor.    Second, to  devise the  machinery by means of which mutual military  aid  can be  broughtwithout the delay which might  prove fatal to the State which is attacked.    With regard to the first of these problems, the Temporary Mixed Commission proposes that the
                                         - T2 -Council of the League should decide, if necessary, by a three-quarters majority, which State  isthe aggressor, and should be obliged to do so within a period of hot more than four days.    Itsuggests that a simple and effective test would be to lay  down that that State is the aggressorwhich has deliberately violated the territory of another, and that for determining this the Councilanight send an expert commission to the spot to enquire into the facts of the situation. It may be,however,  that further investigation will show that a better.test of aggression might  be devised.     For the second purpose, namely, that of securing that  the military aid which is brought shallarrive without the delay which might prove fatal, the Temporary Mixed Commission has made further proposals  as to the lines upon which military collaboration between the State which  isattacked and the other guarantor States might be carried out.   It also suggests that, in additionto the various forms of economic pressure which are provided for in the Covenant and  whichcan  be readily applied, certain armed forces, such as aircraft and warships, are rapidly available and are very likely to be effective in the initial stages of  a war.     The Third Committee has  not thought it possible to examine these proposals in detail, andit cannot  therefore form  any final judgment upon  them.  But it thinks it  right to make ageneral expression of its sense of the value of the work which the Temporary Mixed commission has  clone and of  the suggestions  which it has  made,  and to  ask it to  continue to  work  outin more detail for next year&apos;s Assembly the principles which it has put  forward.     The  Third Committee is  confident that, if such a plan for a Treaty of Mutual Guaranteeas is proposed can be successfully  carried through, it will do much to create that sense of security which will enable the reduction of armaments to be carried out.  This is  the whole purpose of theproposals made by the Temporary Mixed Commission. But the Committee feels it necessary  topoint out with great emphasis that the acceptance of these principles means the recognition  ofthe  fact that, to secure the benefits of a general reduction of armaments, Governments must beprepared in case of necessity to act up to them. This the Third Committee  believes the Governmentsof the Members of the League are ready to do, provided they are certain that in doing so theywill secure the great end which they have in view.  In this belief the Third Committee proposesto the Assembly  the adoption  of the following Resolutions:               The Assembly, having considered the Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission          on  the question of a  general Treaty of Mutual  Guarantee; being of opinion that  this          Report could in no way  affect the complete validity of all the Treaties of Peace or other          schemes which are known to exist between  States; and that this  Report contains valuable          suggestions as to the methods by which a Treaty of Mutual Guarantee could be made          effective, approves the following Resolutions:              i.  No scheme for the reduction of armaments, within the meaning of Article 8 of          the Covenant, can be fully successful unless it is general.              2.  In the present state of the world many Governments would be  unable to accept          the responsibility for a serious reduction of armaments unless they received in exchange          a satisfactory guarantee of the safety of  their countries.              3.  Such a guarantee can be found in a defensive agreement which should be open          to all countries, binding them to provide immediate and effective assistance in accordance          with a pre-arranged plan in the event of one of them being attacked, provided that the          obligation to render assistance to a country attacked shall be limited in principle to those          countries situated in the same part of the globe.  In cases, however, where, for historical,          geographical, or other reasons, a country is in special danger of attack, detailed arrange-          ments should be made for its defence in accordance with the above-mentioned plan.              4.  As a general reduction of armaments is  the object of the preceding resolutions,          and the Treaty of Mutual Guarantee the means of achieving that object, previous consent          to this reduction is therefore the first  condition  for the Treaty.              This reduction could be carried out either  by means of a general Treaty, which is          the most desirable plan, or by means of partial treaties designed to be extended and  open          to  all countries.              In the former case,  the Treaty will carry with it a general reduction of armaments.          In  the latter case, the reduction should be proportionate to the guarantees afforded  by          the Treaty.              The Council of the League, after  having taken the advice  of the Temporary Mixed          Commission, which will examine how each of these two systems  could be carried out,          will further formulate the plan on which the Governments will be invited  to  express          their views and  to give an independent decision for  the machinery, at the  same time          political and military, necessary to bring them clearly into effect.              The Assembly requests the Council to submit to the various Governments the above          proposals for their observation, and requests the Temporary Mixed Commission to conti-          nue its investigations, and, in order to give precision to the above resolutions, to prepare          a draft Treaty embodying the principles contained in them.      V.  REGIONAL AGREEMENTS FOR THE REDUCTION OF ARMAMENTS.  ,    In the previous sections of  this Report, the Third Committee has considered the problemof the reduction of armaments as being a matter which must be carried out by general conventions
entered into by all the States which are Members of the League, and dealing with, in the first place,naval armaments, and, in the second  place, land and aerial armaments.    The Committee is nevertheless of the view that, in certain parts of the world, the geographical iand political conditions are such that the States which are situated there may be able with advan-tage and without sacrifice of security to go further in the direction of reduction, either on sea redon land, than can be achieved by other States  less fortunately situated. For this reason it coPMsiclers that the Temporary Mixed Commission should be instructed to investigate the possibilitiesof progress in this direction, and it therefore recommends to the Assembly the adoption of thefollowing Resolution:            The Assembly  of the League of Nations,             Whilst declaring that the reduction of armaments contemplated by Article 8 of the        Covenant cannot achieve its  full effect for world-peace unless it be general,           I             Desires . to  emphasise the   importance of regional agreements for the  purpose&apos;        of reducing armaments   agreements which, if necessary,  might even go beyond the        measures decided upon in respect of  general reduction;            And requests the Council to ask the Temporary Mixed Commission to take into        consideration, during its  subsequent  work,  the  possibility  of recommending the con-        clusion of similar agreements to  States which might be concerned.                     jVI. GENERAL CONCLUSIONS.    The Temporary Mixed  Commission has in its  Report explained  at  length the difficultieswhich it has encountered in working out a practical scheme for the reduction of armaments, andit has indicated the lines on which it hopes a solution of them may be found.    But the Third Committee is of opinion that, in spite of the great economic pressure whichevery Government feels and  which operates in favour of reduction of armaments, the politicaland economic condition of Europe is so precarious that no general  scheme for reduction of themeans of defence would at the present  time be accepted.  It is not only that the Governmentsof many countries are&apos; preoccupied by  the imminence of great  catastrophes with incalculableconsequences.  Apart from these menacing dangers, the general economic situation is such thatthe world is kept in a condition of suspicion and unrest incompatible with real peace.  Withoutpeace,  without moral disarmament, plans for the reduction of material armaments are vain.    Anyone who seeks to reduce armaments, therefore,  must proceed to the further question:What are the  causes that are paralysing the machinery of international commerce and exchange and producing economic and  political unrest ?  The answer is well known.  Beyond a doubt, thecause that is of overwhelming importance is the intergovernmental indebtedness which is embarras-sing the Governments  of all the greater States  of Europe.    These  intergovernmental  debts, whether they take  the form of reparation obligations,  of relief credits or of the debts contracted between the Allies in the Great War, constitute an obstaclewhich must be removed before the economic life of Europe can be re-established.  Until measures have been taken to this end, there can be no hope that the fall of the exchanges can be checkedand international commerce can again  flourish.  The  Financial Committee of the League has expressed itself as follows: &quot;It is our firm conviction that it is hopeless to expect the economicwelfare of the world to be restored until the problem of intergovernmental indebtedness has beensolved in a sober and practical manner.&quot;  And the Third Committee believes it may be taken as generally accepted that the machinery of exchange of products, by means  of which european nations have always lived, cannot be reinstated until this problem has been satisfactorily settled.    The Third Committee is  of opinion that  action on this matter should  be taken as soon  aspossible. It may be that a full solution cannot be hoped for without  the assistance of the UnitedStates.  But that is no reason for doing nothing until that assistance is forthcoming. With the col-laboration  of European Governments and those outside  Europe which are,  as welfare happy  toknow, read3&apos; to help, much may be done; and if so, it should be done without delay. For all com-petent observers agree  that the time within which Europe can find  financial ^salvation  and thusavert  the disasters that are impending is now short.    The Committee does not feel it within its province to propose more precisely the measures that are required  nor the part which the League of Nations might usefully be called upon to take in finding a solution. They feel it their duty to urge the pressing necessity for action and to repeatonce more that, until the financial difficulties of Europe are settled, there can be no return of poli-tical confidence and stability;  and without these conditions there can be none of that moral dis-armament upon which  any scheme for the reduction of material armaments  must depend for itsisuccess.  It therefore proposes the  following  Resolution:             The Assembly,             Considering that moral disarmament is an essential preliminary condition of material         disarmament,  and that this moral disarmament can only be achieved in an atmosphere;         of mutual  confidence and  security;                                                j
     Declares:     That such confidence cannot be attained so long as the world continues to suffer from disorganisation of the exchanges, economic chaos and unemployment, and that theonly method of remedying these evils is to put an end to the uncertainty which prevailsregarding the means for the restoration of the devastated regions and the settlement-of the inter-Allied debts;     Expresses the hope that, in so far as these questions can be regulated by the unaided&apos; efforts of the European nations, the Governments signatories of the international treaties and agreements which deal with  these questions, and within the framework of whichthey must be envisaged, will achieve as soon  as  possible a  general settlement of theproblem of reparations and inter-Allied debts;     And it  further recommends:     That the Council shall devote constant attention to every effort made in this direc-tion by the  Governments concerned, it being understood that it can only usefully assist in the solution of these problems if requested to do so by the Governments in question.
                                                 A. 135.  1922.TROISIEME ASSEMBLEE  DE  LA  SOCIETE  DES  NATIONS                                                  Geneve,                                                      le 27 septembre 1922.         REDUCTION   DES   ARMEMENTS           Resolutions adoptees par 1&apos;Assembleedans  sa  seance du mercredi 27  septembre 1922 (matin)           (a la suite du rapport de la  troisieme Commission).Resolution  No 23    I a. L&apos;Assemblee estime qu&apos;il est desirable que la Commission temporaire mixte soitinvitee a poursuivre,  pendant  une annee  encore, les travaux qu&apos;elle a entrepris, etqu&apos;elle presente son rapport en temps utile avant la prochaine Assemblee. L&apos;Assembleeprie en outre le Conseil d&apos;inviter les Membres de la Societe a prefer tout leur appuia la Commission dans sa tache difficile et a lui donner avis et assistance en ce quiconcerne les projets de desarmement terrestre et le traite de garantie mutuelle.    b. L&apos;Assemblee tient a signaler la valeur particuliere qu&apos;elle attache a la collabo-ration  qui a toujours existe entre la Commission  temporaire mixte et la Commissionpermanente consultative et a exprimer le vceu que cette collaboration se poursuive etdevienne, si  possible, plus etroite encore. Elle estime que la competence technique  dela Commission permanente consultative  est  indispensable a 1&apos;etude  du point  de vuetechnique militaire des questions dont sbccupe la Commission temporaire mixte.    II.  L&apos;Assemblee emet le vceu que, pour commencer, les Etats europeens existantavant la guerre de 1914 sous leur denomination actuelle, dont cette guerre n&apos;a pas modi-fie le  statut juridique et qui ne se trouvent pas, a 1&apos;heure actuelle,  engages dans desoperations militaires qui justifient leurs armements, soient invites a ramener le totalde leurs depenses militaires, navales et aeriennes aux chiffres de 1913, calcules sur la basedes  prix d&apos;avant-guerre, suivant la methode employee par la Commission temporairemixte.    III.  L&apos;Assemblee exprime sa satisfaction pour 1&apos;effort remarquable accompli dans la reunion et 1&apos;elaboration des donnees statistiques dans un domaine tout nouveau etparticulierement difficile.    Tenant compte du travail accompli et reservant la question  de savoir quelle por-tee  il  pourrait etre necessaire  de donner plus tard a 1&apos;etude statistique,  1&apos;Assembleedesire fixer, pour 1&apos;annee a venir, le  programme  qui lui parait immediatement  utile etpratiquement realisable. Elle propose done que le programme soit  limite aux  deuxpoints suivants:-    1. Armement du temps de paix.    2. Depenses d&apos;armements.    L&apos;Assemblee estime qu&apos;il serait desirable que le Conseil priat la Commission perma-permanente  consultative de bien  vouloir apporter  a la Commission temporaire  mixte sacollaboration pour la partie technique militaire, navale et aerienne de cette enquete.    IV. L&apos;Assemblee, apres avoir examine le rapport de la Commission temporaire mixteestime que  la seule mesure pratique qu&apos;il y a lieu de prendre au sujet des stocks  d&apos;armeset de munitions en excedent  consiste  a etablir un controle du trafic international desarmes.    V. L&apos;Assemblee ayant pris acte de la proposition de la Commission temporaire mixterelative a un accord international sur le controle de la fabrication privee, prie le conseil &apos;examiner  s&apos;il est desirable  de convoquer au  moment opportun une conference des membres de la Societe des Nations pour donner a cet accord la forme  d&apos;une convention.L&apos;Assemblee estime d&apos;autre part que les Etats qui ne sont pas Membres de la societe des Nations devraient etre invites a prendre part a cette Conference et a collaborer a lapolitique qu&apos;elle pourrait adopter.
     V. a) L&apos;Assemblee estime qu&apos;il est hautement desirable que le  Gouvernement des Etats-Unis  exprime les objections qu&apos;il a a formuler contre les dispositions de la Con- vention de Saint-Germain, ainsi que les propositions qu&apos;il pourrait desirer faire sur la facon dont il serait possible de lever ces objections.     b)  L/Assemblee est d&apos;avis que la Commission temporaire mixte devrait etre charges d&apos;elaborer un nouveau projet de controle  du trafic  international des armes qui pourl rait etre examine par la meme conference  que celle  qui  doit  traiter de la fabrication privee des armes.     c)  L&apos;Assemblee prie le  Conseil de prendre telles mesures qu&apos;il jugera opportunespour atteindre les buts vises ci-dessus.     VII. a) EAssemblee, ayant examine le rapport de la Commission temporaire mixte surle developpement de la guerre chimique, approuvela Commission d&apos;avoir charge une sous-commission speciale de presenter un rapport sur les effets probables des decouvertes chimiques dans les prochaines guerres;  elle  prie le Conseil et la Commission temporaire mixte d&apos;assurer, par tous les  moyens possibles, la publicite la plus complete du rapport de cette Sous-Commission.     b) L&apos;Assemblee prie le Conseil de recommanderaux Membres de la Societe des Nations et aux autres nations  de donner leur adhesion au Traite conclu a Washington le 6 fe- vrier 1922, sur 1&apos;emploi des gaz asphyxiants et des sous-marins  en temps  de guerre et autres  questions similaires.     VIII. L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine les reponses des gouvernements de vingt-six Membres de la Societe des Nations a 1&apos;enquete qui leur a ete adresseepar le Conseil sur les exigences de leur securite nationale, tient a declarer qu&apos;elle attache un grand prix a  ces reponses qui fournissent une base  aux deliberations  ulterieures  de  la  Commission temporaire mixte et exprime le vceu que le Conseil invite a nouveau des Membres de la Societe des Nations qui n&apos;ont pas  encore envoye leur reponse a le faire sans delai.     IX. L&apos;Assemblee approuve le vceu  de la Commission  temporaire mixte  tendant a ce que le Conseil considere si le moment n&apos;est pas venu d&apos;etudier application de Falinea du paragraphe 8 du Pacte  relatif a 1&apos;echange  de renseignements militaires entre les Etats Membres de la Societe des Nations.    X. L&apos;Assemblee exprime la satisfaction qu&apos;elle a eprouvee de Pceuvre accomplie a Washington dans le domaine de la reduction des armements navals.     XI a)  L&apos;Assemblee accueille avec  interet Pinitiative du Gouvernement chilien ten- dant a soumettre la question du desarmement a la Conference pan-americaine qui doit avoir lieu a Santiago au mois de mars 1923.     L&apos;Assemblee exprime 1&apos;espoir que la Conference aboutisse a  des solutions pratiques, susceptibles de rentrer dans le cadre plus general du desarmement qui fait 1&apos;objet des travaux de .1a Societe des Nations.     b) L&apos;Assemblee recommande au Conseil que les services  specialises de la Societe des Nations soient,  le cas  echeant, autorises  a  prefer leur  collaboration a la Conference pan-americaine de Santiago.     XII. L&apos;Assemblee emet le vceu:     a) que le Conseil  convoque aussitot que possible  une conference internationale  a laquelle seront pries d&apos;assister tous les Etats, qu&apos;ils soient ou non Membres  de la Societe des Nations, en vue de considerer Pextension des principes du Traite de Washington sur la limitation des armements navals a tous les Etats non signataires dudit traite. II reste entendu que tous les  cas particuliers,  y compris  ceux des Etats nouvellement formes, seront specialement examines a cette  Conference.     b) que le rapport de la Commission temporaire mixte,  ainsi que Ie rapport et le projet de convention prepares par la  Commission permanente  consultative et  le  texte du Traite  de Washington,  soient soumis  sans delai a 1&apos;examen des  differents gou- gouvernements.     XIII. L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine le rapport de la Commission temporaire mixte sur les principes generaux du desarmement terrestre  et  aerien, charge  la Commission -de poursuivre ses investigations sur la base de ces principes, a  Peffet de preparer  un plan precis de reduction generale des armements terrestres et aeriens qui pourra etre soumis a l&apos;examen de la prochaine Assemblee .     XIV. a) L&apos;Assemblee, ayant examine le rapport de la Commissi on temporaire mixte sur la question d&apos;un traite general de garantie mutuelle, estimant d&apos;une part, que ce rapport ne saurait. affecter en rien la complete validite de tous les traites cle paix ou autres accords existants et connus entre les Etats, et que, d&apos;autre part, ce rapport renferme des suggestions precieuses quant a la methode propre a rendre effectif le traite de garantie mutuelle, declare que:     1.  Aucun plan de reduction des armements, dans le  sens de Particle 8  du Pacte, ne peut  pleinement aboutir que s&apos;il est general.
     2. Dans 1&apos;etat actuel du monde, un grand nombre de Gouvernements ne pourraientassumer la responsabilite d&apos;une serieuse reduction des armements a moins de recevoiren echange une garantie satisfaisante pour la securite de leur pays.     3. Une telle garantie peut etre fournie par un accord  defensif, accessible a tous lespays, qui engagerait les Parties a porter assistance effective et immediate et suivant unplan pre-etabli au cas ou 1&apos;une d&apos;elles serait attaquee, pourvu que 1&apos;obligation de venir enaide a un pays attaque soit limitee en principe aux pays situes dans la meme  partie duglobe. Cependant, dans des cas ou pour des raisons historiques, geographiques ou autres,un pays court tout particulierement risque d&apos;etre attaque, des mesures special.es devrontetre prises pour sa defense, en execution du plan precedent.     4. La reduction generale des armements etant le but. des trois propositions qui precedentet le traite de garantie mutuelle le moyen de realisation, il va de soi que le consentementprealable  a cette reduction est la premiere condition de ce traite.     Cette reduction peut s&apos;operer soit sous la forme, qui serait la plus souhaitable, d&apos;untraite general, soit sous la forme de traites particuliers, mais destines a s&apos;elargir et demeu-rant accessibles a tous les pays.     Dans le  premier cas, le traite entraine la reduction generale des armements.     Dans le second cas, la reduction devra  etre proportionnee aux securites que letraite  de  garantie apportera.     Le Conseil de la Societe des Nations, apres  avoir pris 1&apos;a.vis de la Commission tempo-raire mixte,  qui etudiera les conditions dans lesquelles pourront etre appliques l&apos;un etPautrc de ces systemes, etablira ulterieurement, pour la soumettre a 1&apos;appreciation et ala decision souveraine des Gouvernements, le plan du mecanisme, a la fois  politiqueet militaire, charge d&apos;en preparer et d&apos;en assurer avec precision la realisation.     b) L&apos;Assemblee prie le Conseil de demander aux divers Gouvernements leur avis surles propositions ci-dessus; elle demande a la Commission temporaire mixte de poursuivreses travaux et,  ahn de  donner  toutes precisions aux propositions ci-dessus, de preparerun projet de traite base sur les principes envisages dans ces resolutions.     XV.  L&apos;Assemblee,     Tout  en afhrmant que  la reduction des armements visee par 1&apos;article 8 du Pacte nepeut porter tous ses effets pour la paix du monde que si elle est generale,     Tient a  souligner 1&apos;importance que peuvent  avoir des accords regionaux tendant aune reduction des armements, et qui, le cas echeant, pourront meme depasser les mesuresfixees pour la reduction generale,     Et prie  le Conseil de demander a la Commission temporaire mixte d&apos;envisage.r, aucours de ses travaux ulterieurs,  la possibilite de recommander la conclusion de semblablesaccords aux Etats qui pourraient y etre interesses.     XVI. L&apos;Assemblee, considerant que le desarmement materiel exige d&apos; abord le desarme-ment moral,  que celui-ci ne peut etre realise que dans une atmosphere de securite et deconfiance  mutuelle;     Constate que  cette confiance sera impossible tant que se perpetueront le desequi-libre des changes, le chaos economique et le chomage dont souffre le monde, et  que seulela cessation de  1&apos;incertitude qui regne sur les moyens par lesquels peuvent etre restaureesles regions devastees  et sur le reglement des dettes interalliees permettra de porterremede a  ces maux;   .  Emet le vceu que, dans la mesure ou des questions peuvent etre reglees par le seulconcours des nations europeennes, les gouvernements signataires des traites et accordsinternationaux dont ces questions sont 1&apos;objet, et dans le cadre desquelles elles doiventetre  envisagees, aboutissent le plus tot possible a une solution d&apos;ensemble du  problemedes reparations et  du  probleme des dettes interalliees;     Emet le vceu que le Conseil donne a tous les efforts faits dans ce sens par les gouver-nements interesses une attention constante, etant entendu qu&apos;il ne peut apporter a lasolution de  ces problemes une contribution utile sans  que ces gouvernements lui enfassent la demande.
A.  435. 1922.THIRD  ASSEMBLY  OF  THE LEAGUE  OF NATIONSGeneva,   September 27th, 1922.                     REDUCTION  OF  ARMAMENTS                   RESOLUTIONS  ADOPTED BY THE  assembly at ITS MEETING HELD  ON WEDNESDAY,  SEPTEMBER 27TH,  1922 (MORNING)                    (adopted on the report of the Third Committee).    I. a)  The Assembly considers it desirable that the Temporary Mixed commission should be asked to continue for another year the work which it has begun and that itsreport be  submitted at an  early date previous to that of the next  Assembly.   TheAssembly  further requests  the Council to invite the Members of the League to lendtheir assistance to the Commission in its difficult task, and to give  their assistance and advice with regard to proposals for reduction of land  armaments and a Treaty of mutual  Guarantee.    b)  The Assembly desires to express its sense of the great value of the collaborationthat has  existed between the Temporary  Mixed  Commission  and  the PermanentAdvisory Commission, and trusts that it will continue and, if possible,  increase.  TheAssembly  is of opinion that the great technical competence of the Permanent advisory commission cannot but  be of  essential  service in the  study,  from  the technicalmilitary point of view, of the questions with which the Temporary Mixed Commissiondeals.    II.  The Assembly recommends that, as  a preliminary step, the European Statesexisting before the war of 1914,  under their present description, whose juridical statushas not  been altered by the war,  and which are not, at the moment, engaged in militaryoperations  which justify their armaments,  be invited  to reduce the  total of  their military, naval  and air expenditure to the figures for 1913, calculated on the basis of pre-war prices according to the method employed by the Temporary Mixed Commission.    III. The Assembly expresses its satisfaction at  the remarkable work accomplishedin collecting and drawing up statistical data in an entirely  new and peculiarly difficultfield.    Taking into account the work accomplished, and reserving the question of the scopewhich it might be necessary to give to a statistical enquiry at a later date, the Assemblydesires to  determine for the coming  year  the programme which appears to it bothimmediately useful and practicable.  It therefore proposes that this programme shouldbe limited  to the two following points:          (1)  Peace-time armaments;        (2)  Expenditure on armaments.    The Assembly considers it desirable that the  Council  should request the  Per-manent Advisory Commission to collaborate with the  Temporary Mixed Commissionin that part of the work which deals with technical military, naval and air questions.    IV. The Assembly, having considered the  report of the Temporary Mixed Commis-sion, is of  opinion that the  only step which could usefully  be taken in connection  withsurplus  stocks of arms and ammunition is the control of the international traffic in arms.    V.  The Assembly, having noted the proposal of the Temporary Mixed commission for an international agreement for  the control of the manufacture of arms by private companies, urges on the Council to consider the advisability of summoning, at an appro-priate moment, a conference of the  Members of the League to embody this agreement in the form of a convention.  The Assembly is further of the opinion that States not Mem-bers of  the League  should be invited to participate in this  conference and to co-operate in the policy on which it may agree.Resolution  No. 23
        a) The Assembly considers it highly  desirable that the Government of the  United    States should express the objections which it has to formulate to the provisions of the    Convention of St. Germain, as well  as any  proposals which it may care to make as to    the way  in which  these objections can be overcome.        b) The Assembly is of the opinion that the Temporary Mixed Commission should bef^    instructed to prepare a scheme for the control of the international traffic in arms, to be    considered by the Conference  which  is to deal with  the private manufacture of arms.        c) The Assembly requests the Council to take such steps as it thinks  advisable to    carry out the purposes above indicated.        VII a). The Assembly, having considered the report of the Temporary Mixed Corn-    mission on the subject of the development  of chemical warfare, approves its action in estab-    lishing a special Sub-Committee to report on the probable effects of chemical discoveries    in future wars, and requests the Council and the Temporary  Mixed Commission to    take every  possible measure to secure the fullest publicity for the report  of this Sub-    Committee.        b) The Assembly requests the Council to  recommend  the Members of the  League    and other nations to adhere to the Treaty  of Washington (February 6th, 1922) concerning    the use of asphyxiating gas and submarines in war, and other similar matters.        VIII. The Assembly, having considered the answers from the Governments of twenty-    six Members cf  the League to the enquiry issued to them by the Council, as to the require-    ments of their  national security desires to  state that it  attaches the utmost  impor-    tance  to these replies as affording a basis for the further deliberations  of the Temporary    Mixed Commission, and recommends to the Council that it should once again urge the     Members of the League which have not yet  sent  in their replies  to do so without    delay.        IX.  The Assembly approves the recommendation of the Temporary Mixed Corn-    mission that the Council should consider whether the time has not come to discuss the    application of the  paragraph of Article 8 of the Covenant relating to the exchange of    military information between States Members of the  League.        The Assembly expresses its satisfaction at the work accomplished at Washington in    connection  with the reduction of naval armaments.        XI.  (a)  The Assembly welcomes with interest the Chilian Governmenfs initiative    in submitting  the question of disarmament to the  Pan-American  Conference which    is  to meet at Santiago in March 1923.        The Assembly expresses  the hope  that  the Conference may arrive at  practical    solutions capable of being fitted into the  more general scheme of disarmament which is    being considered by the League of Nations.        (b) The Assembly recommends to  the Council  that  the  expert services of the    League of  Nations should eventually be authorised to co-operate in the work of the    Pan-American Conference of  Santiago.The Assembly recommends:        XII. (a) That an  International Conference should be  summoned by the Council as    soon as possible, to which all States, whether Members of the League or not, should be    invited, with a view to considering the  extension  to all  non-signatory States of the    principles of the Washington Treaty  for the limitation of naval armaments, it being    understood that any special cases, including those of the new States, shall be given due    consideration at the Conference;        (&amp;) That the report of the Temporary Mixed Commission, together with the report    and the  draft  Convention prepared by the Permanent Advisory Commission,  as  well    as the text of the  Washington Treaty, should be forwarded immediately to the  various    Governments for consideration.        XIII. The Assembly, having examined the report of the Temporary Mixed Commission    on the general principles of  land and air  disarmament, instructs the  Commission to    continue its investigations on the basis of these principles, with  a view to  preparing for    the consideration of the next Assembly a definite scheme for the general reduction of    land and air armaments.        XIV. a)  The  Assembly, having considered the  report of  the  Temporary Mixed    Commission on the question of a general Treaty of Mutual Guarantee, being of  opinion    that  this report can in no way affect the complete validity of all the Treaties of Peace    or other agreements which are known to exist between States; and considering that this    report contains valuable suggestions as to the methods  by which a Treaty of  Mutual    Guarantee  could be made effective, is of the opinion that:        1.  No scheme for the reduction of armaments, within the meaning of Article 8 of    the Covenant,  can be  fully successful unless it is general.
    2. In the present state of the world many Governments would be unable to acceptthe responsibility for a serious reduction of armaments unless they received in exchangea satisfactory guarantee of the safety of their country.    3. Such a guarantee can be found in a defensive agreement which should be opento all countries, binding them to provide immediate and effective assistance in accordancewith a pre-arranged plan in the event of one of them being attacked, provided that theobligation to render assistance to a country attacked shall be limited in principle to thosecountries situated in the same part of the globe.  In cases, however, where, for historical,geographical, or other reasons, a country is in special danger of attack, detailed arrange-ments should be made for its defence in accordance with the above-mentioned plan.    4. As  a general reduction of armaments is the object  of the three preceding state-ments, and the Treaty of Mutual Guarantee the means of achieving that object, previousconsent to this reduction is therefore  the first condition for the Treaty.    This reduction could be carried out either by means  of a general Treaty, which isthe most desirable plan, or by means of partial treaties designed to be extended and opento all countries.    In the former case, the Treaty will carry with it a general reduction of armaments.In the latter case, the reduction should be proportionate to the guarantees afforded bythe Treaty.    The Council of the League, after having taken the advice of the Temporary mixed commission, which will examine  how each of these  two systems could be carried out,should further formulate and submit to the Governments for their consideration andsovereign decision the  plan  of  the  machinery, both political and  military,  necessaryto bring  them clearly  into effect.^    b) The  Assembly requests the Council to submit to the various Governments theabove proposals for their observations, and requests the Temporary Mixed Commission tocontinue its investigations, and, in order to give precision to the above statements,  toprepare a draft Treaty embodying the principles contained therein.    XV. The Assembly,    Whilst declaring  that the reduction of armaments contemplated by Article 8 of theCovenant cannot achieve its full effect for world-peace  unless it be general,     Desires  to emphasise  the  importance of regional  agreements for the purposeof reducing armaments   agreements which, if necessary, might  even go  beyond themeasures decided upon in respect Of general reduction;    And requests the Council to ask the Temporary Mixed Commission to  take intoconsideration,  during  its subsequent  work,  the possibility of recommending the  con-clusion of similar agreements to States which might be concerned.     XVI.  The Assembly,     Considering that  moral disarmament is an essential preliminary condition of materialdisarmament, and that this  moral disarmament  can only be achieved in an atmosphere of mutual  confidence  and security;     Declares:     That such confidence cannot be attained so long as  the  world continues to suffer from disorganisation of the exchanges, economic chaos and unemployment, and that theonly  method of remedying these  evils is to put an end to the uncertainty which prevailsregarding  the means for the restoration  of the devastated regions  and the  settlementof the inter-Allied debts;     Expresses the hope that, in so far as these questions can be regulated by the unaidedefforts of the European nations, the Governments signatories of the international treaties and  agreements which deal with these questions,  and within the  framework of whichthey must  be envisaged, will achieve as soon as possible a  general settlement of  theproblem of reparations and inter-Allied debts     It further recommends:     That the Council shall devote constant attention to every effort made in this direc-tion  by the Governments concerned,  it being understood that it can only usefully assist in the solution of these problems if requested to do so by the Governments in question.

</content>
</cab>
