<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 764-764</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r  [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1922.SECRET.CP.  4284.                                   CABINET.REPORT OF  COMMITTEE ON  CROWN  AND  GOVERNMENT  LANDS.               MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF  STATE FOR  AIR.     1.  AS stated in the Appendices (pages 2L-22) of the Report of Sir Howard Frank&apos;s Committee, the  Air Ministry holds about 20,000 acres of land permanently, together with 14,000 acres which are in process of  disposal ; and  the management and  control of  these  properties are, with a  few  exceptions,  undertaken, as regards headquarters work, by  a special section of the  Lands Directorate of the War Office, and,  as regards local work, by the Lands Officers of the War Office serving in  the various Commands. In  a few exceptional cases the  Valuation Officers  of the Inland  Revenue perform management work for the Air Ministry.     2.  This system is not regarded as satisfactory.   For reasons very similar to those urged  by the Admiralty and the War Office  in CP. 4I4.H and CP. 4130  against a system  of dual control,  it is considered necessary that  the officers engaged on manage- in ent of Air  Ministry properties  should be responsible solely to the Air Ministry and be  under  its orders and  control.   A change in the  direction  of entrusting  land management, work to the local Works and Buildings  staff, whose  services can  readily be made available for this  duty, has long been contemplated, but was deferred  until such time as the Frank Committee&apos;s Report should  have been rendered.   In my opinion and in that of my advisers, a system which would  leave the  staff employed on management responsible in part  to this  and  in  part to  an  outside Department  is unsound in principle and   objectionable in practice.   The Air Ministry should  be solely responsible for and should  employ its own officers on work of this kind.     3.  The objections referred to above, and more fully set forth in the Memoranda of the  First  Lord  and the Secretary of State for  War, with whose remarks  generally I wish  to associate myself, would  not apply in the same degree to  the sale, purchase and valuation as they do to the management of Air Ministry properties by an outside Departments officers.   Practically the effect of the Committee&apos;s proposals,  so far as work of the former  kind   is  concerned,  would  be  that what is now done for this Ministry by the  Lands  Directorate of  the  War Office  and  the Valuation Department of the Inland Revenue would in future be done by the  new Central Lands Department. To this  proposal I have  no objection to \irge.   Management, however, as stated above, is an entirely different  matter, and I consider  that the furthest that we can safely go in the direction  of the Committee&apos;s  proposals in this respect is to  draw  the small expert staff who would be required at the  Air Ministry itself, to advise the Director of Works  and Buildings on all  technical lands questions, from  the officials of the new Central Department.  These officials, while serving  at the Air Ministry, should  be wholly responsible to the Director of  Works and Buildings, and should in fact be Air Ministry officials for the time being.     4. I observe that responsibility for lands  work abroad, a  question in which the Air Ministry  is  considerably interested, does not appear to be dealt with in the Report. The intervention of a Central Lands Department in the  sale, purchase or administration of lands at foreign stations would appear to serve  no useful purpose.  The services ofthe  local Government and of the  legal and other expert assistance  at its disposal are normally utilised in such cases  by the Air Officer Commanding, and no change fromthe  present system is considered necessary or desirable.                                                                      F. E. G.     Air Ministry, October 12, 1922.[8976]

</content>
</cab>
