<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 765-766</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/      /   /ResolutionGeneva,   September 29th, 1922.THIRD ASSEMBLY OF THE LEAGUE OF  NATIONSSELECTION  OF THE  NON-PERMANENT MEMBERS  OF THE  COUNCILResolutions adopted by the  Assembly at its meeting  held  on Friday,                     September 29th, 1922 (morning).(Adopted on the report of the First Committee.)                                    RESOLUTIONS    I. The Assembly adopts, for the election of the non-permanent Members of the Council, thefollowing rules of procedure;    The Members whose representatives are to sit On the Council as non-permanent Members ofthat body shall be selected by the Assembly by secret ballot.    Where several seats are to be filled, the election shall be made by voting a list of names.  Anyballot paper containing more names than there are seats  to be filled shall be null and void.    No Member shall be elected at the first Or at the second ballot unless it has obtained at least the absolute majority of the votes. If, after two ballots, there still remain seats to be filled, a thirdballot shall be held upon a list consisting of the candidates which obtained most votes at the secondballot, up to a number  double that of the seats still to be filled,  and those Members shall be electedwhich obtain  the greatest number of votes.    It two or more Members obtain the same number of votes and there is not a  seat availablefor each, a special ballot shall be held between them; if they again obtain an equal number of votes, the President shall decide between them by drawing lots.    II. Pending the ratification by theStates of the amendment to Article 4 of the Covenant voted bythe Assembly in 1921,  and without prejudice to the right of the Assembly to  &quot;select in its discre-tion&quot;, in accordance with the provisions of  the Covenant, the non-permanent  Members of theCouncil, the Assembly  recommends that the fourth Assembly adopt the following rules :    The non-permanent Members of the Council are elected for a period of three years, commencingon the first day of January following the date of their election.    Retiring Members  are not eligible for re-election until the expiration of a period  of three years.    One-third of the non-permanent part of the Council shall be renewed each year.    If one or  two of the Members now on the Council are re-elected, their mandates shall terminateat the end of  the first year.    If more than two Members now on the Council are re-elected, lots shall be drawn to determinewhich one or which two of them shall not retire until the  end of the second year.    If necessary, lots will be drawn to determine the order of retirement as between newly elected members, so as to bring up to two the number of Members retiring.    If, for any reason, a seat on the Council filled by any State should become vacant during thefirst period of three years, the State shall be considered as having retired, with the result that,if such vacancy occurs  during the first year, lots shall only be drawn for one seat, and if the vacancyoccurs during the second year,  lots  shall again only  be drawn for one seat.    If such a vacancy occurs after the expiration of the  first period of three years, the Assemblyshall fill it at  the session following its occurrence, but the Member so elected shall only complete the current mandate.                                   RECOMMENDATION.    It is desirable that the Assembly, in electing the six non-permanent Members  of the Councihshould make  its choice with due consideration for the main geographical divisions of the world,the great ethnical groups, the different  religious traditions, the various types of civilisation andthe chief sources of wealth.[P. T. O.
                                                    A  155  T922                                       Geneve,                   ;: ,: .                                       le 29 septembre 1922. .   .-         . &apos;. j     j;;-                .                   y; V  j/,- . ij    &apos;    * TROISIEME ASSEMBLEE  DE  LA SOCIETE DES NATIONS        t.DESIGNATION  DES  MEMBRES  NON-PERMANENTS  DU  CONSEIL   Resolutions adoptees parTAsseriiblee dans sa seance du vendredi,                         29 septembre  1922  (matin)                  (a la suite du rapport-de la premiere  Commission).RESOLUTIONS     I. L Assemblee adopte pour 1&apos;election des membres non permanents du Conseil les regies de procedure suivantes:                  . .                      .    ......     Les Membres dont les representants sont appeles a faire partie du Coriseila titre non perma- nent sont designes par 1&apos;Assemblee  au scrutin secret.                 ......     Lorsqu&apos;il y a lieu de pourvoir a la vacance de plusieurs sieges, 1&apos;election se fait au scrutin de liste. Est nul, tout bulletin contenarit plus de noms qu&apos;il n&apos;y a de sieges a pourvoir..     Nul n&apos;est elu au premier et au second tour de scrutin s&apos;il n&apos;a pbtenu au moins la majorite absolue des voix. Si, apres deux tours de scrutin, il reste encore des sieges a pourvoir, il est procede a un troisieme tour sur une liste comprenant les candidats les plus fayorisesdu deuxi,eme tour en nombre double des sieges a pourvoir; sont alors elus les menibres ayant obtenule plus grand nombre de suffrages.                                                               . .       -.*:&apos;.-?     Si  deux ou plusieurs membres  ont obtenu le meme nombre de voix sans qu&apos;il&apos;y ait un siege pour chacun, il est procede a un tour special de scrutin entre ces membres; en cas d&apos;egalite nou- yelle, ilest tire  au sort par le President.                                                 -     II. En attendant la ratification par les Etats de 1&apos;amendement a 1&apos;article 4 du Pacte, vote par l&apos;Asseinblee en 1921, et sans porter atteinte au droit de 1&apos;Assemblee de K designer librement B selon les termes du Pacte, les membres non permanents du Conseil, la Commission recommaride a la quatrieme Assemblee-d&apos;adopter les regies suivantes :     Les membres non permanents  du Conseil  sont elus pour une duree de trois ans a partir du ier Janvier qui suit le jour de 1&apos;election.  &apos;   Les membres sortants sont ineligibles  pendant trois ans.     L&apos;element non permanent du Conseil est renouvele chaque annee par  tiers.     Si un ou deux membres actuellement au Conseil sont reelus, leur mandat prendra fin au bout de la premiere annee.     Si plus de deux membres actuellement au Conseii sont  reelus, le sort designera entre eux celui ou ceux ne sortant qu&apos;au bout de la seconde annee.     Si c&apos;est necessaire, le sort designera  les membres nouvellement elus appeles a sortir, de facon a. completer le nombre de deux sortants.                                ...&quot;     Au cas oil, pour une cause quelconque, un siege occupe au Conseil par un Etat. devieridrait vacant  au cours de la premiere periode de trois ans cet Etat  serait considere comme sortant,  de&quot; telle sorte que si un siege devenait vacant au cours de la premiere anriee, ie tirage au sort n&apos;aurait plus lieu que pour un siege; et si elle se produisait au cours de la seconde annee, le tirage au sort n&apos;aurait plus lieu egalement que  pour un siege.     Si une vacance se produit apres  1&apos;expiratibn de la premiere periode de trois ans, il y est pourvu par rAssemblee dans la reunion  qui suit la vacance, le membre-alors elu ne pouvaiit qu&apos;acnever. le mandat en cours.                                                     &apos;.    &apos;         &apos;&apos;,                                         VCEU    II est  desirable que 1&apos;Assemblee, dans 1&apos;election des six membres non permanents du Conseil,etablisse son choix en tenant compte des divisions geographiques dominantes, des graiides familiesethniques, des differentes traditions religieuses, des divers types de civilisation et.des sourcesprincipales de richesse.                                                         &apos;;.Resolution  No  33[T. S. V. P.

</content>
</cab>
