<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 774-775</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
p - DO0UM3HT IS THE .JPR0P3RTY OP HIS BRITANNIC  MAJ&quot;fiSTYT S  GOVERNMENT)                         0 A 3 ,1 M. g  T.                   IH3 BBAR SAST. SlTH.ATiOy;                   &apos; ^                                                 Smyrna,                                                   September 29th,  1922.      M. le President, I have the honour to  inform your  Excellency that tho reply to the Note addressed  on September 25, 1922.,  hy the three Allied Powers to the Government of  the  Grand National[Assembly pf Turkey will be given in a few days  by my Government. Confident in the assurances which M.  Franklin-Bouillon,  who is now with the Commander-in-Chief of  the Turkish  Armies, has  given inI accordance with the representations of the  Entente Powers  assembled inI Paris, and persuaded that negotiations will be  proceeded with atI once in order  to establish a just peace,  the  order has  been given immediately to step our military operationss  which were developed uninterruptedly in the direction of Constantinople and  Chanak Kale in pursuit of the Greek Army,      The assurances given by M, Franklin-Bouillon have  proved the sense &quot;of justice which has inspired the proposals of  the Entente with a view 1)0 guaranteeing the rights of Turkey.    Nevertheless, since  to keep Thrace.., if only for a single day more  under  the ad mini strati on of the Greek Army of occupation, is the causa of  a variety of dangers&quot; and of suffering to the Turkish population, it  is indispensable to evacuate the Greek Ircmsdiately  as a matter  of urgency,  and restore Thrace to the Government of tho Grand National  Assembly of Turkey as far as the west of Maritza,  including  A&amp;rlanople.1
     As to the convocation at Mudania Of a 8onference of theAllied generals in order to determine questions of urgencyin accor-dsnce with the desires and proposals of the entente powers, the meeting of this conference  is proposed for October3rd, 19SS.   General Ismet Pasha, Commander of the Armies on theWestern Front, is personally designated to represent us at theconference at Mudania.   If the  date suggested is convenient,I shall be glad if you will designate generals to attend theconforence and inform us of their names.                         (Sgd)   Y0U8S0UF KEMAL,                                  Minister of Foreign Affairs,                   to the Government of the Grand national                                    Assembly of Turkey.., Whitehall  Gardens,  S.V7.1.    October  16th,  1922.

</content>
</cab>
