<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/139/0 images: 779-782</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
      THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.                                 CABINET.         REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON EXPENDITURE (CIVIL DEPARTMENTS).      MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF LABOUR ON THE ESTIMATES FOR      INDUSTRIAL TRAINING 1923-24.ICRBT       I understand that the report of Sir Robert Horne&apos;s committee-D g8*&quot;A.  on Expenditure (Civil Departments) is being circulated.   accord-      ingly I attach a copy of a memorandum (CP. 4288) by Dr. Macnamara      on the Estimates for Industrial Training (1923-24).   For reasons      of general policy I support the recommendation made by him in that      memorandum,  namely to provide in respect of Industrial Training      the sum of  4,691,500 as in the current year instead of  3,000,000      as recommended by the Committee on Expenditure.           I wish to add the following, further points;-           There will inevitably be a Debate in the House of Commons on      the Report of Sir John Davidson&apos;s Select Committee.   If we insert      in the published Estimates a lower figure than that for the current      year, it will be clear that by leaving no margin for acting on the      recommendations with regard to Industrial Training made in that      Report, we have entirely pre-judged the discussion.                                 (Signed) C A. MONTAGUE BARLOW.Ministry of Labour,   2nd November, 1922
jjglS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOV7&apos;ffiNMBNT.                              CABINET.I&apos;              REPORT OF THE COMMITTED ON EXPENDITURE.                        ( OIVII&apos; DEPARTMENTS ).          Memorandum by the Minister of.....Labour on the Estimates                     for Industrial Training 1923-24.SECRETCP.4288.      In view  of  the proposals with  regard  to provisionfor  the Industrial Training of Disabled Ex-Service Men(E.C.S, 10 Part  I) which have been  approved by  theSecretary of  State for ilar&apos;s Sub-Committee and  submittedby the Chancellor of the Exchequer  (CP.4270) for theconsideration of the Cabinet, I desire to  recirculatebelow certain observations which I  had previously placed before the Sub-Committee, but which I think my  Colleaguesmust certainly have in mind in arriving at a finaldeoision.(1)  In my sketch Estimates for the Ministry of Labour1923-24,  I provided fox the purpose of Industrial training the same sum  as was taken for 1922-23, namely  4,691,500.I observe from the Chancellor of the Exchequers memorandum(CP,4270) that it Is proposed to reduce this figure to 3,000,000,  with a possible further reduction to 2,700,000 if the scale of pensions is reduced,   I amunable to agree with this proposal and I would urge theCabinet to retain the same figure as for 1922-23, namely 4,691,500.(2)  The stun  required for this service has always been,and still is,  exceedingly difficult to estimate inadvance,  because the progress of the Training Scheme is directly dependent upon the state Of trade and upon theattitude of Trade Advisory Committees, whom the Ministrycan only control to a very limited extent.   The result has been that in the past expenditure has fallen belowthe estimate,  because trade has been worse than wasanticluated.
 (3)   The  advocates  of the  ex-Service men have pointed to the  difference  between expenditure and estimates as a proof that the  Government  is economising at their expense.   This point has been  raised  more than once in the House of Commons, and  the Report  of the  Select Committee on the Training and Employment of Disabled Ex-service  Men, recently published, emphasizes it.   In my opinion, to reduce the estimate for 1923-24 presents the ex-Service man with an argument for attacking the Government which it is exceedingly difficult to answer in any manner at all convincing to him or to the public, (4)   It must be borne  In mind that a strong oase can,  on merits, be made out for remodelling the existing Training Scheme in a way which would Involve a very much larger expendi- ture  of money.   The Scheme provides in general for a period of training in an Institution on full maintenance followed by a period  known as improvership with an employer on part main-tenance,   and a further period on reduced wages.    The  greatdifficulty during the period of trade depression has been tofind  improverships,  with the result that a large number ofmen  (at the present moment over 4,000)  have been discharged from  training centres and are waiting for improverships whichthey must pass through before they can become  fully skilled men,    I am perpetually confronted with the argument that theonly way  in which the country can discharge its obligation to these men is to take them back into training centres and keep them  there for the full periods laid down in the Scheme,The select Committee deal with this point as follows:- &quot;The period of Training In Government Instructional Factories is not altogether satisfactory; ............ Trainees  shouldnot normally be discharged from a Factory until an Improver-ship has been found fox them, and those who have been dis- charged and for whom no improverships have been found should
 be brought back, at their option,  to the Factory&quot;.    As these  men have  reached the stage at  which they require, and can perform,  a large amount of productive  work,  the expense of carrying them up to the end  of their full  period of training is  very large,  and would really  entail  the conversion of training centres into  productive factories, either  wasting  their products  or competing In  restricted industrial markets.    For this reason I have so far resisted it,  but if the  ex-Service men  were to find a competent and persistent advocate  who  could  state  the case clearly  to the  publics  it would,  in my opinion,  become Impossible to resist  the claim.    If we give the ex-Service  men reason for  thinking that we are deliberately economising at  their expense  and do  not  intend to carry out  our obligations, their demands will  become much more  insistent. (5)  The effect of  any improvement In trade (as  to which see  Paper  T.P.29 by  the  President  of  the Board of Trade)will be  greatly to accelerate  the  rate  at which we can placemen  into  training and consequently the  expenditure during 1933-24.    It would  be,  in  my  opinion,  In  any  case imprudent to reduce  the amount,  and It is  politically most unwise.                           (Signed) T. J. MAOBAMARA.Ministry of Labour, 16th October, 19S2.

</content>
</cab>
