<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/44/21 images: 168-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (44)150th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 150 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at No. 10 Downing Street,.S.W.1, on Wednesday, 15th November, 1944, at 6-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,- Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,.Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Brendan Bkacken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel The Right - Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.   (Items 1-3.)The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport. (items-5.)The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs. (items-5.)Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.
WAR CABINET 150 (44). ^Contents.minute no.                                      Subject. page 1      Civil Service........................      ....      227Recruitment during the Reconstruction Period.2      Prisoners of War     ........................      227British Prisoners in Siam.3      Leave for the Army Overseas       ....      ....      ....      ....      2284      Relaxation of Lighting Restrictions in the London Area      2295      Closing of Shops..................      ....      230
227W.M. ISO (44).Civil. 1.   At their meeting of the 2nd November the War CabinetService. had approved in principle the proposals contained in a memorandumRecruitment by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (44) 598) about recruit-during the ment to the Civil Service during the reconstruction period.   -Eecon- The War Cabinet had noted that the Chancellor of  thestruction Exchequer  proposed  to  receive  a  deputation of Members  of period. Parliament on this subject; and had invited him to give further(Previous consideration to the question of how the measure of ex-ServiceReference: reservation proposed could best be presented, and to report againW.M. (44) 145th after he had received the deputation.Conclusions, The War Cabinet now had before them a further memorandumMinute 6.)&apos; by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (44) 620) which contained a revised draft statement of the Governments views.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had received thedeputation of Members of Parliament to whom he had communi-cated in confidence the percentages of posts in the Administrative,Executive and Clerical classes which would be reserved forex-Service candidates. These proposals had received a very favour-able reception.The War Cabinet Approved the revised statement contained in W.P. (44) 626,and authorised the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrangefor the presentation to Parliament of the White Paper.2. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theSecretary of State for War (W.P. (44) 646) about prisoners of warin Siam. About 700 Australian and 600 United Kingdom prisonersof war had been embarked on a Japanese&apos; ship at Singapore inSeptember for transfer to Japan. The ship had been torpedoedby a United States submarine, and all the prisoners except some150 had been drowned. The Australian survivors had been sent toAustralia and the United Kingdom survivors had been brought tothis country and had now been sent to their homes.The Secretary of State for War explained that at first it hadbeen understood that the Australian Government intended to issue a statement in the near future. A statement had accordingly beenprepared for him &quot;to make in the House of Commons on the14th November simultaneously with the release of the Australianstatement. The Australian Government, however, had asked thatour statement should be deferred as they were not ready to makeone. This change in attitude was believed to be due to the fact thatthe United States Government, who had also been notified, had expressed concern lest the proposed statement should affect an exchange of nationals which they had proposed to the Japanese.The Secretary of State for war felt that as the United Kingdomsurvivors were now in this country, news of their treatment was bound to leak out, and that he ought to make a statement to theHouse before it rose. Appended to his memorandum was a draft statement (Appendix D) which was confined to a narrative of thefacts without comment.The following points were made in discussion :-(a) The Minister of Information said that the press had agreednot to give publicity for the time being to stories from these returnedprisoners. But it would be impossible to hold the positionindefinitely. Moreover, the stories told by individual prisonerswould be far more harrowing than the proposed statement by theSecretary of State for War.(b) The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs said that the Foreign Office saw no objection to the proposed statement if the Australian Government agreed to it. It was clear,however, that the United States Government felt some concern asto the effect of the proposed statement on the Japanese, who hadPrisonersof War.BritishPrisonersin Siam.
recently been rather more forthcoming in regard to matters affecting prisoners of war. Thus, . they had agreed that therepresentative of the International Red Cross should visit prisoncamps in the South Pacific.(c) This change of attitude on the part of the Japanese had first become evident shortly after a statement made by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs about the conditions of British prisonersof war in Japanese hands. But it was impossible to say whetherthe change was attributable to this statement, or whether it was dueto weakening Japanese confidence in the outcome of the war.(d) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that hehad seen Mr. Bruce, who had informed him that the australian government attitude would shortly be known. Mr. Bruce had pressed that we should take no firm decision until the australian government had let us know their considered views on the matter.\e) The Prime Minister said that after the end of the german war it might be desirable to give full publicity to the sufferings ofour prisoners in the Far East in order to harden public opinionagainst Japan. But at the present moment he felt that our actionsshould be guided by consideration of what would best serve the welfare of our prisoners. It was not easy to say what would be theeffect on the welfare of our prisoners of a statement in Parliamentsuch as that proposed by the Secretary of State for War. Moreover,he was unwilling to take action in this matter which ran counter to United.States opinion. In any event, no decision could be taken until we had learnt the views of the Australian Government.(/) Reference was also made to the fact that the War cabinet would shortly by considering a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs about the proposed exchange of UnitedStates prisoners of war with isolated- Japanese garrisons (W.P. (44)650).The War Cabinet-Deferred a decision on the Secretary of State for War&apos;s paper, and agreed that the matter should again be brought up for discussion when the views of the Australian Govern-ment had been received.3. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theSecretary of State for War (W.P. (44) 644) setting out proposals fora scheme of home leave for the Army overseas. Annexed to thememorandum was a draft statement which it was suggested thatthe Prime Minister should make in the House of Commons.The Secretary of State for War said that there was increasing pressure for the posting to the home establishment of men with longcontinuous service overseas. A certain amount had already been achieved in this direction, but the man-power position did not permitany general reduction of the overseas tour appreciably below fouryears for India and South-East Asia Command and 4f yearselsewhere. The Commanders-in-Chief in Italy and other more distant theatres felt that some system of home leave was desirable inorder to maintain morale, and the War Office had accordinglyprepared a scheme under which each month a quota of men from each of the overseas theatres would be given a month&apos;s leave at home.The men would be chosen by the theatre commanders and there wouldbe no minimum qualifying period of service overseas. The guiding principle, however, would be that the leave was a reward for good and lengthy service overseas, particularly in the fighting line.The following points were raised in discussion : .(a) The Secretary of State for India suggested that the scheme should be extended to include British officers and men serving withthe Indian Army. There were about 16,000 officers and 3,000 otherLeave foxthe ArmyOverseas.
ranks in this position, and it was desirable that they should secure ashare of the monthly quota of 1,500 men from India and South-east asia Command.  The shaxe might amount to, say, 400 places.The Secretary of State for War suggested that the problem ofleave for the Indian Army officers and men should be treatedseparately.. The monthly quota of 1,500 would)robably include notmore than 60 out of some 12,000 officers in British Army Units inIndia and South-East Asia Command, and it would give rise to greatdissatisfaction if, against this, some 400 places were allocated to indian Army officers.The Prime Minister said that officers and men in the indian army ought to be covered by the scheme and suggested that theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs might settle, after consulta-.tion with the two Ministers concerned, what should be the proportionate share of the Indian Army, having regard to all thecircumstances.The Minister of W&apos;ar Transport said that it might be possibleto meet a small part of the needs of the Indian Army by grantingthem- passages which would otherwise be given to civilians.&apos; (b) The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he wouldlike to consider, with the Secretary of State for War, whether officersand non-commissioned officers in the East and West African units in India and South-East Asia Command should participate in thescheme.(c) The Minister of War Transport said that it might bepossible to relieve to some extent our shipping difficulties if we could persuade the Soviet Government to use, for the purpose ofrepatriating Russian prisoners of war, the two Roumanianpassenger ships which had been captured in the Black Sea. He-would prepare a telegram on this subject which the Prime minister might send to Marshal Stalin.*The War Cabinet (1) Gave general approval to the scheme for home leave for theArmy from overseas theatres set out in W.P. (44) 644.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs&apos;, afterconsultation with the Secretary of State for India andthe Secretary of State for War, to settle the proportionof the monthly quota to be allotted to British officers andmen in the Indian Army.(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would make a statement in the House on the lines of the Annex to W.P. (44) 644.(4) Took note that the Minister of War Transport would send the Prime Minister a draft telegram on the pointreferred to at &quot;X.&quot;Relaxation 4.   At the Prime Ministers request the Home Secretary andof Lighting Minister of Home Security informed the War Cabinet that in threeRestrictions Qr four of the London boroughs street lighting up to the standardin the London permitted in other parts of the country had now been installed and area, that in other boroughs work was in progress. He had called for a(Previous       report on the position and was doing everything possible to reference:      encourage an improvement in the lighting of London.    It must beW.M. (44) 147th recognised, however, that to instal street lighting in accordance with conclusions,    the permitted standard involved the local authorities in considerableMinute 4.)      expenditure and made calls on the limited amount of labour andmaterial available.    Unless,  therefore, the War Cabinet wereprepared to authorise a return to full peacetime lighting whichmight well help the enemy in his flying-bomb attacks it was doubtful whether any rapid improvement could be expected.* See CO.S. (44) 368th Meeting (0), Minute 8.
The Prime Minister said that, in his view, a substantial improvement in the lighting of London was essential and that hewould like to make a statement at an early date on the subject. Sofar as street lighting was concerned, the aim should be to secure adefinite improvement in all the London boroughs. A return to the relatively lavish peacetime standard should naturally be avoided, butprogress should not be impeded by a rigid adherence to the standardpermitted up to date.With regard to domestic lighting, could not the requirement be withdrawn that householders should blackout their windows whenthe alert was sounded on an attack by flying bombs ? This would stillbe necessary in the case of piloted raids, but the alert couldpresumably be given in a different form if a piloted raid took place.The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security said that,in consultation with the Secretary of State for Air, he would prepare a report on the proposals made by the Prime Minister.The War Cabinet-Agreed to resume consideration of the question of the relaxation of lighting restrictions in the following week.Closing 5.   The Prime Minister drew attention to the debate on theof Shops.        adjournment on the previous day about the closing of shops inLondon.It was explained that the restriction applied only to shops inthe central London area and was confined to a period of eight weeks.Shops selling food and restaurants, as well as shops with not morethan two assistants, were exempt. The need for the restriction aroseout of the fact that, if shops were allowed to remain open after4 p.m. in the central London area, the combination of returningshoppers with office workers going home was more than could be handled by the existing transport resources. Vehicles, petrol andtyres were available to enable additional bus services to be run, butthe shortage of labour made it very difficult to increase the bus services. The position was aggravated by the fact that, owing tothe limited supply of bus conductors, their eight-hour period of work had to be spread over fourteen hours, and this made the workunattractive. If enough additional labour could be supplied toreduce the spread-over from fourteen to twelve hours, the positionwould be greatly improved. The Ministry of Labour were doing everything possible to supply the necessary labour, but, in view ofother demands, it was doubtful whether any very substantial improvement could be expected.The War Cabinet Took note of the position with regard to the closing o shops in the central London area.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,lhth November, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
