<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/20/0 images: 27-36</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENT&apos;Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1951SECRET Copy No..CM. (51)54th Conclusions&quot; CABINET 54 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, SWA,on Monday, 23rd July, 1951, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.      &apos; .The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C, M.P., President of theBoard of Trade.Trie Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.R,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The Right Hon. Alfred Robens, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Richard Stokes, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The following v*The Right Hon. Lord Pakenham, FirstLord of the Admiralty (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Arthur Henderson,K.C., M.P., Secretary of State for Air(Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. K. G. Younger, M.P.,Minister of State (Item 7).The Right Hon. John Wheatley, K.C.,M.P., Lord Advocate (Item 3).41037-1re also present:The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power(Items 1-2).The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Pensions (Item 7).The Right Hon. Sir Frank Soskice,K.C., M.P., Attorney-General(Items 1-4).Mr. F. T. Willey, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Food (Item 6).B
Admiral of the Fleet Lord Fraser of north Cape, First Sea Lord and Chiefof Naval Staff (Items 1-2).Marshal of the Royal Air Force sir john Slessor, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-2).Field Marshal Sir William Slim, Chiefof   the    Imperial   General    Staff(Items 1-2).Lieut-General Sir Nevil Brownjohn,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff (Items 1-2).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Lieut-General Sir Kenneth McLean.Mr. A. Johnston.Mr. O. C. Morland.minute no.13467ContentsSubjectPersiaWithdrawal of A.I.O.C. Staff from the Oilfields.Resumption of Negotiations with the Persian Government.Military Measures.Exports to Persia.Financial Measures.Germany ..................Exports from Berlin.Control of Sale of Rented Houses in ScotlandIndustrial Disputes     ...      ......      ...      ...Conditions of Employment and National Arbitration Order.Education Act  ...      ...............Denominational Schools.British Sugar Corporation     ............Japanese Assets in the United Kingdom     ......Page169170171172173174174
Persia.(previous reference:CM. (51) 53rdConclusions,Minute 4.)Withdrawalof A.I.O.C.Staff fromthe Oilfields.I. The Foreign Secretary said that, in the light of the views expressed by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Tehran, he had decidedto postpone until 23rd July his announcement of the Cabinetsdecision to withdraw the British staff of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Com-pany (A.I.O.C.) from the oilfields. Mr. Harriman, however, had now advised a further postponement as he believed that there was a real prospect of his being able to persuade the Persian Governmentto re-open negotiations, possibly with a United Kingdom mission led by a Minister. The United States Government had endorsedMr. Harriman&apos;s suggestion, and His Ma&apos;jesty&apos;s Ambassador at Tehranhad also urged that the announcement should be deferred. the ambassador had impressed on Mr. Harriman the importance ofsecuring the recall of Mr. Makki from Khuzistan in order to securemore reasonable conditions for the Company in Southern Persia.The Company&apos;s representatives there still felt that it would be unwise to postpone the withdrawal; but the Foreign Secretary said that on balance he was satisfied that it would be wise to delay it for a furtherday or two, though it was disquieting that the Persian Prime minister had so far given no evidence of a change in his attitude. If theCabinet endorsed his view, he would explain the position to theLeaders of the Opposition; and, if it became necessary to make any statement in the House of Commons that day, he would say no morethan that there were indications of a possible improvement in thegeneral situation. He might wish in the meantime to send a further message to the Company&apos;s staff in Persia reiterating the Governmentssympathy and appreciation of their difficulties.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the withdrawal of the British staff of the A.I.O.C.from the oilfields should be postponed at least for a furthertwenty-four hours, and that no announcement about itshould be made that day.Resumption of In further discussion it was suggested that it might be made clearNegotiations once more to Mr. Harriman on what basis we should be ready to with the resume negotiations with the Persian Government. Before Mr.Persian Harriman left Washington we had explained our position to theGovernment. United States Government in some detail, but there was a danger thatas a result of further discussions between Mr. Harriman and thePersian Government we might be confronted with unacceptable con-ditions. The Persians now claimed that they had learnt for the first time from Mr. Harriman that we were prepared to concede theprinciple of nationalisation, but we need not take exception to this ifit provided them with a pretext for reopening negotiations, nor should we lay too much stress on the interim decision of the international court, provided that the negotiations could be resumed substantiallyon the basis of that decision.Military The Foreign Secretary said that he had circulated a memo-Measures, randum on the question of military intervention (CP. (51) 212) so thathis colleagues might take account of the fact that it would be militarilypossible to use forces brought into Abadan in order to safeguardBritish lives for the further purpose of protecting the continuedoperation of the refinery. Since circulating it he had obtained theviews of His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadors at Washington and Tehran, andof our representative at the United Nations, and they all saw diffi-culties in taking action on these lines, at any rate for the time being.He did not ask his colleagues to reach a decision on this point atpresent, but he felt that they would like to have before them a state-ment of the considerations for and against such action.The Attorney-General said that he felt bound to point out thatthe arguments stated in paragraph 4 (a) of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s paper did not in his view correctly present the legal position.   It was41037-1 b 2
his opinion that in international law military intervention could onlybe justified, as a last resort, for the purpose of saving British liveswhich were actually endangered in a country whose Government was clearly unable or unwilling to take the necessary steps to ensure their protection-and that, even then, we should be justified in using onlythe minimum amount of force necessary, and for the minimum periodnecessary, for that purpose. This, he believed, was the most we could hope to justify in international law; and even this could not now besaid with certainty to be permissible in view of Article 2 (4) of theUnited Nations Charter.Thie Cabinet (2) Agreed to defer consideration of the question whethermilitary force should be used to hold and operate theA.I.O.C. refinery at Abadan.Exports to The President of the Board of Trade said that at their meetingPersia. on 19th July the Cabinet had decided to continue to delay by adminis-trative means the shipment of exports to Persia. This had been done,though he understood that a further shipment of sugar had now left the United Kingdom; but it would not be possible to apply thispolicy much longer without a certain amount of publicity and with-out accepting an obligation to indemnify consignors and shippers ifthis proved necessary.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that exports to Persia should continue to be delayedfor the time being, but that consignors and shippers shouldbe indemnified if shipment could not otherwise be prevented.Financial   &apos; The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he proposed to delayMeasures.       for a further day or two the issue, and the announcement, of theOrder limiting Persian facilities for the use of sterling.The Cabinet-(4) Took note of the Chancellor^ statement.Germany. 2.   The Cabinets attention was drawn to the economic and exports from political difficulties which were being caused by Soviet interferenceBerlin. with the export trade from Berlin.   The British, United States andFrench Commandants in Berlin had recommended that, inaddition to the measures already sanctioned with a view to coercingthe Soviet authorities into lifting their restrictions, arrangements should also be made to remove by air some of the accumulation ofgoods awaiting export from Berlin. The Mayor of Berlin was satisfied that even a token air-lift of this kind would produce most valuable results both in encouraging the population of Berlin and in: 1      inducing the Russians to lift their restrictions.The Chief of the Air Staff said that, so long as the Royal AirForce were required to hold transport aircraft in the Middle Eastin readiness for an operation to cover the evacuation of Britishsubjects from Persia, no British contribution could be made towardsany substantial air-lift from Berlin. The Cabinet were, however,informed that the authorities iri Berlin were not suggesting anything more than a token air-lift, of which the British share would be the carriage of not more than 50 tons per day.The Cabinet took note of these statements.
Sale ofRentedHouses inScotland.Control of3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Scotand (CP. (51) 191) proposing that legislation shouldbe introduced to prohibit the sale, without the consent of the localhousing authority, of unoccupied houses in Scotland let at a rent notexceeding  30 a year.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that there was con-siderable disquiet among members of all political parties in Scotlandabout the sale at exorbitant prices of tenement dwellings of a lowstandard. He had brought the matter before the Lord President^Committee on 29th June; and, in deference to the views thenexpressed, he had modified his proposal by reducing the maximumrental of the dwellings which would be subject to control from  45to  30 a year. He was also prepared to give to the local housingauthority, or (if it were thought preferable) to the Rents Tribunal,power to allow sales where hardship would otherwise be caused tothe owner.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The Cabinet had not before them sufficient information to judge what types of dwelling would come within the proposedprohibition of sale. The proposal put before the Lord President^Committee had covered about 90 per cent, of all the dwellings inScotland, and the present modified proposal might cover 70 per cent,of rented dwellings. While a substantial number of these would beowned by local authorities, the remainder would not necessarily below-grade accommodation but might include a number of smalltenement dwellings with modern conveniences. Some of these wouldhave been bought by working-class people for occupation or as an investment. Where they were no longer occupied by the owner andwould fall under the prohibition, considerable hardship might be caused. A maximum rental of  30 a year would also cover a numberof small detached houses in towns and villages throughout Scotland.(b) In so far as persons of small means owned, but did notoccupy, dwellings which would fall within the proposed prohibition,there would be complaints of unfair treatment. If a Scottish precedentled to a demand for similar restrictions in England and Wales, diffi-culties would arise from the fact that many working-class and lowermiddle-class people had bought small houses, usually for occupation in the first instance. They would resent it if they were prevented fromrealising the value of their properties. The prohibition would seemthe more inequitable because the limit of rent was necessarily some-what arbitrary. It was not proposed to impose any restriction on thesale of houses with rents above  30 a year.(c) The question of controlling the selling price of houses hadbeen examined by an interdepartmental committee in 1945, and theGovernment had then decided against control because of the practicaldifficulties involved. A great many sales at high prices had takenplace since that date, including the sale of dwellings in Scotland whichwould now come under the proposed prohibition. Cases would doubtless be quoted of persons who had recently paid large sums for small dwellings in Scotland and would find themselves unable to recover the cost if, by reason of a change in circumstances, they wishedto sell the dwelling and find accommodation elsewhere.(d) The proposal put forward by the Secretary of State presented a number of serious legal difficulties. Should the tribunal which couldauthorise sales be the local housing authority, the Rents Tribunal orthe Sheriff? What criteria was the tribunal to bear in mind in deciding whether to authorise a sale? What would be the position if an owner who had been refused permission to sell decided that hecould not afford the expenses of a new tenancey and left the houseunoccupied? What would be the position of executors who were refused permission to sell a dwelling although they needed the pro-ceeds for the payment of death duties? These difficulties, though notperhaps insuperable, illustrated the need to work out the scheme indetail before reaching a final decision.41037-1B 3
It was the general view of the Cabinet that they had not enoughinformation about the scope of this proposal to take a final decisionon it. Any acceptable proposal would have to be framed in a form which did not invite the suggestion that similar restrictions should beapplied in England, since the Minister of Local Government did notconsider that in present circumstances a case could be made out fora similar scheme in England and Wales. As the cases which caused a social mischief were confined to poor-grade tenement buildings, theright course appeared to be to endeavour to restrict the proposedprohibition to tenement dwellings. Since flats were not bought andsold in England, there would be less risk of such a limited prohibitionhaving repercussions outside Scotland. It would also be desirable,before a final decision on policy was taken, for the Secretary of state to set out his proposals in detail, preferably in the form of a Bill,,indicating the nature of the tribunal which would decide whether salescould be permitted, the criteria which it would bear in mind and theextent to which sales would be permitted on grounds of personalhardship.The Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for&apos;Scotland to considerwhether it would be practicable to restrict any prohibition on the sale of houses to tenement dwellings rented at  30 ayear or less and to bring detailed proposals before them forfurther examination of the issues of policy involved.industrial disputes.Conditions ofEmploymentand NationalArbitrationOrder.(previous reference:CM. (51) 3rdConclusions,Minute 4.)4. The Minister of Labour said that he had circulated to theCabinet a memorandum (CP. (51) 221) covering the draft of an industrial Disputes Order which would take the place of the Con-ditions of Employment and National Arbitration Order. He under-stood that the Cabinet were to consider this draft at their meetingon 26th July. If they then approved it, there might be advantage in presenting it to Parliament forthwith so that the House of Commonscould, if they so desired, discuss its terms before they adjourned forthe summer Recess. The Cabinet might therefore wish to authorise him to make immediate arrangements for the printing of the Order,so that it would be available for presentation to Parliament beforethe end of the week.The Home Secretary said that he was doubtful whether it wouldbe expedient to invite a debate on this subject in the last few days before the Recess, when it might be difficult to secure a full attendance of Government supporters in the House of Commons. No doubt itwould be desirable that the Order should be presented before Parlia-ment adjourned, so that full publicity could be given to it during the recess; but he was disposed to think that it would be preferable to delay its presentation until the last few days before the House rose.In that event no special steps need be taken to begin the printing ofthe Order before it was considered by the Cabinet at their meetingon 26th July.The Cabinet Invited the Home Secretary to consider, in consultation withthe Minister of Labour and the Chief Whip, the time-table for the presentation of the Industrial Disputes Order, 1951.
EducationActDenomina-tionalSchools.(previous reference:CM. (51) 35thConclusions,Minute 6.)5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofEducation (CP. (51) 209) seeking authority to discuss with theinterests concerned certain proposals for modifying the 1944 settle-ment relating to financial assistance for denominational schools.The Minister of Education said that current dissatisfaction withthe working of the 1944 settlement might be eased to some extent by minor modifications of section 104 of the Education Act, 1944,and section 1 of the Education Act, 1946. The first of these sectionsempowered him to pay, in certain circumstances; half the cost ofproviding educational facilities for pupils displaced from anotherschool; and he had it in mind to propose that this financial assistance should in future be available for a new category of displaced pupils,viz., pupils displaced as a result of action taken under the enactments relating to housing or town and country planning. He also proposedthat displaced pupils&apos; grant should in future be payable, not only inrespect of the construction of a new school, but also in cases where an existing building was used as the premises, or as a nucleus of thepremises, of a new school. These two changes would benefit mainly the Roman Catholic community. To assist the Church of Englandschools he proposed to enable local education authorities, not only to enlarge existing controlled schools, but also to provide new controlledschools under section 1 of the Act of 1946. In rural areas there were many Church of England schools which would ultimately have to berebuilt, and in many of these areas it would be desirable, both on educational and on economic grounds, to replace two or more ofthese by a single school; but under the existing law local educationauthorities had no power to provide a new controlled school in those circumstances.The Minister said that the annual Exchequer cost of his pro-posals over the next few years was not likely to amount to more than 125- 150,000. The ultimate increase in Exchequer grant, as a resultof his proposed amendment of section 104 of the Act of 1944, might amount to  4- 5 millions.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, according to hisestimate, the ultimate cost might be in the neighbourhood of  8- 10millions. He did not wish to raise objection to the Ministers pro-posals on financial grounds; but he asked for an assurance that discussion of these relatively minor adjustments would not have theresult of reopening the &quot;whole of the 1944 settlement.In discussion it was pointed out that, as experience at the lastGeneral Election had shown, none of the political Parties couldguarantee that all their supporters would be prepared to stand firm on the basis of the 1944 settlement. The Government would there-fore be well-advised to seek the support of the Opposition Parties forsome relatively minor concessions which would be acceptable to theChurch interests. The Cabinet recognised, however, that concessionsof this character, while they might be welcomed for what they wereworth, would not be accepted by the Roman Catholic community asa final satisfaction of their claims.The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Education to undertake confi-dential consultations, with the Opposition Parties and withthe Church interests concerned, with a view to ascertaining wether the proposals outlined in CP. (51) 209 could be putforward without risk of provoking major controversy overthe 1944 settlement regarding denominational schools; and invited him to report to them in due course the results ofthose consultations.
BritishSugarCorporation.(previous reference:CM. (50) 68thConclusions,Minute 3.)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Food (CP. (51) 211) proposing that the British Sugar CorporationBill should not make any provision for ending the Sugar RefiningAgreement.The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Food, said that, afterconsultation with the Lord Chancellor and the Attorney-General, theMinister of Food was satisfied that it would not be practicable to take powers in the Bill to determine the Sugar Refining Agreement. Itwould have been necessary, when introducing the Bill, to explain thecircumstances in which, and the purposes for which, the Governmentwould exercise the power to bring the agreement to an end, and itwould not be practicable for the Government to do this.In discussion it was suggested that, even if it contained no provision for ending the Refining Agreement, the Bill would be ofsome value since it would improve the status of the British sugar corporation by removing private interests from the shareholders andthe board of directors. As against this, however, it was argued thatit was worth considering whether these improvements were of sufficient practical advantage to outweigh the serious objections to bringing forward a Bill which only dealt with a small part of the sugar industry and would be severely criticised because it made no provisionfor terminating the Refining Agreement. As had happened in theprevious year, it would be practicable in the autumn of 1951 tocontinue the existing emergency powers relating to the British sugar corporation for a further twelve months by a comprehensive Order-in-Council under the Emergency Laws (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act,1947, at the same time as Parliament was asked to renew the supplies and Services Acts.The Cabinet Invited the Minister.of Food to submit to the socialisation of Industries Committee a memorandum discussing therespective merits of proceeding with the British sugar corporation Bill or continuing to rely on emergency powers.japanese assets inthe UnitedKingdom.(previous reference :CM. (51) 30thConclusions,Minute 4.)7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (51) 208) recommending that Japanese assets in theUnited Kingdom, amounting to about  1^ million, should be handedover to Service charities and other voluntary organisations, for distri-bution among former prisoners of war and civilian internees.The Foreign Secretary said that it had been agreed with theUnited States authorities that Japanese assets in neutral and ex-enemy countries should be transferred to the International Red Cross, for distribution to prisoners of war who had suffered at Japanese hands,and a provision to that effect had been included in the draft peace treaty. The proposal in his paper was that the assets in the UnitedKingdom should be divided proportionately to the numbers of service personnel and of civilians who had been captured or interned by theenemy during the 1939-45 war. 60 per cent, of the Services&apos; sharewould be distributed between the principal Service charitable organi-sations, and the remainder, with the whole of the civilian share, wouldbe distributed among appropriate organisations which cared for members of the Services and civilians who had suffered during thewar. It was not proposed to confine the distribution to those who had suffered at Japanese hands. If these arrangements were approved he proposed to make an early announcement on the lines of the draft annexed to his paper. He would make it clear that the Japanese assets in Colonial territories would be at the disposal of the Secretary ofState for the Colonies for the benefit of the Colonies concerned.
In discussion doubts were expressed about the expediency ofmaking grants to prisoners of war as being contrary to the traditions of the Services. It was, however, pointed out that this had alreadybeen accepted by the Cabinet in respect of the Japanese assets in neutral countries, and that there was very strong public feeling aboutthe treatment of prisoners of war by the Japanese.It was pointed out that a reference to distribution of the funds bythe organisations among claimants might lead to the submission of alarge number of individual claims to be met from the small total sumavailable. It was agreed that no reference should be made to thedistribution of these funds: it should be stated merely that the funds would be put at the disposal of the organisations for the purposesexplained in the announcement. It was also agreed that the announce-ment should refer to voluntary, rather than charitable, organisations,and that the reference to Japanese assets in Colonial territories shouldmake it clear that the Secretary of State for the Colonies would actin consultation with the Colonial Governments concerned.The Cabinet Subject to the points made in discussion, approved theproposals in CP. (51) 208.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,23rd July, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
