<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/20/0 images: 49-60</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. July 1951SECRET Copy No.     2CM. (51)56th conclusions cabinet 56 (51)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.I.,on Monday, 30th July, 1951, at 10.0 a.m.Present:The Rt. Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (In the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 5-6).The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Local Government and planning.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C., M.P., President of theBoard of Trade.The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth&apos; Relations.The Right Hon. Alfred Robens, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Rt. Hon. Richard Stokes, M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord Pakenham, FirstLord of the Admiralty (Items 2, 5and 6).The Right Hon. Arthur Henderson,K.C., M.P., Secretary of State for Air(Items 5-6).The Right Hon. John Wheatley, K.C,M.P., Lord Advocate (Item 2).The Right Hon. Lord Henderson,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (Item 4).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Items 4-6).The Right Hon. P. J, Noel-Baker, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 5).Sir Lynn Ungoed-Thomas, K.C., M.P.,Solicitor-General (Items 1-5).Admiral of the Fleet Lord Fraser of north Cape, First Sea Lord and chief of Naval Staff (Items 5-6).THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENT
Marshal of the Royal Air Force,Sir John Slessor, Chief of the AirStaff (Items 5-6).Sir Francis Shepherd, His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Tehran (Item 5).Lt.-General Sir Nevil Brownjohn, ViceChief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 5-6).Mr. R. J. Bowker, Foreign Office(Item 5).Secretariat:.Sir Norman Brook.Lt.-General Sir Kenneth McLean.Mr. O. C. Morland.Mr. G. Mallaby.Contents:Minute subject Leasehold Reform        ...............2 Naval Discipline Act     ................3 European Defence and European Integration Schemes4      Geneva Conventions, 1949............Treatment of War Victims.5      Persia       .........      ............Persian Proposal for a Resumption of Negotiations.Statement in the House of Commons.Payment by the A.I.O.C. to the Persian Government.Persian Dealings in Sterling.6      Germany   ......      ......      .....&apos;.Rearmament.Page189189190191192194
Leasehold 1.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the reform.        Attorney-General (CP. (51) 205) covering a report by officials on the(Previous       problems which would have to be dealt with in permanent legislationReference:      on leasehold reform, and seeking guidance from the Cabinet on certainCM. (51) 44th major points of policy.   The Prime Minister had invited the LordConclusions,    Chancellor to arrange for the Ministers most closely concerned to minute 1.)      give some preliminary consideration to the problems raised in the attorney-General&apos;s memorandum; and the Cabinet also had beforethem a memorandum by the Lord Chancellor (CP. (51) 228) report-ing the results of those preliminary discussions.The Lord Chancellor said that he and the other ministers concerned were agreed in recommending the Cabinet to approve the proposals in the Attorney-GeneraFs memorandum for givingstatutory security of tenure to residential tenants not at presentcovered by the Rent Acts. There had been some difference of opinionon the question whether the legislation should, in addition, providefor some measure of leasehold enfranchisement; and it was recom-mended that a scheme should be worked out on a provisional basis inorder that Ministers might decide, in the light of the difficulties whichwould then emerge, whether it would be worth while to put forwardsuch a measure. Subject to the Cabinet&apos;s approval, officials could undertake this further examination of the problem during the summer recess, and the results of their work could be considered by theCabinet in the autumn.The Cabinet were informed that the Attorney-General and theLord Advocate concurred in the recommendations made in the lord chancellor&apos;s memorandum.The Cabinet-(1) Approved   the   recommendations   made   bv   the   LordChancellor in CP. (51) 228.(2) Invited the Attorney-General to arrange for the Committeeof officials to continue their work on the basis proposedin CP. (51) 228.2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty (CP. (51) 229) seeking the Cabinefs approval for theintroduction of legislation designed to reduce the powers of navalcourts-martial to impose the death penalty for offences against naval discipline.The First Lord of the Admiralty recalled that on 22nd january the Cabinet had agreed that a Bill should be prepared to amend the Naval Discipline Act in the light of the recommendations ofthe Lewis and Pilcher Committees on court-martial procedure. Theintroduction of this Bill would be bound to provoke discussion ofthe existing powers of naval courts-martial to impose the death penalty, since these powers differed markedly from those available under the Army and Air Force Acts. The First Lord was thereforeanxious to include in the Naval Discipline Bill amendments whichwould bring those powers into line with the powers under the Armyand Air Force Acts, so far as inherent differences in circumstancesallowed, and would generally ensure that naval courts-martial were able to impose the death penalty only in those cases where it wouldbe defensible under modern conditions. The detailed amendments which he proposed to include in this legislation were set out in theAppendix to his memorandum.In discussion the Lord Chancellor and the Solicitor-Generalraised the following points:  (a) The memorandum contemplated that for certain offencesnaval courts-martial should have a discretion to impose either the death penalty or some lesser penalty.   No objection was raised to theNavalDiscipline Act(previous reference:CM. (51) 7thConclusions,Minute 3.)
exercise of this discretion by courts-martial; but it had always beenheld that in the civil courts a single Judge could not reasonably beasked to exercise such a discretion. The Law Officers should there-fore be given an opportunity to satisfy themselves, that this amend-ment of the Naval Discipline Act could not in any circumstances havethe effect of putting a Judge of the High Court in the position of having to decide between the death penalty or some lesser penalty.(b) The amendments proposed in the memorandum would havethe effect of empowering naval courts-martial to impose some lesserpenalty than death for offences described as &quot; traitorous.&quot; In the civil courts treason was punishable only by death. The Law officers should therefore consider whether this amendment of the naval discipline Act was likely to have any repercussion on the law oftreason.(c) The introduction of this legislation would draw public attention to section 6 of the Naval Discipline Act, which providedthat &quot; all spies for the enemy &quot; should be deemed subject to the Actand liable to the death penalty. This section appeared to have theeffect that any person, whatever his nationality or occupation, was liable to be tried for espionage by a naval court-martial as though he were a person subject to the Naval Discipline Act. The admiralty should consider, in consultation with the Law Officers, whether itwould be possible to justify such a provision under modern conditions.The Cabinet (1) Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty to discuss with theLaw Officers his proposals for modifying the powers ofnaval courts-martial to impose.the death penalty including,in particular, the points noted in paragraphs (a)-(c) above.(2) Subject to any comments which the Law Officers might offer,agreed that the Naval Discipline Bill should include the amendments described in CP. (51) 229.european defence andEuropeanIntegrationSchemes.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (51) 230) reviewing the policy of the United KingdomGovernment towards schemes of European integration and con-sidering what could be done to stimulate European interest inrearmament. After analysing the causes of the low state of moralein Western Europe, the memorandum went on to outline arguments which United Kingdom Ministers might use to rally public support for European rearmament and to suggest occasions, at forthcomingmeetings of the Council of Europe and the North Atlantic Council, atwhich these arguments could he put forward. The Foreign secretary proposed, in particular, that he should take steps to counter theimpression, now prevalent in Europe, that the United KingdomGovernment were hostile towards schemes of European integration.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) In Italy and France the Communists had achieved some success in discrediting the North Atlantic Treaty and portrayingrearmament as a burden imposed on Europe at the behest of theUnited States. This situation had not been improved by the mistrustof the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.) which had beendisplayed, especially in Paris, by those concerned in the work of theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.). this latter difficulty had now been largely removed by the creation of theFinancial and Economic Board of N.A.T.O. and the arrangement bywhich it worked in Paris and drew upon the staff and facilities ofO.E.E.C. It was hoped that the meeting of the North atlantic council in September would give an opportunity to present the workof N.A.T.O. in a more favourable light to public opinion in Europe.
Geneva 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the ForeignConventions, Secretary and the Home Secretary (CP. (51) 220) recommending that1949. legislation should be introduced to enable the United KingdomTreatment of   Government to ratify the four Geneva Conventions for the ProtectionWar Victims,   of War Victims, which had been signed by the United KingdomGovernment and twenty-seven other Governments in December 1949,and that the Conventions should be ratified when this legislation hadbeen passed.The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said that we had signed the Conventions in 1949 subject to one reser-vation, related to the imposition of the death penalty in occupied territory for certain specified crimes. Since then many of the signatories had ratified the Conventions, and it was desirable, for thereasons indicated in paragraphs 6-8 of the memorandum, that the conventions should now be ratified by the United Kingdom Govern-ment. It was therefore recommended that we should ratify the conventions, subject to the same reservation, as soon as we werelegally in a position to implement them.The Home Secretary said that there were certain features in theproposed legislation which presented very great difficulties. Inparticular, an amendment of the law relating to extradition requiredby the provisions of Articles 146 and 147 of the Civilian convention would seriously weaken our right to grant asylum to political refugees.In reply it was pointed out that in paragraphs 14 and 15 of CP. (51)220 it was suggested that the legislative changes should facilitatetrial in our own courts rather than enable us to hand offenders overto other contracting parties.(b) The Western Union organisation had provided a more con-venient forum for stimulating other European Governments toincrease their defence efforts. N.A.T.O. was proving a less suitableinstrument for this purpose,&apos; since it included a larger number of countries.(c) The difficulties discussed in the memorandum had been increased by some lack of consistency in the policies of the UnitedStates Government. Thus, the French had undertaken to raise tennew divisions by the end of 1951, and further divisions in subsequent years, on the basis of United States promises to supply a large pro-portion of the equipment required. In the event the United states had supplied only part of the equipment which they had promised,and it was now clear that the French would not raise more than fiveadditional divisions by the end of this year. For some time past wehad been pressing the French to increase to two years their periodof military service. They had at last undertaken to raise it to eighteen months, but even this had not yet been brought into operation. Thedelay was due partly to their shortage of training cadres while so manyof their regular forces were on active service in Indo-China.(d) Many of the Europeans attending the Civil Defence Collegein this country seemed to have no conception of civil defence asancillary to active defence. They seemed to assume that in the eventof major war in Europe their countries would rapidly be overrun.This suggested that the general state of public morale in Europe was unsatisfactory.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the general policy outlined bythe Foreign Secretary in CP. (51) 230; and invited theForeign Secretary, the Chancellor of the Exchequer andthe Minister of Defence to carry out the specific recommen-dations made in paragraphs 6-8 of that memorandum.
The Lord Chancellor, while agreeing that there were many legalobstacles to be overcome, said that if ratification was politicallydesirable means must be found of overcoming these obstacles.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) The difficulty regarding sentences of death (paragraphs 10-13)of the memorandum) raised awkward problems in respect of theexercise of the prerogative of mercy.(b) It was not unlikely that other signatories of the Conventionsmight ratify them without first carrying out the legislative changesnecessary for their full implementation. If enquiries showed that thiswas so, it might be desirable for the United Kingdom Governmentto adopt the same procedure on this occasion.The Cabinet agreed that it was politically desirable that theUnited Kingdom Government should ratify the Conventions but that,before they decided to introduce legislation in advance of ratification,enquiries should be made about the procedure which some of the otherprincipal signatories, including the United States and France, pro-posed to adopt. Other Commonwealth Governments should alsobe consulted.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that, if other principal signatories of the Conventionswere proposing to ratify them before passing legislationenabling them fully to implement them, the UnitedKingdom Government should follow the same course.(2) Authorised the Foreign Secretary in that event to proceedwith the ratification of the Conventions.(3) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider further, in consul-tation with the Home Secretary, what amending legislationneed be introduced if &quot;the Conventions were ratified.Persia.(previous reference :CM. (51) 55thConclusions,Minute 3.)PersianProposal fora Resumptionof Negotiations.5. The Foreign Secretary said that after a full discussion with ministers on the afternoon of 28th July Mr. Harriman had agreed,at our request, to transmit an informal message to the PersianGovernment accepting the Persian proposal to resume negotiations,reaffirming our recognition of the principle of nationalisation and stating that a mission, headed by a Cabinet Minister, would immediately be sent to Tehran if the Persian Government would give us an assurance that they recognised that the negotiations could notbe conducted in a satisfactory manner unless the present tension inthe oilfields was relieved. Mr. Harriman had received the Persianreply to this message on the previous day. This reply was entirelyunsatisfactory, in that it denied the existence of any tension in the oilfields. It added, however, that the resumption of discussions would no doubt improve the atmosphere, and that the PersianGovernment would welcome the despatch of a mission. The replyreferred to discussions of the means of executing the nationalisationlaw in so far as they would be required in order to serve the interestsof the two countries, but it made no mention of the later nationalisa-tion law of 1st May.On receiving this reply Mr. Harriman had informed the PersianGovernment that he was not prepared to transmit it to the UnitedKingdom Government since it was unresponsive to the offer we had made, and he had invited them to reconsider their attitude.Mr. Harriman was now awaiting a further Persian reply, but it was understood that he had it in mind to give to the Persian Governmentmeanwhile a further indication of the lines of a reply which he would regard as satisfactory. The Foreign Secretary understood that thiswould conform generally with the terms of our message of 28th July,but that it would suggest to the Persian Government that they should state that they recognised that it was desirable (rather than essential)
that the tension in the oilfields should be relieved. (Later in themeeting it was ascertained that Mr. Harriman had included in hisresponse to the Persian Government&apos;s unacceptable reply an indica-tion of the terms which he would consider to be acceptable, and thathe did not intend to send a further message to the Persian government until they had replied to this response.)The Foreign Secretary, while regretting that the further delaymade it impossible for him to explain the position at all fully in the debate in the House of Commons that evening, felt that we must nowawait the further Persian reply. If the reply was again unacceptable,Mr. Harriman would attempt, on his return to Tehran, to persuade the Persian Government to modify their attitude. If it was satis-factory the mission, which would be led by the Lord Privy Seal, couldbe sent without delay.In discussion there was general agreement that the Persianattitude on conditions in the oilfields was entirely unacceptable, andthat no mission should be sent from this country unless the Persiansgave some assurance on the lines agreed in the discussions withMr. Hafriman on 28th July.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that no further steps should be taken to resume nego-tiations with the Persian Government until a further reply had been received to the informal message transmitted byMr. Harriman on 28th July.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that as the result of a discussion with Mr. Levy, Mr. Harriman&apos;s adviser on oil matters, itappeared that the United States view about the future position of theAnglo-Iranian Oil Company (A:I.O.C.) was less satisfactory than wehad hoped. Mr. Levy considered that oil operations in Persia mighthave to be carried out by a new foreign company, jointly controlled by a number of oil companies, and that this company would not havethe monopoly of the sale of Persian oil. He visualised freedom fromPersian control for the day-to-day operations of the company and negotiation with the Persian Government of the way in which theearlier nationalisation law (of March 1951) should be applied to it.He believed that the Persian Government would agree not to proceedwith the implementation of the later nationalisation law (of May 1951),and to receive a share of the Company&apos;s revenue no greater than wasthe case in other countries where similar arrangements were in opera-tion. He considered that the Persian Government would not welcomeany close association of the United Kingdom Government with thenew company, and this would raise difficult points for considerationif negotiations proceeded on the lines he predicted. The Chancellorsaid that it would be difficult to maintain in the negotiations an attitude which diverged substantially from that of the United StatesGovernment, and this would probably follow fairly closely the lineindicated by Mr. Levy.(b) Sir Francis Shepherd said that the Persian Government hadbeen greatly encouraged by Mr. Harriman&apos;s visit to Tehran, and theirlatest proposals were probably a bid for greater concessions than they expected finally to receive. There were increasing signs of oppositionto the Mussadiq regime. He had no doubt that the effect on theCompany&apos;s staff would be deplorable if a Ministerial mission were sent before we had any assurance from the Persian Government about an improvement of conditions in the oilfields.The Foreign Secretary said that he would endeavour in the debate in the House of Commons that evening, which would deal with thesituation in the Middle East generally, to prevent discussion of theposition in Persia. He proposed to inform the House of commons that negotiations were continuing in connection with the PersianStatement inthe Houseof Commons.
offer to resume negotiations, and that all arrangements had been madefor the despatch of a mission to Tehran, led by the Lord Privy Seal.He would add that, if the mission were sent, the Lord Privy Seal would pay a visit to South Persia at the earliest opportunity in order toobtain first-hand information about the situation at Abadan and inthe oilfields.The Cabinet-(2) Took note with approval of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.Payment by The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the A.I.O.C. had asked the A.I.O.C. for guidance about the payment to the Persian Government of theto the Persian share due to them under the Company&apos;s concession of a distribution toGovernment. shareholders in respect of the Company&apos;s operations in 1950. Thedistribution was to be made on the following day and the sharepayable to the Persian Government amounted to about  1 million.The Company&apos;s legal advisers had recommended that payment shouldnot be made to the Persian Government, and that the money shouldinstead be lodged in a special account pending further developments in the oil dispute.The Lord Privy Seal said that, if the mission were sent to Tehran,he hoped that the payment would not be withheld.The Prime Minister said that before reaching a decision theChancellor of the Exchequer would wish to consult the Law officers on this point. They might be able to suggest to the Company&apos;s legal advisers a means by which payment could be made.The Cabinet (3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to give guidance onthis question to the A.I.O.C. in the light of the LawOfficers&apos; views.Persian The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that a Bill authorising theDealings Persian Government to utilise  14 million from their sterling note in Sterling. cover in London had been passed by the Majlis on the previous day(Previous and would now go to the Senate. Since the prospect, of resuming the reference: negotiations with the Persian Government was not clear, he proposedCM. (51) 53rd to defer for a day or two the issue of an Order controlling PersianConclusions.)    dealings in sterling, but circumstances might arise in which he would wish to arrange for the issue of the Order at very short notice withoutfurther reference to the Cabinet.The Cabinet (4) Authorised the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultationwith the Foreign Secretary, to arrange for the issue of theOrder when he considered this to be desirable.Germany.Rearmament.(previous reference:   .CM. (51) 12thConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (51) 233) seeking approval of the instructions to besent to our representatives in Washington in politico-militarydiscussions with representatives of the United States and french governments on the subject of German rearmament.The Foreign Secretary said that the object of these discussionswas to enable concrete proposals to be prepared for submission tothe Council of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.) inSeptember. The Cabinet had accepted the principle of rearmingWestern Germany so that she could make a contribution to thedefence of Western Europe, though reservations had been made aboutthe timing and method of this rearmament.   Since then discussions
had been proceeding in Paris between certain European Powers aboutthe formation of a European Army. The United States and UnitedKingdom Governments had been represented by observers at these discussions. Simultaneously, there had been consultation at Bonnbetween the Occupying Powers and the German Federal Republic onthe form which a German contribution to the defence of western europe should take. The time had now come to decide whether theUnited Kingdom Government would support further steps towardsputting into execution the principle which they had already accepted.The United States Government and General Eisenhower regardedwillingness to support German rearmament as a test of the sincerity of European countries to defend Western Europe. It was certain thatWestern Europe could not be effectively defended unless the Germanstook a share in its defence. If Germany, and thereafter the whole of western Europe, were overrun, the United Kingdom would be inmortal danger. The Russians had already begun to rearm eastern germany, and to leave the Western Germans unarmed and uncertainof our ability to defend them might well drive them to make terms with the Russians. It was no solution to suggest that we should insist upon the disarmament of the Eastern Germans and thus leave thewhole of Germany unarmed. That would play into the hands of theCommunist Fifth Column in Germany. He felt, therefore, that the risks which attended the rearming of Western Germany must beaccepted and that he should be free to discuss the question at theforthcoming meeting of the North Atlantic Treaty Council on thelines suggested in the memorandum before the Cabinet, i.e., thatany German forces raised would eventually form part of the european army though, if they were raised before the European Army was sufficiently organised to receive them, they should temporarily beplaced under General Eisenhower&apos;s Command. This line of approach would probably overcome French reluctance to proceed with german rearmament, and would be less provocative to the Russians. He didnot wish at this stage to ask the Cabinet to enter into a firm commit-ment: there were still unknown and variable factors. In particular,the proposals for the formation of the European Army were far fromclear. He wished, however, to have a general line to follow at themeeting of the North Atlantic Council where discussion of this prob-lem could not be avoided.The Minister of Local Government said that, although theCabinet had accepted the principle of a German contribution to european defence, he believed that several of his colleagues hadshared his reluctance to see Germany rearmed. In his view theGerman attitude towards the use of armed forces was totally different from that of the members of N.A.T.O. and our other allies.&quot; Whereaswe were rearming in self-defence, the Germans were capable ofrearming for purposes of aggression, and many of them would have ja positive interest in provoking war with Russia to recover their losthomes. Any German army would include ex-Nazis and refugeeswhose main motive would be revenge. The Germans were not a peace-loving or trustworthy people and he himself would not like tosee a German army in being, even if it formed part of a european army. If the Germans were allowed to rearm, they might be led byself-interest to co-operate, not with us, but with the Soviet Union;that was not true of any other European country on this side of theIron Curtain. There was also the risk of offering provocation to theSoviet Union. That risk was always there, but it was surelyimprudent to increase it at a time when we were weak by takingpositive steps to rearm the Germans now. From this point of view it would be better to delay the creation of any German units until theN.A.T.O. Powers were much stronger than they were at the presenttime. The Germans should certainly be the last to receive supplies of american equipment, and nothing should be given to them until theneeds of all the N.A.T.O. countries and of Turkey, Greece and41082-1 r
Yugoslavia had been fully met. He was, therefore, in favour ofdelaying as long as possible any actual rearming of Germany. Weshould not bring pressure on the French to speed up German rearmament -ment and we should certainly not agree to the organisation of any german units outside the European Army, where at least therewould be some chance of preventing the growth of a dominantGerman General Staff. Planning and preparations could go forward,but we should delay the provocative step of putting arms into thehands of the Germans.In support of the views expressed by the Minister of LocalGovernment the following points were made:  (a) The C.I.G.S. had expressed the view that the rearming of germans would be the most decisive provocation that could be offered to the Soviet Union. The timing of any action in this respect wastherefore vital; and it would be rash to set it in motion before theWestern Powers were sufficiently strong to prevent Europe being over-run by the Russians. No action should be taken until the end of1953, when we ourselves would be stronger and the European Armymight have taken shape. The incorporation of German units into theEuropean Army might then be set on foot as a sound and practical proposition.(b) It Would be dangerous to press the French to accept a policywhich might increase the political instability of France and the powerof the French Communists. It was natural for the French to insist that German forces should only be raised as part of a european army and, in view of our relations with the French and our relianceupon them for the security of Western Europe, we ought to accept and support their views in this matter.(c) The rearmament of Germany at the present time, so far from being a contribution to the defence of Western Europe, might wellimpede and retard our own rearmament because of the demands which it would make on supplies of steel and other materials.Against these arguments and in support of the general line ofpolicy proposed by the Foreign Secretary and Minister of defence the following points were made:  (d) The Chiefs of Staff pointed out that German rearmamentwas not the only possible cause of provocation to the Soviet Union.In their latest appreciation they had expressed the view that the soviet union would not deliberately start a war before 1954, though it was just possible that the immense scale of American rearmament and the rearmament of Western Germany, if realised, might lead the soviet union to start or provoke a total war before Western rearmamentbecame effective. While the West remained weak in conventionalarms, the Soviet Union would exploit this weakness by local aggres-sion wherever the opportunity arose. But, if the Western Powersmade it clear that they were prepared to use atomic bombs againstthe Soviet Union, the Soviet Government would withdraw. In theperiod up to 1954 the moment of greatest danger would probablybe about the end of 1952.(e) Western Europe could not be effectively defended without thesupport of German armed forces, and it was better to start at once the preparatory work required before German units could become effective than to wait eighteen months or two years and thus put offstill further the moment when it would be possible for the western powers to negotiate on equal terms with the Soviet Union. In fact,if the measures proposed in the memorandum were approved by theNorth Atlantic Council in September, enrolment of German volun-teers would not begin before June 1952, the first units would not be formed before October 1952, and would then have only a light trainingscale of equipment, and the first two divisions would not be ready to begin collective training on a training scale of heavy equipment before april 1953. No battle-worthy divisions would be ready before theautumn of that year. The proposals could not, therefore, be regardedas involving any precipitate action.
(/) There was no question of giving the Germans any priority inthe supply of equipment. They were starting from nothing, and itwas only proposed to give them a training scale of equipment for thenext eighteen months or two years. It was important that they shouldnot receive arms at the expense of other N.A.T.O. Powers or of turkey and Yugoslavia, but it was believed that the Americans would have sufficient supplies of equipment for everyone by 1953.(g) The proposed programme for the rearmament of germany would fit in with the rate of the organisation of the European Army,but it would be a mistake to insist that, unless the European army was organised, no German armed forces should be raised at all. it remained doubtful if the European Army was a practical proposition,and, in any case, it could only become so if its components were already available. It was therefore logical to accept the suggestion made in the memorandum that German forces should be raised for eventual incorporation in the European Army. There was now some reason to think that better progress was being made with theorganisation of the European Army than had been expected, and ifit could be satisfactorily organised there was no doubt that it wouldgive better control of German forces than a system by which theywere attached as national forces directly to General Eisenhower&apos;command.(h) The risk of provoking the Soviet Union could be exaggerated.The Soviet Government had not been provoked into retaliation bythe campaign for the admission of Turkey into N.A.T.O. Yet Turkey was a strong country on the borders of the Soviet Union inspired bya hereditary enmity to Russia, and her inclusion in a pact, the veryexistence of which was claimed by the Soviet Union to be a provo-cation, might well have been regarded by them as a greater challengethan the gradual rearmament of small numbers of West Germans.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that some reference to this question was inevitable at the forthcoming meetingof the North Atlantic Council, and the Foreign Secretary would be guided, when the time came for him to take part in those discussions,by the views expressed by his Cabinet colleagues. He would doubtlessconsult the Cabinet before agreeing to any proposal involving theearly implementation of the principle of German rearmament. Itwould be helpful if more information were available about theorganisation of the European Army before any further decision wastaken on German rearmament. In the meantime the Foreign Secre-tary should consider, in consultation with the Minister of defence and the Chiefs of Staff, what instructions could be given, in viewof the Cabinefs discussion, to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in washington and the United Kingdom representative on the StandingGroup regarding the line which they should take in the exploratory conversations which they were to have on this question with repre-sentatives of the United States and French Governments before themeeting of the North Atlantic Council in September.Cabinet Office, SWA,30th July, 1951.


</content>
</cab>
