<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/24/33 images: 318-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PR, HBBMmicMAJESTVS government secret .P. (42) 203(Also C.O.S. (42) 261)May 14, 1942TQ B  KEPT UNDEF-----It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 141)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 May 7th, to0700 May I4th,1942[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room
General Review.1. Three of ELM. destroyers and two submarines have been lost in theMediterranean.An outward-bound convoy has been heavily attacked by U-boats in the north atlantic.Shipping losses have been heavy.American sea-borne aircraft have inflicted losses on Japanese naval forces and transports in the Solomon Islands and to the south-eastward of New Guinea.Home Waters and North Atlantic.2. On the 8th H.M. Trawler Horatio, off Worthing, was attacked by sixenemy aircraft, one of which she destroyed.    Horatio suffered some damage.Early on the 12th M.G.B. 67 damaged an E-boat off the Dutch coast, and onthe evening of that day two M.G.Bs. engaged four enemy torpedo boats steamingup-channel from Boulogne. Early on the 13th a heavily escorted vessel pro-ceeding down-Channel was intercepted by M.T.Bs. and M.G.Bs. During the engagement one enemy torpedo boat is believed to have been torpedoed. Unemployment.T.B. is presumed lost and the remainder of our force were damaged.H.M.S. Sirius, a new cruiser of the &quot; Dido &quot; class, has been commissioned.During the week approximately 60,000 tons of enemy shipping have been sunk or damaged by aircraft.   Details are given under Air Situation.Mediterranean.3. A force of destroyers which left Alexandria to intercept an enemyconvoy was attacked by aircraft during the afternoon of the 12th to the south ofCrete and H.M. Destroyers Lively, Kipling and Jackal were sunk. About 500survivors from the three destroyers were rescued. Beaufighters shot down oneHe. Ill and damaged six enemy aircraft.The hospital ship Ramb IV was bombed and sunk while on passage fromTobruk to Alexandria. It is estimated that there were about 150 casualties, mostof whom were patients.A reinforcement of aircraft for Malta was successfully flown off from.M. Aircraft Carrier Eagle and the American Aircraft Carrier Wasp on the9th.  Sixty Spitfires out of 65 arrived safely.H.M. Fast Minelayer Welshman was damaged by near misses in an air attack on Malta on the 10th, but her seagoing efficiency was not affected.H.M. Submarine Olympus was mined and sunk off Malta on the 8th;nine ratings were rescued. H.M. Submarine Urge is overdue and must beconsidered lost.During the week 11,788 tons of French merchant shipping eastbound and5,247 tons westbound passed through the Straits of Gibraltar under escort. TheFrench submarine Vengeur and one unidentified vessel passed eastbouncl onthe 9th.Pacific.4. Following on the concentration of Japanese warships and transports inthe area to the eastward of New Guinea, reported in the Resume of last week, anenemy force of three cruisers and 12 transports entered Tulagi, in the SolomonIslands, on the 4th May, which we had previously evacuated. On the following day this force was attacked by Allied aircraft, which were reported to have sunkone cruiser, two destroyers, four small naval vessels and two transports. On the7th an enemy force of 11 warships, including cruisers and aircraft carriers,covering a convoy of 19 transports, whose probable objective was Port Moresby, was attacked by aircraft from two American aircraft carriers near the LouisiadeArchipelago. The Japanese aircraft carrier Ryukaku (a recently convertedmerchant ship with a carrying capacity of 48 aircraft) and a cruiser (possiblyan 8-inch &quot; Aoba &quot; class) were reported to have been sunk, and the Shokaku, a modern carrier of 60 aircraft, damaged.   Subsequent reports indicated that the
force had turned back towards Rabaul. There has been no report of Allied navallosses in this action. During the engagement a total of 26 enemy aircraft, were reported destroyed, in addition to those lost in the carriers. In attacks by allied aircraft on the seaplane base at Deboyne Island (Louisiade Archipelago) on the9th and 10th, an enemy seaplane-tender was damaged, one seaplane was sunk andthree were damaged.Anti-Submarine Operations.5. A U-boat was sunk by the American Coast Guard Cutter Icarus on the9th south of Cape Hatteras. On the 7th a U-boat was probably destroyed north-east of Tobruk by H.M. destroyers and aircraft. Twenty-one other attacks havebeen reported during the week : ten by surface craft (including three american and two Canadian ships), one by submarine and ten by aircraft (including fourAmerican).The majority of the attacks was carried out off the Canadian and Americancoasts, including one off Dutch Guiana and one north-east of the Amazon.Other attacks were made west of the Hebrides, south-west of Iceland (C), in the bay of Biscay area, and in the Eastern Mediterranean.Enemy Intelligence.German.6. There is no certain change in the position of main units. A. report statesthat the pocket battleship Admiral Scheer is at Narvik, where she is to be joined by the Lutzow as soon as the latter is worked up.Italian.During the week three ships totalling about 8,000 tons reached Benghazi.This is the smallest total for some weeks.Japanese.The main Japanese fleet, which has been in the southern Mandated Islands, isat present unlocated. In the New Guinea area there are probably two aircraft carriers, three heavy cruisers, four light cruisers and possibly a battleship.In addition to &quot;Rabaul in New Britain, the Queen Carola Harbour and the harbours of Tulagi and Faisi Island (all in the Solomon Group) and DeboyneIsland in the Louisiade Archipelago have been used by the enemy during recent operations as assembly ports and fuelling bases.U-Boats.There has been a recrudescence of attacks by U-boats on the convoy routes in mid-Atlantic and to the north of the Cape Verde Islands. Attacks continue inthe West Atlantic and in the Caribbean Sea, and in addition U-boats have beenreported in the Gulf of St. Lawrence and in the Gulf of Mexico.Protection of Seaborne Trade.7. During the week ending the 13th May, 1,087 ships, including 296 allied and 24 neutral, have been convoyed. Two armed merchant cruisers, three anti-aircraft ships, 66 destroyers (including ten American) and 87 sloops, cutters and corvettes were employed on escort duty. Imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy during the week ending the 9th May totalled 692,000 tons compared with 621,000 tons during the previous seven days and an average of624,000 tons for the past ten weeks. Of the week&apos;s imports 110,000 tons^vereoil of various grades.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.8.   Of twenty ships reported to have been attacked by U-boats during theweek, nine are known to have sunk.   Seven ships were torpedoed and sunk inattacks on an outward-bound convoy in mid-Atlantic and one in a homeward[23818] &apos; b
convoy to the north of the Cape Verde Islands. The remainder were attackedchiefly between the Florida coast and Dutch Guiana, but two ships were torpedoedoff Nova Scotia and two in the mouth of the St. Lawrence River.One ship was bombed and sunk to the west of the Faroes and another was severely damaged by aircraft at Southampton.Shipping losses from enemy action in April 1942, so far reported, were105 ships totalling 571,253 tons, details of which are given in Appendix 1. this includes the loss of 30 tankers totalling 224,561 tons, of which six were British,11 American, four Panamanian, one Dutch and eight Norwegian.This figure, although showing a reduction on the previous month&apos;s total, isthe fourth highest monthly total since the war began and delayed reports are flikely to increase it. 67 ships totalling 400,873 tons were sunk by U-boats, mostlyin the North Atlantic, off the American Atlantic seaboard and in the CaribbeanSea. Six ships were sunk by mines, 16 by aircraft attack and 11 by surface craft ofwhich six were in the Indian Ocean. During the month 116,000 tons of shipping has been seriously damaged by enemy action, of which 54,000 tons were Britishand 62,000 Allied.British Minelaying.9.   Surface craft have laid mines during the week off the Flemish and northFrench. coasts and in the Faroes to Iceland area.Aircraft have laid mines in the Baltic and Heligoland Bight areas.Enemy Minelaying and British Minesweeping.10. Enemy aircraft and E-boats have laid mines on the east coast betweenthe Humber and Southwold.Nine magnetic, one acoustic and six moored mines have been destroyed duringthe week. The mine totals are 2,024 magnetic, 1,268 acoustic and 1,236 moored mines.Foreign Waters.Mines have been laid, probably by E-boats, off Grand Harbour, Malta, where12 mines have recently been destroyed. Fifty-five moored mines were swept inthe approaches to Courrier Bay, Madagascar, prior to the landing on the 5th May.Enemy Merchant Shipping.11. The German Wartenfels (6,181 tons) has been burnt out in dry dock and the Italian ships Somalia (2,699 tons) and Duca Degli Abruzzi (2,315 tons)have been scuttled in Diego Suarez.Vichy Shipping.12.   The Conde (7,202 tens) is reported to have sailed from Madagascar onthe 9th, probably for Dakar.MILITARY SITUATION,The Russo-German Campaign.Crimea.13. On the 8th May, after intense preliminary shelling and bombing, theGermans attacked the Russian forces on the Kerch Peninsula with two infantry divisions and part of an armoured division. It is still too early to say what progress the Germans have made.Summary.14. Except in the Crimea, fighting continues to be on a restricted scale andthere are still no indications that the major German offensive on the southern front will start before the end of May or early in June. The total of german divisions in Russia (including Finland) remains at 182.
Libya.15. Patrol activity during the week&apos; has continued. On the 7th Maycasualties were inflicted by. our force on an enemy working party 12 miles west of Gazala. Two days iater enemy columns including tanks, were engagednear Rotunda Segnali and Garet el Asida. The following day, enemy M.T., withsome tanks and armoured cars, were engaged south-west of Sidi Breghisc. Themain enemy M.T. concentration appeared to be still in the area north-east ofRotunda Segnali. Considerable movement of enemy M.T. was apparent in thearea of Bir Temrad on the 12th.Burma.16. Since the 3rd May very few situation reports have been received, butinformation has come in from the British Military Mission at Chungking andother sources.British Front.17. The withdrawal of our main forces continued towards Kalewa, wherea small party of those withdrawing up the Chindwin Valley was reported on the5th. Some of the remainder of our forces were to the south, and others w^erebelieved to be crossing from east of the Chindwin River, having seized all availableriver craft. Our troops, who have been operating at Shwebo, were reported atPyingaing on the 8th, the Japanese then being in occupation of Yeu.On the 11th all our forces were reported to be in the area Kalewa-Tamu, butthe majority of tanks, guns and M.T. had to be abandoned owing to the low-capacity of Shwegyin Ferry. Latest reports are that the enemy are in somestrength on the west bank of the Chindwin.18.   The Japanese have occupied Akyab.Chinese Front.19. The Japanese occupied Bhamo on the 5th and. Myitkyina on the 8th.Chinese forces were reported to be in position north of Myitkyina and in actionnorth of Lashio and also on the Sal ween Front (4th May).Chinese forces at Taunggyi were reported to be fighting successfully andattempting to drive eastward to join other Chinese troops. Further Chineseforces are reported at Paoshan (north of Lungling) and Kentung near the Burma-Indo-China frontier.Intelligence.Norway.20. Although a considerable number of German troops moved into Norwayin April to strengthen the defences against possible British raids, the strengthof the garrison does not exceed 250,000 men.South-West Pacific Area.21. Some islands in the Banda Sea area are believed to be still in Dutchhands.There is no reliable information concerning land operations in the S.W.Pacific Area.Pacific Ocean Area.22. The New Zealand Garrison on Fanning Island was replaced by american Army personnel.on the 28th April.Considerable American reinforcements reached Nukualofa (Tonga Is.) on the10th May.AIR SITUATION.General.23. At night, large-scale bombing was restricted by weather to a raid onWarnenmnde.Anti-shipping operations resulted in damage to about 60,000 tons of enemy shipping in Home and Norwegian waters.
Enemy attacks on Malta were again on a reduced scale. The raiderssuffered heavy losses.Our fighters inflicted heavy casualties on 20 Ju. 52s in the Mediterranean.United Kingdom.24.   Fighter Command flew 2,656 sorties by day and 252 by night.Enemy activity against this country was on a small scale except on the night of the 8th/9th. when about 50 aircraft ineffectively bombed scattered areas inNorfolk.Seven raiders were destroyed and another was damaged during the week.The German long-range bomber effort against Great Britain from january to May of this year was approximately 20 per cent, of the effort over the sameperiod last year. This is some measure of the present dispersal and commitments of the German Air Force. During the period of two weeks from the 25th april to the 9th May, which includes the &quot; reprisal &quot; raids, about 25 per cent, of thetotal sorties were made by aircraft of Reserve Training Units.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.25. Fighter and Bomber Command despatched 1,189 and 34 sorties respec-tively, compared with 2,701 and 78 last week.Bostons, with fighter escort, attacked objectives at Dieppe, Zeebrugge,Bruges and Ostend; hits were obtained on railway yards, factories, and port facilities.   Some details of these attacks appear in Appendix VII.In support of these operations and in offensive sweeps over enemy territory,91 squadron sorties were flown by Fighter Command. No hostile reaction by fighters was encountered except on one day, when an enemy aircraft was destroyed and six damaged by Spitfires, of which eight are missing.Night.26. Owing to unfavourable weather, only one attack against a land targetwas carried out by Bomber Command.A total of 138 aircraft dropped 252 tons of H.E. bombs (including12 x 4,000-lb.) and 31 tons of incendiaries at Warnemunde, where the principalobjective was the Heinkel factory. Observation of results was severely hampered by searchlight glare, and, though several searchlights were put out of action by low-flying aircraft detailed for the task, the concentration was so intense that dazzlewas not appreciably diminished. Some crews, however, identified the aircraftworks and photographs taken subsequently indicate that hits were obtained onthe aircraft factory, on warehouses and on the railway station (videAppendix VII). In addition to the searchlight screen, enemy opposition includedsevere anti-aircraft gunfire, numerous night fighters and a recently installedballoon barrage.Nineteen of our bombers did not return. Ten of these were engaged inlow-level attacks which, in some instances, were carried out from a height of30 feet.A further 50 tons of H.E. bombs were dropped on other objectives in enemy territory.Coastal Operations.27. Coastal Command flew 511 sorties, of which 56 were on convoy escort.Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Command involved 646 sorties.A total of 104 aircraft of Bomber Command laid 238 sea mines, principallyin the Baltic and off Heligoland and Kiel.Hudsons of Coastal Command carried out a number of successful attacks on enemy shipping. In an attack on a convoy of 12 ships off Texel, a vessel of6,000 tons and another of 4,000 tons were each hit by four bombs and five other ships were also hit.In Norwegian waters, two vessels, of 10,000 and 7,000 tons, were set on fire and two others, of 5,000 and 2,500 tons, were heavily damaged. A ship of6,000 tons, already beached, was left a total wreck.Minelaying by enemy aircraft was carried out off the East Coast. Oneattack was made against our shipping.
Mediterranean.Libya and Egypt.28. Our fighters maintained their offensive activities in the forward area and provided protection for shipping off the Egyptian Coast. Two S. 79s..which attacked shipping off Damietta, were intercepted by a Beaufighter. one was destroyed and the other was damaged.Twenty Ju. 52s. (transport aircraft), escorted by three Me. 110s., were intercepted 50 miles north of Derna by eight long-range Kittyhawks and fourBeaufighters. Thirteen Ju. 52s. and two Me. 110s. were destroyed, and theremaining Ju. 52s, were either probably destroyed or&apos;damaged. One Beaufighteris missing.The quays and shipping at Benghazi were attacked on two nights by a totalof 40 Wellingtons.   Seven other Wellingtons bombed Berca aerodrome.A total of 17 enemy aircraft made two attacks on the railhead at Capuzzo.They caused several casualties and some damage to the railway track.Sea Communications.29. Wellingtons attacked and hit with bombs a 5.000-ton merchant vesselnine miles north of Benghazi. A Beaufort delivered a torpedo attack on a convoy80 miles north-west of Benghazi, but results were not observed.Malta.30. Enemy attacks on the Island were again on a smaller scale and were carried out by a total of 256 bombers escorted by fighters, some of which carriedbombs.The aerodromes were hit, one Spitfire on the ground was destroyed and six were damaged.   Hal Far aerodrome was rendered temporarily unserviceable.During the week our fighters destroyed 45 enemy aircraft, probably destroyed40 and damaged 59. Anti-aircraft guns destroyed 12 and damaged five. Of this total of 161 aircraft, 141 were German and 20 Italian. We lost 13 Spitfires, butsix pilots are safe.On the 9th a reinforcement of 60 Spitfires reached. Malta and 57 of them were in action within 35 minutes of their arrival.Sicily and Italy.31. Several reconnaissances were made of harbours and aerodromes in sicily and Southern Italy.Russia.32. Strong bomber and dive-bomber formations of the German Air Forcesupported the German ground troops in the attacks on the Russian positions in the Kerch Peninsula.India.33. Japanese aircraft bombed and machine-gunned the landing ground atChittagong on the 8th and 9th. The runway was rendered unserviceable bydelayed-action bombs and one Blenheim was destroyed on the ground. An enemy aircraft carried out a reconnaissance of the Calcutta district on the 9th.Burma.34. Our bombers started fires in the Rangoon dock area and on the aerodromes at Mingaladon, Magwe and Akyab. A total of four enemy aircraft were destroyed, two probably destroyed and six damaged on the ground at Magweand Akyab. A fire was also started among 35 enemy aircraft parked atMyitkyina.Enemy attacks were carried out against Shwegyin (below Kalewa), Honnaing(Kalewa-Tamu road), Imphal (250 miles N.W.&quot; of Mandalay) and Inbaung(30 miles N.W. of Kalewa).   .
Pacific Zone.35. A 3.000-ton Japanese ship was sunk by Huclsons oft&apos; Amboine on the12th and two others were damaged.During five attacks by Japanese aircraft on aerodromes at Port Moresbysix Allied aircraft were damaged on the ground, two of our fighters were shot down and three damaged in the air. One of the raiders was destroyed, four more were probably destmyed and four others damaged.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.By Day.36. A few bombs were dropped on each day of the week, except the 13th, atpoints on the East and South Coasts.A school at Deal was demolished, railway property at Deal and Eastbourneand a power station at Southwick were damaged, but nowhere seriously. Otherdamage was mostly confined to residential property.By Night.37. Bombs were dropped on the 7th/8th at several points in Kent and Sussexand on the 8th/9th in and around Norwich.  No serious damage was done.Casualties.38. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 hours on the13th May are 24 killed and 57 seriously injured.
Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages lost by enemy action during the month of April 1942.Table I.The following table shows the division of losses into cause and nationality : Flag.	Submarine.		1     Surface Mine.             ^   ,. Craft. ^ \     ^			Aircraft.		Other Causes and   Cause Unknown.		Total.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross  i x-Tons.    No&quot;	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.british allied-Belgian...Dutch ...Greek   ...NorwegianPanamanianUnited states other AlliesTotal of Allied lossesNeutral countriesTotal       .....18   119,0076,1071,8293 18,2511 I 2,1166 j 37,3498 , 51,03126 ! 149,5703 !  16,33347 1 274,6502 !    7,2161,829 I   81,87467   400,8736 I    9,810 I 1117,928 i 11    65,006     3 j  12,5342,55826,6754,9862,0734,2192 !  11,5,94911,17724,936 !   2 !    5,94952,147 ! 16 I 89,942 &apos;   5 I  18,48339 ! 220,5821 I 1,8296 !  22,8821158293631052,11681,65951,031165,73316,333341,5839,090571,255
Table II.The following table shows the division of losses into cause and area: Area.Submarine.Mine.surface craft.i  Gross    XTAO. !   ,p No.\. Tons.GrossTons.No.GrossTons., Other CausesAircraft.    j   and CauseI   Unknown.Total.INo.Gross I ^Tons.   ITonsAtlantic   ...Indian OceanRest of Far East   andPacific ...MediterraneanUnited Kingdom coastal waters ...ElsewhereTotal57   34-2,2745    32,4042      7,3793 1  18,8166 . 25,472    111009,710o    26,675... 67 1400,873 !&apos; 6      9,810   11    52,147 i 1661,068     5 :  18,48328,874Note. For the purpose of this table, Indian Ocean is as defined in C.A.F.O. 194/42.G,ross     No     Grossions.5 * 342,27427     137,42;7,4795 9,71013       74,36589,942     5 :  18,483   105   ! 571:2551Table III.The following table shows the losses inflicted on Ocean and Coastal convoys during April:  	Number Con-voved. &quot;	Number Lost.					Percentage Lost.						Sub-marine.	: Surface Mme- ; Craft.		Air-craft.	Total.	Sub-marine.	Mine.	Surface Craft.	Air-craft.	Total.Ocean   convoys Coastal convoys	1,009 3,238	o	5		2 -	4 5	-19	-15		-19	-38 -15	4,245	2	5		2	9	-05	-11		-05	-21consequently convoys suffered no considerable loss.
otal Losses by Enemy Action and Marine Causes of Merchant Ships, including Tankers,other than Merchant Ships commissioned for Naval Service.Including vessels of all tonnages for losses by enemy action and vessels of 100 gross tonsand over for losses by marine causes.)A. British, Allied and Neutral Losses.Months.September-December(4 months)January-March(3 months)April-June ...(3 months)July-September   ..(3 months)October-December(3 months)941 january february march april may ...june...july ...augustseptemberOctobernovemberdecember42-january february.marchapril31.7297315348364&quot;9313715316613912259661116765167126135172120Total.		British.		Allied.		Neutral.	No.	Thousands of Gross Tons.	No.	Thousands of Gross Tons.	No.	Thousands of Gross Tons.	- No.	Thousands of Gross Tons.3,5399298001,0531,3321,3364024615676615364511481603382331S4460487&quot;67073260012,54015811115321125455981018496654443764139101615967:   !I464983524699259802353593743643922801121102541601172482123132592311366566029243668; 24356:   101417. 10; 5458J 74.10370903632621123415475147247106143243446. 5S331812603404683581421739681509151614192291321916127-22434141225819612213274650382812163815343115175111,9637,244S44 3,571   I     732I1,725
B. Losses analysed by cause.(In Thousands of Gross Tons.)Months.1939-September-December(4 months)1940-January-March ...(3 months)April-June(3 months)July-September ...(3 months)October-December(3 months)1941-JanuaryFebruaryMarchAprilMayJuneJulyAugustSeptemberOctoberNovember.December .1942-J anuary   .February .MarchAprilTotal.Enemy Action.Marine liisk.Total.929S001,0531,3321,336402461567661536451148-* r* r\J.OU33823318446048767073260012,540Sub-marine7345249351,15132737653462350142012113027820510441135660768257110,8452913461,246 I     7706901251842342403312949480205152621062934245334016,276Mine.421 i     2581691545413330162325231491151426410191710Sur-Surface draft.Air-craft.7423121994821634815186251531763124Other ;Causes;orCauseUn-  ;known. ITotal33250179897790112293132.66924413523313511345901,060    1,092 I  1,77031111122042172832120415398318594Over-duepre-sumedlost.*18627611886185758533383531273060288049131635029I1,695* Some of these losses may eventually be held to be due to enemy action,j- Including losses due to vessels running on British mines.
Appendix III (1) will be inserted in a subsequent Resume.(2) Merchant Ships (100 gross tons and over) under construction in the UnitedKingdom as at 30th April, 1942.	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.Coasting ships and colliers  ... Other ships     ...       ...       ...... Total    .:.      .:.	9 39	6,000 327,000	13 169*	22,000 862,000	48	333,000	182	884,000* Including 11 ships (7,000 gross tons) of Merchant type intended for Naval use.In addition the following merchant ships are on order in the UnitedKingdom and abroad : 	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.United Kingdom Canada and United States Total...........	17	118,000	97f 57$	397,000 410,000	17	118,000	154	807,000f Including 6 vessels (3,000 gross tons) building for the Navy.j Some of these vessels are already under construction but details are not available.APPENDIX IV.No alterations to figures furnished in weekly statement,dated 6th May, 1942.APPENDIX V.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.May 7-Motor Launch ISO lost with all hands off Malta.May 11. Tug C 808 mined and sunk off Malta.   Seven survivors.The following casualties to Naval personnel have been reported : -Officers : Killed 33, missing 24, wounded 7.Ratings : Killed 115, missing 10, wounded 34.The above includes casualties from H.M.S. Edinburgh.
Provisional operational aircraft battle casualties for the period: dawn, Thursday,7th May, to dawn, Thursday, 14th May, 1942.British.BombersFighters ...&apos; Coastal   ...Army Co-operation total metropolitan Area.In the Air..,..... 20.1.       &apos;.. 8...       ... 5I.       ... 33On the Ground.Enemy.bombers fighters miscellaneous total destroyed.7411ProbablyDestroyed.3Damaged.5914Of the above totals 1 bomber &quot; destroyed &quot; was shared by A.A. and Balloon commands.Middle East (including Malta).British.Bombers.Fighters .OthersTotalIn the Air......... 4..     : ...       ... 21........ 251 crew and 9 pilots are safe.On the Ground.1Enemy.Bombers ...Fighters ...miscellaneous total destroyed.3425 -13*72ProbablyDestroyed.2317j*t43Damaged.3928n74Of the above totals, 13 were destroyed, 2 probably destroyed and 5 damaged by A.A.Miscellaneous includes:    * 13 Ju. 52;   f 2 Ju. 52;   $ 5 Ju. 52.Far East.British and Allied.Bombers ...Fighters ...OthersTotalEnemy.Bombers  ...FightersMiscellaneousIn the Air.211Destroyed324ProbablyDestroyed.On the Ground.1...23Damaged.&quot;3Total27JfoTBS. (a) No account is taken of enemy aircraft destroyed on the ground in any theatre,(fa) No account is taken of British Naval aircraft casualties.
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week : Germany.Rostock. Photographs taken on the 26th and 27th April show that the attacks on the nights of the 25th and 26th resulted in the following damage : (i) Heinkel Aircaft Factories.(a) Main factory at Marienehe : The roof of the main assembly, hangarhas been destroyed over an area of at least 305 feet by 135 feet, and the prototype assembly shop has been damaged by blast. The machine shop, thepaint shop and the chemical products store have been partly destroyed by fire or H.E.; two large workshops have been damaged by blast, and severaloffice buildings and living quarters destroyed or damaged.(b) In the sub-factory south of Neptune Yards, the south-east corner of the main building has been hit and there is considerable roof damage.(c) One of the buildings of the sub-factory adjoining the gas works hasbeen burnt out and there is some damage to the roof of the main building.(ii) Port and Storage Facilities.(a) A large shed in the Neptune Shipbuilding Yard has been badly damaged.(b) On the quayside north of the old town several small buildings in and near the Otter Ludewig and J. Mollier Shipbuilding Yard and the largestorage depot at the west end of the quay has been almost entirely burnt out.(c) To the east of the town practically the whole of the extensive storage facilities have been destroyed by fire, including the following : (i) Twelve storage sheds in the timber storage depot north of thePetridamm.(ii) Four very large storage sheds in the storage depot to the south of thePetridamm.In addition, a smaller store in the same area, already damaged in a previousraid, has had additional damage.(iii) Communications.(a) In the Central railway station the entrance hall, booking office anda large part of the roof has been damaged by fire.(b) The booking hall and offices in the Friedrich Franz railway station and all the goods station buildings are burnt out.(c) The railway tracks have been damaged in several places; i.e., north-west of the main railway station; on the lines leading from the FriedrichFranz Strasse; at the level-crossing of the main Rostock-Stralsund line atWeisses-Kreuz; and on the line which runs alongside the Heinkel works atMarienehe.(iy) Residential and Commercial.Approximately 130 acres of the. old town, including nearly 1,000 houses,have been devastated mainly as a result of fire. Outside and to the south ofthe old town there are two further areas of destruction by fire, about700 and 500 yards long respectively, and of varying width; and many othersmaller areas badly damaged. There is also considerable damage to&quot; thesuburbs and surrounding farms, and south of the River Warnow several smallfactories have been destroyed or damaged by fire.The recent attacks are said to have caused a complete stoppage of all war supplies to Denmark via Rostock-Warnemunde and the train ferry thence toGjedser.
Cologne. Photographs made on the 6th May cover part of the east bankof the Rhine, which was not covered in the previous reconnaissance on the29th April.  It is seen that (i) Two large shops in the south-west part of the Citroen Motor works have been gutted, and a stick of bombs fell across the railway in theimmediate vicinity, and(ii) The corner of a large shop in the Humboldt Deutz motor works and domestic property in the neighbourhood has been destroyed by fire or damaged.It has been reported on two occasions in the month of February that therewas no rail traffic passing through the main station across the Hohenzollernbridge. One report stated that in the middle of February part of the roof ofthe jnain station was destroyed, and that the reason why no trains could use this route was that one of the arches on the approach to the bridge had been soweakened as to cause all traffic to be suspended. It is considered that this damage was caused in the attacks in December, when it is known that a train approaching the main station from the east was hit. In the interval passenger traffic is saidto have been routed through and from the south station. It is not known how long this suspension lasted, but it is noteworthy that in the photographs taken onthe 25th March, although the station and bridge appear intact, there is a remarkable lack of rail activity in the neighbourhood of the station and the bridge.It has also been reported on two occasions that, in the raid of the 27th/28th April a bomb pierced the Hange bridge to the south of the Hohenzollembridge, exploding in the river underneath. Traffic was interrupted by the holemade in the roadway. In the same attack buildings in the Kaiser Friedrich Uferfacing the river to the north of the Hohenzoilern bridge were damaged, and a bomb fell in the front of Cologne&apos;s most famous restaurant, the &quot; Bastei.&quot;Wamemiinde. Photographs of the 9th May show the following damageresulting from the attack on the 8th/9th May :  (a) There is roof damage to the Assembly Hall of the Heinkel (Arado) Works,and evidence of scorching by fire.(b) The aerodrome is rendered unserviceable by a large number of craters,and the seaplane station is damaged.(c) Two large dock buildings in the immediate vicinity of the harbour basinare damaged by direct hits and the passenger railway station building is seriously damaged.(d) There is a considerable amount of destruction and damage to residentialand commercial buildings.Hamburg. In the attack on the 3rd-4th May very severe damage was caused to property in the northern parts of the city. The Hamburger Fremdenblattannounces that on these nights almost without exception all bombs dropped hitdensely populated residential districts. Photographs-taken on the 7th May, how-ever, show that in the harbour  11*6  1 cl large warehouse on the Amerika Kai hadbeen entirely demolished, another on the Oswald Kai partially demolished, andin addition the main shop of an unidentified factory had been damaged.Stuttgart. After the attack on the 4th-5th May the districts Heumaden andSillanbuch to the south of Stuttgart were burning throughout the whole night.Dortmtmd. A traveller who wished to stay at the &quot; Hotel Rheinischerhof &quot;near the main station in the middle of April found on arrival he was unable to doso as the hotel had been &quot; bombed out of existence.&quot;Mannheim. In the raid on the 11th-12th February the National Theatreand the Castle were both seriously damaged.General. The attacks on Rostock have caused nervousness in all Baltictowns, in particular Stettin, where A.R.P. measures and the defences have been strengthened.The Westdeutscher Beobachter announces that the Mayor of Cologne hasbeen empowered to requisition all empty flats of over 100 marks a month rentin order to accommodate persons rendered homeless by air attacks.
Occupied Territory.Dunkirk. Photographs taken on the 3rd May show bombs bursting amongbuildings to the north and on the quay to the north-east of Guilleminot barracks.he Havre. During the attack on the 4th May, photographs were made which show bombs bursting on the quayside, buildings and barges in the Bassin Bauban.Bombs also fell in the vicinity of the railway station and on a building near thepower station. The attack on the 11th April interrupted the electricity supply for 48 hours.Dieppe. Photographs taken during the attack on the 8th May show thateight bombs fell on the marshalling yards and railway lines to the east, three on buildings to the west of the yards, one being a direct hit on the engine sheds, andthree on buildings to the south of the marshalling yard.Zeebrugge. Photographs taken during an attack on the 7th May show tenbombs bursting across buildings at the east end of the Solway coking plant and chemical works, and one on the lubricating oil depot immediately north of theSolway works.Bruges. Photographs taken during the attack on the 9th May show fivebombs bursting on the north quay of the Bassin Ouest, including one on the lightrailway; and one bomb bursting on a building at the north-west corner of thelock between the Bassin Ouest and the outer port.Flushing. Photographs taken during the attack on the 30th April show-bombs falling on the sea wall south of the dry dock off the Verbreed Canal, on buildings south-west of the repairing dock and on the south end of the west quayin the Verbindings Canal. Bombs also fell on the bridge and in the north quayof the marine dock.Sea Mining.The Swedish Press reports that on the 5th May the second ship in a north-bound escorted German convoy of four ships was damaged by a mine in thevicinity of Helsingborg.  .The German wireless reports that the French fishing boat Marie Gilbertehas been mined outside La Rochelle.






</content>
</cab>
