<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/68/0 images: 1-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I    this document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1954 ^^^kThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.  It is issued^fl for the personal use of........................^.r...q,^&gt;fr^r,3..r^J^.TOP SECRET Copy No. 12 ^|I C. (54) 151I 27   April, 1954CABINET^fl RELATIONS WITH THE UNITED STATESNote by the Prime MinisterI feel it my duty to circulate to certain of my colleagues these three veryI private letters exchanged between President Eisenhower and myself.70 Downing Street, S.W. 1,27sf /4pn7, 7954.
mmm mm\\The White House, Washington,^L-M             Dear Winston,                                                           February 9, 1954. ^-MRecent reports that you have been on the firing range personally testing themerits of the new Belgian rifle would indicate that you are again in the very best ^-Mof health. Needless to say, your friends here greet such indications with great joy. ^-MMy official reports from Berlin are not quite so discouraging as would be ^-M^LwW             expected after reading some of the Molotov outbursts in the daily press. I grow ^-Mweary of bad manners in international relationships.   When abuse grows so ^-MVAYJ             flagrant as to include insult, false charges and outright vituperation, I sometimes VAVJ^--M             wonder whether we help our own cause by allowing the world to believe us meekly ^-Mready to sit quietly under such attacks for no other apparent reason than a desperatehope for a crumb of concession out of the propaganda feast the enemy enjoys at ^-MMWm             our expense.                                                                                        j I VAVJ^LmW                  The free nations&apos; case must be better understood by the entire world-including ^-M^L^M             ourselves. More and more I come to the conclusion that the salvation of liberty ^-M^LWm             rests upon the unremitting effort of all of us to establish a solidarity among our- ^-m^LWM             selves that in major objectives and purposes will remain firm against any assault. ^-USuch an association of free nations must be expanded as widely as possible, even ^-M^LWm             to include very weak nations when those weak nations are exposed directly or ^-M^L-M indirectly to the threats and blandishments of the Soviets. We are deeply concerned ^-M^LWm              of course with Indo-China, Iran and Egypt.  But the entire Moslem World, IndiaVAVJ             and Southeast Asia, as well as our European friends, are all important to us! ^-M^LWM                   Such an association of nations must have clear political, economic and military ^-M^LWM             objectives of its own; while avoiding all belligerence in its attitude, it must still ^-MK^H             be so firmly confident of its own security that it will have no reason to worry about ^-MV_VJ the possibility that the stupid and savage individuals in the Kremlin will move 1 B_Vj^-m              against us in any vital way.^LWM At the very best, of course, to produce such an association of nations will^LWm             require the finest of leadership. To this we, the larger nations, must contribute. ^-M^-W             We must be generous, understanding, determined, and always faithful to our WWu^LWm pledges. Tactics will vary. In some areas and on some subjects, we will have to^LWM use cajolery, in others firmness.  In some situations, some particular one of the^LWM             principal countries of the coalition should take the lead in the conduct of negotia- ^L-Wtions; in others, another will have to assume the burden. ^L-M^--\ . Of one thing I am certain. If we could get real unity of understanding \m mmU^--\             and basic purpose among a few of the principal nations Of the free world-including, of course, West Germany-it would not be long until the common ^LWw^L-M             security of us all was vastly improved and the material fortunes of our countrieswould be advanced markedly and continuously. ^-M^LW\                   The problem, of course, is to achieve much more than mere paper agreement.Our consortion must rest solidly upon a common understanding of the Russian ^Lmm^-M             menace and in the clear conviction that only through unity, stubbornly maintained ^LWmin the face of every inconsequential point of argument and difference among us, ^-Mcan these great things be achieved. P_VJ
^1 ^1Of course there is no real reason for writing you such a letter as this. Notonly do you understand these things better than I-in many instances 1 haveabsorbed my ideas from you. But I&apos;ve been thinking a bit of the future. I amI sure, that when history looks back upon us of to-day it will not long rememberanyone of this era who was merely a distinguished wat leader, whether on the xbattlefield or in the council chamber. It will remember and salute those people whosucceed, out of the greatness of their understanding and the skill of their leadership,in establishing ties among the independent nations of the world that will throwback the Russian threat and allow civilisation, as we have known it, to continueits progress.Indeed, Unless individuals and nations of our time are successful-soon-inthis effort, there will be no history of any kind, as we know it. There will be onlya concocted story made up by the Communist conquerors of the world.It is only when one allows his mind to contemplate momentarily such a disasterfor the world and attempts to picture an atheistic, materialism in complete domina-tion of all human life, that he fully appreciates how necessary it is to seek renewedfaith and strength from his God, and sharpen up his sword for the struggle thatcannot possibly be escaped.Destiny has given priceless opportunity to some of this epoch, You are oneof them. Perhaps I am also one of the company on whom this great responsibilityhas fallen. , .?j Jl$ &apos;isvcBWith warm personal regard,m^mm ttf&gt;&quot; As ever,I j&lt;miq  IKE. dtaMThe Rt. Hon. Sir Winston Churchill,K.G., O.M., C.H., M.P.,The Prime Minister, &lt; p fwfttcja London.-yPersonal. fpj|Most Secret and ConfidentialMy dear Friend, March 8, 1954.Thank you for your letter.  I am honoured by the kind personal things youThere is no difference between us upon the major issues which overhang theworld, namely, resistance to Communism, the unity of the free nations, the con-centration of the English-Speaking world, United Europe and N.A.T.O. All thesewill and must increase if we are tp come through the anxious years and perhapsdecades which lie ahead of hopeful but puzzled mankind.On the day that the Soviets discovered and developed the Atomic Bombthe consequences of war became far more terrible. But that brief tremendousphase-now lies in the past. &amp; % .&quot;&apos;&quot;*.?*&quot;* |gfe   I ?
An incomparably graver situation is presented by the public statements ofMr. Sterling Cole at Chicago on February 17. I have discussed these with myexpert advisers. They tell me that the 175-ft. displacement of the ocean bed atEniwetok Atoll may well have involved a pulverisation of the earth&apos;s surface three rl^^lor four times as deep. This in practice would, of course, make all protection,except for small Staff groups, impossible. You can imagine what my thoughts&apos;are about London. I am told that several million people would certainly beobliterated by four or five of the latest H Bombs. In a few more years thesecould be delivered by rocket without even hazarding the life of a pilot.- NewYork and your other great cities have immeasurable perils too, though distanceis a valuable advantage at least as long as pilots are used.Another ugly idea has been put in my head, namely, the dropping of anH Bomb in the sea to windward of the Island or any other seaborne country, insuitable weather, by rocket or airplane, or perhaps released by submarine. Theexplosion would generate an enormous radio-active cloud, many square miles inextent, which would drift over the land attacked and extinguish human life oververy large areas. Our small size and density of population emphasises this dangerMr. Cole further stated that Soviet Russia, though perhaps a year behind theUnited States, possessed the know-how and was increasing its production andpower of delivery (or words to that effect). Moreover after a certain quantityhave been produced on either side the factor of &quot; over-taking,&quot; &quot; superiority,&quot;&amp;c, loses much of its meaning. If one side has five hundred and the other twohundred both might be destroyed. A powerful incentive to achieve surprise wouldbe given to the weaker-what about Pearl Harbour. His natural fears wouldprey upon his moral and spiritual inhibitions (if indeed he was so encumbered).When I read Mr. Cole&apos;s widely reported speech, I was surprised that itssearing statements attracted so little comment. The reason is that human mindsrecoil from the realisation of such facts. The people, including the well-informed,can only gape and console themselves with the reflection that death comes to allanyhow, sometime. This merciful numbness cannot be enjoyed by the few menupon whom the supreme responsibility falls. They have to drive their mindsforward into these hideous and deadly spheres of thought. All the things thatare happening now put together, added to all the material things that have everhappened, are scarcely more important to the human race. I consider that youand, if my strength lasts, I, cannot flinch from the mental exertions involved.I wondered, pondering on your letter, whether this was the background which?b^H HBr&apos; f had forced you to express yourself with such intense earnestness. I understand,of course, that in speaking of the faith that must inspire us in the struggle againstatheistic materialism, you are referring to the spiritual struggle, and that like me,you still believe that war is not inevitable. I am glad to think that in your spirit,as in mine, resolve to find a way out of this agony of peril transcends all else.I entirely agree with Mr. Cole&apos;s remark that in this matter &quot; It is more sinfulto conceal the power of the atom than to reveal it.&quot; This would not of coursemean one-sided imparting of secret knowledge. But perhaps we have now reached,l 4H
I or are reaching, the moment when both sides know enough to outline the doom-I laden facts to each other.Of course I recur to my earlier proposal of a personal meeting between Three.I ftjlen have to settle with men, no matter how vast, and in part beyond their com-I prehension, the business in hand may be. I can even imagine that a few simpleI words, spoken in the awe which may at once oppress and inspire the speakersI might lift this nuclear monster from our world.It might be that the proposals which you made at Bermuda and which areI accepted by the Soviets for parleys on this subject, could without raising the issueI formally give a better chance of survival than any yet mentioned. The advantageI of the process you have set in motion is that it might probe the chances of settle-merit to the heart without at the same time bringing nearer the explosion we seekI toYours very sincerely, ^^flWINSTON S. CHURCHILL.^fl      I TOP SECRET^MW\ The White House, Washington,March 19, 1954.|fl Dear Winston, MWMI have pondered over your letter. You are quite right in your estimate of WMMI mY grave concern at the steady increase in methods of mass destruction. WhetherI or not the specific possibilities of devastation that you mention are indeed demon-I strated capabilities, the prospects are truly appalling. Ways of lessening or, ifI possible, of eliminating the danger must be found. That has been my principalI preoccupation throughout the last year.It was after many weeks of thinking and study with political and technicalI advisers that I finally reached the conclusions which we talked over at Bermuda^^fl I and which were embodied in my eighth of December address to the United Nations ^^flI Assembly. As you are well aware, that plan was designed primarily as a means ofI opening the door of world-wide discussion-with some confidence on both sides-I rather than as a substantive foundation of an international plan for the controlI or elimination of nuclear weapons. But honest, open technical discussions on WWWI an internationally supported plan to promote peaceful uses of this new scienceI might lead to something much more comprehensive.Since last December, we have been following up this matter as actively as itsI&apos;m technical character permits.  Foster had two or more talks with Molotov whenI they were at Berlin.  We have a draft plan which, after consultation with your WMMWWW]     I people and those of two or three other countries, will, I expect, be transmitted to^^fl     I the Soviet Union through diplomatic channels, as agreed, probably next week.While there have been some indications that the Soviets might want to confuseI the issues with extraneous political matters, on the whole it is encouraging that they WMMI so far seem prepared to accept businesslike procedures.
I la its entirety the problem is one of immensity and difficulty, as you so II graphically stated.  But I repeat that I deem it important to make a beginning II in an exchange of views, which as you suggest, could open up new and morehopeful vistas for the future.I I doubt whether the project oh which we are engaged would, at this moment, IH be advanced by a meeting of heads of government. In fact, I can see that such a II meeting might inject complications.   From our side, there is the question of II France, which is very delicate at the moment.  The Soviets have indicated that, II if there were oral conversations, they would want to bring in the ChineseCommunists.H My impression is that matters are in a reasonably good way, but that they II require constant concern and vigilance and, I hope, frequent and intimate personalexchanges of views between the two of us. f^HI With warm regard, II As ever, I?The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill,? K.G., O.M., C.H., MR,The Prime Minister,London, England.B _A

</content>
</cab>
