<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/68/0 images: 31-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3^HpWe think it desirable to consult our colleagues on certain recentdisturbing developments concerning the Portuguese possessions in India.Indian Attitude to Foreign Possessions in India2,      Both Portugal and France retain certain possessions in India.The Government of India resent this and wish to secure the incorporation of these territories in the Indian Union, though they have stated that they intend to use peaceful methods only.    They have recently increasedpressure on the foreign territories.    In the Portuguese territory of Goaespecially the campaign has taken the form of economic and administrativeharassment by means of frontier control together with intensivepropaganda, organised demonstrations and the formation by variousprivate individuals of so-called volunteer bands for the &quot;liberation&quot; ofGoa.    The French Government have never refused to negotiate a settlement with the Indians, on the basis of a referendum in their territories, andhave not sought external intervention in their dispute with India.    ThePortuguese Government, on the other hand, have always flatly rejected allIndian claims to the Portuguese possessions in India and do not admit thatthere is any ground for Indo-Portuguese negotiations over them.Portuguese Request for Support3.      The Portuguese Ambassador in London and the Portuguese ForeignMinister have on two recent occasions drawn the Foreign Secretary&apos;attention to the situtation and, after referring to the Anglo-PortugueseTreaties and the North Atlantic Treaty, have asked Her Majesty!s Govern-ment for(a) Their good offices with the Indian Government to secure a reduction of tension.(b) An assurance of Her Majesty&apos;s Governments support, should thePortuguese find it necessary to bring the matter to the North atlantic council under Article IV of the North Atlantic Treaty.The Portuguese Foreign Minister stated that he quite understood our difficulties and did not expect us to do the impossible but that it would beof great value to the Portuguese people to know that they could count upon our doing whatever we could to help.secret CABINET office record COPY . - ^Ca(54) 159 COPY NO, 6 OCABINETPORTUGUESE POSSESSIONS IN india memorandum by the Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations and the Minister of State
4.     Her Majestyfs Government may be caused great embarrasment in view of India&apos;s membership of the Commonwealth and of the treatylinks of Her Majesty&apos;s Government with Portugal;-(a) Under the Anglo-Portuguese Treaty of 1373 and subsequent Treatiesas confirmed by the Secret Anglo-Portuguese Agreement of 1899thesre. is a clear obligation on Her Majesty&apos;s Government in theUnited Kingdom to defend Portuguese overseas territory,(b) Under Article IV of the North Atlantic Treaty Portugal would clearly have the right to require consultation with the other members of theOrganisation on the ground that a threat existed to the territorial integrity of a Portuguese possession, whether part of MetropolitanPortugal or of the oversea territories for whose international relations the Government of the Metropolitan territory are responsible.At the recent meeting of the North Atlantic Council the PortugueseMinister for Foreign Affairs mentioned the s;situation in Goa withoutrequesting any specific action.    (Article V of the Treaty which dealswith action including the use of armed forces to be taken as a result ofan armed attack against one of the Parties could not be invokedbecause Goa lies outside the North Atlantic area).Indian Misapprehensions about the Legal position .     The United Kingdom High Commissioner in New Delhi hasrecently received requests from the Indian authorities for clarification of the Treaty position.    In recent public statements Mr. Nehru has,however, said that neither the North Atlantic Treaty nor the Anglo-Portuguese Treaties are relevant to Goa and in a recent Aide Memoireto the High Commissioner in Delhi the Indian Government askedHer majesty&apos;s Government to confirm this view.Effect on United Kingdom Colonial Possessions6.      There is an obvious parallel between Goa and such british possesions as Hong Kong, Gibraltar and the High commission territories;  it would therefore be dangerous for us to show any symapathy for the Indian Governments contention that they have an intrinsic rightto these settlements.recommendations.     It is inconceivable that Her Majesty&apos;s Government could agree totake military action against a fellow-member of the Commonwealth, andwe must not raise false hopes in the Portuguese.    On the other hand the indians should not be allowed to remain under any misapprehension aboutthe Treaty position.    We therefore propose that in giving to the Indiansthe clarification which they have requested the United Kingdom HighCommissioner should be instructed(a) to draw the attention of the Indian Government to the relevant provisionsof the various Anglo-Portuguese Treaties and the position ofHer Majesty&apos;s Government under Article IV of the North Atlantic Treaty,making it clear that, technically, circumstances could arise in whichthe Portuguese Government could legally invoke these Treaties withrespect to Goa;
(b) to refer to the Indian Prime Minister&apos;s repeated public assurances that he intends that any settlement with the Portuguese should be by peaceful means;(c.) to say that Her Majesty&apos;s Government assume that the indian government do not therefore contemplate any action which could give the Portuguese Government reasonable grounds for claiming acasus foederis;(d) to explain that, if the Portuguese Government were to claim acacus foederis, it would put both the United Kingdom and the indian governments in an extremely embarrassing position,8.     When the Portuguese Ambassador is informed that we havespoken to the Indian Government and of any assurances which theIndian Government may give he might be told(a) That we hope it will preclude the need to bring the matter before theNorth Atlantic Council.(b) That, in any event, our own advice would be not to bring the matter before the Council, since, so far from helping Portugal, it would further incense India.(c) That there are limits to the extent to which we can assist in a dispute with a fellow-member of the Commonwealth but that we shall always be prepared to use our influence in any way possible to reduce tension.SWINTONSaJ-j,3rd May, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
