<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/68/0 images: 91-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(54) 182 ^ .nt^,r- COPY NO.--- CABINe r OFFIOte1st June, 1954 RECORD  COPYCABINETDISPOSAL OF LAND ACQUIRED CQMPULSORILYFOR PUBLIC PURPOSESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the home department and Minister for Welsh AffairsIntroductionIn my Memorandum C. (54) 16 I submitted, on behalf of theCommittee of Ministers on the Crichel Down case, the following recommendations on the procedure which should be followed in thedisposal of agricultural land acquired compulsorily for public purposesbut no longer required by the Government!&quot;(a) that no statutory right of pre-emption should be accorded to former owners of such land;(b) that steps should in future be taken administratively tosecure that former owners or their successors in title, if they could betraced without undue difficulty, should be notified that it was proposed tosell the land and be given an opportunity of buying it in competition withother prospective purchasers.The Cabinet, at their meeting on 18th January (C.C.(54) 3rdConclusions, Minute 7), deferred a decision on these recommendations and invited the Committee to give further thought to the practical possibilitiesof according to former owners some form of pre-emptive opportunity.2. The Committee have given this matter prolonged andexhaustive examination but have deferred submission of their recommend&quot;ations until they could be considered in the light of the report of theCrichel Down Public Enquiry, which the Minister of Agriculture is nowcirculating to the Cabinet as C. (54) 183.The Majority view. The majority of the Committee reached the conclusion thatthe Government ought to recognise that former owners and their successors may have a moral claim to recover their land when theGovernment no longer requires it, and that the procedure followed by departments for disposing of land should be designed to enable them, sofar as possible, to do so.    They accordingly reached agreement on theterms of a proposed public announcement of a modification of present government policy to secure this object.   This proposed announcement is reproduced in the. Appendix to this memorandum.
 joThe Minority View4. At least two of our colleagues entertain serious doubts aboutthe justification for a change of Government policy on the lines suggested.The Lord Chancellor is apprehensive about the consequences of bringing into operation, by means of an undertaking to Parliament and administrative arrangements only, a system of pre-emption in respect of state-owned land of a kind for which over a period of many years it has proved impracticable to provide by statutute.    Both he and the Financial Secretary, Treasury,moreover, feel grave doubt about the propriety of selling without statutory authority state-owned land at a price lower than the maximum price which such land could command in the open market, and the Financial secretary has felt compelled to reserve fully the Chancellor of the Exchequersposition in regard to any such arrangement.5^ On this latter aspect of the matter it was the view of themajority of the Committee that, if former owners were to be given a genuine opportunity to recover their land, it followed that the government must be ready to sell it to them at a price to be fixed by the District Valuer,and that such an arrangement was entirely defensible on the ground thatthe same method was being adopted for determining the price at which theland should be sold as had earlier been used for determining the price atwhich it should be compulsorily acquired.recommendation. Subject to the reservations recorded in paragraph 4 above,the Committee recommend that at an appropriate time a statement of future policy on this matter should be made on the Governments behalfon the lines of the appended draft.D.M.F.Home Office, S.W.I.31st May, 1954.appendix draft statement the Government have had under review the policy hithertofollowed with regard to the disposal of agricultural land which was acquiredcompulsorily or under threat of compulsion and which is no longer required for Government purposes.2. The Government recognise that the former owner and his successors may have a moral claim to be considered as purchasers ofsuch land.    The Government will seek to ensure that in future those withsuch claims will have an opportunity to buy the land.    This decisioncannot apply where the land has already been disposed of and will notapply to certain categories of land of which details are annexed.3. In the ordinary way there should be no difficulty in carryingout this policy.    The procedure will normally be for an announcement tobe made that the land is to be disposed of and by this and other means itis hoped that those who have such claims will become aware of the factthat the land is to be sold.    If the responsible Minister concludes that a
claim is well-founded, he will gHqt the land to the claimant at the priceassessed by the District Valuer as the current market price.4. This policy will be followed both where the land compulsorily acquired was the whole, and where it was part, of an estate.    In carryingout this policy regard will be had to the obligations placed upon theMinister of Agriculture by the Agriculture Act, 1947 and upon theSecretary of State for Scotland by the Agriculture (Scotland) Act, 1948.ANNEXEXCEPTED CATEGORIES OF LAND(i) Airfields and land with buildings, other than agriculturalbuildings, on it, except where the buildings or otherdevelopment are of little value and cover only a small proportion of the land.(ii) Land which was acquired within three years after it hadbeen publicly offered for sale by the person from whom it was acquired.(iii) Land acquired through the National Land Fund Procedure.(iv) Land which at the time of disposal is wanted by a localauthority for a purpose for which compulsory purchasepowers could be used.(v) Land acquired by the Board of Trade in Development Areas,for sale for private industrial development.(vi) Small strips of land.(vii) Small parcels left over from the land which has been acquired e. g. for trunk roads.(viii) Land which was previously in a number of small plots.(ix) Land acquired by the Minister of Agriculture under sections 16, 84 and 85 of the Agriculture Act, 1947and acquired under the similar provisions of the agriculture (Scotland) Act, 1 948.(x) Land acquired by the Forestry Commission which issurplus to afforestation needs and which was includedin a purchase at the request of the former owner.

</content>
</cab>
