<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/68/0 images: 135-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1954SECRETCopy No. ? 0C. (54) 1851st June, 1954CABINET office record copyCABINETEXPENDITURE ON THE OVERSEAS INFORMATION services from 1955 ONWARDSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department and Minister for Welsh AffairsIntroductionIn my memorandum C. (53) 359, giving my Committee&apos;s views on expenditureon the information services for 1954-55, I stated that recommendations would follow on the scope of the information services for 1955 onwards.2. The Drogheda Report recommended an increase in expenditure on theinformation services of some  2^ millions. The Overseas Ministers, in C. (53) 315,asked for  935,700 to cover immediate essentials. After the Cabinet&apos;s decision of3rd February (C.C. (54) 7th Conclusions, Minute 5) a net increase of the order of 300,000 was finally agreed on for 1954-55.3. We have carefully examined the Report of the Drogheda Committee andthe many papers submitted on it. We have also discussed the problem with theDepartments concerned. In reaching the conclusions which follow my Committeehave sought to consider the problem solely on its merits, irrespective of any economies which may have to be undertaken as the result of other deliberations.We have also treated the problem as one requiring a general decision of policy,this decision is not intended to prejudice or preclude any economies or improve-ments which may be possible as matters of administration.The Problem4. Basically, the problem before my Committee was how to reconcile the viewof the Overseas Departments, that it is essential to implement forthwith at least the requirement set out in C. (53) 315 and preferably the whole Report, with theview of the Treasury, that financial limitations preclude this. Both these views are supported by extremely cogent arguments, and we can only recommend that a balance be struck between them.Recommendations5. We therefore recommend and the substance of this proposition has beenagreed in principle with the Overseas Departments, though not with the Treasury that Her Majesty&apos;s Government should declare that it is their policy to accept inprinciple all the financial recommendations in the Drogheda Report, but to spread the consequent increase in expenditure of some  2^ millions per annum over aperiod of seven years (instead of three to five as proposed by the drogheda committee, and five as volunteered by the Overseas Ministers). In other words,there would be an increase of  357,000 each year over and above the expenditure onthe existing services, the retention of which was recommended by the drogheda committee, for seven years, or until the Drogheda Report was fully implemented,whichever was the sooner.(a) Future Services46228
6. This is rather more than was agreed to for 1954-55, and rather more than half the amount of  635,000 outstanding after the original 1954-55 claim for 935,700 has been reduced by  300,000 (see paragraph 2). It will, in 1955-56, enablethe Overseas Departments to proceed with certain activities which they have declared to be of the very first importance.7. This annual increase would be subject not only to the normal annual review referred to in the following paragraph, but also to the independent enquiry which the Drogheda Committee recommended should be held in not less than fiveyears&apos; time.(b) Existing services. It has been represented to us that these should be reviewed to see whether any of them could be abolished as being less essential than some of the new servicesrecommended in the Drogheda Report. We do not feel able to carry out sucha review ourselves, and indeed it has been carried out by the Drogheda Committee,who have recommended the abolition of certain services. Accordingly we recom-mend that those existing services, the retention of which was recommended bythe Drogheda Committee, should be retained. The expenditure on them wouldbe subject to annual review in the normal way; this review would of course covernot only the existing services retained under the Drogheda Report, but alsoservices set up under the previous annual increments. It may have to be increasedto meet rising costs, or it may be possible to reduce expenditure, if costs fall, or ifeconomies can be made. We recommend that every effort should be made to run these services as economically as is compatible with efficiency, and that expenditure should be closely supervised. In this connection we recommend an examination of the possibility of obtaining more information about, and exercis-ing closer control over, that part of the expenditure of the B.B.C. which is coveredby the external broadcasting services grant-in-aid and which amounts to half thetotal expenditure of overseas information services.(c) European Broadcasts9. There is one point in the Drogheda recommendations which was acceptedby the Foreign Secretary in C. (53) 315, but from which he has subsequentlydissented namely, the proposal to abolish the French and Italian services of theB.B.C. We are impressed both by the contention of the B.B.C. (whose evidence we have heard), that broadcasting has a special importance as a means of directlyinfluencing the general public, and by the Foreign Secretary&apos;s contention that political considerations make it most desirable to retain these services. In thepresent circumstances the Committee cannot see their way to recommending thatthis particular item in the Drogheda Report should be accepted.D. M. F.Home Office, S.W. 1,31st May, 1954.
CONFIDENTIAL,CABINETThe attached paper will beconsidered under Item 4 of the agenda for the meeting of the Cabinet arranged for the morning of Wednesday, 2nd June.Cabinet Office, S.W.1.31st May, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
