<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/68/0 images: 149-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1^1secret cabinet office.(54) 191 record COPY COPY NO. ^4th June, 1954CABINETEXPENSES OF MEMBERSMemorandum by the Lord Privy seal i have discussed the present position with the Chief Whip, and Iwould like to put forward our views for the consideration of my colleagues on the assumption, of course, that some action is necessary.2.        It was, we think, the general view of the Cabinet at their meetingon 2nd June that a flat-rate increase was undesirable and, in the light ofthe political situation, highly dangerous: but it appeared to be the general view that something should be done, as a matter of urgency, to alleviate the position in which many Members are placed (C. C. (54) 38th Conclusions).This general view seems to represent the highest common factor of agreement which could be reached in the House of Commons as a whole.3.        The following plan would be put forward as an interim arrangement,the announcement of which would be prefaced by a statement that the viewof the majority of the House was on record but that the time for raisingsalaries was inopportune.The statement should also include an expression of the Governmentsdesire to hasten the investigation of an improved but contributory pension scheme for M. Ps. and to consider the position of Junior Ministers.4.        We believe that the simplest interim plan, and the one least opento misunderstanding or misrepresentation, would be a Subsistence Allowancecalculated in accordance with the sittings of the House.    This should beat the rate of  X per day, for four days in any week in which parliament is in session.5.        Any Member who intimated to the Fees Office his desire to receivethis allowance would have it credited to his account monthly or could drawit weekly in cash.It would have to be left to the good feeling of Members to refrain from drawing it in the event of prolonged absence from the House forwhatever reason.6.        No scheme will now please everyone, but we believe this oneprobably has the best chance of general acceptance by the Conservative Partyin the House of Commons;  and, broadly, by the Party in the country.     Ifit was a case of this scheme or nothing, we believe it might well be accepted,faute de mieux, by the Socialists.
The expression &quot;subsistence allowance&quot; has the merit of beingwell understood in Trade Union, Civil Service, Local Government and similar spheres.7.        The allowance would be paid to all Members of Parliament,whether sitting for London or provincial constituencies, because it isintended as a contribution to the heavy expenses necessarily incurred byall Members who, while Parliament is sitting, are engaged at Westminsterfor very exceptional hours of duty: hence the expression &quot;four days&quot;rather than &quot;four nights&quot;.In the interests of simplicity, and for other reasons, it would clearly be best that all Members should be treated alike:  and there is a real case for London Members who also live in London receiving the same treatment as others, owing to the high cost of living in London, the factthat they must have most meals in the House of Commons, i. e. away from home, the larger number of visitors, etc.We think, however, that this view might not be acceptable andtherefore suggest that London Members, as recognised by the InlandRevenue as such, should receive a lower but uniform subsistence allowance8.        The Civil Service Class &quot;A&quot; Rate is 37/6d. a night.    LocalGovernment Members&apos; Normal Rate is 42/- a night.    Local GovernmentMembers&apos; Special London Rate is 50/- a night.    Therefore, 35 sittingweeks in a year would work out at the following:-1.       Civil Service Rate   -    262 10s. Od.2.       Local Government Normal Rate   -    294.3.       Local Government London Rate   -    350.H.C.Office of the Lord Privy Seal, S. W. 1.4th June, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
