<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/68/0 images: 181-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/?copy No.   6 confidential vy.-&quot;-&apos; CABINET office^198 RECORD COPY16th June, 1954CABINETCOMPENSATION TO MINISTERS OF THE CROWN INJURED ORKILLED ON DUTYMemorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerFrom time to time during the last two years or so I have had to answerenquiries from my more peripatetic colleagues about the arrangements for insuringthem against accidents while travelling by air. I have had to tell them that payments for this purpose cannot be made from public funds. They have accepted this reply.But I think, nevertheless, that it may be desirable that we should consider togetherour policy on this somewhat personal and far from simple matter.2. In the last war Civil Servants were for the first time allowed to charge to public funds the cost of premiums on policies insuring them, whilst travelling on duty by air, for a sum equal to two years&apos; salary; and this practice was extended to ministers. (Civil Servants, unlike Ministers, also had, and have, the protectionprovided by the Injury Warrants, which give their widows a pension of between one sixth and one quarter of their salary if they are killed on duty.)3. In 1948 the then Government decided that the war-time practice should cease, that no provision whatever should be made from public funds for this purposeso far as Ministers were concerned, and that Civil Servants should rely on the InjuryWarrants as they had done before the war, payment from public funds for lifeassurance premiums being permitted (within certain limits) only where additionalpremiums are required to validate Civil Servants&apos; own existing insurance policies.4. Thus the present position is that, in the event of their being killed or injuredwhile on official duty, Ministers of the Crown have no rights other than thosederiving from common law or statute. I will not attempt to describe in detail whatthese rights are, but a very short note on this point will be found at Appendix I.5. The question is: are these arrangements adequate? Should they be supplemented, in some way, at the expense of public funds?6.   The main arguments for and against the present policy are as follows:  For(a) Ministers are provided with a salary which the uninformed may thinksufficient to enable them to insure against accidents : to provide furtherout of public funds would be an unjustifiable supplementation ofMinisters&apos; remuneration.(b) The costs of obtaining at private expense insurance cover against accidentsby air are not great. For example, accident cover for  10,000 forten days&apos; flying risks by regular air line would cost  3 10s. 0d., andby private air-line charter plane 5 guineas.(c) If this sort of thing is done for Ministers, there may be a demand for anextension of the practice to cover Members of Parliament.Against(a) Ministers work for the State: the State should cover them as an additionto salary against risks inherent in their job.46291Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1954
(b) While Ministers were handsomely paid before the war, the change inthe value of money has affected their capacity to save and provide fortheir families in the event of their death or disablement. (In any eventJunior Ministers are in a very different position from Senior Ministers.)(c) The position of Ministers can easily be differentiated from that of private members.7.   The possible means of providing cover for Ministers are as follows:  (a) Bringing Ministers within the scope of the Injury WarrantThis would give cover for death or injury on duty extending far beyond accidents incurred while flying. At Appendix II is a note giving a rough summary of the provisions of the Injury Warrant.(b) Re-introduction of the war-time practice of insurance through private companies, the premium being paid out of public funds, and public funds also standing any extra cost of validating existing policies.(c) Reimbursement of the extra cost of validating existing policies, with nofurther coverThese could be restricted to travel by air or could be extended tocover other contingencies as desired.8. As between these alternatives the pros and cons seem to be as follows:  I have no doubt that, if it were decided that Ministers ought to be covered in some way against accidents while on duty at public expense, theproper way to do it is by the Injury Warrants. But to do this would require legislation. To extend their scope to bring in Ministers would not be revolu-tionary so far as the Warrants are concerned, for, although up to 1949 theycovered Civil Servants only, the Superannuation Act, 1949, extended their scope to include persons employed in a civil capacity, whether for rewardor not, for the purposes of Her Majesty&apos;s Government. One might have thought from the wording of the 1949 Act that Ministers would be within thescope of the Warrants; but in the view of the Treasury Solicitor this is not so, since the appointment of a Minister does not create a relationship betweenthe Minister and the Crown of contract of service, or even contract for services: a Minister is not &quot; employed &quot; within the meaning of that word asused in Section 41 (1) in the Superannuation Act, 1949.* Thus, whenLord Cherwell, having ceased to be a Minister of the Crown, flew to Bermudawith the Prime Minister he was within the scope of the Warrant but the PrimeMinister was not.The present does not seem to me to be an opportune time to promote legisla-tion for pensions for Ministers or their dependants, even in the exceptional circumstances of death or disablement on duty.9. It would be possible without legislation to resort to private insurance companies. But it is an established rule of practice that the State carries its ownrisks and there seems no good reason why, if it were decided to cover this risk,the State should pay for it to be carried by private companies. Thus if the practicebecame known it might be alleged that the reason for its adoption was the desireto avoid drawing public attention to the fact that the cover was being provided at all. This is not the sort of criticism to which, I think, we would wish to exposeourselves.10. My own conclusion from all this is that, though the present position may not perhaps be altogether satisfactory, we should be well advised to leavematters as they are for the present. We might, however, reserve the question forconsideration in conjunction with the general question of the financial position ofMinisters as and when it next comes forward for discussion.R. A. B.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,14th June, 1954.* It is also to be noted that for the purpose of the National Insurance Acts, Ministers are deemedto be &quot; self-employed &quot;.
APPENDIX IPOSITION OF MINISTERS UNDER COMMON LAW OR STATUTEA claim to compensation in respect of a Minister killed or injured while on official duty would be possible in one or other of the following circumstances:  (1) Where the negligence of another person can be proved, a claim for com-pensation can be made against that person or, as is more usually done,against the employer of that person. Thus a claim might in thesecircumstances be possible against, e.g., British Railways, a road transport undertaking or the Airways Corporations and any employeeof them.(2) In the case of air travel only, a passenger has additional protection. the warsaw Convention, which was ratified by the Carriage by Air Act,1932, and is subscribed to by many countries who operate air passenger services, lays down that a passenger has a claim to compensation, evenif negligence cannot be proved, so long as the compensation is limitedto 125,000 gold francs, worth at present about  3,000.(3) Again, where negligence can be proved by one of its servants, a claimcan be made against a Government Department. For instance, if a minister were killed or injured as a result of the negligence of a driveremployed in the official car service or a driver paid by the Ministersown Department, a claim could be made.APPENDIX IIPROVISIONS OF THE INJURY warrant the Injury Warrant, 1952, framed under Section 41 of the SuperannuationAct, 1949, provides a scheme of compensation for persons who suffer impairmentof earning capacity as a result of an injury sustained, or a disease contracted, inthe discharge of their duties, or, if the injury or disease proves fatal within seven years, for certain dependants who were wholly or mainly dependent on the deceased at the time of his death. It applies without distinction to establishedCivil Servants and persons employed in a civil capacity for the purpose of her majesty&apos;s Government within certain salary limits, and in their cases the scales of compensation are as follows:  Aircraft accidents       ......Civil disturbances abroadAccidents in normal course of duty    ............WidowsAnnual allowanceI of officers salaryI of officers salary  of officers salaryCivil Servantstotal disablementAnnual allowanceI of officers salaryI of officefs salary% of officers salary2. There are also allowances for children and certain other dependants indeath cases.3. Allowances at a proportionately lower rate are paid for a lesser degreeof disablement.4. Any payments under the warrant are reduced to the extent that compen-sation is received from other quarters, i.e., the value of any damages recoveredand any National Insurance benefits. But no account is taken of private insurancepolicies.5. (Unestablished Civil Servants are also covered by the Injury Warrant,but in their case the compensation payable is in certain respects on a lower scale.)

</content>
</cab>
