<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/13/4 images: 60-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.MOST    SECRET,COPY NO.W.oM..(40). .114th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 1,C onf ident i a1 Annex0(7th May, 1940.)THE NETHERLANDS.Allied liaval,military and air action in theevent of aGerman attack onthe NetherlandIslands.(previous reference:W.M.(40) 109thCone lusions-,Minute 9.)The War Cabinet had before them a Report bythe Chiefs of Staff Committee (W.P.(40) 143).THE PRIME MINISTER said that there was oneobservation which he would like to make at the outset of the discussion.      The Report stated that theoccupation of the Netherland Islands would be merelya first step in a German occupation of Holland-     he felt, however, that it would be unsafe to rule outaltogether the possibility that an attack on the islands might not be followed by the movement ofGerman troops for an appreciable period.      If theAllied troops moved forward into Belgium as soon asthe Germans attacked the Islands, then presumably theGerman Army would also move.        The responsibility forordering the Allied advance, however, lay with theFrench;    they might hesitate to give that order ifthe German move was limited to the occupation of the islands.      Presumably, the right time to attack theGerman marshalling yards was at the earliest possible moment after the German Army had started to move.

THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR thought thatit was inconceivable that the Germans would confine their action to taking the Islands.     He feltcertain that land invasion would inevitablyfollow, and that,therefore, we should strike atGermany at once and not wait until their troops were on the move,THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF agreed.     Itwould be of little value to the Germans merely to occupy the Islands, where they would be subjectto a very heavy scale of air attack,THE PRIME MINISTER said that his point would be met by a statement in the Report to theeffect that air attack on the marshalling yards would notbe  completely automatic, i. e.  they would not, ofcourse, be attacked if they did not actually containGerman troops.The War Cabinet agreed that the report should be amended in the sense suggested by the PrimeMinister,THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF then invitedattention to the main points in the Report.    Thefollowing additional points emerged from the ensuingdiscussion; -attack om the (1)    The difficulties of using the bomber forcewhen there was no moon, were emphasised in paragraph 8.    While it might bedifficult to identify such targets asoil refineries, marshalling yards wouldhave to be lit up if they were in use,while coking plants and power plants were e If - illumina t ing.

Mine-layingin Germanrivers.magnetic mines.Denial ofDutchaerodromesto theGermans.(previous reference:W.M.(40) 113thConclusions,Minute 9.)(2) It was an essential part of our plans toattack the marshalling yards in the Ruhr in theevent of a German invasion of Holland or Belgium.Unless targets in the Ruhr were to he attacked,the heavy bomber force could not be used to counter the attack on Holland or Belgium.    Attackon the marshalling yards would not, however, .employ the whole of our heavy bomber resources,and it was therefore intended, if the german attack took place at a time when there wasno moon, to devote a part of the heavy bomber force to attack self-illuminating targets,such as coking and power plants.(3) The first section of paragraph 9 should be amended to make it clear that the laying of mines in the mouths of the Elbe, Jade, Weserand Ems had been done by Fleet Air Arm andR.A.F. aircraft and not by submarines.(4) Paragraph 9, second sentence.    The presentoutput of magnetic mines was 200 per month and would rise to 500 per month by 1st July.This outpxit was sufficient to allow  both for operation Paul and for mining the Yifestern german ports,(5) No sure information had yet been received of theaction taken by the Dutch to prepare demolitionsat their aerodromes.    The British ambassador at The Hague had been asked to report onthe matter.

Denial of Dutch and belgian resources.previous reference;.M.  (39) 61stjonclusions,;,minute 5.)Strengthening ofNaval Forces on theEast Coast.Mining&apos; of the danube.(previous reference:W.M. (40). 91stConclusions,Minute 4, )(6)    THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO informed theWar Cabinet that a most satisfactory meeting had recently been held in Paris between british, French and Belgian representatives in connection with the denial of resources to Germany in the event of invasion.    So faras Belgium was concerned,  satisfactoryaction had already been taken to reducestocks of raw materials and oil, or to transferthem to the vicinity of the French frontier.Similar precautions had been taken over theBelgian gold reserves.    The position asregards Holland,although not so satisfactory as in the case of Belgium, had shown some improvement,(7)    Submarine patrols off the Dutch Islands hadbeen strengthened.    Two cruisers, hithertobased, on Rosyth, were being sent further south,    No additional destroyers, however,were yet available for the defence of theEast coast.(&apos;8)    THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO said that the laying of fluvial mines in the Danube wouldbe an important corollary to the royal marine Operation and the laying of mines inthe Rhine by aircraft.    The mines would belaid in the German portion of the Danube and?/ould become innocuous before they reachedneutral waters.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF said that once the battle had started on the Western Front, it would absorb the whole of our bomber effort and it would beimpossible to spare bombers for mining operationseither on the Rhine or the Danube.

THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said that his view of the considerations raised in the report was founded on the conviction that a German attack on Hollandwould &quot;be   a decisive move aimed at the very existenceof this country.      Our &quot;best moment to hit back wouldbe as soon as the German attack was made, and before they had time to establish themselves.     The longerwe delayed, the more difficult action would be.        Ifthe Germans attacked the Dutch Islands, we should atonce attack the enemy&apos;s transports on the Islandaerodromes,  and should intensify the laying of mines.Should we go further and take action which would openup unrestricted air war?In the /ight of Supreme War Council decisions,we   were free to do so, but there were two other questions:-(i)    Had we the necessary air strength?(ii)    Was it strategically wise to do soat the present moment?In many ways there would be disadvantages in using the whole of our bomber strength at thepresent moment.     Out total first line long-range bomberstrength was 450.      (This figure included about 100Blenheims, which would not be used for an attack onthe Ruhr O     Of this figure of 450 we had lost 75during the period of the operations in Norway.     Asagainst that loss, 107   long-range bombers had been delivered from aircraft storage units and contractors tooperational units during the same period.      Many of the machines in reserve, however; were short of.necessary a

equipment and modifications, and though every effort was&quot;being made to improve the position, the Air Ministryconsidered that at the present time   they couldnot      rely        on more than 240 heavy bombers,of which only half would be actually serviceable onany given day.      Our available striking force cnany given day was,  therefore, 120 heavy bombers.(This figure   did not include Blenheims,)Was this a sufficient force for carrying out our plan of attack on the Ruhr?It was calculated that with the forceavailable we could drop 28 tons of bombs a night on oil refineries, marshalling yards and vital plants.At this rate we should theoretically be able to destroy the objectives in 11 - 18 days.Our casualties in Scandinavia had been 6%per raid.       In the Ruhr the casualties were assessedat 10% per raid, i.e. 30 bombers a week, althoughoperations would only be carried out at night.Leaving out of account the effect of enemy attack on our aircraft industry, our production inthe same period should be 21 - 34 heavy bombers aweek.- 6 -

It was calculated that we should he ahleto carry on operations at the intensity indicatedfor six weeks, after which the scale of effort would drop by about 50 per cent.He (the Secretary of State for Air) would,naturally, prefer that we should not start these operations until we were in a more satisfactoryposition as regards equipment and, particularly,as regards the A,A, gun position.     We had only40 per cent, of our requirements in heavy A.A. gunsand but 9 per cent, of our light A.A.  gun requirement&amp;He was convinced, however, that the risks of puttingoff the attack were too great.     Moreover,  if we didnot use our heavy bombers to attack the Ruhr, theywould not be used at all.      It would be most wastefulto use our heavy bombers by day for the land battle,for which we had plenty of short-range bombers.      Ifwe confined attack to the marshalling yards, we would bring on total war just as surely as if we attacked the oil refineries.     The plan proposed   did not anticipate the use or exhaustion of our whole heavy 1bomber force on a single objective..In reply to a question,  the CHIEF OF THE AIRSTAFF estimated     that as compared with our figureof 450 heavy bombers,  the German figure of first-lineheavy bomber strength was about 1,900,    The Germanmanufacturing and other resources Were greater thanours, and consequently they would be able to replacelosses more quickly than we could.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that if wewere to attack the German marshalling yards only,this would not necessarily provoke retaliation by the

German Air Force on industry in this country,,On the other hand, if, in addition tomarshalling-yards, we were to attack German oil refineries and coke ovens,  such attack would,in his opinion,  inevitably result in retaliation.The Chiefs of Staff proposed that air action should bo taken against objectives inGermany the moment the Germans moved intoHolland.      A very great effort on the part ofthe Allies would be needed to meet that move.He thought that it was a matter for consider-ation whether air attack on German oil refineries and coke ovens would assist thateffort, or would be worth while , taking intoaccount the very heavy scale of air attack bythe German Sir Force to which it would exposethis country,,THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF considered    %that it would be unsound to assume that we shouldbe saved from retaliation, were we to confineour attacks to marshalling -yards alone.In reply to various questions bearing on the indiscriminate     nature of nightbombing, he explained that heavy bombers on both sides would operate at night0    Neitherwe nor the Germans had as yet any satisfactorymeans of interception in the dark.    During250 out of the 365 nights in the year searchlightswere ineffective in this country, though theproportion of cloudless nights was greater in summer than in winter.      The illumination of

marshalling yards and the glow of coke ovens wouldmake these targets visible at night.    oil refineries would not, however, show up.If we were right in assuming that wecould inflict serious damage on targets in the ruhr, Germany could also inflict damage here.    Weshodld undoubtedly suffer many casualties and damage to such targets as our big ports andindustrial areas.      On the other hand there wasno target in this country comparable to theGerman marshalling yards.In reply to a question as to his personal view, THE VICE CHIEF OP THE IMPERIALGENERAL STAPP said that once the land battle hadbeen joined in the west it would be    wr-ong   to divert any of our resources from itc      heavy bombers were not, of course, suitable for actualco-operation with the land forces in the immediatebattle zone, but he thought that they should   beused to the fullest possible extent wherever theymight be capable of contributing to the successof the land battle0      Since it was accepted thatthey could do this by attacking marshalling yards,he advocated that the full force of our heavy air attack should be diverted to them and not toother targets0Attack on other targets would open upunrestricted warfare.    He was ready to believethat the higher morale of the people of thiscountry would enable them to withstand air attack

better than the people of Germany.    He alsounderstood that in certain spheres   of civil defence,  such as fire fighting, we v/ere betterequipped than the Germans.    It was open toargument, therefore, whether unrestricted airwarfare might not be to our advantage.    he fully believed, however, that it would be a mistake, on military grounds,  to attempt to employour Air Force on these two separate anddistinct roles at one and the same time.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY saidthat although he fully appreciated the forceof the arguments of the Secretary of State forAir, he considered that it would be very dangerous and undesirable to take the initiative in opening unrestricted air warfare at a timewhen we possessed only a quarter of the strikingpower of the German Air Force.    Even a limitedinitiative on our part might result in awholesale indiscriminate bombing of thiscountry.    If this happened,we should not be ableto appeal to the United States, who would beable to retort that it was we who had taken thefirst step.    He suggested that we should presson with the production of small incendiarycapsules for the destruction of German harvests:and forests.      We should use the existence ofthis weapon as a threat to induce our enemiesto confine air bombing to the zone of operations,,

THE PRIME MINISTER said that the FirstLord of the Admiralty and the Vice-Chief of theImperial General Staff both felt objection toattacking targets such as oil refineries and coke ovens, but on somewhat different grounds..    the vice--Chief of the Imperial General Staffsobjection was based on the fact that such anattack would constitute a dispersal of effort.There was also the further point    that, althoughthe difference between bombing a marshalling yardand an oil refinery might be a fine one, neutral,and particularly American, opinion mightrecognise the former, but not the latter, as a legitimate military objectiveTHE LORD PRIVY seal i said that he had always felt that the Germans had been nervousabout air attacks on their civil population.He doubted therefore whether, despite the markednumerical superiority of their air force, theywould take the initiative in carrying out an air attack on this country which would provokeretaliation on Germany and consequently put the morale of the German people to the test,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIRreiterated his view that If we failed to take immediate advantage of a German invasion of holland to launch our air attack on Germany,an opportunity so favourable to us might neverrecur.      We had reason to believe that ournavigation by might was superior to that of the

Germans;    and it was to be remembered that 80per cent of the German armament industry was concentrated in the Ruhr and thereforeconstituted a target v/hich had no counterpartin this country.    An air attack of the kind whichwas contemplated would, moreover, be carrying thewar into Germany for the first time.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF made it clearthat it was not the desire of the Air Staff to open up the &quot;air war&quot;.      Their reason for advocatingair attack on Germany   in the contingencycontemplated was that in their view the invasion of Holland would be merely a preliminary to aGerman &quot;air war&quot; on this country;    and consequentlythat it would be preferable that we should loseno time in seizing what, :&apos;;&apos;./om car point of View ,would be the most favourable moment to open theair war.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO reminded the War Cabinet of the reply which had been madeby His Majesty&apos;s Government to the appeal againstunrestricted air warfare which had been made by president Roosevelt on the outbreak of war.    Inthis we had declared that we would scrupulouslyobserve the rules until they had been broken bythe enemy.    He thought that it would be desirablethat the Chiefs of Staff should be satisfied thatthe Germans had,  in fact, broken the rules to an extent which would justify an attack by ourselves on German oil refineries and coke ovens.    As an argument in favour of delay, he mentioned that developments in the application of R. D. F. held outpromises of giving our Fighters the power to intercept bombers in the darke

Germans;    and it was to &quot;be remembered that 80per cent of the German armament industry was concentrated in the Ruhr and thereforeconstituted a target which had no counterpartin this country,,    An air attack of the kind whichwas contemplated would, moreover, &quot;be carrying thewar into Germany for the first time,THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF made it clearthat it was not the desire of the Air Staff to open up the &quot;air war&quot;.      Their reason for advocatingair attack on Germany   in the contingencycontemplated was that in their view the invasion of Holland would &quot;be merely a preliminary to aGerman &quot;air war&quot; on this country;    and consequentlythat it would he preferable that we should loseno time in seizing what, f;?oai our point of &quot;View ,would be the most favourable moment to open theair war.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO reminded the War Cabinet of the reply which had been madeby His Majesty&apos;s Government to the appeal againstunrestricted air warfare which had been made by president Roosevelt on the outbreak of war.    Inthis we had declared that we would scrupulouslyobserve the rules until they had been broken bythe enemy.    He thought that it would be desirablethat the Chiefs of Staff should be satisfied thatthe Germans had,  in fact, broken the rules to an extent which would justify an attack by ourselves on German oil refineries and coke ovens.    As an argument in favour of delay, he mentioned that developments in the application of R. D. F. held outpromises of giving our Fighters the power to intercept bombers in the dark*

THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said thatthese hopes were as yet not very firm.    He would himself prefer to postpone an attack on military objectives in Germany, but for his conviction that todo so in the event of a German invasion of Holland wouldbe to deny us our only means of countering such aGerman move*THE FIRST LORD OP THE ADMIRALTY consideredthat a better counter to this move would be found inthe land battle which would be joined by the Frenchand British Armies,THE VICE-CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF1suggested that the Germans, while invading Holland,might be content to move up to the Albert Canalwithout advancing further into Belgium.    In this eventeven if the British and French Armies moved up beyondthe Namur-Antwerp Line the land battle might not bejoined.THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was clearthat the War Cabinet felt considerable doubt about theproposals contained in the Report by the Chiefs ofStaff in regard to the initiation of air action againstmilitary objectives in Germany.   , Kffi sr.^rested, thatChiefs of Staff should re-examine the question, inline__light of the discussion which had taken place.     He asked that the First Lord of the Admiralty, in consultation withthe Secretary of State for F reign Affairs,  should beresponsible for ascertaining what action the French army would take in the event of a German attack on the netherland Islands, as opposed to a German invasion of holland.

The War Cabinet(l) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to give further consideration, in the lightof the above discussion, to the preciseobjectives of our heavy bomber forcein the event of a German invasion of holland and/or Belgium:(2)  Took note that the Chiefs of Staffs&apos;recommendations were based on theassumption that the occupation of the netherland Islands would immediately be followed by the invasion of Hollanditself.   The Chiefs of Staff were invited to consider what our airobjectives should be if this assumptionwas incorrect:(3) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to give further consideration,  in the lightof (l) and   (2) above, to their Reporton Allied action in the event of aGerman attack on the Netherland Islands(W.P.(40)  143), and to re-submit  itto the War Cabinet.(4)  Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty,in consultation with the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, to make suchenquiry as might appear desirable to confirm that the French High Command,in the event of a German attack on the netherland Islands, would order theAllied Armies to advance into Belgium,in accordance with existing plans.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.MOST SECRZT.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO.operations in NORWAY.(previous reference:W.M.  (40)  113thConclusions,Minute 3.)Narvik.W.M.(40) 114th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 4.Confidential Annex.(7th May,  1940.)THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said thata part of Admiral Lord Cork&apos;s telegram in regard tothe possibility of carrying out an early attack onNarvik had been received, but that the remainder was still to come.     The part already received showed thathe appreciated the reasons for capturing Narvik assoon as possible and that his own opinion was thatdecided efforts should be made to do so.     the telegram referred to the difficulties from which theGerman garrison must be suffering as indicating thatthey could not be in very good heart.     It seemed clear that Lord Cork&apos;s final conclusion would be infavour of an early attack.     He (the First Lord) was of opinion that,  if this were Lord Cork&apos;s decision,nothing should be done to stop him from making the attempt.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed with this view,which was generally accepted by the War Cabinet,subject to no new feature being disclosed by thefurther telegram awaited from Lord Cork.The War Cabinet: -(l) Agreed that if Lord Cork&apos;s further telegram confirmed that he favoured anearly attempt to capture Narvik anddisclosed no new feature, he should begiven discretion forthwith to adoptthat course.(2) Invited the Prime Minister, the FirstLord of the Admiralty and the Secretaryof State for War to consider Lord Cork&apos;sfurther telegram and to decide whethera repjly should be sent as in (l) with-&apos;    &quot;he Warout further reference to thCabinet.Richmond Terrace, 8,J,1,




</content>
</cab>
