<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/56/1 images: 21-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret&apos;0/l  * * COTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cc(75) 1stConclusionsCOPY NO      g ^cabinet conclusions of a I^meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 9 JANUARY 1975at 10. 30 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hen Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams MP&quot;ecretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon John Morris qc mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy seal the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon Robert MeUish mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Rt Hon John Silkin mp minister for Planning and Local Government
ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Edmund Dell mp paymaster GeneralSECRETARIATSir John hunt mr P Benner (Item 1)Mr J A Hamilton (Item 2)Mr E J G Smith (Items 3 and 4)Mr J Peters (Item 2)Mr N Summers (Item 1)C ONTE NTSItemSubjectPageSPECIAL FAMILY ALLOWANCE120THE LUMP33,SUGAR74.PARLIAMENTARY affairs debate on e.c. Documents8
5PECLALFAMILYALLOWANCEPreviousReference:CC(74) 49thConclusions,Minute 31. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the paymaster general (C(75) 1) about the proposal for a Special Family Allowance(Special FAM),THE PAYMASTER GENERAL recalled that the Secretary of State for social Services had during the Cabinet5s recent discussion cf public expenditure proposed the extension in 1976-77 of family allowances tothe first child of one-parent families.    At the Cabinet&apos;s request, thisproposal had been examined further by the Committee on Poverty, andhis memorandum set out the facts and arguments relating to it.Special FAM was proposed for 1976-77 only, and would be absorbed into the Child Benefits scheme which was to be introduced in April1977.    It would accrue to rather more than half of one-parent families, the largest groups to be helped being those who neither drewFamily Income Supplement (FIS) nor paid income tax, who would receive  1. 50 a week;  and those who did not receive FIS but paidincome tax, who would receive 67p a week.    The former numberedperhaps 40, 000-45, 000, and the latter about 200, 000.    TheCommittee on Poverty had identified the main arguments for and against introducing Special FAM; but the conclusions to which theyled were matters of political judgment.    The Treasury had argued that it might in practice not be possible to absorb Special FAM intothe Child Benefits scheme in 1977; the additional cost of a continuedseparate benefit for one-parent families might be between 13 million and  43 million,    Alternatively it was arguable that, inorder to secure its absorption, it would be necessary to introduceChild Benefits at a level higher than  2.16 (the rate assumed for thepublic expenditure programmes which had recently been approved bythe Cabinet), since if account were taken both of Special FAM and ofthe child tax allowance, some of the beneficiaries would already be receiving a net benefit equivalent to  2.20 a week;  and if there werepressure to maintain not just the monetary but also the real value,the initial rate of Child Benefit might be as much as  2.50, whichwould add about  100 million a year to the cost of the scheme.    TheDepartment of Health and Social Security had however taken the viewthat Special FAM could be absorbed into the Child Benefits scheme without carrying any implication for the level of benefit, on which theCabinet would be entirely free to decide when the time came.In discussion it was argued that it was not clear that the needs of one-parent families were more pressing than those of some othervulnerable social groups, for example the homeless,    Nearly half ofone-parent families would not benefit from Special FAM; not all one-parent families were among the poorest, and some two-parent families&apos; needs were greater than the needs of those who would benefit from Special FAM.    Moreover it would be quite wrong in present economic circumstances for the Government to commit themselves toa measure which carried with it an identifiable risk of repercussions
which could add as much as  100 million a year to the cost of the child benefits scheme.    And the presentational advantages of the proposal by the Secretary of State for Social Services would be considerably reduced by the recent unfortunate leakage to the Press of information about the Government^ decision to defer introduction of the child benefits scheme from 1976 to 1977,On the other hand it was argued that there was strong evidence thatone-parent families, whose needs had been highlighted by the FinerReport, were a group seriously at risk; the cost of Special FAM in1976-77 would be modest, and it would be the only benefit provided forthis group, the Government having rejected the Finer Committee&apos;proposal for a Guaranteed Maintenance Allowance for all one-parent families.    It should not be too difficult to resist pressure for apermanent benefit for one-parent families;  and there was no reason why the proposals should lead to any increase in pressure for ahigher introductory rate of Child Benefit, bearing in mind that, inrespect of all children other than the first, assimilation to the new scheme would be related to rates of family allowance which had been fixed two years previously, in 1975,,    The announcement of SpecialFAM would moreover undoubtedly help to mitigate the unfavourableresponse to the Government^ decision, which v/ould have to be announced soon, to defer until. 1977 the introduction of the child benefits scheme, of which it would be presented as a small advanceinstalment.    There might however be advantage in considering whether the announcement about Special FAM could be timed so that itwould form part of any package of budgetary or counter-inflationary measures which the Government might need to take in the near future.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed in principle to the proposal for the payment ofSpecial FAM in 1976-77 in respect of the first children of one-parent families, on the strict understanding that it would not later be used asan argument for setting the rate for Child Benefit higher than thelevel envisaged during the Cabinet!s recent discussions of public expenditure.    The Secretary of State for Social Services was now free to go ahead with confidential preparations for the scheme within herDepartment.    She should discuss with the Lord President of theCouncil the most appropriate legislative vehicle for it, and the latter should inform him of the conclusions reached.    subsequent consideration should be given to the timing of the announcement of theGovernments decision on Special FAM so that it could form part ofany package of budgetary or counter-inflationary measures which mightshortly become necessary.The Cabinet -Took noter with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.
Tj-jE 2. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Minister forLUMP Planning and Local Government (C(75) 4) and by the Central policy review Staff (CPRS) (C(75) 2) about the means of tackling the abusesof the Lump in the construction industry.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the ministerial committee on Economic Policy (EC) ixnder his chairmanship had discussed this problem a number of times.    The Queen&apos;s Speech said&quot;proposals will be brought forward to tackle the abuses of the Lumpas a step towards creating a stable work force in the construction industry&quot;.    EC had examined two main alternative sets of proposals,one by the Minister for Planning and Local Government, and one bypi the Paymaster General: broadly, the former proposed a publicregister of sub-contractors and a penal levy on main contractors whoused unregistered labour, while the latter proposed to tighten up theexisting tax deduction scheme.    On balance, the majority of ECfavoured the Minister&apos;s scheme, but there were two very importantconsequences of that scheme which the Cabinet should consider: thefirst concerned the position of the genuine self-employed sub-contractor who met his obligations, the second concerned the penallevy which was part of the scheme.    Under the Ministers scheme, a self-employed tradesman who worked for a private client would not beaffected, but there was no safeguard for a self-employed man whoworked as a sub-contractor, unless of course he evaded his tax and insurance obligations by improper means.    It seemed wrong to ECthat to employ such men should involve the main contractor in penalsanctions far outstripping (when combined with the existing taxdeduction) normal liability to tax and national insurance payments.To devise a safeguard might well be difficult, if not impossible, asthe CPRS paper explained; the Minister therefore proposed inC(75) 4 that genuine self-employed men should have a period of graceduring which to become employers or employees; the levy would notbite in this period.The second major point of principle arose on the proposed penal levy on the main contractor of up to 40 per cent.    Under the Ministersscheme, this levy would be additional to the existing tax deduction of30 per cent already made by any main contractor who engaged a non-certificated sub-contractor.    The combined deduction of 70 per cent,in the view of the Inland Revenue, would be so oppressive aspositively to encourage a contractor and a sub-contractor to connivetogether to avoid both the levy and the tax deduction by falsifying theiraccounts: oppressive taxation which encouraged evasion was contraryto normal revenue principles, and he must tell the Cabinet that in his view it would be impossible for the Chairman of the Inland Revenue,who had a statutory duty to administer the Taxes Act, to defend beforethe Public Accounts Committee a situation in which tax revenue was lost as a result of the administration by the Inland Revenue of an
oppressively penal levy.    Besides this very important point ofprinciple, the Inland Revenue were currently working on a number of major new taxes to which he was sure his colleagues attached greatimportance, including the capital transfer tax, the wealth tax, thedevelopment land tax, and the petroleum revenue tax: they did nothave the spare capacity to mount a major penal campaign against the lump through a levy.    After very full discussion in EC, twosolutions had been proposed.    One was to reduce the penal levy to20 per cent, at which it would be effective, but not oppressive.   the inland Revenue would be prepared, reluctantly, to enforce a levy up tothis level.    The CPRS paper supported this solution.    The othersolution would be for the Secretary of State for the Environment totake on the whole task of administering, collecting and policing ahigher rate of levy as well as running the proposed compulsory publicregister:   this was expected to cost 550-650 extra staff, of whom400-500 would be needed for the levy.    The Minister for Planning andLocal Government had now proposed, in C(75) 4, to narrow the gap by accepting a levy rate of 30 per cent: but this was still too high for the inland Revenue to administer.THE MINISTER FOR PLANNING AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT saidthat in the view of the construction unions and the Trades UnionCongress, the Construction Industry Contracts Bill introduced in 1970represented the minimum which they could now accept:  indeed, theywere anxious to proceed rapidly to the complete decasualisation of theindustry.    This was not possible for the time being, which made it allthe more important to proceed on the basis of a scheme at least asstringent as that of 1970.    The report of the Phelps-Brown Committeein 1968 had given a number of arguments in favour of abolishing the lump: apart from the loss of tax and of insurance contributions, the lump increased the risk of injury in an industry which had anappalling safety record, it tended to fragment the industry andweaken the trades unions, it stifled the training of apprentices, and itresulted in shoddy work.     The Misselbrook working party in 1973 had represented both sides of industry and recommended something on thelines of the 1970 Bill, brought up to date.    In 1970 the penal levy hadbeen proposed at a rate of 30 per cent, and he had suggestedincreasing this to 40 per cent because the trades unions now felt evenmore strongly than in 1970; however, if it was necessary to secure agreement he was prepared to start at 30 per cent, a rate which theCabinet had accepted in 1969.    As regards the genuine, self-employedperson, he now proposed a period of two years&apos; grace from theintroduction of the scheme during which time he could decide to worksolely for private clients, or become an employer or an employee.As he saw it, the difference between his proposals and those of the inland Revenue was that while he aimed to abolish the Lump, theyaimed to control it, and therefore in a sense to make it legitimate.In spite of the Inland Revenue objections to collecting the proposedpenal levy, it did not seem sensible for the Department of the
Environment to manage the scheme, and there might well be public criticism of such an arrangement.THE PAYMASTER GENERAL said that his main concern was to dealwith the abuses of the Lump effectively, and in his view the InlandRevenue scheme would be more effective than the Minister&apos;s scheme.He was prepared to accept, reluctantly, a levy rate of 20 per cent which the Revenue would collect, but no more.    He feared that theMinister !s scheme would encourage large-scale evasion of control,with the result that the tax deduction scheme itself would become less effective.    Finally, as regards the self-employed man, the Phelps-Brown report had said that his interest must be safeguarded, and itwas no light matter to say to a group of people, however small, whowere responsible citizens in every sense, that they must now becomeemployees of other people, or form their own firms, simply to helpcontrol other, less reputable tradesmen.    The Minister&apos;s proposal toallow a two-year period of grace did not answer the point, because intwo years&apos; time it would still be wrong to force the self-employed manto conform.In discussion of the main issues the following points were made -a. It was essential that the Government should be seen tobe tackling the abuses of the Lump firmly, and evendramatically.    The trades union movement at the highest levelwas adamant in demanding action:   half-measures would inevitably influence attitudes towards the social contract,,b. The rate of penal levy should therefore be substantial:but it would be wrong to impose its collection on the InlandRevenue contrary to their principles, whereas if the scheme were administered by the Department of the Environment theywould be able to apply a degree of knowledge of the industry,and therefore of discrimination, which would not be open to theRevenue.    It was important for the Inland Revenue to pressahead with tightening up the existing tax deduction scheme, andthat the collection of the penal levy should not make taxcollection more difficult.c. The problem of the genuine self-employed tradesmanraised an important point of principle;  even though no meanshad yet been found to devise a safeguard for such a man whoworked for a main contractor, the period of grace proposed bythe Minister for Planning and Local Government should beaccepted, and efforts to devise a safeguard should continueduring this period.
d. The construction industry faced a severe depression,and this made it all the more important to tackle the Lump;there were other difficulties too facing that part of the industryengaged in the development of the North Sea oilfields, whichneeded urgent examination.e. The main contractors as well as the trades unions were anxious to deal with the Lump, and the whole of the industry would be represented on a statutory panel charged withsupervising the Minister for Planning and Local Governmentsscheme: if the scheme was to be administered by theDepartment of the Environment, it would be helpful if the inland Revenue were represented on the panel.    It was also important that the proposed arrangements for a public register,and certificates of registration, should be proof against forgeryand impersonation.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that legislation to tackle the abuses of the Lump shouldbe based on the scheme put forward by the Minister for Planning andLocal Government, as modified by him in C(?5) 4.    The levy would begin at the rate of 30 per cent, and go up to 40 per cent at the end ofthe period of grace of two years (from the introduction of the scheme)during which a genuine self-employed person who complied with the revised Inland R.evenue rules would be treated as registered under theAct.    During the period of grace, the Minister for Planning and LocalGovernment should continue to seek a sound method of safeguarding the genuine self-employed sub-contractor, and report the result toEC; that Committee should also consider whether all the proceeds of the levy should go to the Consolidated Fund, or whetherpart should be put to other uses.    The task of administering theMinister&apos;s scheme, and collecting the levy, should be carried out bythe Department of the Environment.    The Inland Revenue should proceed separately with their own arrangements for tightening up theexisting tax deduction scheme, and it might be helpful if they were represented on the construction industry panel which would supervise the working of the Ministers scheme.    As regards the possible effects of the Minister&apos;s scheme on the on-shore development programme for North Sea oil, including the building of platforms, theSecretary of State for Scotland in consultation with the Secretary ofState for Employment should circulate a paper on the whole of thelabour situation in the on-shore industry, including the need toprovide accommodation for the construction teams at isolated sites.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.
2. Invited the Minister for Planning and LocalGovernment to draft the Bill to give effect to his schemefor tackling the abuses of the Lump, on the basisoutlined in the summing up.3. Invited the Secretary of State for the environment to prepare the machinery within his department for administering the scheme andcollecting the levy.4. Invited the Paymaster General to press ahead with the plans of the Inland Revenue to tighten up theexisting tax deduction scheme,5. Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for Employment,to circulate to the Ministerial Committee on Energy a paper on the labour situation in the on-shore North Seaoil development industry.SUGARPreviousReference:CC(74) 48thConclusions,Minute 23. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR PRICES AND consumer protection said that she had circulated to members of the cabinet a report of a meeting of the Ministers directly concerned on the line tobe taken in the resumed negotiations on the price to be paid for theimport of sugar from certain developing, principally Commonwealth,countries under Protocol 22 of the Treaty of Accession to theEuropean Economic Community (e.c.).    The meeting had consideredtwo issues - the long-term pylce to be guaranteed by the e.c.;  and theprice actually to be paid in 1975, to be guaranteed by the BritishGovernment.    On the first issue, it had been agreed that the sugarproducing countries should be urged to accept a price equivalent to theprice of beet sugar produced in the e.c..    On the second issue, it hadbeen agreed that in the last resort the Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food could offer a price up to a limit of  250 a ton ciffor 1975, plus, if necessary to obtain agreement by the Caribbeanproducers, an offer of supplementary payments related to 1974shipments from Jamaica, Barbados and Trinidad.    However, a priceof  250 a ton was very high.     If the producing countries would not accept this, the matter should be brought again to the Cabinet, who should consider whether it would be better to accept the consequences of a shortage of sugar rather than pay more.In discussion it was urged that it would be a mistake to increase theprice we were prepared to guarantee from the   215 a ton already offered, which was itself a profitable price for the producers, being
ready if need be to take steps to deal with the consequences of anyshortage ol&quot; sugar that might result.    An increase in the price of theorder suggested would be a very heavy burden on the balance ofpayments, costing us in 1975 some  200 million more than in 1974.Ministers were that afternoon to consider the whole difficult balanceof payments position, and a decision to increase the price offeredshould be deferred until the overall situation had been examined.On the other hand it was argued that since the Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food was opening that afternoon price negotiations withrepresentatives of the producing countries, he must have authority tonegotiate within the terms already agreed by Ministers if animmediate breakdown was to be avoided.    If agreement could not bereached on that basis then the whole matter could be reappraised.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that on balance the Cabinet agreed that on the long-term guarantee the producers should be urged to accept a price equivalent to the e.c. beetprice as giving them considerable stability in a highly volatilecommodity.    On the price to be guaranteed for 1975, the Minister ofAgriculture, Fisheries and Food should conduct his current negotiations with representatives of the producers on the basis agreed at the meeting of Ministers concerned.    If it proved impossible toreach agreement with the producers on that basis he should bring thematter back to the Cabinet for decision on which course to follow.The Cabinet -1, Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.2. Invited the Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and Food to proceed accordingly in his negotiationswith representatives of the sugar producing countries.4. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES saidthat two proposals for directives by the Council of Ministers of theEuropean Economic Community (e.c.) were due to be debated, on therecommendation of the House of Commons Scrutiny Committee, in theHouse on the evening of Tuesday 14 January.    This debate had beenarranged to precede the expected discussion of the draft directives inthe Council of Ministers on 20 January, but that had now been deferred until 10 February.    The draft directives provided for the free movement of doctors within the e.c., in accordance with theprovisions of Articles 52-58 of the Treaty of Rome on freedom of establishment.    She had serious doubts on the principle involved, andwould be unhappy at having to defend it, particularly since the
spokesman for the doctors was claiming that it would increase theirbargaining power against their employers in the National health service.    Moreover Government supporters in the House wereunhappy with the draft directives, and it was by no means certain thatthe Government could carry the day.In discussion it was noted that the subject matter of the draftdirectives had been discussed over a considerable time, and that whenthe proposals had been debated in the House of Lords on9 December 1974 the Government spokesman had given them a generalwelcome.    Any policy difficulties should have been resolved in theappropriate Cabinet Committee before now.It was also noted that this debate was one of a considerable number ofdebates due to be held in the House of Commons on therecommendation of the Scrutiny Committee, and that some government supporters were likely to be unhappy with them.    It would be difficultto ensure that the Government won the vote in every case, and therewas mach to be said for the Minister responsible for each debateseeking to reach agreement in advance with those government supporters who felt strongly on the subject concerned, so as to avoiddivisions.    A memorandum on the whole issue of the handling ofdebate on e.c. instruments recommended by the Scrutiny Committeewas under preparation.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the ministerial Committee on European Questions should aim to meet onMonday 13 January to decide the line to be taken in the debate and theGovernment Motion that would need to be tabled that nightc    Theresults of the discussion could be reported if necessary to a meetingof the Cabinet the following day.    The Cabinet would have an earlydiscussion of the whole question of the handling of debates arisingfrom recommendations of the Scrutiny Committee.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.2. Invited the Secretary of State for social services to circulate a memorandum on the issue to the Ministerial Committee on European Questions.
3. Invited the Secretary of State for social services to discuss with those Government supportersconcerned their attitude to the directives.4. Invited the Lord President of the Council, inconsultation with the Foreign and commonwealth secretary, to circulate a memorandum on the handling of debates on European Economic Communitydraft legislation recommended by the ScrutinyCommittee for discussion at an early meeting of theCabinet.Cabinet Office9 January 1975


</content>
</cab>
