<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/6/27 images: 262-265</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
em131COPY NO.WAR CABINET,NORWEGIAN TANKER TONNAGE.Memorandum by the Minister of Ship-ping.1, In the conclusions of the War Cabinet at their meeting on2hth April, the Minister of Shipping was invited to furnish areport on the extent to which Norwegian tanker tonnage was being brought under Allied control, with special reference to theextent to which such tonnage is still being used to meet Italianr e qui r ement s.2. Under the Norwegian Shipping Arrangement, 145 tankers(including U7 already so used on pre-war charters) were to bemade available on time charter for the use of the Allies.      Ofthese, 6 have been caught in Scandinavian ports, 1 taken by theNorwegian Authorities for special service, and 2 have not so far been nominated, but these deficiencies have been made good by 9extra ships chartered under the arrangement, which can thus beregarded as practically complete.     The Allies have now chartered150 Norwegian tankers on scheme terms and 126 have actually bee:delivered.3* The following is a brief summary of the employment of theremaining 95 Norwegian tankers, so far as it is ascertainable:-12 detained or captured by the enemy in Scandinavia(including 6 due to be delivered under the scheme),11 owned by American oil interests under the Norwegian flag.3h chartered to American oil interests for varying periods.3 time chartered for Peru.h time chartered to Japanese interests.5 chartered for South American voyages.1 on Portuguese charter.2 on Norwegian Government Service,23 various (most of these charters will soon expire).Total 2 k. At the time of the invasion, there were 15 Norwegian tankers(included in the foregoing numbers) loaded, loading or on charter to load for Italy.      Of these 5 have been cancelled by theNorwegian authorities and the cancellation of another is under

consideration.     Three further vessels, due to discharge in italy, are chartered for Switzerland, hut have been diverted to Marseilles.The tankers trading to Italy have been or are being putunder requisition by the Norwegian Government and the Norwegianauthorities are arranging to allot them to the Allies for latervoyages.     Those already loaded for Italian destinations, of whichthere were 9, are being allowed (in accordance with War cabinet decision) to discharge in Italy in pairs, after which they willnot be permitted to continue on this service.     The ultimatedestination of all such cargoes is examined by the contraband control before vessels are allovi/ed to proceed.5. In order to protect the status of Norwegian vessels in neutral ports, the Norwegian Government have informed us that they intend to requisition their whole mercantile marine and, inconsultation with the Ministry of Shipping, this will be done in stages, special priority being given to tankers.      The effect ofthis requisition is to break the existing charters.     Obviouslythis power of talcing ships out of their present service must beused with discretion, after an investigation of the needs of allcountries concerned, in particular United States coastwise traffic,and traffic between the oil producing areas and South America,      Itshould also be possible by this means to exercise more control overlthe carriage of oil to Japan than has been possible hitherto,if6. Over and above the tankers, the Norwegian whaling fleet,consisting of 10 whaling factories, will almost immediately beavailable for the conveyance of petroleum products during the sunmer months almost of them should also be available next winter since even if it be Idecided (and a decision will shortly be taken) that any whalingexpeditions under either Norwegian or British control need proceedto the Antarctic next winter, the expeditions will be few,.7. Until a full survey of the world situation is made and the reasonable needs of neutral charterers have been assessed, it willnot be possible to indicate how much additional tonnage which theAllies may secure in the new circumstances.      It will also benecessary to take care not to exercise the power of diversion insuch a way as to cause neutral tankers (.e.g. those under the Panama Iflag), now trading in the Allied interest, to be withdrawn and placed on routes which might find themselves deprived of Norwegiantonnage.R.S.H.INISTRY OP SHIPPING.


</content>
</cab>
