<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/30 images: 320-327</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  September 1972CM (71) Copy No. \ 330th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 10 June, 1971,at 11.30 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of St.Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mp, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for Defence (items and 2)The Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon, q c,mp, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Da vies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry and President of the Boardof trade also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend . N. F. cairncross sir Philip adams mr. B. G. Tucker
contents subject parliamentary Affairs      ............European Economic CommunitiesOversea Affairs      ...............PakistanNorth Atlantic Treaty OrganisationPortugalUpper Clyde Shipbuilders............Occupational Pensioners and Unemployment BenefitNon-Industrial Civil Service Pay.........
ParliamentaryAffairsEuropeanEconomicCommunitiesPreviousReference:CM (71) 27thConclusionsCM 30 (71)secret. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons the following week.The Cabinet discussed the arrangements to be made to seekParliamentary approval of the terms of our accession to the european economic Communities (e.c.), on the assumption that the next meeting with representatives of the Communities on 21-22 Junewould finally dispose of the remaining obstacles to our membership.It was generally agreed that it would be desirable to publish a white Paper as soon as possible after that meeting and to arrangefor it to be debated before Parliament adjourned for the summer recess. It might be wise, however, to seek an early opportunityto make it clear that this debate would not necessarily be directed to securing final and definitive approval of the White Paper&apos;sproposals. A statement to this effect would serve to dispel theimpression, which was already prevalent and would gain strengthas the forthcoming meeting in Brussels approached, that theGovernment intended to try to compel Parliament to decide theissue of accession without proper time for reflection; and it should help to reassure those Members who felt that the month of Julywould allow too little time for them to consult their constituentsbefore being asked to cast a vote which could be regarded as effectively committing them irrevocably to a view on accession. Itwould be preferable to dispel these doubts at the present juncturethan to appear to be compelled to concede the point later underpressure; and this consideration was reinforced by the fact that theGovernment should in any event be on their guard against appearing to take it for granted that the outcome of the forthcoming discussions in Brussels would be wholly acceptable.On the other hand a statement on the lines suggested, if madeat this stage, might give the Communities the impression of a lackof urgency on our part and so endanger our chances of reachingfinal agreement on the outstanding issues at the forthcoming meeting in Brussels. Moreover, it would afford the opponents of accessionmore room for manoeuvre and greater opportunity to try to winover those whose minds were not yet made up.In further discussion it was suggested that the disquiet inParliament derived to some extent from an insufficient appreciation of (the various stages, including legislation, by which parliamentary approval of our accession to the e.c. would have to be sought overthe next 18 months before ,we formally achieved membership on1 January, 1973. The most satisfactory course, therefore, might befor the Prime Minister to undertake that afternoon in the House of
Commons to make a considerable statement, probably in the.following week, which would indicate the whole of the Parliamentary?timetable which would be involved if the outcome of the forthcoming!meeting in Brussels was satisfactory. This would allow the timing iof any definitive debate to be set in a rational context, with duelregard to the need to allow Members of Parliament adequate time!to consult their constituents; and it could perhaps be turned toladditional advantage in relation to the forthcoming meeting ailBrussels by demonstrating to the Communities that the requirements Iof our constitutional procedures, as far from allowing us to slacken 1our efforts to conclude the negotiations, made it imperative that they should be successfully terminated by the end of June.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that it was Igenerally agreed that the Government should seek to avoid creating!any impression that they intended to force a premature decision on Jthe issue of our accession to the e.c.. He would therefore inform!the House of Commons that afternoon that he would shortly make!a statement on the subject; and he would consider further, in the lightof the points made in the Cabinefs discussion, the means by which!such a statement might best reassure public opinion without prejudicing our negotiating position in Brussels.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing fup of their discussion.OverseaAffairsPakistanPreviousReference:CM (71) 29thConclusions,Minute 3NorthAtlanticTreatyOrganisationSECRET;2.   The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that therewere some indications that Parliamentary and public opinion doubted whether the subscription of  1 million which the Government hadalready made to the relief of refugees from East Pakistan was Isufficient in view of the gravity of their plight and that it might be;necessary for us to supplement this contribution, preferably in the;form of a single lump sum.  As soon as we knew more clearly the;scale of total further aid which was required he would discuss an,increase in the British contribution with the Chancellor of the;Exchequer.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary reported that he had Irecently attended a meeting of the North Atlantic Ministerial Council]at Lisbon and that the results of the meeting had been satisfactory. 1There was general agreement among the Foreign Ministers concerned 1that in the absence of progress towards a settlement of the problem?of Berlin there could be little hope of a more general detente in f
Upper ClydeShipbuildersPreviousReference:CM (71) 6thConclusions,Minute 2SECRET3. The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that theChairman of Upper Clyde Shipbuilders (UCS) had informed himearlier that week that, on the basis of revised forecasts, the UCSBoard now considered the company to be insolvent and that, if theycontinued trading, their total indebtedness to creditors by Augustwould exceed  9 million and they would have a net asset deficiency of at least  4 million. They did not have the cash to continue payingstaff wages after Friday, 18 June. The Board were accordinglyexpected to decide on 10 June that they could not continue in business and should apply for the appointment of a provisionalliquidator; and a decision to this effect would be conveyed to theunions the same afternoon.The situation disclosed by this report had been discussed in the ministerial Committee on Economic Strategy earlier that morning;and he had since made arrangements with the Board that they woulddefer any action until at least the following Tuesday, 15 June, in orderto give the Government, as their principal shareholder, time in whichi to consider the situation further. In return for this delay he had giventhe Board two assurances: that finance would be provided to enablerelations with the Soviet bloc. It had therefore been decided to concentrate efforts on seeking to persuade the Soviet Government to conclude a reasonable agreement on Berlin.Portugal The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that he hadtaken the opportunity of his presence in Lisbon for the North atlantic council Ministerial meeting to have discussions with the portuguese government, whose attitude had been cordial and co-operative. Hehad not been pressed on any of the points of contention betweenthe two Governments, including the continuation of the Beira Patrol.The Portuguese Prime Minister, Professor Caetano, had said that hewould be prepared to write at an appropriate time to the leader ofthe regime in Rhodesia, Mr. Ian Smith, urging him to make asettlement with us, if we judged that this would be helpful. ProfessorCaetano had also indicated that the Portuguese Government might wish to place orders for warships in this country; and it would benecessary to give further consideration to our attitude towards anysuch orders.The Cabinet-i Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary.
staff wages due on 25 June to be paid, if necessary by the provisionalliquidator, and that the members of the Board would be indemnifiedin respect of any liabilities personally incurred by them, as a resultof delaying until 15 June an announcement that the Company was unable to continue trading.The Prime Minister said that the Economic Strategy Committeehad commissioned an urgent study of means by which, in the eventof the collapse of UCS, an orderly rundown could be secured and individual shipyards now comprised in the UCS group might be protected to some extent. The Committee would meet again afterthe week-end; and, if necessary, a further report would be made tothe Cabinet at an early date.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Secretary of State for trade and Industry and the Prime Minister.occupational pensioners andUnemploymentBenefitPreviousReference :CM (71) 17thConclusions,Minute 8CONFIDENTIAL4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Social Services (CP (71) 66), to which was annexed amemorandum about occupational pensioners and unemploymentbenefit which had been considered by the Home and Social AffairsCommittee (HS) on 7 June.The Secretary of State for Social Services said that HS had considered the situation which had resulted from the loss during theCommittee Stage of the National Insurance Bill of the clause which sought to limit the misuse of unemployment benefit by individuals who had retired from their career employment with substantialoccupational pensions and were doubtfully, if at all, in the employ-ment field. HS had concluded that no attempt should be made to restore the clause to the Bill on Report, sincelt was lack of support from Government back-benchers which had enabled the Oppositionto carry the deletion of the clause in Committee and the necessarysupport from the Government side would not be forthcoming for itsrestoration.HS had also concurred in his suggestion that, as a logicalconsequence of this recommendation, the Government should seek to delete from the Bill on Report the clause which removed theliability of individuals over 60 to pay the non-employed person&apos;national Insurance contribution, since this clause had been introduced only in order to render more acceptable the restrictionson unemployment benefit which it was now proposed to abandon.
sThe Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the statement by the Secretaryof State for Social Services and invited him to proceed accordingly.Non-industrial civil ServicePayPreviousReference :CM (71) 28thConclusions,Minute 1SECRET*5. The Lord Privy Seal said that the Cabinet had authorised him on 25 May to seek a negotiated settlement, based on pay research, up to 11-7 per cent for Civil Service Clerical grades and upto 9\ per cent for the Administrative/Executive grades. Hardnegotiations, coupled with the ability to meet the Staff Associationson certain points of scale construction which they would have beenunlikely to have secured at arbitration, had resulted in a settlement for the Clerical grades costing a little over \\\ per cent. In thenegotiations with the Administrative /Executive grades, however, the scales resulting from implementation of almost the full amountauthorised by the Cabinet had been rejected by the Staff Associationsconcerned. His assessment was that a settlement could certainly bet obtained by offering 10 per cent and might be obtained at 9f percent. A negotiated settlement was desirable in the interests of morale and good management. The staff concerned had so far hadcompounded increases of only 14 per cent since 1 January, 1968,compared with a rise in the wages index of nearly 30 per cent in thesame period. For the Executive Officer grade, a large proportion ofwhom were working substantial overtime to implement Governmentprogrammes, the present pay offer would provide only a 5-6 per cent increase. A settlement within a maximum of 9f per cent for theAdministrative/Executive grades as a whole would enable significantimprovements to be made at key points in the Executive Officer scale and would strengthen the hands of the moderate elements in theStaff Associations. It would still represent a stringent interpretation of the pay research evidence. If agreement were not reached, thealternative would be to allow the claim to go to arbitration; and thiswould involve a real risk of a substantially higher award. Becauseof the advantages of a negotiated settlement, he therefore sought authority to try to settle with the Administrative/Executive grades ata figure not exceeding 9f per cent.In discussion it was argued that the concession of a further\ per cent to the Administrative/Executive grades would encourageboth the Staff Associations and the unions representing the industrial civil Service to negotiate on the footing that the Government couldbe brought to raise their offers by intransigence and threats ofi; * Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.
industrial action. In particular, the Society of Civil Servants had before them a Resolution calling for a ban on overtime from 14 June jjif no agreement had been reached by then. To settle with the IAdministrative/Executive grades at per cent, moreover, would increase the average of the two pay research settlements with the non-industrial Civil Service; and it was this average which wouldinfluence the attitude of local authorities towards the pay of their jown staffs. On the other hand the rise in the average increase under fthe two settlements from 10^-10^ per cent would not be significant; fand a negotiated settlement with the Administrative/Executive grades 1at 91 per cent was greatly to be preferred to the risks of allowing the iclaim to be decided by arbitration. If an overtime ban were imposed Iby Executive grades in default of an agreed settlement, the 1programme for uprating social security benefits would &quot;be jeopardised;Moreover, the low &quot; open &quot; offer which it would be necessary tomake at arbitration to avoid the &quot; without prejudice &quot; offers becoming Ithe floor for the arbitration would consist of salary scales considerably less favourable than those which had already been rejected in negotiation. The conventions at arbitration were understood by the associations&apos; negotiators, but not by the rank and file; and thepublication of a very low &quot; open &quot; offer would create strong resent-ment among the grades concerned.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed on balance that the Lord Privy Seal should beauthorised to seek a negotiated settlement with the Administrative/Executive grades at a figure not exceeding 9f per cent. It would be important to ensure that any settlement reached on that basis waspublicly presented as being designed to restore lost ground; and thefact that the settlement for the Clerical grades had achieved general facceptance on that basis encouraged the belief that this should be;possible. In order to ensure that the Government retained theinitiative in regard to the public presentation of the settlement, or ofHany breakdown in the negotiations, it was important to avoid;premature disclosure; and the Lord Privy Seal-should arrange for the IOfficial Side negotiators to keep in close touch with the Prime]Ministers Press Office.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing!up of their discussion and invited the Lord Privy Seal to belguided accordingly.

</content>
</cab>
