<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/62/0 images: 53-56</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tv ofSECRET. 26th August 1918.^io\ REPORT ON THE OUTPUT OF MATERIEL.Half-year ended 30th June 1918.ADMIRALTY MEMORANDUM FOR THE WAR CABINET.The work of the Controllers Department in the production of materiel for the Navy has been reviewed, and the following extracts are submitted as it is thought they may be of interest to the War Cabinet.Warships and Auxiliaries.New Construction.During the last half-year the following warships and auxiliary vessels have been completed : Light Cruisers        -        -        - -             2Flotilla Leaders       -        -        - -             2T.B.D.&apos;s......34Submarines   -        -        -        - - -  18Sloops         -        -        -        - - -  15Patrol Boats -        -        -        - - -    6Submarine Depot Ship        -        - -              1Coast Defence Vessel -        -        - -             1Trawlers      -      &apos;-        -        - - -86,Drifters       -        - - -  28Minesweepers -        -        -        - - -  20Other Auxiliary Vessels       -        - - -  86This output compares with the completions of naval vessels during the last 41 years thus : Period,	No.	Displacement.	Average Size.		Tons.	Tods.	75	294,436	3,925	209	425,428	2,035,,   1916    -     -     -   - -	304	770,819	2,5351917 &apos; -     -     -     -     -     -     -	368	519,631	1,412Half-year 1918......	299	214,272	716The policy of constructing smaller craft for anti-submarine work which has been adopted is clearly reflected in this table. The number of vessels added to the Navy during the half-year ended 30th June was 299, with an average displacement of only 716 tons per ship as compared with 3,925 tons in 1914.Although the displacement tonnage has fallen compared with previous years, the labour required for new construction of naval vessels cannot be proportionately reduced. Generally speaking, the lighter craft, such as destroyers and trawlers, require more labour per displacement ton than the heavier ships. The labour employed in private yards on new construction amounted to 139,000 at the 30th June as compared with .128,000 in January last. The increase is almost entirely on the construction of hulls, the numbers employed on machinery showing only a very slight increase. This illustrates the point frequently made that the submarine war has told very severely upon British shipbuilding.O (33) AS 6095  Pk        30 8/18  E&amp;S
Bepairs and Befits,Considerable efforts have been made to reduce the work of repairing and refitting naval craft. The length of time between refits of destroyers has been extended from four to six months, and the time between refits for other classes, e.g., trawlers, &amp;c, has been similarly extended. In addition to these steps, the work of refitting is being very closely rationed, no work other than that absolutely necessary for the maintenance of the ships in seaworthy and fighting condition being undertaken. These measures have only slightly reduced the number of vessels requiring to be refitted, as we have the continually increasing anti-submarine fleet of the Royal Navy to provide for (299 ships having been added during the last half-year). Increased provision has been made for refitting American warships in British yards. 106 Allied vessels were refitted last half-year. The number of British vessels repaired and refitted during the half-year amounted to 6,014 as compared with an average half-yearly number of 6,266 during 1916 and 1917.The rationing of repairs and refits has, however, had an effect on the labour required. In private yards the numbers&apos; employed on this work have fallen from 47,000 in January last to 38,000 in June. Of this decrease, roughly 3,000 were employed on hulls and 5,000 to 6,000 on machinery.Guns.The arrangements made for improving the output of guns, although not yet fully operative, have begun to show gratifying results. The following short table shows under four main groups the deliveries of guns during the last five half-years : Half-year.	Above 6-inch.	4-inch to 6-inch.	Below 4-inch.	Howitzers and Bomb-throwers.	Hotel.1916, 1st.....	34	235	929		1,1982nd.....	21	&apos;   355	2,141	 	2,5171917, 1st   -	17	527	1,588	13	. 2,1452nd.....	59	654	1,357	514	2,5811918, 1st  -     -     -     -     -	43	1,128	1,226	615	3,012As will be seen, the total has increased from J ,198 in the first half of 1916 to 3,012 in the first half of 1918. Apart from howitzers.and,,bomb-throwers, which are special weapons for anti-submarine work, the largest increase is in the medium sizes of gun, 4-inch to 6-inch, namely, from 235 to 1,128. These guns are considered to be the most effective weapons for the defence of merchant ships, and are now being largely used for this purpose.   The following table shows the position at the 30th June withregard to the arming of merchant ships : Guns mounted.6-inch     -     -     -     -     -     -     -     -     - 1374-7-inch.......... 6504-inch    -     -           ....... 73012-pdr. and under   -     --     --     --     - 2,303Howitzers      -     --     --     --     -- 580Total     -    .-.    -     -   4,400Ammunition.The output of ammunition during the half-year shows a marked increase. This increased demand is due to causes of which the War Cabinet are aware.Shell.The following table shows the increase in the output of filled shell: Nature,	Half-year ended 81st December 1917.	Half-year ended 30th .June 1918.	Increase.	Per Cent.Above 6-inch                              * 6-inch to 4&apos;inch       -     -Below 4-inch   -     -     -	19,990 124,738 77,992	24,002 227,990 194,566	4,012 103,252 116,574	20 1 82-8 149-5
	Half-year ended 31st December 1917.	Half-year ended 30th June 1918.	Increase.	Per Cent.Fuzes (filled)   -	601,628	1.093,079	491,451	81-7Primers, percussion   -      -      -      -	118,003	982,906	864,903	733-0Adapters ------	75,720	379,893	304,173	401-7B.L. cartridge filling has presented no difficulty, and has kept pace with the output of shell and components. Difficulty has, however, been experienced in obtaining the desired supply of empty cartridge cases for Q.F. and fixed ammunition; but the output during the last half-year although not fully equal to requirements  has shown considerable expansion, and there is every reason to look forward to still greater expansion during the current half-year. The total number approved in the last half-year of all sizes amounted to 1,112,705, an increase of 281,096, or 33 &quot;8 per cent., compared with the previous half-year.Mines.The programme for increased production of mines adopted in the early part of 1917 has been pushed forward as rapidly as possible, and the output of UH.&quot; mines (the particular type most required) reached 41,981 during the half-year, as compared with 14,000 during the previous half-year, an increase of practically 200 per cent. The output during the month of June 1917 was only 21.Depth Charges.The success of the employment of depth charges in the anti-submarine campaign has been very clearly demonstrated oh many occasions, and the output has been considerably developed during the six months ended 30th June. 32,450 were assembled ready for issue, as compared with 10,090 during the previous six months.Depth Charge Throwers.The development of the output of this weapon has received special attention. Up to 3lst December 1917, 297 had been produced. During the last half-year 1,552 were completed.Torpedoes.The output of torpedoes remains steady, being on the average between 50 and 60 per week.  Requirements have been met.Merchant Ships.The responsibility for merchant ship construction and repairs no longer rests on the Navy Controller; but, having regard to the fact that the change-over occurred during the last half-year and also to the fact that this work makes to a large extentA large proportion of the increased output of shell is required for the outfits of defensively-armed merchant ships. In addition to the general satisfactory increase in output, there has been a striking development in the manufacture of A.P. shell for guns 12-inch and above. The design of this ammunition has involved prolonged research and a largo number of experiments; and considerable time elapsed before any maker was able to produce shell to completely satisfy the new requirements. It is satisfactory to report that all the makers have now been able to fully comply with the specification, and supply is steadily coming in.Components.Owing to the high standard which must be observed in naval ammunition, owing to the terrible effect of accidents on board ship and the vital importance of thoroughly effective functioning in the short time available for attack in naval warfare, consider-able difficulty is occasionally experienced in obtaining the full numbers of components, such as fuzes, primers, and adapters. The difficulties which affected output towards the end of 1917 have to a large extent been overcome, and the output during the half-year shows a very satisfactory increase, as the following figures prove : 
demands on the same class of labour and material as naval work, the review would be incomplete without some information on these two points.Neiv Construction.The output during the last five half-years is as under : Gross Tons.1916, 1st half ------- 203,2592nd half -     -..... 338,2931917, 1st half....... 495,5702nd half.....-     - 667,9041918, 1st half....... 763,246In order to obtain the best results it was decided that Naval and Merchant work should be confined as far as possible to Yards most suitable for each class of work, thus avoiding the confusion which is inevitable if both classes of work are carried on side by side each under a separate control. It will be some time yet before all the . warships building on slips hypothecated to merchant ships can be completed, and also all the merchant ships now on slips allocated to warship construction ; but unity of control at each Yard has been established.During the half-year the supply of steel by the Ministry of Munitions has been fully equal to the demands of the Yards. Labour of the right kind has been the limiting factor. The numbers employed on merchant ship new construction during the half-year have only increased by 10,500, and of these nearly 8,000 were employed on hulls and the balance on machinery.Bepairs.The completions of merchant ship repairs, which showed appreciable development partly owing to arrears during the latter months of 1917, continued to increase until the month of May, since when the completions have not been quite so high, due to the fact that the arrears of repairs have now practically been overtaken. The average tonnage completed repair per month during the half-year was 2,190,974. This compares with a monthly average for the last five months of 1917 of 1,552,169, or an increase of 41 per cent. The labour employed on repair of merchant ships has increased from 60,232 on the 31st January to 66,826 on the 30th June. The increase on hulls was nearly 10,000, there being a decrease of 3,000 on machinery. From these figures it will be seen that repairs have made a very large demand on labour which can be employed on hulls, and that is the class of labour in which the greatest shortage is experienced and where dilution and up-grading have proved to be most difficult. It should also be mentioned that the numbers employed on the repair of hulls of merchant ships require a far larger percentage of skilled labour than a similar number employed on new construction.26th August 1918.(Signed)     ERIC GEDDES.

</content>
</cab>
