<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/62/0 images: 114-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Ti&amp;lJDOC^is iij/AB   CABINET .S E C K Jiii T   I IgEQ^/JJXGiKT OF .j;H:,;.VT RAILWAY COI&amp;flJNICATIONS.mmm pn ur n&quot;i i -rifinimiTr rTinnnwin -i,m new n ,n. mii.niiiwMiwrrmri.mil mm gm mi in Bnnam.^^...^^ ..........mm0mmmmmmm0mmwmmwm0mmm\G.T. .5589 gELiiiCTIO^ ftff POINTS. 03? ATTACK PQK AERIALB0S^3fTSpTiSCf RAILWAY COlliMl(l)    Minute from British Military Representative,Supreme War Council, to Secretary, War Cabinet, 24.7.18Enclosure lA.Memorandum by British Section, Inter-Allied Transportation Council.iSn closure B*Memorandum by Fren&amp;h Section, Inter-Allied Transportation Council.(It)    Letter from Air Ministry to Secretary, V/arCabinet. 23.8.18Notes by the Chief of the Air Staff. 23.8.18(I)SfiPy, JS&amp;. J* We,, f     fc&amp;telPkJ&amp;Utety, Representative^ Su^em^go Secretary, War CabinetrHo. 4/C/lSecretary,War Cabinet.t ta m m (j, w m ea m (I attach copies of two papers which have been forwarded to me by the British Representative, Inter-Allied Transportation Council, on the-sutoftetof the prinoiples to Ve observed in selecting points of attack for aerial bombardment, designed to interfere with the enemy&apos;a Railway Communication.It will be noted that the papej; (marked B) drawn up by the Frenoh Section of the Infrer-Allied Transportation Council lays down substantially the same principles as those advocated in the British paper (marked a) though there are several differences in point of detail as well as in arrangement.I (signed)   C. SACKVILLiii V&amp;QTHajor General, Acting British Military Representativav-Supreme Vax Council.ViSRSAILLiJS,Copies to CI.G.S. JULY 24th. 1916. Chief of Air Staff.
ENCLOSURE A TO il) 4 G.T. -5529. PRINCIPLE. AFFECTING THE ;SELECT!ON OF POINTS OF ATTACKON THE OTff&apos; S RAILWAY COMMUNICATIONS . II NTRODUGTORY.The inter-Allied Transportation Council are respon.-sible for tendering&apos;advice as to the points at which the enemyf s railway oomnuni cat ions can he attached from the air with the greatest prospect of success.   Before advice is offered in regard to particular targets it appears desirable that an agreement should he reaohed as to the principles, which, from the transportation point of view, should govern the selection of objectives.TWO CASES FOE CONSIDERATION.It will be convenient to consider the matter separately in two different sets of circumstances(1)    When intensive operations ore in progress, or known to &quot;be impending! upon a particular seator of the front-(2)    When intensive operations are not in progress, and there is no elear indication of unusual enemy activity opposite any particular sector,SEVERANCE OF C01MJHICATION WITH A PARTICULAR SECTOR,    &apos;When intensive fighting is in progress on a partic-ular sector^ or there is clear evidence that it is about .tt begin, it is considered that the primary object of attack from the air upon the enemy railway oommunications should be the severance of tskyep eommunioations between that sector and the enemy8a bases in the rear.   It is clear that to sever one of several lines of communication leading to such a sector will have but a trifling effect in interfering with the enemy(s effort; again from the transportation point *?f view even the cutting of all the lines of communication with a particular sector will have little effect, if &quot;oojaraunio&amp;tioB can be restored within a few hours.   Our object must there-fore be to sever all communication with a particular sector, and to keep it interrupted for as long as possible^MINIUUte DISTANCI:&apos;- FROM TEE FRONTtTO T1IE POINTS OF ATTACK .All past experience goes to eho?/ that aerial attack directed against enemy railway communications at a distance of less than 20 kilometres from the front which these communi cations serve will be of little avails nearer to the,front than this a large number of branch lines are ordinarily avail-able, leading to transhipment stations, railheads and the like, so that complete interruption of traffic is well-nigh impossible, furthermore, even if it were possible to inter-rupt railway traffic entirely within 20 kilometres of the front, the only result would be to add a little to the disia which supplies, emmunition, etc, would have to be carried by road or light railway, and to the distance which troops concentrating in the area would have to march,GENERAL CONSIDERATION OF OBJECTIVES TO BE SELECTED.It is manifest that by attacking engine depots, workshops, watering arrangement a,. and other facilities inconnection
connection with the maintenance of the rolling stock and vorks of a railway, though material dama;;;e may be caused, complete local interruption of traffic cannot be effected, This result can c-aly be obtained by rendering the several railway lines loading to the particular sectcn impassable for trains, that is to say, the Tails must be broken,or best of all, a train wrecked, so as to block the tracks.   The tracks may be broken at :**(a) Important Junctions or marshalling yards(b) Ordinary stations.(o)    Petween stations.Obviously, it is most difficult to break all the available tracks at points such as (a); even if several tracks are broken in a junction station, several other tracks will be available for the passage of trains, while at all the more important junctions, avoiding lines will be available, rendering it possible to divert traffic without causing more than slight inconvenience,   At wayside stations there is more hope of breaking all available tracks, but to do this ivblearly more difficult than between stations.   Furthermore, both at (a) and (b) immediate warning will be given of the fact that the tracks have been -broken, and there is no prospect of a train running into the breach, while men are likely to be upon the spot ready immediately to begin repairs. It is therefore considered that attack with therobject of severing communication should invariably be directed against the track between stations.6*      ARTICULAR OBJaOTIVffa ,The partial destruction of bridges will cause more pro-longed interruption of traffic than the breaking of tracks at any other points.   The damage done to the HiTABi^S bridge on the night of the 30th-31st Liay shows that even a very heavily constructed masonry viaduct can be seriously damaged with complete interruption of traffic by a well directed bomb. Next to a bridge or viaduct, which is after all a very email markj especially a girder bridge, where the girder itself must be cut to achieve anything effective, damage done in cuttings will be the most effective because of the chance of bringing in the sides of the cuttings, and of the greater destruction, and the greater difficulty of clearing the wreck if a train should run into the breach.   It is presumed that from the aviation point of view it will be desirable that straight lengths of line should be selected for attack on account of the greater prospect of reaching the mark.     If it is possible to drop the bomb in front of a moving train the effect will be great.7,     FKSQ.U&amp;NCY OF ATTACK.In the general area selected for attack, traffic will , tend to be most dense from shortly before dusk to shortly after dawn; night attaoks will therefore be preferable to day attacks.   The great desideratum is, however, to pidong the period of interruption, and this etyjeot can only be secured by repeating the attacks on each sector at regular intervals. It is considered that it in desirable that the attacks should be renewed every two hours.   If the first attack has been successful in breaking the line, the subsequent attacks will not be without result, evea if the line is not again broken,
as the work of repair of the line will certainly &quot;be consider-ably i nt erf ercd wi th.8.   ALJEHNATIVE, IvIPlT:fTOD OP^ATTACK. &apos; &apos;It may frequently happen that atmospheric conditions make it impracticable to reach as snail a mark as that pro-sent ed by a line of railway,   *7e must in those circumstances seel: some other method of interrupting traffic with the sector which v/c seek to isolate,   lixpericnoe on our own side of the front goes to, show that an almost complete local para-lysis of traffic can&apos; he caused &quot;by repeated bombardment of J.arge yards in which shunting work is in progress, tbough the panic oauscd among the personnel.   To be effective, attacks must &quot;be repeated at very short intervals, of half-an-hour, say.     The bombs need not be heavy, numerous or particularly well directed.   It is the frequency of the attack, not its violence or its effectiveness, which should be relied upon to produce the moral effect required.   Yards must be select-ed for attack through which the traffic serving the particu-lar sector to be isolated must necessarily pass,9 *   OBJECTS Off ATTACK &apos;./K3N 10 OffJjTOIVE IS III PROGRESS OHWhen intensive -fighting is not in progress, and there is no clear indication of its being imminent upon any partic-ular sector, there is much less object in attemtping to interrupt the enemy * a com.junications with a particular secter. Indiscriminate attacks on the railway communications will produce little effect.   Little permanent materiel damage is caused by breaking tracks, and casual delays to trains will . hav e no inip art ant mi 1 i t ary result.Two effective methods of attack suggest themselves(1)     The interruption of communication between the sources of supply used in Germany and the whole area in which the enemy&apos;s army is operating in Belgium and prance.(2)     Destruction of material which cannot be re-placed rapidly, and such that the want of it will interfere with any transportation which the enemy may wish to carry out,10. INTERRUPT I OH OP C0P&quot;.lJdI^ATI0M JITH GE&amp;ANY.Attacks directed towards severing the enemy&apos;s railway communications with a particular sector T.vill ordinarily be made at no very great distance from the front which their communications serve.   Further from the front than a dis-tance of some 75 kilometres there will ordinarily be little possibility of achieving this result as at any greater dis-tanoc so many alternative lines are likely to be available that to break them all would be impracticable.   It so happens, however, that practically all communication from Germany to the occupied parts of Belgium and Prance can be severed by the breaking of tracks on no mere than five sections.     It    I will be seen that this result can be secured by breaking the five sections noted in the margin.1.-   Between GENMENICH and Of those (1), (2) and (5) are by. farVISE JUNCTION, on the new the most important only a small, por-1   German line AIX-TONGKES.        cent age of the total volume of traffiis believed to use the other two.Br 2.- Through
If persistent bombing of points so. far distant car. be parried&quot; out ix the manner already recommended, the transport of all material and of reinforcements from Germany would for the time being be interrupted&apos;.Clearly, attack against these points should be carried out, not when the offensive has been organ-ised but when the enemy is collec-ting reserves of material and bringing up reinforcements to reform divisions, that is at times when no offensive is in progress or appears imminent.DESTRUCTION 07 MATERIAL.It may be that systematic attack against points as remote as those mentioned in the previous paragraph is impracticable. In any case tho method of attack there proposed cannot be carried out often, for the enemy would so defend these sectors as to make successful attack against such small objectives impossible.   The alternative during times of preparation qt comparative quiet appears to be to destroy material which the enemy is known to require, and which he cannot quickly replace so that the effect will be felt when a serious effort has again to be made.It is considered that there is no way in which greater material damage can be inflicted than by the destruction, partial or complete, of of attack it is clearly transportation point ofthe attack in which alocomotives.   Where this is the object a matter of indifference from, the view at what distance from the front is made, any round house, workshop,- or engine shed, number of locomotives have beenconsiderablecollected, for coaling, watering, or for overhauling will con-stitute a suitable objective.It is impossible to say what is precisely the present position in regard to locomotives; there isth.enemy&apos; s howeverconclusive evidence that he is extremely short of engines, and that he has a great difficulty in overtaking the repairs of the engines that ho has got,   It may be taken therefore as certain that every locomotive destroyed will have to bo replaced by the   enemy; that the loss will reduce for a considerable time the total volume of traffic which the enemy can handle, and that much skilled, labour will be required to make-it good. To construct a locomotive requires the work of from 20 to 30 skilled men for a year; even if complete destruction is but seldom effected it is unquestionable that very considerable material loss will be caused, by a bomb falling in a shod, depot, or workshop.   As an instance of what the enemy have achieved in this direction the case of the aerial attack upon the French Locomotive Depot at ROJ.5E3CAT1PS may be quoted;    In this case a single bomb caused serious damage to Locomotives*four French2.     Through the station of ANGL&quot;:!UR on the southern out-skirsts of LIEGE.3*     Between MARLOIE and CINEY on.the ARLON-NAU.UR line.4. Between HOUYET and DINANT on the lines from LlHRAMOKT or BERTRIX to NAMUR.^.     Between CARIGNAN   and SEDAN on the line from LONGUYON to MBZIERI3S.
Comitfe Interallied desTransports. Paris, le l6 Juillet, 1918.Section Prancaise. No. 277/0.1,T..PRINCIPES K3GISSANT LE CHOIX PES POINTS D! ATTAtiUB 3UR LUIS VOIES FERREES   ENNEMIES.INTRODUCTION. Le Comite Interallied des Transports est chargede donner son avis sur les points des voieo ferries ennemies qu&apos;il eat le plus interessant d&apos;atteindre, au doura d&apos;une attaque aerienne pour faire le plus grand tort possible aux transports ennemis.Avant qu&apos;un avis soit donne au sujet d&apos;un but determine, il semble desirable quo 1*accord existe quant aux principes qui, au point de vue du transport, devraient preoider au ehoix des objectifsTrois cas sont a considerer:1.       EES OPERATIONS ACTIVES SONT EN COURS OU VQNT ETRJ EN COURS BAN!UN SEC!EUR. BIEN ^ETElRl^I^^7w&apos;&quot;,        &quot; **&quot;&quot;2,       tSBS OPERATIONS ACTIVES SONT EN PREPARATION BANS UN SECTEUR&quot;MNEllI INLETERHINE.3.       IL N!Y A PAS D&apos; OPERATIONS ACTIVES EN COURS ET IL N&apos;Y A PAS, D&apos; INDICATIONS NETTES 5&apos;UNE ACTIVITE INUSITEE EE L^NKSlUTNous allons examiner sucees3ivement cos trois cas, 1.       EES OPERATIONS ACTIVES SONT EN COURS OU VONT ETRE EN COURS DAMUN SECTEUR BIEN DETERJ^lW&apos;.Deux moyens sont k notre disposition pour entraver les transports ennemis:A.      RUPTURE LES COMMUNICAT!QNS AVEC UN SECTEUR EETERHINB.^uand un combat intense a lieu sur un secteur partioulier cu quand.il est evident au&apos;il va se produire, nous eonsiderons que le premier objet d&apos;une attaque aerienne our les voies ferrees est la rupture des communications entre $e seeteur, ies bases ennemies de 1&apos;arriere et des secteurs voisins.     II est evident que la rupture d&apos;une seule des nombreuses voies eonduisant a ce secteur n&apos;aura qu&apos; un .effet mediocre sur 1&apos;effort de 1&apos;ennemi.     Le meme, au point de vue transports, la ruptifire de toutes lea lignes de communication avec un secteur determine aura peu d&apos;effets si la circulation peut etre retablie en quelques haures.     Notre but doit etre done de rompre toutes les lignes de communication conduisant a. un secteur determine et de les maintenir rompues pendant le plus longtemps possible.Considerations gjmerales sur le choix des choix d&apos;objectifs.II est de toute evidence que 1&apos;attaque d&apos;un depot de locomotives, d1ateliers, de prises d&apos;eau et des autres installations interessant le materiel -s&apos;en suivait, ne pourrait pas entrainer une interruption locale complete du trafic.     Ce resultat ne pourrait
*m m.etre atteint qu&apos;en pendant impraticables Iob differented Hgneo conduisant au memo seoteur, oe qui revient a dire que loo rails doivent etre ooupes out encore mioux un train deraille sur la voie pour la bloquor.La voie pout etre rompuo:a) aux gares do j emotion ou dans les chant, i era de triage:b) aux stations ordinaires;c) entre les stations.II est tch&amp; difficile do oouper toutes les voies dana les voies tols que a) - meme si plusieurs voieo etaicnt coupees dans une gare de bifurcation plusieurs reeteraiont encore praticables qui permettraient de devier 1c trafic   in ne causant que des inconvenients legers.     Tans les stations il y a evideiameht plus d&apos; espoir de couper toutes lees voies, mais c&apos;est beaucoup plus difficile k faire qu&apos;entre Ion gares.     Bicn plus dans les points a) et b) 1&apos;avis de la rupture des voies nerait immediatement donne et on aurait peu de chance de voir un train a&apos;engager sur la breche;   d&apos; autre part les equioes de reparation nourrnient etre immediatement a pied d&apos;oeuvre.Neue estimons done qulune attaque dans le but d*interrompre les communications 6oit invariablement   etre dirigee sur la voie entre deux stations.Objectifs particuliers,1.     Quyrages d&apos;art.-   La destruction partielle des ponts causera une interruption de trafic plus prolongee que la rupture des voles en tout autre point.    Les degats oauses au pent dHUTAPLIS dans la nuit du 30 Avril au ler Mai montrent q,u&apos;un viadue, meme conetruit en solide maconnerie, peut etre serieusement endommage, entralnant une interruption complete du trafic par une seule bombe bien dirigee. L?amorcage de ces bombes, au point de vue du retard adonner h la fusee, doit faire l&apos;objet d&apos;une $tude particuliere dans- le cas de ehaque ouvrage en maconnerie*Pour les ponts metalliques - qu-1 il est d&apos;ailleurs tres difficile d!endommager - la fusee devra etre instantanee.tres grand plusse jette dansdesirable do choisir des lignes droitos comme points d!attaque, a cause de la plus grande chance d?atteindre le but.     On devra done s!attache? a viser, autant que possible, des voios ferrees a la fois en ligno droite et en deblai de grand profondeur.Le bombardement en pleine voie le plus efficase sera effoctue sur un. point choisi de tolle fa^H du&apos;un train qui se dirige vors ce point ne puisse etre arreteavant de IVatteindre.Distance minimum du front aux points d&apos;attaque.Touto le passe est la pour montrer qu&apos;une attaque aferienne dirigee contre les voies ferrees enneraiee a moins do 20 kilometres du front desservi par cos voios, est do peu d!effct.     Au desaoue de cette distance on dispose generalcment d&apos;un grand ncmbre d&apos;ombranchO&apos; ments de telle sorte qu&apos;une interruption complete du trafii^ est pratiquement impossible. ^ SMI etait possible d*interrompre tout trafic ferrfc dans oette zone do 20 Km, h partir du front, lo seul resultat obtenu serait d!augmentor legeremont la distance a fairo parcourir par route aux vivres et munitions et la distance que-les troupes on voio de concentration auraient a fairo a pied.
Frequence des attagues.B. ENTRAVES APPORTES AU SERVICE EES GARES EE TRIAGE.mmm - mmm .nn.--h.--.m.imhi m v i   i main i mm ft &apos; mm mmmm       m      mm n mmm mm ******* \ mm . mm      n ii.ih*.mhhi.....m.......mmnmnmw. . . np4L1experionye aoquis^ sur notre front domontre qu&apos;uno paralysie pr^sque complete du trafio peut etre occasionnee par un bombardement re-pate des chantiers ou se font les manoeuvres et eel a grace a lapanique creee dans le personnel.     Pc-ur etre of f i oacof les attaques doi^ent etre repot beu a de courts intervalles -   une tiemi-heure par exairple - et pendant plusieurs jours de^suite.     Peu import e que les bojube s so lent tovir.de o - .- -est sur la f requenoe avec laquelie eUles so tit lanc.ee3 et nor. sur leur effet destructeur, qu&apos;il faivt oorapter pour olrcenir 1&apos;effet moral lecherche,     II faut choisir les chant iers a att&amp;e ue:i parmi oeux od pas sent necessairement le trafic du secteur a isoler et attaguer simultanement tous les chantiers qui peurraient mutuellement se remplacer.Ce genre d!Attaque sera le seul possible quand lesconditions atmospheriques ne permettront pas la visee de la pleine voie ou des ouvrages d!art,2&quot;      -EES OPERATIONS ACTIVES SO NT EN PREPARATION BANS UN SECTEURLe but sera d&apos;obtenir 1&apos;interruption des communications entr( des sources de ravitaillement en Allemagne avec la plus grande partie de la zone dans laquelle 1&apos;armee ennemie operc en BBLGIQUE et en FRA1Interruption des communications avec l&apos;Allemagne.Les attaques ayant pour but d;interrpmpre.les communications ennemies avec un secteur particulier ne serene generalement pas faites a une grande distance du front desservl.     A une distance variable suivant les secteurs et qu&apos;011] peut estimer a, environ 75&quot; Km. du front, on se trouve en face d&apos;une multiplicite de routes telle qu&apos; est impossible de pouvoir compter couper tous les moyens de communioA tion pour un secteur determine.Cependant il se presente ce fait que pratiquement toutes les communications d1 Allem**gne aux sones ocoupees en BELCIQ,U1 et en PRAM1 peuvent eyre interrompuos par la rupture des lignes sur cinq sections pas d&apos;avantago.     Ce sent celles situees:1.   Entre GEMENISCH et la bifurcation do VISE sur la nouvelle -ligne d&apos;AIX a. TONGRES:2.   A la station d&apos;ANGLEUR aux environs Sud de LISuE: 3.   Entre EARLOIS et CINEY sur la ligne ARLON-NAMUR: 4.   Entre HOUYET et DINANT, sur les iignes de LIBRATONT et BERTRIa k NAlffUR. nf5*   Entre CARIGNAN et SEDAN sur In ligne de LONGUYON a MEZLERES.Les sections 1, 2 ot 5 sont de beaucoupies plus importanteg et l&apos;on croit qurune faible partie du trafic general passe par les deux autres.Si un bombardement persistant sur les points aussi eloignes peut etre effectue, de la man:&apos;.ere que nous ay ens recormand&amp;c, les transports de tout mater:el et 1:envoi do t:ut renfort d:Allemagne seraient interrompus pour un certain temps.v A Dane la zone choisie pour uno attaque, 1c trafio ttrndtfa,a etre plus intense dopuis Bitot avant lo crepuocule jusque sitot apes l!aurnre;   par consequent los attaques de nuit soront pr6f erablJ aux attaques de jour.     II cst dene a deairer de prolongor la -oeriod(f d&apos;interruption et co but ne pout fitrc atteint qu&apos;en renouvelant les attaquec sur chaque secteur a intervalles regulicrs, on cstime que celles-ci doivent se renouvcler toutcs le? deux heures.     Si la premiere attaque a eu pour offot de rompro la ligno, on devra s&apos;attachor par des bombardements ropotes a on enpecher la reparation]
a (m    ^    .,Bvidemment 1&apos;attaque pontredoes points ne doit pas se produiro quand l1offensive a deja ete organisee, mats quand 1&apos;ennemi eat en train de reunlr ses reserves de materiel et d^mener see renforts pour reformer ses divisions,n3.&apos; IL N&apos;Y A PAS ^OPERATIONS ACTIVES JBN COURS ET IL SPY A PAS&quot; KETTESTFUNE ACTIVITY INUSOTC DF7&apos;P&apos;ENNSllI,tyuand de grands combats ne sont pas en cours et que^rien ne fait prevoir leur imminence dans un secteur particular, il y a beaucoup moins de raisons a tenter la rupture des communications. Les dfcgats materials causes par la rupture eont de peu d1importance et les retards causes aux trains n&apos;ont pas un grand resuitat militaire*Le but sera cVobtenir:1, La destruction du materiel qui ne peut etre remplace rapidement et dont&quot; le oesoin est tel que son absence genera tout transport que 1&apos;ennemi pourrait desirer effectuer. &apos;fII est admis que rien ne eause plus de dommages materiels que la destruction partielle ou totals des locomotives.    Cjuand on vise xxne- telle destruction, la distance entre le front et le point d&apos;attaque tr&apos;a plus aucune importance au point de vue &quot;transport&quot;.   Tout rasaemblement de locomotives, rotondes, ateliers, remises, voies de ravi tail lenient en oharbon ou en eau, constituent un object if convenable,II est impossible de dire quelle eat la situation actuelle de 1&apos;ennemi en ce qui concerns les locomotives,     11 y a cependant evidence qu&apos;il est tr&amp;s a court de machines et qu&apos;il a   les plus grandes difficultee a reparer celles qu*il possede.     On peut done considerer come certain que toute locomotive detruite devra etre remplacee par l^nnemi^8&apos;il est vrai que la destruction d&apos;uneAloeomotive est rarement complete, il est hors de doute que des degats materiels considerables seront causes par la chute d&apos;une bombe sur une remise, un depot ou un atelier.Comme exemple de qq que 1&apos;ennemi a obtenu dans oe sens on peut citer le oas du raid aerien entrepris centre le depot francais de locomotives de ROKE SCAMPS:     une seule bombe a cause des avaries tres serieuses a tyUATRS locomotives franyaises.I 2*, La.destruction des installations,   Comme objectifs secondaires \ s&apos;il rrest pas possibTe&quot;de bombarder un rassemblement de locomotives, on eherchera k detruire les installations les plus difficiles a remplacer;   ateliers de construction ou de reparation, usines elec-triques fournissant leur energie aux Chemins de fer, installations, d^elevation dveau et postes d^iguillage importants,Hi
0 0DISCLOSURE   TO   (II? - GaT0 5529.REMARKS BY THE AIR STAFF ON TY/O PAPERS SUBMITTED BY THE INTERALLIED TRAN qPORTaT I ON COUNCIL ON THE SUBJECT OF aERIALBOMBARDMENTS OF ENEMY F^ILY/iiY STATIONS^ &quot;The proposals laid down in the two attached papers are in substance identical; it is thought, therefore, that a discussion of the points raised in the first paper will suffice as an answer to both.whilst it is possible to express agreement- with some of the opinions statod, it is considered that from the   Air Force point of view they require considerable modification,, in particular as regards the relative importance of different railway targets. Further it is thought that insufficient attention has been paid to &quot;the enemy&apos;s anti-aircraft organisation.   Hostile scouts, and A.A. and Machine guns render flying at low altitudes costly, and exact bomb dropping very difficult.   The increasing speed of present day bombing machines is also apt to hamper accuracy..   J?or the above reasons it is considered preferable, as a general policy, to select for attack definite points in an objective of considerable extent rather than small and narrow targets where the slightest error entails complete failure to inflict any appreciable damage. These considerations are developed more fully below,,To deal seriatim with the points raised,. -Para, 1,   INTRODUCTORY.Para Zn     TffO CaSLS FOR CONSIDERATION..These do not call for remarks.Para, 3,    SEVERANCE 0? OOidMUIIIOATIOlI ,&quot;.ITE a PARTICULAR SECTOR.Para 4,Copy of letter from Air Ministry, to Secretary, War Cabinet.Air Ministry, Strand,London, W.CL2.B.2467.  (cab) 23rd August, 1918,Sir,The British Military Representative, Supreme War Council, Versailles, has forwarded a copy of the recommendations of tho British and French Representatives on tho Inter-Allied Transporta-tion Council, on the subject of the selection of points of attack for aerial bombardment.These two papers have been the subject of careful consideration ^ by tho Air Staff, and of discussion with General Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force in France, and I am commanded by the Air Council to forward you the notes prepared by tho Chief of the Air Staff on tho recommendations contained therein.I amoir,Your obedient Servanthe Secretary, (Signed). H. Mo. AN ALLY.T7ar Cabinet,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.Wil.
Para.4,   MINIMUM DISTANCE FROM jRONT TO THE POINTS ATTACKED. .These hinge on a supposition with which the Air Staff do not concur.   Complete severance of enemy rail communication with a particular sector at a distance of 20 kilos   behind tip line is not practicable;   much less is it possible to maintain this severance.   The utmost that can be Roped for is the temporary dislocation of communications, and the extent of this dislocation must depend on the number of lines supplying the sector in question.   In any case the-complete dislocation of al lines of communication with a particular sector is considered! be a task beyond our present aircraft resources&apos;..Para. 5*    GENERAL CONSIDERATION OF.....OBJECTIVES TO BE SELECTED,,It is agreed that &quot;complete local interruption of traffic&quot; cannot bo effected by attacking &quot;engine depots, works)! watering arrangements, and other facilities in connection with the maintenance of the rolling stock and works of a railway&quot;. It has, however, already been pointed out that such complete interruption is not regarded as practicable *The Inter-Allied Transportation Council suggest that the best point for attack is &quot;between Stations&quot;.   There are tw main objections to this suggestions-(l)      A single, or even a double, railway track offersa very poor target to a machine at any altitude above a hundred fetfto   It is inadvisable for bombers to descend to a low height by day for the reasons alread; stated, and by night there is the additional $anger of collision with unsuspected obstacles.   Further, if the actual track be missed even by a few yards no d&amp;wdge whatsoever is caused.(2)      Experience in previous^ and in the present campaigns, shews that even a complete break in the line can be speedily repaired by special breakdown gangs, whilst the uncertainty of atmospheric conditions alom is likely to render it extremely difficult to conduct further raids with sufficient frequency to preclude . this work of repair,.It is, therefore, the opinion of the Ait Staff that the relative importance of actual railway targets is as folloi(a)   Important Junctions or Marshalling Yards, (b j   Ordinary Stations, (c)   Between Stations,-The objections to an attack on the line between stations have already been stated^   In this connection, it may be remarked that the best prospect of effecting a break in the line between stations appears to be by attack on a moving trai a form of attack which has been carried out with success.Important railway junctions on the other hand afford an excellent target of considerable extent, where a bomb may cause great havoc, despite a large margin of error,   Junctio are the nerve centres of railway traffic.   They contain station buildings and platforms, the demolition of which may)
well block the actual line; signal boxes, important telegraph and telephone systems;   ouantities of rolling, stock, engine sheds, repair shops, turntables, &quot;points&quot;, which are much harder of replacement than the ordinary lengths of rail which form the track between stations;   dumps of stores (often ln-cluding explosives) either awaiting transport or recently delivered; motor lorries etc. standing by to convey the latter to their destination; spare timber, slsepers, and other .   railway material; and last, but not -east, the bulk of trained railway personnel.Further enumeration is unnecessary, with such a variety of important targets concentrated within a small area a large percentage of bombs must take   effect.It may of course be objected that the enemy masses his anti-aircraft defences in the vicinity of such vulnerable objectives.   This is true, but Is discounted by the fact that the large extent of the target presented allows of effective bomb dropping from considerable altitudes.As regards ordinary stations, these possess in a lesser degree the advantages detailed above in the case of the larger junctions.a, 6.   PARTICULAR OBJECTIVES.It is agreed that &quot;the partial destruction of bridges will cause more prolonged interruption of trafflo than the breaking of tracks at any other points.&quot;  But it must be noted that the objections already given to the bombing of a railway track between stations apply to a still greater degree to this class of target.Experience has shewn that a bridge offers so small a target that even from a low altitude it is exceedingly difficult to hit, even direct hits will not as a rule cause any very prolonged interruption of trafflo.     To destroy a bridge an attack in considerable strength and carried out from a low height is necessary.   Such an operation must Inevitably be costly as all important bridges are very strongly defended against, aircraft attack,   Systematic raids on bridges would under existing conditions, entail a policy too expensive to be rnai tainedoAs regards cuttings, - These again constitute targets of very narrow dimensions, and only a direct hit Is likely to produce material damage.   The chance of bringing down the sides of the cuttings is not considered to be a very favourable one.u 7.   FREQUENCY OF ATTACK.It is agreed that the first desideratum in any en-deavour to cut or dislocate railway communications should be a frequent renewal of attack to prevent repairs.   This is a principle the value of which Is clearly recognised by the Air Staff and la frequently carried into effect, e.g*, in the recent operations against Zeebrugge,   It must, however, be borne In nw-nd that to repeat attacks in a number of different localities with any frequency requires a large expenditure of force, which must be diverted from other urgent tasks.. 8.   ALTERNATIVE METHOD OF ATTACK.The great importance of attacks on large Shunting Yards and of the necessity for as frequent a repetition as possible is fully appreciated.Para. 9.
2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., August 28th 1918.Para, 9.   OBJECTS OF ATTACK oWii NO OFFENSIVE IS IN PROGRESS OR XMMlNEN&apos;ftPara. 10,   INTERRUPTION OF OOMUNIC/vTION WITH GERMANY,The same objections apply to the suggested severance of communication with Germany as to the scheme&quot;for isolating communication with a particular sector, set out in para.3 abov in addition, the distance of the objectives referred to in paras.,9 and 10 of the memorandum under review render the suggested operations impracticable with the strength at our disposal.Para.il,   DESTRUCTION OF MATERIAL.As regards the destruction of material which cannot be readily replaced, the Air Staff are in complete agreement with the views expressed   in this paragraph and great importa is attached to attacks on engine shods, workshops etc.   These are included among our present objectives for railway attack,it-   (Signed), F.H. SYKES.Major General.Chief of the Air Staff,Air Ministry,August 23rd, 1916*,

</content>
</cab>
