<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/62/0 images: 184-184</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS pOCUI&amp;lNTIS THE PROjKSRITY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOv^MiiiNT), A /    jitAR cabinet .SECAET &quot;1      /G..T. 5544        I tAN-PO^SR,THE BQYAL AIR FORCE K4SLRVE DEPOT AT ELANDFORD.Memorandum &quot;by Air Ministry.A serious situation has arisen in connection with the extension of the Jr.A.3?. Reserve Depot at Blandford.   The whole of the recruits for the R.A.F. are received at this station where they undergo preliminary training.     The whole of the Records of the Force are also kept there.The Camp was taken over from the Royal Naval Division when the Royal Air Force moved from Aldershot.   At the present time some 3,500 men are under canvas.   It is vitally important to pro-vide accommodation for these men as well aB for 2,000 additional men necessary to meet the expansion of the Air Force, &quot;before the winter, otherwise it will he necessary either to reduce the Air Force programme or to put the recruits under canvas for the winter.Treasury approval has been obtained for the expenditure on the proposed extension of this Depot and arrangements were made some weeks ago with a firm of Contractors then building an aerodrome at Winchester and in a position to transfer a large botfy of men to Blandford to carry out the work.The Building Labour Commitee could not see their way to authorise the payment at Blandford of the same rates as had been paid to the men at Winchester.   It is recognised that the payment of these ratee at Blandford would be liable to lead to demands for an increase of rates at other Government works which are being carried out by the Admiralty, Office of Works and kunitione in the area.   At the same time the fact has to be faced that the Contractors&apos; labour will not carry out the work at the rate proposed by the Building Labour Committee, viz: that in force at Poole.It was estimated that 2,000 men were required to complete the work before the winter if they had commenced when the scheme was originally approved 7 weeks ago.   It has been found impossible to secure more than 700 men, and they have now struck for the Winchester rate of wage.   The War Office have been askec1 whether they could supply any military labour and none is^a^ailaTfcle.  The Ministry of National Service have supplied as many/as they can mostly War Vorks volunteers, but the number is quite inadequate  . and they have now btruck.It appears, therefore, that the only solution is either to agree to the same rate being paid at Blandford as is paid at Winchester or to allocate 2,000 prisoners of war to do the work.A decision is urgently required, as failure to increase the accommodation at Blandford must necessarily lead to a   re-vision of the whole of the Air Force programme in all respects.(aigaed)   JOHN BAIRD, for Secretary of State.aIR MINISTRY,29th August, 1918,

</content>
</cab>
