<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/62/0 images: 209-212</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is the property of Eis Bril^&amp;nnijoJia^ee^^7 IB    G k 3 I Li 2 ?.ii f I&amp;549.IIIEHVEI.&apos; B3I&apos;. SH. L0R3 D^RBY       1:1. OESMOSAU. Copy of letter from lord Derby to Mr. Balfour.British Dmbassy, Paris,August 27th, 1918,oret and Confidential.:.iy a earArthur,I asked to see Clemenceau this morning as I rather wanted to find out how things stood with regard to various matters.   I will put down roughly for you the gist of our conversation.I spoke to him about the Report on our Man-PowerI told him th-^t quite apart from its not being, in my opinion, an accurate statement of the situation there were certain things in it which were calculE-ted to give trouble if it was discussed officially and (as I had received through General Spiers from the :7ar Office a re cru.est that I should do so) I asked him whether he would allow thefigures to be gone into unofficially by one of the Versailles officers and an unbiassed officer of his own, and that they should thoroughly discuss the question, see whether it would not be possible for them to eliminate certain controversial joints and agree to differ, as I am afraid they must do, on aertain otherlatter would have to be discussed officially betweenThePrime minister.   I told Clemeneeaupoints.Clemenceau and Hilner or the that I thought this would at all events eliminate some of the dangers of controversy.   He quite agreed, jumped at the oroposalan oincer, j absolutely ist and not ;who I hope will be unofficial.   It isa certain understood to:.t the request of the 7ar Officeand is going to choose Colonel Georges. It ii be at my -personal requand therefore it is perfectly possible for me to be repudiated if that become necessary, but I think good may come of it.&quot;.7e then turned to other subjects.   I reminded, him of theconversation
t conversa-tion we had had last Sim day we ok in which both he and Foch I expressed their fears that Pershing had got such influence with the Ikpresi&amp;ent that the latter would support him against Foch.   I told &quot;him, without giving my authority, that I thought this was entirelywrong and I felt perfectly certain that the President had accepted jFoch as being in supreme command and they might rely on him support-ing Foch oven against Pershing. Ole.menco.au told me&apos;it was most&apos; &quot;im-l portant that he should know that because it was a. point on which hehad groat doubts in his own mind.   Things wore not going wellbetween Foch and 1&apos;orshing..   LLftny of Foch&quot;s suggestions are ignored by I the latter and he had not dared give him an order for the effect it .might have on the  resident,   Curiously enough however Clomencoau had Itold him yesterday the time had come when ho&quot;must give orders and if I they were not obeyed ho (Clomencoau) would have to telegraph to the 1 President on tho subject. . Ee said therefore tho information I gave 1 him was of the greatest value :.s it strengthened his hand.He then told me that ho wished to s )eak to me about the Ital-lians. . Eo is absolutely disgusted with thorn and with thoir inactivity, I (or worse).    In the first &quot;llaco he says that they have implored the 9 Italians to attack in Italy.  -Ko thinks Sonnino would be quite ready 1 that-there should be an attack but Diaz absolutely declines to do so I and that on tho .Albanian Front -they have retired very precipitately land by so doing have exposed the flank of the French?   Ee told me that j he had sent orders for tho French, if tho Italians evacuated Borat,to at once seize it themselves but tho Italians retreated so fast that 1 the French wore not able to got up in tine.. Eg has therefore tele-graphed, to his Ambassador at&apos;Rome to toll him that for tho moment ho (Clemenceau) looks upon the Italians- armies as a non-existent force whether in Albania, or in Italy and does not propose to consult with them&apos; any. further. - For that, reason there fore and for fear that it would create trouble he does not wish to have a Supreme &apos;&apos;7ar Council at the present, moment. Yet at the same time he thinks that one is essential in order to decide whether the offensive is to be taken at .3alonika or not. In order to get out of the difficulty, of both wanting and not want ing a meeting of the Jupromc 7ar Council he wondered whether it would be posvsible for-England and Franca together to agree as to what should take place in Salonika and to come before, a Supreme. War Council later with the decision as to what was to bo done, a fait accompli as far as England and France wore; concerned.He suggests that as. General Guillaumat is the man............
Ion whom he relies for advice with regard to Salonika matters he I should send him      once^ to London to consult with the 7ar Cabinet, j You met him and &quot;1 think you formed a higbi opinion of him.   Certainly Ihe is a man who lias a very clear mind and puts hie propositions [vary concisely.   I think therefore this proposal might be of extreme lvalue but if it is to be done it must be done at once because if an loffansive be taken there are many requirements of the French Army in ([Salonika, shells, wagons, etc. which Clemenceau would send out at :jpnce.   If no offensive is to be taken - of course as you know he is I strongly of opinion that one should take place - he will send out I some of these things.I ought to mention here that he had had many large demands from Italy for Shells, wagons, tanks, etc., which he would have been perfectly ready to send if the Italians had consented to take the offensive but as they had refused he equally had refused to send anything to them.He then spoke to me on the subject of where the next Supreme &apos;Var Council is to be held.   He told me Lloyl George wanted it to be in London and he wanted me to explain the reasons why he thought it must be at Versailles,   In the first place he wanted you and the Prime Minister to clearly understand that it was not a question of dignity on his part or a question of inconvenience, which made him prefer Versailles*   It was that it was essential that at any meeting to consider these military matters i?och should be present and this was impossible at the present moment if the meeting were-held in London.   Moreover he could not leave Pooh   because, although, as he assured me, he interfered in no way with military mutters, ?och did rely upon him to an inordinate extent, especially in his dealings with the Americans and that just as it was impossible for Foch to leave his Army so it was impossible for him to leave rpoch.   I think therefore you may take it that if there was a Supreme War Council held in London Clemenceau himself would not go.   It seems to me therefore that the only way out of the difficulty with regard to a Salonika decision is that Guillaumat should go over to London at once,    If an agreement is arrived at with him well and aood.   If not than I suppose there would have to be a Supreme &quot;A.r Council and as one would be somewhat useless without ?och or Clemcnceau it would be necessary to hold it at Versailles.     Ao I have said Clemenceau is anxious to have an offensive at Salonika and is very confident of success there.   He will be disappointed if England does not agree to it but at the same time I do -ot think that if we do not agree it will be looked upon as a great grievance or as a matter for friction.As we were parting he just referred to the meeting which is bein^ held in London to-day and he told me he was in entire accord with our people&quot;that if England put the whole of her hand on the table with regard to tonnage for bringing Americans over from the United States of Amerioa, America should equally put her^hartd on the table and disclose all her tonnage and the instructions tcvhis people
Iin London were to support this view.Clemenceau was most friendly throughout.   In high good humour las he had just received the news that the French had taken Roye*He was rather disturbed at the &quot;Tank&quot; losses - he told me they I started with 20 tank Battalions and now have only got 7.Will you wire me about Guillaumat, also if you can what the I decision is about the Supreme War Council, as I should not like to I miss you and want to make my plans accordingly.     I am thinking of i going away for a few days next week if you do not come here.Yours ever,(Signed)   Derby.

</content>
</cab>
