<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/62/0 images: 217-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r ^ uab/%\   this doc^entc^tlie prooortv 0JL     152^ G Ti^^  f 18 Britannlc m-fc^a c.;/::^mnent&apos;: &apos; Copy No.     *m^HALl G^S^SERIAL NO. 7.NOTES ON THE AMERICAN ARMY.General. There are now 33 American divisions in Frunoe, 31 of whioh are under General Pershing, and 2 of which are attached to B.E,F. for training.Of the divisions under General Pershing, 20 are trained, (i.e. capable of being put into the line). 7 are Combat divisions which have recently arrived; or are arriving, and 4 are Depot divisions. One regiment of the 83rd (Depot) division has been sent to Italy, and one regiment of the 85th (Depot) division is en route for North RussiaIn addition there are 18 battalions of coloured troops with the Frenchj and various adninlstrative and lines of communication troops, The following is a summary of the&apos; number of the American forces in, or en route to, Europe at 23rd August :-I In France.General Pershing1s Army - 31 divisions,        )Administrative Units, &amp;c, )..... 1,321,846&apos; With British - 2 divisions; Casual, Medical,) Engineer and Aviation Units, )II For General Pershingfs Army,england - awaiting shipment........... 13,175En route) - England..............Y.109 ,512to       ) - France....................156,032 258,719III With French.! &apos; battalions coloured troops.....................       25,904IV In Italy. ;1 Infantry regiment and variousHospital units..,.............................        5,493V In U.K.Training and duty.................................      26,625VI For North Russia.1 Infantry Regiment............................... _4,726T 0 T A L....&apos;.......... 1,643 ,515At 21st August the Rifle Strength of the 20 trained divisions with General Pershing, and of the 2 divisions with the British was 254,461.
2.2.     Train trip,.W      Divisions with British.  - The 2 divisions are now in the line.(b)      Divisions with American Expeditionary Force.   The training of the rWently&apos;&quot; arrived &quot;divisions &quot;is being completed as qu.ictr.ly as possible in order to have them ready for trie line at the . earliest moment.3.     Operations^(a) Beyond the ordinary incidents of trench warfare, American troops were not engaged in any operations during the past week, though it is probable that by now one of the divisions of the III American Corps has been engaged in battle with the loth trench Army as it had received orders to proceed to this Army,   The other 2 divisions of the III American Corps are still in line with the 6th French Army about FISMES.   The other 17 trained divisions with General ]?ershing are all situated East and South of ST. MIHIEL, and include 3 of the divisions which were with the British.   7 of these 17 divisions are in the line, the remainder being in reserve.(b) The 2 American divisions remaining with the British are now in the line on the Second Army front.4.       CasualtiesAccurate iei.v;cns of casualties have not been received, but up to 14th August the total losses in the American Expeditionary Fcroe (including died of disease, but not including slightly wounded) were reported to be as follows :-Killed ...............    10,630Wounded ,. ..... ............   32, 484Missing and prisoners,     2,928Total  .......    46,042.M.0.1.30*8.18.

</content>
</cab>
