<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/62/0 images: 300-306</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Ma,jesty&apos;s Government. I32SECEET.Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1918.2.10NAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION-No. 66.Week ended 24th August, 1918.NAVAL OPERATIONS.Minelaying operations have been carried out in the North Sea and off the Belgian North Sea. coast.On 20th August, at 2 p.m., the Belgian Relief Ship &quot; Gasconia &quot; was torpedoed or mined when 2\ miles west of Rovaer (Norway).On 23rd August, at 1 a.m., four or five enemy Motor Boats attempted a reconnaissance Flanders of Dunkirk Roads, but were driven off by British and French patrols, assisted by land Area, defences.   The French Destroyer &quot; Obusier&quot; claims to have sunk one Motor Boat. No damage or casualties were sustained by the Allied forces.The weather generally has not been favourable for flying, but in addition to reconnais-sances and patrols which have been carried out in various areas by R.A.F. machines work-ing with the Navy, the following raids have been made by machines from Dunkirk : 	Approximate				weight of	Date.	Objective&apos;.	bombs	Result observed or Remarks.		dropped.	August-		Tons.	18th	Bruges Docks............	1	19th	Bruges Docks... &apos;    ......... Batteries at Westende      ......	1 i 2	21st	Bruges Docks......     ......	f	21st-22nd	Bruges Docks, Zeebrugge, Oostacker Aerodrome and Ghistelles Aero-drome		Large fire started.22nd	Bruges Dock............		Several hits on docks and direct hit on			alongside submarine shelter.22nd-23rd	Bruges Docks, Zeebrugge, Maria-	; &apos; 5	Large explosion at Bruges.	kerke Aerodrome and Maria Alter			Aerodrome		23rd	Bruges Docks............ Ostend Docks; &amp;c..........	1* i f	Two fires caused.24th	Bruges and Ostend Docks......	13		Total weight	20 Tods.	In the course of aerial fighting during these raids three enemy machines were destroyed and three driven down out of control.  One of our machines is missing.On the night of 19th August two of our aircraft left Mudros for a bombing raid on Mediter-Constantinople, but owing to thick weather, only one machine reached the objective, where ranean. bombs were dropped on and near the Admiralty.  The other machine dropped bombs on Eregli and Rodosto, and both machines returned safely.On 20th August five machines from Taranto carried out an attack on Cattaro, and dropped a ton of bombs on submarine quarters and amongst shipping. All the machines returned safely.During the night of the 21st-22nd August our machines dropped three-quarters of a ton of bombs on Galata, causing great damage to buildings and hangars.(C 1358)  Wt,     -  50   8/18   H&amp;S A
On the same night half a ton of bombs was dropped on Nagara aerodrome and forts by British and Greek machines, and Chanak was also attacked,, considerable damage being done at both places. Two of the machines reached Constantinople where they dropped 500lbs. of bombs on military objectives. All machines returned safely except one which fell into the sea, the pilot being saved, but the observer drowned.Casualties.        On 22nd August in Runswick Bay, a Motor Launch was blown to pieces by a torpedo &apos;   which it was endeavouring to salve, three officers and seven men being killed.ATTACK UPON ENEMY SUBMARINES.1Submarines The number of large enemy submarines, of a type which operates further afield than operating, the North Sea, which were located during the week was again 12, included in which number were four of the &quot; cruiser &quot; type, one working in the vicinity of the Azores and the other three on the eastern seaboard of North America. There was a marked absence of activity in the English Channel and the Bay of Biscay, but of! the East Coast of England consider-able activity was experienced, especially between Flamborough and Holy Island, where an average of three boats were working throughout the week.Actions The following Table shows the number of actions between Allied craft and enemywith enemy submarines which are reported to have taken place in all waters during recent weeks submarines. an(j ^ nature 0f the craft which have been engaged ; and also the number of submarines which have been destroyed or lost to the enemy as the result of such actions : 	Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Aug	. 3rd.	Aug.	10th.	Aug.	17th.	Aug.	24th.Nature of Craft, &amp;c.									Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Eesults.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results,T.B.D. and T.B..........	2		6		8		3	A.P. Vessels     .........	12	 	8	i 	9	1	9	 1Aircraft   .........	4		4		12	 	7	 Sloops and Patrol Craft......	4	 	6	 	3	 	4	 Merchant Vessel.........	3	; 	2	 	1	 	2	 Special Service Vessels......	2	1  *	 	 	i -	 	_	 Submarines      ......	3	 	4	 	1	 	 	 Mines     ...   ,.........	1	1	_	 	1	 	 	 Unknown.............	2	 	1	-	1	 	1	-Total	33	2	31	-	36	1	26	-&quot;Results&apos;1 indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.Number and ton-nage of all vessels sunk.MERCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage, of all Merchant Vessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action :-	British Vessels.				Allied and Neutral Vessels.				Total.	Week Ended	1,600 tons gross		Under 1,600 tons		1,600 tons gross		Under 1,600 tons		All sizes.		and over.		8	ross.	and over.		gross.				No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1918.										July 13th	6	27,049	1	339	9	27,319	13	4,515	29	59,222July 20th	10	78,713	2	215	3	11,902	8	8,058	23	98,888July 27th	7	26,668	2	2,150	3	11,755	co	4,866	20	45,439August 3rd	3	15,655	2	1,939	5	20,925	7	3,324	17	41,843August 10th	8	35,422	2	581	6	27,905	7	4,118	23	68,026August 17th	7*	35,657*	2	2,603	8*	37,129*	3	3,548	20*	78,937*August 24th	8	37,028	5	4,823	5	17,468	3	762	21	60,081* Adjusted.
The Table in Appendix I shows the numbers and tonnage of sailings and of losses Losses of by enemy action, and the percentage of losses to sailings of all merchant steamships, both .British and Foreign, of over 500 tons gross register, and the Table in Appendix II is a gteamX^n summary of those percentages for recent weeks. in Trades.While the total tonnage lost during the week under review was less than in the previous week, the losses in United Kingdom Overseas Trades were relatively heavy, and account for nearly 70 per cent, of the total. The percentage of losses to sailings of vessels engaged in such trades which arrived at or left United Kingdom ports during the week is 2.48 as against .78 in the previous week, in Cross-Channel trades is .07 as against .27, and in Coasting trades is -17 as against -40 last week, while the percentage, reckoning all the United Kingdom trades together, is this week - 90 as against - 40 in the previous week.The Table in Appendix III is a comparative statement of all merchant vessels, Foreign Areas as well as British, sunk, damaged and unsuccessfully attacked in the last two weeks by m which enemy craft and by mine, classified according to areas. vessels lost.The decline of activity in the English Channel recorded last week has continued, there having been no attacks whatever in that area during the week under review. On the other hand both in the North Sea and Irish Sea there was a slight increase of activity during the week.*The number of British and Foreign merchant vessels sailing in organised Convoy Vessels which completed their voyages during last week, and the losses sustained whilst in such convoyed. Convoys, compared with corresponding figures for previous periods, are as follows : 	Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		3rd August, 1918.		10th August, 1918.		17th August, 1918.		24th August, 1918.	Convoy.									No. of		No. of		No. of		No. of		ships	No.	ships	No.	ships	No.	ships	No.	convoyed.	lost,	convoyed.	lost.	convoyed.	lost.	convoyed.	lost.Atlantic trades 								Homeward       ......	203	.2	173	 	161	 	122	1Outward.........	130	1	111	 	140	- 	139	1Scandinavia-Methil	110	 	no	 -	103	 	85	1French coal trade......	408	 	. 382	 	391	 	431	 Local East Coast Convoys	383	 	352	 	384	 	335	2(N. of Humber)	-							Mediterranean local	261	4	286	2	269	3	268	2Total   .........	1,495	7	1,414	2	1,448	3	1,380	7During the week under review the losses-in the Mediterranean were one in the Alexandria-Bizerta Convoy and one in the Genoa-Gibraltar Convoy,On the 20th of August the Trawler &quot; Triumph &quot; was captured by an enemy submarine Capture of 100 miles east of Halifax, Nova Scotia, and after a gun had been put on board she was used trawler by to raid the fishing fleet on the Newfoundland Banks. t  enemy.ENEMY MINES.        &apos;. As was anticipated in last week&apos;s Appreciation mines have been located in expected Minelaving positions off the East Coast of Scotland, and during the week under review minelaving activity has taken place also in inshore Waters off Berwick-on-Tweed.   Mines were &quot;also laid by the enemy during the week in the Malta area.(C 1358)
Gfaeualties.       The following Table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed in British mine-sweeping areas and of British vessels sunk by mine in recent Weeks :-Week Ended.	Number of Enemy Moored Mines Destroyed.		Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.	Home Waters.	Abroad.		July 27th...... Aug. 3rd       ...... ,, 10th        ...... 17th       ...... ,, 24th      ......	56 49 52 12 30	3 11	Nil 1 Nil Nil Nil	Nil Nil Nil Nil NilThe mines which were swept up during the week outside Home Waters were found in the Malta approach channels.Although no British vessel was sunk by mine during the period under review, the Paddle-Sweeper &quot; Shirley &quot; was damaged by mine whilst effecting a final clearance of a known area off the Scottish Coast, and a report has come to hand that the S.S. &quot; Umoolosi &quot; has been damaged, off Ceylon, by a mine which must have broken adrift from the old field laid by the Raider &quot; Wolf.&quot;MOVEMENTS OF ENEMY SHIPS.Merchant-        During the week under review seven enemy merchant ships arrived at and eight men-        sailed from Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat.  No enemy ships have entered or left Eotterdam, but again one enemy steamship has arrived at Harlingen from the Rhine.FOREIGN NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. Russia.Very little reliable news has been received during the week, and the general situation -appears to remain unaltered.Both in the Archangel district and in the Far East we are awaiting reinforcements before commencing further operations.One battleship has been added to the Japanese Force on the Russian Pacific Coast. The Vice Admiral Commander-in-Chief of the Third Fleet is in supreme command, and is personally directing operations off the mouth of the Amur River.A British naval detachment, with guns, under Commodore D. T. Norris, R.N., is now on the Caspian, and it is hoped to form a small naval force by acquiring the two Russian gun-boats, and by mounting guns in merchant vessels.Information has been received that Russian mines have recently been laid in the Baltic, evidently with a view to sinking German ships. Negotiations were begun at Mariehamn on August 21st, between German, Swedish, and Finnish delegates, concerning the de-molition of the fortifications on the Aland Islands.Naval Staff.29$ August, 1918.
APPENDIX 1$tatement of numbers amd tonnage of sailings and losses of british and foreign merchant steamships of over 500 tons grossfor the Week ended 24th August, 1918.United Kingdom Trade.Sailings.Losses.Percentage of Losses to Sailings.In.Out.No.Tons.No.Tons.Total.In.No.Tons.No.Tons.Out.Total.No.Tons.No.Tons.In.Out.Total.No.Tons.No.    Tons. ! No.Tons.OverseasCross-Channel ...CoastingTotal of all United Kingdom Trades205 217*420 477*767,441 794,926*665,354 819,227*246247*441 468*823,467 ;   451 997,293*!   464*694,919     861i738,581*   945*1,094 1,071*i 2,406 i 2,48o*1.590,908 1,792,219*11,360,273 1,557,808s1,926,652 1,830,878*14,877,833 5,180,905*!2 1*13,062 &apos;6,978&apos;1,567:71* 126,365 7,094*996 2,603*Losses on other TradesTotal Losses for Week ..* Previous week&apos;s figures adjusted.92*1r136*4 12*&apos; 17 18*39,427 14,072*996 4,170*!3,327 2,697*43;750 20,939*1.98.46*.1.70.88*2.84 . .40*1.21*    .19*.23 .43*3.20.7i*;2.014.122.48 .78* .0735*j   -32*    .27* .17 .40*.27 .09*.54 .24*.90 .40*13,293 54,757&apos;57,043 75,696!
APPENDIX II.Statement showing, as regards British and Foreign Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross sailing to and from United Kingdom Ports, the percentage of tonnage sunk by enemy action to tonnage sailing during recent weeks.United Kingdom Trade.		Weekly Average in July,	Week ended 3rd August.	Week ended 10th Aug.	Week ended 17th Aug.	Week ended 24th Aug.							&quot;In  ...	.50	.27	.27	.83	1.70Overseas.........   &quot;	Out...	2.46	.79	2.40	.71	3.20	; Total	1.45    *	.52	1.49	.78	2.48	&quot;In  ...	.21	1.43	.96	.19	Cross-Channel    ......   &quot;*	Out...	.16	 	 	.35	.14	w Total	.18	,.74	.48	.27	.07Coasting  ...*    ......	Total	.03	.07	.29	.15	.17Total of all United Kingdom Trades...		.58	.42	.75	.40	.90
Statement of the number of British, and Foreign Merchant Vessels sunk, damaged, or molested during weeks ended ___17th and 24th August, 1918, according to Areas.       _		Sunk.						Damaged, but not Sunk.						Unsuccessfully attacked.						Attacks.	Area.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1.600 tons.		Total.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		Total.			Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended			17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.	17th Aug.	24th Aug.Arctic and White Sea	/British... \ Foreign																				Atlantic (Northern) ...	/British... \ Foreign	 	1 1	-	 	 	1														1 1Atlantic (Southern) ...	/British... \ Foreign	1 3	1 1	 	2	1 3	. 1 3	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	1	 	 	 	1	1 3	2 o oBay of Biscay         ......	/British... \ Foreign													1				1	 	1	 Gibraltar Azores	/British... \ Foreign	.  	 	 	 																South of Mogador	/British... \ Foreign																				North Sea......      ...	/British... \ Foreign	1	1	1 1	4 1	2 1	4 2	 	 	 	 	 		1 1	 	1	1	1 2	1	3 3	5 2English Channel	/British... \ Foreign	1	 	-	.  	1	 	 	 	-  	 	 	 	 	 	1	 	1	 	2	 Irish Sea and Bristol Channel	/British... \ Foreign		3 1	1 1	1	1 1	4 1	 	1	. 	 	 	1	1 1	 	2	2	3 1	2	4 2	- 7 1Mediterranean	/British... \ Foreign	2 2	2 1	&apos;: 	 	2 2	2 1	 	1	 	 	 -	1*	1 1	 	1	1	1 2	1	3 4:	3 2American Coast	/British... \ Foreign	2 3	1	l	 	2 4	1	 	1	 	 	 	1	1 1	1 1	 	 	1 1	1 1	3 5	2 2Totals........	/British... \ Foreign	7 8	8 5	2 3	5 3	9 11 I	13 8	 	*3 1	 	 	 	*3 1	4 5	2 1	3 2	3 1	7 7	5 2	16 18	*21 11* 1 Damaged in Indian Ocean.

</content>
</cab>
