<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/40/36 images: 430-451</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC lfiAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET. Copy, NoW.P. (43) 386 I(Also COS. (48) 248) J2nd September, 1943war cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 209)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 26th August, to0700 2nd September,1943[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.1. Allied naval patrols have been maintained nightly off the south-westcoast of Italy and land targets have been bombarded.Small parties of troops have been landed on the toe of Italy and prisoners captured for interrogation. , .One U-boat has been sunk, two probably sunk, one possibly sunk, and onepossibly damaged.Shipping losses have been small.North Atlantic.2. An escort group on A/S patrol off the north-west coast of Spain was attacked at midday on the 27th by 13 Dornier aircraft. H.M.S. Egret (sloop) was sunk with heavy loss of life, and H.M.C.S. Athabaskan (destroyer) was damaged,but reached port with the survivors from Egret, four officers and 30 ratings.There were two killed and 15 wounded in A lhabaskan.Mediterranean.3. Naval activity has continued off the south-west coast and the toe of Italy.On the night of the 23rd and on subsequent nights throughout the week Allieddestroyers and coastal craft patrolled off the Calabrian coast without opposition,except on the 29th when coastal batteries near Melito and Bovalino Marinaopened ineffective fire. On the night of the 24th H.M. cruisers Aurora andPenelope and destroyers swept the Tyrrhenian Sea, and on the 27th U.S. M.T.Bs.patrolled the Gulf of Gaeta, north of Naples.On the 25th H.M.S. Orion (cruiser) bombarded the Calabrian coast, and onthe 28th H.M.S. Uganda (cruiser) and a destroyer shelled Pellaro (south ofReggio). ELM. battleships Nelson and Rodney on the 31st bombarded coastalbatteries north of Reggio, and with cruisers and destroyers engaged batteries inthe Cape Pellaro area which offered ineffective opposition.4. During an air raid on Augusta on the 25th H.M.S. Prinses Astrid(infantry landing ship) and a tanker were slightly damaged.On the night of the 26th a Commando party was landed at Bova Marina,at the extreme south of the toe of Italy, and prisoners were captured who reported the locality undefended. Five more parties were landed the following night andmore prisoners taken.5. ELM.S/M Unseen sank a small ship in the Adriatic on the 27th and aschooner the next day.6. Three landing craft were gutted and one seriously damaged by fire andexplosion at Tripoli (L) on the 28th. H.M.S. Ulster Queen (fighter direction ship)was damaged by aircraft on the 29th east of Gibraltar, but reached port.Black Sea.7.   A Russian submarine has sunk the Bulgarian s.s. Varna (2,141 tons).East Indies.8. Shortly after midnight on the night of the 28th H.M. S/M Tridentattacked the Japanese light cruiser Kashii which was entering Sabang(N. Sumatra), and possibly obtained one torpedo hit.Pacific.9. A U.S. task force attacked Marcus Island, between Wake Island and japan, on the 1st.  No details are known.Japanese warships escorting transports between Rabaul and Bougainvilleare constantly being sighted in the northern Solomon Islands.Anti-Submarine Operations.10. Fifteen attacks on U-boats have been reported during the week, threeby shore-based and three by carrier-borne aircraft, and nine by ships. One ofthese attacks was made in the Mediterranean.
Aircraft from the U.S.S. Card (auxiliary carrier) sank one U-boat andpossibly another in mid-Atlantic on the 27th.. H.M. ships Stork (sloop) and Stonecrop (corvette), after over 25 hours ofpersistent attack, probably sank a U-boat north-west of the Azores on the 30th.H.M.S. Grennille (destroyer) probably sank a U-boat off the N.W. coast of Spainon the 28th. Bales of sheet rubber were recovered, and it is probable that shewas Japanese. A U-boat was possibly damaged on the 25th by the U.S.S. Barker(destroyer) west of the Canary Islands.Enemy Intelligence.U-boats.11. The number of U-boats sunk during August made this the third bestmonth of the war in spite of the reduced number at sea. There are rather moreU-boats at sea now than a month ago, but far fewer than during the peak monthsof April and May. It is believed that operations off Brazil, in the Caribbean,and off West Africa, have failed owing to the enemy&apos;s shortage of supply U-boats,several of which were sunk during July; and that for the past fortnight manyU-boats have been forced to curtail their cruises.The Germans have constructed U-boat shelters and accommodation for theircrews in certain Channel ports, probably for use in the event of an invasion of Western Europe.The examination of prisoners taken from U-boats reveals that officerscaptured in recent months are on the average five or six years younger than thosecaptured a year ago; and that frequently the majority of the crew have had atthe most one year&apos;s service in U-boats and two years&apos; service in the navy.Italian.12. There has been no important movement of Italian warships during theweek.Enemy Attack on Shipping.13. Two U.S. ships in a westbound convoy off Bone were sunk by U-boatduring the week.   No other attacks have been reported.14. A provisional figure for shipping losses from enemy action during august is 115,000 tons.Protection of Seaborne Trade.15. During the week ending the 29th, 1,134 ships were convoyed. Of these,364 ships were in ocean convoys and 770 in British coastal convoys. Seventydestroyers (including 11 U.S. destroyers), 94 sloops, cutters, frigates and corvettes,and one anti-aircraft ship, were employed on escort duties.Four ocean convoys, consisting of 226 ships, arrived in Home Waters without loss.16. During the week ending the 28th, imports into the United kingdom by ships in convoy totalled 1,312,000 tons, compared with 282,000 tons duringthe previous seven days and an average of 994,800 tons during the past ten weeks.Of the week&apos;s imports 526,000 tons were mineral oil of various grades.British Minelaying.17. Mines were laid during the week by surface craft off, the Dutch and belgian coasts, and by aircraft off the German North Sea coast and the biscay ports. .Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.18. There have been no reports of minelaying. by enemy ships or aircraft during the week. .Two mines have been destroyed off the East Coast and two in Lyme Bay.The mine totals are : 4,450 ground and 3,090 moored.[26022] * b
Enemy Merchant Shipping.19. It is reported that in order to increase the tonnage of small craft attheir disposal in the Western Mediterranean, the Germans have requisitioned600 French and 135 Belgian barges, whilst 137 barges have recently left Ghent,and 1,700 French and Belgian personnel have arrived in Marseilles to man bargesalready there or en route. Barges would ensure the widest possible dispersal ofgoods in transit between the mainland, Corsica and Sardinia, and would provide an alternative means of transport along the coast of the Italian mainland.20. Of the merchant shipping now available in the Mediterranean,130,000 tons are believed ready for service in the Western, and 290,000 tons inthe Eastern, Mediterranean.   Damaged shipping is estimated at 680,000 tons.21. On the 1st July 7,800 tons of chrome ore were reported to be stored inthe Istanbul area owing to the shortage of German shipping, and small Turkishmotor boats are being chartered to move it. At the end of August the Germans.s. Alba Julia (5,701 tons) and this be (1,782 tons) were loading ore, and theThisbe is reported to have been sunk on the 30th at the entrance to the Black Seawhen bound for Burgas fully laden.22. The Italian tanker Celeno (3,741 tons) loaded the remaining cargo ofthe damaged Firuz and sailed from Istanbul on the 28th for the piraeus.Danish Intelligence.23. Prior to the recent events in Denmark, the Danish Navy consisted ofthe 5-9&quot; cruiser Niels Juel (1918), the coast defence ship Peder Shram (1905),six torpedo boats (1928-33), five guardships (1918-19), eleven submarines(1915-39), nine minesweepers, and five small minelayers, plus auxiliaries and ships building. The Niels Juel attempted to escape to Sweden, but was bombed&apos;by German aircraft and sunk by her own crew. One torpedo-boat, seven smallcutters, and three small minesweepers reached Sweden. German destroyers and coastal craft have been searching for fugitives still  lib S6 L.MILITARY SITUATION.The Russo-German Campaign.   (An outline map is included as an inset.)Leningrad and Lake llmen Sectors.24. No further activity has been reported south of Lake Ladoga or in thearea of Staraya Russa.Smolensk Sector.25. After a period of fairly static warfare the Russians have now resumedtheir advance and have made very considerable progress towards Smolensk.This advance has taken place mainly to the north of the railway Sukhinichi-Smolensk and has brought them as far as Yelnya, which is on this railway 48 miles east-south-east of Smolensk. From there the line runs roughly northwards to therailway Vyasma-Smolensk at a point 50 miles north-east of the latter town.Bryansk Sector.26. The week has brought no appreciable change in position. There is evidence that the Germans are fortifying the line of River Desna, but this maywell be no more than ordinary precautions, and there are no indications thatthey intend to withdraw further in this sector unless forced by the Russians todo so.Sievsk Sector.27. During the week the Russians launched an attack. On the 27th Sievskitself was taken and the Russians then extended the front of their attacksouthwards, capturing Glukhov, 40 miles to the south-west, on the 31st. this represents a westward advance of some 35 miles in this sector.
Sumy-Kharkov Sector.28. The Russians have now reached the River Psel along a 20-mile stretchimmediately south-west of Sumy and have consolidated their positions there.Further south they have continued to push westwards and south-westwardsand are now threatening the important railway Poltava-Kiev. The fighting inthis area has been particularly fierce. The Germans have been counter-attackingand in places have forced the Russians back, but have then not been able to holdon to the ground regained. In the confused and heavy fighting the Germans have suffered severely, and some of their divisions are considerably below strength.In the immediate neighbourhood of Kharkov the only further progress madeby the Russians has been the capture of Lubotin, a town 17 miles west of the city.Here, too, the Germans have been counter-attacking, but with little or no success.Middle Donetz Sector.29. There has been hard fighting of a local nature in the neighbourhoodof Isyum.Mius Sector.30. The Russian penetration of the German positions west of Kuibyshevohas been followed by a general advance of 25-30 miles between the salient thuscreated and the Sea of Azov. Taganrog has been captured, and the russian advance along the coast has reached a point about half-way between Taganrogand Mariupol.Summary.31. This has been a very successful week for the Russians. On the Smolensk,Sievsk and Mius Sectors they have made very considerable advances, and in theKharkov Sector, where their progress has been slower, they have consolidatedtheir positions and beaten back German counter-attacks. It is significant that since the beginning of the Russian offensive, the German counter-attacks (of whichthere have been many) have met with only minor success and in nearly everyinstance the Russians have subsequently regained the lost ground. The Russianpolicy of maintaining pressure at so many places is having its effect; by forcingthe Germans to fight simultaneously in several sectors they are preventing the concentration of their forces for the defence of any one area.Burma.32.   There has been patrol activity only.Recent reports intimate that the Japanese have been relieving their forward troops in the Mayu Peninsula in Arakan. Enemy defences protecting theMaungdaw-Buthidaung road have been strengthened.In the Sumprabum area in Upper Burma Kachin Levies claim to haveinflicted small casualties on the Japanese.Nicobars.33! The Japanese have been developing Car Nicobar, the northernmostisland of the Nicobar group in the Indian Ocean, where an airfield is being constructed.South-West Pacific Area.New Guinea.34. In the coastal area there has been little change. The Japanese madetwo raids on. Allied artillery positions near Tambu Bay, but although explosivecharges were laid under the guns the enemy were driven off and the chargesremoved.Australian forces which crossed the Francisco River near Bobdubi, about four miles south-west of Salamaua, have now seized some high ground within1,000 yards of Salamaua airfield. Strong Japanese counter-attacks on the 28thwere repulsed.Solomons.35.   Organised resistance in New Georgia Island has now ceased.   Theremains of the Japanese garrison at -Bairoko were evacuated by sea leaving[26022] B 2
behind vehicles and stores, just before the final assault by U.S. troops was dueto begin.U.S. troops have occupied several small islands between New Georgia island and Kolombangara Island. Arundel Island, the latest to be occupied, is separatedby only a mile of water from Vila, the Japanese aerodrome on Kolombangara.AIR SITUATION.General Review.36. Heavy night attacks were made, by aircraft of Bomber Command, onNuremberg, Munchen-Gladbach and Berlin.Extensive bombing was continued on the Italian railway system.United Kingdom.37. Enemy daylight activity overland was confined to a reconnaissance by three aircraft in the Dover-Folkestone area; at night three Me. 410s, probably on intruder operations, mingled with our bombers returning from Berlin, and dropped a few anti-personnel bombs on Norfolk.Home Waters.38. There have been few attacks on enemy shipping. By day, fighters and fighter-bombers damaged a 1,000-ton coaster off Dunkirk and a flak-ship and twotrawlers off the Dutch coast; at night, Naval Albacores damaged four mine-sweepers between Calais and Cherbourg.Aircraft of Bomber Command, of which 88 were despatched, laid 219 sea-mines in enemy waters.During July the Air-Sea Rescue Service, with the co-operation of the Navy,experienced its most successful month since its inception. A total of 248 aircrewwas rescued, 101 of these rescues being effected during the 50 hours between1730 hours on the 25th and 1930 hours on the 27th, a period which followed theheavy day and night raids on Hamburg; during this period as many as 70 long-range aircraft were searching at the same time.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.39. A total of 185 Fortresses (B. 17) and 74 medium bombers made two attacks on aeronautical facilities, in course of construction, at Watten, nearSt. Omer; 426 tons of bombs were dropped and photographs show a number ofhits on the target (see Appendix VI).The following attacks were made on airfields : -Date.	Airfield.	Aircraft despatched.	Attacked Target.	Tonnage.	Eesults.26th 27th 31st	Caen-Carpiquet Poix ... Amiens-Glisy Lille-Vendeville Monchy Le Breton ...	36 Marauders (B. 26) ... 36 Marauders (B. 26)... 170 Fortresses (B. 17) ... 36 Marauders (B. 26) ... 18 Mitchells (B. 25)  ... -	36 35 105 36 17	41 46 281 48 30	Good. Fair to good. Good. Good. Good.In addition, small-scale attacks by fighter-bombers on airfields near Laon andDouai resulted in the destruction of three enemy aircraft on the ground.Medium and light bombers attacked power stations at Gueriedan, Gosnayand Mazingarbe and the railway centre at Roosendaal, near Antwerp.From all the above operations four Fortresses (B. 17), three Bostons (A. 20),one Marauder (B. 26) and one Mitchell (B. 25) are missing, and a further fourFortresses (B. 17) crashed. Escort and withdrawal cover were supplied by143 squadrons of fighters, from which eight aircraft are missing. Twelve enemy aircraft were destroyed by the bombers and 15 by the fighters.Attacks on enemy transport, from Avhich one Mustang (P. 51) is missing,resulted in the destruction of, or damage to, 33 locomotives and 29 barges; inaddition, three enemy fighters were shot down.
Night.40. Aircraft of Bomber Command operated on three nights against thefollowing targets : Date.	Target.	Tonnage of Bombs.	Aircraft Despatched.	Attacked Primary Target.	Missing.	Crashed.27th/28th 30th/31st 31st/lst	Nuremberg   ... Munchen    Gladbach    and Rheydt      ....    ...... Berlin...	1,671 2,272 1,359	674 660 621	5S2 558 460	aa   1   ... 1 i 27            4 47     !      2	At Nuremberg visibility was good and, after a tendency to scattered bombingin the early stages, a good concentration was achieved later; many very large fires were seen over a wide area. Over Munchen Gladbach, its neighbouring town ofRheydt and Berlin there was variable cloud which rendered difficult the observa-tion and assessment of results. No photographic evidence is at present available.Strong fighter opposition was encountered at all three targets and losses represent5-g- per cent, of the sorties despatched; 18 enemy night-fighters were destroyed and a further eight were probably destroyed.Ammunition dumps near St. Omer and in the Foret de Hesdin were attacked by 32 and 36 bombers respectively; a number of large explosions was observed atthe latter target.Mosquitoes made small-scale attacks on Cologne, Duisburg (twice) and on atransformer station at Brauweiler, and intruder aircraft, of which 108 were despatched, attacked 12 enemy airfields; two Mosquitoes were lost on these operations.Italy.41. An intensive offensive was maintained against Italian railway communications.The heaviest single operation was carried out by 152 Fortresses (B. 17)against the railway centre at Pisa. Over 400 tons of bombs were dropped andhits were made on rolling stock and tracks, and also on the Piaggio aircraft factory, industrial buildings, warehouses .and the gas works. Hangars,administrative buildings and aircraft on the ground were severely damaged onthe adjoining airfield at San Guisto.In the Rome area attacks were made by Fortresses (B. 17) and Liberators(B. 24) on the railway centres at term , Sulmona, Orte and Pescara, and byMitchells (B. 25) and Wellingtons on Civitavecchia. A total of 812 tons of bombs was released and heavy damage to tracks and railroad property resulted.In the Naples area the daylight bombing was carried out by Mitchells (B. 25)and Marauders (B. 26) escorted by Lightnings (P. 38); the marshalling- yardsattacked were at Aversa, Benevento, Casata, Cancello, Torre Annunziata. by night Wellingtons bombed Bagnoli, Torre Annunziata and Salerno. Many ofthe main-line tracks were cut, rolling stock was wrecked, buildings and repairshops were seriously damaged and dislocation was caused to the railway system.In addition, successful attacks were made on the Capua and Grazzanise (N. ofNaples) airfields. The total weight of bombs dropped was 1,000 tons.In the foot of Italy railway centres were attacked by medium and light bombers and fighter-bombers. Taranto was bombed on three occasions by liberators (B. 24) and Wellingtons.  A total of 650 tons of bombs was released.Enemy opposition was most pronounced in the Naples area, and ourformations were opposed by from 25 to 50 fighters, although in an attack onAversa the number was reported to be 75, 17 of which were destroyed for the lossof 13 Lightnings (P. 38).In these operations over Italy for the week ended the 31st August, 137 enemy fighters were shot down; Allied losses were 42 fighters, six heavy-bombers and nine medium-bombers.Sardinia.42. Two offensive patrols, each of over 40 war hawks (P. 40F) were flownover the Island. Fragmentation bombs were dropped on military targets, and six enemy aircraft were shot down.
Mediterranean.North A frica.43. The German long-range bomber force did not operate in daylight; itseems likely that the threat of interception by Allied fighters now based in Sicilyis sufficient to compel the bombers to operate only during the hours of darkness.An attack by about 50 aircraft was carried out in the Algiers area on the night of the 26th/27th August.   Three enemy aircraft were destroyed.Russia.44. The Soviet Air Force has been actively supporting Russian operations over the front. In the area south-west of Kharkov considerable activity has beendisplayed in close support work by day. At night troop concentrations and M/Thave been attacked, and the railway junction at Poltava was bombed. Heavy air activity was reported south-west of Isyum, and air support was afforded to theRussian land forces in their outflanking of Taganrog.The German Air Force has been heavily engaged along the whole front fromBryansk southward, although the main concentration has been employed in the attempt to hold the Russian thrust west from Kuibyschevo (40 miles north ofTaganrog). It was the failure of this attempt, in support of which some close-support aircraft are thought to have been moved south from the Central Front,which necessitated the evacuation of Taganrog.The German fighter weakness, the result above all else of the overridingclaims of the Western Front and the defence of Western Germany, is the para-mount weakness of the G.A.F. in Russia, making it difficult either to giveadequate fighter support for long-range bomber and close-support units, or toprotect German airfields and rearward bases from incessant Soviet attack.Burma.45. In the North, heavy and medium bombers made a successful attack onMyitkyina; 32 tons of bombs were dropped, and photographs show the main station to have been destroyed and serious damage clone to rolling stock and buildings.In Central Burma, a total of 61 heavy and medium bombers made five attacks on railway installations; at Thazi (80 miles S. of Mandalay) and Thityabin (98miles N.N.W. of Mandalay), considerable quantities of rolling stock were destroyed.In the Mayu peninsula area, 45 Liberators (B. 24) and Mitchells (B. 25)dropped 70 tons of bombs on the town of Akyab.Attacks on shipping on the Irrawaddy, the Kaladan river and off the Arakancoast resulted in the destruction of, or damage to, 270 small craft.China.46. Two attacks, by a total of 30 escorted Allied bombers, were made on thetown and docks of Kowloon (Hongkong); two 550-foot ships and the power plantwere hit.Escorted Mitchells (B. 25) bombed the Tien Ho airfield at Canton and King-men airfield. 100 miles W.N.W. of Hankow; four enemy aircraft were destroyed and eight were probably destroyed for the loss of oneKittyhawk (P. 40).A total of 75 escorted enemy bombers attacked Wanhsien (155 miles S.S.E. ofHankow) and the outskirts of Chungking, where minor damage was done.Pacific Zone.New Guinea.47. A total of 204 tons of bombs was dropped in two effective attacks by heavy and medium bombers on the Hansa Bay area; 11 luggers and many bargeswere destroyed, a small freighter was set on fire and A.A. positions, gun emplace-ments and. fuel dumps were also hit.Three attacks, by a total of 99 escorted heavy bombers, were made on airfields and other targets in the Wewak area; photographs show nine enemy aircraft destroyed on the ground and, in combat, 26 enemy aircraft were destroyed, 12probably destroyed and 18 damaged for the loss of one Liberator (B. 24).
In the Bogadyim area, medium bombers obtained three hits on a bridge overthe Gori area and destroyed a number of barges and fuel dumps.Barges and jetties were attacked at Lae and Salamaua and, at the former,three jetties were destroyed.Small-scale raids were made on Finschhafen and on Babo in the Dutch new guinea.New Britain A rea.48. Beaufighters, in two attacks on shipping off the Vitu Islands, sunk or damaged seven patrol boats, 12 camouflaged, barges and three small craft.New Ireland A rea.49. Liberators (B. 24) hit, and left listing, a transport off Mussau island and damaged a merchantman in the same area.Timor.50. Small-scale night raids were made by medium bombers on Lauten, theKoepang area, Atamboea and Dill.Amboina Archipelago.51. Hudsons (A. 29) bombed Langgoer (Kai Islands) and Beaufightersattacked float planes at Taberfane (Aru Islands); two Beaufighters are missing.Solomons.52. Allied aircraft made three attacks on Kahili airfield (BougainvilleIsland) where eight enemy aircraft were destroyed on the ground and 18 in combat.Liberators (B. 24) bombed and hit one of three destroyers north-east of BukaPassage and also damaged a ship off Faisi Island.Off Choiseul Island, Kitty hawks (P. 40) destroyed three ships, probablyM.T.B&apos;s, and Mitchells (B. 25) in an attack on Kakasa destroyed ten barges.In combat over Vella Lavella, Allied fighters destroyed 20 enemy aircraft;another was shot down by A.A. fire.Medium and light bombers made three attacks on barges and gun positions in the southern part of Kolombangara Island.Rekata Bay on Ysabel Island was raided on three occasions by heavy bombers;medium bombers attacked the north-west area of the Island.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.53. A minor bombing incident occurred in Norfolk on the night of the31st August-1st September.   No damage or civilian casualties were caused.APPENDICES I, II, III and IY will be published periodically.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary vessels and to Naval Personnel.25th August. M.T.B. 349 damaged in action off Ijmuiden.27th August. Levant schooner No. 4 overdue at Cyprus since the 23rd.29th August. M/S A/S trawler Jtdiet slightly damaged in air attack onCatania.1st September. L.C.S. (L) SOI sunk after collision off Hastings.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 16 killed (including 1 W.R.N.S.); 9 wounded.Ratings : 23 killed ; 15 wounded.In addition, 21 officers killed (including 1 W.R.N.S.), previously reported missing; 14 officers prisoners&apos; of war, previously reported&apos;missing.
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports have been received during the week : Germany.Berlin. Information regarding the results of the first major attack on the23rd/24th August is as yet meagre. It is clear, however, that in the areas attackedconditions similar to those prevailing in Hamburg resulted and serious admmistra-tive chaos ensued as a result of uncontrolled evacuation from the town and the dislocation of the supply organisation.Among the important factories seriously damaged were Daimler-Benz A.G.(Marienfelde) (heavy tanks, lorries, &amp;c), Fritz Werner AG. (Marienfelde)(milling and grinding machines), Askania Werke A.G. (Mariendorf) (precisioninstruments), and Henschel Flugzeugwerke A.G. (Schonefeld).In the Mosquito attack on the 12th August the Warsaw bridge undergroundstation was severely damaged by direct hits and the army clothing office for south-east Berlin, situated in Mariennen Strasse, Eichwalde, was burnt out with considerable loss of stores.An informant who left Berlin prior to the recent attack gave the followingaccount of conditions when he left: 1- &quot;The stories of the Hamburg attacks spread throughout Germany bythe evacuees have played a greater part in undermining morale than any eventthat has yet taken place. In Berlin morale changed from a limited confidence to almost complete panic. Everyone who can takes steps to leave the city eachnight. The outlying towns are filled and many camp in barns or fields. Thestaff of some of the ministries has been evacuated to Frankfurt on the Oderand neighbouring towns such as Furstenwalde (30 miles east-south-east)and Eberswalde (25 miles north-east). The working of night shifts in factories has become very unpopular and many now only work during theday. The general uneasiness has been increased by the fact that Hitler hasneither appeared nor spoken.&quot;Hamburg. The authorities are taking all possible steps to restore somesemblance of life to the city. Almost the whole of the business centre of thecity and all the administrative buildings in the port area were destroyed. Theport area was closed to traffic, not only by reason of the damage to quays,bunker and unloading facilties, but by the fact that at the few quays whereunloading was still possible no labour was available. In addition many of the canals were blocked by sunken barges.Owing to lack of water due to burst mains and no pressure, fires were com-pletely out of control and left to burn themselves out. One informant states thatthe districts which were less damaged were those in which water tanks had beenestablished. These proved of great value and in his view the damage would havebeen considerably less if such facilities had been available in all parts of the city.Reports state that eight submarines on the slips at Blohm and Voss were severely damaged.At present it is hoped to reopen the port to general traffic about the7th September.Mannheim. In the attack on the 9th-10th August further severe damage was caused to buildings and warehouses around the Industrie Hafen andVerbindungskanal. As a result barge traffic was considerably slowed down butnot entirely stopped. As late as the 18th August through trains still by-passed the main station.Austria.Wiener Neustadt. Photographs taken on the 16th August show thefollowing damage resulting from the attack by U.S.A.A.F. aircraft onthe 13th :-Wiener Neustadt Flugzeugwerke (airframe works).  On the western side themain machine shop has been damaged by H.E. and blast, and two large assemblyshops have been partially destroyed.   The largest stores building has been hit,
one of the three large flight hangars destroyed, and several smaller buildingsdestroyed or damaged. Installations affected include the compass swing base anda gunnery synchronisation station, while about 20 aircraft, mostly Me. 109&apos;s,appear to have been damaged or destroyed. A labour camp and workmen&apos;sdwellings south-east of the works have been affected.Steyr-Daimler-Puch A.G. (engineering). All the large buildings have been hit more or less severely. One of the two large machine and assembly shops has ahole in the roof of over 5,400 sq. ft., while lesser roof damage extends over morethan half the area. The workshop at the southern end (over two acres) isdestroyed over more than 4,000 sq. ft., with other blast damage to three-quarters of the roof.Henschel Works (heavy engineering). In the Henschel Works a very longstores building has received considerable damage at one end from a direct hit,and a workshop (more than three-quarters of an acre) has been one-thirddestroyed.Italy.term . Photographs taken after the attack on the 11th August show that considerable damage has been caused in the town and in the industrial area.immediately to the east of it. Railway communications and railway buildingsnorth of the town have suffered, causing dislocation of traffic. In the term  steelworks part of the rolling mills has been destroyed and the end of the boiler-housevery severely damaged. Four other large workshops have been heavily damaged by direct hits.The jute mill situated to the south-west of the steel works has been entirelydestroyed. Three and a half acres have been gutted and the main buildingspartially destroyed, while five other shops are seen to have been gutted and arestill burning.The wool mill adjoining the jute mills has received five direct hits through the roof and a large area on the western side of the plant has been gutted. Two other large sheds have been more than half destroyed, and there is considerable damageby blast.Damage to rail communications includes the destruction of eight bays in therailway repair shops, blast damage to the station building, the destruction of tworailway buildings in the yards, and the destruction and derailment of rolling-stockin the station and marshalling yard. A road bridge east of the marshalling yardshas received a direct hit.France.Villacoublay. Photographs taken  after the  U.S.A.A.F.  attack on the24th August show the following damage to buildings of the S.N.C.A. du Nord : In the northern section :  3 hangars demolished.3 hangars damaged.4-bay shed over half destroyed.10 sheds of varying sizes demolished or damaged.1 unidentified building gutted and two damaged.In the south-western section : 1 hangar three-quarters destroyed.4 living huts damaged.In S.N.C.A. Loire &amp; Olivier a hangar previously damaged and partlyreconstructed has again been gutted.Watt en.- An immediate interpretation of photographs taken after theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 27th August shows that the site and buildings in courseof construction for aeronautical facilities have been heavily hit. On the northside the general mass of construction has probably been destroyed for almost halfits depth, while at the west end the S.W. wall of a deep excavation has partiallycollapsed. Several smaller buildings on the top of the N. escarpment have been destroyed, and on the S. side a building has been severely damaged. The variousrailway tracks running through and around the side have been cut in many places.[26022] &apos;    . c
Sea Mining.The following casualties have been reported : 5th August. The fishing vessel Olga mined and sunk, south of Kjeini(S.W. corner of the Kattegat).8th August. German schooner Landkirchen damaged near TolkedybLight Buoy, Great Belt.VIth A ugust. Fishing vessel N. 314 Margrethe mined and sunk offAsko, Smaaland.It is reported by U-boat survivors that U. 226 was mined and sunk outsideLorient early in 1943 whilst returning from a 21-week patrol.











</content>
</cab>
