<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/5/50 images: 640-666</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY5S GOVERNMENT.)8 E 0 R E T.W.P.(G.)(40)  100. COPY NO.STH APRIL,   1940.WAR CABINET,REVIEW OP IMPORT PROGRAMMES IN THEFIRST YEAR OF THE WAR FROM THESHIPPING STANDPOINT.Report Toy the Lord Privy Seal.At their meeting held on 1st March,  1940 (W. M.(4056th Conclusions, Minute 1) the War Cabinet discussed areport on the shipping position prepared by my predecessorand agreed(a) that the import programme of 47 million tons forthe first year of the war should be reviewed asfollows:-(1)  The, Ministry of Supply Programme should be examined, by the Lord Privy Seal so far as concerned the Fighting Services,  in con-junction with the Minister for Coordinationof Defence;    and so far as concerned rawmaterials for manufacture for export tradeand for civilian consumption in the home market,  in conjunction with the Presidentof the Board of Trade and other ministers concerned:(2) The jMijSjeeJLlaneous, and Unallocated Items- should be&quot; examined by the Lord Privy seal in conjunction with the President of theBoard of Trade,  with a view to -(i)  reducing the total from 3*3 million tons to not more than 2^3 million tonsin a full year,(ii)  arranging as far as practicable forthe allocation of the items comprisedunder this head to the Ministry ofSupply or Ministry of Food Programmes,with a view to such imports being brought under control:(3) The^Jlinistry of Food Programme should be examined by&quot;the Lord&quot; Privy Seal,  as Chairmanof the Food Policy Committee, with a view to reducing consumption to a basis which was10 per cento less than the provisionalfigures Indicated in the Food import programmes.

Treasury Chambers, S.W.10entered into consultation with the Permanent Heads of theDepartments concerned with a view to arriving at conclusionsregarding the nature of the cuts in the import programmes which could he reasonably asked for in the remaining portionof the first year of the warj.    and he has now furnished tome the attached statement setting out the results of theinter-Departmental discussions^3. It will be Been that it has been possible to agree upon reductions in the import programme for the first year of the war of the order of 2 million tons, representing a cut of approximately 7 per cento  in the second half of thefirst year of the war,      The Departments are agreed that if further cuts on any considerable scale are to be made,  theywould need to be at the expense of animal feeding stuffs;the results of cutting feeding stuffs just now would be unfortunate I think and we should not do so unless theshipping position should deteriorate..4.- I recommend that the War Cabinet should agree t -(a) that the cut of 800,000 tons should be made inthe Import Programme of the Ministry of Supply,though as regards the suggested cut in &quot;paper and paper-making materials&quot; special attention will need to be given to possible repercussions on the internal economy of Newfoundland and tothe representations which may be expected from canada;    (paragraphs 15 and 16).(b) that the cuts proposed in the Ministry of PoodProgramme should be made without prejudice tothe question of sugar imports which is being brought to the War Cabinet separately onexchange grounds by the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Minister of Pood (paragraph 12).(c) that for the time being no cut should be made inthe import programme for animal feeding stuffs;but that, as in the case of all other items inthe shipping programme,  this item should be reviewed if for any unforeseen reason shipping difficulties increase;    and that in any case thewhole position in regard to these imports shouldbe re^examipod in the autumn when we know the outcome of this year5s harvest at home;(paragraphs 18 and 19) .(Intldo)    K. W.

vji kl 0REVIEW OP IMPORT PROGRAMMES IN THE first year OF THE WAR FROM THE SHIPPING STANDPOINT,Copy of a Minute?,   dated 5th April, 1940, from Sir HoraceWilson to theLord Privy Seal.In accordance with the request which your predecessormade to me after the meeting of the War Cabinet held on 1stMarch, 1940,  (W.M. (1+0) 56th Conclusions, Minute 2) at whichhis Report on Import Programmes (Paper W. P. (ho) 6I+) wasconsidered, I have been in consultation with the PermanentHeads of the Departments concerned with a view to arriving atagreed conclusions regarding the nature of the cuts in imports which could be made in the remaining portion of the first. ye&amp;r-of the war.The original.2,. .      You,will recall that Sir Samuel Hoare started from theprogramme.&quot;&quot;-&quot;&quot;basis, adopted by&apos;the. Minister of-Shipping in his Memorandumof 5th.November last (Paper W.P. (G-.) (39) 89) that the totalimports -in,the first year of the war (other than petroleum and&quot;its products) would amount to hi million tons distributed asfollows-: -Commodities controlled by theMinistry of FoodCommodities specifically covered; by the Ministry of supply programme,  including molassesMiscellaneous and unallocated items,000 tons.19,80023,9003,300Adjustmentformolasses,-1+7,0003. Petroleum and its products were excluded from theabove total because thejr are imported in tankers,  and theirimport therefore presents a separate shipping problem.      TheMinistry of Supply Programme represented by 23.9 million tonsgiven in the table in the preceding paragraph included molasses;for that Department is responsible for its purchase.      In view,however,  of the fact that molasses is normally imported intankers,  it is desirable that in the consideration of the

\0 &amp; iTransfer ofunallocateditems toappropriateprogrammes.shipping,  as distinct from the exchange aspect of theimport programmes, molasses,  like petroleum,  should heexcluded from account.      The figure of 23.-9 million tonsshould therefore be reduced by 0,&apos;:5 million tons,.&apos; and thefigure of h7 million tons by a like amount.      The original programme now under consideration is therefore as follows:-1,000 tons.Ministry of PoodMinistry of Supply (raw materials)Miscellaneous and Unallocated Items19,80023,^003,300h6,500U. The War Cabinet agreed that items which till thenhad figured in the Programme for Miscellaneous andUnallocated Items, but which are in fact appropriate eitherto the Ministry of Pood or the Ministry of Supply,  should infuture be Included in the Import Programmes of those departments..     As the result of a careful review,  the Boardof Trade has estimated that the above decision of the WarCabinet involves the following transfers from the programme for Miscellaneous --and- Ujaalloc-atad-Iterasi-1 .000 tons..-To the Ministry of Pood 200To the Ministry of Supply 900When this adjustment has been made,  the subdivision of theoriginal import programme is seen to be as follows:-1.000 tons.Ministry of Pood 20,000Ministry of Supply (raw materials) 2h,300Other Goods 2,200h6,500

Imports&apos;&quot;&apos;in thefirst sixmonths.import programme forthe secondoix months.Ministryof PoodProgramme.5. On the basis adopted by the Board of Trade theactual imports during the first six months of the war,which amounted to 20.2 million tons are divisible betweenthe three parts of the import programme as follows:-1.000 tons.Ministry of Pood35 9,522Ministry of Supply (raw materials) 10,071Other Goods 59720,190On the same basis,  the import programme in the secondsix months would amount to 26.3 million tons if the original programme for importing U6.5 million tons in the first year of the war were to be achieved.6. It will be convenient at this stage to examine in turn the import programmes for the second six months ofthe war submitted by the Departments concerned.7. The Ministry of Pood state that on the basis hitherto contemplated the lr --shjLppTfn-g-r^e^^ the ser-nnd sixmonths would amount to 10.3 million tons.     &quot;This figure&quot;,&quot;however,  excludes imports of beer and livestock, bothimported from Eire, which it is estimated will amount to approximately 200,000 tons in the period in question.-    both these items must-be regarded as forming part of the PoodImport Programme in view of the decision by the War Cabinet36 The figures here given include all food items imported in theperiod in question, since under the new re-allocation all such items are referable to the Ministry of Food&apos;s import programme.      It should be realised however that in theearlier months especially there were appreciable imports offoods of. various kinds,  the import of which was not thenunder control, which the Ministrjr of Food would not themselves have imported.

Ministryof supply programme.programme for Otherioods.tj hi fc*that there should he included in each programme every itemrelevant thereto,      The Food Import Programme for thesecond six months on this basis-should be placed at 10.5 million tons,      Actual imports in the first six months ofthe war attributable to items now included in,this Programmeamounted (as shown in paragraph 5 above) to 9*5 million tons.The total imports in respect of the Food Programme for thefirst year of the war would,  therefore,  amount to 20.million tons,80. The Ministry of Supply estimate that their shippingrequirements in the second six months of the war would amountto 1^=37 million tons on the basis hitherto contemplated.Actual imports in respect of the items now included in that programme amounted in the first six months of the war to10.07 million tons,      On this basis,  therefore,  the totalimports in respect of this programme would amount to 2I4..I4I4.million tons in the first year of the war,9o The Programme for Other Goods, which replaces theformer Programme for Miscellaneous and Unallocated Items,comprises imports of every kind (other than petroleum products and molasses )  shown in the Trade and Navigation Accountswhich have not been included either in the Ministry of food programme or in the Ministry of Supply ProgrammeB      The itemscomprised in the Programme for Other Goods consist partly ofimports of manufactured goods required for the FightingServices (including the Ministry of Supply), and partly of miscellaneous items required for civil consumption and export.The Board of Trade estimate that imports in respect of this programme in the second six months will amount to 550,000 tonsActual imports in the first six months amounted to 600,000tons.      The total requirements of this programme in the first year of the war amount therefore to 1.15 million tons.* See paragraph 3 above.

*j 6 4Estimatedtotalimportrequire-ments in;, L,he first year ofthe war on thepresentbasis.10.        It is now possible to compare the total import requirements in the first year of the war on the present &apos;basis with the first approximation made in November lastby the Minister of Shipping, as reassembled in paragraph habove:-(million tons)Old ProgrammeBefore afterreallocations.  reallocations.Ministry of PoodMinistry ofSupplyOther Goods19*8023 ohO3.3020.002h.302.20PresentProgramme.20.001+6.50q.6.502q..hii1.15d-5.59Possiblecuts inthe portionof theMinistryof PopdProgrammerelatingto food for human!&apos; ^-sumption.11.       The foregoing table shows that the present programme,which unlike the first of the Ministry of Pood and Ministryof Supply programmes covers the whole of the relevant imports,falls short of the original by almost exactly 1 million tons.This reduction has been secured-entirely at the expense -of the miscellaneous Programme.      Effect has thus been given to thedecision by the War Cabinet that that programme should be cut by 1 million tons.      It remains to set out the cuts which theDepartments have indicated might be made in their programmeswithout serious detriment either to our war effort or toBritish agriculture.12.       The Ministry of Pood have furnished detailedexplanations in regard to each of the items other thananimal feeding stuffs figuring in their import programme,from which the following conclusions emerge:-

\? &apos;) KCj)       t?The Ministry of Food state that, if the meat ration were now reduced from ls.lOd. tols&apos;.&apos;8d. and corresponding adjustments made inregard to catering establishments, etc., itwould be possible to reduce imports by 5Q0O0tons in the remainder of the first year of thewar.      The Ministry hold the view, which Ishare, that an immediate reduction cannot beregarded as practical politics;   but they haveagreed that the possibility of reducing the ration should be re-examined in say two months&apos;time.      They have undertaken, therefore, notto enter into any relatively long termcommitments in the Argentine based on the need to maintain the existing ration, unless very definite price advantages can be gained thereby.;(b) Fresh Fruit.The Ministry of Food believe that it should bepossible to effect some reduction under this head;   but, in view of the fact that they have only recently assumed control of fresh fruit and are not aware of the extent to whichcommitments may have been entered into, theyare not in a position at the present time toset a figure on the saving which can be made;(c) Butter.In view of the recent discussion at the ministerial Sub-Committee on Food Policy, itis not suggested that any cut should be madein this item;    but the Ministry of Food have indicated that from a purely Departmentalpoint of view they would have been prepared tosupport a reduction in butter imports;(d) Oil and Seeds.The Ministry of Food have indicated that a saving of 130,000 tons could have been achieved in the remaining portion of the first year of thewar if margarine were   rationed at 3 oz. a headas from 1st of this month, and compound lard at oz.  a head, and if at the same time supplies to linoleum and paint manufacturers had beenreduced by 50 and 20 per cent, respectivelybelow their normal requirements.      The Ministry &apos;consider - and I agree - that the introduction of margarine rationing at the present time would raise serious difficulties in view of the recent decision to increase the butter ration.     As inthe case of meat, the Ministry of Food haveagreed, however, that the question of reducingthe home consumption of margarine and compoundlard by means of rationing should be re-examined in, say, two months&apos;  time.

Consideration should further he given to thepossibility of reducing the industrial use of seed oils , though care should be taken not tointerfere with the important export trade inlinoleum and paints,      A reduction in importsof oil seeds which might be effected by the rationing of linoleum and paint manufacturers to the extent indicated above would involvea consequential diminution in the supply of oil cakes - an essential feeding stuff fordairy cattle - of some 28,000 tons;SugarcThe Ministry of Pood, point outthat if as from 1st of this month the domesticration had been reduced from 12 oz.  to 8 oz. ,a saving of approximately 122,500 tons could have been achieved in the remainder of thefirst year.      This question has been underdiscussion, from the point of view of Exchange,between the Chancellor of the Exchequer andthe Minister of Pood by whom it is being brought before the War Cabinet separately;Canned Fruit.The Ministry of Food have offered to reduceimports in the period to the end of Augustnext by 255000 tons;Canned Salmon0It is desirable on exchange grounds that theimport of canned salmon should be completelydiscontinued.      The Ministry of Food are opposed to such a course since they fear thatit might involve them in the purchase ofmore expensive alternative foods elsewhere.They agree, however, that in view of thestock position imports could be curtailedfor the time being without prejudice to thegeneral question;Eggs.The Ministry of Food have undertaken to investigate the possibility of reducingimports of liquid eggs, which are used only for commercial purposes by confectioners etc. ;Cocoa.,The Ministry of Food agree that stocks inthis country ore adequate.      The problem here is not a food problem but a financial one,and owes its origin to the Government havingbought the whole West African crop.      Thiscrop will perish unless, before the rains,it is shipped either to this country or to any -alternative markets which can be found for it.      From a shipping point of view the tonnageused f^r ^&quot;&quot;o^ing cocoa to this country could be better used to import ground nuts.

IImportsofAnimal[Feeding-Stuffs.PutsSuggestedin theMinistrypf Supply&quot;Pro gramme.cy cy pi13.The foregoing may he summarised as follows(a)    a reduction of 25:.000 tons of importswill he effected in Canned Fruit;Ob)cuts of amounts which it is not possible at- this stage to estimate will be made inthe imports of;--(i)sh fruit;(ii)    oilseeds for industrial uses(other than exports)jmmcanned salmon;:quao. egus :(c)(d)(e)the possibility of securing a reductionm sugar imports of 122,500 tons is beingtaken to the    War Cabinet separately;from the food. as distinct from thefinancial, point of -view, a reduction inoeoa iiioo:couiQ oesecurercuts are technically possible but notexpedient at the present time in thecase of meat, butter, and oilseeds forthe manufacturing of margarine andcompound lard;On the basis indicated above... I conclude that, even if the sugar ration is reduced, imports of food for human consumption in the remaining part of the first year of the war could hardly be reduced by as much as 200 .,000 tons , without undesir-able depletion of stocks or considerable interference with thenormal diet of the population^Ike Both the Agricultural Departments and the Ministryof Food agree that;j if any substantial reduction is to bemade in the Ministry of Food Import Programme during theremainder of the first year of the war, this can only beachieved at the expense of animal feeding stuffs,.      the implications of action in this sense are discussed inparagraph 18 telow.-15. The Ministry of Supply have Indicated that theywould be prepared to agree to the following reductions intheir import programme during the remainder of the first year of the wars-

tons.300 ,00050,00015,00050 ,00050,000328 ,0007,000800,000Approximately one-half of the reductions suggested would heeffected either by drawing upon stocks or by reducing therate at which stocks diminished since the outbreak of war are now being re-built^      In making the offer set out above,the Ministry of Supply stated.-Any further reductions in the programme would create greater difficulties,      It is unlikely thata reduction in paper and paper-making materials from the Baltic would result in shipping being available to us for other materials^      some further reduction in cotton might be possible with a more severe restriction of home use andsome danger to the export trade;    but reductions would have to be made in United States cotton;and there are difficulties here both from thepoint of view of the market and of relationswith that country      Any further reduction iniron and steel, non-ferrous metals and timberwould at once affect Service or export pro-grammes or both,      The only other single largeitem of imports is sulphuric acid and fertilisers-Fertilisers alone (including the pyrites requiredfor making sulphuric acid used in theirmanufacture) account for some 1,070,000 tons ofthe total of 1,42+5,000 tons, and the Ministryof Supply have been asked to prepare for alarger programme of fertiliser production nextyear,,Iron OreManganese OreLeadBauxiteRaw CottonPaper and paper makingmaterialsTanning materialsThe possibility of imposing a further reduction in theimports of United States cotton has already been raised with HoM. Embassy, Washington,

16. The cuts proposed in the imports of paper and paper-making materials - while -justifiable from the point of viewof shipping and exchange - involve a reduction of 77,000 tonsin imports from Canada (Newsprint 27,000 tons; wood pulp,including that for rayon, 50,000 tons) and 159,000 tons from newfoundland (pulpwood 132,000 tons; newsprint 27,000 tons).The cut in newsprint imports from Canada, which means a virtual cessation of Canadian imports over the next five months, is likely to cause difficulties and in fact re-presentations were received from the Canadian Government when a much smaller cut was contemplated,,    In the case of Newfound-land the results of the virtual cessation of newsprint imports and the complete cessation of pulpwood imports which these cutsinvolve will he serious.    Very strong representations were madeby the Newfoundland Government, at a time when reductions ofapproximately 50 per cent in newsprint only were proposed, thatthis reduction would have serious effects on employment and theeconomic stability of the Island, which is dependent to an exceptional degree on this industry.The responsibility for the administration and finances of Newfoundland, which was taken over by the United KingdomGovernment in 1933, makes it necessary to call attention to thepolitical and financial consequences which may follow adecision so to curtail our imports from the Island.Reduced     17. If the cuts offered by the Departments were securedImportProgramme and if no cuts were to be made in animal feeding stuffs,  theoffered.import programme for the first year of the war would be asfollows:-1,000 tonsMinistry of Pood (say) 19,000 - 19,950Ministry of Supply 23,6h0Other Goods 1,150TOTAL Uh,590 - hh,7U0

were to be put at the smaller of the two figures given in theabove range, the reduction on the original figure of U6.5 million tons would be 1.91 million tons or approximately h.lper cent;    a reduction of this amount would represent, however,a cut of 7.3 per cent in the imports amounting to 26.3 million tons which would need to be brought in during the second sixmonths of the war.to complete the original programme.mimal 18. In addition to the cuts indicated above, we havecedingtuffs considered at length the question whether a cut in animalprogrammefeeding s^^tiffs of the order of 1 million tons should be made.IOn this question, the Agricultural Departments have.....submitted the following observations:-   -If it is decided that the Ministry of food programme for the first year of war must bereduced by about 10 per cent,  it seems evidentthat feeding stuffs must be reduced by approximately one million tons during the five months April to August out of a programme ofimports during that period of rather less than2 million tons of cereals.    In the interest ofthe milk supply,   it would be -undesirable to makeany cut in oilseeds and oilcakes.A reduction of this order would be farheavier than is proposed on any item in the .Ministry of Supply programme and it would follow a substantial reduction in imports of feedingstuffs during the first seven months of the war of about 30 per cent of normal requirements.    Inorder to safeguard the milk supply next winter and to enable a rationing scheme for feedingstuffs,  if found practicable,, to be introduced in the autumn,  it will be necessary, whether ornot imports of feeding stuffs are reduced in thenext five months,  to build up moderate reserves of both oilcake and cereals.    Moreover, loadingsfor April and May arrival are already short ofthe programme figures by nearly 100,000 tons per month.While it might be possible to accumulate thenecessary reserves and maintain a fair proportionof the existing pig and poultry populations,even if actual imports fall somewhat below theprogramme figure for the next five months, a cut of the order of magnitude of 1 million tons would render it necessary to contemplate and to-announce to the agricultural industry that theremust be a drastic reduction in numbers of pigs&apos;and poultry this summer.    This would mean the virtual elimination of the large number of specialist producers, including those on State-owned or assisted smallholdings, with all thepolitical,  social and other implications involved by. such an announcement and the destruction of a

ptg treasury sanction(requiredIjforI foreign  exchange.Treasury Chambers, S,W,1.5th April,  19^0..large part of the capital assets at presentemployed in the pig and poultry industries ofa value that may he roughly estimated at 75,000,000.On the other hand,  if the cut could hedeferred until after next harvest, a substantial proportion of our pigs and poultry could bemaintained not only through the summer but probably also through next winter, and thisvaluable reserve of livestock would be preserved.19. Having regard to the considerations set out above andto the fact that current rates of imports do not suggest thatit need be regarded as certain that we shall not be ablesubstantially to complete the import programme already laiddown,  for the remaining part of the first year of the war,the wiser course would seem to be to make no cut at thepresent time in the animal feeding stuffs programme.Naturally, as with all other items in the shipping programme,this item would have to be reviewed, if for any unforeseenreason shipping difficulties increase.    In any case thewhole question of feeding stuffs imports should be re-examined in the autumn when..the outcome of this year&apos;s homeharvest is known.20. It is clearly understood by all the Departmentsconcerned that the inclusion of a given item in a Depart-mental Import Programme is not to be taken as prejudging thequestion whether the foreign exchange can be made availablefor the purchase of the whole of that item in the currencyproposed.    It will remain the duty of the Departmentsconcerned to obtain Treasury sanction for purchases in thesame manner as hitherto.(Signed) H. J, WILSON.

</content>
</cab>
