<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/72/0 images: 89-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
           The question of the&apos;welfare  of  the natives  of Tropical  Africa  will  come up  at  the Peace Conference  in connexion with the revision of the Brussels Act  and is no doubt  one in  which the American representatives will show considerable interest.           The Brussels Act of 1890 dealt  with the Slave Trade,  Arms  Traffic,  and  Liquor  Traffic.           Tha first of these  is, happily,  no longer a live issue.   With regard  to the  Arms Traffic, this country has  for  many  years been  endeavouring to  place matters oh a more satisfactory basis,  but  has hitherto been persistently opposed by  the,French who have been mainly  preoccupied to pre serve, the trade  at Djibouti.. The  French have  now proposed  to  us that we should come to a preliminary agreement on this question before the Conference,  and  the Foreign Office, in consultation with the  India  Office  and  Colonial  Office,  are  drafting some very stringent provisions as  a basis of discussipn. .           For some unexplained reason philanthropists,                   dangerous ignoring,the  far more/traffic  in Arms, have always concentrated  their attention  on the trade  in Liquor and  there  are  few  questions which have.given rise to more persistent exaggeration  and misrepresentation.This was clearly established by the Commission of enquiry which investigated the matter  locally under the presidency of  Sir Mackenzie Chalmers in.1909 and which only confirmed the views  held by a succession of responsible, officials engaged  in, the administration ofthe countries in question.          It has  however,  always  been recognised by this                                             country
 country  that  the  trade  33  an undesirable one, which might well  be replaced  by  a trada  in. other commodities and  that every effort should be made to reduce it to the  lowest  possible limits.   Accordingly at the Brussels Conference in  1889-90 tha British rapresenta- tive proposed that a minimum import duty of 200 Frvper hectolitre  (7s/2iVd per  gallon) should be imposed, in those countries in tropical Africa where the trade was already  in  existence.   Owing to the opposition of other Powers this duty  was eventually reduced to 15 Fr. per hecto (64-d per gallon).         In 1899 Great Britain brought the matter before a second  international  Conference at Brussels and suc- ceadad in obtaining an  increase of the minimum duty from 15 Fr: to 75  Fr: per hecto, with an exceptional duty of 60 Fr: per hecto:  for  Togo]and and Dahomey.         In 1906 she took action once more and at length succeeded in.  securing the general minimum of 100 Fr:per  hocto: (3s/7d per gallon)  B minimum which,- inpractice h*s been largely exceeded in all the british possesions.    Finally in 1912 n fourth international conference was summoned at her suggestion with a viewto concerting measures  for a  further increase.of duty and  for preventing the traffic from penetrating into newdistricts.   This Conference,  however,  proved entirelyabortive.         It must therefore be  admitted that,  both byexample and precept,  this country has in the  past donaits utmost to limit the  traffic in its own territories and to induce the other Powers  territorially  interested-in tropical Africa to  do the  same.
          I am of opinion that the time has now come for further action and that the British represen-tatives at the Peace Conference should or, their own initiative propose to the other Powers that tho res-restrictions now in force in thy prohibition areas shouldbe extended at the earliest possible date to the wholeof the territories subject to the 3russels Act.  Thiswill entail a great sacrifice of revenue (amountingin the case of Nigeria to some  1,000,000 on a pre-war basis,  and of the Gold Coast to some  500,000)by Colonies which have already been seriously affectedby the War, and p;reat care will be required in thereadjustment of their budgets.           I have no doubt that my colleagues willconcur in my proposals and that the announcement ofthem to the Conference will materially assist theBritish representatives to press their views as tothe future of the German Colonies in tropical africa.                                W.H.L.                                  18* 12.18.

</content>
</cab>
