<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/72/0 images: 197-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
12l/Railways/420.WAR.. CABINET.Sale of Transportation Equipment    to the French Government. 1471*2.Memorandum by the Seoretary of State for War.          The French Government, through M. Olaveille, has expressed a desire to purchase the transport material held by the British Army in France, i.e. Broad  and Light Railways.          Rails, Locomotives, Wagons, Coaching Stook,     Locomotive &amp; Wagon Workshop Machinery, Mobile Light     Railway Workshops, Tractors, Rumps and Watering     Equipment. Port Equipment,          Cranes, Power Plants, Tackle. Inland Water Transport.          Tugs , Barge s, Cranes, Workshop Et]uipment. Railway Engineering Plant.          Pile Drivers, Steam Navvies, Contractors Hallway     Plant, Bridging Tackle, Bridge Girders. Road Plant.          Road Rollers. Quarry Plant, Foden Lorries,     Scrapers, etc., etc,          Ji. Claveille states that the French Government propose t reinstate the railway systems within the ensuing two years and also to make up for the&apos; shortage of railway equipment prior to thewar by purchase of manufacture of rolling stock and other transport material.          It it? considered that if the British and American equipment in France be purchased and the output of Frenchmanufactures called upon to the utmost, there  will still remain a -necessity for the placing of orders in other countries to carry out the  programme within the time specified.  To enable an estimate to bo made of the magnitude of purchase from other countries, U.  Clave illegitimate desires immediate information of the- rolling stock, track, etc., which the British Government wouldbe willing to leave in France after their Armies needs havebeen met.          The position at present with regard  to the sale, ofBritish rolling stock is limited to the disposal.of 5,60C wagonsto the French.at cost less 4  per annum depreciation and 9,250wagons to the  Belgians upon similar terms.          It has been thought desirable to  bring to the UnitedKingdom some of this material for use on light railways and canalsand otherwise.  On the other hand,  it may be that in order to                                                           ,.keep
Colonel 17. Dally JonesWar Cabinet.Correction to G.T.  6542.(Sale of transportation equipment to the PreitcJa.                    Gorernnent.)     In the last line of the liemorandun for&quot;Disposal Board&quot; read  &quot;Disposal  Board of theMinistry of Supply&quot;.                                      MXLKTCR.27th December, 1918.
I jeep manufacturers  going  it will  bo  in the national  interest toI jive out  orders  at  home for such  new material as may be  neededI for these  purposes.           In any ease  it  appears  undesirable to dispose  of rorkshop  maohinory,  of which  there is a large and valuable jolleotion in the repair  shops  for locomotives and other stock, inoluding road and .malntenaii.ee vehicles.           Again,  road  rollers and tractors are -wanted  for home servioe and could not  be  re plated for use in the United  kingdom dthln a  reasonable  time,  having  regard to the requirements of iho Head  Board.           To pull up railway  track,  heavy and light, of  which there Is  roughly 2500  and  3000  miles  respectively, will be costly apart from time,  labour and  shipping  neoessary to transport  it to England, ani it is a question whether  it would not be advantageous to iisposo of it in situ  to  the  French.           As to  flanal  eraft these, to an extent, are useful on French canals, but  are unsuitable to British conditions.           Further,  there  is the financial question of  increasing the indebtedness of the French  to the British Government.           The magnitudo of the  question ie suoh that a decision of the War Cabinet  is  sought on  tho  following points     1,     Is M,  Claveille to be  informed that the Transport material Lees such items  as  workshop machinery, road rollers, etc., required for use in the United  Kingdom,  whioh his Government  desires to[purchase,  is at  his  disposal  on terms to be agreed.     2.    la IL9  Olaveille to  bo told that all equipment  is required it  homo and that it is proposes to transport it to England?     3,    l1hc-re  is  the further  question  in th&amp; event  of No.l being locepted,  viz. who  is  to  negotiate the sale?  There  is in existencef&apos;hc Butte rvrorth  *commission charged with tho settlement of transport  ocounts  between the two  Governments and originally  authorized to  ell the  roxling stock to the French or the Belgians.  Is this  ommiseion to carry through the negotiations, strengthened by the idditlon  of a railway  engineer, or&quot;is  it considered  that the Disposal  Board should  svttl*  terms?3rd December, 1916.em

</content>
</cab>
