<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/72/0 images: 398-402</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
w. c.Vis theTrfvty df(This Docinr             His Bntai i             ^eminent)            9trtr         IX.CONFIDENTIAL.             Political Intelligence Department,21.Deoul918.                           Foreign Office,f Lssi                                               Germany/027.EkltW^            MEMORANDUM                        ON .          THE PROSPECTS  OF OXTER AND ORDERED GK)VEKMffiWT                        IN BERLIN.It        It  is difficult to gather a complete or clearidea of the  political situation in Germany in so far asit can be distinguished from the economic  That theeconomic  situation is very menacing admits of no doubt;and there seems to be no prospect of improvement until a stable Government supported by the great majority ofthe people is formed, and until the raw materials ofindustry are available in adequate quantities.  The wayto a stable Government for the whole of Germany - a federal government of the United States of Germany - lies through,the Constituent Assembly.  The meeting of the Congress of delegates of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos;  Councils from allGermany which opened in the Prussian Chamber on Monday.,December 16,  resulted in an overwhelming majority for theConstituent and in the expression of an eager desire that itshould be elected and should assemble sooner that the previously contemplated date,  February 16..  It appears thatthe Ebert-Haase Government will try to expedite the electionsc.2,    &apos;   The elections for the Constituent Assemblies ofthe separate States are beginning.  In Mecklenburg,.hitherto the most reactionary of all the States&apos;and without&apos;
ANY POPULAR REPRESENTATION,  A LARGE RADICAL(1..C,JJJN  -SOCIALIST) MAJORITY HA.&quot; BEEN RETURNED.  IN ANHALT-DESSAU, a PARTLY INDUSTRIAL  STATE, TIC MAJORITY IS MODERATESOCIALIST (EBER/B APD SCHEIDEMANN&apos;s PARTY).3,       STILL LEAVING THE ECONOMIC SITUATION  OUT of account, THERE BOOT TO BE CLEAR EVIDENCE THAT THE GREATMAJORITIES IN THE WORKMEN&apos;S AND SOLDIERS&apos; CO UNOILS,UNDER THE INFLUENCE MAINLY OF THE SOLDIERS, ARE STRONGLY INFAVOUR OF ORDERLY, CONSTRUCTIVE, REPUBLICAN CONSTITUTION-ALISM AND FEDERALISM.   THE IDEA OF A 5Unitarian&apos;  REPUBLICWITH ITS SEAT AT BERLIN HAS HITHERTO FOUND SUPPORT onlyIN SAXONY, AND EVEN THERE IT WOULD APPEAR TO BE YIELDINGTO THE GENERAL FEDERALIST TENDENCY,4.       GREAT CAUTION OUGHT TO BE EXERCISED IN the reaction OF REPORTS&apos;FROM NEUTRAL COUNTRIES REGARDING THESTRENGTH OF THE DISINTEGRATING, OR BOLSHEVIST, ELEMENTS,IN THE SITUATION.  IT IS NOTICEABLE IN PARTICULAR THAT THEZURICH TELEGRAMS TO            ^OF PARIS) WEAR A&quot;TENDEHCIOUS1 ASPECT.   THOSE WHO SUPPLY THESE TELEGRAMSMUST OONEEIVC IT TO BE IN THE INTEREST OF PRANCE THATGERMANY SHOULD LAPSE INTO A STATE OF ANARCHY - FOR A time at ANY RATE.;  THERE ARE TWO SECTIONS OF OPINION INFRANCE WHICH INCLINE TO this DESIRE.   THE first ISCHAUVINIST, IMPERIALIST AND ANNOXIONIST, WITHOUT EVENWORLDLY WISDOM.  IT WANTS AS MUCH OF GERMANY ON THE LEFTBARJT OF THE RHINE AS IT CAN GET, AND DOES NOT WANT GERMANYEVER AGAIN TO BECOME A GREAT EUROPEAN POWER.  THE OTHERSECTION IS AFRAID OF A SUCCESSFUL, PROGRESSIVE AND REALLYDEMOCRATIC GERMAN REPUBLIC.  IF THE GERMANS.- SUCCEEDED INORGANIZING A FEDERAL Republic ON A REALLY POPULARBASIS, AND PUT INTO THE ORGANIZATION OF THEIR DEMOCRACY ALL
 1                                                            21 all  the ability (some would add all  the  honesty)  which  used tc characterize^their semi-autocratic and wholly  bureaucratic Empire  before  the war;   if  they achieved as  great success in h organizing Labour in the  interest of the masses  and  of  renewed industrial prosperity,  .s they achieved  in the commroial and military spheres before the war,  the new German  Republic would soon contrast  v-ry favourably with France, and,  after due expiation,  might regain the good opinion of  the  world,  For it  is too  often forgotten that  in the &apos;eighties and  early Nineties, there was almost everywhere a chorus of  admiration fer  modern  -.germany,  and that not least in England and America, 5,        Disintegrating and destructive  elements undoubtedly exist.   The Spartacus. group led by Lieblcnecht  and Rosa  luxembourg - burg would not of itself  be formidable.   A man who celebrates. the  Revolution by establishing himself in the  Berlin Royal Castle  and sleeping in the  Kaiser&apos;s  bed,  as  Liebknecht  is reported to have done on  Novome. r 9,  must be nearly  as&quot; extra- vagant  and theatrical in  his methods as  the  Kaiser himself. That kind of conduct docs not commend itself to  the  German working man, who is serious and argumentative, and is distrust- ful  cf  extravagances and  eccentricities.   It is  rather  as a  - permanent point of crystallization for all discontented and disorderly elements that  the Spartacus ^joup my become dann;,rous.  That is what  happened on Friday, December 6, when a  report got abroad (enoourv?:ed by the imprudent overtures of  a demonstration  of soldiers outside Eberfs official residence) that Ebert contemplated allowing himself  to.  be elevated forthwit to the  Presidency of the  Republic,   All  opinion  which really counts  at the  moment -  that is to say, tho opinion which has behind  it the  votes of  the  majority  and  the  arms of  the soldiers is in favour of two things  (1) the General Gernjan Constituent Assembly,(2)the retention of the ultimate authority  and the pro-Visional representation of  the nation by  the collectivity of the                                                  /./orlemon1 s and
Soldiers1  (Councils, until the Constituent is elected anda stable 0&apos;OTran Federal G^vernmerVaetatlished on thef]s&amp;s of tine Majority of the Constituents&apos; views.6,          &quot;When it is reported that the Workmen1s and SoldiersCouncils will not be willing to surrender power and oontrolafter the Constituent has done itB work and has superseded themby establishing a Government capable of governing, these state-ments are bas^ on symptons and inferences which are not, sofar, convincing.  It is quite true that certain elements in the council&apos;s - a section of the workmen and the more extremeSocialist leaders like Richard MCLler, who signs with BrutusMoikenbuhr for the Executive Committee of the Berlin Workmen&apos;sand Soldiers&apos; Councils - cling to power.  They know or fear  .that the majority of the Constituent will not be even Socialistin colour, and they would fain insist that, before the Constituent assembles and establishes the Federal Republic, the presentholders of power should establish the Soc4Mist state by aseries ftf decrees in lieu of legislation,- It is also truethat a number of members of the Councils  cling to their pros-ent positions and the emoluments whioh they have voted them-selves.   On the other hand, it must not  be forgotten that,formally,at least -, though there are still frequent irregular-ities    the Berlin Councils have divested themselves of executive power, which they at first claimed and which .theywere sometimes e -ercising in a grotesque  enough fashion.Perhaps intld..fi Councils, or more or less irresponsible andarbitrary members of them, are still, here and there, inter-fsring with the administration.  It is reported that GeneralScheuch has resigned the portfolio of War because Socialistofficers refused to obey-orders, and because one of his directSubordinates was arrested and kept in prison in spite of theWar Minister&apos;s protests,  A representative of the Potsdam
259Workmen^and.. Soldiers&quot;-Counc 11 had also objected to theWar Office appointment of a Commandant ...f or&apos; Potsdam,......because he wanted the post himself.7.     Revolutions cannot be made with rose-water, and mani-festati.ons of this kind will continue unless, or until, theConstituent can establish a Constitute onal Republic and a stable government.  Ebert has declared his desire that theAll-German Congress of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils should&quot;draw a fcroad line&quot; against increasing attempts to cripple bymeans of brutal violence the State and Communal administrationsBut the only remedy for &quot;brutal violence&quot; is the exercise ofsuperior force.   It does not appear that the Ebert- HaaseGovernment is yet prepared to exercise the force which thevast majority of the troops now in and about Berlin is readyto place at their disposal.   A successful provisional Govern-ment like the Haase-Ebert  &quot;People&apos;s commission&apos; must be atonce disinterested and firm.  The Ebert-Haase combination isevidently unable to overcome its traditional party repugnanceto methods of force, and fears the groundless charge, v/hichthe Spartacus Group bring against it, of wanting to establish a reactionary personal dictatorship.   The force whichsuppressed with some bloodshed the Spartacus emeute of Friday,December 6, was not put in action by the Government.  Itconsisted of troops just home from the front, and now quarteredin the neighbourhood of Berlin.   The question whether thepreservation of orderm until order is firmly re-established on a constitutional basis, can be left with any confidence to the orderly portion of the troops, undirected by the Pro-visional Government, can only be decided by the event.  Thenext month or six weeks will decide the issue between order and anarchy.  Much will depend upon the economic situation,regarding which and its dangers another report has been presented..

</content>
</cab>
