<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/72/0 images: 433-434</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0.7^6568*          g A g   C A BIN F. T*          telegram from Lord Derby to Foreign Office,                                                POLITICAL.Decyplier.  Lord Derby (Paris) Decerabor 15th, 1918.           D.  10*58 pttma December 15th, 1918.           I-   8.0  a,nu December 16th, 1918ailOu 1779 (R) .      Your telegram Wo, 2 7  2,      Peaoe Conference.      Following is subs banco of note from ivlinistor  forForeign affairs.      Frenoh Jovernmont share  the view of &apos;..&apos;Ss kaJestyTsGovernment that it is important not to wound tho sus-coptibilities of our allies and our friends,      If you. accept the suggestion, minister for ForeignAffairs would bo prepared at once to give the followingindications to different parties interested^      Allied Great Powers will be invited to appoint 5plenipotentiaries, small jillier- Powers 3, now Statesrecognised as allies 2, States in course of formetion 1,neutral States 1,      Principles on which summonses v.ould be issued mightbe the following:-  Representative of Allied Great powers at all sittings and committee os;  small Allied Powersand new allied States to have  the right to be represented at all sittings at which questions concerning them are tobe discussed;   possible representation of States in courseof formation and neutral states at sumnons of Great Powers,at sittings devoted to discussion of tneir interests anddosiderata,     . In the opinion of Minister for Foreign hi fairs ques-tion of. presence of enemy delegates at sittings at whichare discussed  formulae to figure in  &apos;eace preliminariesdoes not arise,              *      allied -heat Powers will hove to discuss among thorn-selves question of allowing a M-latersl discussion of finalconditions of  treaty of perce.
      It   pears et, first  sigi:t that congress  should becoiDposoa of two phases.      (1)  The settlement  properly s talcing of  the war.      (2)  The eventual organisation of society of nations.      In the End phase the presence ol all belligerentsneutrals and new States seems justified,  since  accordingto its definition each otete will be oriled upon to par-tici^-to in this organisation oi future oesco between thonations,  minister for Foreign Affairs would be  giad to learn rhothor His uaLiesty&apos;s Government are in  agreementwith the French  Government on the above mentionedprinciples.

</content>
</cab>
