<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/72/0 images: 480-481</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel W. Dally Jones.

Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland.

This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.

?6586

FOOD PRODUCTION SCHEMES, IRELAND.

Memorandum prepared in compliance with Chief Secretary&apos;s Minute of 17th March, 1917.

Week ended ? December, 1918.

The following is a brief statement on the work of the Department during the past week in furtherance of increased Food Production in Ireland:-

LOANS FOR AGRICULTURAL IMPLEMENTS.

Seventeen applications for loans for agricultural implements were received by the Department during the past week. The total value of machinery ordered from the beginning of the present year, to date, under the Scheme, amounts to £106,387.

COMPULSORY TILLAGE.

Claims for the total or partial exemption of their holdings from the requirements of the Tillage (Ireland) General Order, 1919, are now being received from occupiers. The number of claims received so far, is, however,  very small.

PROGRESS OF FARM WORK.

Ploughing of lea and stubble was continued during the week so far as the weather, which was unfavourable, permitted.  Pulling of the turnip crop is being completed on many farms.

Complaints have been received from several counties of potatoes r?ting badly, and some sprouting in the pits is also reported.

The mildness of the weather has, up to the present, enabled farmers to economise considerably in the use of roots and fodder, with the result that there is little danger of  shortage in this respect.

1/1/10
FLAX.

Flaxseed (Ireland) Order, 1?18.

Five ? have been prosecuted during the season for accepting flax for scutching, without declarations from the growers that one-eighth of their crops had been reserved for seed. In view of the gravity of the offence the Department pressed for substantial penalties in each case, but notwithstanding this, in four cases the results of which have now been communicated to the Department, the fines inflicted were merely nominal, amounting in each case only to s.d. 2/6.

Scutchers&apos; Wages.

Scutchers in almost all mills are paid at the piece rate of ls. 7d. per stone. Their average weekly earnings vary from £2 to £3. Generally speaking, scutchers are content with their remuneration, but occasionally  strikes occur owing to a fall in earnings due to poor flax having been brought in for scutching. Disputes which have occurred have not, however, led to stoppages of long duration.

Disposal of Tow.

Owing to the dissatisfaction caused in recent years by the action of millowners in insisting on retaining their customers&apos; tow, the Department are making every endeavour to have the practice discontinued, now that it has been made illegal under the Scutchmills (Ireland) Order, 1918, Regulations.

MAINTENANCE OF LIVE STOCK.

During the period from 84th to 30th ultimo, inclusive,  230 applications for licences to slaughter or export heifers, 82 applications for licences to slaughter bulls or bullocks, 128 applications for licences to export milch cows, and 179 applications for licences to export store heifers and stripper cows, were received.

</content>
</cab>
