<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/72/0 images: 490-497</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ftlefhoitt: -VICTORIA 8210,Telegrams.--GROWMORK, SOWEST, LONDON.BOARD OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES.                                FOOD PRODUCTION  DEPARTMENT.                                           72,  VICTORIA STREET,                                                     LONDON,  S.W, (1).Reference No.............-------.,__,___                                            1st January,  1919,      Sir,                I beg to s\ibmit the following Report on the work of the      B&apos;ood Production Department for  the  fortnight  ended 31st December      1918s-                        Th e Wen th er and C ond iti on ^of C r 6ps.                Very little work on the land  was done  during -the closing      fortnight of the year.   Over the greater part of the country a      considerable amount of rain fell, and in the  north there was heavy-      snow at the beginning of the period.    In Wales  and  the north of      England a considerable area of  land was flooded.  On some of the      lighter lands, both ploughing ond sowing continued, however, apart      from the break for the holidays.    Autumn sown corn  looks well,      and the absence of severe weather has helped  farmers  to save feed-      ing stuffs and hay,                        LOCAL ORGANISATION DIVISION.                 Work of Agricultural Executive Committees.      Gloucestershire,  The Executive Committee have been  authorised to      take possession of 19 acres of neglected land at Winchcombe.      belonging to a widow who, owing to  lack of means, is  obliged to      work ns a dairy-woman on an adjacent farm.   The L?nd in question      is in the occupation of a man who pays  no rent for it and who      has neither the means nor ability to make it  productive.   Under      proper management the land Is capable of producing good cereal      crops, ond the Committee intend to  let  it to  a suitable tenant.   &quot;t avoid delay, address all cemmunicatitns to ;-*&apos;,&apos;   C A TUE DIJRBQTOR GENERAL.\
Herefordshire t  A farm of 24 acres near Vfnlford, partly  arableand partly pasture, came under the observation  of  the ExecutiveCommittee in September, 1917, and aa  in their opinion the  landVYPS not being  so cultivated as to increase  food production, an  Iorder was served by them on the owner-occupier  directing varioilPImprovements.   The owner did not carry out  these  instructions, Iand as in spite of a further order being  served; none of thework ordered in the notices was commenced,  the  Committeej  after an inspection by the Board&apos;s District Commissioner, have nowbeen authorised to take possession and to arrange  for the.cultt*vation of the farm under an experienced farmer.$93? $&amp;J!Qj.l*  The owner-occupier of a farm at Creech St, iviichahaving failed to harvest and carry the corn  crops  on certain ofhis fields, which had been ploughed in accordance  with an  orderserved by the Committee, was warned by them  that they wouldtake over the land themselves.   The owner failed  to do  asdirected,&apos;and the Committee have been authorised to takepossession and to let the land to a suitable tenant *^IEa L.^X.ii&apos;.?-iBS.&apos;  Action under the Rabbits Order and under  thePheasants Order is reported from Kent.Determination of Tenancies.  During the past fortnight 10  orders Ihave been made by the Board determining tenancies  on account of bad farming in respect of 756 acres.                     Land Drainage.Cumberland.  The Executive Committee have sent  to  the Board .&quot;1. rep Iof the work in the- last two years on the cleansing of natural and!artificial water courses.   Since the end of August,, 1917, when  Jnotices were first sent out, 1.34 miles have been dealt with byserving compulsory notices on the adjoining  occupiers to clennsethe channels, and the requirements of the notices  have in  themajority of cases been satisfactorily carried out.   Fourteen milhave also been cleaned out by voluntary agreement  among  those interested.    In addition to the above, about  12  miles  have beencleansed by soldier labour.   It is hoped thc*t the Committee maybe able to arrange for the installation of flap doors at tidaloutfalls where these are lacking.
                   HORTICULTURAL LIVISION. Provision  of  Land  for Allotments.  During the week ended 21st December 12 Local  Authorities agreed to acquire for allotments a  total of 154 acres, (2,255 allotments), including 110 acres at Walthamstow,          At  Hale  (Cheshire) 68$ of the 2,250 householders are cultivating either a garden of 250 sq. yards or an allotment of 300  sq. yards.   In addition the Local Council are cultivating 10 acres.           It is interesting to note that from the allotments in the  Beckenham area, the following quantities of produce have been obtained.                    Potatoes ,.,...,.800 tons.                    Onions ..........51  &quot;                    Cabbages ........250,000.          Eight appeals against notice to quit have been dealt with recently and in each case a continuance of the tenancy has been arranged.   These  appeals affected 211 allotment holders, cultivating an area of 27 acres, Fruit Section.   A very successful conference and public meeting was held in Norwich on the 21st Instant,  when the Departments proposals for securing a greater supply of fruit In this country were outlined.   The meeting was well  attended by all  the principal fruit growers in Norfolk. Bees.  Up to date  33 Bee Committees have  been formed in accordance with the Departments scheme for registration and &quot;re-stocking. Marketing Section.   Arrangements are being made in West Suffolk whereby it is hoped that the Framlngham TSgg  Collecting Society will be able to make arrangements for undertaking a Marketing Scheme in the county under the auspices of the Horticultural Sub-Committee.          A visit has Deen paid to the Cumberland Fruit and Vegetable Society and the  Central Depot has  been inspected.  The arrangements  made are excellent, and it Is hoped that  the Societywill meet a long felt want in the district.
 General.  Conferences have been held in Oxfordshire and Surrey, and the Departments Technical Inspectors have attended severe^ meetings of Horticultural Sub-Committees during the last fortni The Departments schemes for stimulating food production among! small cultivators were discussed and keen interest was shown in! the proposals.                         TECHNICAL DIVISION. Inspection of Land.   An inspection has  recently been made of Kettell&apos;s  Farm,  on the Southwold and Old Parks Kstate of Sir;Vauncey Crewe.    This farm which extends to  550 acres,  nearly j half  arable  was  taken over by the Leicestershire Executive Committee  last Spring,  after an inspection of the land had beer! made  by the  Technical Adviser.    In the  report then submitted (dated  4th December,  1917)  the  farm was  described as  being &quot;ini utterly neglected condition,  some of it  practically derelict. 1 smallest possible amount  of labour seems to  have been expended]-, much  of the  hay  was  either uncut  or not  carted,  and left to rotl in  the  fields.    The  hedges,  ditches  and drains  are in urgent I need  of attention,&quot;    Since the farnrwas&apos; taken over,  however, J great change  has h-.en effected, and it&apos;would&apos;bo, difficult  to  fig a more  striking  example  of  rapid  improvement-.    Most  of the crij obtained this year would  be regarded  as  quite  fair  even if the! land  had been in good condition to  begin with,  and  some of theng e,g.  the swedes,  potatoes,  and  part  of the corn,  are  as good  asI could be expected under any circumstances  from this class  of  If I                                              &apos;                 I Faggot, Draining.   Useful  information ,has  been obtained as the J result  of  an enquiry  into  the practice of  faggot  draining,  whiclwas at  one time  common, and is  still  carried  on  dn  some parts m the country.   It  is  proposed to  publish the  information in leaflet  form, as  in view of the scarcity and expense  of tile  1drains,  faggot draining could no  doubt be usefully  practised imconnection with many mole-draining  schemes.                   j
                   LABOUR DIVISION.Demobilisation.   The names of 7,990 agriculturists have beenforwarder1 to the Department of Demobilisation and Re-settlement for early release from the Colours as &quot;pivotal&quot; men in agriculture.Mo information has yeA been received that any of these men have actually been released.Soldier Labour.   The number of soldier ploughmen released bythe Military Authorities on agricultural furlough to assistwith autumn cultivations is now 7,,453  an increase of 1,5 2 duringthe last fortnight.  In addition 1,885 soldiers stated to havehad experience of threshing work are an agricultural leave,together with 668 soldiers still out to complete the harvestingof the small remaining area of potatoes not yet gathered.          Endeavours are being made to obtain the release onfurlough of any other agriculturists serving at home of whatevermedical category for  attachment  to Agricultural Companies, pendingthe issue of any general orders relating to demobilisation.   Inthis way, men will get out to work more quickly than If they waitto be demobilised, and this will materially assist farmers untilall farm workers have been released from the Colours.          Arrangements have been made for soldiers of AgriculturalCompanies to be demobilised,in the same way as other soldiers.In the meantime, in order to cause as little dislocation as possiblewhen general demobilisation begins, soldiers out on agriculture whowill not be remaining on farm Fork after being demobilised are beinggradually withdrawn as opportunity offers and other labour becomes available.   Similarly soldiers who will be remaining on farmwork are being transferred wherever possible to the farmer for whom they will work when demobilised.                           Fomen&apos;s branch.          There Is a surplus of women in the Land Army unemployed at the present time.   The Women^ War Agricultural Committees havebeen asked to review the cases of unemployed, women in order that
those not primarily suitable for agricultural work should be a 11 oweto withdraw.          Many members of the Land Army are expressing a desire totake up small holdings as soon as possible.  Others are eager to I-emigrate, and write urgent enquiries on the subject.   A carefulrecord is being kept of the desires expressed by individual workerAn enquiry has recently Oeen made of all in the Land Army as towhether they wish to continue permanently in land work or not.Some 6,500 answers have been received - 4,000 answer yes j and 2,50j          An Efficiency Test was held in Bedfordshire lust week.Out of four girls tested for horse work three obtained 100 per cenjend the fourth 95 per cent.    The farmer who was judging statedthat they were the best women he had seen for some time with horse!Those tested for milking also obtained a high percentage of marks,          An award of Good Service Hiboons and Distinguished ServiBars has recently been instituted for members of the Land Army.former is given after six months continuous satisfactory, service the latter only for special  acts of bravery or devotion to duty.                      CULTIVATION DIVISIONTreetor Scheme.  The following statement shows the position withregard to the provision of tractors, machinery and implements owns]by the Department for the two weeks ended 28th December, 1918.-No. consignedTotal NoTractorsduring fortnight.   with counties                        4,198(  5 withdrawn)Ploughs...............Cultivators 9/11 tine ,5,3311,472          Luring the two weeks ended 13th December, 17,599 acreswere ploughed, 65 acres were cross-ploughed, and 793 seres cultivslHorse Scheme.  26 Brood mares and 16 surplus Geldings were 3old ir]Northampton at an average price of  56, 10s. 6d, a horse, and 12horses in Westmorland at ^n average of  45.Steam Tackle.  The acreage dealt with during the p&amp;st two weeks ites follows:-  ploughed 2,033 acres, cultivated 12 acres, mole-   idrained 7 acres.   Total 2,052 acres.                            &quot;* 6 -A
                     SUPPLIES DIVISION,.Nitrate; of Soda.  Nitrate of soda from Government stocks is nowbeing  offered for sale through agricultural merchants at  20 perton delivered to purchasers nearest-station.   The sale ofnitrate of soda may result in a smaller demand for sulphate of -ammonia.Binder Twine.  The Hemp Controller has announced a reduction inthe price of hemp from  100 to  80 per ton, thus bringing theprice to rather less than that prevailing at this timo last yaer.If full effect were given to this reduction, the price of bindertwine to the farmer should fall to approximately  120 -  125 per ton.The stock of binder twine in.the hands of the Department is being offered at  136,15s. per ton net cash on January 31st, lessdiscount to dealers.   Statements are appearing in the press to theeffect that the Food Production Department has fixed the price for next season at  146.   This is entirely incorrect, and a press notice is being issued contradicting the statement, and advisingagricultural merchants and dealers to obtain quotations from different sources in order to buy in the cheapest market.          particulars are given belowi of the total amounts of seed potatoes and cereal seed distributed during the year ending 31stDecember, 1918.Seed Potatoes.           Distributed in England and Wales to Allotment Holders,                      Smallholders&quot;and FarmaraV             Varieties immune from If?art Disease .... 13^000 tons             Susceptible varieties .................  9,000  &quot;                                                     22,000  &quot;           Shipped to the British Expeditionary Force.             In France...........................9,000 tons             In Salonica...........................  .  200_^                                                      9,200  &quot;           To Allied Governments.................... JLLI500  &quot;                                          Total.     32,800 tons.. 7 -
     Cereal Seeds.              Seed Wheat..............................  8,700 qrs.              Seed Oats   ............................. 29,700  &quot;              Maize,  (South African Flat White)  ......  4,100  &quot;     Export of Seed Oats from Scotland to England.  Licences were iss     for the removal of 335,800 qrs.     y/art Disease.  During the year the whole of  the counties in Engle     and Wales have been surveyed with care in order to ascertain to     what extent Wart  Disease is prevalent.  As a result of this surve     and of information previously obtained, 68 districts have been     certified as Infected Areas under the Wart Disease of Potatoes Or     1918.  Among the  most Important are (1) a district including the     county of Glamorgan and parts of the counties of Monmouth, Carmar     and Brecon;  (2)  the whole of the district of Lancashire south of     River Ribblo;  (3) a number of parishes in the county of Nottingh     and In parts of Derbyshire.  It has a.lso been decided that the wh     of the county of  Staffordshire should.become an Infected Area as     tho 1st January,  1920.     Spraying Potatoes.  During the year considerably more&quot;attention h     been directed to  the spraying of farm crops  and the uae of horse-     drawn machines, with the result that the acreage actually sprayed*     under the supervision of the Board1s officers was very substantia     increased as compared with the area of potatoes sprayed in 1917.              Trials  and demonstrations were carefully planned and     organised, and the results have now boon tabulated and will form     subject of a report.  The evidence, so far as it can be judged, g     tc show conclusively that there is a definite gain in yield in al     cases where potatoes arc sprayed with a properly prepared mixture     and where the fluid is properly applied.                                 I am, - Jl         :     ;;v  1&apos; \ : &quot; ) ;;   1   1 - &apos;  Sir, :                                          Your obedient Servant,                   -   !-                            Director-General.Tho  Rt. Hon. Rowland  E. Prothoro, M.P.,       President of tho Board of Agriculture                         and Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
