<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/31/0 images: 16-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Pocuriierftfo the Property ofH?s Britannic sfeajesty^ Ccv-rnment;PLEASE ATI&apos;ACiJ TO K5..PORT XLII*
4451  1269/G91  10,000  10/17  J. P.   Gp. 158Circular No. 28.MINISTRY  OF  PENSIONS,Westminster House,Millbank, S.W. 1.-   29fch October, 1917.TRAINING OF DISABLED MEN IN MUNITIONS WORK.Sir,I am directed by the Minister of Pensions to inform you that he has been, in communication with the Ministry of Munitions in regard to the training of discharged partially disabled sailors and soldiers in the manufacture of munitions. Particulars of the arrangements agreed upon are given below,-and the information herein contained supersedes that given in Circular 23 of the War Pensions, &amp;c, Statutory Committee.The training of men for the production of munitions is not usually a form of training which the Minister regards as within the scope of Article 6 of the Ptoyal Warrant, since it is not intended to provide the man with a permanent livelihood, and the training given is usually of too short and of too specialised a character to give the man such a start as will of itself enable him to find employment readily after the War. The production of. munitions is, however, imperatively demanded by present circumstances, and accordingly the Training Department of the Ministry of Munitions have established Training Centres throughout the country, and they have expressed their willingness to receive for training at these centres such discharged sailors and soldiers as are physically capable of working under normal factory conditions. Men will be considered particularly suitable if they have in the past been skilled artisans in the engineering trades and can bring to the work the experience and knowledge previously gained as skilled craftsmen.
When a Local Committee receives au application from a man who desires to undergo this training and appears to be able to undertake the work, the Committee should make an application on his behalf to the Secretary of the Training Section of the Ministry of Munitions, 6, Whitehall Gardens. London, S.W. 1., who will make the necessary arrangements for him to be interviewed and for his training if he is considered suitable. The Ministry of Munitions will also send to the Local Committee a notification of the amount of the grant made to him by them during the period of training.The Ministry of Munitions have also agreed to instruct all their Training Centres that the names and addresses of all discharged disabled sailors and soldiers who are sent to a Training Centre otherwise than on the recommendation of the Local Committee, should be notified by the Principal of the Institute to the Local Committee immediately upon the man being accepted as a suitable pupil.It is the general practice of the Ministry of Munitions to pay an allowance of  2 per week during the course of training, and no maintenance allowance can be paid either to the man or his dependants by the Local Committee, but he will continue to draw his pension.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,Secretary.The Secretary,Local War Pensions Committee.
Fens i pels .Number Qf PensIflttfi.-    The number of pensions granted during^iie week to officers and men, and to widows, children and dependantsweek before.     since the beginning of the war $22,696 penolons,Appendix II shows that la3t week 29 grants of supplementary pen&amp;Itns and special allowances were made by the Special Grants Committee against 51 in the previous week, The total number to date, including,.grants by the former Statutory Committee, is 4,675.2. Pensions to Soldiers. The number of fresh claims to pension of disabled soldiers dealt with by the Awards to Soldiers. Branch during the week ending 2nd November was 6,000 - including 311 which had been rejected under previous Warrants. - as oompared with a,300 during the previous week, and 8,000 during the week before..tf pension, permanent tr temporary, and 1,819 by the grant of gratuities, and in 32 cases the claims were rejected.     Claims which had previously been rejected under former Warrants were admitted in 311 cases, 291 of the men being granted gratuities and 20 pensions, -   The total number of claims previously rejected which have been dealt with up to date Xn &apos;12,6.11 of which 1,231 have been met by the award of pension and 11,380 &quot;By gratuities.S* Questioning Disabled men as to Earnings.   To prevent  pprehensitn on the part of disabled men that increased earning power due to training will interfere with their pension Article 5(Appendix I) v/as 14,933 against 15,045 last week and 15,847 theincluding children1s allowances, have been awarded.Of the $,000 cases 4,149 were disposed tf by the awardcfperi6d frcm 27th October te 2nd November, 1917.MINISTRY OF PENSIONSCONFIDE HE IAL.
of the Royal Warrant expressly lays it down that when apermanent pension has been granted it shall net toe altered onaccount of any change in a man:s earning capacity, whetherresulting from training or other cause, and on this point, inall its leaflets and posters, the Ministry lays great insistence,It has, however) been brought to notice that Medical Boards inexamining, men far pension purposes are in the habit, of making toenquiries/as the s.Qtual earnings ^f the man,     This practice,to bp contraryA,G.X. 1615 ([Appendix III) declares/to present policy and directs its discontinuance.4, Pensions to Widows and Dependants. The work of awarding and authorising payment of Widows and Dependants pensions in current . oases is completely up to date.1,248 re-assessments of dependants pensions were made during the week against 1,C67 last week and 1^654 the weok before. There remain  57 cases to toe dealt with.     In many of these the dependant has   not yet: returned the form sent for completion; in the remainder t$ere is difficulty in obtaining necessary documents from the War* Off ice or. Paymasters..     Steps are toeing taken tt expedite matters and it is hoped to complete the re-assessment at a very early date.     (Appendix IV),    The 1,248 cases this week include 53 dependants^penBiendd under the 3id Warrant who have benefitted toy the reassessment to the average extent of 4/5 a week, and 697 dependant parents whose cases had toeen settled by a gratuity under the Old Warrant but have now been, placed en pension at an average rate af 8/3 a week.    The rest of the 1,24a receive nc benefit, their pensions already being equal to pre-war dependance,As a result of the week&apos;s re examinations as to entitlement under the New Warrant 1 widow^not previously helped has been admitted to full pension, and 2 to temporary pension, 5 (widows and dependants) remain to be dealt with cut of the original total of 4,722. (Appendix V),
5t pension to Parents, Now Scheme.   995 Parents1 pensions of loss than 3/6d. have been increased during the week jto that amount with effect from the 1st September, 1917.    The average rate of increase is l/&quot; a *eelC4    The total number of increases to 5/Sd. is now 5,974,5. Forfeitures, &amp;c. of Widows1 Pensions,The report on Forfeitures, occ,, of Widows&apos; pensionsfor the month of October gives the following figures:-From Commence-Pensions forfeited During October  ment of Statra-tcry Committee.Pensions forfeited f   21 195.Gratuities forfeited 8 S5-Pensions administered in trust 14 ftlPensions restored 5 60Pensions suspended 6No action W 337The &quot;No action&quot; cases include those where the evidenceis insufficient to require forfeiture, but sufficient to makefurther reports desirable.7. Pensions Appeal Tribunal. 1,198 Appeal forms had been received by the 51st Cctiber, an increase of 116 since the 17th October, Cf these cases 633 have been finally disposed of.     I gre cases have been considered by the Tribunal than appear in the Appendix VI hereto attached bat- the official record of decisions has not yet been received.,     The Tribunal will sit at Edinburgh from the 5th to the 9th November for the purpose of hearing appeals from residing in Scotland. Retired Pay ef Army Officers, &amp;c.   The following is a summary of the progress made in the review of cases under the Officers Warrant of the 1st August, 1917,officers.   Retired pay has been re-examined in 713 cases, of which 566 have received increased rates, the average increase being  30 a year.     About QZf remain to be re-examined, 28 Officers &quot;slightly impaired&quot; have been placed on retired pay in lieu of gratuities previously granted and a have had theirgratuities * -
gratuities increased by an average amount of  37, 52 gratuities in non-attributable cases have been increased the average increase being  48, 12 gratuities of an average amount of  44 have been awarded where no previous grant was admissible.Nurses. 53 have had their pensions increased, the average increase being  51, one &quot;slightly impaired&quot; has been granted a pension in lieu of gratuity previously awarded and 4 have received increased gratuities the average increase being 33.Widows and Children.   Intermediate pensions have been re-examined in 120 cases af which 58 widows have had their pensions increased tt the highest rate, the average increase being  39.     About 13.&amp; remain to be re-examined.     Ordinary pensions have been re-examined in 6 cases, 5. of which have been ralsel to the Intermediate rate the average increase being  49. Abi*ut 144 remain to be re-examined,     154 Children1 s allowances (intermediate and ordinary) have been re-examined cf which 76 have been Increased, the average increase being  6,     About 386 remain to be re-examined.12 Widows who had previously been granted gratuities where no pension was previously admissible have been granted pension at the intermediate rate; about 90 remain to be re-examined, 12 children in these cases have also been granted an allowance.Other relatives.     Progress is now being made with the re-examination of these cases and awards will begin to be made very shortly.Retired Pay pg Navy Officers,     Under the Order in Council of 29th September, 1917, 92 cases of Naval Officers (including Warrant Officers) have been re-examined of which 86 have received increased retired pay, the average increase being  29. About 148 remain tc be examined.Three gratuities of an average amount cf  77 have been awarded where no previous grant was admissible.
Treatment g9.   gharggs for trocggiggfc og ai^oli^^d men .tr-^spitaga^    As -a. result of the meeting of the British Hospitals AssocUtivOA-iarito 19th ultimo, which wa3 referred to in the weekly Report for the 23rd ultimo, the Llinister has been asked to receive a deputation fr9m the Association in order t6       before him their claims for an increoso in the Qharges payable by the i/dnistry for discharged men in civil-hospitals.    The claim of the Assrciaticn is twqfoid, namely: -(a) that the terms of remuneration fer maintenance *frem.  in SehMule I to the Instructions of the Ministry are tos low and do not/ in fact/ meet the cost s$f treatment: (h) that these terms should be .increased to include remuneration fcr the doctors in addition to the ordinary charges for maintenance,. As the War Office were also Doing approached by the Association on the same subject,, the Llinlster considered that the tffg departments should deal jointly with the issues raised and after a preliminary discussion with Sir Alfred Ke2^). it was suggested to Lord Derby that he and the liinixter should see the deputation together,3iC, Medioai referees. The Committee sf Selection fcr the appoint-ment of Medical Referees held a further meeting this week and agreed yti recommendations to the Minister for the appointment of 33 Iviedlcal practitioners for the County of London,     It is proposed t* proceed with the appointment of iledioai Referees for Scotland at an early date and for this peruse to ask the Local Government Board, the Insurance Commissioners and the Scottish Medical Services Emergency Committee tc nominate representatives to a email committee of Selection on the same lines as have been % adopted for England and Wales.     The Committee would meet in Edinburgh,    A copy of the form of iledical Certificate for the use af Lfedical Referees II given in Appendix VII.
11. Payment of Pensions during treatment la &amp; Poor Law Institution,, Reference has been made in previous reports to Conferences which have taken place between the Ministry, the War Office, Admiralty and Looal Government Board as to the best method of dealing with Separation Allowance or pension during any period when the beneficiary is in receipt of treatment in a Poor Law Institution. As a result of these Conferences a memorandum 7/as submitted to the War Cabinet andconsidered by them on the 24th October when the reoommendations of the Conference wore adopted and instructions given to carry them into effect.     The Departments and branches of the Ministry concerned have been notified accordingly and the neoessary instructions will be sent at once tc Local Committees. 12tDocentralization of the payment of s.llov;ancesj in certain cases of treatmentt     Under the Instructions for the Treatment and Training issued by the Ministry, prevision was made that any oases where the Ministry procured the admission by direct arrangement of a man to certain classes of institution the allow-ances payable during treatment were tc be paid by the Pension Issue Office,    The cases referred to are those where men require tc be sent tc one or other of the orthopaedic centres and where a man suffering from tuberculosis is on discharge from Military Service admitted direct to a sanatorium through the Insurance Commissioners.     Provision for central payment was adopted in the Instructions in the view that it would assist Local Committees who had not up to the present time been in the habit of lealing by way of allowances with such cases and might not ascertain in time that the man had been so dealt with. Complaints have, however, arisen that the system is net working well and that there is delay in the payment of allowances owing partly to the difficulty of ascertaining in time the manfs family circumstances, e.g., names and address of his family and dependants^    &apos; It is now proposed, therefore, tc decentralizepayment
; 22I  ypayment * &apos;&quot;&apos;allowances ia. ail possible cases and to require Local Committees to undertake the work,13,   Joint Committee on Institutional Treatment.   The twenty-seventh meeting of the Committee was held on November 1st.     A report which is given in Appendix IX contains a useful summary of the provision made for Institutions for Neurasthenia and Tuberculosis which hGvs been or are proposed      be provided. 24, Orthopaedic treatment.   Representations have been made to the Minister from several quarters that discharged men requiring Orthopaedic treatment experience difficulty and delay In obtaining admission to the orthopaedic centres.     These centres which number at the present time 12 and will shortly number 14 are primarily, of course, for the service of undischarged soldiers ahd discharged men who require treatment at a centre are usually admitted on the footing of cut-patients though a certain number are found from tjJme to time to require in-patient treatment.The liinistry have been in consultation with Sir Robert Jones, Inspector of Military Orthopaedics, with a view, to increae-ing the provision made for orthopaedic treatment,     In accordance with his recommendation it is proposed to establish in the first instance sub-centres or annexes to a certain number of the princip&amp;j orthopaedic centres at which out-patient treatment only will be given.    These eub-centres or annexes would be in the largo towns and situated perhaps at a distance of a mile or two from the principal centre, but s$fficiently near to be visited frequently by the Officer In Charge fcf the centre.     It is possible, however, that sub-centres may be fgund necessary in districts remote from one cf the principal centres,     A Circular has been addressed t* the representatives of the Ministry in each Joint Committee Area requesting them to consult their Local Committees and the Joint Committee as %Q the most suitable districts in which to place one Of these sub-centres and Sir Robert Jones has been asked to furnish an estimate of the cost and nature of the equipmentrequired
urequired by the Sub-Centre and the medical staff and number of attendants necessary.15, Lunacy.   A copy of the Instruction issued by the Board of Control, Superintendent of Asylums, referred to in last week!s report is given as Appendix X.     Notification is being sent by the Ministry to Local V/ar Pensions Committees. 16, Treatment of the Deaf.   In the Report for the week ending the 29th June last reference was made to the decision of the Health Sdction of the Statutory Committee to form a Special Aural Board to examine all disabled deaf men and to advise as to their treatment and training.     Dr. Dundas Grant was asked to become President, of this Board and the Report for the following week oontains a letter putting him in posaftteaien fcf the views of the Ministry.    A conference followed (paragraph 1C of Report for week ending 20th July) and in the result a Special Aural Board was formed of five leading aural surgeons and a lip-reading specialist for London, the intention being to extend the operation of this Board all over the country by the creation of beards associated with it in the areas of the various Joint (Disablement) Committees   These B.oard3 consist of two or more of the leading aurists in the areas with a lip-reading specialist selected by the Beard of Education.     The duty of the     Beards will be to determine the treatment or lip-reading training required by any deaf disabled man sent by Medical Boards or Joint Disablement Committees, and also to make recommendations in the question of pension in cases so sent tc them.     Boards have been established for the London area, the North-west area (Lancashire, Westmoreland and Cheshire) and the Yorkshire area and also for Scotland.     For lip-reading training classes have been or are being established by the Beard of Education wherever sufficient men are found who are certified to require lip-reading training and are willing to take it.     Classes are now going on in London and Lancashire and will shortly beresumed
resumed in Edinburgh- and started In Doncaster, while arrangements are being made at a number of other centres.     For treatment special arrangements have been made in London by the establishment c  three Aural Clinics, one in the centre, one in the East and one in the West of London,     A similar clinic will be established in any centre of peculation where it is found to be necessary.In order that the deaf men requiring either treatment training might be got hold of, Local Committees were circularised by the Statutory Committee on the 6th July last, but as this did nbt result in any large number of names being obtained an examination has been made of the files in the Pensions Awards Branches of the Ministry and all cases of deaf soldiers and sailors from the beginning of 1916 have been picked out.     The names and addresses cf the men residing in each Joint Disablement Committee area have been sent to that Committee and similar lists are now cent.- month by month..Where, apart frem the arrangements above reoorded, individual cases of deaf disabled men requiring lip-reading training come to notice, special arrangements are made with the Board of Education for doing what is necessary.The specialists doing work for the Ministry are the leading aural surgeons and lip-reading specialists cf the country and where the arrangements are complete as in London which contains about a quarter of the total number of cases, any deaf disabled man who comes forward can receive absolutely the best treatment and. ,.   training that the country can offer and apart from this every effort is made by hunting up cases to get him to come forward.     Appendix XI gives the report of the Special Aural Board for London for the month of October,The &quot;Frederick uilner&quot; Hostels have been established b-y Sir Frederick. Llilner with the assistance of ;ir. Wilson, both men suffering from the severe disability of deafness.     They are mainly intended to provide for the social needs of the deaf soldiers and sailors, and, by giving an agreeable environment to thetreatment
treatment and training to add to the number of men who will consent to undergo these.   At present it is believed that there is only one such hostel at 26, Wilton Street, in London and on the suggestion of Mr. Wilson fehs London lip-reading classes wercr transferred there from Fitzroy Square and arrangements were made for the special Aural Board to hold their weekly meetings there. It is understood to be in contemplation to establish a similar hostel in Edinburgh and it is believed that Ivir. Wilson has been in communication with various persons with a view to the establishment of hostels for deaf disabled men in the great centres *f population.     It is sery doubtful how far they will be neoessary or advisable.     Deaf disabled men when onoe trained in lip-reading will not be isolated from the rest of the community and should not desire to congregate together.   Though the total number of eases in which men have been invalided from the Army and Navy is considerable (4,795 up to 30t&amp; Sepilember) a great number of these have either wholly or partially recovered and the numbers in any particular town will not be considerable. 17. Dental Treatment.   Reference has been made in previous reports to the prevision of dental treatment for discharged disabled men.     It is now proposed to issue to Local Committees the Instruction and form of application for such treatment given in Appendix XII,1&amp;. General Schemes cf treatment. Appendix XIII contains a report on the general schemes of treatment submitted end sanctioned during the week.     The cemprehensiso arrangements made by the Joint Committee of Bucks., Hants. and Oxford, and by the Kent Local Committee may be noticed,A Circular urging on all Local Committee the cempleti of their arrangements is now being sent out,19* ^vi^ual Cases of Treatment.   The great bulk of cases of treatment are under general schemes which have received approval,buton
but a small number of cases requiring special treatment or treatment in institutions for which approval has not previously been given are submitted each week.     During the week ended 51st October 92 such cases were so sanctioned.20, Numbers under Treatment.   Appendix XIV shows the number of men for whom treatment has been provided under arrangements made or approved by the Ministry and to whom allowances under   Article 6 of the Royal Warrant are payable.     It will be seen that 350 cases were admitted for treatment during the week ended 31st October and that 2,434 men were under treatment cn that date, as compared with 2,198 men at the end of the previous week.The Table shews also the nature of the disablements for which treatment was required, and it will be seen that more than two-fifths of the cases are of wounds cr injuries, 3,75 per cent being cases of paraplegia.     97 cases of neurasthenia are under treatment at holders Green and 32 of advanced tuberculosis in the hospitals t  the metropolitan Asylums Board in London.The number of discharged men in Lunatic asylums who have been admitted to the benefit of the special arrangements for &quot;Service Patients&quot; referred to in previous reports was, on the 31st October 729.     Of these 88 had been admitted during the week.21 * Treatment of Offioers,     Since the last report cf the Committee the War Office has been approached with reference to A.C.I, 1424 which deals with the admission to Military Hospitals of officers not on the Active list and the proposal has fceen made to the War Office that all applications from officers to be dealt with under this A.CI, shall be submitted t6 Sir Alfred Pearce Gould for his approval.During October 37 applications have been received for treatment and medical expenses mostly already incurred; in 10 cases a decision has been reached and the necessary action is being taken.Training
Training and- Employment.22( Training in Munition Work.     A Circular (No. 28) has been issued to Local Committees drawing their attention to the facilities afforded by the Minister of liunitions for training and rate of remuneration being paid during training.     It also points rut the steps that are to be taken to keep Local Committees informed of the men who are accepted by the Minister of Munitions for training at either cf their special training centres.     The Circular is given as Appendix XV, 23, The Cheshire Agricultural College.   This college at Holmes Chapel has been inspected by the Director of Training accompanied by the representatives from Cheshire and Lancashire on the 21st October.     His report is annexed as Appendix XVI.It recommends the taking over of the college by the Ministry for the trailing &amp;f disabled soldiers in agricultural pursuits and is under consideration.24. Training in Cheshire.   The Cheshire Joint Committee have now appointed a special Sub-Committee with the view of formulating schemes of training within the area so as not to depend entirely on the training facilities of Lancashire as hitherto.     This Committee meets next week to draw up their scheme. 25* Hostel at Sheffield6   Sheffield has been visited during the week by the Director of Training at the request of the Lord Mayor and as a result of a conference it is probable that a special Training Hostel on the lines of the Cowen Home, Newcastle, will be established.     The acquisition of an excellent housy on the outskirts of the twn with residential accommodation for 35 residents and training accommodation for ICC wen is under consideration.The Vice Chancellor of the University wag: also interview-ed and he is formulating a scheme cf training at the University inmore
more advanced and professional branchep of study to meet the demands of the better educated type of man desirous cf and suitable for more advanced courses of study.     These courses will be open to men from any part of the Country. 26. Diamond Cutting at Brighton,   The new workshops for exnension of the Diamond Cutting, Training Classes at the Technical College at Brighton,will be completed this week and 23 additional men making 45 in all will be in training on H^nday next.     As soon as the new premises that have been acquired olose to the training classes are completed accommodation for the training of some 500 men will be available.27* Trade Advisory Committees.   Appendix XVII contains a report of meetings held during the week ended the 31st October by the Trade Advisory Committees representing the General Engineering, Printing and the Basket, Skip and Hamper Trades, various schemes were approved,28. Schemes of graining.   Appendix XVIII is a note on schemes of training submitted to the ilinistry during the week from Newcastle, Brighton, Bradford, Plymouth, Midland Ireland and the Western Counties.29. Individual Cases of Training.   Turing the week 102 cases oftraining autside approved schemes were sanctioned.     In 105 casesfurther information was asked for or a modification of theandoriginal proposals suggested/in 12 oases where direct application was received reference was made to the Local Committee for enquiry.50* Number of ;.ien under Training,   Appendix XIX shows that 44 men were admitted tu and 1  discharged from training by Local Committees during the week and that the total number reported an under training at the end of the week was 652. 31* Interned Prisoners in Switzerland,   Instructors in leather work, wood work, electrical, motor mechanics and tailCring have been sent out to conduct special courses of training amongst themen
^en interned in Switzerland.     A report has been received stating that these instructors are visiting the various camps and selecting&apos; suitable men for training.     In most cases arrangements have been made wita firms in England to give employment to all these men who complete their training when they return to this country.     In the cases of the wood and leather work, the firms 0f Messrs. Brinsmead and of Worrall &amp; Company have agreed to provide at their own expense the cost of these classes and have sent out thei:? own instructors and will pay the men in training for whatever wcrk they do.    The &quot;Auto Car&quot; have agreed to pay the expenses ( .600 per annum) for the cost cf the ilctor liechanics Courses and the Army Clothing department have provided all the tools and materials for the employment of from *C to 60 men. Other firms art. offering similar facilities as the opportunity arises32, Training c  Officers.      During the course of the past month progress has been made in pbtainin^ information from the Universities and fther educational bodies regarding courses of instruction suitable for disabled officers,     34 of fleers have- -applied for trcining, 23 of these seem suitable cases and enquiries are being made as to the prospect of their getting employment,     92 other officers who are considered litoly to benefit by training have teen communicated with, 30 applications, for training have been received and enquiry is being made inti; 23 oases vrtiich seemed prima facie suitable.Ehe employment Register of the ilinistry of labour reports that during October 73 applications for employment have been received through this Department, that 42 applicants have been P^ced. and that 765 cases remain upon the Register.St.
ORGANIZATION.33m   RepTts of Inspectors.   Extracts from reports of Inspectors&apos; n  Acc&amp;unts for the week ended 31st October are contained in Appendix XX.   From the Northumberland Sub-Committee at Earsdon, all of whose members are either miners or connected with mining, comes an encouraging report.   In the West Riding the Keighley Local Committee are working well, Halifax continues its good record and gives special attention to disabled men, Leeds has passed satisfactorily and most searching audit, and Barns ley gives better . promise for the future.   In the North Weot Area the Middleton Committee appear to be making emergency grants too freelyj out of three Branch Committees of the Lancashire Local Committee tt?o are doing good work whilst the third is shortly to be re-inspected.   In the West Midlands the visitors of the Smethwick Committee are in good touch with their oases and the labour trouble feared by the Inspector in March last (Report for week ending 23rd March) is net referred to;   to the Stoke-on-Trent Committee (whose two previous reports have been bad) the Inspector says he spoke very frankly and steps are being taken towards improvement.Of Clackmannanshire there is nothing to report, 34,   Special Grants Committee.   A meeting of the Special Grants Committee was held ^n the 16th October.   The Minutes of this meeting are annexed as Appendix XXJi   The Committee approved a scheme formulating the procedure m cases involving the forfeiture of separation allowances and pensions.   They also approved a circular letter to the Local Committees suggesting the practice which should be fallowed in such cases.   The procedure adopted is not only generous but tactful and sympathetic;   it aims at a fair treatment of the woman, the best provision for any children, the avoidance as much as possible of publicity and the minimum of pain to the persons involved.A resolution was passed that where proper clothes were a necessity for a child a grant up to  5 might be regarded as part of the expenses of eduoation,
The Committee requested their Secretary (l)   to inform the Ministry that they view with grave concern the delay in dealing with the proposed Regulations for Officers and the Amendments to Part I of the Regulations and (2) to point out to the Ministry that the present practise in dealing with Parents Special pensions is productive of delay, cost and serious irritation to Local Committees,    The representatives of Local Committees or the Committee added that Local Committees are being sorely tried by the amount of work asked of them and suggested fewer forms; they also referred to delays,35,   Representation of Discharged Disabled men an LocalCommittees.      The Naval &amp; Military War Pensions, Sec,, (Local Committees) Bill referred to in last week&apos;s report was read a 2nd time on the 29th October,     In explaining the object of the Bill the Parliamentary Secretary stated that the representative on the Local Committee would be a man who had been actually discharged in the present war and he pointed out that the exact methods by which a man would be appointed could not be laid down but that it would be left to each Committee to devise the manner of appointment.     In debate the principle of the Bill was, In a small house, universally welcomed but three points were taken. First the Government were asked to make the language of the Bill absolutely clear so that there could be no doubt that the representative must be a man who has been actually discharged and not merely a person who was only interested, in discharged men; secondly the Government were pressed to substitute for the words &quot;at least one representative&quot; the rc-ords &quot;at least two representa-tives&quot;; and thirdly most of the speakers urged that one of the representatives should be a war widow.     In reply the Parliamen-tary Secretary reiterated that the representations meant was a discharged man and added that the Government were quite willing to consider any amendments set down,
36.   Visit of Parliamentary Secretary,to Cardiff.      Oonference with Joint Committee for the South Vfeles Area.     At a conference with this Joint Committee at Cardiff on the 26th October the Parliamentary Secretary addressed the Committee on the Ministry1 s attitude with regard to Pensions, treatment and training and explained the duties of the Joint Committee in relation to the ,&apos;Looal Committees within the Area.     Various speakers then gave their views on the needs of the Joint Committee.     They complained of being always met by trifling difficulties which they had no authority to deal with, they urged that unless they were given more administrative power the system was valueless, they firmly believed in the Joint Area System  but they claimed larger powers and some authority in the direction of expenditure, and they called for further provision for neuresthenics and Tuberculosis schemes. Their demands came under three broad principles(1) there was not enough elasticity in the Regulations.(2) the funds for institutions should be provided by the State and the Joint Area Committees should administer them in their respected areas, and(3) there was a great need for convalseent institutions and technical training.In reply the Parliamentary Secretary stated that the Ministry was determined to decentralize as far as possible that certain of the points discussed were under consideration and suggested that the Committee should put forward an institutional scheme and should show its necessity, but that the Ministry could only deal with advanced cases of tuberculosis and be touched on the question of convalscent homes.Deputations and Meetings.     In the evening the Parliamentary Secretary received deputations from the Cardiff Association of Discharged Soldiers and Sailors and from the Pontypridd Local Committee and he answered and explained a number of questions.
Later in the evening he addressed a public meeting at the City Hall and subsequently attended an Informal meeting to discuss the facilities for the treatment of tuberculosis in Wales.Visits to Hospitals.     On the 27th October the Parliamentary Secretary inspected the Welsh Metropolitan War Hospital v/here he addressed the patients on the Ministry^ anxiety for the welfare of disabled men*     He also inspected the Prince (bf Wales Hospital for limbless men and the 3rd Western General Hospital.     A note on the visit is attached as Appendix.57*&apos;: Intelligence Notes.        A statement from the Intelligence Department, attached as Appendix XXII. gives information as to what is being done elsewhere.     It contains a note on the 3rd report of the Patriotic Association of Newfoundland where it is proposed to adopt the Canadian Pension rates, a summary of the French Law providing for the guardianship of children whose parents have-been killed or injured as a result of the war, an account of the proposed pension registration in the United States, and notices of reports from Germany on unemployed war-disabled men and on loans for the purpose of reinstating disabled men In their former trade or profession.The most Interesting item in the United States Bill Is the scheme for Government insurance with the premium, paid in part by the State and in part &amp;j the Insured,     This scheme is based on the existing Act passed in 1914 providing V/ar Risk Insurance for the benefit of seamen and the Merchant service.     Under the Bill as it stands application to come under the scheme must be made within the first 120 days after entrance into the service.     The scale of compensation provided in the Bill is higher than with us but there is, apparently, nc provision for supplementation of pensions and allowances.
38.   War Pensions Gazette.      In the 7th issue of this Gazette (Appendix XXIII ) Mrs McKenna in a leading article deals with provision for the day-care of children of women workers and urges that expert advice as to the care and treatment of children should be placed at the disposal of mothers.,     The Gazette also contains a portion of an admirable address to soldiers on their discharge, a useful account of the work of the Local Committee of Dumfriesshire, and a letter from the Ministry on the subject of the supply of artificial limbs to disabled soldiers.Staff etc39*   Numbers of Staff.      Appendix XXIV shows an addition of 38 to the staff of the Ministry during the $eek, 23 having been added to the Awards to Soldiers Branch, 8 to the Administration Branch and 10 to the Pensions Issue Office whilst there have been some decreases.     The staff on the books of the Ministry now comprises 275 men and 4,550 women, or 4825 In all, 40,   Sick percentage. The daily percentage of absences during the week was 4- among   the male and 5*4 among the female staff.MATTHEW NATHAN.3rd November, 1917.
Summary of Pensions and Allov/anees granted to Soldiers and Sailors Disabled and to the \:&apos;idov;s,Children and other Dependants of Soldiers and Sailors Deceased.period.	Officers Lien and Nurses *	Vlidows * -	Children*	1 Dependants u	Total.	I Period,   j	Officers len and Hur sos?	1 \7idowa *	Children* 1	Dependants. *	TotalScrtal from 3-6/2/17 to 29/3/17 for ?reek end-ing 5/9/17	74,127 3,857	29,735 847	130,296 5,364	49,516 2,567	283,674 12,635	Prom beginning of vrai4 to 5/9/17]	217,261	93,876	417,392	80,771	809,30012/9/17	4,404	865	5,965	2,404	13,638	&quot;12/9/17 i	221,665	94,741	423,357	83,175	822,93819/9/17	3,762	977	5,976	2,143	12.858	&quot; 19/9/17	225,427	95,718	429,333	85^318	835,79626/9/17	4,215	668	6,041	3,058	13,982	&quot;26/9/17	229,642	96,386	435,374	88,376	849,7785/l0/l7	3,843	604	5,629	2,721	12,797	&quot;2/10/17	233,485	96,990	441,003	91,007	862,57510^10/17	4,273	796	5,879	3,348	14,296	&quot; 10/10/17	237,758	97,786	446,882	94,445	876,87117/10/17	5,076	1,057	7,350	2,364	15,847	&quot;17/10/17	242,834	98,845	454,232	96,809	892,71824/10/17	4,544	1,220	6,957	2,324	15,045	&quot;24/10/17	247;,378	100,063	461,189	99,133	907,76331/10/17	4,292	1,319	6,794	2,528	14,933	&quot;31/10/17	251,670	101,382	467,983	101,661	922,696COcn
APPENDIX   IISULii-ARY OF AWARDS OFSUPPLEMENTARY ALLOWANCES AND SFECIAL ALLOWANCES BY THE .SPEOIAL GRANTS (k)Mi-lITTEE.For the weok onded 17th October, 1917.During weok       Total to 31st tttidod 31st Oct.  19i7.Oct. 1917.Disabled Officers..	D		39Off ioorc &apos; Widows.  .	0		66Officers&apos; Dependants.	2		149Educational Grants (Officers)	0		139Educational Grants (iinn)	0		115Disablod Sailors and Soldiers.	0		982Sailors&apos; and Soldiers&apos; Widows.	23	2,	489Sailors&apos; and Soldiers&apos; Dependants.	4		694TOTAL	29	4,	675
APPENDIX III. [FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY.]p7ABMY COUNCIL INSTRUCTION.No. 1615 of 1917.War Office,27th October, 1917.j5i Medical Boards.   Pensioners not to be questioned as to the amount of their actual earnings.It has been brought to notice that Medical Boards, when lessing the physical disablement of soldiers about to be invalided, of pensioners who are being examined for re-assessment of their jsions, are in the habit of making enquiries as to the actual niugs of the pensioners. This is contrary to the present policy. Iu no cases are men to be questioned as to the amount of ;ir earnings.7/Gen. No./8278 (A.M.D.3).By Command of the Army Council,\pies for G.Os.G.-in-C. and G.Os.G. at Home (and for distri-Imtion to all Military Hospitals and Medical Boards&apos;); Ministry of Pensions.](s 13339-1700)  6000   10/17   H&amp;S  A. 17/1700
TU3P0RT AS TO RE - A 5 SE S Sk&apos;i ENT  OP DEPENDANTS  PENSIONS FOR WEEK ENDED October 31st,  1917.     (-APPENDIX II)Gratuities con-Terted into pensions.Gratuities allow-cd to stand temp-orarily pre-war *Sependence being -under 3/6 a week.Bensions incr:tensions granted (no previous grant.)Pensions unchang-ed (already equal to pre-war dependence).TOTALParents dependent on one s on., :io . sAv&apos; ge I Av&apos;ge ^Rat-e , I -Incr.143Pr.rs.utc depdt on mors than one s on.466 ! 8/4       0/4258/94/483 !j39778/4No. jAvr ge jAv&apos; ge JRate  dncr.242: 8/2t25 ! 10/7i    94 1    9/40/24/5G-ipc ri ftp iront s and Poster Parents.No. Av&apos; ge ; Av1 ge &apos;Rate.iIncr.o/- I a/-;iIParents drawing S.A. as wife or ponsion as widow.No. i A v1 ge &apos; Rate86/56TO&quot;4/47/8Av&apos; ge Incr.6/5Class B-widow 10/-a week.No.Av1 ge Incr.7/8Illeg. children 5/-a week.No.16noAv1 ge Incr.Mis :150150Total No.    Ccorrected) to be re-assessed as at April 4th 1917. 72,500 Summary for week.Re-as^essed as per previous reports. 70,295 Pensions increased 53 av.Incr. 4/5 per week.1,248 Pensions granted, previously settled byabove Balance.957 gratuity 6S7AVerage rate of pension 0/3 a week.COoo
AfPENbtX v39iReoort for Treek ended 31st October, 1917 as to new entitlement tov;ido&apos;7S and Dependants pensions.The following shews the approximate number of c ases to be reconsidered at date 4th April, 1917.Widows vfidows Dependants&quot;Aggravation&quot; gratuity admitted...............503.No claim under Old Warrant...................1522.Do. 2697tTOTAL.4722.Total re-examined to date.WIDOWS.Aggrav.cases *: Other casesr o.17. .17.Full pension granted.503503Full ;o ens ion64&apos;admitted.Finally Total refused643Short ponsion66Q26622312312036 3DIIPXiD/iNTb.Pens orgr at s admit eel.117820391178Finarofus - edTotal150226S01502 !2680Number still to bo disposed of.........3
APJENDIX VI.ANALYSIS eF TRIBUNAL CASES DEALT WITH DP TO WEUJESDA.Y OCTOBER 31st 1917.Number of Appeal Forms received 1138Number sent to Tribunal but notified as notbeing on points within their Reference 263Number of oases given &quot;due to&quot; or&quot;aggravated T*y&apos;f *n further enquiry 313Cases considered by Tribunal:-Given attributable etc., 33Given not attributable 24Adjourned 11Cases ready for Tribunal but not heard Cases awaiting Appeal Boards131423       1198
APPENDIX Tiltes where can not jonailyId.MEDICAL CERTIFICATE.Name of Man_ .I hereby certify that I have this day (examined(considered the case ( of xthe abo?,e-named discharged man, and having regard to themedical report &amp;o* referred to me, I am of opinion that(a) he is suffering from__,sent incapa-jviously not ore conneot-miiitarythe rest of rtifioate be struck(b) his present incapacity is, eo far as I can judge(due to      ) or oonneoted with his disablement and (not due to)the conditions of his military service.(c) he [is incapacitatod for work(should on medical grounds not be allowed to work.,B an&amp;C ;ernative.A.(d) he should be referred for examination and, if possible, spooial treatment, to (name the civil or military hospital and state is as in or out patient)Krical Tfment Blescent Bment, Iment foror (if the Medical Referee can indioate the treatment the man should receive(d) he should receive special treatment consisting of,aas in-patient la ^ as out-patient in)(name of civil (institution (if any.(o) the period 6f such treatment, so far as it cantism, Sec,   be forseen, should be__hether in or at        _&apos;        &quot;stitution. or 1      aaasig.....&apos;&apos;&quot; &apos;&quot; &apos;&quot;..............................aaaaC.or (if the Medical Referee oonsiders that the man requires no special treatment beyond such as his panel practitioner can give him),(d) he should be referred to his panel practitioner for treatment.cSignedSecretary or Clerk pne Local Har Pensions Committee,kedical Referee.Date
APPENDIX    IX.JOIfiT COMMITTED OH INSTITUTIONAL TK ATiiSliT.*The twenty seventh, meeting of the Committee was held on Thursday November 1st 1917 at Westminster House, MlllbankiPRESENT *&quot;       colonel Sir Arthur Griffith Boscawen (Chairman) &quot;        Sir Alfred Pearoe Gould General Sir George Bullock.&apos;with 3ir H. Haward Sir John Collie Major H, 3. Hartley and Mr-,&quot;Hore.   -1.MINUTES.The minutes of the last meeting were confirmed. 2.HSUEA3TH3BIA.Sir John Collie reported as follows:* (a)Craigend, Edinburgh.   Progress was being made with the equip-merit and staffing of this Institution, (b)Callaby Castle (c h/hittingham(d)Bamborough Castle. -The question of the possibility of using any of the above three homes was discussed and it was resolved not to consider them further as possible Homes of Recovery.   The Committee decided that if further homes were required they should, be established near Bristol and Cardiff in order to meet cases from the  eat of England and South Wales.(ejy/estgate. Beokenham.   Mrs. De Veer expected to have this Home ready to receive patients on or about the 9th instant.   There was at present one man awaiting admission to the Institution which could accommodate up to SO patients.   It was not intended t have a resident Uedical Officer.   Sir Alfred Pearoe Gould said he would make enquiries and communicate with Sir John Collie with regard to obtaining a suitable visiting Medical Officer.(f )Leopard3town. Ireland.   The Board of Works had undertaken the carrying out of the repairs at this Home and it was thought that it would take two or three months to complete same after whioh the furniture would have to be put in.(g/Leicester Frith, Leicester.   There had been unavoidable delay in getting necessary work done.   Bedding and household linen was now ready for fifty patients.   It was expected that (he Home would be opened on or about December 1st next.   Mr. Msrsdon had been appointed occupation Officer and Assistant secretary. Cases from Leicester were to have preference.(h)Allerton Hall, Leeds.   The British Red Cross Society was obtain-ing tenders for the necessary work and the Institution was not expected to be ready for opening for six or eight weeks.(i)Craig Avon, Belfast.   This Institution could only accommodate fifteen or sixteen patients at the present time and there was not any prospect of further accommodation being provided for some months.(1 hvoodbourne, Altrincham.   It was hoped that ivoodbourno would bo ready for opening in four weeks time provided that the Priority Certificate from the ministry of Munitions in connection withneoessary
necessary work was forwarded as promised.   Accommodation would be provided for severity patients,(k) Abbotswood.   Progress was being made with the necessary work and tho Institution would be used as a Convaloscent Home.(L) Home of Recovery,;Golders Green.(1) The number of Patients in the home on October 2nd was 97 &quot;      &quot;      &quot;   orders issued sinoe was 113. &quot;       &quot;       &quot;   refusals was 53. &quot;      &quot;      &quot;   admission was 60. &quot;       &quot;       &quot;   discharges 11 60. &quot;      &quot;       &quot; in the home on 30th October 97.A general discussion took place on the form of the return and it was decided that the return for the future should in addition to the above, contain in connection with the return of discharges the following information..(a) Why the Patient 14ft.(b) whether discharged cured i.e. abl6 to resume his original or other work.(o) whether uncured lie. no progress(d)      11   discharged for misconduct and if so the natur6 of it.The Committee considered that as the whole scheme for treatment of Neurasthenia was more or less an experiment the foregoing particulars would be of material assistance in watching and fudging the result of the treatment.(2) Appointment of Organiser:   A letter dated 31st October from Mr, Burleigh, Secretary to the Home was read relative to the appointment of Mr.. Hose as Organiser of occupations.   The letter stated that the House Committee had considered the matter and were of opinion that the existing arrangements would prove satisfactory and they desired that consideration of the appointment should be postponed until the present scheme had had its trial,,   a general discussion took place and it was decided to adopt the suggestion of the House Committee. Sir John Collie undertook to see Mr. Rose and explain the position.(.3) Passes for admission.   The question of the decision to issu6 passes for admission to Golders Green was discussed and a letter dated 16th October from Mr. Burleigh to Sir John Collie was read.   After a general discussion it was decided that no card ef admission should be required for relatives or friends of the Patients, and that no casual visitor should be admitted withont a personal Cr formal card which may be given by any member of the Staff of the Home or Maida Yalo Hospital authorities or the Ministry,   The formal card of admission should be as followsCARD 0? ADMISSION. TO VISITPlease Admit Mr. AddroBS..Secretary Ministry ,of Pensions(m)
Officers for the varljous Institatijons about to be opened was discussed..   There were at present four Docrtors training at Maghull for the purpose of taking positions in the new Homes which are shortly to be opened-   It was resolved to recommend to the Ministry that a letter be writton to the Central Medical War Committee urging that steps be ^takjen to release the few medical men necessary to staff the Tsxlxwit? Institutions and pointing out that unless this was done the Ministry18 work in providing treatment for discharged * soldiers and sailors would be seriously hampered.   This letter not to be written until after the receipt of a memorandum from Sir John Collie as to the exact position.(3) TUBERCULOSIS.Major Hartley reported as follows:-(a) Standard Pavilions:   He expected that tenders would be out any day for the Pavilions which were to bo erooted at Dorb^ Bristol, Birmingham and St. Helens.   The Birmingham Pavilion would anaommodate 24 patients and each of the others 12.   It was proposed to erect a pavilion near Exeter.   Dr. Chapman and Mr.  itchon (LoG.B. Architect) were going to make an inspection on the 12th,   Captain iinight the Ministry&apos;s Representative for the Southern Area (Central) had suggested the necessity for the erection of a Pavilion at Southampton, and said the Southampton Borough were anxious to try the experiment in connection with their Isolation Hospital proTided the annexe was built and equipped and that a sum of not less than 35/- per week per occupied bed be paid for upkeep.   The matter had been approved by the Local Health Committee on the advioe of Major Lauder, K.A.U.0^   There were 6 advanced cases at present,in Southampton alone.    It was pointed out during a gonoral discussion that the Red Cross had undertaken to pay for 4 Pavilions.   If othere were wanted a complete sohome must be drawn up and if approved placed before the Board of Works for completion.Major Hartley read a letter from Mr. Pratt, Secretary Joint (Disablement) Committee Southern Area (Central) addrossod to him and dated 29th October forwarding him the following resolution of the Committee &quot;That the Institutional Committee bo recommended to establish an Annexe in connection with the Southampton Isolation Hospital and that in addition to this treatment It be recommended that in cases where no arrangements can be made for accommodation, sufficient income, allowances etc. be afforded to ensure that in his own housea) Each man has a room to himselfb) &quot;     &quot;   receives proper attendance and nourishment&quot; It was resolved that the matter be allowed to stand over till a later stage when a scheme would be drawn up and considered.(V) Manchester.   Major Hartley said that there was not anyaooommodation for advanced cases in Manchester and he was in communication with the Local Government Board in connection with the matter.   A suggestion had been made thpt. accommodation should be provided at Bolton Isolation Hospital or Bagulay Sanatorium.    It was decided that Major Hartley should write and got the Hon. Mr, Cozens-Hardy1s views as to the necessity for accommodation in that area and report to a subsequent meeting.(c) TUBERCULOSIS CONPSBSUCE:    Sir Arthur Boscawen said that the Conference on this question had been called.   It was necessary to consider before the meeting what practical proposals were to be made.   The question of x^arm Colonies and the whole system of treatment and training would be , discussed
Mr, Bore reported the list of names of those who had &quot;been invited to the Conference.(d)   Accommodation for Officers:   A general discussion took place with regard to accommodation for discharged tuberculous officers.   Sir Arthur Boscawen said that he had discussed the matter yesterday with Lady Dudley who apparently was seeing as far as possible to the provision of convalescent homes for all officers both those still in the Army and those invalided out.   Tho Committee decided that it was advisable that all treatment for pensioned officers should be provided through the Ministry.Sir A.lfred Pearce Gould said that he had had two interviews with Lady Dudley who had stated there was not sufficient accommodation and chat she had at presssat a list of 35 Officers certified to bo sufioring from Tuberculosis and for whom she could not  i-nd any accommodation.   He had pointed out that the Ministry could only deal with Officers invalided out.   Lady Dudley would like to get &quot;Pinewuod&quot; handed over sololy for Tuberculous Officers still holding Commissions and had promised to let him have a list of Officers who had been invalided out and were on her list.   The Treatment Committee would like to have an additional hut erected for pensioned Officers at Midhurst and if necessary erect a second one. Ha thought this a good Scheme and all the kinistry could be expected to provide.   It was open to any Officer V;ho desired more expensive quarters to obtain it on paying the additional cost.It v-as Anally decided that Sir A. Pearce Gould would draw up a report and submit same to a subsequent meeting and that Sir Arthur Boscawen would have a further interview with Lady Dudley and explain the position.
AfftfiDIX XThe Board of Control,66, Victoria Street, S.W. 1. Slst October, 1917.SUPPLEMENTARY INSTRUCTIONS RELATING TO THE CLASSIFICATION OF DISCHARGED SOLDIERS AND SAILORS AS &quot; SERVICE PATIENTS.&quot;1 In supplement of the &quot;Instructions relating to the Classification and Treatment of Soldiers and Sailors as &apos; Service Patients,&apos; &quot; issued by the Board of Control on the 27th June last, arrangements have now been made by the Minister of Pensions, with the sanction of the Treasury, whereby in future any soldier or sailor, discharged from service in the present war on account of insanity and who is admitted to an asylum on such discharge on the procedure referred to in Instruction 3 hereunder, will be maintained at the cost of the Ministry of Pensions during the period between the date of admission and the date on which the Superintendent is notified that the man is or is not entitled to be classed as a &quot; Service Patient,&quot;2. The date as from which the Ministry of Pensions will be responsible for such maintenance will be the 10th October or the date of admission if later.o. Cases for which the Ministry of Pensions will thus be responsible are those of men admitted to County and. Borough Asylums directly on discharge from service under Section 9.1 of the Army Actor Section 3 of the Naval Enlistment Act, 1884, namely (a) men at present in the asylums in respect of whom notification has not yet been received from the Pension Issue Office that the man is or is not entitled to be classed as a &quot; Service Patient&quot; ; and (b) men admitted to asylums in future under the enactments referred to. Every man so admitted should be regarded during the interim period as a private patient and should on admission or from the 10th October, whichever date is applicable, be entered on the books as such.4. In the cases referred to in the preceding paragraph, accounts for the maintenance of the men for the period between the date of admission or the 10th October, 1917 (whichever is the later), and the date of notification by the Pension Issue Office should be forwarded to the Pension Issue Office. If the man becomes a &quot; Service Patient&quot; the account for maintenance of the patient prior to the date of notification should be forwarded with the quarterly account prescribed in paragraph 9 of the Instructions of the 27th June, 1917. If the man is declared not to be entitled to be a &quot;Service Patient&quot; the account for maintenance up to the date of notification should be transmitted to the Pension Issue Office immediately upon such notification.5. During this interim period the cost of maintenance for which the Ministry of Pensions will be responsible will be calculated at the current weekly pauper rate, not including the additional items of charge numbered (b), (c) and (d) in paragraph 9 of the Instructions.6. In any case where the Superintendent is notified by the Pension Issue Office that the man is not entitled to be a &quot; Service Patient &quot; the Guardians of the Union to which the man is chargeable-as shown on the Statement of Particulars accompanying the Reception Order should at once be communicated with, and informed accordingly. As from the date at which notification is given by the Pension Issue Office unless he is otherwise provided for by relatives, the Guardians become liable for the man&apos;s maintenance and from that date he should be transferred on the books to the pauper class.7. It is important that application should be made to the Pension Issue Office as soon after a man&apos;s admission to the asylum as possible, and the directions given in paragraphs 4, o and 6 of the Instructions issued on the 27th June, 1917, should not be read as meaning that Superintendents should delay application to the Pension Issue Office pending supplementary information as to the man&apos;s position being obtained.(Signed)     E. MARRIOTT COOKE,Chairman.(13857.)   Wt.      -0 216.   4000.   10/17.   D &amp; S.   Gr. 2.
APPENDIX XI.SPECIAL AURAL ECARD, 50th October, 1917,Sir,I have the hoacur to submit my report for the month *f October as Secretary cf She Special Aural Board.During the month the Board has hold seven meetings aod the foXIvWing men have been examined, the recommendation of the Board in 6ach oase is stated,J,T. Baker, 3, Bayham Street, N.W,1. recommended for out-patient treatment at Central London Hospital and attend evening classes in lip-reading, -Edward Lindsey, 42, Bells Garden Read, Peckham^ SJS* to receive treati.ient at. (^ueenTs Square Hospital on ThurscafB:&quot;&apos; to be re-examined in 6 months,E..A,. Oomraerford, 66, Great Bland Street, S,E, to attend clinic at Queen?s Square Hospital as out-patient.   Recommended fc&amp;*&apos; training In lip-reading,Ycilliam Garr, 95, Brocklehurst Street. New Cross, SJ2,, 14, instructed to attend Nation Hospital, CJueen&apos;s Square, for electric treatment Thursdays at 2 p,m, and to attend evening classes in lip-*reading.J:T,J, Burke, 74, Campbell Road, Pins bury Park. T.q be treated at Central Threat &amp; Ear Hospital, Friday evenings: to continue attending day class In lip-reading,FsJ, Abraham. 4,0CC, llerton Road, S*V?,18, instructed t* attend special evening clinic, Grayls Inn Road Hospital,Frank-Bray. &quot;Cakwccd&quot;, Castle Road, N.Finchley, instoKJt* sd to attend 0&quot; cr.i rs. IThrcat &amp; Ear Hospital on Friday evenings.Prod Bo-well, Eye, Suffolk, to be treated as in-patient at Queenls Square Hospital, afterwards to attend classes in  lp-reading,T,m, WooIs prove, 120, Arlington Road, Oamden Town, Hearing net sufficiently defective for instruction in lip^reaiiing^Tjjfau ^agj^, 110, Franclsca Road, Upper Tocting, to continue attendance at evening class,F.0, Putman, 112, Raglan Read, Plumstead, recommended for treatment at Central London Hospital,, attending evening clacsea,5pi, JtA. Brock, South African, sent to us by Lt, Col, Thornton, 0,C. South African Hospital, Richmond Park, Surrey, to bo student at the day class in lip-reading.fames Frost, 2., Rinhfcrd Road, Portway, West Ham, E,15, to be treated at ^ueen iviary:s Hospital, Stratford, Wednesday evenings,L.F. y/hittington, 60, Heme Hill Road, Herne Hill, S,,E, 24, to receive tr.eati.ient at King^ College Hospital, suitable fcr evening class,,   v Albert Farmiioe. 72, liuriel Street, King&apos;s Gross, H,W,to be treated at Grayrs Inn Road Hospital or St. Bartholomew*s,T.P. Lynch. 10, Wilcove Place, Itiarylebone, N,13, to be    -treated at special evening clinic at Central London Hospital, reoommended for evening olass,E.W, Bcwden. 20, Wellington Street, Camden Town, H,W, ^receive treatment at Central London Hospital, special evening.     .        Sey-rge li. Gibbs. 148, Qmznls Road, Batter sea, S*W*11, Zo attend Central London &quot;HoaprltBJ. for ti^tmairo of polypus,special eveninr clinic.Sir *Mthew Nathan, G,C ,;a,G,, * *of Pensions.
Wm. Walsh, 1, Dorset Street, New Kent Road, S.E. to be treated at special evening clinic at Central Throat, &amp; Ear Hospital on Friday evenings.



F.A. Vowles, 21, Balgrave Road, N. Kensington, instructed to attend Thursdays at 4 o/clock, Queen&apos;s Square Hospital for treatment.



Henry W. French, 10, Walder St. Fishpool, Bury Lancs. This man came up from Bury for examination and the report on his case was transmitted to the S.M.O. Chelsea Hospital.

Philip Poulter, 73, Amelia Street, Southwark, This man was re-examined on applying for pension. The Presient of the Board&apos;s intention was to prepare a reccommendation to the Minister.

Henry Frewer, 48, London Road, Stockwell, S.W. to be X-rayed at King George&apos;s Hospital.

J.E. Allum, 295, High Street, Stratford, to be treated at Stratford evening clinic.

A.E. Ruffells. examination not completed, to appear again on November 6th

Dawney George E, 78. Cunningham Road, Shepherds Bush. to be treated at Queen&apos;s Square Hospital.

G.L. Marwin. 12 Swanage Road, Wandsworth, S.E.18, to be treated at Hammersmith evening clinic, suitable for evening class in lip-reading.

George Hazel, 12, Bygrove Street, Poplar, E.14, recommended for evening class in lip-reading.

Walter R. Day, Rayleigh, Essex, to be treated at Stafford evening clinic, attending day-class in lip-reading.

Cramer. T.H., Harrow St Boro, High Street S.E.1. to be treated at Hammersmith evening clinic, after he has undergone an operation in the hospital.

In the day class in lip-reading there are at present eight pupils and in the evening class sixteen. A few of the evening pupils have discontinued coming for the present, owing to the air raids, and will resume later on. The evening class has been divided into two sections with two teachers, and I am informed by those in charge that all the men are getting on well. A great difference has been noticed in the health and general appearance of some of the men since they have been attending these classes. They have a more hopeful view of life and a are in every way more content. Without exception they all exceedingly anxious to secure all the knowledge that they can during the short time that the course is open to them.

Through the kindress of Miss Ruddock, the day pupils are supplied at nominal cost with a good hot dinner at noon each day, and the evening pupils, some of whom came straight from work without getting anything to eat, are given something hot, either soup, cocoa, or coffee, for the small price of a penny. The men are made to feel that they are welcome at this house, where everything is arranged for their comfort and convenience. Social evenings at which they may bring their friends, have been arranged.

A pupil who was secured for the day class yesterday can neither read nor write, and I am getting a young lady especially to teach him. He can learn of reading and writing,and later on can go into the other classes.

Owing to the extent of the work of their office, it has not been possible for me to do much visiting during the month of October, but Mrs. Comyns Carr and Miss F.M. Lewis, have very kindly undertaken to assist me in this regard, and it is hoped very soon, to be in touch with all the discharged soldiers and sailors within the London area.


1 have also t-o acknowledge the valuable assistance rendered me by iliss Balby, without Whose help the work could not possibly have been done.     T^e business of the Aural Boarc8 is branching out, and it will be absolutely necessary f or-.the Secretary -to have a stenographer all the time,All of which Is respectfully submitted.I have the honour to be.Sir,Your obedient -Savant,(Signed) H.L. INGRAM.Oapt-Secretary * Special Aural Board.
a APPENDIX XIICorrection Slip No. 4.--50Treatment and training.B.si?&apos;j on page 38.Dental Treatment.J Where a disabled man is found by the InvaKding Board on discharge to require Artificial Teeth or Dental Beatment, a recommendation to this effect will be in-Bided in the report of the Board, and the case will be Bait with by the Ministry of Pensions, Royal Hospital, BieLsea.W Cases arising after discharge or found to require such Beatment will be dealt with by Local Committees. It j.- been decided that Artificial Teeth or Dental Treatment. Bay be provided at the public expense in the following Bscs: I (1) Where the dental defect requires the provision 1 of artificial teeth and such defect can be attributed I to conditions arising from or aggravated by service I in the present War. These conditions may be I assumed in any case where a man&apos;s teeth have I been extracted during service, otherwise the certifi-f cate of the Medical Referee must be obtained. I (2) Where a man is undergoing a course of treat-I ment and the supply of teeth or dental treatment 1 is certified to be necessary for the efficacy of that I treatment. This may occur, for example, in cases I    of dyspepsia, gastritis or tuberculosis.I In any case in which these conditions are fulfilled, the local Committee should take steps to secure that dental Ireatment is given. For this purpose arrangements have pen made for the time being with the Ivory Cross Society, liiich has carried out similar work on behalf of the War fcffice, and has a panel of dentists in all parts of the Kingdom with whom terms of treatment have been liranged. Under the arrangements now proposed, the local Committee should send one of the forms enclosed frith this Instruction to the Secretary, The Ivory Cross I      x   (37)4311   Wt 4268-G 103   100   11/17   E&amp;S
Society, 10, Conduit&apos; Street, London, W. 1, who arrange for the required treatment to be provided hi locality. - It should be clearly understood that * the c of this treatment will be paid by. the Ministry and not the Society, but allowances during treatment will be p by the Local Committee in all cases in which treatm allowances are admissible under Instructions 34-40. Si cases need not be submitted for sanction,
MINISTRY OF  PENSIONS,ANDTHE  IVORY CROSS  SOCIETY.Note. This form when completed must be filled in and returned to the Hon. Secretary, Offices of the Ivory Cross Society, 10, Conduit Street London, W. 1.Certificate of Medical Referees.I hereby certify that the undermentioned man, being a discharged disabled man, requires dental treatment on account of dental defects which, so far as I can judge,(a) are due to or have been aggravated by his military service.(b) should be attended to if the medical treatment which he is under-going on account of his disablement is to be efficacious.Date___Signed __________Medical Referee.Name___^ No.Regimentor Ship___Regimental Rank_____Present addressMost convenient centre for treatmentSigned Clerk toLocal Committee.4787  4235/G102   Pfs.   10/17   J. P.   Gp. 158
APPENDIX       XIIITRBATLUImm.Report of Sdiemos etc, sanctioned during the woending October 31st.The Joint Advisory Committee for Bedfordshire, Hertfordshire, and Huntingdon submitted a schono for treatment embodying uilitary, Auxiliary, Rod Cross and civil institutions in their area- with several military Institutions outside the Joint Advisory Committee area.     Of those 39 ivere approved and further enaairy was addressed to the constituent Local -Committoes concerning certain Institutions in respect of which full information Fas net forth-coningt     The question of Convalescent treatment does not appear to have received sufficient consideration- and all the Local Committees concerned, and the Ministerfs Representative, have been ashed to ascertain what facilities exist in their area and what arrangements they propose to make to provide for the large number of men who require t...is form of treatments, The Kent Local Committee submitted a comprehensive scheme embodying Military, Auxiliary, Voluntary Aid Detachment and civil hospitals in their area together Tilth several specialist Institutions outside the area of the Joint Advisory Committee.. The use of the ililitary Hospitals mentioned in the scheme was approved, vrith a for? exceptions outside the area of the Joint Advisory Committee, which in view of  the comprehensive nature of the scheme, 7: ere unnecessary.     The Schedule had ha?ever to be returned for information as to the terms accepted by the Auxiliary and Voluntary Aid Detachment Hospitals.     The Devonshire Hospital, Buxton Teas approved for the treatment of rheumatism and encu iry made as to the terms proposed with the St.. John1 s Brine Baths, Droitwich.     The Warncford, Leamington and South Warwickshire Hospitals, Leamington Spa.     Further enquiry was also made as to the proposed charges of the Kent County Opthalmic Hospital and the Eye and Bar Hospital, Tunbridge &quot;&quot;ells.     The use of the established clinics for the treatment of deafness at the Queen llary Hospital, Stratford, and the Central London Throat andEar Hospital was approved.     Ho provision was made in this scheme for Convalescent treatment and the Committee were requested to submit information as to any Institutions in their area suitcb le for the purpose,&apos;     The matter was also referred to the ministers Representative and the Local Committee requested to co-operate with him in the preparation of a general scheme for the wider area of the Joint Advisory Committee,. The Ilontgomery Local Committee received sanction for payment of 10/6 for four consecutive monthly attendances at the special eye, ear and throat department of the Newtown Infirmary,* Approval was given to the use of the fcillosden Council&apos;s Clinic for out-patient treatment at a fee of 2/-&apos; when both doctor and nurse were required and l/- vrhen a nurse only was r equired. These terms were approved in view of the fact that special medical provision had to be made for the treatment cf pensioners.* The Newcastle-on-Tyne.Committee received sanction to use Dunston Hill House for in-patient treatment at schedule rates.-* The Buckinghamshire Committee received general sanction to the use of the Royal Mineral Water Hospital Bath at a fee of3/- per day.
7. The Joint Committee for the Northern area have forwarded to the Ilinister a resolution asking that provision may be made for electrical treatment aid massage for Socth. Durham and Teeside^ preferably at Stockton.    The LIinistryfs Representative has been asked to see v/hat arrangements can be made *Gt The employment of a masseuse at  2*10.0 a week has been sanctioned provisionally for 3 months at OsTrestry Military Hospital *
Return of  cases under Treatment  Tor week ended 31st  October,  19X7.[Nature of DisabilityWounds c&apos;c neurasthenia jParaplegia Epilepsy     tuberculosis jOtherInquiriess^i 03-p 030) oso o-) cocci O O 03o cd *1 oEcbrought forward (unde^ treatment on 24.10.17.     j--Lc3 -U 03-p cdC tocd hio o&quot;- &quot;1-------ij rh*   : co *,    u   ! ^ ojco    cd    ; -p cdo     co    i c) 03o     crf    i cd ctiv-3    o    I o oI rh- j- aJ03as a)o 0?o o5PI o137    677131152.114-p cds3 03cd cdo orh 03o cao ajp3 o03-p    cd3     03cd go&quot; o   oIDisea: o s03cd o 03 o cd i-l o.13No.reported during week as admitted for Treatment -6157&apos;13No. reported during week as discharged from. Treatment.,29;14-1491109U 03i a c3cd 05I o oirh 03cj cdo coo gjpi oIIow treated.InInstitutions.TotalsOtherwise.jft 03-p cdcd cio o124      177 i 655j   2198 l      702ro cdo 03o cdr-3 ot-* ca-p cdC wcd ajO o132930 I    45!     3302141054-.1361942163a cdo     03o &amp;1581110Total under Treatment on 31,10.17Total who have been or are under Treatment up to 31,10.17.193 I 705      143i 38114!1323 t 877;     332 I 54     )    12812LJ.250192941271452011 6429311 848 i24344955895 ;   13713002 I   1743159201
Appendix XV net yet received fromprinters; will followe
5 3APPENDIX  XVI.Proposal by Director of Training for utilization cf the Cheshire Agricultural College.__Accompanied by Mr. Gozens-Hardy the Representative for Cheshire and Lancashire, I visited the Cheshire County Agricultural College at Holmes Chap*i.Soon after the out-break of the war the students of the College had joined up and the College was closed. It was then taken over by the Agricultural Board in connection with their Small Holding scheme and a number of Discharged Soldiers were trained but the effort proved disappointing to the men who were under the impression apparently that they would be placed upon a holding.   They were, however, given to understand they would have to provide about ^ 00 Capital which as none were able to do they left and the effort was given up and the College closed.Later it was taken over by the iiational oerviee Department for training women and good work in this direction had oeen done.   This however, is now being given up as difficulty is being experienced in finding employment for the women and the College is again closed tomorrow the -2nd instant.we vent over tne College which has an admirably built building for separate cubicles for about 60 pupils in addition to excellent dining, recreation and class rooms.   It is fitted with electric light the current being generated by their own plant.The out-buildings are of a model character and there are v?oo&amp; work and other workshops, laboratories etcThe grounds extend to about 100 acres of Forrest ^arm and fruit vegetable and horticultural gardens.   There are also good glass house fruit and vegetable preserving sheds, etc.The College grounds would to my mind prove an ideal place for agricultural; training under exceptionally favourable conditions as men could be trained forHorticulture^armwork - there is a motor-tractor in the equipmentIvlarket-gardeningForestry etc.Country Hou^e Attendants.The workshops could be utilised for training for ordinary farm wood work, smithing etc and for basket and hurdle making glass frame making etc such as is required for garden and farm purposes generally.ken could oe trained as useful men for country houses and be trained in addition to ordinary farm and garden work to drive a motor car tractor plough and to look after a country house electric lighting set.   /or such men there are continuous openings and at good rates of pay.    It is estimated that the whole of this work could oe done for from 3,010 to 3,50C as an outside figure per annum and I strongly recommend that effort should be made to secure the use of the College as a Training Centre for Cheshire and Lancashire and any adjoining area. The
The demand has been demonstrated by the fact that for the 35 places at Hutton Farm Sohool, Lancashire. 1bH applications for admission wore received within 3 weeks.I would propose that the Cheshire County Council be approached to place the College and groundB at the disposition of the Pensions Ministry, paying rents, ratet. taxes and maintenance of building up to a sum of  1,000 per annum and the balance be paid for maintenance of the men who would rooeive lodging, washing etc. froe* paying for their own food under conditions we find so satisfactory in oonneotion with the Eccentric Club Hostels, vi ., that the men form their own Mess Committee, arrango for payment of purchase of their own provisions whioh shall be oookod and served free by the House Staffs   By this means complaints that inevitably arise in connection with amount and variety of food supplied is in the men&apos;c own power at all times to remedy.Tho cost of feeding will in this manner amount in tho Hostels to about 14/- to 15/- per week and the men are well fod which is a real necessity.   This sum would in all probability be greatly roduood at the College as a great deal of their supplies could be obtained at cost price from their own productions.A disabled man could be utilised as Carpentry Instructor another as Basket Making Instructor also as Instructors for tho Electric Plant and tho Motor Tractor Work.The Head Gardener who was brought up as an Estate Steward is a very capable man and would it is felt be just the man to take superintendence of the work, he having a good all round knowledge of the requiremente and in addition of a temporament likely to be most satisfactory in dealing with this class of men.The coat per week would work out assuming the total cost to the Ministry would be  2400 per annum at 15/- per week per man for instruction to 60 men.   This amount should be very considerably roduced by sales of produce.It is decided aotion should be taken; the Cheshire County Council should be communicated with without delay as the collego may otherwise be utilised for other purposes.   The management should then be placed under the Cheshire Joint Area Committee.
APPENDIX XV11TRAIHIHG.Trade Advisory Committees and the Training of Disabled-Ken. Report for v/eek ending October- 31st. 1917.GENERAL MCI1ESRIMG.The Engineering ^ub Committee at its meeting on Ootober 25th prepared a provisional liBt of machine processes to which the following schema of training should apply.First three months amployerfs contribution EO/-, the Ministry of Pensions to bring it up to Maintenance Allowance.Second period of three months labourer&apos;8 rate plus 2/6.Third three months labourer&apos;s rato plus 3/6.Fourth three months labourer&apos;s rate plus 5/-.It was also suggested that this scheme should apply to a number of othsr semi-a)cU..WUhand operations.PRINTING.The meeting of the main Committee was held on Monday. October 29th.   The scheme previously mentioned was-approved in regardtoa) Hand Compositing, Platen Machine Minder. Monotype Caster.Copy Holder. Proof Puller.b) Lithography.o) Process fcork..... Some difficulties have been experienced with regard to Bookbinding on the part of the Trade Union concerned and it was agreed that a deputation consisting of ivlr. Holmes and Mr. Heath should inter-view the Emergency Executive Committee representing the Bookbinding Trade Union.gASOg SgP AM) HAMPER.        Tuesday October 30th.A report was received from the Ministry of Pensions with regard to tho scheme recommended by the Trade Advisory Committee * The Ministry expressed its Inability to sanction training for more than two years and this decision was accepted by the Trade Advisory Committee.Mr. Maurice of the Pood Production Department of the Board0? Agriculture attended the meeting by special invitation andmentioned there would be an enormous demand for baskets foragricultural produce during the next year and that:if the.trade couldjot meet the demand the Government would have to take the matter overjor themselves.   This statement was very helpful- in reassuring the*rade Unionists present with regard to the Introduction of disabled flon.
A PPENDIX XVil!58TRAINING.Schemes submitted or sanctioned during week ended the51st October, 1917.A scheme submitted by the Rutherford College Newcastle was approved provided the same was adopted and submitted by the Newcastle Local Committee.The Brighton Local Committee have submitted a scheme for training disabled men at the Brighton Municipal Technical College grid Municipal School of Art In the following occupations :-(a) Telegraphy,  (b) Tailoring, (c) Surveying,  (d) Metal Work, (Turning and Fitting),  (e) Dispensing,  (f) Carpentry and Joining (g) Confectionery,  (h) Electrical Engineering and v;Iring (i) Diamond Cutting (j) Boot Repairing (k) Clerical work,  (1) Bricklaying and Masonry (m) Plumbing (n) Builders&apos; Drawing and Mechanical Drawing, Commercial design and Poster Viork (o) v.!ood Carving (p) Letter cutting in Wood and Stone (q) Sign Writing and Lettering.The terms (length of course, fees, etc.,) are favourable and the future prospects of employment for the men on completion of training are good.Tiie Bradford Local Committee have submitted a scheme for the training of disabled men in a number of subjects including the engineering, Textile, Building, Printing and Cabinet making trades together with training in Miscellaneous occupations.The Plymouth Local Committee have submitted a scheme for training disabled men in Woodwork, Electric Viiring, Metal V;ork, Kiscellaneous Drafts and Boot Bepairing.     The training will take place for the most part at the Plymouth Technical School, but Electric Wiring and Boot Repairing will be taught at local work-shops.   Facilities are also available for the training of the Blind at the Devon and Cornwall Institution for the Blind, Plymouth.The Aberdeen Local Committee have submitted a scheme for the training of disabled men in (a) Cinema Operating (b) Boot and Shoe making (c) Mechanism of Marine tootors.The Joint Advisory Committee for Midland Ireland have submitted a scheme for the training of disabled men In Commercial Subjects free of expense at Boss College, Dublin.     The proposal has been sanctioned on the understanding that the trainin/, is limit-d to specially selected men.All the foregoing schemes 1 to 6 are under consideration.    In the cases,where the subjects belong to the &quot;Special Trades&quot; the conditions imposed by the Trade Advisory Committees are bein;: made a condition of approval.In those Trades wh.,ch are still under discussion by the Respective Joint Advisory Committee approval .s being suspended until Unal conditions have been arranged.f Tlie Western Counties Joint Committee have submitted a schemeI02- graining discharged disabled men in Electrical work at the -v-indon Corporation Electrical Department..     As the conditions are favourable sanction has been given.
APPENDIX XIX. TRAINING.59Cases in receipt of allowances during Training in clinical Institutes and Factories or Workshops in week ended.31*\Op$,ph.er.,17In Technical InstitutionsIn FactoriesTotal.Reported No. under Training on,.24-1Qt17	438	165	604.Ho. reported during week as admitted for Training.	35	9	44No. reported during week a3 discharged from Training,            j	I                         1 i        is     !	f 3	16        j1 Total under Training ; on.....$XihQiVZ.....;	i           460	172	I 632         \Occupations of men reported as having begun Training iring week ended 31st October. 1917. --   -               - -   -.....                            -      Branch of   Trade	1 No. of men,Agriculture,	t 2Arts and Crafts.	Baking and Confectionery.	Boot and Shoe,	4Brushmaking.	i ;3uilding,	mtCane and Willow.	-Cinematography,	Commercial.	8Diamond Cutting.	Domestic Service,	1(Electrical.	6Engineering (Marine,	-!                        (Mechanical,	4j    Furniture,	Class Manufacture.	j    Gold, Silver and Jewellery Trade.	M1    Leather and Leather Goods Manufacture,	1!    Miscellaneous.	7Printing, Professional, Sur gi c a 1 App 1 i ancs M aker, Tailoring.Textile manufactures. Transport.Training for Blind and Deaf.1 10
60Extracts from Reports of Inspectors for week ended 31st October 1917-SMETEWICK   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.An examination by the Inspector shows that the Regulations have been observed.   Rather fuller information is, however, required on the case-papers and the Committee has been advised on this point.   Grants are disbursed by visitors at the aprli-cants&apos; homes, a more desirable arrangement than disbursement at a Central Office as it enables the visitor to get into touch with the case.The accounting is well done owing to the fact that the present Secretary is also the Borough Accountant. Weekly payments are being made in 660 cases on an average.    The Inspector desires to call attention to the large number of advances to soldiers1 dependants, which average 60 a week.   Advances are also necessita-ted owing to delays in the issue of new Draft Books.   A number of cases were reported where no Separation Allowance had been paid though several months had elapsed since the soldierrs enlistment.KEIGHLEY   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.In the opinion of the Inspector this Committee is working very well.    The accounts are in very good order; advances are well made and recovered.MIDDLETON   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.Grants under Regulation 13(e) appear to be given rather too freely.    The Secretary has been written to pointing out the provisions of this Regulation.   Several payments have been stopped on the Inspector notifying that they were not justified under the Regulation.HALIFAX   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.On the whole a very good Committee.    Disabled men get particular attention.    Every case notified is immediately visited and close watch is kept over the men.    There are two whole-time Disablement Visitors who are also the Hospital Visitors.   At present  200 a month is being spent in Training and Treatment. Many disabled men are being given treatment at home.    The Committee has had to be &quot;earned to work in accordance with the Instructions as they were still granting supplementation under old Regulation 12 of the Statutory Committee, giving as their reason that they were waiting for the appointment of the Medical Referee,APPENDIX   XX ORGANIZATION   BRANCH,
61Many claims to Alternative Pensions are also held up awaiting the appointment of the Enquiry Officer.    The Committee has been notified that these are to be investigated by members of their own staff and submitted in due course and this will be done.The accounts are in first-class order&apos;and auditedto date.STOKE-ON-TRM?   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.Payments are still being made which are not in accord-anoe with the Regulations but a serious effort is being mado to bring these into line and to see that the -Regulations are observed in all new cases.The Inspector has had to speak very frankly to this Looal Committee and to the local Sub--Committees, of which thera are six.   There is extremely good material in the form of voluntary workers in this Local Committee&apos;s area and.steps havo been taken to seriously deal with the unsatisfactory state of affairs which have existed hitherto.IIORTEUMBERLAJID   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.The Inspector was impressed on his inspection with the keen and conscientious work done at Earsdon, the third largest district in the County, where he had an opportunity of address-ing a meeting of the Sub-Ccmmittee, all of whom are miners or connected with mining.    The Distributers in the several wards were all members of the Committee and they engage in discussing each others eases with sympathy, common-sense and knowledge of the Regulations which it was very enoouraging to witness.LANCASHIRE   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.Formby Branch Committee.Case-papers were examined and found in good order and payments in accordance with the Regulations.   The work is efficiently done by this Branch Committee.Great Crosby Branch Committee.Case-papers examined and with few exceptions, which are now being attended to, the payments are all in order.   Some grants have been made under wrong Regulations but these will be amended.Litherland Branch Committee.In the majority of cases the papers do not give all the particulars required and it was not possible for the Inspector to say whether the grants were all warranted; he is doubtful about many of them.   Caoe-paints shall, however, be shortly completed and the Committee will then review all the grants made.   The Inspector will pay srether visit tc this Branch Committee at an early date, and he has meanwhile instructed the Secretary of the conditions under which rent allowances may be made.
\- -gJjACOCAMM SE IRE  . LOCAL. COMMITTEE.The Regulations appear to-be adhered-to with the exception that there is a tendency to make grants to relieve men discharged with small pensions who may not require any particular course of treatment or training, but Ydiose health is not sufficiently robust to allow them to work continuously Gases cf this kind will, however, be dealt with under Regulation 13(g)..LEEDS   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.A new Secretary has been appointed to the local Committee and the Inspector is very favourably impressed with his work6   further tests of grants made were found to be in order and those previously objected to have all been correctly amended,.    The new instructions are being most carefully carried cut in all particulars.The accounts are in good order and the auditors have just oompleted a most searching audit.3 Of SIM   LOCAL   COMMITTEE.There a?3 still some grants made by this Local Committee which are not in accordance with the Regulations.. The Inspector gives examples..     He, however, states that he will see that they are all put in ordercThe Committee have taken central premises entirely devoted to War Pensions work.    This was urgently necessary., A most capable woman is in charge with another one under her and both give full time to the work.-3-
APPENDIX  XXI SPECIAL GRANTS COMMITTEE*Minutes .of Meeting held at 22, Abingdon Street, S.W, On Tuesday, 16th October, 1917. ,PRESENT.C.J. Mathew, Esq.,    (In the Ghair).Coles Child Esq.,B.B. Cubitt Esq.,Corporal Linard.W.L. Marshall, Esq.,Mrs. MoKenna.Mro. Shakespeare.Sir Prederiok Stopford.Ben Turner Esq.,The Chair was taken by the Chairman,The Minutes of the meeting held on 2nd October, which had been circulated to members, were confirmed and signed by the Chairman.The following scheme approved by the Forfeiture Section was dulyconsidered and was adopted ao amended, and the oiroularletter approved as amended:-1. When the complaint against a woman is received in theform of an anonymous letter, a copy to be sent at onse to the Local Committee asking for their opinion as to whether it calls for any further notice or not.It will be pointed out that if any enquiries are necessary they must be very carefully made so as not to cast any reflection on the woman in case the allegations are unfounded as they are in a large number of cases.2. When the Complaint comes from the man and the offenceis admitted by the woman the separation Allowance shall be stopped at once, but in suitable cases the matter should be referred to the Local Committee with a suggestion that if they think desirable the man may be written to with a view to condonation and restoration of the allowance.The Committee will in such oases be asked to advise as to restoration in trust.3. in all other oases where a prima facie case has beenmade out the Local Committee to be sent particulars of the complaint, with a request that they will oause the woman to be interviewed and find out any particulars of any defence she may have or any facts which may be put forward in excuse.     In all cases where a good result is possible
64they should be asked to advise that the money should be administered in trust until such time as either it may be restored to the woman or the oase is decided to be hopeless.4, Local Committee should be asked to appoint a verysmall sub-Committee to deal with all these oases or even an individual member in order to insure that there is no unnecessary publicity.5. The Local Committee to be notified, if possible, ofany prosecutions that may be pending In order that a representative of the Local Committee may attend if it is thought desirable.     The police and the National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children be asked to do this.6. That a circular be prepared embodying the abovesuggestions and asking for the co-operation of the Local Committee and particularly drawing attention to the necessity of finding homes for the children of undesirable households or where the mother is imprisoned.     It might be pointed out that where the children1s rate is insufficient the man should be asked to allot.7. In no case shall the soldier be informed of anycomplaint until the matter has been fully investigated.8. The National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty toChildren are informed of every case where the Children1s Act might have to be put in force and also in every case where neglect is alleged.     This praotioe will be continued.9, The Police will also be asked as heretofore for aconfidential report.10. When any case is in the hands of a trustee no furtherenquiries will be made by the office of the police except in very exceptional circumstances.11. The Local Committee will be asked to make enquiriesand will not be limited to information appearing on their books subject, however, to the necessity for avoiding duplicate enquiries at the same time as the Police.Circular Letter.I am directed to inform you that the Special Grants Committee have had under consideration the practice adopted in dealing with cases involving the forfeiture -of separation allowances and pensions.     Under the Naval and Military War Pensions (Transfer of Powers) Act the functions exercised by the War Pensions, &amp;e., Statutory Committee under Section 3(l)(4]of the Act of 1915 have been transferred to the Special Grants Committee.     The Special Grants Committee are anxious that the policy inaugurated by the Statutory Committee should be continued and that every effort should be made either by means of a private warning or by administer-ing the allowance in trust to avoid the necessity for actual forfeiture.Through the help of the local Committees it is certain that a little encouragement and sympathetic advice given at the right moment will often prevent a position
I6arising when punitive measures &quot;become necessary.     In many oases in which it would be impossible or unwise to continue or restore the payment direct to the woman, the Special Grants Committee would gladly authorise payment of the allowance of the wife and her children through some representative who would undertake to administer the allowance and to keep in touch with the home, always having In view the ultimate restoration of the allowance as soon as advisable.     This Administration in Trust has already proved of great value and although there may be oocasional failures, the Special Grants Committee are satisfied that the practise of payment under supervision is capable of substantial and very useful development.In a very large number of cases the woman has been - given no opportunity to meet the allegation made against her and although the evidence may appear olear, there is often some explanation or excuse which oughtto be taken into account. It is of the utmost importance, in order that justice may be done, that in each case the woman shall be given every facility to meet the charge.     In future it is proposed to furnish particulars of the general nature of the complaint and the evidence in support of it to the Secretary of the Local Committee personally, in order that some suitable person may visit the woman and hear whet she may wish to say in her own defenoe.     Sometimes it has been found sufficient to give a formal warning that any repetition of undesirable conduct will lead to forfeiture.     A full report should then be sent to the Special Grants Committee together with the advice of the Local Committee as to whether forfeiture is necessary or whether administration in trust is likely to prove successful.In fairness to the woman it is important that knowledge of the charges, some of which are quite unfounded, should be confined to as few persons as possible and it might be well if this work can be conducted by a very small Sub-Committee or even by a single member of the Local Committee.The Special Grants Committee do not propose to ask Local Committees to be responsible for the detection of offences or for obtaining evidence against the woman; this oan be done by other methods, although Local Committees will no doubt report any oases that come under their observation, whigh ought to be dealt with.In oases involving cruelty to children, the National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children has always given all possible assistance, and have undertaken in most of such cases the subsequent care of children.     In some instances the oustody of the children is given by the Court to the Guardians who are usually able to provide for them in oottage homes.     The National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children organization has, however, been seriously depleted, and the co-operation of Looal Committees would be weloomed.In other oases - desertion, convictions not involving cruelty, etc., - the only general organization apart from that of Local Committees, is the Poor Law, and Local Committees will no doubt agree that wherever possible, boarding out should ba effected by  Goal Committees rather than by the Poor Law, an&amp; that everything should be done to obviate the necessity of placing children in the Workhouse.
The Special Grants Committee would be glad, therefore, if Local Committees would place themselves in communication with the Local Representatives of the National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, with the Police and the Guardians, with a view to making arrangements for general co-operation, and for the care of children in cases arising in their areas. In this connection it may be pointed out that Local Committees have power, under Part II Regulation 13(c) to make provision for outfit and other necessary expenses involved.

The instructions to Part I were duly considered and the general Scheme was approved. The matter was, however, referred to the Section dealing with Regulations to be completed as soon as the sanction of the Minister has been obtained.

The case of Mrs. Mary Maggs, P. 3861, was duly considered by the full Committee and it was decided that this was not a case in which assistance should be granted. The case of Mrs. Jameson, P.8013, was duly considered by the full Committee and it was decided to accept this case as an exceptional one for assistance.

On a question raised by Sir Frederick Stopford with reference to the necessity for a grant for clothing in certain education cases where children had obtained scholarships, it was unanimously decided that:-

"It is the opinion of the Special Grants Committee that it is necessary to provide clothes for any child in order to enable the child to take proper advantage of the education offered, a grant not exceeding 5 may be regarded as part of the necessary expenses of the education."

The Special Grants Committee requested the Secretary to inform the Ministry that they view with grave concern the delay in dealing with following matters submitted by them:-

(a) The proposed Regulations for Officers.

(b) Amendments and additions to Part I. Regulations.

(c) Amendments to Part II Regulations.
67The Speoirl Grants Committee further directed tho Secretary to point out to the Ministry that in dealing with cases of Parents&apos; Special Pensions it would save delay, cost and serious irritation to Local Committees if these oases could he rssessed forthwith &quot;both for grants up to the 1st September and for the Pension after that date, instead of the present arrangement, requiring Looal Committees to&apos; complete a further set of new and complica-ted forms within a very short interval.The representatives of Looal Committees on the Special Grants Committee stated that they wish it represented to the Minister of Pensions that Local Committeesare being sorely tried through the amount of work asked of them and they fear wholesale resignations of Local Committees if these are to be called upon to complete numerous and intricate forms and returns, which could be obviated, while in spite of their efforts delays continue to occur whidh are so vexatious both to the applicant and to themselves.
68the Chairman.I &quot;beg to report that the Section dealing with Part I Regulations regarding officers, held a meeting on Friday, October 5th to consider oases.The following tabular statement gives particulars cf cases decided by the Section:-RegulationTotal   Number   Number    Amount of annualgranted   refused allowances granted,32 2221(b) Renewals27 (2)  (b)  (iv)27 (b) (1) Renewals Recoverable if State Pension awarded27 (b) (2) Renewal Recoverable if Stat-o Pension awarded,242012 4 1 21 11 2 41  1 1 36. 0. 0,  88. 0. 0.  142. 0,0.  13. 0. 0,  205. 0. 0, 50. 0. 0.GEORGE   A. PONSONBY. Head of Officers1 Section 4.3th October, 1917.
69Tjrtne Chairman.1 beg to report that the Section dealing with part I Regulations regarding officers, held a meeting on Friday, October 12th to consider cases.The following tabular statement gives particulars of cases decided by the Section.RegulationTotal    Number      Number      Amount of annualgranted    refused    allowances granted,27 b.227 b.2 Renewal, Recoverable if State Pension awarded.27 2 (b) (iv) Renewal,22 Renewal20 Renewal24Cases referred for decision under Section 3, Sub-Section (1) (a).2 11 1 12 11 1A Number decided14. 100.   0.   0,  32.   0..   0. 13,    0,    0, &apos;52, 0, O,  72,   0.    0.15th October, 1917.(SGD.)    GEORGE A. POUSOlfBY.Lt.Head of Officers1 Section.
part   ii  regulations.I teg to report that the Section have dealt with the cases shown in the following statements:-During the week ended October 6th. During the week ended October 15th.Regulation	Total number of oases	Number granted	Number -refused	Amount of weekly allowances granted	Total number of cases	Number granted	Number refused	Amount of weekly allowances granted7(l)(f))	16	8	a	 1.13 .9	16	8	.8;	 2.18.9) Apprentices								9(b)      )	17	6	li	 1,18,9 ..	14	8	6	 2. 5.6   -7(2)         Disproportion	23	17	6	 5.  6.4	37	32	5	 9 ..10.69(c)    Temporary Cessation	 	 	 	-   -	1	 	1	10(b)       Paid Housekeeper	1	 	i	-   -	 	 	 	-   -( Increased Grant	2	2	--	17.0	6	6		 2.15.0l?(a)   (								( Extension of Time	1	1	 	-   -	--	-	--	-   -12(d)       Rate-aided	- -		--		1	1		2.3Institutions								IS            Unspecified	10	5	5	 10.14-3	8	1	7	 2. 0.0Emergencies								Paragraph 53	2	2		 12.15.0	. -*	--		- -- -(signed)     P. G. HIIIKS.
to  the  chairman.I have to report that the Section dealing with Part I of the Regulations held Meetings on the 2nd and 5th of October0The following tabular statement gives particulars of cases decided by the Section Committee:-During the week ending Sth October     During the week ending 15th OctoberAmount of Regulation             Total dumber   Number   weekly granted refused allowances granted	Amount of Total Number   Number   weekly granted refused allowances grantedI. Supplementary                                                         s*    d* Allowances:-Widows                   24           22           2      ) )6. 17.    2 Dependants             7            6           1      ) II.Special Allowances!:-Widows                    1             1           0      ) 1.    2.    6 Dependants            3            2           1      )	 .    s .    d. 31         27         4        ) )9, 15.    1 3            3          0        ) 3            12) )      10.    0 2            0          2        )In addition the Section considered 21 applications for grants under the Royal Warrant and made recommendation to the Ministry in 17 cases.	In addition the Section considered 19 applications for grants under tho Royal Warrant and made recom-mendation to the Ministry in 16 cases,(Signed)    STEPHEN DEMETRIADI.8.1^.17. 15.10.17.    Head 0f Branch No&apos; 2*
AAPPENDIX XXII STATEMENT AS TO PENSIONS AND THE CARE OF -DISABLED SOLDIERS IN OTHER COUNTRIES.NEWFOUNDLAND:     Summary of the first Report of Pensions andDisabilities Board.FRANCE-: Provision for State Guardinaship of WarOrphans, &amp;c,UNITED STATES:   The Alexander-Simmons Bill.GERMANY; Unemployed Disabled Men in the Rhine Province.Loans for Disabled Soldiers.-Hger.ce Department, -ocal Government Board,31st October, 1917.
73NEWFOUNDLAND.The Third Report of the Patriotic Association of Newfoundland, presented by Sir VI .E.Davidson, K.CM.G. as Chairman, on 24th May, 1917, contains an account of the work done by the Pensions and Disabilities Board from the date of its appointment in October, 1916.An Auxiliary Committee from the Women&apos;s Patriotic Association had been designated to co-operate with the Board. A Standing Medical Board, consisting of three medical men, had also been appointed.The Board, after mature consideration, decided to recommend to the Patriotic Association the adoption of the Canadian scale of pensions.   This recommendation was adopted, and the Board was authorised to begin to deal with cases awaiting pensions, and to pay them according to the Canadian rates.   Up to the end of February last 110 cases of returned soldiers had been considered: pensions had been awarded to 72, 19 were held to be non-pensionable, and 19 were still under considoration.Steps had been taken to ascertain the facts regard-ing the widows of the officers and men reported as killed or missing, with a view to making provision for them.It was intended to deal with Naval pensions also, but the Beard being officially advised that the Imperial regulations regarding naval and military pensions were being revised, it was decided to wait until official information on this point was at hand, and in the meantime to make some temporary provision for cases that must be dealt with immediately.The Board having been entrusted with the care of tuberculous soldiers and sailors, had taken over from the Government an institution which it was carrying on as a sanatorium for ten patients.    There were at the time of reporting six military and two naval patients:    if all tho men needing treatment were Induced to come in, the beds provided would be filled.It had been arranged that the Board should pay towards the upkeep of this institution an amount per man equal to that which it cost during the three months when it was carried on directly by tho Government, and that the ^omen^ Committee should provide any additional amounts needed.The organisation of a Convalescent Home had also been taken in hand, and it was hoped to be able to begin this service before long.The question of providing for the vocational re-education of disabled men who arc- unfitted by their disabilities from pursuing their former avocations, or their training for new callings, was receiving attention; and it was expected that before long some definite steps might be taken in this direction although the question was a difficult one
74PRANCE.&quot;La Revue Philanthropique&quot; for August, 1917 contains the text of a Law promulgated on the 27th,July, 1917 which provides for the State guardianship of children whose parents have been killed or injured as a result of the war.The Law is entitled, &quot;Loi instituant des pupilles de la nation&apos;.&apos;The Law provides that children whose father, mother guardian or breadwinner has either been killed or has died as the result of the war, or ic. unable to gain a living by reason of wounds received or Illness contracted as a result of the war, may be placod under bublic guardianship and aaintained and educated at the charge of the State until they are of age.    In the case of partial disability on the part of the parent or breadwinner the State will undertake partial responsibility.A child will not, however, become automatically a ward of the State on becoming an orphan or in need. Application on its behalf must be made by certain persons prescribed in the Law, and local courts will decide 7/hether or not the conditions which entitle a child to become a ward are fulfilled.An elaborate special organisation is set up to carry out the intentions of the law.   A central office, the &quot;Office national&quot; is to be attached to the Ministry of Public Instruction but it is to have its own staff.   The Council of the central office is to consist of 89 elected members, representative of the &quot;Conseils generaux&quot;, municipal authorities, educational interests and social organisations. This Council may co-opt a3 members women known for their work on behalf of children.    Three at least of the permanent officers of the central office must be women.In each department also an offico will be set up and a council formed composed cf members elected to represent the various local interests and representatives of the State.   One-third of the eiec-ied delegates must be vromen.The department offices have power to set up local committees in each commune, if they think it desirable.The department offices become, in effect, the guardians of all children who are adopted in accordance with the Law as wards of the State.   They have certain legal rights over the children, and are responsible for their care and well-being.    They may place them in families as boarders, or in institutions, and are responsible for their education, apprenticeship, and placing in employment.The department offices will have funds at their disposal, derived from local (departmental and communal) sources from the contributions   of public and private associations, from legacies and from the monies allotted to them by the centra office out of the credits voted by Parliament for the purpose.
75UNITED STATES:THEALEXANDER-SIMMONS BILL.Recent numbers of the relating to the above Bill.burvo^-itcontain articlesThe Bill which was introduced in the House and Senate in August last makes provision for compensation and life insurance for men killed, injured or made sick in the federal service, and allowances for their families during service.The Bill applies to enlisted men of all ranks in all branches of the military and naval forces and to the women of the army and navy nursing service.    It is drafted in four senctions:    Part I is administrative;   Part II makes provision for the families and dependants of men while on service;   Part III deals with compensation to those injuredto their families;   free hospital treatment for mutilated men are provided for and the require them to undergo vocational training and Part IV is a scheme of government insurance with in part by the insured and in part by the government.    Insurance against death or total disablement is provided at low rates for any amount not less that $1,000 or more than $10,000.on service and and appliances government may re-education; a premium paidPart IV of the Bill takes the form of an amendment to the Act which established the existing Bureau of v/ar Risk Insurance set up In the Treasury Department in 1914 for the benefit of seamen and the merchant service.   Application for insurance under this scheme was to be made within the first 120 days after entrance into the service.In order to encourage investment in the government insurance the Bill prescribes that the V/ar and Navy Departments may compel men who do not allot one half of their pay to dependants or for Insurance to deposit with the government the difference between their allotment and one half their pay.   The deposits will bear compound interest at 4$,The scales of compensation proposed in the Bill are:-In case of death:-Tc widow; no children 25% of pay but not less than $30 a monthMo &quot;n it ii ttand 1child   35^ &quot; &quot; 2 children40?i &quot; &quot; 3       &quot;       45fo &quot; &quot; 4       &quot;       50% &quot; No widow but 1 child   20% 11 &quot;      &quot; 2 children30fi &quot;3II It  4ii     n       ,, 5 To Vidowed mother40% 45% &quot; 50% &quot; 20% &quot;ti u ii u ii ii n it ii iiii ii ii it ii it ii it n iiii ii n iiii ii n ii ii ii$50 $55 $60 $15 $25 $35 $45 $55 $25n ii it ii ii ii ti it nn it it it it ii ii n ii ttwith a limit of $200.In case of total disablement:-If a widower with 1 child     50% of pay but not loss than $502 children55;, &quot; ,1     &quot;     &quot;     &quot;        &quot;   $603 or ndre 60;, 11 &quot;     &quot;     &quot;     M        &quot;   $70 childrentt iii)niiiiIf
76If the man&apos;has:- ,        .     rfneither wife nor children 4:0% of pa^r but not less than ^40 a wife but no &apos; 50* M&quot;   &quot;     ^-n^ 1 child 55%.      *   2 rtTiwr. &quot;      *0% &apos;1      &quot;      &quot;  470Dependent widowed mother   x0% P-uAn additional allowance Gf $20 In tho caso ot those ia need of an attendant.There are also scales of compensation for partial disablement.Where the disablement is partial provision is made that there shall be no reduction in the rate-of compensation for individual success In overcoming the handicap. Rehabilitation, re-education, and vocational training is to be enforced under penalty of loss of compensation benefits.Tho draft of this Bill was prepared by Judge Mack under the authority of the Council of National Defence, and endorsed by the Committee on Labour.    Its proposals were supported In many influential quarters and by the Secretary of the Treasury.   They were nevertheless criticised as being too costly, but it was pointed out by the Secretary of the Treasury that if the plan for insurance and compensation were rejected and a pension system resorted to the cost would possibly be as great, while the benefits would not be so comprehensive as those provided for in the Bill.There has been, not unnaturally, opposition to Part IV on the part of private insurance interests.   The insurance companies fear that the government may continue and extend the insurance scheme after the war.   A committee representa-tivs of insurance companies and societies reported adversely on government insurance over and above the compensation on the ground that the other provisions wore liberal enough.The House discussed the Bill on 13th September lastK and the section dealing with compensation was then consider-ably amended.   In the original draft compensation is provided for death or disability resulting from personal injury suffered or disease contracted &quot;in the course of the service&quot;. The phraso quoted was altered in the House to &quot;in the line of duty1&apos;,The scales of compensation proposed in the case of death were altered by the substitution of a scale of specific amounts higher than the minima prescribed in the scales quoted above.In the case of total disability compensation also, the percentages were eliminated, but whore tho disablement consisted of loss of both hands, feet or the sight of both eyes the rate of $100 a month 7ras fixed.   The rates are to __. . beIt was reported in the Press on 6th October that the United States Senate had ratified unanimously the Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Insurance Bill.
77be applied regardless of previous earning capacity.In actual working the percentages proposed in both scales would have applied mainly in the case of officers and the minimum amounts In that of the men.    It was argued during the discussion in the House that under the present army conditions the social status of the men is in many cases equal to that of the officers and that military rank was to an extent accidental,   k scale which allowed of differentia-tion was therefore Undesirable.The limit of insurance was reduced by the House from $10,000 to $5,000.In an article criticising the Bill as originally drafted Dr. I.M.Rubinow of New York (an insurance authority) objects to the allowances for children a3 too small.   He also criticises the Bill because it does not provide for any dependant other than the widow or widowed mother..   He considers that as aged parents and minor brothers and sisters havo rights under most compensation laws those should not be so lightly cast aside.The write fears that the substitution of &quot;in the line of duty&quot; for &quot;in the course of the service&quot; may give rise to difficulty in administration.With regard to the insurance provisions the writer considers that a system of compulsory insurance on a graduated scale adjusted to the various grades of service would be much more effective than an optional insurance.He considers the effort to re-habilitate and re-educate the partially disabled one of the most important provisions of the Bill.Joseph P.Chamberlain of Columbia University, writing in the &quot;Survey&quot; of 8th September, on Part IV of the Bill considers that the $5,000 limit of insurance is unnecessarily high,, and that the net result would probably, be that the better off men would alone be benefited by the higher amount..   He thinks it would be fairer to fix the amount of insurance for which the Government pays the war oremium at $2,000 or $2,500..The limitation to 120 days after enlistment as the time during which insurance must be applied fcr is criticised on the ground that promoted men would have no opportunity to increase their insurance or to apply for a policy if they had not already done so.    The writer urges that every advance in rank should entitle a man to make a new application.Attention is drawn to the importance of some provision to prevent an undue number of lapae3 after the war.
78GERMANY:UNEMPLOYED DISABLED SOLDIERS IK THE RHINE PROVINCE.In a recent number of &quot;Sozlale Praxis&quot; a report issued at the beginning of June last by the Committee for the Care of the Disabled in the Rhine Provinces la summarised.The 43 local committees on the Province report between them 927 cases of unemployed disabled soldiers; this number represents.4 per cent of the total number of disabled men known to the Provincial Committee.The casesare placed in four groups -209 are classed as willing tc work,92 as &quot;work-shy&quot;395 as   temporarily unfit for work,231 as permanently unfit.447 are single men and 480 married; the wives and children of the married men represent a total of 1,989 persons.The average loss of earnings for all these unemployed disabled men was estimated at 66.3 per cent. The average monthly pension received by them worked out at 55*30 M; in the case of the married men the pension represents 12,80 hi. for each member of the family.The greatest number cf unemployed in one class were the nervous cases, whe number 1S9, or 20.5 per cent; next the tubercular, 187 or 20.3 per cent; the blind number 16 or 1,8 per cent and those with an amputated arm 28 or 3 per cent.The men fit for work and willing to do it were as a rule unable to obtain it because their capacity was toe much reduced by their injuries.    Those shy of work did not obtain it, either because their capacity to work was under-estimated, or because they had no desire to work, or because they received a pension or some other allowance which dis-inclined them to make any effort.The majority of the unemployed who are willing to work are disabled in the arm or leg, showing that 3uch injuries are a severe handicap even in the present favourable-state of the labour market.   A large number are suffering from internal injuries; in these cases the serious reduction of bodily strength appears to be a great hindrance in obtaining work.The majority of those classed as work-shy are injured in the arm.   Nervous cases are also numerous and cases of injury to the head and legs.The temporarily unfit for work are tubercular or mental cases or those suffering from internal complaints.Among the permanently unfit are a large number of hopeless cases, most of whom will have to be maintained in provincial institutions for an indefinite poriod.    Thereare
79are also a number of nervous cases and of mental cases in this class.Resumption of work is found to be easiest for agriculturalists, brain workers, hand workers, and professional men and most difficult tQr unskilled men and miners.The amount of pension granted does not by any mean3 correspond to the decrease in earning power.   Pensions are lowest in the case of tubercular, nervous and internal cases. The highest pensionsare paid for arm and leg amputations, arm and leg wounds, head wounds, mental diseases and blindness.LOANS FOR DISABLED SOLDIERS.The Central Committee of the German Union of the Red Cross have informed the Imperial Committee for the Care of Disabled Soldiers that they are prepared to set aside certain sums to enable Provincial Committees for the Care -of the Disabled to grant loan3 free of interest to suitable disabled men.The loans will be granted only through the Provincial Committees for the Care of the Disabled, who will be required tr show that an applicant for a grant is a fit person as to character, past life and ability to use the money to advantage:    only married men of industrious habits are to be eligible.    The loans are intended to enable them to reinstate themselves in their former trade or profession. As a rule loans will not exceed  125 and must be repaid In 10 years.Soziale Praxis, 6 September, 1917.
APPENDIX XXIII, THE8rar Pensions GazetteA MONTHLY JOURNAL FOR WAR PENSIONS LOCAL COMMITTEES. AND FOR ALL INTERESTED IN THEIR WORK.1 Let us finish the work tee are in, to bind up the nation&apos;s wounds, to care for him who shall have borne the buttle, and for his widow and his orphans.&quot; Abraham Lincoln, Inaugural Address, March 4, 1865.JO.LONDON, NOVEMBER, 1917.ONE PENNY.Contents.-o-1110 CHILDREN        ..............losTHLY Notes..............-hi-: U.S.A. and War Pensions        .....x Address to Discharged Soldiers ocal Committees at Work No. 7.   The County of Dumfriesshire. .discharged Soldiers in Sheffield.....Tin: Treatment and Training of the DisabledNo. 7,   In Switzerland    ........Vktifigtal Limbs..............Jlestions and Answers......-o-Page. 77,78 78,79 79 8082,84 8688 89 91All communications to be addressed to the Editor, War Pensions Gazette,&quot; 22 Abingdon St., London,8.W. 1.The Children.OF all the great tasks which the War has laid upon us at home, the care and upbringing of the children whose fathers have fought and died for their country is perhaps the most vital. Each day brings a new casualty list the record of lives lost and broken ; and behind the list of lost lives there are so many broken homes.To help to the best of our ability in the recon-st ruction of these homes is the work which lies before all of us in the service of the Ministry of Pensions.What provision has been made for the care of t he children, and what help can be given to their mothers to fill the place of the natural support so suddenly taken from them ?This country has made a great effort to realise its responsibility for those who have fought the nation&apos;s battle. But when we try to carry out our duty towards the children they have left in our care-the most sacred of all trusts we cannot fail to see that there are many ways in which we eau improve the conditions of to-day.   Perhaps Imay briefly touch upon some of the conditions of a child&apos;s life in the bereaved home as it passes from babyhood to an age of independence.There are innumerable families where the mother is keeping her home together partly by her own earnings, and what to do with the little ones under school age divring the day-time is a serious difficulty. The ideal solution is, of course, for the mother to give up her work and stay with them at home, but at the present time, when the nation is in need of the labour of every able-bodied man and woman, this is not a practicable remedy. So we must fall back upon the second best solution and try to provide an adequate number of day nurseries. A creche started at Portsmouth two years ago for the babies of naval wives and widows who were mostly at work in the dockyard, proved a perfect god-send, and it is hoped that many others may be opened and carried on upon similar lines.From the day nursery the child passes to school. Here the State, by the national school system, already makes provision. This, however, does not suffice in all cases, and it is the declared policy of the Ministry to insure for the child a standard of education and training at least equal to that which would have been received had the father remained in civil life.The care of orphans has been the subject of special arrangements, and possibly Local Com-mittees do not all fully realise the opportunities open to them. Large grants have been distributed among the best managed orphanages throughout the country which will enable them to taka under their care children sent to them by the Special Grants Committee.Then there are the problems of illness which haunt every mother and from which there seem to be no escape in rearing a family. Money grants may enable the mothers to meet actual expenses, but expert advice as to hospital facilities and general home treatment is equally needed. Every mother longs to do what is best for her child, but
not every mother knows how to set about doing it. There must he in each locality at least one woman with special experience of children and their ailments, who will be willing to place her know-ledge at the service of others. On the question of feeding, the root of so many evils, communal kitchens may be strongly recommended as a means of providing children with the healthiest and most nourishing food. At a public kitchen started this year in Westminster we could never make enough rice pudding enlivened with jam sauce or a few sultanas there was an unending demand. Milk will be a great difficulty during the coming winter. Could not some effort be made to secure for the babies of our fighting men a sufficient supply at a reasonable price ? We are told that this question is &quot; now under consideration,&quot; and until some practical scheme is announced we can only suggest that each district might make a beginning, and the Local Committee lead the way.We must always bear in mind that it is not enough to frame regulations and obtain power to administer them; we must endeavour to make them so widely known that there is no mother in the whole country who, through lack of knowledge, is struggling with difficulties from which the State has given her a right to be relieved. We know how much added labour this propaganda entails. Every extension and development of an administrative system places a fresh strain upon the already overburdened local workers, who have all our sympathy and admiration for the untiring manner in which they have responded to the complex and often trying demands of their head office, but let them be assured that every effort, however ineffective it may have seemed, has been made to render their task not more difficult than was inevitable. And particularly in relation to the children, whenever a case has come up for help, it has been almost a point of honour never to say no.We are indeed &quot; a chosen generation,&quot; and have been called upon to bear an infinite burden of suffering.   But like the Happy Warrior &quot; Who doomed to go in company with pain And fear and bloodshed, miserable train, Turns his necessity to glorious gain,&quot;we also can find comfort in devoting all that we have left to the care of our children, and in handing on to a finer generation our country&apos;s heritage.PAMELA McKENNA.The Minister has received from a Manchester gentle-man, who desires to remain anonymous, an intimation of his readiness to subscribe  50,000 towards the cost of institutional treatment of disabled sailors and soldiers discharged from the forces in consequence of disabilities arising from the present war.Monthly Notes.-o--it is advisable to correct an error which has fou way into a number of London and provincial p The Minister is wrongly report An Error     having stated that there wore Corrected.      900,000 disabled men in receipt pension.   The fact is that this ber represents roughly the total number of pei awarded since the beginning of the war, and b officers and men, it includes widows and depeiK and children&apos;s allowances.   The actual numb officers and men pensioned for disability to 30th tember was approximately 225,000.-o-We give elsewhere an extract from an adm address delivered daily to men who are being disch from   a   certain   Discharge   ( An Address to   immediately before their return Discharged Men. to civil life.   We have printed portion of the address which is to be of interest to Local Committees.-o-In his article on the work of the Dumfriesshire Committee this month, the Chairman points oi great   value   of   Hospital   V: Hospital      Reports to his District Visit oi Visitors Reports, is a matter for regret that, iexperience, reports are still received in only a small proportion of cases. In Council Instruction, No. 1,531, it is requested th fullest facilities should be given to duly accn representatives of Local Committees to visit and both with hospital authorities and also with tin concerned.-o-The Ministry are aware that considerable diflk are being experienced by Local Committees in d with discharged men who, for vs The Discharged reasons, are in need of help d Man. the period intervening betweendischarge and the final assessiw pension. This, and other matters concerning discharged man, are now receiving attention, and necessary first step towards a proper considerati the whole problem, the Ministry have forwarded to representatives a statement of the cases of hat that have been brought to their notice, and have s that it shall be supplemented by the light of experience with a view to a proper realisation solution of the difficulties.-o-We print this week an avticle which appeared ii Sheffield Daily Telegraph on September 21st: It urges that Sheffield should i Local        a special effort to raise a local Funds.        for the benefit of its own citizen^ have  suffered in the  war.  .1 Local Committees can testify to the value of mi
81nd in dealing with their daily problems. Regulations u being constantly expanded to meet cases of hardship &quot;they arise, but pending the necessary sanction, a few bunds from an independent source may remove many grievance.or the future, it is inconceivable that, however idely the net of official regulations may be cast, yet here will slip through individual cases for which it is ipossible to provide adequately.Other cases will undoubtedly arise where, though mch sympathy will be felt for the widow or dependent, et it will be recognised that it is not possible to ask the tate to accept responsibility.-o-Owing to the ease with which employment can be btained there are at present only a few applications being received for the training of Training for   widows.   Instructions have, however Widows.      now been drawn up to enable Local Committees to deal with the matter systematic lines. The Ministry are pursuing very careful enquiry, with help of the Board of Education, the Ministry of abour, and Women&apos;s Employment Bureau and through ; Federation of Women&apos;s Trades Unions as to the ades for which training can be suitably provided and i conditions under which such training should be en, and it is hoped shortly to issue to Local Commit-an account of the results of these investigations. Vpplications for training have at present been con-id to Nursing, Massage and Midwifery.-o-It is a matter for congratulation that the problem of disabled soldier is now receiving fuller and more general recognition.   We welcome the The Tmperial appearance  of  a  thoughtful little Obligation.&quot;    book published under this title by Messrs. Grant Richards, Ltd. (price 6d. net).    The author, Mr. T. H. Mawson, of the iool of Civic Design at Liverpool University, is the 11-known Town Planning expect.   His idea is to iblish village communities to be inhabited by disabled n and their families, who will find their employment pecialised industries suited to then&apos; physical capacity. Mawson adds to the attractiveness of his scheme by sketches.   Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig con-butes an introduction to the volume.The second number of this Journal has now made its pearance.   It contains two very interesting articles on &quot; Neurasthenia and Allied Dis-Recalled to    orders &quot; and &quot; Tuberculosis,&quot; by Sir Life. John Collie, and Mayor P. Horton-Smith Hartley respectively.   Judge ynne James, in a letter, expresses a hope that the itutions now being set up to treat and train the ier may become permanent after the war and avail-e to the injured English workman in civil life, for hom at present there is an entire lack of such facilities.The U.S.A. and War Pensions.&quot;When the hour arrived for the American people to take up their share of the War&apos;s burden, their first and most natural resolve was to avail themselves of all that the past three years&apos; experience of the belligerent nations could teach them in every field of activity con-nected with the war.This determination was forwarded by the Allies by every means in their power. We have read in the news-papers of Naval and of Military Missions, but, though it has not attracted public notice, yet the work, for which in this country the Ministry of Pensions is res-ponsible, has also been the subject of special investigation on the part of the American Government.It has been a great pleasure to the Minister to afford all the information which it was in his power to give.In tracing out, for the benefit of the American officer concerned, a short history of the evolution of the work from those days in early August. 1914 (which America will never know and which were surely the best proof of the unpreparedness of this country) down to the present time, it brought home to the writer how great and how frequent have been the changes in our adminis-tration.At least we can never be accused of not preserving an open mind and not being ready to give any scheme a chance.This country has seen three changes in the system  first the purely charitable organisation, then the quasi-Government organisation, then the State itself.How much better we could do if we started again with our experience behind us.So far as we understand the American system (and in pension work they are not without experience) it has been decided to centralise all their wrork.Taking into consideration that there is at present at least no intention in America of supplementing either State allowances or pensions as with us, no difficulty should be experienced in adhering to this decision.It follows that there will be no local organisations corresponding to our Local Committees.If one word of criticism may be permitted, however, perfect the machinery may be, it is almost inconceivable that it may not break down in certain individual cases, and that it may be found necessary to have some scheme for advancing money to wives or to discharged men should this occur.The greatest innovation in American practice is the scheme of soldiers&apos; insurance by the State.This provides compensation for disability or death on service, varying from  8 to  20 a month, and for death up to  2,000.The policies are issued at the equivalent of pre-war rates, the Government acting as Insurer.The Cardiganshire War Pensions Committee have appointed Mr. J. D. Evans, a discharged soldier, as secretary to the Committee.
Address to Discharged Soldiers at a Discharge Centre,-o-Before you leave this Centre on your return to Civil Life, I want to talk to you for a few minutes about several matters connected with your discharge, and your pay and pension, in order that you may know from what sources and at what times money is due to you.Date of Discharge.-In the first place, I want to im-press upon you that your discharge dates three weeks from yesterday not from the day you go home but in three weeks time. Until you are actually discharged the Army is responsible for keeping you and for paying your wife&apos;s separation allowance as before. Now, you will receive  1 as an advance of gratuity on discharge in a few minutes, and the rest of your pay for the next three weeks as follows : (a) The Officer Commanding your old Unit  the one from which you came to this Centre will pay you in a few days time one iveelc&apos;s ration alloic-ance in advance, and, if your pay account is not in debt, a iveeJc&apos;s pay. You will also receive an allowance of 17s. 7d. in place of plain clothes if they have not been issued to you here, and any arrears of pay to which your old Officer Commanding knows you are entitled. This money should be sent to your home in about three or four days time : if you do not receive it then, write to the Officer Commanding your old Unit and tell him that you were sent home from the Discharge Centre to-day, but that you have not yet received your first week&apos;s pay. If you say that nicely, it will, doubtless, have the required effect.(b) A week from now you should receive a further week&apos;s ration allowance and pay (if you are not in debt) from the Regimental Paymaster of your old Corps R.F.A., A.S.C., or whatever it may be. I expect you are old enough soldiers to know the address of your Regimental Paymaster. He should also send you any balance of pay which his accounts show to be due to you.(c) Similarly, in a fortnighfs time you should receive again from the Regimental Paymaster your final week&apos;s ration allowance and pay, and also the balance of your account, if not settled before. This will include the balance of gratuity due on discharge.If you do not receive these two weekly payments from the Regimental Paymaster, go to the Local Pensions Committee about which I shall speak in a few minutes and ask the Secretary to write for you. By this help the money should be forth-coming.Separation Allowance. During these three weeks your wife will receive the separation allowance just as if you were still serving. The &quot; Ring Paper &quot; should not be withdrawn, and the money is payable at the same Post Office as at present. This separation allowance will, in addition, be paid in respect of two iceelcs afteryour discharge. By this means your return to civil will be made smooth and you ought to have no \vi about the home. If, for any reason, there arises difficulty about the separation allowance, go tc Local Pensions Sub-Committee, and explain the ca them, when everything will be done to help you.Protection Certificate. I have put on the back o Protection Certificates this buff form given to y( prevent your being called up again for at least weeks the information I have just given you. very briefly. If you forget what I have said, reai back of your Protection Certificate, or go to the Pen Committee.Pensions. I now want to speak about what haj after\ your discharge from the Army the pensio gratuity to which you may be entitled, and aboiii medical treatment or training for some new trade \, may be required.The business of looking after you after you have discharged from the Army has been entrusted to a Ministry specially arranged for the purpose-Ministry of Pensions. This body lias in each to sort of office (in some large towns more than one-Local Pensions Sub-Committee, as it is called. &quot; Pensions Sub-Committee&quot; is responsible for case of seeing that whatever pension or gratutit; get is the correct one ; of providing certain hospita other treatment if you require it; of arranging ci courses of training in skilled trades. It is to Committee that you should go for all help and a-Explain your case, say what you want, and tin that can be done will be done for you. For exa I referred a few minutes ago to certain payments made to you next week, and the week after li Regimental Paymaster. Well, if this money forthcoming, you should go to the Pensions Conn in your town you can get the address at any Post ( and tell them how things stand, producing, of a your Protection Certificate. The Secretary will write to the Regimental Paymaster for you, an money should then be forthcoming. Keep in i with the Pensions Committee who are there to hel; at all times.After dealing comprehensively and in a language with pensions, allowances and treat: the address concludes with Training. Lastly, I have a few words to say s training. This only refers to the men who are disek with a disability caused or aggravated by id service. Some of you men, as a result of your inj will not be able to earn your old wages at your old i Still, there may be a certain number who won capable of learning some new trade which they7 cov. and at which they could earn sufficient to ira living. Also some men, chiefly the younger one.&apos;-, have been in unskilled trades before the war, labtf messengers, etc., simply because they had no cl to learn a skilled trade. These might be capal becoming good workmen, capable of earning goodv
Bthey were taught a new trade. For men of these Rsses the Pensions Committee have authority to Binge for training in new trades. Some of the training PI)] De in workshops, some in technical institutes. For Ijtcli men as take up these courses of training, the same Bowances will he paid as I told you when I was speaking Bhospitals, and in addition there is a bonus or reward Bthe end, of 5s. for each week of the training. So that Bian who does a six months&apos; course, say, in bootmaking, K] not only be kept while learning, but will receive a Batuity at the end of  6 10s. in cash. I You &quot;must all remember, in this connection, that the Bndition of the Labour Market to which you are return-ffg just now is not what it is in normal times, or what it Kj be after the war. Therefore, although it is com-Bratively easy to earn good wages in munition factories Rid other jobs just now, after the war such posts will ffither not exist, or will be given to more capable crafts-Ken. So you should consider seriously whether, if you Have an opportunity it would not be better to become a milled workman with the chance of a definite wage after jjie war, than a munition worker now, and unemploy-Kent staring you in the face when the war is over. I This is all I have to say about this subject. I have Iked to give you an idea of what arrangements have Been made for your care after discharge, and to tell you mere to apply for information. My final words are :  In case of difficulty, go to the Pensions Committee.The Ministry of Labour.-o--I Enquiries have been received as to the number and nature of the Committees that are being set up by the pViinistry of Labour to deal with the training of the [disabled man. We give below particulars of these bodies, but Local Committees must, however, bear in mind that any questions upon which they may be in doubt should be referred by them to the Ministry of Pensions, Westminster House, Millbank.Trade Advisory Committees.These Committees are set up in conjunction with the Ministry of Pensions to advise as to the conditions under which the training of disabled men in the par-tic ular trade concerned can best be given, the best methods of training, the suitable centres, and generally to secure uniformity of method. Thirteen Committees have at present been set up for the following trades, all of which meet in London : 1.   Engineering and Shipbuilding. Sub-Committee Aeroplane Work.2.   Building.Sub-Committees Bricklaying.Carpentry and Joinery.Masonry.Painting.Plumbing.Plastering.Slating and Tiling.3.   Printing and Kindred Trades.4.   Furniture.5.   Leather Goods.6.   Boot and Shoe Manufacture (Machine).7.   Hand-Sewn Boot &amp; Shoe Making &amp; Repairing.8.   Tailoring.9.   Cinematograph Industry.10.   Cane and Willow Industry.11.   Gold, Silver, Jewellery &amp; Kindred Trades.12.   Brush Making.13. Dental Mechanics. The Committees consist of an equal number of representatives nominated by associations of employers and workpeople respectively, and in addition a repre-sentative of the Employment Department of the Ministry of Labour, and a representative of the Ministry of Pensions attend the meetings in a consultative capacity, but without the right to vote.Local Technical Advisory Committees.Where training in any particular trade has been approved by the Minister of Pensions, the Ministry of Labour may, on the advice of the Trade Advisory Committee, set up for the area in which the training is to be given, a Local Technical Advisory Committee. This Committee consists also of an equal number of representatives of Associations of Employers and Workpeople. Provided always that the two Ministries in consultation recognise the Committee as properly representative of the trade in that particular area, then the Local War Pensions Committee by whom the training is arranged shall consult this Local Technical Advisory Committee in regard to the following points :  (a) The selection of candidates for training, withregard to their suitability for the tra de ;(6) The suitability of the training offered intechnical schools and similar institutes ;(c) The suitability of the training offered in factories and workshops with special reference to the prospects of permanent employment and the rate of wages offered at the termination of the training ;(d) Any other technical point arieing out of the training of disabled men for this trade.The Local Technical Advisory Committee is to inform the Local War Pensions Committee and the Trade Advisory Committee if at any time, in their opinion, a sufficient number of men have been trained for their trade in the area in question.In addition to the above Committees, Advisory Wages Boards have been instituted in various towns, but, as it is understood that there may be further development in respect of these bodies, we defer consideration of them for the present.The Minister of Pensions has granted applications for separate Local Committees in the case of the Boroughs of Llanelly, Worthing, Guildford and Richmond, and of the Urban Districts of Abersychan, Abertillery, Bed-welty, Ebbw Vale and Tredegar in Monmouthshire.
Local Committees at Work.-o-No. 7.-The County o  Dumfriesshire.-o-Dumfriesshire covers an area of roughly 50 miles by 28, and has a population of about 100,000. It is chiefly agricultural, but it includes (1) the town of Dumfries, with a population of some 20,000, whose staple industry is tweed and hosiery manufacture ; (2) various other burghs, centres of tweed manufacture, engineering, etc. ; (3) a coal-mining district which employs about 1,000 men, while (4) since the war, there have sprung up at Gretna large munition works where, on land which up to 1915 was in the peaceful occupation of prosperous farmers, 25,000 bustling men and women are now turning out large quantities of high explosives for the destruction of the enemy of mankind.It will, therefore, be seen that the cases to be considered are very varied in character, but thanks to a capable and enthusiastic body of workers all are promptly dealt with, and so sympathetically that the wives, widows, dependents and men now look on the District Visitors as their friends and have confidence that every case of hardship will receive consideration.The whole staff is voluntary with the exception of two lady clerks, and our aim has been, while giving tfo the District Sub-Committees as much responsibility as is compatible with uniformity of treatment, to concen-trate in the Head Office as much as possible of the clerical work.Last July, we had a conference at headquarters to which all the workers were invited that they might have an opportunity of discussing each others difficulties and receiving guidance and advice. This was attended by over one hundred members and was so helpful and encouraging that we mean to repeat it from time to time.Owing to the great difficulty of communication in these days, either by road or rail, the Local Committee sit only occasionally to receive the reports of the various Sub-Committees which attend to different branches of the work.   The most important of these are : 1. District Sub-Committees. The county is divided into eight Districts, each with a Committee composed of two or more members of the Local Committee, a Chair-man, Secretary, and one or more Visitors for each parish or ward of which the District consists. It is the duty of these Sub-Committees on receiving notice from the Head Office of the impending arrival of a discharged man to get in touch with his family before his arrival if possible, then to see the man himself and to fill up a form giving particulars of his condition and wishes regarding treatment, training and employment. In this connection I would like to point out to any Hospital Visitors who may read this how very helpful their reports are to the District Visitors. We receive Hospital Visitors&apos; reports only in a small proportion of cases, but where they are received they enable the District Visitor to follow up the advice regarding the man&apos;sfuture career which the Hospital Visitor has found acceptable to him, thus avoiding a conflict of ad which might otherwise arise. Many men, after experience of military discipline, followed in most c by hospital restrictions, not unnaturally prefer t( left alone, when at last they get home and in the e days of our work were inclined to look with suspi on the attentions and enquiries of the Visitor, but oi to the tact with which they have been handled and satisfactory results which have followed the notifies of their wants, that attitude is being changed into of confidence that the Visitor and the Committee ] only one object in view the men&apos;s own advani The District Sub-Committees also investigate all cl for allowances, grants and pensions under the Eej tions. Powers under certain of the Regulations, Pan are delegated to them, and in the others they n recommendations to the Local Committee.2. Claims Sub-Committee. All claims received! the District Sub-Committees for allowances or gr are passed to this Committee, and its compositk designed to ensure similarity of decision in the diftV Districts ; for this purpose it reviews all decisio the District Sub-Committees, reserving to itself right of veto, but accepts their findings on poin! fact, for in country districts and in small towns sue those with which we deal there are few claims in v the circumstances are not personally known to at! one member of the Committee. The right of vcl retained because the Local Committee is responsiH the Auditor for seeing that all payments are autlio: by the Regulations. The Claims Sub-Committe composed of the Chairman of each of the- District Committees (who has the power to send s substitute the Secretary or some other member o: Committee) a representative of Labour, two men of the Head Office staff and a Secretary who specia in the Regulations. Thus each District Sub-Comm is able to satisfy itself through its representative its claims are adequately considered, and is kei touch with what is being done in every other part o: county. The Rural Committee knows how the cl of the townsmen are dealt with ; that of the mi area sees that the claims peculiar to it receive the s treatment as those of the engineering district and si3. Disablement Sub-Committee. As on this ( mittee rests the responsibility for seeing that e discharged man is provided with the medical treati most suited to his needs, for re-educating him, am finding him employment, its work is of far-reac importance. It has Sub-Committees dealing seve with (1) Treatment of which the Medical Officer oi County is convenor; (2) Training with H.M.I.S. expert in technical training, as convenor, and (3)Em] ment presided over by the Manager of the Employ) Exchange. The Convenors of these three Sub-( mittees sit also as an Advisory Committee along an employer of labour, a working man and the Chaii of the Local Committee, presided over by the Chaii of the Disablements Sub-Committee, for the purpo
8Bterviewing men who want assistance and advice, lie have just added a discharged soldier to this Com-littee; a man who was one of &quot; Kitchener&apos;s first KdO 000,&quot; and was knocked out at the battle of Loos. t[e is anxious to devote his spare time to helping his Bsabled comrades, and we expect that his experience mil be helpful. Men when they come before this iommittee (which is not as formidable in practice as it jboks on paper), are asked to bring with them, or if possible to send in advance, a report by their Panel f)octor on their condition, and with that assistance the fledical Member of the Committee is generahy able jo advise as to what treatment is necessary or whether jfxpert advice at an orthopaedic and other hospital should le obtained ; and knowing his physical condition and jhis pre-war history the other members of the Committee ire in most cases able to suggest a choice of training or Employment which in most cases leads to practical lesults. At first we had some difficulty in inducing men to come and be interviewed. It is something of an Id-deal for a man to appear before a bench of solemn look-Int,&apos; strangers, and in some few cases may be reminiscent fof former wrongdoings and moreover the fear still does [exist that if a man improves his earning capacity it will tre-act upon his pension. But we are overcoming that, and at each meeting of the Advisory Committee a larger [proportion of those invited turns up, and now we have mien applying to come. Our thanks for that are due largely to the local press, who gratuitously publish the results obtained, and also to our District Visitors, to whom we circulate particulars of specific cases benefited, foi there is no doubt that one concrete instance of what has been done is better argument with a disabled man than a learned dissertation of what may be done.Though the men know pretty well in general terms that they can obtain certain benefits by undergoing treatment and training it comes home to them more pointedly when they hear that John Smith, whom they knew as a man crippled with rheumatism and drawing a pension of 16s. 6d. has been sent through the intervention of the Local Committee to Buxton for a cure, during which he is getting 27s. 6d. and 13s. 9d. for his wife, or that Tom Jones, who owing to his disability is no longer lit for his former occupation as ploughman, has got a job as a machinist in an engineering works with 35s. a week to add to his pension.Our experience is that owing to the arrangements made by the Ministry of Pensions and by the Joint Committee for the South-West of Scotland to which we belong, we have little difficulty in dealing with men requiring treatment, but it is not so easy to supply the training required. We can give training locaUy in agriculture and in some trades, and as the Joint Com-mittee will no doubt soon have completed its arrange-ments we hope that re-education will shortly be provided tor ah who require it. We were led to expect from the Minority Eeport of the Departmental Committee on the Employment of Sailors and Soldiers on the Land that there would be large demand for training in agriculture, and arrangements were made and sanctioned by theStatutory Committee for the training of twelve men at a model farm in this neighbourhood, but so far with the exception of one man, who was before enlistment a general farm worker and being unable to continue in that occupation has asked for training as a shepherd, no desire has been expressed for any form of training in agriculture.Employment is also a problem not because there is difficulty in rinding work, for thanks to the energy of the Local Manager of the Employment Exchange, we have few men on our index for whom it is not available, but rather because so much employment of a temporary nature is offered at high rates of wages that men prefer to take it rather that fit themselves for what would be to their more lasting advantage. At the munition works at Gretna to which reference has already been made, unskilled men can get 45s. a week, and were earning even more while construction was in progress. While these conditions continue it is understandable that only the most farsighted will undertake training, generous as are the terms offered under the new Royal Warrant, or forego the tempting temporary 50s. for a more permanent 35s. a week.At first we contemplated adding an employment bureau to our other activities, and we issued 700 copies of an appeal to employers, asking those who were willing to find employment for one or more partially disabled man to fill in a detachable slip and post it to us. The result was 40 replies !We very soon found too that it would require from the District Secretaries a larger amount of time than could reasonably be expected of busy men doing volun-tary work. We also found that the Employment Exchange was already in touch with the men, so we gave up the idea, and now we act in close co-operation with that department. We propose to make a point of seeing that suitable employment is found for every man who undertakes treatment or training and will also give particular attention to any who may prefer to apply to us rather than to the Exchange, but further than that we think it unnecessary and inadvisable to do so.For a time, when the unskilled men employed in construction work at Gretna were being discharged in large numbers, we had some trouble with the tramp question, as many of the men began to find it profitable to tramp to then- homes, soliciting charity on the way, and as the high road from Gretna to the north runs through Dumfriesshire, they commenced then operations in this county. We were thus faced with the difficulty of seeing a number of maimed men begging on the road, whom the general public thought it was the duty of the Local Committee to assist. We eventually laid down a rule, with the sanction of the Ministry of Pensions, that in any case where a man could show good reason for being unable to pay his railway fare and that he had a prospect of employment on reaching his destination, his railway fare might be paid. This is a matter which must be handled with discretion for it is obviously open to abuse, but it is one which will no doubt have to be
faced everywhere, though at the moment it is less in evidence here than it was.Two other Sub-Committees of the Disablements Sub-Committee have come into existance in the last few days. One to carry out the instructions contained in Circular No. 17, dealing with applications from men who claim that their invaliding is wrongly classed as non-attributable, and we mean to approach that question in the spirit which evidently inspires the Appeal Tribunal over which Judge Parry presides ; the other to consider claims for Alternative Pensions.Our records relating to discharged men are kept by means of card indices, of which we have at present six : (1) A white card (the main index) is made out for every discharged man and filed alphabetically, bearing the number against the man&apos;s name in the register.(2) When treatment is asked for, the second card (green) is made out and filed according to the nature of treatment he is undergoing.(3) When training is undertaken a blue card is made out with particulars of the training and similarly filed in the third index.(4) When employment is wanted, a fourth card is made out and indexed under the nature of employ-ment desirod.(5) There is an index (alphabetical) of employers who offer employment, and(6) Another indexed according to nature of employment offered, showing particulars of who offers it and on what terms.All correspondence and information concerning each man is placed in a folder bearing the number of the case in the register and in the main index. We can thus tell at a glance how many men are undergoing treatment or training at any time and whether in an institution as an out-patient or at home, what offers of employment have reached us and what men want it, and full particulars of each case are to be found in the folder.As returns required by the Statutory Committee, Circular 30, will not be required after September, these particulars may not be so necessary in future, but no doubt other returns will be required in their place and a card index system is so adaptable that it would be a matter of no great difficulty to re-arrange it to suit future requirements.But office organisation alone will not bring to the men who have fought and bled, nor to the women who have silently suffered for us the benefits which the nation has resolved they shall have as a right, and the more I see of the work the more am I impressed with the importance of those who unostentatiously carry out the duties of Visitor, whether in the crowded streets of the busy town or the lonely glens of the quiet countryside ; they are the good Samaritans who inspire new life and hope, who bring to many a fireside the assurance that the nation has not forgotten those to whom it owes so much.W. MAITLAND-HEPJOT, Chairman Dumfriesshire local Committee.War Commissions and Committe-o-In accordance with a request we have received, give below a list of certain Commissions and Commit set up to deal with public questions arising out of war, with which it is possible that Local Commit may be more particularly concerned in carrying their duties : Empire Settlement Committee. Secretary, Mr J. Harding, Colonial Office, S.W. 1.Food Ministry. Grosvenor House, W. 1.Graves (Soldiers) Prince op Wales Committki Secretary, Capt. S. C. Taydor, Winchester House. James&apos;s Square, S.W. 1.Labour Ministry. Secretary, Mr. D. .T. Shacklei C.B., Montague House, Whitehall, S.W. 1.Trade Advisory Committees (Disabled Soldi and Sailors). For details see separate article.Enquiries from Local Committees regarding the ab should be addressed to the Ministry of Pensions. AY minster House, Millbank, S.W. 1.Land Settlement after the War Committe! Secretary, Mr. D. C. Barnard, 4, Whitehall Place, S.A1Military Service (Civil Liabilities) Departs  Secretary, Imperial House, Kingsway, W.C. 2.Milk Distribution Committee. Secretary, Jii Mackintosh, 72, Victoria Street, S.W. 1.National Health Insurance Commission. ] lington House, Buckingham Gate, S.W. 1.National Relief Fund. Secretary, Mr. L. Brock, 3, Queen Anne&apos;s Gate, S.W. 1.National Service Department. Secretary, AY: sor Hotel, Westminster, S.AV. 1.Pensions Ministry. AA^estminster House, Millb: S.W. 1.Pensions Appeal Tribunal. Secretary, Mr. .T. Parry, 22, Abingdon Street, S.W. 1.Relief of Distress Committee. Secretary, Mr V. Symonds, C.B., Local Government Board, S.W. 1 1.   London. Secretary, Mr. A. N. C. She!Local Government Board, 8.W. 1. 2.   Women&apos;s Employment.- Secretary, Miss R. Mac Arthur, 8, Grosvenor Place, S.AV 3.   Professional Classes. Secretary, Mr. J. Talbot, Board of Education, S.AV. 1. Petrol Control Committee. Chief Clerk, Mr. B. Cole, 19, Berkeley Street, W. 1.Soldiers and Sailors (Disabled) Employment British Railways Committee. Secretary, Mr. 1. Scott Main, 47, Victoria Street, S.W. 1.Soldiers Dependants&apos; Appeals Assessment Co MITtee. Secretary, Mr. J. J. R. Bridge, 142, Croim Road, S.W. 7.War Charities (Control) Committee. Secrets Mr. J. A. Johnston, Home Office, SW. 1.War Savings (National) Committee. Secreta&apos; Mr. T. Chambers, Salisbury Square, Fleet Street, E.C.War  Refugees  Committee. Secretary,   Mr. Maudslay, General Buildings, Aldwych, W.C. 2.
Meetings of Local Committees.wolverhampton.H a recent meeting the Chairman expressed his ftisfaction at the opportunity offered to the Local Immittee to assist the man whose case was being Iferred to the Special Appeal Tribunal, f The Chamber of Commerce was asked to receive a Iputation with a view to obtaining the best facilities It training and employment. It was further resolved Lt a report should be drawn up of the difficulties sperienced by the Committee in meeting properly the eeds of the discharged man.Plymouth.It was agreed at a meeting of the Committee that need listed for a home locally for the treatment of discharged bkliers and especially those suffering from neurasthenia, id the Press were asked to state that offers to lend a louse with some land, suitable for a rest home, would Be gladly welcomed.West Ham.It was agreed to co-opt two nominees of the local jranch of the  National  Federation  of  Discharged loldiers and Sailors to serve on the Canning Town and itratford Sub-Committees respectively. Out of 75 applications for the post of chief assistant the Secretary, an ex-soldier was appointed.Wallasey.An appeal was made by the Chairman for a sum of &apos;500 to enable the Committee to continue the payment if certain small grants which had been made during the )ast three years.Some of the payments they desired to make were sitlier outside the Regulations or slightly in excess of the prescribed scale. Help had in particular been extended to widowed mothers or childless wives of soldiers with a smalt allowance which they were unable to supplement by earnings, to dependants of naval men without separation allowances, and to provide railway fares where it was desired to visit wounded soldiers in distant hospitals. It was estimated that about  25 per week was necessary to maintain the present basis of distribution.Merthyr.it was resolved that, owing to the difficulty experi-enced in providing satisfactory convalescent treatment for men discharged from the Army and Navy after hospital treatment, the Joint Committee should be urged to take steps to provide an institution in Glamorganshire.Isle of Wight. The Committee had made representations to the Ministry suggesting that, except where a pension had been granted for specific injuries, Local Committees should be consulted before a pension or gratuity was finally settled.   They reported that a reply had beenreceived from the Ministry stating that awards of pensions were made in accordance with the decisions arrived at by the medical boards, and so far as the pension granted purely for disablement was concerned, the question of earning capacity did not enter. As regards gratuities, these Avere mainly dependent upon the extent of the disability on discharge, and the length an d character of the man&apos;s service. There was, however, no objection to the representation of a &quot; gratuity &quot; case for further consideration on the grounds of its being exceptional .because of the man&apos;s high pre-war earnings, just as was done in the case of alternative pensions.County of Somerset.At a recent meeting the Chairman alluded to the constant increase in the work, particularly in connection with disabled men. It was stated that of the 725 cases of discharged soldiers already disposed of by far the greater number had returned to work many to their former occupations. Those who wrere permanently unfit were not very many, and only three or four had died. In regard to the 535 cases reported on they had been referred back to the visitors, as most of the men were still unfit, suffering from shell shock or other ailments and requiring a considerable period of rest. A large number of the men hoped when they were well to be able to return to their former employment. The Committee owed a great debt of gratitude to the Aasitors, who were scattered all over the country, for the great trouble they had taken in dealing with the cases., Thirty-seven cases were being treated, and 109 required training or work. In regard to the latter he was of opinion that it was absolutely necessary, if the matter was to be dealt with efficiently, that this branch of the work should take up one man&apos;s whole time. It required a great deal of detailed investigations, and the one who undertook the wrork Avould require both tact and sympathy.noravich.A report of the After-Care Committee stated that the training classes for discharged soldiers as boot and shoe Avorkers had been started at the Technical Institute. Further applications at the rate of tAvo or three a week were coming in, and it Avas hoped that other classes Avould be started shortly.The Chairman said they had not had many applica-tions in Norwich for agricultural training. A few men AA^ere out undergoing training in horticulture, but not in agriculture, and these were in the hands of private firms.It Avas stated that from January to August claims and pensions bad increased by 350 per cent.Yorkshire (West Riding).The report of this Committee shovre that upwards of 30,000 discharged disabled men AA^ere on the register, and discharges at the rate of 2,000 a month were being received. At present upwards of 900 men had been given institutional treatment, while arrangements had -been made for 250 men to receive a course of training.
A special Sub-Committee bad been established, at the request of the Ministry of Pensions, to hear appeals against the refusal to award State pensions. So far 150 appeals had been received, and the Sub-Committee were waiting particulars from the Ministry as to the ground of refusal. Appeals were being received at the rate of 50 a month. Since the beginning nearly 4,000 cases of widows, involving upwards of 8,500 children, had passed through the hands of the Committee. A large number of appeals had been received from widows for alternative pensions and special allowances. There had been dealt with 2,500 cases of dependents (other than widows) of men who had lost their lives, and new cases at the rate of about 350 per month were coming to hand. He was sorry to say that so far upwards of 110 wives, widows, and dependents of soldiers had forfeited their allowances of pensions owing to misconduct or other reasons. In a number of instances the Committee were acting as almoners.Correspondence.-o-To the Editor, &quot; War Pensions Gazette.&quot;Motherless and Orphaned Children.Dear Sir, The reference in the account given in your October issue of the meeting of the Burton Local Com-mittee, to the need of homes for motherless and orphaned children suggests to me that it might be useful to &quot;acquaint Local Committees, through the medium of your valuable publication, with the fact that a Home for a limited number of Roman Catholic war-orphaned boys is being set up here in Bodmin by the Sisters of Mercy. &apos;The locality is very healthy and there is an elementary school near by staffed by the same Sisters. The idea is to keep the establishment, if possible, exclusively for war orphaned children so that it will have since only a small number can be accommodated the character of a home rather than that of an ordinary orphanage. Building alterations are now in progress, but meanwhile a few children could be taken. Applica-tion should be made to the Superioress, Convent of Mercy, Bodmin, Cornwall.Yours faithfully, (Signed)   (Rev.) R, A. McETROYS,Member of Bodmin Local Committee.The Korrespondenzblatt discusses&apos; a proposal lately made at Essen for establishing a separate organisation or Union of Economic Associations for disabled soldiers in Germany. The Trade Unions, of which the journal is the organ, contend that, there is no need for such an organisation, and that by their co-operation with the employers&apos; associations, they have themselves in many cases secured the reinstatement of disabled soldiers. It asks those disabled on service to rely on the Trade Unions to which they formerly belonged, and says that they are ready and willing to assist them in every way.Discharged Soldiers.-0-In Sheffield.-o-So far no special effort has been made by the cit Sheffield to show its gratitude to its discharged sol  to those citizens who have returned to them v health and fortunes impaired after having risked al the service of their country.The Lord Mayor of Leicester is endeavouriun complete a fund for  100,000 for the benefit of charged soldiers in Leicester, and in his appeal puts case so ably that we cannot do better than quote it&quot; In the first place it must not be forgotten that vast majority of those who have been called upor render this memorable service had no greater resj sibility for the defence of the country than those have remained behind in comparative security, exi that they were younger and were physically fit for task.   Further, they had not chosen soldiering career, otherwise it might be said with some shov reason that they, like those in other walks of life, be prepared to take the rough with the smooth.&quot; But they were our neighbours, our fellow wort our fellow tradesmen, and they had their home inte just as others had. When the call came they expected to make the sacrifice, and in the majorit cases they cheerfully went forth not counting the. impelled by the highest sense of duty to the State givirg up in many cases good situations with far lx incomes than the Army pay they received. In i instances the businesses of small owners establi after years of anxious toil had to be closed d involving considerable loss to themselves.&quot; In face of the foregoing, although it is already known, it needs to be stated again, that many remai at home have been in receipt of larger incomes they were before the war. They have enjoyed the tection of body as well as estate, and on all such t surely rests a binding responsibility towards those have been disabled&apos;while rendering this national sen:Mr. Jonathan North has been Mayor of Loicestti three years, and a well-known public man in She who knows him speaks in the highest terms of his humanity and largeness of heart. It is such a tc as this which is needed in dealing with that bur question of the treatment of the discharged soldier.Various Efforts.The Government has done and is doing its I The scheme for training disabled soldiers, making ti at the same time an allowance of  1 a week, is admin The arrangement for graduating pensions accordiii; income earned before the war does away with a t deal of injustice. But it is a question whether Government scheme, however generous or \vi administered, obviates the need for a fund to deal special conditions that may not have been taken account, and to supply not merely necessities, not i justice, but bounty in the shape of a few luxuries, al
I. to act as tangible evidence to the man returned roken  down after the unspeakable experience  of odern warfare that his city has not forgotten him. Later, no doubt, there will be talk of a memorial to e men who have fallen at the front.   No better cmorial could be erected than the kindness and care own now to the one discharged as unfit for further nice.   Such is the memorial which would have been est appreciated by the man who has laid down his &apos;e for his country.So Leicester has evidently thought, at any rate, in ising this big fund in honour of its discharged soldiers, ot as a charity, as Leicester&apos;s Lord Mayor says.Charity ? No ! A thousand times No. A sacred ebt which will beyond doubt be most cheerfully paid v the people of Leicester. To speak of what is pro-osed to be done as &apos; charity &apos; shows a total misconcep-on of the situation. Who ever thinks of the work of le Red Cross and St. John as &apos; charity&apos; ? Further, he Government have made ample hospital accommoda-ioD for the wounded. They have equipped them with very thing necessary for restoration, but nobody hjects to the et ceieras motor rides, social functions, ifts of various kinds. Nor has it ever occurred to those ho have taken delight in these visible manifestations f goodwill and appreciation that they were bestowing charity,&apos; and yet what a world of difference has been jiade by such kind acts, the &apos; touch of nature,&apos; etc.Sheffield&apos;s FameSheffield has made itself a name by its treatment of he wounded soldiers.   A resident recently heard some [Canadians discussing this in a railwajr carriage. I &quot; We all pray at the front to get to Sheffield,&quot; theytea id.; Not only has Sheffield supplied the best of surgeons, who have toiled with self-denying devotion and sacrifice for the benefit of the boys, but gardens have been thrown open for their enjoyment, motor-cars have been given up to take them for rides, flowers have been sent week by week, and the Soldiers&apos; Comfort Depot, that wonder-fully managed organisation, has, through the support of Sheffield people, been able to keep up a constant supply of luxuries and necessaries of all kinds at the hospitals.No one thinks of these things as superfluous. No one would wish to hand the invalid over to the Govern-nient and forbid private enterprise. The same applies to the work of the Army and Navy Aid Committee. Sir Edward Ward is best qualified to speak of the differ-once to the men between the Government issue of socks and the home knitted variety, with love in every stitch, and perhaps, if the work is a child&apos;s, a tiny note in baby handwriting stuffed in the toe. The &quot;writer heard recently of a soldier on leave who made a point of calling to see the child who had written one of these small notes.And does the discharged soldier want none of these Uttle attentions ?The fact that the men themselves feel the need of special funds to deal with disabled men, widows andorphans, is proved by the fact that so many regiments have raised such funds. A concert held by The Pelicans recently in Sheffield was for this purpose.Sir Douglas Haig himself writing to the organiser of such a fund, says : &quot; I wish you all success in your undertaking. I can think of no more worthy object than the succouring of those who have freely given their health and strength in their country&apos;s service. Gifts for such a purpose are no charity, but the due fulfilment of a nation&apos;s debt.&quot;There are, of course, existing organisations which have done much good work, such as the Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Help Society, but this is after all, a more or less private institution got up by certain members of the com-munity all credit to them and hardly known even by name to the man in the street. Also the funds of this organisation are small.Need for a Fund.There is no fund to do what the Leicester Fund is doing, that is, among other things, giving financial assistance to suitable and deserving men to start again the business relinquished when enlisting. Yet one of the pathetic tragedies of the war is the way in which such men have had to give up businesses to which they have devoted their best energies for years, and to come back and find themselves with nothing but a pension. To quote an actual case in point a man with no income except his pension, married, and with several children at school, has started a poultry farm with every prospect of success. Until he begins to make a profit he must guarantee the bank for an overdraft of  50. How is he to obtain such a guarantee ? Sheffield Daily Telegraph.The Oxfordshire War Pensioners Committee recently sent two discharged soldiers to the Northampton Poly-technic Institute, Clerkenwell, to undergo a course of training to fit them for work in connection with the distribution of electricity. It is the custom at the Institute to award two prizes at the end of each course, and at the close of the course finished last week, the first prize was awarded to Mr. John Smart, of Headington, and the second to Mr. W. H. Gibbard, of Woodstock  the two men sent by the Oxfordshire Committee. -o-Mr. Watson Hartley, chartered accountant, Colwyn Bay, has been appointed inspector of accounts under the Ministry of Pensions for the six counties of North Wales and Cheshire. Mr. Hartley was for some years account-ant to the Colwyn Urban District Council, and prior to that chief assistant to the borough treasurer of Nelson. His headquarters will be at Llewelyn Chambers, Colwyn Bay.-o-The Minister visited Birmingham on the 15th October and met representatives of the Local Com-mittees for that and adjoining districts and discussed with them their difficulties. The Minister subsequently opened a hostel provided by the Eccentric Club at Edgbaston with accommodation for 50 men.
The Treatment and Training of the Disabled.--o-No. 7. In Switzerland.-o-Report on Training Courses for Prisoners oe War in Switzerland. -o-In place of our usual article we make no apologies for including this month an extract from the very interesting report presented by Major Mitchell to the Chairman of the British Red Cross Society regarding the training courses that have already been arranged for British interned men in Switzerland. We alluded to the enquiry into this matter, which has aroused general interest, in our last number, and the progress made seems remarkable.* *        &quot; * *Lord Sandwich, who has left for Holland, has desired me to report the progress that has been made in the arrangements for organising courses of training amongst the British interned in Switzerland in accordance with the wishes of the British Red Cross Society.Piano Manufacture. Arrangements were made for Messrs. Brinsmead&apos;s managers to visit Switzerland and ascertain the possibilities for purchasing materials, etc. They have returned quite satisfied with their enquiries and the accommodation we suggested they should utilise. They are prepared to send out at once instruc-tors and to employ from 20, increasing to 60 or 80 men, on productive work subject to transport facilities being granted. There should be no difficulty in this as any cost that may be incurred would be far less than the normal cost of training would be, and Messrs. Brinsmead undertake to pay all other expenses, and to pay full value for all work done.Leather Work. Arrangements have been completed with Messrs. Worrall and Company of Birmingham, to send out three expert members of their staff, materials, etc., sufficient to employ 50 to 60 men, on remunerative work, full value being paid for all work done by the internees.Tailoring. Arrangements have been made with the Royal Army Clothing Stores, whereby at least 40 men may be instructed in military clothing, and all materials and appliances have been provided free, and one of their chief master tailors has been lent as chief instructor.Carpentry and Joinery. A very skilled instructor who possesses the Silver Medal of the Worshipful Company of Carpenters and has also had over ten years&apos; experience in teaching has arrived in Lucerne, and Lieutenant-Colonel H. P. Picot, Officer i/c British Interned in Switzerland, has been asked to detail 20 men to commence at once.Electrical Work. A skilled operative electrician, who has had experience also in teaching,&apos; has arrived in Lucerne and will as soon as possible start with 20 men, to be increased to 30 as soon as the work-shop equipment is ready. Several gifts of valiu apparatus have already been promised by well-kno firms towards equipping this class.Motor Mechanism. Additional premises have b secured at Vevey so that 45 men can be put through course of training at one time, and we are hoping t Lieutenant Wallis, who has just been repatriated has permanent injury, may be permitted to return Vevey to continue the work he has done with s success during his internment.   In connection v the Motor Mechanics School we desire to express appreciation of the kind offer of the proprietors of &quot; Autocar,&quot; who have undertaken to cover the cos conducting this school.   We estimate the cost to bt least  600 per annum.   A cheque for  200 for the quarter&apos;s cost has already been received.Watch and Clock Repairing.-Arrangements arc progress for starting a special instruction course watch and clock repairing. There is at the pre time, and was before the war, a great dearth of repair and the Watch and Clockmakers Employers&apos; Federal have guaranteed places for 100 men when trained.Commercial Courses. A Commercial Training ( has been commenced and 17 men have been deta for this course.Art Training. A very able Scotch artist was covered amongst the internees, and it is propose hold a special Art Training Course for any of the who previous to joining up were art students.The main feature in all our arrangements has 1 as far as possible to provide training in such tr where employment would be assured on return of men to England, and such assurance has been obtai in practically all the courses so far organised.The Swiss military authorities, together with Col Picot, agreed to our proposals : (1) That Vevey, Nurengen and Seeburg should regarded as industrial centres and only the woi sent there, thus preventing any distraction from t work by the presence of a number of non-workers.(2) That a regulation should be made requiring ei Fit man to do 30 hours work per week of some kind prevent him degenerating into anidle and purposelessWe hope at an early date to commence course training in Acetylene Welding, for which there is a field of employment.   Also in Boot Repairing Making, the Royal Army Clothing Department ha offered similar facilities as those given for tailoring.Major Charley who, during the period of his int ment took considerable interest in training, has sented to return to Switzerland and will join the of Colonel Picot, who has agreed to arrange for him superintend the work at the various centres, viz., V Nurengen and Seeburg.Holland. Lord Sandwich is at the present time Holland making a survey of possibilities of sin work there, and so soon as tho proposed exchanu prisoners has been made we shall endeavour to i similar satisfactory arrangements for the internet that country. ROBERT MITCHELL, Maj
Artificial Limbs.-o-Tho following letter addressed by the Ministry to the swich Local Committee in answer to questions raised r them on the supply of artificial limbs may be of neral interest: &quot; I am now directed by the Minister of Pensions to ply to your letter on the subject of the care and treat-ent of the artificial limbs supplied to disabled sailors nd soldiers. I am in the first place to express the icknowledgements of the Minister of the interest taken, v your Committee in the subject, and of their action n bringing bo his notice the difficulties experienced by isabled men, and to say that he is glad to have this p port unity of explaining to them through your Com-littee how these difficulties may best be met. As egards the earlier fitted cases to which you refer, I am o explain that the practice at Eoehampton is that rhen any man returns to hospital with an obsolete )attern of limb, a new limb of the latest approvedIattorn is requisitioned, and this has repeatedly been one. If you wiU bring to the notice of this branch of le Ministry cases in which a more up-to-date pattern in with advantage be supplied the necessary arrange-lents will be made. The short thigh stumps to which ou refer are now fitted with a tilting table, and the -suits are good. Probably the cases under question were supplied with a leg before the tilting table had been devised. All cases of above-knee amputation are now being fitted with inside knee control. This takes &quot;all the friction from the shoulder to the inside of the knee (Le., inside the bucket), and is e great improvement on other controls either in front or at the side.&quot; The Minister will be obliged if you will report the names and regimental numbers of the man who was unable to wear his artificial leg, and of the two men who wore peg legs provided by themselves. It is the inten-iion of the Government that these men should be pro-vided with sound and serviceable artificial limbs, and they should be instructed to produce for examination at the nearest military hospital those which were sup-plied to them by the State, in order that a report may thence be sent to this office for consideration and action. The same instruction applies to cases such as are referred to in your letter where a small mishap necessitates repair. The officer in charge of the hospital is able to say at once whether repairs can be carried out locally, and if so, he is authorised to have them done. This is considered better than leaving the disabled man to do his own repairs, because in doing them without sufficient knowledge, he would be apt to damage the delicate mechanism of the limb. If the repairs cannot be carried out locally re-admission to a fitting hospital is arranged for, or the limb is sent to its maker. It is certainly desirable that in order to meet such a contingency each man should be supplied with a spare artificial limb, and this principle has received the approval of the Minister. The delay in giving it effect is due to three causes. &quot; In the first place it would be useless to supply thespare limb until the limb first supplied has been proper! y adjusted to the changes in the stump which occur during the first six months or more after the limb has been first fitted. In the second place the limb makers are fully occupied with the manufacture of limbs for fresh ainpu-tations, and it is of greater urgency to supply one fresh limb for each fresh case tha.n to provide a spare limb for each man who has already been fitted. In the third place, while everything points to the peg leg as the most suitable to take the place of the other during the short periods when it is under repair at any rate until such time as an ideal pattern of mechanical leg has been devised there are several types of peg legs, and experi-ments are being made with a view to the selection of the best. If, however, you will bring to my notice special cases in which it is desirable that the spare limb should be supplied at once, their requirements will be met if possible. In regard to shrinkage of the stump, I am to say that the suggestion as to the use of pads is not considered surgically sound. The only way to deal with such shrinkage is to have inside linings to the bucket or extra stump socks until it becomes necessary to make a new bucket. The Minister is glad to learn that the Committee have taken upon themselves the task of arranging terms between disabled men and their employers in cases where the former have to re-enter a fitting hospital for treatment.&quot;In a circular of the 12th July last the Statutory Committee directed the attention of Local Committees to a statement of the Minister of Pensions that he looked upon it as of importance that Local Committees should be acquainted with the views of disabled dis-charged men in matters affecting their interests, and suggested that Local Committees should consider the desirability of including such men in their Disablement Committees. The Minister now deems it advisable that further steps shovild be taken in this direction, and that statutory provision should be made for the inclusion in the Local Committee itself of at least one representa-tive of disabled men who haA&apos;e been discharged from the military or naval service, and with that object the Naval and Military War Pensions, etc. (Local Com-mittees), Bill has been prepared and was introduced on the 17th instant.--o-Major Dundas Grant, consulting surgeon to the Central London Nose, Throat, and Ear Hospital, who is the Chairman of the Special Aural Board set up by the Minister of Pensions, has now completed his arrange-ments for dealing at specially-arranged evening clinics with the cases of soldiers discharged as deaf in the Metropolitan and Greater London Area. Three of these clinics have now been set up. One of the hospitals is the Central London at King&apos;s Cross, another the Military Hospital at Fulham, and the third Queen Mary&apos;s Hospital for the East End, formerly West Ham Hospital. Patients will be dealt with between 5 p.m. and 8 p.m,
The Allied Delegates in London.-0-The second meeting of the Permanent Committee of the Inter-Allied Conference was held in London during the week ending October 13th.The delegates arrived in England on the 8th October. During their stay in this country they visited the Orthopaedic Hospital at Shepherd&apos;s Bush, Colder&apos;s Green Hospital, St. Dunstan&apos;s, the Regent Street Poly-technic and other institutions.The following are the names of the delegates who attended the meeting : M. M. Le Docteur Bourillon, Lucien March, and Charles Kvug (Prance); M. M. Alleman and Jauniaux (Belgium), M. Mouravieff-Apostol (Russia), M. Agathonovitch and Col. Soubotitch (Serbia), Drs. Pontes and Formigal-Luzes (Portugal), Miss Grace Harper, Mr. Veditz, Major R. D. Osgood and Brigadier-General Birmingham (U.S.A.). Col. MacLaren, R.A.M.C., represented Canada, Col. Thornton South Africa, Sir Thos. Mackenzie and General Richardson New Zealand, while the Ministry were represented by Sir A. Griffith-Boscawen Sir Charles Nicholson, Col. E. A. Stanton and Major Mitchell.From the beginning of the War to the end of September 774 totally blind soldiers and sailors have been admitted to the Blinded Soldiers and Sailors&apos; Hostel, St. Dunstan&apos;s, Regenfs Park, and its annexes, of whom 298 have been discharged. Of this number 257 have been fully trained and have set up for themselves, and the remaining 41, owing to mental or physical disability, had left without being set up. Fifty-three were admitted during August, and 21 were discharged, and at the end of the month there were 476 in residence. One hundred and five in hospital were to follow when fit to be dis-charged.-o-During September the following numbers were admitted to and discharged from the various limb-fitting hospitals : Number   Number Name of Hospital. admitted, discharged.Roehampton House	412	500Dover House (Officers)......	42	19Prince of Wales&apos; Hospital, Cardiff	17	27Princess Louise&apos;s Hospital, Glas-		gow      ...      .........	100	123Edenhall Hospital, Kelso	31	32Duke of Connaughfs Hospital,		Bray    ...      ...      ...	10	6Ulster Volunteer Force Hospital,		Belfast............	12	5Totals    ......	624	712Some Notes on Training.An interesting development has taken place regard to the training of New Zealanders.   Captai Richards, the officer in charge of the training of Zealand limbless soldiers, had had Trade Union difl ties with regard to the training of disabled New Zeal ers in a boot factory in Wolverhampton.   As the Zealanders are not discharged until they retun New Zealand no wages can be paid to them in add to their Army pay and the Trade Unions compla that the employer was contributing nothing.   Caj Richards was therefore invited to attend the T Advisory Committee (Boot Manufacture), and it there agreed that training for New Zealanders n be given in accordance with the lines laid down in recommendations of the Committee, and that regard to the contribution payable by the empl the disabled men should be invited to suggest any 1 of war charity to which they would like the mone be applied, and on this condition all Trade Union op] tion was waived.-0-The Joint Committee for Leinster and Connai have submitted a scheme for training disabled me the care and management of horses. The scheme be sanctioned subject to satisfactory informatioi certain points of detail, such as the number of L training, the selection of suitable men, and the stej be taken to ensure that the training shall be adequat -o-The Northampton Local Committee have made posals for the training of disabled men in Hairdre. The whole question of the advisability7 of training ni this industry has been under consideration in conne with the scheme of the Local Committee for Wimbl&apos; and the Minister of Labour, to whom the matter referred, has been in consultation with the Presiden the Incorporated Guild of Hairdressers, who is opinion that there will be good openings as hairdre: for disabled men who have been thoroughly well trai and has expressed his willingness to give the beneti his advice to any Local Committee who may wisl provide facilities for training in this process.Sanction has been given to the training of 18 indivii men and in 35 other cases further information has I requested or modifications have been suggested.-o-It is proposed to start at Roehampton a Trail Course in the making of artificial limbs. Men will invited to undergo a six months&apos; course of training, at the end of this period, the firms engaged at I hampton will retain them at the estandard rate of waThe number of trained artificial limb makers avaih at the present time is far below the number requi particularly in connection with the different Oil paedic centres and in view of the fact that the demand the provision and repairing of artificial limbs is likel; be great for the next 30 or 40 years, this trade wo appear to offer good prospects for the permanent empl ment of disabled men.
A School of Lamp Working.-o-Lamp working is the process by which glass tubing is eated in a &quot; lamp &quot; or blow pipe, and then, by manipu-tion and blowing, shaped into the required article, is used in the production of medical, scientific and ilar apparatus, and also in the making of artificial wS. it is done seated, and would be suitable for &quot;sabled men who have lost one or even both legs, rovided that they have sound lungs and the free use &apos; arms and fingers, aDd that their age and previous cupation do not prevent them from acquiring the ecessary suppleness and lightness of touch. The demand for workers in this industry is at present uch greater than the supply, and as it is a new occupa-on in this country the demand is likely to continue ter the War.A school of training has been opened at Sheffield niversity in connection with the Department of Glass technology, under Dr. W. E. S. Turner, and a portion f the accommodation is at present reserved for disabled oldiers who are recommended to take the elementary ourse, lasting three months, and the intermediate, sting a further six months.Local War Pensions Committees wishing to refer en for this training should communicate with theheffield War Pensions Committee, from whom fullarticidars can be obtained.The Local Committee for Aberdeen have submitted roposals to train disabled men in agriculture, horti-ulture and forestry at the North of Scotland Agricul--ural  College,  Craibstone.   The  necessary enquiries aving been completed the scheme has been sanctioned. Great importance is attached to the proper selection f the men who are to undergo training at agricultural olleges, and the Board of Agriculture for Scotland tave been requested to arrange for this work to be mdertaken by their travelling instructors, who are onstantly in touch with the farmers in their districts, nd probably in many cases have personal knowledge f the men who are proposed for training and could advise both as to their suitability for the work and as &apos;o their prospects of future employment.Where the instructors have no such previous know-jledge of the men applying for training, it has been suggested that the Local Committee concerned should arrange for an interview, and that the men selected by the instructors should be sent to the college for a pro-bationary course, during which the principal would be Able to form an opinion as to their suitability.The Local Committee have been requested to take the necessary steps to bring this scheme into operation at the earliest possible moment.-o-The Special Grants Committee of the Ministry hope, at an early date, to issue a circular dealing with the effect upon the existing Regulations of the New Pay Scheme for sailors and soldiers.Questions and Answers.-o-Q. 49. A widowed mother is receiving 12/6 a week pension in respect of one son, and is informed no Govern-ment allowance is admissible for a second son as his allol-ment of 3s. 6d. a week and the pension of 12s. Qd. makes the maximum Government allowance in the case of one dependant of two soldiers. Does a pension rank as separation allowance for the purpose of this regulation ? If so, and assistance can be given under Regulation 7 (1) (d), what would be the assessed dependence in the case of the second son, as the Pension Officer found a dependency of 11s. 1A. The answer to the first part of the question is in the affirmative. As regards the question of an allow7-ance under Part II. Regulations it is understood that no such case has hitherto been before the Statutory Committee or the Special Grants Committee. It is suggested that full particulars should be forwarded to the Ministry for consideration by the Special Grants Committee.Q. 50. Dependant (mother) received separation alloic-ance and allotment 12s. Qd. Son marries and wife note receiving separation allowance and allotment 12s. Qd. Dependant lives alone, and State separation allowance and allotment has been stopped. She teas entirely dependant on the soldier. It is presumed no allotment will be made by the soldier to his mother. Is the dependant, who is unable to maintain lierself, entitled to special separation allowance under Regulation 8 in Part 2, and what amount may the Committee allow. The dependency was assessed by the Pension Officer at 12s. Qd. ?A. An allowance may be possible under Regulation 8 (a).   See paragraph 4 of Part 2, Instruction 36.Q. 51. 7s there any provision under Part 2 Regula-tions, or elsewhere, to help a discharged disabled man immediately after his discharge from the military hospital, and who is not now needing further treatment, but as a result of his injuries due to war service he is not able to follow his former employment and has applied to his Local Committee for training. The man is receiving a temporary allowance of 14s. per week under Article 8 Royal Warrant. The Ring Paper has not, of course, been issued, and therefore cannot be recovered by Local Committee, and training cannot commence for two or three iceeks. The soldier has 3 or 4 children dependant on him, his wife is unable to ivork, and his total income from all sources is the temporary allowance 14s. a week, until he is supplied with a Ring Paper and his training com-mences. Circular 57 deals with men certified to be &quot; unfit for work,&quot; but in this case the man tvill be able to work, not at Ms old occupation certainly, but at the trade for ivhich he is going to be trained 1A. The Minister has now arranged that in every case a man is given pension at the full rate for the first four weeks after discharge precisely to meet this diffi-cxilty.
Q. 52. What is a payment under Article 8, Royal Warrant ? An allowance or a pension 1 If an allow-ance, can Regulation 13 (a), page 70 (Part 2), be-construed lo mean that if a soldier discharged and still under medical care receiving a payment under Article 8 amounting to 14s. per week, can he receive in addition to such money an Emergency Grant under Regulation 13 (a) pending the settlement of his claim to State pension ?A. -It is a temporary allowance. If necessary Regulation 13 (a) can be applied, but the whole matter of this and other cases of hardship to the disabled which are not at present fully covered by Regulation or Instructions is teeing carefully considered.      jQ. 53. Can Local Committees incur expenses or give money to defray the cost of such things as false teeth, spectacles, and other desirable things of a similar nature, where there is evidence that a man can reasonably say and prove that had it not been for his military service such articles would not have been needed. Several men have been discharged who had teeth extracted whilst in the Army, and one man has been discharged owing to eye trouble, attributable to military service, and glasses have bein certified to be necessary &quot;by the Army Medical Officers 1A. In cases where the man&apos;s need of dental or other treatment is found by medical opinion to be due to military service Local Committees can provide the treatment. Wherever a man has lost teeth during his service they can be replaced. Arrangements are now being made for this to be done expeditiously through the Ivory Cross.Q. 54. A man&apos;s pension has been reduced from 25s. a week to 8s. 3d., presumably on the ground that he is capable of work. He has tried his best, but finds that after two or three days he breaks down, and a local medical man has given him a certificate to say that he is incapable of work. The case is evidently one for review or appeal. Can the Local Committee assist him by advance or other-wise during the time that must elapse before he can get a decision ?A. The case is not necessarily one for review7 or appeal. The man should be examined by the Medical Referee or an independent doctor, who should be asked to say whether the man needs treatment in an institution or otherwise, or is suitable for training if he cannot resume his old employment. During such period he can of course receive allowances under Instruction 34. If at the same time the Local Committee consider that, in addition, the case is one that has been wrongly assessed they should put up the case for review.Q.. 55. When a discharged disabled soldier is sen convalescent home by a Local Committee, should the cedure in regard to pension, laid down in Instruction page 12 of &quot; Notes on Treatment and Training, followed, or does that only apply when a man is sent for actual medical treatment ?A. Yes. The Ring Paper should be recovered sent up with Form T.R. 1 to Pension Issue () This procedure should be adopted in every case v treatment and training of any kind with allowam given.Q. 56. A mother is drawing separation alloicam a son. The father, as a discharged disabled soldii admitted to a military hospital on account of war die ment. Under the Treatment and Training Reguh his wife is entitled to an allowance of 13s. 9d. per \ Is the woman entitled to draw two allowances, one f, son and one for her husband, or should there be a deduciA. The allowance during treatment has nothii do with, and is not affected by the separation al ance payable to her on other grounds.Q. 57. A wife is drawing an allowance undo Treatment and Training Regulations and whilst doh attains the age of 45 years. Is she entitled to an inc. from 13s. 9d. to 15s., according to the widoivs scale ij the Royal Warrant ?A.-Yes.Q. 58.- Are widoivs who are pensionable under A 15, Article 17, or Article Id of the Royal Warram Order in Council, and widows who are pensionable \ Article 11 or under any of the foregoing Articles, bid husbands&apos; deaths have occurred since their discharge the Service or transfer to the Reserve, eligible fo\ gratuity of  5 where the death of the sailor or si occurred after June 30th, 1916 1- Is a remarried n eligible for the gratuity ?A. Assuming the widow&apos;s claim to pension toj been established, the answer is   Article.   Death during service.   Death after diselJ11 Yes. Yes.15 Yes. No.17 No. No.19 No. No.Widows who had pensions under Article 11 wj husbands died after 30th June, 1916, and who) remarried have been granted the gratuity. ILONDON:PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;3 STATIONERY OFFICE.To be purchased through any Bookseller or directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following: addresses Imperial House, Kingsway, London, W.C. 2, and 28, Abingdon Street, London, S.W. 1; 37, Peter Street, Manohestm 1, St. Andrew&apos;8 Crescent, Cardiff ; 23, Forth Street, Edinburgh; or from E. PONSONBY, Ltd., 116, Grafton Street, DdbiI19] 7. Price Id. Net.Printed under the authority of His Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office by Merritt &amp; Hatcher. Ltd-. London and Greenwich.
APPENDIX XXIV.STAFF   OF MINISTRY OF PENSIONS1st   November, 1917.87a[ministration &apos;eatment &amp; Training lards to Officers fards to Seamen, fards to Soldiers ternative Pensions ards to Tidows. and Dep-endants. nsion Issue, ecial Grants Committee ecial Medical Board.41 9 12 1593a2723 48 2194 28 34 35 1666 267651734 57 9275235 37 46 50. 1759 317921759 105 114825

</content>
</cab>
