<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/31/0 images: 231-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Monel Jonesis Docume^tJ^Jhe Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government)  C R J3JLWARCABINET.G.T. 2543.SUPPLY OP OATS TO TEE ITALIAN ARMY.(Copy of letter from Sir E. Wyldbore Smith to Secretary, War Cabinet).Commission Internationale de Eavitaillement,India House,Zings way, Vf.C7th November, 1917.Dear Hanksy,I should be glad if you would draw the attention of the War Cabinet once more to the situation as regards the supply of oats to the Italian Army.The normal Italian military requirements for oats are eal-culated on a basis of 5 kilos per horse or mule per diem, and amount to 60,000 tons a month.During the period July/October, the deficit amounted to 62,000 tons or nearly 26^*   The estimated arrivals for the months of November and December amount to an approximate total of 57,000 tons, leaving a deficit of 53,000 tons or nearly 53$.Owing to lack of supplies it has been necessary since August last to reduce the daily ration to 3*5 lbs.   Such a ration was obviously insufficient for horses and mules operating in such a mountainous country; it was eonsequently necessary to supplement the reduced oats ration by ether cereals, hay and straw.The demand, however, for all cereals for human consumption has recently become so acute and the supply of straw so poor on account of the failure of the wheat harvest that even substitutes are now no longer available in sufficient quantities.As the result of the recent retirement, moreover, such stocks as it had been possible to accumulate on the front have fallen into the hands of the enemy, while on the other hand the strain put upon the cavalry, horses and mules has become very accentuated.In these circumstances the situation has become extremely serious and demands the immediate adoption of measures of relief.The situation has been reported to the Ministry of Shipping who, however, are unable to see their way to provide additional tonnage.     Representations have been made to the French Govera-ment with the result that a cargo of 6,900 tons of Indian Grain now on its way from Port Said to France has been diverted to Italy on the understanding that compensation to the French Government will be made in January next.This action on the part of the French should increase the quantity of oats exoected to arrive in Italy in November from 22,500 to 29,400 tons.
(Signed) E, Wyl&amp;bore Smith,This quantity, however, is still insufficient and I would suggest for the consideration of the War Cabinet that as many.cargoes as practicable now on their way from the ?    U. s.A * to this country with oats for the British Army should be diverted to Italy, the oats thus transferred to Italy to be replaced from stocks in this country.iYours sincerely,

</content>
</cab>
