<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/31/0 images: 265-289</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Documents tfc$ Property ofHit Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government)w *        __in ii&apos;i* ihijiih&apos;f ymmn^i&apos; mii TrnriiitnnrrjnTrrinf n i hrrmruinrfWMJWMMMMBBtlllTrnvr i    &quot;1SECRET.H.M, OFFICE OF WORKS, etc.REPORT for the fortnight ended 9th November, 1917, for the information of the Prime MinisterACCOMMODATION.      1.     The accommodation for the Ministryof Food in Palace Chambers and St. Stephenrs House has proved inadequate to house some of the Sections, and the Sugar Commission and the Sugar Section of the Ministry of Food are to be located in 14, Great Smith Street.2.     It has now been decided that the Wheat Commission shall remain in Trafalgar House, Waterloo Place, and should include the Flour Milling,  and Home Crown Cereals Section of the Ministry of Food.     In order to carry out this arrangement the French and Italian Commissions and a portion of the Accounting Staff of the Wheat Commission are being rehoused, the former in lo/l9 Pall Mall and the latter in Carlton House, Regent Street.3.      It is proposed to accommodate the Sugar Rationing Section of the Ministry of Food in the Imperial Institute.4.     Additional accommodation is being provided for the United States Naval Headquarters in 30, Grosvenor Gardens by the acquisition of two adjoining houses.If
5.     In order to provide additional accommodation for the Air Council, it is under consideration to acquire the Offices if the Metropolitan Water Board.Section of the Ministry of Munitions, Explosives Supply Department, Broadway House and it is proposed to requisition Broadway Chambers for this purpose.7,     Additional accommodation is being provided for the Petrol Committee in the Almack Club, Berkeley Street.8.     During the past fortnight 47 removals of Departments and 49 Internal removals have been carried out.ST. JAMES*S PARK. Work has been commenced on an extensionof the Shipping Controllers Department building.HORSE GUARDS PARADE.     Extensions to temporary buildings have been put in hand for Admiralty occupation.FARNBOROUGH HOUSING SCHEME. (250 houses). Good progress is being made in spite of bad weather and fluctuating number of men.     The present position is as follows:-6.Additional space is required by the FinanceNumber of men on building contract Do.        (including prisoners of War) on road work.600249849nousesDo. Do. Do. Do. Do.completed. 2slated 109slating in hand 10up to roof level 28 rafters being fixed 8 walls rising at&apos;various heights,      ^93
0HALB&apos;OIIT ST. PETERS COLONY FOR EPILEPTICS.      Good progrfssis being made in spite of - difficulty in getting mento stay.     There are 39 men at work.     The presentposition is:-Block 1.     Carpenters work practically completed, Internal plumbing, etc., well in hand.Block 2.     Completed.Block.5,     Plastering nearly finished.   Carpenters&apos; work well in hand.,     Joinory being delivered,SOUTH AFRICAN HOSPITAL, RICHMOND PARK.    Additional Workshops and Canteen.     Tender received.     Work started cn the 5th instant.MINISTRY OF MUNITIONS, MONTAGU HOUSE. Temporary building in Forecourt. Tenders received. Supply of steel now sanctioned.MINISTRY OF MUNITIONS, EXPLOSIVES SUPPLY DEPARTMENT.(Mineral Oil Production Section).     Tenders received. Supply of steel now sanctioned.TRAFALGAR SQUARE EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGE BUILDING for RECRUITING. WOMEN.     Completed and formally opened on the 7th instant.KEW.    EXTENSION OF HEAD INSURANCE OFFICE.    Temporarybuilding to deal with Industrial Census of Home Army. Drawings made and quantities being prepared.3.
MOUNT VERNON HOSPITAL) HAHPSTEAD, EXTENSION. Awaiting information from tho Air Board as to scheme under consideration,HOSPITALS FOR SOLDIERS SUFFERING FROM NERVE TROUBLES.Preliminary scheme for a standard type of building being prepared for Ministry of Pensions.EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES NEW PROGRAMME.(l)    Schemes approved by the Ministry of Labour(a) New premises and Alterations 50(b) Alterations approved andcompleted 555(2)    Schemes under consideration by tho- Ministry of Labour 41(3)    Premises in view, negotiating orawaiting visit 22(4)    Premises not yet found 30(5)    Awaiting particulars of requirementsfrom the Ministry of Labour x(6)    Awaiting information from the SuppliesDivision.     New premises London. 12Minor alterations are practically all completeor else complete except for counter grilles.A list of further new Exchanges has been received from the Ministry of Labour, but before the matter can bo advanced, particulars of the accommodation required are awaited from the Ministry.
3 b G R   T, WORK FOR THE WAR OFFICE.LOU DOM (WESTMINSTER.,)    New Office, Australian Forces Headquarters.    During the process of excavations it has been found that the subsoil of site is totally unsuited for the erection of a three storey building as asked for by the war Office.   A proposal is being considered to erect a two storey building on the Chadwick Street site, and another one storey building on an adjacent site..   This suggestion has been&apos; recommended, to the War Office and approved.WORK FOR THE MINISTRY OF MUNITIONS.AINTREE (Nr.- LIVERPOOL). NATIONAL FILLING AND AMATOL FACTORIES.    The twenty lavatory flecks have now been completed.Work in connection with the Railway sidings next Assembling House and ^helil Painting House is proceeding satisfactorily.BANBURY NATIONAL FILLING, FACTORY. The Engineering V/ork   in connection with erection and extension is completed,BIRMINGHAM (SMALL HEATH) PACKING SHED. Financial approval is now awaited.BIRMINGHAM GAUGE STORE,  etc. The Impossibility of obtaining any additional labour and the holding up by the Railway Company of the delivery of Granite chippings for the granolithic floor, still very much delay these works.
BIRMINGHAM (WASHWOOD HEATH).    A tender for the erection of the Canteen has now been approved, and th -j work will bo put in hand forthwith.BUXTON NEW STORE.     Better progress has beenmade at this job during the fortnight, the Store nowexceptbeing complete /r&quot;or painting, glazing, the hanging of doors and external finishings.COVENTRY NATIONAL FILLING FACTORY      The Boiler and Pump House is now finished.     The Chimney   shaft is about half built, some delay in the erection of this having been caused by a delivery of inferior quality of bricks.     A new consignment has   now been received and the work should now proceed without interruption.Rest Room for the use of Women workers employed at the Factory.      Instructions are awaited.The last Boiler for the extension is now on the way and it is hoped to have this seated within the next month.DAGENHAM DOCK NATIONAL CARTRIDGE &amp; BOX REPAIR. FACTORY.      All machine beds have now been formed in concrete and all piers and hollow brick walls completed for the Machine Tool shop.     Drainage work is well advanced..Mess Room, Sorting Shed, new roofs to platforr and sidings..     A tender has been approved and the work of clearing the&apos; site has commenced..     Working drawings for tho nyw shed/ 300&apos; x 160&apos; are being prepared, pending approval.&apos;
GLASGOW (PARTICK) TIMBER DRYING KIMS..   Progress at this Kiln has been somewhat delayed owing to inclement weather;Excavations for Walls adjoining the railway and for the central and end walls have now been completed and concrete laid for foundations.Sheds for the storage of building materials have been erected.Engineering Work.Progress is fairly satisfactory but difficulty is experienced in obtaining iron tubes required.GLOUCESTER NATIONAL FILLING FACTORY. This service is almost completed.HEREFORD NATIONAL FILLING FACTORY. r&apos;ith the exception of some one or two supplementary buildings, the whole of the Factory is now in the hands of the Ministry.Progress is satisfactory on the extra Plant required in connection with alterations to process. Some of the plant salved from Morecambe is being transferred for use at this Factory.HEREFORD (CREDENHILL).. A.Q.D. STORES. The first two railvray tracks are complete.Stores Nos. 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8 and 10 are practically complete.   The Pump Station is ready for the
Engineers to fix plant.    The Locomotive Shed is practically complete with the exception of the track. The Military Fence is very nearly complete,INVERNESS TIMBER DRYING KILN&apos;..    Instructions are still, awaited regarding this Kiln.KIIMARIOCK (AYRSHIRE) TIMBER DRYING KILNS.   No progress has been made on this service as approval has not yet been obtained.LONDON (HENDON) AIR-CRAFT STORES &amp; ERECTION SHOP. The large Sliding doors have been completed to the south half of the shed and the hanging of sane is proceeding.This portion of the building.is now being utilised for the fitting up of Aeroplanes-The Office Block is now occupied...Progress to these works has been greatly retarded owing to a strike of navvies and labourers, which occurred on the 29th October involving the temporary loss from the job of 250 men.   The trouble arose through a demand being made by the men for&apos; double time payments for work carried out before 8 a..m* although the labourers agreement for the London District specifically states that the rate of payment shall be time and a quarter.    It was pointed out that no departure could be made from this rule, but the men, who argued that labourers employed at the Grahame Phite Aerodrome, were receiving double time
w t) 1payment, persisted in their demands and declined to resume work-vUp to&quot; the present.149 men have returned and it is anticipated with others following and by obtaining new labour that the full number of labourers and navvies required will be made up in a short time. There are.350 workmen employed on these works.Fork in connection with the Railway is proceeding satisfactorily.&apos;Torking drawings for cloak room and lavatory accommodation have been completed,- and the work will be started immediately.The heat in the first half of the shed is now on and this is being used for storage purposes.LONDON (HHITDQjQ HOUSING SCHEME.   Tenders for this scheme have been invited and are returnable on Thursday the 8th instant.&quot;   A rough estimate of the cost is  140,-000.&apos;LONDON fPARK ROYAL) THiBSR DRYING KILNS.    Instructions have been received for the erection of a Timber Drying Kiln next to the National Box Factory.-The building will be constructed in hollow brick tiles with reinforcing brick piers, timber roof and corrugated iron covering and will afford a drying space of 75,000 super feet.9i
The cost will amount to about  8,000.&apos; Sketch plans have been prepared and forwarded to the Ministry for approval.LOI-nOE (PUTNEY YALE) MACHINE SHOP. Twelve roof principals have been fixed and Turlins and roof boarding to same are being laicLBrickwork to wall on south side of building to Transformer House   -is completed.\ ith regard to the Canteen, the lines of building have been set out and excavations for foundations have been commenced.The delivery of materials other than timber is now more satisfactory but delay to the progress of the work is still being caused through shortage of labour and the non-delivery of a small balance of timbe ordered.The matter of labour has been taken up with Local Employment Exchanges, who have promised to send some men along at an early date, while the Controller o Timber Supplies has been urged to complete the deliveries of timfeer.HQBIIHOQD ENGINEERING &quot;.QRKS.    Good progress is being made though difficulty is being experienced obtaining poles necessary for carrying the overhead High Tension Electric Line,10 o
LONDON (SHEPHERDS BUSH). TRENCH WARFARE INSPECTION BOND.    Instructions have been received for the t/roction at a Trench Warfare Inspection Bond to be built on a site in V/ood Lane adjoining the existing Munition Stores.The scheme will consist of two Sheds constructed in steel framework with patent hollGW brick filling corrugated iron roofs on steel trusses and reinforced concrete floors, giving a total floor area of 250,000 superficial feet.The scheme embraces the provision of Railway Sidings and connections to the G.W.Railway, a Canteen for tho accommodation of 500 workers and an Administrative Office block.The total approximate coot exclusive of engineering services will amount to  57,000.   Eorking drawings are in the course of preparation.LONDON (SURREY DOCKS) DRYING KILNS. The terra cotta blocks forming walls of Kiln have now reached an average height of 6* above the ground level.A large consignment of bricks having been received it has been possible to make good progress to the brickwork of Kiln and Boiler House.Engineering Work..     The same applies as to Partick
.    LONDON (WILLESDEH) ADDITIONAL A,STORE. Inspection Bond No. 3705.     It has now be^n decided toomit this Store from this scheme and to modify thej iarrangements of partition in the Offices.   Variationsto the working drawings are being prepared and it isestimated that a saving of about  2*000 will boeffected.LUTON TIMBER   DRYING KILN.       For the Ministry of Munitions to be erected at an approximate cost of  3,500...The building which is to be erected on the site of Messrs, Brown and Sons Mills will consist of a shed constructed on brick piers and hollow bricks walls timber roof and corrugated iron sheeting-, and will a &quot;ford a storage area of 6,200 super, ft.The drying of home grown timber for the manufacturers of ammunition boxes will bo carried out by means of s.team heating, brought from an?.existing Boiler House, to the underside of the floor of the kiln.Working drawings have been prepared&apos; and financial approval is now awaited to proceed.A tender has been invited for the dryingPlrjit.12.
13.:,iORE0AMBE NATIONAL FILL I. 0: FACTORY.    The repairs to all the intern. 1 Railways have been completed, except the Sidings to Units 5 and 6.Clearing of walls to Press and Incorporating Houses is proceeding.The&apos; work to the Power House is proceeding satisfactorily.     The glazing of the. Boiler Housejisjnow practically completed.-The cooling Tower is completed with the exception of coating with wSolignum&quot;*The brickwork to the Loco, Shed is all finished and the roof is being temporarily strutted.The work to the Empty Shell St^re is proceeding with all speed;,-     bOfo of. the brickwork is completed and 60$ of the iron sheeting to the roof is finished.The hard core to the Oil and Paint Store is being deposited :preparatory to laying a concrete floor,The veerk to the roof of the Fire Station, and the sashes Is In hand.The Canteen is about half complete.Lavatories.     The corrugated iron is being--fixed ovorvthe .roof to afford accommodation for workmen on the site.
Engineering Work..     Tho bad. weather has retarded progress but Engineers are employed cleaning   up and repairing damaged machinesKEV;POPT NATIONAL CARTRIDGE &amp; BOX REPAIR FACTORY. Tho i illwrights shop and Engine Shed have been delayed through the non-delivery of timber.   This has now been advised and it is hoped that the work will now proceed rapidly to completion.SHEFFIELD TESTING STATION.     Instructions have been recoived for the provision of a Chemical Laboratory and Shell Tes-ing station.It is proposed to requisition premisestobelonging/the Yorkshire Motor Co., situated in Townhead Street and to adapt the buildings to the Ministry&apos;s requirements ,Tht^ cost of this will amount to about  1,500. A survey of the existing premises has been made and working drawings are now being prepared.SOUTHAMPTON TIMBER DRYING KILN * It is proposed to erect a Timber Drying Kiln on the site of Messrs.   -Driver &amp; Sons Saw Hills     The building which will provide a storage area of 52,500 super, feet, will be constructed in hollow brick partitions blocks with reinforcing brick piers and the cost wil ,amount to about  4,000.
Heat for the drying&apos; of the timber will be obtained from an adjacent existing Boiler House.Working drawings have been prepared and tenders invited;    these are returnable on the 10th instant.SOUTHAMPTON (HYTHE), SEAPLANE SPIED.    Instructions have been received for the provision of a large sea-plane shed and attendant buildings, at a total approximate cost of  95,000.A site possessing natural advantages for the scheme has been selected at Winterton Hall and will provide an area of 4 acres.It is proposed to demolish the existing residence on the site and clear the ground of trees and out^-buildings oThe Seaplane Shed is to be constructed in steel framing with corrugated iron covering, the whole being braced with wind resisting raking shores and will provide 300*000 super, ft. of concreted floor assembling space.   Special attention has been observed with regard to the latter, it being necessary to obtain as large an unobstructed area as possible.With this purpose in view, the steelwork has been so designed that only twelve stanoheons supporting the upper works will occur and. there will be intermediate between seaplanes or groups of seaplanes housed in the sheds.
Owing to the had effect of sunlight upon the fuselage of seaplanes, it has been decided to construct this roof with Northern top lighting.    The front or southern side of shed will face the sea, and will be provided with sliding doors 35 ft. high designed to allow the entrance and oxit of the latest type of planes.n. concrete marshalling platform 500&apos; x 100&apos; will be provided on this front, with a slipway 5001 long and 30r wide, running down to the Water&apos;s edgo and constructed in reinforced concrete direct on the sea bed.Boiler House.   For heating the above shed and for the supply of water, a Boiler House will be constructed in brickwork and will provide a superficial area of 8,300 ft.Power House.     Constructed in brickwork and with a superficial area of 1,500 ft. this will provide electri power and lighting for the whole scheme, and will be built to adjoin the existing Power House in the Shipyard of Messrs. May Harden and May-.In connection with the whole scheme, about 1,062 tons of steel will be required of which 460 tons will be of commercial mild steel, the remainder being made up from &quot;discard steel&quot;.Tenders for this steel have been received and submitted to the Ministry   for approval.
Working drawings for the complete scheme are now in course of preparation.A tender has been received for the electric Generating Plant and submitted for approval.SV.IiviJQN (SXRATTON).   An estimate has been sent forward for the extension consisting of an additional Crystallize!- Block and an additional Filter House.WHYTELEAFE.       The Box Store is now practically complete.WORK FOR HIS MAJESTY&apos;S OFFICE OF WORKS.BRAMLEY STORES.     Working drawings for the proposed 28 new buildings are now in course of preparation. Brick huts are being erected for the accommodation of &quot;1,500 Prisoners of War, who will be employed on the Stores extension when the building operations are commenced.GRAIN STORES.SWANSEA.       Owing to&quot;heavy rain falling at night the men employed on Site No. 1 have left off work at 6 p,m.     The progress made during the day time has, however, been satisfactory.Sufficient supplies of bricks, sand ballast, hard core and timber have arrived regularly and mechanical crushers and mortar mixers have been set up with a view to expediting the concreting of floors.
i IArrangements have been made for a regular supply of trucks for the steel contractors use soV that no delays may arise in the delivery of this material.The work of levelling Site No. 1. is now complete and hard core is being spread and rolled.Concrete bases for half the stancheons are complete, the progress to brickwork generally being satisfactory.Progress on Site No. 2 has been good, one fifth of the whole of the brickwork having been completed and practically all the floor area has been levelled and partially hardcored.   The amount of timber converted for use from old ammunition boxes is now 43,500 sq. ft.AVONMOUTH.     Pumping to the flooded trenches is still found to be necessary, but generally the progress at these Stores has been better.The excavations which will complete those to No. 1 shed are proceeding and concreting to all trenches of No. 2 shed is complete.Concreting to. trenches of No. 3 shed, is proceeding, the brickwork to Sheds Nos. 1 and 2 and to    i retaining walls of loading platforms is showing satisfactory progress.   Over 1,300 tons of materials comprising bricks, sand, cement,  slag, ballast, broken bricks, etc., have been delivered during the past week-
and arrangements having &quot;been made for a regular supply of trucks to the steelwork contractor.; - it is hoped to obtain a consignment of stancheons, trusses, etc., by the end of the week.   The system of temporary electric lighting for Sheds No. 1 and 2 has been completed.. BARRY.-   Progress at these works has not been up to anticipation owing, to continuous rainy weather.   The laying and rolling of hardcore generally has, however, been completed, and concreting to receive paving is well advanced.The present state of the work is as follows:-Shed B*   Hardcore filling completed and surface concrete progressing.   Brickwork to S*W. end of Shed and to four gables is completed, and elsewhere has reached lintol height.   Roof boarding is fixed, slating and glazing commenced and the fixing of all gutters completed.Shed D.   Foundations have been completed and the brick-work has reached floor level.   About one-third of the drainage is completed.CARDIFF.    The supply and delivery of materials oontinues to be satisfactory, 1,686 tons having been delivered on the site in 230 wagons during the last weekShed No. 1.   The steel erectors are completing thefixing of roof trusses, and this finishes the wholeof the constructional steelwork for this Shed.   Purlins
have been fixed on both sides of the 15 roofs covering, the shed, and boarding completed in the case of 14 roofs ,Some 58,000 slates have been laid on the roofs and 12,000 others have been prepared for fixing.Excavations for the new railway line between sheds Noa.1 and 2 are nearing completion..Temporary electric lighting has been installed around the sheds enabling the workmen to work early and late each day.Shed No. 2*   To facilitate the work of steel erectors, the building of end walls is being pushed on as rapidly as possible.45 steel stancheons and 36 roof trusses have already been fixed and the laying of purlins and roof boarding is proceeding.Shed No.. 3.-   The foundati ons have been built to the walls at the North end of shed and for about half the length to wall on the East side.NEWPORT (Houlders Shed).    The concrete floor has been completed.The contractor has promised to put additional labour on to these works with a view to expediting progress.
Wooden bins have been made for testing the wheat direct on the concrete floor,,FALiftOUTH DOCK.     The weather having been unfavour-able the progress at these stores has been somewhat delayed.Concreting to East and South trenches has been completed and brickwork commenced to South East angle of building.Three truckloads of bricks have been delivered during the last ^veek, together with 90 tons of cement ballast and sand.PLYMOUTH (MILBAY DOCK).    The position regarding this Grain Store is as stated in the last report.Progress in the Engineering work of these Grain Stores is satisfactory but approval to proceed with Plant for Plymouth has not yet been obtained.jONDON AIR DEFENCES.In addition tc the work mentioned in the last Report, work is now proceeding at.:-Harp end en.    G. oc L. Wheathampstead.    G. it L.Additional sites have also been selected forGun and Light Stations at: -Eton.Stoke Poges.- Fulm er.- Gerrards Cross. Chalfont St. Peter. Chalfont St. Giles.- Burtons Farm.
Flaunden, Bovington. Boxmoor. Virginia Water. Burrow Hill. Horsell. Woking. Sutton Green, kerrovv, Shere.and for a new Gun Station at Englefield Green.In connection with a certain scheme of defence prepared by the War Office the following works are being carried out in the Eastern Counties under the supervision of this Department:-3,000 yards of rough roadways, temporary bridges over watercourses, balloon beds and screens.Work is also proceeding for the erection of hutting accommodation for the officers and men stationed at the various centres.LONDON  (REGENT&apos;S PARK) AIRCRAFT STORAGE SHEDS EXTENSIONo    Instructions regarding this scheme are still awaited from the War uffice.   Meanwhile in order to ascertain the conditions regarding the &quot;price of steel-v/ork, tenderi3 for the supply of this material have been invited.LONDON  (ST.  JAMES1 PARK) NEW TEMPORARY OFFICES. Working drawings for this scheme with Bills of Quantities have been submitted to tender. Replies are asked for on the 10th instant.
WORKS EXECUTED ABROAD.OVERSEAS LIGHT RAILWAY WORKSHOPS.    About one-half of the sectional sheds t^be used as workshops for the repair of wagons have now been made,  and instructions with regard to the shipping of these are now awaited.OVERSEAS ESTABLISHMENT, FRANCE.    Information has been received for the preparation of the Fire protecting scheme.     All other schemes are designed and the material necessary is on the way.ORDNANCE SURVEY ESTABLISHMENT, FRANCE. A barge of materials for this scheme completed loading at Riehborough on the 2nd instant ready for consignment to France.,   Further materials comprising sectional parts,   joinery work,  etc., have been put on rail. Preliminary work on the site is proceeding.CHERBOURG.      In connection with the existing Sheds and sectional huts,  it is proposed to erect awnings constructed in steel sections with corrugated iron sheeting, as a protection to the loading platforms, Drawings have been prepared and a tender approved.The sectional parts are in course of construction.The cost of these additions will amount to  1,500.0&apos;X
TOTCJTORJJLgg GENTRAL CONTROL jJJAaD (LIQUOR TRAFFIC;)*HULL KING GEORGE&apos;S DOCK.      Canteen.    With regard to the proposed Canteen in the vicinity of King George&apos;s Dock for 350 persons, it has been decided to select a new site approved by the Dock Company and to prepare new plans suitable for the site fcr submission to the Control Board.SWANSEA CANTEEN.    The sketch plans are still awaiting approval by the Control Board.CANTEENS GENERALLY. On behalf cf the Central Control Board, plans have been examined, the sites visited; and the schemes recommended for approval in the cases of 191 canteens.    The erection of 146 further canteens, which have been approved, is being supervised by this Department.    Under the arrangements made with the Controller of Timber Supplies for the release of Timber for the use in the erection of these Canteens, 271 standards have been released since 12th July,The accounts of 131 completed Canteens have been examined and checked, and a final statement made to the Control Eoard,    The approximate cost of these 468 buildings is  999,827.WORK FOR THE BOARD OF TRAPS.LONDON DOCKS;    British Industries Fair.     The work will .4e commended immediately the site is handed over by the Port Authority.24. - . -u
CULTIVATION Ite THE ROYAL PARKS.RICHMOND &amp; BUSHY PARKS, A good many acres have now &quot;been ploughed in each Park in addition to the 45 acres required for winter wheat.The cost of ploughing has been well unders.20/- per acre.The area for winter wheat has b-en harrowedand dressed with lime, and drilling has been commenced;-edthe seed wheat having been obtain/from Yorkshire through the Board of Agriculture.The 2 varieties Used are &quot;Browick&quot; and &quot;Little Joss&quot;,The cat crop in rsushy Park has been threshed 50 acres have yielded 140 bushels or at the rate of 2.8 quarters per acre, :Although this is less than estimated when the crop was standing,  the bad weather at harvest time reduced the yield by perhaps 1 quarter per acre.The contractor who carried out the threshing expressed an opinion that he had with one exception not threshed any better oats this year in thi neighbourhood.A sample was sent to Professor Biffen who, however, does not consider the seed fit to be used for sewing in the spring&quot;.    It will be necessary, therefore, to purchase seed oats.(Sd); Lionel Earle.

</content>
</cab>
