<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/31/0 images: 322-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
f   T5   T?   T&quot;!/    i.1   -Lj    X n561.Mi toutes jlLJh$J&amp;tG  !L Mejetin^..The Coaraittee held their 2nd - Meeting at 2, Whitehall Garden3;  S,  on Wednesday,  31st October,  1917.at 4, 30 P *ni-PresentGeneral Smuts    (in the Chair). Si i&quot; Eric Oeddes -Lord Coray.Matfor-General Sir R.D*Whigham.(representing theSecretary of State for War).The^ following also a;bt ended ;t-Ad.rural Sir J, Jellicoe.Lt-. -General Si r David Henderson -Major Storr    (Secretary),1.    THE CHAIRMAN said the Committee had met to consider at once certain papers which had been circulated to the War Cabinet and to members of the Committee,  e;g.. -&quot;Air Organisation&apos;5 - Memorandum by Lord Hilxier,(G,T. 2409 ij&quot;Progress of Aerial Offensive&quot; - Memorandum by Sir DavidHenderson. (G.T. 2422),&quot;Offensive Aerial Operations against German Territory as distinct from immediate military objectives -Correspondence between the Chief cf the Imperial General Staff and Sir Douglas Haig. (G.T. 2379).&quot;Correspondence between Sir Douglas Haig and General Petain on the subject of Bombing behind the German Lines.    (G.T. 2428).&quot;Formation cf Separate Air Ministry&quot; - Minutes from the C.I-.G.S. and observations by Sir Douglas Haig(G.T. 2058).&apos;He wished to drarw attention to .the following extracts from those papers :-(a) &quot;Ministry or no Ministry therefore - and I gatherthat a full-fledged Ministry will take some time to construct - and Air Staff composed on the lines of the Imperial General Staff is an urgent necessity ........Who in the meantime is doing the work of that Air Staff which, by common consent, is so.urgently required ? Is it the Committee that has been appointed to advise the Cabinet on all matters of Air Policy?   If that is to be our only Air Staff during the critical time ahead   c-
 of us, I venture to say that the arrangement is quite inadequate."



(Lord Milner&apos;s Memorandum G.T.2409).



(B) Under present arrangements no independent bombing operations can be undertaken before the spring of 1918, except by aeroplanes detached from the Naval and Military Forces .....

It is essential that an Officer and staff should at once commence the necessary preliminary work for these operations".

(General Henderson&apos;s Memorandum G.T.2422).

LORD COUWDRAY pointed out that the decision at which the Committee had arrived at its Meeting on October 16th., relative to the appointment of the officer to take charge of the Long Distance Bombing had been ignored.

The decisions then taken had been :-

(A) That as regards aerial operations on our Western Front these should be under a separate Air Commander under the command of the Field Marshal Commander-in-Chief in France and that when possible Naval machines should be attached to co-operate with the Military Aircraft.

(B) That the First Sea Lord and C.I.G.S. and Sir David Henderson should consult together and submit names to the Committee at their next meeting to enable the Committee to select on Air Commander for the independent offensive on the Western Front.

Following upon these decisions the Army Council had, however, written to Sir Douglas Haig on October 18th in terms which implied that the Commander of the bombing force would necessarily be a Military Officer and which left the selection of the suitable names to Sir Douglas Haig and which further stated that the names of Naval Officers from whom a second-in-command would be selected would be suggested by the Admiralty.

Lord Cowdray further pointed out that this exceeded and varied the decisions which he had quoted, and that Sir Douglas Haig&apos;s reply removed the proposed arrangements still further from the terms of those decisions.

  


In this connection SIR DAVID HENDERSON said that he had interviewed the Chief of the Imperial General Staff on the subject and he drew attention to&apos;correspondence which has passed between the Secretary to the War Office and Sir Douglas Haig (G.T.2379). The Secretary to the War Office has written&quot;............... The most suitable officer as Commanderis left for your consideration.     The names of Naval Officers as second in command will be suggested by the Board of Admiralty,     The Council would be glad If you would submit your recommendations at an early date,&quot;To this Sir Douglas Haig had replied&quot; ........... It is necessary that the General OfficerCommanding, Royal Flying Corps in the Field, should remain responsible to me for the operations of the whole of the Aerial Forces in France, and for working out the detailed plans necessary io carry out the Instructions of the 7-&apos;ar Cabinet as regards long-distance bombing, but the Officer appointed to command the bombing squadrons will be given a very free hand in carrying out the.operations.The 41st V-ing is now under the command ofLt,Col. Newall, RrfF0G.,......... He is the next WingCommander in France for appointment as Brigadier, and I have every intention of recommending him for pro-motion as soon as sufficient bombing squadrons are available to enable me to expand the 41st Wing Into a Brigade,      When additional bombing brigades are formed hereafter, it may become necessary to appoint a Major-General in command of the whole, in order to limit the mcrmber of formations to be dealt with direct by the G..O.C.., R.-.F.C., in the field.As regards Naval Squadrons lent to the Army, at present the G.O,C, R.F.C., has a Naval Officer on his Staff to deal with the administrative work in connection with these.     This arrangement meets existing needs., but should a number of bombing squadrons of the Royal Kaval   Air Service be placed under my command, I should be glad of the services of a Naval   Officer, as Wing, or if necessary, Brigade Commander.   In my opinion this arrangement -would be altogether prefer-able to appointing an Officer as second in command of the long-distance bombing   squadrons, both In principle and practice,&quot;. LORD COY/DRAY said he understood that the Air Board was at present only concerned with the supply of aircraft suitable for carrying out the policy to be laid down by the Committee, but pending this policy being formulated by the Committee the Air Board was continuing the methods and policy it has hitherto followed as regp^rds design and supply.     In regard to policy the Committee had a dual function :-(a) To determine the design and numbers of aircraft for the Navy and Army and for the Independent Offensive:(b) To.draw up plans of Independent Aerial Offensive Operations.
THE CHAIRMAN stated that the Committee was really an interim arrangement to act until the new Air Ministry came into being, to determine questions of Air Policy in general and to outline plans of independent aerial operations to be worked out in full by the Imperial General Staff and the Naval War Staff and later by tho Air General Staff.SIR DAVID HENDERSON said , in regard to future independent aerial operations on the Western Front it was essential that immediate steps should be taksn to select places for aerodromes, depots and parks and for the arrangements for the transport and for contracts for buildings in consultation with tho French Authorities.THE CHAIRMAN stated that he understood also that arrange-raents were being effected with due regard of importance of no time being lost in concert with the French.GENERAL WHICHAM stated that good progress had already been made in regard to the establishment of aerodromes and depots in France .THE CHAIRMAN stated that the discussion could not profitably be further continued in the unavoidable absence of Lord Derby (who was with the Prime Minister) and the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (who was absent, on the Continent),THE COMMITTEE recommended that two Junior Staff Officers be selected by the Admiralty and War Office respectively to be detailed to attend all meetings of the Committee to assist in the Secretarial work connected therewith, to maintain a close liaison with the two Departments concerned, the intention being that the two said Officers should eventually become part of the Air General Staff .&apos;THE COMMITTEE had a brief preliminary; discussion Of certain suggestions made by Sir David Henderson in his paper (G.T.2422 page 3) as regards the shortage of personnel for the Royal Naval Air Service .     General Henderson stated that he thought, the Admiralty would only have a few men for the Central Force if they met the full requirements of the Navy; in view of the great expansion in the future he expressed the hope that the Navy would train as many men as possible in advance and in excess of immediate requirements , as in the course of a few months the output of aircraft would outpace the training of the pilots .   He instanced the fact that tho Navy are asking for 100 Handley-Page Machines, while the Air Board were ordering another 300 Machines of the same type for the Central Air Force.THE COMMITTEE discussed the possibility of training Warrant Officers and Nob-Commissioned Officers as Pilots of the bigger machines which at present were only entrusted to officers .   It was pointed out that the Pilots of such machines must have a certain standard of education and a strong sense of responsibility.GENERAL WHIG-HAM informed the Committee that the Secretary of State for V/ar had had this matter under consideration and had consulted Sir Douglas Haig on the question .   Sir D. Haig&apos; had submitted an experimental scheme under which a limited number of pilots for the larger machines would be Warrant or Non-Commis--sioned Officers .   General Whigham added that Sir D.- Henderson knew of this proposal and undertook to ascertain from the Director-General of Military Aeronautics (Major-General Salmond) what steps were being taken to give effect to it.
Whitehall Gardens,  S.W. 10th November, 1917GENERAL HENDERSON stated that he hoped the War Office would relax existing regulations in regard to the terms of employment of women.   He stated that thousands of women could be obtained for aeroplane construction if it was guaranteed that they were not liable to be shifted from place to place. In regard to the lack of hutting for the Royal Plying Corps personnel who it was feared would have to be accommodated in $rents during the winter,  General Henderson said that tents were quite unsuitable for men who were engaged in sedentary occupations and not of robust health; a large number cf the men who were working en aircraft construction had been placed in &quot;B&quot; and &quot;C&quot; Classes.LORD COWDRAY stated that he was going into this question with the Shipping Controller with a view to ascertaining whether a certain amount of timber could not be released for the construction of huts.As regards personnel for the Royal Flj/ing Corps GENERAL HENDERSON stated that there was likely to be a con-side rable shortage,  on the present programme,  skilled, half-skilled and ordinary mechanics were badly needed.   These men could only be obtained now through the Ministry of National Service and he hoped that the Committee would make a recom-mendaticn to the Minister of National Service to grant priority to the Royal Plying Corps.   Arrangements had been made to keep 5,000 unskilled and semi-skillec men continuously under training for the Royal Flying Corps.   This would be possible by the end of the year.GENERAL HENDERSON urged strongly the importance of a much larger proportion of men being taken into the Royal Flying Corps and the Royal Naval Air Service during the coming three months in order to anticipate the vastly in-creased output of aircraft in the Spring.GENERAL WHIGHAM undertook to go into this question,  so far as the Royal Flying Corps was concerned, *dth the Secretary of State for War and the Adjutant-General in connection with the general question of Man-Power.Further discussion of the papers before the Committee was adjourned.

</content>
</cab>
