<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/98/0 images: 7-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Documentj ihllL0J l!L:EL RESERVE FOR BRITISH OIL-BURNING MERCHANT SHIPS.oranduxi prepared by the admiralty and the petroleum executivefor the Cabinet.^S^^Ak^-^^^A-duiiralty and the Petroleum Executive consider it necessary that the Cabinet should now decide&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;flTe policy to be adopted for meeting the war requirements of essential oil-burning Merchant Ships and the^        scale on which this should be done.   The following observations are put forward in connection with this,     ,very important national question.\- \ \- I      The WarCabinet on the 17th January 1919 had before them a Memorandum by the Admiralty (Paper\ IIJG-.T. 6594), together with a Memorandum by Mr. Long, as Minister in Charge of Petroleum Affairs(Paper Gr.T. 6634), in regard to the oil fuel reserve for the Navy in Home waters, and approved the pro-posals contained in the Admiralty Memorandum that a minimum reserve, of twelve months&apos; consumption ona war basis should be provided.A portion of the financial expenditure necessary for giving effect to the War Cabinet decision has beenincluded in the Navy Estimates for this year.The position of British shipping using oil fuel instead of coal has since been carefully considered.The clear intention of large shipping companies is to convert a portion of their existing ships to use oilfuel and to build new ships as oil-burning vessels.In the case of converted ships there is some possibility of reverting to the use of coal in an emergencyif necessary, but vessels designed for oil burning cannot turn over to coal after completion.It may be assumed with confidence that future Mercantile Fleets will comprise a large proportion ofvessels designed to use oil fuel, and that the ships so equipped will be of the class upon which this countrywill need to rely for food and essential commodities in war.The change from coal to oil for bunkering Merchant Ships, while it has important advantages, hascertain drawbacks, because of the serious effect it will have upon the foreign trade of the United Kingdom.Coal is, in bulk, by far the largest exportable commodity of this country, and any serious diminution of its useby Merchant Ships generally is likely to have a prejudicial effect upon British trade and upon the foreignexchanges. On the other hand, to impose restrictions upon the building of British Merchant tonnagedesigned to burn oil is inconceivable, as it would handicap British shipowners in competing with foreignshipping companies, which are themselves turning over from&apos;coal to oil.The effect of the change from coal to oil to some extent must therefore be accepted ; but it is of primeimportance that whatever fuel is used this country should retain control of the bunkering of neutral ships,especially in time of Avar, and that the requirements for running our own essential Merchant Ships shouldhe ensured.Our coal resources afford us this advantage in so far as coal-burning ships are concerned, but the presentdependence of this country upon the goodwill of the United States of America for the major portion of oilfuel supplies deprives us of the same measure of advantage in the case of oil-burning ships.Already the use of oil fuel in ships of certain countries is increasing rapidly, and unless therefore wetake early steps to convert our coaling stations to oiling stations we shall risk losing, to some extent,the means of bunker control of neutrals which was so valuable in the recent war when coal was ingeneral use.Even if full effect is given to the Home production of creosote from coal, it would-be necessary tocarbonise 40,000,000 tons of coal to produce 2,000,000 tons of creosote. This quantity, if availableannually, would leave the country dependent upon overseas sources of supply for about two-thirds of thetotal Naval and commercial requirements in war. Moreover, tankage for receiving the home-producedcreosote would be necessary and also stocks of oil fuel to mix with it before issue to ships.It will be seen, therefore, that the existing inadequacy of tankage and stocks makes it impossible tomaintain the same supremacy with oil fuel as with coal, unless special measures are taken to secure theBritish oil fuel position.The Admiralty and the Petroleum Executive are of opinion that this security can only be achieved bythe provision of adequate stocks of oil fuel for commercial purposes in addition to the stocks approved forthe Navy.The Admiralty view with grave concern the danger of Admiralty stocks being drawn upon in war forcommercial necessities, thus limiting Fleet movements when least desirable. This will inevitably occurif sufficient commercial reserves are not available.It is probable that Oil Bunkering Companies will be unwilling to expend capital in providingaccommodation and maintaining commercial stocks of oil fuel in excess of a few months&apos; turnover intheir ordinary trade.It is estimated, on the experience of mercantile expenditure obtained during the recent war, that atleast 1^ million tons of oil fuel should be available in the United Kingdom, to meet the annual consumptionof British oil-burning Merchantmen ten years hence : assuming, as is probable, that 75 per cent, of thelarge ships will then be running on oil fuel.We therefore recommend : (a) That a twelve months&apos; war reserve shall be laid down at home and at each important bunkeringstation abroad as a national necessity in war for commercial purposes.  This reserve to bein addition to the approved reserve for Naval purposes ;a (b) That the commercial war reserve stock be provided and maintained by the State.W (Intlld.)      W. II. L.H. G.5.2.20.a  (88) AS 7968-15   Pk 34S9  85  2/20  E&amp;S

</content>
</cab>
