<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/98/0 images: 285-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT Ig .THE- PROPERTY. OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVOTMENT) .S e C R e t.\jg-&apos; ;abii .e t*ARMY estimates, 192Q -.31.,Ivsnte by the Seorctary.0i.With reference to cabinet 10 (2o), Conclusion (l), Icirculate, by direction of the Prime Minister, the Minutesof the Finance Committee, 19th Meeting., held on the 9th,instant, when the Army Estimates, 1920 - 21, were discussed.(Sgd.)   M.P.A. hamey;Secretary,Cabinet.Whitehall gardens, S.W. 1*16th February, 192q,
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE. PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY13 GOVERNMENT)SECRETtp ,C * 19th Minutes,ffinal Copy.4CABIN E T,FINANCE COMMITTEE,CONCLUSIONS \Pf a meeting hold at 10 Downing Street, S.W.on MONDAY, FEBRUARY 9th. 1920, at 5.0. p,uwPRESENT;The Prime Minister &apos;   (in the Chair)he Rt. Hon, A. Chamberlain, M.P.Ohancollor of the Exchequer.he Rt. Hori. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,hord PriTjf Seal.The Rt. Hon. Sir Auckland 4eddes,EoCiB.,M*P. President of theBoard of TraderThe following were also present;-He Rt. Hon. The Earl Oarzon of[odleston,  .G. ,0.0.3*1. ,G.C,IeE.,Secretary of State for Foreignp: &amp;irs.jye Rt. Hon. W. Long, M.P.,pirst Lord of the Admiralty.3 Rt. Hon. H.A.L.Eisher, M.P.,  ,resident of the Board of Education.The Rt. Hon. W.S.Churohill, M*P?Secretary of State for War &amp; Air,Major-General Sir P,P*de B.Radoli fejICoCoM^G. eC*B. ,D.S.0.., Directorof Military Operations.Sir        Duke, G.CI.E.,E.C.S.I.,Permanent Under Secretary ofState.eutenant-Colonel Sir M.P.A* Hanlcey, G.O.B............... Seoretary.J&amp;F.W. teitn Ross........................Assistant  Secretary.o-utenant-Oolenel L. Storr,.C,B...........Assistant   Seoretary.
ABMY ESTIMATES1980-21.MESOPOTAMIA.(1) , The Committee had before them a summary of ArmyEstimates, 1920-21 (C0.-585), together with a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for War (C.2.-586).   TheseEstimates amounted to a gross total. ofLiU^^CKKvOOO-k &quot;made up as follows:-(a) The normal peace-time Army, for which a.maximum of  62,000,000 had been settledby the, Cabinet, &quot;but which would only re-quire  55,500,000 in 1220-21, owing tothe use of surplus.stocks of stores andclothing;(b) Terminal expenses of the War (transportcharges, separation allowances, reinstate-. meat&quot;of property* medals, war graves, etc.)for which  30,500,000 would be required:(c) Abnormal expenditure arising out oftemporary obligations (e.g. the Rhine,Constantinople) or new responsibilities,(e.g,Palestine, Mesopotamia, Persia) for/ v which  48,000,000 was assigned.It was explained that the provision for the normal fpeace-time -Army was based on the pre-war establishment,which, of course, at present prices would cost roughlydouble what it did before the War. &apos; Some question wasraised as to whether this was the correct basis to adopthaving regard to the alteration fua oiroumstancas.   No&apos; re-duction, however, appeared practicable owing to the d-is-appearanoe of Germany as a military Power, in view of thefact that the pre-war Army, though&apos; organised to meet anemergency on the Continent, had been designed, so far asits strength was concerned, solely with a view to thodefence of the Empire, and our liabilities in this respect,so far from being diminished, had been   increased by theacceptance of the mandates over Palestine and Mesopotamia.It was polilted out, however$ that  3,750,000 towards thecost of the garrisons in these oountries had been foundout,of the provision for ,the normal peace-time Army.(8)   The Estimates submitted by the Secretary of Statefor War provided for the maintenance of 14,000 white and50,000 native troops in Mesopotamia, at a cost of  18^00,000exclusive of  3,000,000 for capital expenditure on barrackaccommodation, etc. -1-
21SIt was recognized that the cost of such a garrison forMesopotamia was prohibitive and that it must be curtailed..The suggestion was made that the Mosul Province should beevacuated, but it was pointed out that this district was-therichest part of Mesopotamia and the centre of the oilfields,and that if it were abandoned the withdrawal from Mesopotamiaaltogether would have to be considered,.It was agreed that no such drastic decision could becontemplated or discussed, pending   *-(a)   the receipt of the Survey Report whichthe Secretary of State for War had beenasked to obtain in regard to the oil.resources of Mesopotamia, the prelimin-ary accounts of which were highly promising(Cabinet 8 (20), Appendix II (1)   )   ;(b) The receipt of the Report from GeneralHaldane, the new Gonoral Officer Com-manding, who had been given specialinstructions to review the whole situa-tion with a view to a reduction in thestrength of the garrison;(o) the conclusion of the Treaty of Peace withTurkey, on the operation of which it wasrecognised that the future state of orderin these territories would i*.epand*Pending the abo^e developmentsThe Committee accepted a proposal by theSecretary of State for War that the sumof  21,500,000 proposed for the mainten-ance of the garrison in Mesopotamiashould be halved, discretion being leftto the War Office to determine themethod by which this reduction shouldbe secured?It was pointed out,.however, that, in the event of anattack by the Turks or Arabs, reinforcements would.be required,and that the above arrangements would then have to be re-considered. .(3)    The Provisional Army Estimates included a sum of 2,750,.000 for the maintenance of the force now stationedin North-W&apos;est Persia, and it did not include a provision of 8,750,000 which the Indian Government was claiming inrespect of the forces in other -parts of Persia.   It was agreedthat the War Office could reasonably protest against being
charged with this e?p. OnditurSj which appeared on the face ofit excessive, and the India Offioe was requested to enquirehow this figure was arrived at*It was pointed out that the troops were quite inadequateto resist any serious attacks by the Bolsheviks,After a discussion with the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, the director of Military Operations and Mr.PUA.L.Fisher and Sir William Duke, representing the IndiaOffice, the Committee agreedThat, as a corollary to the decision notto hold the Caspian (Cabinet Conferenceat Paris on January 19, 1920, Conclusion 3)the following re-dispositions of troops inPersia should be made:-(a)   The Immediate and entire with-drawal of the force of approxi-mately 1,700 men under GeneralMalleson at Meshed together withthe troops on their lines ofcommunications.(b) The completion, as rapidly aspossible, of the withdrawal, whichfiad already been decided on, ofthe force of approximately 10,000men in South Persia:(c) The.retention for the present ofthe force at Hamadan, but thereduction of the figure of 2,750,000 proposed for theupkeep of the forces in North-West Persia to one half, discre-iion being left to the War Officeto secure this rediiction asappeared best) tetjj either inthe form of a reduction of theforce or of the time withinwhich the occupation should beContinued:i(d) The Committee decided that theIndia Office should send a tele- ram oomnunieating the abovedecisions to the Government ofIndia,vt and       (4)   The Armv^ Estimates Included provision for the main-fcetlne*tenance of 6,000 white and 23,000 native troops in Egypt(over and above the pre-war garrison of 6,000 white troops)at a cost of approximately  7,000,000 a year, and for a forceof 9,000 British and 26,000 native troops in Palestine, at acost of about  7,750,000, exclusive of  1,250,000 for land andhutting.
It was agreed that provision on this acaXe*^sp^eciarLy&quot;for the maintenance of order in Palestine, where no serioustrouble could he anticipated, was indefensible,fand thetCommittee decidedThat, in view of the general financial situation,the total amount included for the cost of thegarrisons of Egypt and Palestine, over and abovethe cost of the normal garrison of 6,000 men forEgypt must be reduced by one-half:The Prime Minister-undertook to transmit thisdecision to Lord Milner, and to request him togo into the whole question with Lord Allenby onthe spot, and to report what dispositions wouldbe made to meet the new situation caused bythis decision.A copy of the telegram is attached (Appendix) .Iropriationa (5) the Secretary of State for War had proposed to deductn Aid.from the gross estimate of  155,000,000 appropriations inaid amounting to  103,000,000, made up as followsOrdinary appropriations in aid .......    21,000,000jsx.tra appropriations in aid, repres-enting (a) charges to the Vote ofCredit prior to April 1, 1919, re-payable by the Dominions............     34,000,000and(b) Charges to the Vote of Credit andto subsequent Army Votes repayable byGermany............................      48,000,000It was pointed out that there was considerable doubtwhether extraordinary receipts to anything like the suggestedamount would be realised during the forthcoming year.   Somepayment would, no doubt, be secured from Germany, but itwas doubtful whether the amount available for payment toGreat Britain of her share of the cost of the Army ofOccupation would be so much as  48,000,000 in 1920-21.Further, it appeared that the Australian Government was alsobudgeting on the expectation of realising its share of re-parations, and that if these were not received the Dominionrepayments to the-Exchequer&apos;might also be postponed.It was also explained that there were great Parlia-mentary objections to taking extraordinary receipts asappropriations in aid of ordinary Votesj instead of pausingthem into ihe Exchequer.
The committee decided :-(a) That the Army Estimates should onlyinclude ordinary receipts as appro-. priations in aid.(b) That extraordinary receipts shouldbe paid into the Exchequer, but thata clear note in regard to these   iextraordinary, receipts should be putinto the Army Estimates.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.9 th February, 192Q. &apos;
A P P E N D I X.SECRET CYPHER TT^EGRAM.From :- Foreign Office,To Lord Allenby, Cairo.Following for Lord Milner from prime Minister.War Office report to Cabinet that maintenance of 6,000white and 23,000 native troops in Egypt over and above pre-war garrison of 6,000 will cost 7 millions a year.   Maintenanceof 9,000 British and 26,000 native troops in Palestine willcost    &quot;7j millions, exclusive of l  millions for land andhutting.In view of financial situation Cabinet have decided thatthis sum of 16 millions must be reduced by one-half,   Pleasego into whole question with Lord Allenby and report bytelegram what dispositions he can make to meet this Situation.Question is urgent in connection with Estimates.a o A . * *

</content>
</cab>
