<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/98/0 images: 361-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
VAILG - - ----wTSMOMDUM BY TRU PiSSIDlsW OP 5Hj BOARD OP TBADD.DKrOOK^Oli OP POQDC(fillIn connection with the report of the Committee onf\ Do-control of Pood there are two points and two only, tov    which I desire to call attention.&apos;&quot;1.   It is highly desirable that the Pood Manufacturingand Canning Trades ih this country should be freed from .all forms of direct or indirect control.   These industriesr    have to compete in foreign markets,with similar industriesy   in other countries-particularly in America, where enterpriseis untrammelled by any Government restrictions-and representa-tions have been made &quot;to the Board to the effect that ourproducers will be handicapped in competition if they are notleft with a free hand.   This matter is one of great importanceif Pood Control is continued for another four or five years.I submit that it is perfectly consistent with the maintenanceof control in vital matters for those industries to be licensedto purchase their supplies and disposo of their productswithout any form of Government interference.   As a matter offact, their activities enter only fractionally into the problem,of Pood supply and its cost, and I am certainly of opinionthat in their case the predominant consideration  from thopoint of view of present National interosts, is the commercialone.2;  While, I think it dosizable as recommended in thereport, that such control,as is retained should be exercisedas far&apos;as possible, through traders (and consequently throughAssociations of Traders to render the administration manageable)I think it most important that.action along these lines shouldnot be allowed to develop into the deliberate establishment andfostering of Trade combinations or Trusts.   It has already boenmade apparent in tho House, in tho case of Goal, that the Statecreation of Trusts would be resented and resisted by a powerfulsection of the community.   In view of: this, if for no otherreason, I should regard it as highly imprudent for the Governmentto take any action which could bo interpreted as an encouragementof Pood Trusts or Combinations.   The Government is already, underthe Profiteering Act, investigating Trusts and Combinations, andit would,not be consistent at the same time to promote them intho Pood industries.   Indeed, to do so might give riso to apopular agitation, which it would be most difficult to moot.A,0,Geddes.18th February, 1920,

</content>
</cab>
