<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/98/0 images: 365-369</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
H.8 Britannic M^w^&quot;^r $///&apos;.IRISH PRISONERS IN WORilVOOD SCRUBS PRISON.------^ (circulated by the Home Secretary)./      I circulate to my colleagues a Memorandum which I have received fromALl^fe^lwSlyo Ruggles-Brise, the Chairman of the Prison Commissioners, covering&quot;a report from Major BriBCoe, the Governor of Wormwood Sorubs Prison.    MajorBriscoe is an experienced and competent Governor, in whose judgment andability I have every confidence.The matter is urgent, and I should be glad to have Cabinet authorityat the earliest possible moment for the transfer of these men from myoustody to that of the War Office in an Internment Camp.&apos; E.S.19th February, 1920.PRISOB COMMISSION,HOME OFFICE,WHITEHALL,19th February, 1920.The Secretary of State.Major Briscoe, the Governor of Wormwood Scrubs Prison, has handed mehis report this morning, and, after conversation with him, I am satisfiedthat the continued internment of these men at Wormwood Scrubs Prison iefraught with much danger.The presence of the man MoGrath is at the bottom of the trouble.Until his arrival the other internees, who are on the whole a respectablebody of men, were apparently content to live quietly under the regulationswhich were approved with much care and thought, providing only for thesafe custody consistent with their enjoyment of as much privilege as couldbe allowed.    Few, if any, oomplaints were reoeived by the Commissionersuntil the arrival of MoGrath, but now it is a recurrence of the trouble withwhich we became so familiar when the Irish convicts under de Valera were atLewes, and later when the Irish deportees were oentred in small companiesat different Prisons.    It is the old story of these men organising underthe leadership of one man, and obeyed him implicitly whatever their ownfeelings and inclinations might be.     It is evident that such a body hasnow been organised at Wormwood Sorubs, and having regard to the probabilitythat the number now there, 70, will in the near future be increased perhapsto two or three hundred, the position is serious and requires graveconsideration on the part of the Government.    I am satisfied, having newhad long experience in dealing with these Irishmen, both as ordinary oonviotaat Dartmoor, Portland and Lewes, and later as deportees at various Prisons,
colthat the root cause of the defiant and rebellious attitude which theyassume lies in the fact that they are interned in a Prison, and are madesubject to Prison regulations in many respects identioal with thosein force for convicted prisoners.    The demand of the Irishmen at Lewes in1916 was for recognition as &quot;belligerents&quot;, i.e. internment in a MilitaryCamp,    This was refused at the time, and the grave difficulties that arosewere solved only, as it will be remembered, by a general amnesty.    Thedemand of the deportees at a later period was exactly identioal.    I am not-aware what itte views of the Government may be as to the policy of acoeptingthe status of &quot;belligerenoy&quot; implied by internment in a Military Camp, butI have from the beginning urged that internment in a Military Camp was thesafest and best and wisest method of custody for these Irishmen.    I amsupported by my colleagues and by all Governors who have handled these menin English Prisons.    We have had during the last few years amplepreoedent to show what misohief and trouble may arise if by continuedoontumaoy prisoners force themselves into a situation where close cellularconfinement is the only remedy against their insubordination.    We have hadthiB precedent not only in the oase ef Irishmen, but in the case of theConscientious Objectors, whom we were obliged to keep for long periods oftime, even several weeks, in close cellular confinement, as they would notgive an undertaking to abstain from disorder if allowed out of their cells,even for exercise whioh health demanded.    The consequence of this was, asthe Secretary of State will remember, that these men were the subject ofconstant medical care and attention, and that many had to be released, andthat in the intervals they disturbed not only the order and discipline   ofthe Prison where they were confined, but they caused public scandal byBhouting and yelling from their windows to the   annoyanoe of people livingin the neighbourhood.I feel certain that if these Irishmen are kept at Wormwood ScrubsPrison under the present regulations! which, as stated by the Governor,give no power of effeotive punishment, we shall have a repetition of allthese thingB.    Vfe shall.have medical difficulties and releases on grounds ofill health;   and this in itself would defeat the purpose of the IrishGovernment which is, as I understand, that these men should be kept out ofIreland and in safe custody in this Country.     I believe, as I have alwaysbelieved, that Buch Bafe custody can be secured in a Military Camp.    Atleast I would earnestly desire that the experiment be tried, not becausethe Prison Authorities desire to shift their responsibilities.    On thecontrary, they are prepared to go on to the end if the Government areprepared to face the dangers whioh will, I think, inevitably arise.    Iunderstood from the Irish Seoretary at our interview this morning thatthe Irish Government do net set great store on the question of belligerencywhich would be conceded by internment in a Military Camp.    If this is theoase, it seems to me that the only objection to internment in a MilitaryCamp is removed, and in the general interests of order and security Iwould strongly advise that the Irish deportees be at the earliest possible
moment removed from Wormwood Sorubs and plaoed under the Military Authorities.Inquiries have been made at the War Office, and it has been ascertainedthat the Internment Damp at Oawestry is   in process of being dismantled, butthat that process is not yet completed.    The oamp, generally speaking, isstill standing.    The barbed wire haB been taken down and rolled up, but isnot yet removed, and can be put up again quickly.    The Camp consists ofseveral Compounds which oould accommodate 1000 men each.    Any one of theseoould be taken into use as a separate Camp.    Oswestry is a centre at whioh,moreover, there are some troops.    There are two possible alternatives,namely, Brocton in Staffordshire and Oatteriok in Yorkshire, but at both ofthese Camps the dismantling has gone further and the wire has been takenright away.    All considerations seem to point to making use of one of theCompounds at Oswestry.(Signed)   E* RUGGLES-BRISE.H.M. PRISON,WORMWOOD SCRUBS, W.19th February, 192Q,.Tg the Prison Commissioners.Gentlemen,I have the honour to call your urgent attention to the very gravestate of affairs likely to arise at Wormwood Sorubs under the existingregulations for the treatment of the Irish internees.    They now number 70in all, but I understand that a considerably larger number are likely to besent   here.   They are treated, as you are aware, under special regulationsapproved by the Secretary of State and by the Irish Government.    The firstbatoh we received on the 12th December, numbering 4 only.    This number waBgradually increased to 28, and eventually a few weeks ago te the presentnumber, 70.At the beginning things proceeded smoothly.    The men gave no troubleand were apparently satisfied with the regulations under which they weretreated, but with the advent of J. MoGrath a quite different state of affairehas arisen.    This nan has constituted himself Captain, and receives implicitobedience from the rest.    Immediately after his arrival, demands beganto be made for various oonoessions.    In some smaller matters the.Commissioners granted their requests, but it soon became evident that withevery request granted more olaims were likely to be made.    The matterculminated yesterday when I discovered that one of the internees, Gubbins,was in seoret possession cf a cheque bookj   although under the regulationsinternees are allowed to keep private books, documents, etc cheque booksare regarded as being in the same oategcry as money, and the interneeB have
not been allowed to retain them.    It is obvious that by so doing theywould be able if in possession of private means to suborn the officers ofthe Prison whence muoh mischief might ensue.    All internees are searchedon reoeption, but the search is conducted with great delicacyi and is notmade more oppressive than possible.     In this particular Case the fact thatGubbins had a cheque book on his person escaped notice, and it only beoameknown to me when Gubbins enclosed a cheque in a letter, although I knewI had not given him  permission to have the use of hie cheque book.    I sentfor the man and told him that he must give up his cheque book.    He declinedto do bo without the authority of McGrath.    I saw MoGrath, and he, in amost defiant and insolent way, defied me to take possession of the ohequebook by force, threatening that in such event there would be very serioustrouble both to myself personally and to the Staff, and that they were onlywaiting for such an opportunity.    This threat following upon others whichhave been made when I have expressed myself unable to make small concessionsplaces me in a very difficult and almost unbearable position, for it must beremembered that the Governor has little or no powers of punishment under theregulations as approved for internees.    All he can do is to deprive themof association, or of exeroise, or of magazines, and these powers are futile,having regard to the fact that these men are now acting as one organised bodyunder their Captain, McGrath, and in the event of these punishments beingordered they would probably oo-operate in a body to defeat it.    I amsatisfied from olose observation of the manner and demeanour of these mensince the advent of MoGrath that very grave trouble is brewing, and the timeis arriving to decide definitely whether these men are to have all theconcessions that they ask, or whether they are to be firmly governed underapproved regulations    I think it my duty to warn the Commissioners that inthe oourse of the next few days, if the numberless demands they are nowmaking, e.g. razors, knives, articles of food, extra letters, visits, etcand longer association , are not conceded, we may have a repetition of thevery grave events when the Irishmen were detained under more or less similarconditions at Lewes.     If I punish one man for defiance of orders orinsolence, and shut him up in his cell, the probability is that his cell doorwould be broken open, and eventually every man following the lead of McGrathwould be punished by cellular confinement.    In suoh oase, apart from thebreaking up which would be sure to ensue, there would be the difficulty ofexeroising these men, for they could not be allowed exercise in bodies, and toexeroise singly or by two or three, would be too great a strain on my staff,nor would there be time to carry it out in the day.I am, of course, quite prepared to carry out the orders of theGovernment, and keep these men in safe custody to the best of my ability,but the Commissioners will, I know, realise the great difficulty in which Iam plaoed if as I say, no power of effective punishment is available;   and itis having the gravest effect on the Staff, seeing a3 they do, day by day theGovernor brow-beaten and insulted by defiant men asking for privileges whichcannot be granted.    All say, one and all, that so long as they are kept in aPrison and are subject to Prison Rules and Regulations like ordinary
convicted men they will continue to defy authority.    The solicitor v.-bom Isaw frequently in the oaBe of Alderman Kelly, lately released on medicalgrounds, tcld me that there&quot;could be no cessation of trouble as long asthese men are kept in Prisdn.I consider that in spite of the arrangements for the safe custody withthe assistance of both the military and the police, the internaladministration is of extreme difficulty, and I do not see my way clearlyto carry out the government of the Prison unless my powers of punishment aregreatly inoreased.In my opinion the proper remedy is to take these men away entirely fromPrison surroundings * and  laoe them in a Military Camp.    I don!t knowwhat objection there may be to such a Course, but it seems to me distinctlythe best and safest way of keeping these men in the quiet custody which, Iunderstand, is the great object to which they are aiming.X am,Gentlemen,Your obedient Servant?(Signed)A.V. BRISOOE.Governor.SP144-8.

</content>
</cab>
