<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/98/0 images: 397-402</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS ER.ITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT^;*r    secret,% C / , CABINET.C. P. 683. .    -royal ^grigult^,Memo ran dugi by the Minist e r \ o f^ Agf i culture &amp;-Fisheries../    /Xu. Ministry of Agriculture &amp; Fisheries&quot;--- 4 --Whitehall Place, S.W.I.I wish to ask the permission of the Cabinet to- sendthe letter (of which I attach a copy marked &quot;A&quot;) to theChairman of the Royal Commission on Agriculture,   I also     &apos;attach copies of his two letters, to which mine is the    .--suggested reply.The matter is one of some urgency, as the next -meeting of the Commission has been fixed for February 2.6th,and it is necessary that the decisions of the Governmentshould be communicated to them before that date.   I shallbe glad, therefore, if the question can be disposed of atthe next meeting of the Cabinet,(Initialled)     l cf F,19th February, 1920.
Draft Reply to chairman. Royal Commissionon Agriculture.Ministry of&quot;A^riouTture k5&apos;isheri es*4, Whitehall, PI ace:&apos;,S.WV&quot;1.February, 1920.Sir,I beg to acknowledge receipt of your&apos;two letters,cf January 29th and 30th, informing me of the resignationsfrom the Royal Commission on Agriculture of yourself (asJ1 William Ashley-Chariman) and of the six other members whose names are inR\S, Cautley,K.C, M.P.      the margin,  on the general grounds that a majority of theG,,G. Pea.w,H. paiker.     commission had resolved to embark upon the examination offt Anker Simmons.genry overman,   a long &quot;list of further subjects which are not includedin the terms of Reference, and for the consideration ofwhich the composition of the Commission could not be con-sidered sufficiently representative or otherwise appropri-ate iThe first of these subjects, upon the considerationtf which the Commission proposes to embark, is that of&quot;Security of Tenure,&quot; and with regard to this it hasannounced its intention &quot;to go fully into the matter andto consider it in all its bearings as it affects theAgricultural industry&quot;.This decision is in effect a refusal to accept theofficial definition of the scope of the Reference which$as communicated to you, on the authority of the PrimeMinister, by sir Arthur Boscawen in his letter of July27th last.   He therein stated&quot;The Government purposely limited the Referencein the first instance so as to exclude wider ,questions, by which I understand is meant suchquestions as security of tenure and the nationalisa-\tion of the land, because they wish to have an &apos;early)
report on the economic question, and for this reasonthey placed on the Commission no direct representa-tives of land-owners hut an equal number of repre-sentatives of agriculturist?! and labourers.   It wouldbe manifestly unfair that these question, which pro-foundly affect the interest of land-owners, should beconsidered in the absence of any representation of them.The Government realise that evidence on these subjectscannot be excluded altogether, in so far at leastas it may bear on the economic position of the industry,but they are of obinion that if there is to be the fulli examination and consideration of these questions itshould be undertaken by a separate Royal Commissionerpecially constituted for the purpose.&quot;With regard to the remaining subjects which the Commissiondesires to add to the terms of its Reference, I do not un&amp;er-estimate their importance but.as they have nearly all been ex-haustively examined and fully reported upon, very recently, by theAgricultural Reconstruction committee presided over by LordSelborne, and are already being dealt with under the administrativeand legislative programme of the Government, it does not 3earnnecessary or desirable to trouble tho Commission to consider themafresh.-In these circumstances, and in view of the other reasons whichyou advance, I have come to the conclusion, after the most carefuland anxious consideration, that it will be my duty to represent tothe prime Minister that he should advise His Majesty to releasethe Commission from its duties,&quot; and to bring its proceedings toa close.At the same time, I desire to express the cordial thanks of.the Government for the zeal, care and ability which you, as Chair-man, and all your fellow commissioners, have devoted to the con-sideration of the questions dealt with in the Interim Report sub-mitt ed on December loth, and to assure you that your joint labourshave contributed most usefully to the solution of a very importantand urgent problem.Believe me,Yours very faithfully,ir William Peat.
COPIES Off LETTERS FROM THE CHAIRMAN^ ROYAL QOHfclBSIOH. OHAGRICULTURE TO THE MINISTER OF AGRgCULTURr iliD ?ISKBRl5jS.1, Queen Anners Gate Buildings,So&apos;//. * . .1 .29th January. 1920.My Lord,At the first Meeting of the Commission afterthe Christmas Recess, I informed the Commission that forvarious reasons which I indioated I desired to retire.   Ireminded them that twelve members of the Commission basedtheir Interim Report upon the julicy of the Corn ProductionAct, 1917 ( as regards guarantees of corn prices to farmersand consequent requirements as to cultivation) being a recog-nised policy of the State until 1922, and that the Governmenthad&apos;indioated its desire to continue and stitngthen that p&amp;ioyand, therefore, without being responsible for that policy, thosetwelve Commissioners recommended a prooedure by which itcould be made effective.   The other members of the Commissionwere not prepared to approve of that pelioy and inthsir InterimReport recommended that the farmers be left free to cultivatetheir lands according to the rules, of good husbandry free fromany control.At the meeting referred to above, I also men-tioned that I felt that the prospects of the Commission doinguseful work in the future was open to questionsThe Commission has adopted the Minutes of theEvidence Subcommittee in which 16 matters ,described as prelim-inary list of subjects whioh should be placed before theCommission for attention) were set out, vizj-I. Security of Tenure, and the amendment of AgriculturalHoldings Acts.2. Local Taxation and Rating.3, Game Laws.4. Weights and Measures.5. AatIcultural Education, Research and Demonstrations6* Co-operation^7. Credits8. Insurance*9. Draining?10. Transport and Marketing.II. Small Holdings.12a Hou9ing*13. Eradication of Diseases of Animals.14, Eradication of Weeds and Pests,15. Distribution of Information.16. Rural Re-organlsation*and by a resolution carried by 13 votes to 4 (aorae members ofthe Commit!.ion not voting) it was deoidod to deal with thesematters, leaving the Government) to appoint more members tothe Commission if it thinks fit.
It was also agreed, that it was not possible forthe GommisBion in future to Limit the consideration of thequestion ox Security of Tenure Ias the Commission nMendeavoured   to do in the past) and that they would go^fully!Into thrt matter and consider it in all its bearings as itaffected the agricultural industry.This resolution 1b reference to Security ofTentre   is in opposition to the views of the Governmentexpressed in Sir Arthur Boscawenrs letter of the  9th July,1919, in which he stated that the Government was &quot;of opinionthat if there is to be a full examination and consideration -of these questions (Security of Tenure and Land ftationali-saiion) they should be undertaken by a separate Royal Oom-mission specially constituted for tho purpose&quot;.I am hot prepared to say that it i3 possible tolimit the consideration o  becurity of Tenure, &quot;but I am also&quot;&apos;not prepared to consider it as a member of this commissionunless all partios direotly interested are represented onW$ CommissionsI also say that an exhaustive examination of the16 matters above referred to. which the Commission has deter-mined to consider  as a preliminary list of subjects, wouldOBuse me to doubt if the labours of the Commission can bebrought to an early conclusion.   In addition to these 16 sitb-jects . many bthers equally germane to the agricultural in-dustry may be Iprou^ht forward for the consideration of theCommission, and If all exhaustively dealt with the prospectof bringing the labours of the Commission to an end, in myjudgementj would be remote*On a review of all the circumstances, I am un-willingly led to the conclusion that the claims which my ownbusiness make upon me require such attention that t cannotContinue to occupy the Chair and must ask leave to be relievedof my duties as a member of. the Commission,aYours faithfully,(sd)   W,B*PEAT*The Bt. Hon, Lord Lee of -Fareham, P.C, G.B.E,   K.CB,Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries,- Whitehall S.W,.1,
The Bt, Hon. Sord Lee of Pareham, P.C,   0*3.32.   Kft0*B,President,Board olericulture and Fioheries,WHITEHALL     S.W..1.My Lord,I have the honour to inform you thatyesterday^ Meeting of the Commission, resignations fromMr. G.G.Rea, Mr. W.Anker Simmons, Mrft Henry Overmanc IffiriH.S*Cautley, and Mr, Parker were tendered in addition tomy own*   Sir William Ashleyf3 resignation wa3 reportedto the Commission on the 15th instant*   I have informsdthe gentlemen in question that the fact of their resignnations would be formally notified by mo to yourself9The  Sooretary will formally notify theSecretary of State for the Home Department of these resignnation-s in due course.Yours faithfully,(Sd) mt BoPSATiRoyal Commission., on Agriculture.1, Queen Anncrs Gate Buildings,30th January, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
