<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/98/0 images: 435-438</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THI3 DOCTO-IENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MJg3TYIS GOVERNMENT.YS 7. C R E T .C. P. 689.CABINET.COMMITTEE ON IRELAND.HE-ARRANCEMENT OP THE IRISH. JUDICIARY,Note by Mr. Lonp,,The Committee on Ireland ha6 considered the attachedproposals, with regard to tho division of the Judiciary&quot;bet we on the North and South, put forward &quot;by the LordChancellor of Ireland.     The Committee had the advantage ofconsulting the Lord Chancellor personally in regard to them-and now r-ecoranend that they bo accepted by the Cabinet.A Sub-Committee is working out the details of thoLord Chancellor&apos;s scheme and draft clauses will be presentedto the Cabinet early next week.(Signed)   $4 H. LONG.20th February, 1920.
^Ggs^ygp fs*. mpmfMs^ w tiis ir ibh judiq im y com sequent0:1 T3;i! PROPOSES Off HIS MAJESTY&apos;3 ggTggJBBMgM8,moT,ahdtai by ^the / Lord 0hanu;3eXlprMiof Ireland^I understand that it is now decided that there shouldbe separate judiciaries for Northern and Southern Ireland, andthe object of this memorandum is to suggest the establishmentof one High Court of appeal for the whole of Ireland for the^termination of appeals from the courts in either provincean arrangement, which, I understand% will not be objected toby the representatives from Ulster,It is obvious that if there are to be separate anddistinct judiciaries for the two provinces, the minorities ineach Province will regard the courts of that Province withsuspicion and distrust &amp;   The remedy for this is to $tfovide astrong Court of ippoal for the&apos; ftato^xUraiion of all appealsfrom either Province,,   This ooart should consist of fivejudges, namely,, the Lord Chancellor and Chief Justice of theSouthern Province and the Chief Justice of the Northern Pro-vinoe? and a judge of the same province to the nominated byhim.     This court when so constituted, should have power toco-opt and additional judge, to be selected by them fromeither judiciary0    Under the existing practice in Ireland,there is still retained a primary appeal to the DivisionalCourtt   This appeal was many years ago abolished in Englandwith the result that the appeal in all cases tried by a singlejudge with or without a jury goes direct to the Court of AppealMy proposal is that for this purpose each Province should haveits own Oourt of Appeal, to which all such appeals should godirect,    Por the protection ands^tisfaotion of the minorities/in eaohCONTOSNTIAl.
in each Province and to meet in addition the many cases inwhich one of the partids to the appeal to the ProvincialCourt of Appeal will be&apos; resident within the limits of theother Province, a further appeal is essential to such acourt as I have above suggested, namely, a Court      whichmight be oiled the &quot;High Court of Appeal in Ireland&apos;1 for thedetermination of all appeals from either of the ProvincialCourts of Appeal.     This plan not only preserves the Imperialor National element in the fligh &quot;Court of Appeal., but also miti-gates the provincialism or decentralisation of both branchesof the lagal profession while It is also has the advantage ofproviding work for the members of the existing Court of Appealin Ireland.      As at present constituted it consists of theLord Chancellor with two permanent Lords Justices, while theChief Justice and the Master of the Bolls are ex-officio mem-bers.     It could be retained in that form for the purposesof the Provincial Court of Appeal of Southern Ireland just asin England at present the Lord Chancellor and the Chief Justiceare ex-officio members of the Court of Appeal, though the for-mer never and the latter but seldom sits in it.   Similarly, theLord Chancellor and Chief Justice of the Southern Provinceneed not sit In it but could reserve themselves exclusivelyfor the &quot;High Court of Appeal&quot; leaving the Provincial Court ofAppeal to consist of the Master of the Polls, and the two LordsJustices with power in case of emergency to call in, as inEngland at present, the services of * puisne judge as an adli-tional member.     This would not multiply the right of appealif the suggested abolition of the present appeal to the Divisional/Court
19th ffebr uorfy^ 1920(ACourt was abolished,    To satisfy Provincial sentiment thisHigh Court of ^peal should sit in tho Northern Province forthe hearing of all appeals from the Court of Appeal cf thatProvince, and, similarly, i- should sit in the Southern Pro-^vinoo in the converse oase.(3d)   J.Ho CAMPBELL.

</content>
</cab>
