<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/40/16 images: 166-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  A ugust 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 366.9th A ugust, 1943.Copy No.SUMMARY    OF    OPERATIONS    OF    BOMBER    COMMAND    for fortnight ENDING 1200 HOURS, SUNDAY, 1st AUGUST, 1943.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.HAMBURG has suffered a series of the most devastating attacks everlaunched against a great city. Essen and Remscheid have been successfullyraided. Lancasters returning from North Africa attacked the docks at Leghorn.In the month of July the record activities of June were surpassed; 6,320 sorties were flown and 16,830 tons of bombs dropped.Summary of Operations.Target.HamburgLeghorn      ...EssenHamburgHamburgRemscheidIn addition, 45 sorties were launched on small harassing raids on german towns; 10 aircraft were despatched on anti-submarine patrols and 268 mines were laid.Night Operations.Hamburg (24th/25th, 27th/28th and 29th/30th July).Hamburg is the second city and most important maritime centre of germany with a population in the neighbourhood of 2 millions.   Its main divisions are (i) The city of Hamburg proper, S. and S.E. of the Alster (a largeartificial lake in the middle of the area).   This is the business and commercial centre of the city,(ii) Altona.   S.W. of the Alster containing an important dock area.(iii) The principal docks, mostly on the south bank of the Elbe, containing the big shipbuilding yards and oil refineries.(iv) The rich residential area round the N. end of the Alster (corresponding to the residential part of the London West End),(v) An inner suburban ring consisting mainly of workers&apos; houses,(vi) Dormitory  suburbs  up  to  5  miles  from  the centre of  the  city,e.g., Wandsbeck.The elimination of Hamburg by bombing is the largest single bombingoperation yet undertaken, and decisive results could not be expected without avery heavy and protracted effort. The total destruction of the city, which is notyet completely accomplished, would, apart from the obvious direct results, havethe most severe effect on German morale, since it would be obvious throughout thecountry that, if the German defences, which had failed in the Ruhr andRhineland, could not save Hamburg from annihilation, the expectation of lifeenjoyed by Hanover, Magdeburg and Berlin itself would be small.[25902] bDate.24/25 July24/2525/2627/2829/3030/31Number of. aircraft dispatched.79133705787777273
The night attacks carried out during the last week in July were supple-nlented by the daylight attacks of the Eighth Bomber Command on the 25th and26th July. All these raids followed each other in such quick succession that itis impossible to distinguish the damage caused on- any particular occasion. the series must be considered as one continuous assault and the damage assessed asa whole.The full effects of the attack are not yet known, since complete photographiccover has been prevented by the clouds and smoke which have obscured large partsof the city. It is, however, established that tremendous damage has been done,and that the business and dock areas have suffered particularly severely. A large area of devastation has also been caused near the main station of Altona.The most serious items of industrial damage identified so far are :&apos;- -(i) Blohm und Voss (submarine building yards).   Very severe damage hasbeen caused throughout the works.    One dry dock has apparently been sunk and another has heeled over,(ii) Ffowaldtswerke (submarine building yards).    Damage includes threeshops hit in the M.A.N. Diesel Engine Works which are nearby.(iii) Ebano Asphaltwerke A.G.(iv) Rhenania Ossag Mineralolwerke A.G. (Lubricating Plant).A full assessment of the damage to the many other undertakings of lesserimportance which have been hit can only be made when full photographic coverhas been obtained.   Prints Nos. 1 and 2 show some of the damage.Essen (25th/26th July).There was good visibility over the target on this occasion and early reportsindicated that a successful and concentrated attack had been delivered. Thefirst photographic reconnaissance aircraft to visit the town 12 hours laterreported that almost the whole of Krupps works was obscured by smoke fromfires still burning. On the following day good cover was obtained though someof the fires had still not been extinguished.The devastation both in Krupps and in the adjacent parts of the town iscomparable to that caused by our earlier attacks in March and April. The mostheavily damaged residential area is that immediately W. and S.W. of Kruppswhich had escaped comparatively lightly from previous assaults; it largely con-sisted of housing estates for Krupps workers, as did other areas in theneighbourhood of the works which were destroyed in this attack. In all, about350 acres were devastated.self, the most serious damage is in the central section of theworks which is mainly concerned with steel processing and heavy machineryassembly. Damage has also been done to the pit-head equipment of the twocoalmines which are inside Krupps perimeter and to the shops in the south partof the works (see print No. 3) which are thought to process &quot; Widia &quot; a specialalloy.It is hoped that this attack will have prevented any resumption of producetion in Essen and will have discouraged attempts to restore production in otherRuhr and Rhineland cities even where there may still be substantial numbersof inhabitable houses and undestroyed factory buildings.Remscheid (30th/31st July).Remscheid, for its size (107,000 inhabitants), plays an.important part in theGerman industrial system. It is the fifth largest producer of special steels inthe Reich and is a considerable manufacturer of tools and equipment of various kinds.In the first photographs the town was so obscured by smoke from fires still burning that detailed assessment was impossible. Later photographs show thatdevastation on a large scale has been caused.Results of Previous Raids.Wuppertal (Elberfeld).Photographs have now been obtained and show that the attack on the24th/25th June was as completely successful as had been hoped.   Almost thewhole town has been destroyed : 500 acres out of a possible 540 of fully built-up area have been devastated by fire and by H.E.   When added to the almost totaldestruction of Wuppertal/Barmen, previously effected, this attack completes the
virtual annihilation of Wuppertal. The most important factory in Elberfeld a branch of I.G. Farben is more than half destroyed, and most of the largenumber of miscellaneous smaller factories which made up the town&apos;s considerableindustrial potential are out of action as a result of direct damage.Miilheim.&apos; The attack made on Miilheim on 22nd/23rd June is now. shown by photo-graphs to have been completely successful. Here as at Elberfeld the city centre and practically the whole of the closely built-up area has been gutted. Direct damage was done to two big industrial undertakings, the August Thyssen Hiitte(Steelworks) and the Friedrich Wilhelmshutte (Iron Foundry). The damagealone could not have been expected to keep both works completely idle for amonth the period between the attack and the production of day photographiccover; in fact, however, both appeared to be entirely dead on the 24th July. Thisconfirms the view that it is possible to stop production,-not only by direct damageinflicted upon industrial establishments, but also by the destruction of the houses,public utilities and administrative centres, without which organised factory work is impossible.Cologne.Detailed examination of photographs taken on the 4th July reveals the extentof the devastation which the central city area suffered during the attacks on the28th/29th June and the 3rd/4th July. Over 80 per cent, has now been destroyed and of the whole area defined by the river and the green belt nearly 60 per cent,has been devastated. Amongst &quot;numerous industrial and public buildings nowidentified which have been destroyed or severely damaged are the RailwayInspectorate and Railway Management Offices, the Town Hall, the Main PostOffice and Main Telegraph Office.Photographs taken on the 16th July confirm the devastation of the important industrial area on the East bank of the river and show that the importantengineering and armaments factories of Humboldt Deutz have been practicallydestroyed.A reliable source states that when he passed through Cologne on the30th June, two days after the first of these two attacks, fires were still burningin the centre of the town, but he was unable to ascertain the reason for the largenumber of workmen employed on the Hohenzollern Bridge. No damage to thisbridge can be seen on photographs, but it seems probable that the bridge was infact damaged during one of the raids in June.Eder Dam. &apos;Although their propaganda has been busy explaining that the attacks on thedams were of no consequence and caused no dislocation or inconvenience, it is significant to note that&quot;the Germans have already started large-scale reconstruc-tion. Photographs taken on the 17th July show that the Eder Reservoir hasbeen drained and that much preparation has been made for the reconstruction ofthe dam. Extensive hutted camps have been built to accommodate workmenemployed on repairing, and emergency repairs to road and railway bridges havebeen or are being completed along the entire stretch of the Eder Valley. It isnow estimated that the breach of the dam is 96 ft. deep and further damage isvisible beneath this mark. The gap measures 245 ft. along the crown and 123 ft.along the base.Turin.It is reported that the attack on the 12th/13th July was the most successfulyet made on the city. Owing to the lack of water, some fires were still burning two days later. Rail transport suffered badly and some 45 industrial concerns were damaged including the engine plant and warehouses at the Snia Viscose artificial silk works where damage is said to have been very severe.North Italy Switching and Transformer Stations.Although it is difficult to assess from photographs the extent of damage caused by attacks on the switching and transformer stations recently attacked, itcan be stated with certainty that two of the six were damaged, while it is reportedthat a third was severely damaged. It has been reliably reported that the attackscaused, some panic-in Genoa, Parma and Bologna and that as a result civilianswere evacuated from these towns to places in the country.[25902] . b 2
GeneralAn interesting side-light on the present inadequacy of the A.R.P. arrange-ments in the Ruhr is shown by a recent report which states that the Germanscan no longer handle small individual fires started by our raids, but concentratetheir activities on the saving of public buildings, banks, post-offices and the like.After a heavy attack, fires are so numerous that one of their principal tasks is toensure that two or three safety lanes are kept open through the fires to enable thepopulation to proceed to safety.Mining.The following mining successes have been reported : 12th June. A German patrol vessel was damaged by a mine off Arnager,Bornholm.23rd June. A fishing vessel, E-71 Duen, was mined and, sunk off the danish West Coast.2Qth June. Motor Schooner Vitus-Bering was mined and sunk in theKattegat.27th June. The Swedish Dane (1,196 tons) was mined and sunk N.of Elsinore.1st July. The sand-pumper Krocolororg was mined and sunk offMosede Harbour (12 miles S.W. of Copenhagen).23rd July. A patrol vessel was mined, off Tarschellig on the 20th july and later sank. A patrol vessel was mined in the Great Belt on the 20th july and later sank.The Swedish press reports the following :  7tht July. Bodies of German sailors from the German Magdalene(3,283 ftpjis) have been washed up on the West Coast of Skaldeviken (N.E.of the North entrance to the Sound).9th July. A German auxiliary was mined off the coast between Gj edserand Moen.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry,9th August, 1943.













</content>
</cab>
