<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/63/0 images: 76-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1953SECRET GAB!Mi&quot;. &apos;.    .,ri&apos;iVc Copy No.  fin- prA^DH    CODY W&quot;C. (53) 2702nd October, 1953CABINETEAST/WEST TRADE-SECURITY CONTROLS ON THE SALE OFMERCHANT SHIPS AND FISHING VESSELS TO THE SOVIETBLOCMemorandum by the President of the Board of Trade and theFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyWe think the time has arrived when we should modify the rules governing the sale of ships to the Soviet bloc, other than China.2. The policy was last considered by Ministers in July .1950 when the previous government confirmed an earlier decision to prohibit the export of tankers to the bloc, and decided also to impose an embargo on the export of merchant ships ofover 10,000 gross registered tonnage or over 12 knots, and of certain types of fishing vessels. They directed that this policy should be advocated in the international discussions on the subject about to begin in the Paris Group, and that our own position should be reconsidered if necessary when the results of these discussions were known.3. During the Paris discussions there was considerable opposition to theseproposals by certain other countries, and agreement could only be reached toembargo the export of tankers, whaling factories and large ice breakers. It wasagreed, however, that the export of merchant ships, small ice breakers and fishing vessels should be restricted quantitatively, and that countries would not acceptorders for fishing vessels of certain types nor of merchant vessels of over 7,000gross registered tonnage (10,000 dead weight), or of over 12 knots speed, without prior consultation with the other participating countries through the Co-co-ordinating committee of the Paris Group.4. The embargo of tankers, whaling factories and large ice breakers by all members of the Paris Group continues and these ships are not therefore further considered in this paper. Since 1950, however, some countries in the Paris Grouphave exported merchant ships and fishing vessels to the Soviet bloc under the agreed rules, but in accordance with the decisions of Ministers no orders for such ships have been accepted by the United Kingdom although a number of enquiriesfrom the bloc have been received.5. Since United Kingdom shipbuilders generally have had full order booksfor some time ahead and have until recently shown no inclination to build ships for Russia or other countries of the bloc, the policy followed by the UnitedKingdom has not been submitted to Ministers for reconsideration.6. The situation has now materially altered. In general, the larger&apos; yardsstill have full order books, but this is no longer the case in the smaller yards.Some of these yards are already in need of further orders and unless new orders are forthcoming workmen will probably be discharged;7. Fresh enquiries have recently been made by the Soviet Trade delegation and the Polish Purchasing Commission for trawlers and cargo vessels in the UnitedKingdom. They have approached both the Admiralty and the Board of Trade anda number of United Kingdom shipbuilding firms direct.   Some of these firms are44937
anxious to negotiate orders and have asked for assurances that they will be givenbuilding licences if they succeed. Enquiries have also been received for secondhandtrawlers.8. A summary of the enquiries made of United Kingdom firms with an indi-cation of values, is attached. It will be seen that the number of ships of various types required is indefinite and there is no doubt a certain amount of overlappingbetween the various enquiries. It is not possible therefore to assess the actualvolume of orders involved in the enquiries, but there seems no reason to doubt that both the Russians and Poles are serious and that, if terms satisfactory to both sidescan be agreed, substantial orders totalling several million pounds could be secured.The building of grant-aided trawlers would not be prejudiced by acceptance oforders for the number of trawlers now under consideration as there is ample buildingcapacity for this type of vessel.9. In these circumstances, and as other countries had not accepted the pro-posals for embargo which we made in 1950, the Naval Staff were requested to review the case for embargo in the light of the strategic situation as it exists to-day.This has now been done.10. Broadly the argument on which the 1950 decision was based was thattrawlers and merchant ships above the limits of size and speed specified were ofsignificant strategic importance because they were capable of being used for warlikepurposes. Trawlers could be converted for use as minesweepers, anti-submarineor patrol vessels, while merchant ships above a certain size and speed would beavailable as commerce raiders or supply ships. Under present circumstances, how-ever, the Naval Staff consider that the strategic reasons for refusing these classes ofship to the Soviet bloc are less strong for the following reasons:  (a) In our strategic thinking we are giving greater weight to the assumptionthat we must face a prolonged period of cold war, while still maintainingpreparations for, and a deterrent against, a hot war.(b) From this longer term point of view the maintenance of the United King-dom shipbuilding industry in a healthy condition is an importantstrategic consideration as well as being obviously desirable on other grounds; the denial of orders from the Soviet bloc would be a doubtfulbenefit if as a result skilled labour was dispersed and building capacitylost.(c) Under modern conditions converted ships, as compared with specially designed naval vessels, are becoming increasingly inadequate in warlikeoperations against a first-class naval power.(d) Despite the implications of paragraph 10 (c) above, large numbers of British trawlers are earmarked for naval purposes in war. It will be essentialto employ these less effective craft as our requirements cannot be metsolely by naval shipbuilding owing to the extent of the threat and the vital necessity of keeping open our ports and shipping channels. these considerations apply to a much lesser degree to Russia and the Satellitecountries who do not depend on sea communications for their survival.(e) Ships of 15 knots and over are suitable for conversion to commerce raidersor supply ships. But apart from their normal trading functions, shipsbelow this speed would only be suitable in war for the supply ofmilitary forces or as fleet auxiliaries.11. For the reasons given in paragraph 10, the Naval Staff consider thatthere is no strong strategic reason for banning the sale to the Soviet bloc ofmerchant ships below 15 knots or fishing vessels. They should, however, remain subject to quantitative control since a significantly reinforced Soviet ocean-goingmerchant fleet could be employed to our disadvantage in the Far East and else-where in support of Communist activities in the cold war. It is still the view ofthe Naval Staff that merchants ships of 15 knots or more, irrespective of size, areof sufficient strategic importance to justify continued embargo on sales to the bloc.They also consider that a particularly careful control should be maintained overthe sale of ships easily convertible to troop carriers in war and of small coasters(of under 1,000 tons) which are relatively immune from mining.   -12. We accept the views of the Naval Staff, which the Chiefs of Staff endorsefrom the strictly military viewpoint, and we consider that United Kingdom firms
should now be allowed to accept orders for ships, either new or secondhand, whichwould not be embargoed under these new criteria, subject, of course, to compliance with the rules of the Paris Group.13. These rules require the members of the Group to restrict the sales ofships which are not embargoed to the quantities necessary to secure essential supplies from the bloc; also, in the case of the more strategic ships, to consult theGroup before any sales are approved. It is intended to press for the modificationof these rules in the light of the revised strategic assessment in paragraphs 10 and 11above, but it will, of course, be necessary to comply with them until agreement totheir alteration can be obtained. We must therefore consult the Paris Group inadvance about ships mentioned in the Appendix for which firm orders are received.14. The United States will undoubtedly oppose the export of these ships (asthey have done in the case of similar sales by other countries), but it should notbe difficult to justify their export to the satifaction of all other members of the paris Group. Except for certain quantities of consumer goods admitted under thePolish and Czech Trade Agreement, and an occasional barter exchange ininessentials, all our imports from the bloc are of essential supplies. The mostimportant items are coarse grains and timber (which are also dollar-savers) and the bloc can supply a fairly wide range of valuable raw materials including the highlystrategic commodity manganese ore. Our present exports to the bloc are insufficient to pay for the desirable level of imports of these important supplies,and it is only by building up our own exports that we can hope to maintain orincrease the imports we need. Moreover, the Russians in particular are becoming increasingly selective in the goods they are prepared to take from us. Ships areone of the few items to which they attach great importance.15.   We therefore ask our colleagues to agree that(a) we should cease to apply a unilateral embargo on fishing vessels and merchant ships and should bring our policy into line with the quantita-tive control operated by other members of the Paris Group, with theexception that we should maintain our embargo on merchant ships of15 knots or over;(b) in accordance with this revised policy the orders mentioned in the appendix to this paper may be accepted (for the reasons given in paragraph 14above) provided that the export would comply with the rules of the paris Group under which we have to show a need to safeguard our essential supplies from Eastern Europe, and provided that the ships are otherwise free from features to which we ourselves should object;we should so inform the Paris Group;(c) subsequently we should recommend to the Paris Group that(i) the quantitative control over ships of 15 knots and over irrespective of size should be replaced by embargo;.(ii) the larger fishing vessels and other merchant ships should remain subject to quantitative control. This control should, however,be reinforced by the procedure of prior consultation in the paris group before orders are accepted for small coasters and shipsreadily convertible to troop carriers.P. T.J. P. L. T.31st September, 1953.
appendix summary of Current Enquiries from the Soviet bloc concerning the Building orPurchasing of ShipsApproximateValue(Each)Russia                             -  (1) John Lewis &amp; Sons, Aberdeen5-10 Stern operating slipway trawlers (240&apos; length)    ... 750,000(2) The Brooke Marine&apos;Co., Ltd. Lowestoft(i) 20 Icelandic-Type trawlers (150&apos; length, engines950 h.p.)     .................. 160,000(ii) 7 Stern operating trawlers   ...      ....      ...... 750,000(3) Hall Russell &amp; Co., Ltd., Aberdeen.(i) 1-10 Steam or motor trawlers (183&apos; 6&quot; length)    ... 195,000(ii) 1 or more motor trawlers (125&apos; length)    ...... 100,000(iii) 2 dry-cargo motor ships (8,000 tons deadweight,16 knots, 12 passengers).........      ... 820,000(iv) 2 steam Whalecatchers (147&apos; 8&quot; length)     ...... 200,000(4) Cook Welton &amp; Gemmell, HullUp to 10 motor trawlers of latest design ...      ...      ... 200,000(5) An Anglo-Russian Business Consultant has informed theAdmiralty that the Russians would like to buy severalcaifgo ships of approximately 10,000 tons deadweight(about 7,000 gross registered tons), speed 12^-14 knots,suitable for Black Sea export cargoes such as grainand ore       ...      ...      ............      ... 700,000Poland(1) Cook Welton &amp; Gemmell4 or 5 trawlers of Northella type (185&apos; length, 1,100 h.p.) 190-195,000(2) St. Andrews Steam Fishing Co., Ltd.4 secondhand trawlers built 1930-36 (150-160&apos; length)      27-46,000Note A. These enquiries are in various stages of negotiations between firms and the Soviet bloc countries.Note B. Item 3 (iii) above is still subject to embargo under the proposals in paragraph 11 of the memorandum and orders will not be accepted.

</content>
</cab>
