<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/63/0 images: 80-82</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*6SECRET Copy N(K 7 0C. (53) 271-2nd October, 1953CABINETFOOD SUBSIDIESMemorandum by the Minister of FoodIt is now clear that the recent increases in the price of butter, margarine, &amp;c,will not suffice to keep subsidies within the ceiling of  220 millions which was set.for this financial year.2. After the price increases which came into effect in September, the cost of continuing subsidies in the current financial year is estimated as follows:    millions14*3839163454837240711258* This figure would be slightly reduced if any of the price cuts recently made can be restoredduring this financial year.3. These subsidy figures leave relatively restricted scope for manoeuvre in theremainder of the Financial Year.4. I assume that we cannot this year reduce the  48 millions on welfareschemes and that we are not contemplating an alteration in the direct agriculturalsubsidies ( 37 millions) borne on the Votes of the Agricultural Departments. Ofthe remaining  173 millions, 85 per cent, represents subsidies on home-producedfood, that is, the losses incurred by the Ministry of Food in buying from thehome producer at the guaranteed price and selling to the consumer at a lowerprice. While it is not practicable to apportion the benefits of all these subsidiesbetween consumers and producers, we have reached a stage when we must look atthem more in the context of maintaining home agricultural production than inthe context of consumer food subsidies.  I would draw particular attention to44943Bacon...      .........      ............Meat.........      ...      ...      ......Milk......Butter......      ................Cheese        ...      ...      ......      ......Bread .........      .........   &apos; ...Welfare Schemes    ..................Subsidies on Votes of Agricultural DepartmentsTotal       ...      .........Add:-Miscellaneous and non-continuing subsidies, e.g., sugar,losses, on disposal of stocks of feeding-stuffs andcanned milk, offset by certain profits       ......Cost of implementing support guarantees on home-growncereals from 1953 harvest    ...      .........Grand total       ......Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1953
the item of  11 millions for supporting home-grown cereals this year. This is entirely a producer subsidy and represents a new form of expenditure in the subsidyaccount. &apos;&quot;-5.   I turn now to the individual items of commodity subsidies:  (a) Bacon  14 millionsThe subsidy on bacon is the balance between a loss of  25 millions on home-produced bacon and a profit of  11 millions on imported bacon. If the Govern-ment ceased to import bacon this profit would disappear and the loss would increase to the extent that cheaper imported bacon reduced the price which thepublic would pay for home-produced. It has recently proved necessary to reducethe prices of certain cuts of bacon in order to sell them. Some of these reductions,e.g., on gammon ham, may be only temporary, in which case there would be a saving of  2 or  3 millions in the bacon subsidy, but it is clear that further price increases are out of the question.(b) Meat- 38 millionsThe subsidy on meat is the balance between a loss of  44 millions on home-produced meat and a net profit of some  6 millions on imported meat. In orderto sell the meat a reduction in the price of mutton and a temporary reduction(now restored) in the price of pork were made in the summer, compensated by increases in beef prices. Beef prices might, perhaps, stand a little more, and anaverage increase of 2d. a lb. would save  4 millions over the remainder of the year.The effect on the Cost of Living Index would be an addition of 0-27 of a point.But the events of this summer suggest that we have reached the limit on othervarieties of meat.The profit on imported meat would disappear next year if meat imports weredecontrolled and we should have to make this loss of  6 millions good from someother source.(c) Milk (other than Welfare Milk).- 39 millions.As we shall shortly have to consider proposals for the decontrol of milk,milk products and fats, I do not wish to make any adjustments in this subsidy justnow. A seasonal price schedule for milk is being tried out this year which for aperiod (August to October inclusive) carried the price to Id. a pint. There arealready indications that if we raised the price much beyond the present average figure of 6^d. people would buy appreciably less. The experience of the next fewmonths will give us valuable data on this point. It might be possible to maintainthe present price of Id. a pint over the remainder of the financial year, with a saving of about  6 millions. But so far it can only be concluded that if we wishto maintain anything like the present volume of liquid consumption, any advance in the price of milk would be risky. We are obviously very near the point herewhere the remaining subsidy cost is a producer subsidy. In any case we havealready announced prices to March 1954 and it would be difficult to go back onthis announcement without apparent breach of faith.The items dealt with in this paragraph account for  91 millions out of the field of  173 millions.6. There remain butter ( 16 millions), cheese ( 3 millions) and bread( 45 millions). The butter price went up in September from 3s. to 3s. 4d. per lb.It would probably stand more but there would be obvious difficulties in makinga further substantial increase in price so soon after the recent increase. The currentsubsidy on butter is just over 4d. per lb. An increase in the retail price by4d. per lb. from 1st November would save  4 millions in the current FinancialYear. The trade view is that a price of 3s. 8d. per lb. is about the highest at whichbutter will sell freely in this country. Cheese and butter should be dealt withon parallel lines and an increase of 2d. a lb. on cheese (which is the present rateof subsidy) from the same date would save about  1 million. 4d. a lb. on butter and 2d. a lb. on cheese would add about 0-36 of a point to the Cost-of-living index.7. The only other subsidy on which substantial and early saving would bepossible without reaction on the home agricultural front is the bread subsidy.There is less case for. this subsidy nutrionally than for most others since demand,is pretty inelastic.  There is little hope that the price of wheat will fall low enough
Savings in of Living1953-54 IndexAmount of Increase                       m. PointsBeef: 2d. per lb. from 1st December    ...       4 0-27Milk: Maintain present price of Id. a pint       6 NilButter: Ad. per lb. from 1st November...       4 0-26Cheese: 2d. per lb. from 1st November ...       1 0-10Bread:   2-W. per If-lb. loaf from  11th,October...............      20 1-4635 2-09These subsidies would then stand at  223 millions.G. L.-G.Ministry of Food, S.W.1,1st October, 1953.of itself to clear the subsidy in the foreseeable future. Moreover, the level at winchthe subsidy has run since the removal of the flour subsidy is so high that it offersserious and constant temptation to fraud against which no really effective safeguardexists. The present subsidy on bread amounts to 2\d. per lf-lb. loaf costing l\d.The removal of this subsidy would save some  20 millions in the current financialyear. The effect on the Cost-of-Living Index would be an addition of 1-46 points.8.   SummaryIf we are to approach the ceiling of  220 millions in this Financial Year thefollowing possibilities present themselves:  ApproximateEffecton the Cost

</content>
</cab>
