<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/63/0 images: 107-114</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EGYPT:  DEFENCE negotiations note by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues a letteron the present state of our negotiations in Egypt which I have received fromGeneral Sir Brian Robertson and H.3VI. Charge d&apos;Affaires in Cairo.It will be apparent that final decisions in this matter may haveto be taken in the very near future.Foreign Office, 3.W.I.13th October, 1953.BRITISH EMBASSY,CAIRO.12th October, 1953.Dear Secretary of State,We feel that at this critical point in our negotiations you maylike to have a personal appreciation from us of the position.   We are sendingit to you by hand of Brigadier Dove, because he will be able to elucidateand amplify our ideas if that is necessary.   He has attended all the meetings and is well acquainted with our thoughts.Before we went to the meeting with the Egyptians today we hadalready come to the conclusion that the time had arrived to bring these negotiations finally to a head.   Nothing is to be gained now by furtherprotracted arguments.   Everything that can usefully be said has been saidseveral times over.   With one exception (the Final Period) the gap betweenthe two sides has been narrowed to the last leap and is quite clear.   ThePress know too much already and the whole position will soon be so exposedas to make further negotiation impossible.   The Egyptians, who have beenpatient and good tempered for over two months are now yielding to the innateweaknesses of their character.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of top SECRET Copy NoC. (53) 26114th OCTOBER, 1953.J, .BINET
Moreover they have forced the issue from their side.   Theirtactics at recent meetings, their hysterics after Margate and their disclosuresto the Press have created a situation in which confidential, quiet discussioncannot be continued.   The meeting which has now been fixed for Saturdaynext was their idea as much as ours.   They intend to make it decisive in all .respects and it is likely, even if it is not certain, that they will stick to thatintention.There seem to us to be broadly two courses open to her majesty&apos;s Government.The first is based upon the premise that Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment have indeed said their last word and are not willing to make anymore concessions.   In that case there can be no Agreement and the Egyptianswill almost certainly break off the negotiations either at the meeting on saturday or very shortly thereafter.   Adopting this alternative our object at3aturd.ay&apos;s meeting should be to ensure that the break occurs on good ground.This means that we should focus all attention on the availability clause and. thepaper on the organisation of the Base.   On the first we should stand quite pat,offering no new proposal.   On the second we should reject their amendments toour paper wholesale as destroying the character of the paper itself.   All othermatters we should dismiss as being of subsidiary importance   to the cardinal -question of an efficiently organised Base that will be available to us when we need it.The second alternative is to attempt to secure final agreement on principles at Saturday&apos;s meeting.   This means that the Delegation shouldbe given such instructions as may secure a final composition of all outstanding points.   There will be no object in taking this course unless the composition is reasonably likely to secure agreement, and it should representthe furthest point to which Her Majesty&apos;s Government wishes to go, there being no certain expectation that another opportunity for settlement will beprovided.The choice between these two alternatives is a matter of highpolicy on which we do not feel that we wish to make a recommendation.However, if Her MIajestyls Government adopt the second alternative they will presumably want to know our view as to what composition might secure agreement.   We set out in the Appendix to this letter our ideas in this regard.Perhaps we - might make one comment.   A review of the differences to be composed shows that, with the possible exception of the paragraph onavailability, they are relatively small in substance and that what we regard as necessary to resolve them does not represent a considerable retreat from the stand which Her Majesty&apos;s Government have made.As you know, our next meeting is fixed for 10. 00 a. m. on saturday, 17th October.   It would, of course, be possible to secure a postponement but we should point out that we originally suggested Monday,19th October to the Egyptians and they themselves asked for Saturday.   Inview of the pressure which we have always exerted on them for dealing with matters promptly, we think it to be very advisable to adhere to Saturdayfor the meeting if it is at all possible for you to give us our instructions intime.Yours sincerely,(Sgd)  Brian H. RobertsonRobin Hankey.The Rt. Hon. Anthony Eden, M.C., ML.P.,Foreign Office, S.1/7.1.
appendix a. Duration of the Agreement7 years.B. Period of withdrawal15 months from date on which the Agreement comes into force.Egyptians to be informed verbally that we shall start withdrawing sometroops immediately after agreement has been reached on principles,conditional upon reduction in tension, cessation of training commandos,and co-operation from Egyptian civil and military authorities.We believe that these points would be acceptable to the Chiefsof Staff.     They would make a lot of difference to the Egyptian attitude and might well tip the scale in securing their acceptance of other points on which we are not meeting them in full.Technicians - first period4,000 technicians for 4-?; years from the date on which theAgreement comes into force.D. Technicians - final periodWe have asked for guidance in our telegram No. 1407 and should include in this composition the minimum that can be accepted,E. AvailabilityIn view of the very rigid Egyptian position we are in difficulty about proposing a suitable composition.    We presume that the egyptians would accept that the Base should be made immediately available in theevent that the General Assembly of the United Nations made a specific recommendation to that effect, but we do not know whether that will be good enough for Her Majesty&apos;s Government.    The prospects of gettinganything stronger than this are small.    If the idea is acceptable to you,you may care to give us a draft.    On the consultation clause we feel thatwe could get an improvement and stipulate consultation in the event of a threat of war in wide terms.F. UniformBefore we had received your telegram No. 1722 we had evolveda very similar idea.    We propose that we should present the followingformula:-&quot;British personnel in the Base will be entitled towear the uniform of the Service to which they belong.However   in deference to Egyptian public opinion theywill normally dress as follows:  When at work, overallsor shirts (non-khaki) and shorts, with rank distinctions.At other times plain clothes.    All British personnel tobe entitled to carry a weapon for their personal protection. &quot;
This is settled by your telegram No. 1723.H. Air mattersWe can attend to this without further guidance provided thatthe proposition in our telegram No. 1427, is acceptable.    It appears to us tobe well within our brief, and was accepted as such by the representativeof the Commander-in-Chief, Middle East Air Force.I. Organisation of the BaseWe have been told that we may expect the Egyptian amendmentsa.m. Wednesday, 14th October.    We should send you an urgent telegramas soon as we get them, to obtain any instructions which you may have for us about them.
EGYPT:  DEFENCE negotiations note by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues a letteron the present state of our negotiations in Egypt which I have received fromGeneral Sir Brian Robertson and K.M. Charge d&apos;Affaires in Cairo.It will be apparent that final decisions in this matter may haveto be taken in the very near future.\Foreign Office, 3.W.I.13th October, 1953.BRITISH EMBASSY,CAIRO.12th October, 1953.Dear Secretary of State,We feel that at this critical point in our negotiations you maylike to have a personal appreciation from us of the position.   We are sendingit to you by hand of Brigadier Dove, because he will be able to elucidateand amplify our ideas if that is necessary.   He has attended all the meetings and is well acquainted with our thoughts,.Before we went to the meeting with the Egyptians today we hadalready come to the conclusion that the time had arrived to bring these negotiations finally to a head.   Nothing is to be gained now by furtherprotracted arguments.   Everything that can usefully be said has been saidseveral times over.   With one exception (the Final Period) the gap betweenthe two sides has been narrowed to the last leap and is quite clear.   ThePress know too much already and the whole position will soon be so exposedas to make further negotiation impossible.   The Egyptians, who have beenpatient and good tempered for over two months are now yielding to the innateweaknesses of their character.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of...........................TOP SECRET Copy No.....C. (53) 28114th OCTOBER, 1953.CABINET
Moreover they have forced the issue from their side. Theirtactics at recent meetings, their hysterics after Margate and their disclosuresto the Press have created a situation in which confidential, quiet discussioncannot be continued. The meeting which has now been fixed for Saturdaynext was their idea as much as ours. They intend to make it decisive in all respects and it is likely, even if it is not certain, that they will stick to thatintention.There seem to us to be broadly two courses open to her majesty&apos;s Government.The first is based upon the premise that Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment have indeed said their last word and are not willing to make anymore concessions.   In that case there can be no Agreement and the Egyptianswill almost certainly break off the negotiations either at the meeting on saturday or very shortly thereafter.   Adopting this alternative our object at3aturday&apos;s meeting should be to ensure that the break occurs on good ground.This means that we should focus all attention on the availability clause and thepaper on the organisation of the Base.   On the first we should stand quite pat,offering no new proposal.   On the second we should reject their amendments toour paper wholesale as destroying the character of the paper itself.   All othermatters we should dismiss as being of subsidiary importance   to the cardinalquestion of an efficiently organised Base that will be available to us when we need it.The second alternative is to attempt to secure final agreement on principles at Saturday&apos;s meeting.   This means that the Delegation shouldbe given such instructions as may secure a final composition of all outstanding points.   There will be no object in taking this course unless the composition is reasonably likely to secure agreement, and it should representthe furthest point to which Her Majesty&apos;s Government wishes to go, there being no certain expectation that another opportunity for settlement will beprovided.The choice between these two alternatives is a matter of highpolicy on which we do not feel that we wish to make a recommendation.However, if Her Majesty&apos;s Government adopt the second alternative they will presumably want to know our view as to what composition might secure agreement.   We set out in the Appendix to this letter our ideas in this regard.Perhaps we &apos; might make one comment.   A review of the differences to be composed shows that, with the possible exception of the paragraph onavailability, they are relatively small in substance and that what we regard as necessary to resolve them does not represent a considerable retreat from the stand which Her Majesty&apos;s Government have made.As you know, our next meeting is fixed for 10. 00 a. m. on saturday, 17th October.   It would, of course, be possible to secure a postponement but we should point out that we originally suggested Monday,19th October to the Egyptians and they themselves asked for Saturday.   Inview of the pressure which we have always exerted on thern for dealing with matters promptly, we think it to be very advisable to adhere to Saturdayfor the meeting if it is at all possible for you to give us our instructions intime.Yours sincerely,(Sgd)  Brian H. RobertsonRobin Hankey.The Rt. Hon. Anthony Eden, M.C., M.P.,Foreign Office, S.W.1.
A. Duration of the Agreement7 years.B. Period of withdrawal15 months from date on which the Agreement coro.es into force.Egyptians to be informed verbally that we shall start withdrawing sometroops immediately after agreement has been reached on principles,conditional upon reduction in tension, cessation of training commandos,and co-operation from Egyptian civil and military authorities.We believe that these points would, be acceptable to the Chiefsof Staff.    They would make a lot of difference to the Egyptian attitude and might well tip the scale in securing their acceptance of other points on which we are not meeting them, in full.C. Technicians - first period4,000 technicians for 4-: years from the date on which theAgreement comes into force.D. Technicians - final perioclWe have asked for guidance in our telegram No. 1407 and should include in this composition the minimum that can be accepted.E. AvailabilityIn view of the very rigid Egyptian position we are in difficulty about proposing a suitable composition.    We presume that the egyptians would accept that the Base should, be made immediately available in theevent that the General Assembly of the United Nations made a specific recommendation to that effect, but we do not know whether that will be good enough for Her Majesty&apos;s Government.    The prospects of gettinganything stronger than this are small.    If the idea is acceptable to you,you may care to give us a draft.    On the consultation clause we feel thatwe could get an improvement and stipulate consultation in the event of a threat of war in wide terms.F. UniformBefore we had received your telegram No. 1722 we had evolveda very similar idea.    We propose that we should present the followingformula&quot;British personnel in the Base will be entitled towear the uniform of the Service to which they belong.I-Iowever  in deference to Egyptian public opinion theywill normally dress as follows:  When at work, overallsor shirts (non-khaki) and shorts, with rank distinctions.At other times plain clothes.    All British personnel tobe entitled, to carry a weapon for their personal protection. &quot;
110This is settled by your telegram No, 1723,H. Air matters&quot;We can attend to this without further guidance provided thatthe proposition in our telegram No. 1427 is acceptable.    It appears t.i usbe well within our brief, and was accepted as such by the representativeof the Commander-in-Chief, Middle illast Air Force.I. Organisation of the BaseWe have been told that we may expect the Egyptian amendmentsa,m, Wednesday, 14th October.    We should send you an urgent telegramas soon as we get them, to obtain any instructions which you may have for us about them.

</content>
</cab>
