<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/63/0 images: 130-130</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ia4SECRETC. (53) 28817th OCTOBER, 1953.COPY NO.CABINETDECONTROL OF FOODMemorandum by the Minister of food the Economic Policy Committee on 12th October decided inprinciple to decontrol processed milk, butter, margarine, cheese and cookingfats (E.A.(53) 24th Meeting, Item 2).2. At a meeting between Ministers and representatives of the national farmers&apos; Unions (N.F.Us.) in the afternoon of the same day, with theChancellor of the Exchequer in the Chair, the decision of the Economic PolicyCommittee was told to the N.F.Us. because it was related to the possibilityof restoring some of the powers of the Milk Marketing Boards,   The farmers were asked for their views on this restoration of powers and it was agreed that,in the meantime, no public statement should be made.3. The N.F.Us. must necessarily discuss this matter in a fairly widecircle and I am very much afraid that it will be impossible to maintain secrecyabout the general decontrol proposal for more than a few days.   It would obviously be most embarrassing to our relations with the trades concerned andmost damaging to the Governments reputation for handling affairs, if the firstnews of this important action vitally affecting these trades reached them as aresult of a leakage through farmers1 organisations.4. I therefore propose, subject to the concurrence of my colleagues, to announce our decision in principle to decontrol these foods next year.   Theannouncement need have no reference to the Milk Marketing Boards.   In this announcement it will not he necessary for me to indicate precise dates,   I shallsimply say that processed milk will be decontrolled in the early spring and the butter, margarine and cheese group (which must be dealt with as a whole) inthe early summer.   I have promised to give the margarine manufacturers atleast six months&apos; notice of decontrol, and on some of the other foods I havecommitments to Commonwealth producers, who also expect to receive advancenotice of any change.   On general grounds, therefore, it is important that anannouncement of our intentions should be made as quickly as possible.5. I ought to add that the Chancellor of the Exchequer did hint to the farmers at the meeting that the decision to decontrol might have to be reviewed in the light of their redactions to anything short of complete decontrol of milk.While it is true that the decision to decontrol this group of commodities was thought likely to be useful in the subsequent discussions with the farmers, it neverthelesswas taken on the basis of the general public policy considerations set out in my paper to the Economic Policy Committee (E,A.(53) 121).   I am sure that ifthere were any leakage to the trades concerned we could not avow as a reasonfor an apparent withdrawal of a firm decision the attitude of the farmers.G. LL-G.Ministry of Food, S.W.1.16th October, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
