<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/63/0 images: 135-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1953SECRET Copy No. 66C. (53) 290 (Revise)26th October, 1953CABINETTELEVISION-RELIGION AND POLITICSMemorandum by the Postmaster GeneralIf my colleagues agree that competitive stations should be allowed to broadcast on religious and political subjects, an additional paragraph on the following lines would need to be inserted in the new White Paper:  &quot; Since broadcasting would be under the control of a public corporation,the ban on politics and religion mentioned in the Government^ previous white Paper would no longer be necessary. Broadcasting on these topicswould be permitted as part of the programmes (but not as advertisements)under similar arrangements to those followed by the B.B.C. these arrangements are:  (a) for religion; a Central Religious Advisory Committee, with regional commitees;(b) for politics; an agreement (revised from time to time) between theParties and the B.B.C. on party political matters, and impartialityin the treatment of all controversial issues;(c) the Corporation is not allowed to broadcast its own views.&quot;2. Last years White Paper (Cmd. 8550) said that &quot; the new stations wouldnot be permitted to engage in political or religious broadcasting.&quot; This was in the context of stations under completely private ownership and some programmes atany rate sponsored directly by advertisers. We have now ruled out sponsoringaltogether, and are insisting upon the advertiser having at most a minor influence on programmes; we also have an effective controlling body, owning the stations aswell as supervising programmes.3. Nobody has any serious complaint against the way in which the B.B.C.handles these matters; but that is not really the point. If we are to break theB.B.C&apos;s monopoly, we should take particular care to break it as regards contro-versial subjects because it is in the realm of ideas that monopoly is potentiallythe biggest danger.4. The practical objection to a ban is the difficulty of defining what is political or religious for this purpose. There would inevitably be embarrassing border linecases; jokes about members of the Government, complaints about high prices,lectures by people like Vernon Bartlett on, say, the Middle East, might all providedoubtful cases on the political side. As for religion, are we to forbid broadcastsof the Messiah or programmes of hymn or carol singing?5. I think we might be able to make some fairly satisfactory definition of religion but politics would present very considerable difficulty. My conclusion is that, with the kind of arrangements we now have in mind and the safeguardswe can secure through the corporation, we can safely allow these subjects fromthe start.D.Post Office Headquarters, E.C. 1,26th October, 1953.45027

</content>
</cab>
