<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/140/0 images: 337-342</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1922.SECRET.CP. 4339.CABINET.SITUATION IN IRAQ. Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.I CIRCULATE a note on the situation in Iraq by the Air Staff and corre-spondence with Sir John Salmond, the Air Officer Commanding. I would ask the Cabinet for an early decision upon the point that is raised in these papers.S. F .Air Ministry, December 5, 1922.Note by the Air Staff on Sir John Salmond&apos;s Proposal for a Forward Policy in the event of Turkish Invasion of Iraq or a Resumption of Hostilities with Turkey.1. IN the event of a resumption of hostilities with Turkey, we must be prepared to face the possibility of a Turkish invasion of Iraq. To meet such a situation, Sir John Salmond&apos;s proposals are, briefly, that, of the nine Imperial battalions at present in Iraq, four should be concentrated in a battle position north of Mosul, the remainder to be placed, two north of Baghdad, two at Baghdad and one at Shaibah. At present there is only one battalion at Mosul, and all positions north of Mosul are held by native forces.2. The reasons for the adoption of the forward policy are as follows :  (a.) The country north of Mosul, on left bank of the Tigris, and on lines of probable enemy advance, lends itself to effective defence.(&amp;.) The holding of these forward positions, in the strength proposed, will make it possible to maintain the action, which may well be decisive, of strong air forces based on Mosul and Kirkouk for a prolonged period, since retirement of the ground forces covering the air bases will not be necessitated at an early stage.The number of squadrons would, it is proposed, be raised from one to five.On the other hand, if our policy were to evacuate Mosul, air action would have to cease altogether during the period when the main Turkish forces would be vulnerable, i.e., while they are still in difficult country, and would not restart until the enemy came within striking distance of a more southerly air base. For the purpose of any air action on a considerable scale, the first practicable base is Baghdad, from which point Mosul itself is only just within striking distance of the majority of our aircraft.(c.) From these positions the ground forces would be able to protect air bases,, and thus enable the air squadrons to hammer the enemy&apos;s main forces and his bases, such as Jazireh and Mardin.(d.) With a strong air contingent we shall have early intelligence of all enemy movements, and thus avert any probability of land forces being cut off owing to the action of Turkish forces.(e.) Lastly, and above all, it must be remembered that in dealing with an Oriental people the appearance of facing the enemy is a factor of paramount value. For this reason the northward move of our forces will have a stabilising effect not only upon the tribes of the Mosul Vilayet, but on the moral of the whole country. On the other hand, a withdrawal from Mosul would in itself be interpreted as a sign of defeat. It would render hostile not only all the tribes who are now &quot;sitting on the fence &apos;&apos; to see what will happen, but also many of those who are at present well disposed.3. The Air Staff are in entire agreement both with the conclusions of the Air Officer Commanding and the premises on which they rest. It appears to them that, for the present, two possible military situations require consideration : (a.) On the assumption that the Turks made the European front their main objective, a weak attack on Mosul might be launched on a scale which the resources [9181] &quot; jj
-of the existing garrison of Iraq should be able to defeat, if the forward policy was adopted. This policy, as shown above, will enable us to strike at the enemy&apos;s own bases; and it will avoid an initial withdrawal from Mosul and abandonment of Kurdistan, which would undoubtedly convert even an intrinsically weak enemy attack into a formidable movement.The Air Staff have already indicated (CP. 4309) that, in their view, with-drawal from Mosul, consequent on a breach with Turkey and followed by the Turkish occupation of the district, with all that it would imply, militarily and politically, would render reinforcements for Baghdad and the lines of communication south of Baghdad essential to guard against internal risings.In view of the possibility of a weak attack developing into a strong attack, referred to in (b) below, some reinforcements shoidd be designated to arrive in the country at the earliest possible moment.(&amp;.) A Turkish attack may be made on a scale which the existing garrison could not hope to meet without reinforcements. The Air Staff are of opinion that in this case reinforcements will be necessary (1) whether we stand at Mosul or (2) at Baghdad or (3) to enable us to withdraw to Basra : also that those reinforcements should reach Iraq before the invasion develops. The strength required in the above cases is being-discussed with the Air Officer Commanding.*A forward policy again offers the greater prospect of success, in that the danger of internal rising being added to external invasion will be greatly reduced by its adoption. It should be added that, from the Turkish point of view, an invasion in force would be a serious undertaking, of which we could rely on receiving ample warning and which could not, it is believed, eventuate before the spring.4. To sum up : (a.) The Air Staff,are of opinion that, in the event of attack by the Turks, rein-forcements will be necessary whether we adopt a forward policy or whether we decide to evacuate.(b.) The Air Staff recommend that, in the event of the Lausanne Conference resulting in a definite rupture with the Turks, and of any consequent threat of invasion in the north of Iraq, the Air Officer Commanding should be authorised to adopt the forward policy. Since, in the contingency of the vigorous action of the air forces failing to stop an invasion in force, it is assumed that it is not the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government to provide reinforcements adequate to fight to a finish for the integrity of the present boundaries of Iraq, the Air Officer Commanding should be instructed to limit the ground forces in the forward area to such as are required to cover the air operations.(c.) As immediate measures, (i) the Air Officer Commanding should be notified in this sense, and instructed to make his disposition accordingly, but not to move troops for the purpose without further authority from His Majesty&apos;s Government.(ii.) The High Commissioner and Air Officer Commanding should receive sanction for any reasonable proposals they may put forward for the improvement of the general internal situation by enlisting the aid of the tribes as a counter-move to prevent Turkish propaganda and infiltration, and should be empowered to make the necessary preliminary arrangements, subject to political considerations, to explore the measure of assistance which might be obtained from the tribes to meet a Turkish invasion.5. The Air Staff confine themselves to the hypothesis of a definite breakdown of the Lausanne Conference, as it is to meet that contingency that a clear indication of policy is needed for the guidance of the Air Officer Commanding. If, on the other hand, the Lausanne Conference ends either in an agreement with Turkey or comes to no conclusions either way, the position should be again reviewed.This paper has been drawn up in general agreement with the General Staff at the War Office. A supplementary note on the subject of reinforcements will be submitted if required by the Cabinet.Air Staff, December 4, 1922.* The scale of the garrison of Iraq lias never comprised provision for guarding the country against serious external invasion ; and we could not contemplate a retirement of our existing garrison lighting rearguard actions from Mosul to Basra in face of a Turkish attack in strength. General Townsend fought .a successful battle at Ctesiphon with 14,000 troops against 13,000 regulars, but having to retire was beleaguered within 8 days in Rut, some 100 miles south.
Annexure A.Appreciation by Sir John Salmond of the Military Situation with Special Reference to Turkish Invasion of Iraq.   October 1, 1922.TOO late in the year for serious attack by Turks from Rowanduz direction. Roads south of Van too difficult.2. Probability of increased propaganda and incitement of Kurdish tribes to act against us on our eastern flank, combined with a Turkish attack from the-north-west, especially from Jezire-ibn-Omar direction.3. Presumably Turks would consider the Dardanelles their main front, and if they desire to hit us in this direction, they might reasonably consider a detachment of two divisions and one cavalry brigade sufficient to retake Mosul.All Kurdish tribes would probably side with the Turks so long as they thought, that the Turks would win.The only friendlies we could count upon north of Mosul would be the Assyrians, and only those settled near Dohuk (about 2,000 men partly armed) would be in a-position to assist us.4. Although&quot; the defence of. Mosul, with the long line of communications to Basra, cannot be said to be a sound military proposition under present conditions, still, in my opinion, it would be fully justified for the following reasons : (a.) Prestige and obligations to the Iraq Government.(b.) Possibility of inflicting defeat on the above-mentioned Turkish invading forces, by even such a small force as five battalions and two batteries if combined with the whole weight of the Royal Air Force. If successful, our prestige would be enormously increased, and the frontier of Iraq secured.(c.) The ground north of Mosul, on the left bank of the Tigris, lends itself to-skilful manoeuvre of our ground forces. Also any hostile force advancing on Mosul from Jezire-ibn-Omar or Nisibin directions would be exceptionally vulnerable from the air.5. In my opinion, the danger of the Kurdish forces backed by Turks advancing west of the Aqra-Erbil-Kirkuk-Kifri line, against our line of communications on the right bank of the Tigris, is a danger which could be countered by the levies and Royal Air Force.6. Probable Dispositions.Outposts Zone. Assyrian levies (2 battalions, 1 pack battery, 2 squadrons at Zakho and Aqra, with supports near Dohuk nd Mindan) holding their present positions.   Road over Zakho pass to be prepared for demolition.Battle Position. Already selected near Butak Su, about half-way between Mosul and Zakho.Striking Force One brigade group consisting of  1 Indian Pack (Howitzer) Battery1 Indian Infantry Battalion I ,1 Armoured Car Company (less 1 section) f*rom Mosul. 2 sections Combined Field Ambulance      J1 Indian Battalion from Baghdad-Mosul Line of Communication leaving. 1 Pioneer Battalion on Line of Communication to be held in reserve.Brigade headquarters 1 brigade Signal Section 1 Field (Howitzer) Battery 1 company Sappers and Miners 2 British battalions  Armoured Car Company (less 2 sections) 1 Combined Field Ambulance (less 2 sections) 1 Mobile Veterinary SectionAdd1 Indian Infantry Battalion \ From Kirkuk-Kingerban if circurn-1 section Armoured Car Company J stances permit.[9181] b 2From Baghdad.
Line of Communication 1 Indian Battalion \ N rfh  f Baghdad.1 section Armoured Car Company J n*2 Indian battalions at Baghdad. I Indian Battalion 1 Basrah,Shaibah.1 section Armoured Car Company J7. If considered necessary politically, two companies 1st Battalion Levies from Naseriyah could be sent as garrisons to Kut and Amarah. In my opinion there is no military necessity to garrison these places with regular troops. The safeguarding of the Tigris line of communication will depend on the four defence vessels and armoured barges.8. Transport. There is sufficient regular transport in the country to complete all regular units with 1st and 2nd line transport, with the exception of a few pack mules which could be easily hired.9. Forces not included in above Royal Air Forces 3 squadrons D.H. 9 A Mosul. 1 Snipe squadron \ Ki k k 1 Bristol squadron J2 Vickers Yernon squadrons Baghdad. 1 squadron D.H. 9 As Shaibah.(a.) Levies 1 cavalry regiment (less 1 squadron) Arbil. 1 cavalry regiment Kirkuk-Alton Keupri. 1 squadron Khanikin.1 battalion (without British officers) Sulaimaniyah. 1 battalion Naseriyah.(b.) Iraq Army 1 cavalry regiment Tel Afar.1 cavalry regiment ^1 pack battery I Mosul1 infantry battalion f1 transport company (A.T. carts) JI suggest that the Iraq infantry battalion might be employed to guard the bridge and aerodrome at Mosul, and that the Iraq cavalry and guns might operate on the right bank of Tigris in co-operation with the British Indian force.1 cavalry regiment   1 1 pack battery f Baghdad.1 infantry battalion JI suggest that these remain in reserve 1 infantry battalion (less 2 companies)-Hillah.I S^lS BalTage IE-s VaHey.Annexure B.(Most Secret.)Sir, November 1, 1922.I AM commanded by the Air Council to say that they have had under considera-tion your appreciation (Annexure A) of the situation and proposed disposition of J forces in the event of a Turkish offensive against Iraq which were forwarded witlil your communication of&apos;the 12th October (Air/606/ ). In reply I am to inform! you that the determined attitude which you would propose to adopt and the offensivel role assigned to the Air units is in full accord with the principles held by the Aiif* This would entail the move of 1 Indian battalion (less 2 companies already at Baghdad) from Kut andl 1 Indian battalion from Amarah (including- 2 companies temporarily detached at Basrah).
Annex ure C.Cipher telegram from A..O.C, Iraq, to Air Ministry. (Despatched November 21,1922, 20-50; Received November 22, 1922, 9-30. (Secret.) &apos; AM 1134.(Paraphrase.) Three Parts.Part I.X5053 of 21st November. Reference your letter of 1st November, S18081/S6 (Annexure B), in which it is suggested that under certain conditions His Majesty&apos;s Government views with apprehension the offensive policy to be adopted in the event of Turkish aggression, and that it may have to be modified considerably to defensive policy nearer to Baghdad.I have to offer the following observations :  If, at an advance by [ % Turkish] forces Mosul area is abandoned, the con-sequences on Iraq may prove disastrous, as in all probability the whole country will rise against us. The effect of air action alone from Mosul, against an. advance of a Turkish army of two or three divisions would be to delay it, but not to prevent it. The inhabitants would interpret the sight of troops retiring from Mosul as a defeat and the news, magnified a hundred times would travel immediately from Mosul to Baghdad. Air action would cease for a while against the advancing enemy as the last troops left Mosul, until they again came within striking distance of an air base further south. Baghdad is the next base from Mosul from which consider-able [one group indecipherable] air action could be carried out. Every hostile element would have meanwhile raised its banner, and at the news of the British defeat, the sight of our supply dumps burning at Mosul, and the retirement of the existing garrison from there, all those who are now sitting on the fence would flock to them. The march of this small force to Baghdad would become under these circumstances, which are not overstated, an operation of extreme difficulty.Part II.Further, the line Erbil-Kirkuk-Khanikin would become exposed by a retire-ment from Mosul, and, as this line is held with a minimum of levy troops, its abandonment would follow as a necessary corollary. Kurdistan would therefore be left to Turkey, while the repercussion of this on the tribes between this line and the Tigris would be anarchic. Baghdad itself would follow suit, and although!, undoubtedly, a closer defence of strongly defended points would have an effect on the people of the city, as the enemy&apos;s advance sweeps nearer only a small proportion of the troops could be spared for the city itself, a situation of which full advantage would be taken.Communication would cease almost entirely from Baghdad to Basra and vice versa, as the railway track would undoubtedly be torn up and the only line remaining would be in the river.Staff. It is agreed in particular that Turkish forces advancing from Jezire-ibn-Omar or Nisibin should be exceptionally vulnerable to attacks from the air.The Air Council have, however, to consider the possibility that in certain circumstances (as for example in case of attack by still larger forces than those envisaged by you) His Majesty&apos;s Government would view with apprehension a plan which placed a large proportion of the garrison in a very advanced position, and that they might require your operations to be limited to a closer radius of strongly defended points.I am, therefore, to request that you will submit an alternative scheme or schemes to meet that contingency.I am, &amp;c. (Signed) J. A. WEBSTER.The Air Officer Commanding, Air Headquarters, British Forces in Iraq, Baghdad.
The advantages of a forward policy, as defined, are as follows :  Paragraph 1. That the country north of Mosul on left bank of the Tigris and on line of probable enemy advance lends itself to a protracted defence, and also to counter-offensive against an enemy force equal to, or slighly superior to, the one it is proposed to maintain, there.Paragraph 2. The terrain is eminently suited to rearguard actions in the event of an advance of great superiority of enemy numbers, Mosul itself being one of the bounds in such a rearguard action, which, if necessary, would be continued to Baghdad and Basra. Unless it is the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to despatch reinforcements it is not proposed that the force should remain at Baghdad to become invested.Part III.Paragraph 3. Owing to the early intelligence provided by the Air Force the probability of our forces being cut off is infinitesimal.Paragraph 4. Behind a retiring force of these dimensions a much larger con-centration of air forces can be made than behind a force of the size of the existing garrison of Mosul carrying out a similar operation.[ ? Paragraph 5.] The initial move of our troops north will enhance our prestige among the tribes and raise their moral.Paragraph 6. In that there is every possibility of the enemy&apos;s advanced echelon [ ? word omitted] such severe hammering that he might never recover while the air forces co-operating deal with the remainder of his body reaching back to Jazireh-ibn-Omar, and with that base itself, it contains the gerros of success.I would ask that, before submitting an alternative scheme as required in your letter under discussion, the above appreciation be carefully considered as I see no vast success in anjr other alternative with number of forces under my command at the present time.It is most essential for me to know, if I am to consider further the close defence indicated, the prospects of reinforcements, if any, which His Majesty&apos;s Government have in mind, their approximate numbers and the date after outbreak of war on which the first echelon bargained for is expected to reach Basra. This summary of the situation is concurred in by His Excellency the High Commissioner.o

</content>
</cab>
