<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/140/0 images: 408-408</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1922.SECRET. C.P.-4347.CABINET.ADEN.I circulate, for the consideration of my colleagues, the following memorandum, prepared in the Middle East Department, about the control of Aden. In the interests of smooth administration an early decision is desired.DEVONSHIRE.Colonial Office, December 1922.THE establishment of a Middle East Department within the Colonial Office, whose sphere was to comprise in principle Mesopotamia, Aden and Palestine, was decided upon by the late Cabinet on the Hist I lecember, 1920. A Committee appointed by the Cabinet, under the&apos; Chairmanship of Sir James Masterton Smith, presented a report on the 31st January, 1921. which resulted in the formation of the Department, and the Cabinet then approved the transfer of Aden to the Colonial Office subject to the concurrence of the Government of India in that report. The Viceroy telegraphed on the 21st March, 1921, that the Government of India were likely to accept the report in principle &quot; subject to satisfactory financial adjustments,&quot; but that &quot; any proposal to saddle India with financial liabilities for Aden on its transfer to the Colonial Office must be strenuously resisted.&quot;The Secretary of State for the Colonies immediately informed the Secretary of State for India that there could of course be no question of the Colonial Office accepting the transfer of Aden unless a substantial contribution were made by India for the maintenance of Indian interests and responsibilities in Arabia. Since then there have been repeated discussions, both ministerial and departmental, as to the figure of the Indian contribution, but no agreement has been reached. Aden remains administratively under the control of the India Office, but the Colonial Office (Middle East Department) is politically responsible. Everyone agrees that the arrangement is most detrimental to the interests of Aden and that the division of responsibility is against the public interest. At a meeting of the Middle East Committee on the 21st October last, at which the Colonial Office, India Office, War Office, Air Ministry and Treasury were represented, it was decided To record that the Committee considered it desirable that the coutrol of Aden should be transferred from the Government of India to the Imperial Government, subject to a suitable allocation of cost between the Imperial and Indian Exchequers ;And that, having regard to the local inconveniences arising from divided control, the matter should be brought to the notice of the new Secretary of State for the Colonies, with a view to being considered by the Cabinet, with the least possible delay.The matter is accordingly submitted to the Secretary of Stale with the recom-mendation that the Cabinet should be invited to set up a Committee forthwith, with a Minister as cnairman, to frame a recommendation to the Cabinet for the contribution to be paid by the Government of India in respect of Arabian interests and responsibilities on the transfer of Aden to the Colonial Office.Colonial Office, November 1022.[9186]

</content>
</cab>
