<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/140/0 images: 519-520</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ilHETj. As my colleagues.es axe aware, as a result of representations?1,        which, were made with regard to the working of the Trade Boards Acts, ay predecessor appointed a Committee under the 0hairman-ship of the lord Chancellor to enquire into this question. That Committee, which was composed of. leading representatives of employers and labour, as well as of impartial persons,, presented a unanimous report.,     That report, while approving in general of the Trade Board system, recommended certain important alterations in the existing Actse     She 3.ate Govern-ment accepted the report as a whole and a Bill was prepared following the lines of its recommendations,,     It v;as, however, found impossible to iutrodu.ee the Bill0For a number of reasons the question is still a living one and I think the Government will have to decide whether they intend to introduce a Bill, and if so, what the nature of the&apos; Bill should be.      Before such a decision can be reached,however a number of difficult points raised by the Cave Committee will have to be settled,  such as -(a) whether a limitation upon the rate-fixing powers of the Boards such as is recommended by the Cave Committee should be imposed;(b) whether greater regard should be had to local needs and conditions by the compulsory institution of District Boards and Committees, and(o) whether the conditions governing the application of the Aots should be n&amp;d.o more explicit and whether, before application in. every case, a compulsory public inquiry should be held*/These
3 Q ;These questions have a long and difficult history and their solution involves the survey of a wide field.     I suggest, therefore, that the matter should he referred to a small Committee of the cabinet.     I would further suggest that the Lord Chancellor should he invited to aot as Chairman of that Committee.(Intd.) M.B.   -Ministry of Lahour. -December 2lst. 1922.

</content>
</cab>
