<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/5/11 images: 166-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS JjtpnjRm^J^S.THB PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.COPY NO.W. ?.  (R. )(40)61.WAR cabinet coal POSITION.Supplement to the Tenth Fortnightly Report submitted by the ;ecretary for Mines (Previous Paper: Paper No. W.  P.  (R. )(40) 46.)(Initialled) G. L.Richmond Terrace,5 W. 1.J4th February, 1940.

COAL POSITION.^-j^^jjmntjtp,the Tenth Fortnightly Report.,I submitted supplements to the 9th Fortnightly Report onthe 24th and 50th January and again referred to the existingdifficulties in the 10th Report of the 3rd February.      As thesituation has again deteriorated it is desirable that I should report specially on the position.Since the weather broke sufficiently to allow normal trainmovement to resume the exceptional policy of despatching specialtrains direct from collieries to consuming areas has &quot;been abandonedas the movement of such trains, while meeting urgent needs inparticular areas, would interfere in normal weather with theordinary flow of coal traffic, and on balance would reduce the total quantity of coal moving by rail.Last week-end the Railways succeeded in moving sufficientloaded wagons from the collieries to give hope that arrivals of coalat the terminals in consuming areas would be sufficient to meet theday to day demand;    and a meeting under the Chairmanship of thePresident of the Board of Trade was held on Monday, 12th February,to consider what steps could be taken by sea and rail to enablestocks to be built up to safer levels during the period to the endof March and during the period March to October.Unfortunately the hopes referred to above in regard to day today movement have not been fulfilled.      Coal is not reaching theterminals in sufficient quantities to allow sales, even of 2 cwt.per week per household, to all those requiring coal, and complaintsthat households are completely out of coal and cannot securereplenishments are now coming in from all over the country.      Inaddition, a number of industries are now complaining that their coalstocks are approaching exhaustion.Very large quantities of coal are on the rails and the movementof coal from the collieries is now normal.      In view of theixhaustion of stocks in the consuming areas, something considerably

2 -more than the normal quantities are required to meet the presenturgent day to day demands.      But if the coal which is at present on the rail and leaving the colliery premises can he got throughrapidly to the terminals, the immediate situation will he saved.I know of no other method of saving it, and I have, therefore,today addressed a letter to the Minister of Transport asking thatabsolute priority for a few days shall at once he given to coaltrains.In view of the exceptional position of   Glasgow, I am tonightsending a special officer to that area to assist the DivisionalCoal Officer and to endeavour, in co-operation with him and withthe Coal Supplies Officer, to secure that adequate supplies of house coal reach that town.


</content>
</cab>
