<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/2/11 images: 144-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT    &apos;TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. ^It is requested that special care may be taken, toensure the secrecy of this document.0\SECRET. COPY NO.       ^ ^&quot;W.P.  (39) 61.WAR   CABINET.SCALE OF RESERVES IN THE MIDDLE EAST.Note by the Secretary.By direction of the Prime Minister, I circulate herewith for consideration by the War Cabinet, the attached report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee dealing with the   -Scale of Reserves in the Middle East.     (Paper No. CO.S.(39) 60).(Signed)    E.E. BRIDGES.Secretary.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.Slid October, 1939.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT,M.....II&quot;&quot;&quot;   IIH-&apos; I &apos;TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND  KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.C R E T.jT (39) SO. COPY NO.      /efrWAR CABINET.CHIEFS OF STAFF CO.. 1 &quot;ITTEE.SCALE OF RESERVES IN dllE MIDDLE EAST.(Preyipus Paper NOo GS0,S?(39) 59).Memorandum.We have thought it right to bring to the notice ofthe   War Cabinet       the present state of reserves in theMiddle East, and to recommend a policy to be followed in building them up.2. The Committee of Imperial Defence, at their meetingon 22nd May, 1939, approved the recommendation containedin paragraph 306 of the European Appreciation, 1939-40(C.I.D.Paper No. D.P.  (p) 44) that -&quot;reserves adequate to cover all requirements for90 days of war should be maintained in theMiddle East for the approved garrison andinitial reinforcements.&quot;Reserves for the Army.,3. At the outbreak of war, approximate^ three monthsreserves of all items had already been placed in theMiddle East,  for the normal garrison, and for thereinforcenients of 1 Brigade and attached Troops planned tobe sent from India.     Further reinforcements are now en route from India to Egypt.     They are bringing with them five months reserve of food only.     Reserves of other items cannotbe made available for this force at present, and as a result the pool of reserves in the Middle East will drop belowthe figure of three months.      If additional reinforcementsare sent to the Middle East, this scale of reserves will tend to drop still further.Royal Air Force Reserves.4. Generally speaking, reserves for the Royal Air force at present in the Middle East are equivalent to from two to three months supply.      In the cases of aircraft, reservesamount to 140 per cent,  of initial equipment, which will beincreased to 200 per cent, when aircraft become available.

t e)Three months reserve of fuel is held, and will shortly be increased by five weeks supply in contractors&apos; bulkstorage. Explosives held also amount to three monthssupply.Policy Recommended.5. The present position is not entirely satisfactory^and, owing to the fact that all efforts are nowdirected to supplying   the requirements of theforces at hone and in France, it will not be easy torectify matters in the near future.      It is recommended,therefore, that the policy should be to build up reservesgradually to the full three months scale, as and whenshipping becomes available, and prior demands are met.India should be drawn&apos; upon to provide reserves ofthe limited range of stores which she can *pro5.uod.(Signed)   DUDLEY POUND.&quot; R.F. ADAMa (D.C.X*&amp;lS.)(For C.I.G.S.)&quot; R.S.C. PEIRSE. (D.C.A.S.)(For C .A.S .)richmond Terrace, S.W.1,1st October, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
