<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/7/13 images: 178-187</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.WAR CABINET.g.F.(R)(40) 195.Copy No.24th September,,1940.Analysis of Shipping Employment - 51st August, 1940.Memorandum by the Minister of Shipping*(Previous Paper W.P. (R)(40)l80).This return is circulated in continuation of the Analysis ofShipping Employment 51st July, 1940, previously circulated.R.H.C.MINISTRY OP SHIPPING.24th September, 1940B

employment OF BRITISH VESSELS OF 500   GROSS TONS AND OVERON 51ST AUGUST, 1940.(Tonnage figures in thousands)PART I - SUMMARY.500-1,599 G.T.Vessels other than Tankers.A* Fighting services (excluding vessels under,repair)...........................B. Importing services of the United Kingdom . .CV Coasting trade of the United Kingdom &amp; Eire ). Trading between countries other than theUnited Kingdom and Eire9*...............(i) Liners and other vessels on berth ..(ia) Vessels other than Liners...........(ii) Vessels engaged In local tradingabroad ..,.E. Repairing, Damaged or Not in use o . o.----1----&apos;No.!   G.T.158854661521074322606325562D.W.18515955427978j1,600 G.T. &amp; over no.. i G.T.D.W.367J 2,7381,571., 8,00210710384622632,52511,502314669361,6849392,094233i 1,372; 1.755Tankers. K1,032 jl,008 j 1,265 jj 2,651 j 14,784i ii     6764Totalso p i o t ( t.1,099 1,072II I74       452! 3,164TO   1QS4,5501,329 i 3,103\17,9281 23,733For analysis of the figures under the abovegroups, see subsequent pages.These figures include vessels detained by the French Authorities (see Section Dof the Monthly Shipping Report - page 5.)
PART II - ANALYSIS OP A.B. &amp; 0.A.B.Fighting Services.fa) Naval Service ,(b; Milllilitary ServiceTotcl of A,liaporting Services of the United Kingdom,(i) Liners and other vessels on berthbetween the United Kingdom and Eireand:-Faroe Islands, Iceland and GreenlandSpain and PortugalEast Mediterranean (via Cape) and TraderService (lied,) including vessels talcingcargo out but not allocated homewardIndia, Persian Gulf and BurmaPar East ,Australia and New ZealandS, Si E. AfricaV/, /if ricaIT, America and AtlanticIndies, Gulf and N, BrazilAmerica AtlanticAmerica Pacific ,S.a,N. America PacificTotal of B(i)(ii) Vessels other than. Liners loaded orAllocated te load:-Faroe Islands, Iceland and GreenlandSpain and PortugalEast Mediterranean (via Cape) includesvessels taking cargo out but notallocated homewardIndia, Persian Gulf and BurmaFar EastAustralia &amp; New ZealandS, &amp; E. AfricaV7, African, America and AtlanticVf, Indies, Gulf and N. BrazilS, America atlantic, America Pacificn* AmeitLca PacificTotal of B (ii)Total of B (i) &amp;B (ii)Coasting trade of United Kingdom andEire.Vessels registered in U.K., Eire, theDominions, or chartered, by U,K. Govt,wo, I G-vr.10949158328106461523355133634 !   4334213 I   1964D.T7127581854507614633198No,19816936734120681135148101526810166902311221491733374256815768185 ! 107159 11371G.T.12771461273819175764495118648222465427247278108492960521105252821391629120324529530738002466   432   554! 107    263 ! 334
PART II (CONTINUED) - ANALYSIS OF D. &amp; E.to        itJm                                                                                                *rtm    J							500 - 1,599.G.H.			1,600 &amp;.T. &amp; Over		T).         Trading &quot;between countries other than United Kingdom and Eire.	No.	G.T.	D,W.	No,	G.T,	D, W,(i) Liners and other vessels on berth: /&apos;             India and Persian Gulf - Australia. India - U.S.A. Atlantic and West				4 9 9 1 1 17 1 8 5 10 10 7 4 8 9	27 52 54 5 4 112 8 54 29 60 66 56 21 52 69	44 72 73 9 7 167 9 77 45 74 100 59 26 78 99S. and E. Africa - Par East ....... S, and Eo Africa - U.S.A........ Australia - Eo Indies and Far East. Australia - Gulf and U. S.A. Atlantic Australia - U. S. A.  and Canada Pacific U. S.A. Atlantic - Bermuda, Gulf and Total of D (i) ... (ia)Vessels other than Liners trading to E. Mediterranean from;-										103	669	939				7 1	28 .    8	46 10Total of D (ia) e. (11)Vessels engaged in local trading abroad. (a) Vessels including liners registered in Dominion and Colonial ports and trading permanently abroad. (a!) Australia and New Zealand.. (Jo) Vessels, other than liners, registered   at U. K. ports and trading temporarily abroad .... (c) Liners registered at U. K. ports engaged in Local trading. Total of D (ii) . Totals ot D (i) &amp; D (ii) D (iia).4,.										8	36	56	87 57 22 85 5 I 1 24	80 59 22 81 5 1 1 26	95 59 24 86 6 1 28	121 89 21 112 25 1 5 88	439 302 93 371 114 8 15 342	547 288 138 495 181 7 12 426	260	255	279	462	1684	2094	260	255	279	573	2389	3089%                 Vessels repairing26, damaged or \                not in uee. Vessels wdorgolng or awaiting repair Prises not yet allocated ......... Vessels detained by French authorities Total of E,	45 10 6 s   4 65	40 10 7 5 62	54 6 10 n o 78 **********	175 15 27 16 235	998 141 172 61	1412 66 177 98 MMitfMI *4 -*** ***** 1753a This information ia necessarily approximate, as it Is largely based on weekly returnsfrom the Part Authorities as submitted to the Admiraltj tho dates of which are normrllyprior to that of this return.- 3 -        i
SUA ART OF ALLIED AND NEUTRAL VESSELS GIT time charter TO THE UNITED iOHGDOIj OH 31st AUGUST, 1940(Excluding Vessels under Enemy or French Control)&quot;&quot;&quot;A.     Analysis by Service(Tonnage figures in Thousands)		Tonnage Groups										500-1599 G.T.			1600 G,T.		&apos;&amp; over	500 G.T. &amp; over				No.	G.T.	D.W.	No.	G.T.	D.W.	No.	G.T.	D.W.I, OTHER THAN TANKERS (a) Defence Services fb) Ship Management Bch. &apos; (c^ Liner Division (d) Coasting &amp; Short Sea Total of I II. TANKERS (a) Defence Services (b) Commercial Services Total of II		2 103 8 73	3 141 11 72	2 221 18 101	22 358 132 1	152 1387 747 2	91 2299 1108 2	24 461 140 74	155 1528 758 74	93 2520 1126 103		186	227	342	513	2288	3500	699	2515	3842		-	-	-	38 141	306 1085	464 1640	38 141	306 1085	464 1640		-	-	-	179	1391	2104	179	1391	2104	B.   Analysis &quot;by Flag									I.OTHER THAN TANKERS Belgian Chinese Dutch Egyptian Greek Hungarian Jugo-Slavian Norwegian Panaivianian Polish Swedish Total of I II. TANKERS Belgian Dutch Norwegian   sc Panamanian Swedish Total of 11		1 28 116 3 38	2 34 138 4 49	2 50 210 6 74	28 1 181 5 104 3 1 124 1 7 58	114 2 989 21 465 10 6 429 5 35 212	148 3 1424 32 775 18 10 699 8 25 358	29 1 209 5 104 3 1 240 1 10 96	116 2 1023 21 465 10 6 567 5 39 261	150 3 1474 32 775 18 10 909 8 31 432		186	227	342	513	2238	3500	699	2515	3842		*-*		tm tm	1 8 164 3 3	5 58 1268 30 30	7 85 1920 &apos; 47 45	1 8 164 3 3	5 58 1268 30 30	7 85 1920 47 45		-	-	-	179	1391	2104	179	1391	2104x   Including 31 Vessels on pre-war Time Charter.
MINISTRY OF SHIPPING.Monthly Shipping Report for August, 1940.Vessels of 500 gross tons and over.Tonnage figures in thousands.(A) British vessels onI    2nd September&quot;&quot; 1*939500/1599 gross tons1,600 gross tons and overTotalTankersNo.66453519G-.T,643,211OthersNo.G.T.1,0582,5233,275      3,5811,02414,39315,417(g) Losses in August, 1940.Sinkings; enemy actionVessels captured by enemyOther deductions:-Marine lossesMi s ce 1 lane ous4547Total ..46562493811298(C)Gains   in August, 1940New vessels enemy vessels capturedDanish vessels transferred toBritish flagFrench vessels under British flagOther additions:-Transfer of flagEx Great Lakes, etc.105713269Total105793731132849461;(D) Net gain (4-) or loss (-) in monthTotal net gain or loss to 31st AugustBritish vessels detained in French ports thestatus of which has not yet been determinedsAdjusted total net gain or loss to date+3-1-1+11-48-4-52+37+102-20h-82+163*355-66-^289(E) (1) Vessels engaged on Naval, Military, orRoyal Air Force Services (includingGovernment owned vessels)(2) Balance14837085223715533110303112675(F) British vessels on 31st August 19405183,2233,66315,706(G) Vessels under construction in U.K. on31st August, 1940282321437&apos;&amp;762s   In arriving at these figures, credit is taken for ?4^,000 gross tons ofFrench and Danish vessels transferred to the British flag (15 tankers 99,000G.T. and ^ other vessels,        ,000 G.T.)




</content>
</cab>
