<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/37/37 images: 340-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTof theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 3rd June, to0700 10th June,1943SECRETCopy NoW.P. (43) 237(Also C.O.S. (43) 172)10th June, 1943WAR CABINET(No. 197)[ Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of &amp;taff.]
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.1. Norwegian light craft have inflicted damage on enemy shipping in norwegian waters.Naval bombardments of Pantelleria have continued during the week.H.M. and Allied submarines have made successful attacks cn shipping inthe Mediterranean.One U-boat has been sunk, one probably sunk and four probably damaged.Three ships have been reported sunk during the week. The shipping losses for May were considerably below the average.Imports for the week were exceptionally heavy.Home Waters and North Atlantic.2. On the 4th Norwegian M,TBs. 620 and 626 sank a 7/8,000-ton south-bound ship and seriously damaged the escort vessel, south of Bergen. shore batteries opened fire, but only superficial damage was done to the M.T.Bs. seven of their crews were wounded.M.T.Bs. and M.G.Bs. attacked a convoy off Dunkirk on the night of the 7thdamaging one trawler.3. On the 6th H.M. Submarine Trusty collided with a Spanish ship west of Cape St. Vincent.   Trusty was damaged and later reached Gibraltar.Mediterranean.4. Pantelleria was bombarded by our cruisers and destroyers with theco-operation of aircraft early on the 3rd, 5th and 8th. Shore batteries replied,but no damage or casualties were suffered.A reconnaissance of Pantelleria harbour on the 8th showed that all thevessels there had been sunk or set on fire with the exception of four lighters.5.   The following attacks have been reported by HM. and Allied submarines.On the 25th May Polish submarine Dzik torpedoed a 7,000-ton northboundtanker off Cape Spartivento (Italy). On the 19th Sportsman sank the VichyFrench s.s. General Bonaparte (2,796 tons) off Cannes, and on the 26th torpedoeda large tanker in the same area. On the 3rd June Unruffled torpedoed a south-bound 8,000-ton tanker off Messina. The Greek submarine Katsonis, on patrolin the ^aegean, torpedoed a 1,200-ton Spanish ship, which was subsequentlybeached and became a total wreck. A 7,000-ton transport in Samos harbour wasalso probably torpedoed.On the 4th a convoy consisting of 12 L.S.Ts. with five ships from gibraltar and nine ships from Malta and Tripoli arrived at Alexandria without incident.6. Seven berths are now available at Bizerta for working coasters; normalrunning repairs can be carried out by the limited facilities available at Ferryville;the canal at Tunis was expected to be clear for small coasters by the 8th. AtTripoli during the week ending the 1st, the average daily discharge was 3,520 tons,excluding petrol in bulk, of which 11,000 tons, were discharged. On the 29th and30th May 5,550 personnel were disembarked and 2,100 (including 108 prisoners)embarked. At Benghazi between the 28th May and the 1st June the averagedaily discharge was 960 tons. On the 6th No. 5 dock at Malta was pumped out and the very extensive repairs to the masonry were seen to have been highly successful.Black Sea.7. During the first week of May a Russian submarine operating off the westcoast of the Crimea sank two ships of 4,000 and 6,000 tons respectively, one ofwhich was carrying troops.During operations by Russian light craft and naval aircraft between the24th and 28th May eight barges were sunk and one ship was set on fire.Anti-Submarine Operations.8. Reports have been received during the week of 34 attacks on U-boats;-20 by aircraft and 14 by ships.
On the 2nd U.S. patrol craft P.C. 565 sank a German U-boat north-east ofNorfolk, Virginia. The Commanding Officer of the U-boat was the only survivor.On the 4th a Hudson aircraft probably sank a U-boat off Cape St. Vincent. FourU-boats were probably damaged; by U.S.S. Bibb (destroyer) south-west of Azores,by a Sunderland aircraft in the S.W. Approaches, and by Hudson aircraft off cape St. Vincent and south of Iceland (C) respectively.Adverse weather conditions have seriously impeded the special operations,being carried out by aircraft in the Bay of Biscay during the week.Enemy Intelligence.German.9. It is reported that the Graf Zeppelin is now carrying out her trials inthe Baltic. Prinz Eugen is reported to have entered the floating dock at Gdyniaon the 24th May.A number of M.T.Bs., escort vessels and barges, which came down the&quot;&quot;Danube, are now operating in the Black Sea. but low water has held up a numberof medium sized ships at Ratisbon, about 200 miles above Vienna.Italian.10. Since the beginning of the war the following warships have been sunk :five 8&quot; cruisers, six 6&quot; cruisers, 38 destroyers, 22 torpedo boats and at least60 U-boats.The main units of the Fleet are now disposed as follows : Three Littorioclass battleships and one light cruiser at Spezia, two Cavour class battleshipsand two light cruisers at Taranto and two light cruisers at Genoa. In addition,39 destroyers, 57 torpedo boats and about 70 U-boats are now effective. Two30,000-ton liners and possibly one Regolo class cruiser are being converted intoaircraft carriers.Japanese.11. Reconnaissance of Rabaul on the 8th showed 39 ships present, including&quot;22 merchant ships totalling about 93,000 tons and one tanker of 8.500 tons.Reconnaissance of Makassar (Celibes) showed 16 merchant ships, themajority under 500 tons.U-boats.12. Between 90 and 100 U-boats are estimated to be in the Atlantic and indian Oceans, 40 of which are operating on the North Atlantic convoy routes.A large group of U-boats is reported south-west of the Azores and about sixare operating between Capetown and Lourenco Marques.It is estimated that six U-boafs are in the Black Sea.Japanese U-boats are reported to be operating in the Tonga area, offNew Caledonia and New Hebrides and off the east coast of Australia.13. Concurrently with the general increase in the A.A. armament ofGerman U-boats, a limited number are reported to be converting for use asanti-aircraft escort U-boats; these are reported to have replaced the present80-mm. gun by a quadruple 20-mm. gun forward.Enemy Attack on Shipping.14. Only two ships are reported to have been attacked by U-boats during theweek.   One ship was sunk off Mozambique and the other off Durban.One ship was mined and sunk off Halifax (Nova Scotia).There have been no shipping losses in the N.W.. Approaches since the 17thMay.15. Shipping losses from enemy action during May, as recorded to date,amounted to 52 ships totalling 266,000 tons, which is the lowest monthly totalsince the United States entered the war, with the exception of January 1943, whenit was 244,000 tons. U-boats accounted for 47 ships (245,000 tons), of which 30ships (145,000 tons) were sunk in the North Atlantic. Japanese U-boats in the pacific sank five ships (33,000 tons). One ship was sunk by U-boat in theMediterranean. Four ships (20,000 tons) were sunk by aircraft and one ship was sunk by mine.Nine tankers, totalling 63,000 tons, were lost during the month.
Protection of Seaborne Trade.16. During the week ended the 6th, 1,061 ships were convoyed. Of these311 were in ocean convoys and 750 in British coastal convoys. Sixty-two destroyers (including 12 U.S. destroyers), 117 sloops, frigates, cutters and corvettes (including one French sloop) one U.S. cruiser and one ocean boardingvessel, were employed on escort duties.During the week 193 ships in five ocean convoys arrived in Home waters without loss.17. Imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy during the weekended the 5th totalled 1,837,000 tons, compared with 689,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average of 822,400 tons during the past ten weeks. Ofthe week&apos;s imports 628,000 tons were mineral oil of various grades. This is thelargest figure for any week since January 1940.18. During May 12 ocean convoys of 354 ships arrived in Home waters without loss and three convoys, originally of 124 ships, lost six ships beforearrival. Thirteen outward bound ocean convoys of 533 ships reached their destination without loss and three convoys, originally of 144 ships, lost 15 shipsbefore arrival; of these 15 ships, 13 were lost during attacks on one convoy.In the West Atlantic and Caribbean 165 convoys of 1,758 ships reached their destination without loss and one convoy, originally of 16 ships, lost one beforearrival.British Minelaying.19. Surface craft laid mines during the week in the Channel and inSt. George&apos;s Channel. Aircraft laid mines off the Frisian Islands, the dutch coast and in the Bay of Biscay.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.20. There has been further E-boat minelaying activity off the South-WestCoast during the week. On the night of the 5th/6th E-boats were operating in Lyme Bay and on the following night south-east of Plymouth. Enemy aircraft were minelaying in the Thames Estuary early on the 5th.Seven ground, and six moored mines have been destroyed in Home Watersduring the week.The mine totals are : -4,351 ground and 2,789 moored.21. In the Mediterranean minesweeping operations in the area east of the cape Bon Peninsula have been considerably hampered by anti-sweeping devices;from the 30th May to the 2nd June, 65 mines were destroyed and 246 anti-sweeping devices were encountered.Twelve moored mines were destroyed in the Bizerta Roads on the last two days of May.22. The presence of enemy mines off Halifax (Nova Scotia) has been confirmed and up to the present 34 mines have been destroyed, which have notbeen included in the mine totals given above.rEnemy Merchant Shipping.23. Nineteen arrivals and nine sailings of ore ships have been reported fromBilbao during the week.The Vichy tanker Firuz (7,326 tons), flying the German flag, passed throughthe Dardanelles on the 6th en route for Constanza. This is the first Vichy tankerto enter the Black Sea.It is reported that the Roumanian ships Basarabia (6,627 tons) andTransilvania (6,627 tons) were about to sail for Burgaz, where they would take on board German troops for the Crimea.24.. During the period 1st/15th May, 37 enemy ships, totalling 51,398 tons were sunk, captured or became constructive total losses, and seven ships (9,800tons) were seriously damaged. Of these, 32 ships (31,635 tons) were sunk and five ships (8,200 tons) were seriously damaged in the Mediterranean.
MILITARY SITUATION.The Russo-German Campaign.Central Sector.25. There has been local activity in the areas Velizh, Eirov and south-west of Orel, in which the Russians have generally taken the initiative.The Germans have now announced a further successful operation againstpartisans operating in their rear.Donetz Sector.26. A number of minor Russian attacks in the Byelgorod and Lisichanskareas have resulted in no positional changes.Taman Bridgehead. ,. ,27. As a result of repeated attacks against the eastern part of the Tamanbridgehead, the Russians have made slight local advances, but German resistanceis as strong as ever and no changes of importance have taken place.Burma.A arakan.28. The monsoon has broken in Burma. Operations have been confined topatrolling, and our forces have maintained their initiative. Between the 2ndand 5th one of our long-range patrols fought a successful action 3 miles north-east of Maungdaw and inflicted casualties on the enemy. It is reported that cholerahas broken out amongst the Japanese in Buthidaung.Chin Hills.29. Heavy rain during the last week has restricted ground and air operations. Our troops have reoccupied Fort White. Levy patrols to the east effort White have made no contact with the enemy.North Pacific.A leutians.30. A U.S. Navy Department communique gives revised figures for operations on Attu Island as 1,791 Japanese killed and 11 taken prisoner.AIR SITUATION.General Review.31. Adverse weather severely restricted operations of the Home-based AirForce.In the Mediterranean the Allied bombing effort was mainly directed againstPantelleria.Activity on the Russian front increased in the Central and Southern sectors.United Kingdom.32. In daylight enemy fighter-bombers continued their programme ofnuisance raids and, on two occasions, a total of 32 aircraft attacked Eastbourne;four of the attackers were destroyed.At night only seven aircraft flew overland, one of which was shot down.Coastal Operations.33. Day and night operations against shipping off the coasts of France andthe Low Countries resulted in damage to three E-boats, two M-class minesweepers,a 2,000-ton ship and eight ships of under 1,000 tons.Aircraft of Bomber Command, of which 51 were despatched, laid 143 sea-mines in enemy waters.
Germany and Occupied Territory.34. Daylight fighter attacks on transport targets resulted in damage to tenlocomotives and six barges; four Spitfires were lost.Night operations were confined to the dropping of leaflets over France by atotal of 29 Wellingtons.Mediterranean.Italy and Sicily.35. A heavy attack by 115 Fortresses (B. 17) was made on the dock area ofSpezia, where the main Italian fleet was located; a &quot; Littorio &quot;-class battleshipwas probably damaged. The three ferry termini of Messina, San Giovanni andReggio di Calabria were bombed by 50 Liberators (B. 24) and a further nightattack by 13 heavy bombers was made on Messina. Direct hits were obtained on one terminus and on railway sidings and many fires were reported, including alarge one at the Central Station, of Messina. Another raid by &quot;Liberators (B. 24)on the airfield at Grottaglie (12 miles E.N.E. of Taranto) caused considerable damage to hangars and administrative buildings and to aircraft on the ground.Other effective attacks were madeon the airfields at Gerbini and Catania. these operations by Liberators (B. 24) were intercepted by enemy fighters, 15 of whichwrere shot down.war hawks (P. 40F) attacked a seaplane base at Stagnone (9 miles S.S.W. ofTrapani) and destroyed 12 and damaged six seaplanes, and left burning oneschooner and three small vessels. Lightnings (P. 38) set three hangars on fire atTrapani/Milo airfield and obtained a direct hit on the mouth of a tunnel atBalestrate (20 miles W.S.W. of Palermo). Three fighters are missing from these attacks.Pantelleria and Sardinia:36. A very heavy scale of attack was directed against Pantelleria, over1,730 sorties being flown by bombers and fighter-bombers. Raids followed one another in succession throughout the day and were also made on most nights.The. harbour, airfield, town, radio station, gun positions and other military targets were the objectives for our bombers and considerable damage was caused.On the 5th enemy fighters were encountered over the island when a force of about20 Me. 109 and F.W. 190 aircraft intercepted our raiding aircraft. In all 23enemy fighters were destroyed and seven Allied aircraft are missing.in Sardinia two attacks by escorted Marauders (B. 26) were made on PortoPonte Romano and the harbours of Terranova and Porto Torres were also bombed; hits were made on three vessels, two of which were set on fire and on anumber of buildings. Lightnings (P. 38) attacked two airfields in the vicinity ofCagliari and set fire to workshops and hangars. The radio station and troops on Antico Island were attacked by war hawks (P. 40F). Enemy defensivefighters were not very effective, two Me. 109s were destroyed, and two Lightnings(P.38) and one Mitchell (B.25) are missing.North West Africa.37. Operations by enemy long-range bombers continued. to be on a small scale. A raid on Sousse by 25 aircraft caused no damage or casualties; a nightattack on Algiers resulted in some damage to barracks and houses. Enemyreconnaissance was exhaustive and all areas of the Mediterranean were covered.Coast of Greece and Eastern Mediterranean.38. Long-range fighters and light bombers destroyed or seriously damaged19 sailing vessels or small ships. In addition, they shot down two Cant Z1007sand damaged a goods train.   One Beaufighter is missing.Russia.39. The Soviet Air Force continued to give very strong support to the land forces in the Kuban. Indirect support to this fighting was provided by attacksoh German sea-borne supplies in the Black Sea. A series of very heavy attacks on German airfields in the Lisichansk area were made on the 6th. Attackscontinued to be made on German railway junctions; Kiev, Roslavl and Unechawere raided and much damage was caused to railway installations as well asstores and ammunition dumps.
The main German activity was that of the long-range bombers. A seriesof raids, amounting in all to 500 sorties, was carried out against Kursk, and itwas claimed that the railway station was destroyed. This operation was probablycarried out with a view to providing indirect support for the army by hamperingSoviet concentrations in the Kursk salient. . Subsequently, however, the long-range bomber force turned to strategic bombing, and for three successive nightsstrong forces were directed against the tank factories at Gorki, 200 miles east of moscow. It is claimed that in all 1,000 sorties were carried out against Gorki,and in the last attack alone 500 tons of bombs were dropped.The resumption of strategic bombing at the present stage may be an indication that the G.A.F. does not feel strong enough to support major military operationsexcept in the Kuban, where the necessity of holding the Russian offensive isenforcing a high scale of effort by close-support units of all categories.The Russians claimed to have destroyed 752 German aircraft in the weekended the 6th June for a loss of 212 of their own.    Nearly 170 of these areclaimed in defensive air fighting over Kursk during a German mass daylight raid ^on the 2nd.Burma.40. In Central Burma, Mitchells (B. 25) continued to attack enemy-communications. Severe damage was done to the railway yards at Mandalay,which were bombed twice, and similar targets were attacked at the nearby townsof Paukkan, Ywataung, Alon and Legyi. At Monywa, the airfield was bombed and a barracks destroyed. Mosquitoes, operating for the first time in Burma,attacked a landing ground at Kangaung (75 miles S.S.W. of Mandalay), settingfire to one aircraft on the ground and probably damaging others.In the Upper Chindwin, Blenheims and Mohawks (P. 36) bombed Kalemyoand Kalewa, and also attacked river craft at Paungbyin. Further south,Mitchells (B. 25) hit an oil storage cistern and the water filtration plant at Chauk(140 miles E.N.E. of Akyab).In the Mayu Peninsula area, enemy positions, M.T. and river craft were attacked, and warehouses at Akyab were bombed and hit.In South Burma, Blenheims bombed the town of Gangaw (90 miles S.E. ofAkyab), and two Liberators (B. 24) attacked radio installations on DiamondIsland (140 miles S.W. of Rangoon).China.41. At Ichang (290 miles E.N.E. of Chungking), escorted Liberators(B. 24) bombed the airfield destroying three aircraft on the ground; in combat,23 enemy aircraft were destroyed and eight probably destroyed for the loss ofone Kittyhawk (P. 40) . Enemy positions and troop concentrations, near Ichang,were attacked by Kittyhawks (P. 40), which also sank a number of bargescarrying crated aircraft. Several attacks were made on targets near Yochow(100 miles S.W. of Hankow), in the course of which four locomotives were&apos; destroyed and damage was done to other rolling-stock, warehouses and toriver craft.Enemy bombers attacked the airfield at Liangshan (105 miles N.N.E. ofChungking) ; 11 Allied aircraft on the ground were destroyed.Pacific Zone.New Guinea.42. U.S. heavy bombers dropped about 35 tons of bombs on Lae airfield and,in the north-east of the Island, attacked the airfields at But, Dagua, Wewakand Boran. Babo airfield, in the north-west, was- attacked on three occasionsby Liberators (B. 24) and Catalinas (P.BY.); in the same area, a raid wasmade on Mabire airfield, where hits on two warehouses, probably containingmunitions, resulted in a very heavy explosion..   Over Finschafen, a Fortress (P. 17) destroyed five of 16 enemy fighters whichintercepted.Enemy aircraft attacked Bulldog (95 miles N.N.W. of Port Moresby) andWau; at both places damage was slight.Timor.43. Three small-scale, attacks were made on Koepang; a barracks was seton fire and, in combat, three enemy aircraft were destroyed.
Solomon Islands.44. An enemy convoy, escorted by three destroyers, was attacked off Buin(Bougainville Island); one destroyer was probably sunk and two merchant ships were set on fire. In combat, 15 enemy aircraft were destroyed for the loss of fiveAllied aircraft.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.45.   Enemy raids over this country have been limited to one night and two days.On the night of the 4th/5th minor incidents occurred in the London area and at scattered points in Kent, Sussex, Wiltshire, Warwickshire andLeicestershire.On the morning of the 4th and in the afternoon of the 5th Eastbourne was bombed and machine-gunned; in both these raids private property sufferedconsiderable damage and some temporary dislocation was caused to the southern railway system.Casualties.46. The estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 hours onthe 9th were 14 killed and 44 seriously injured; of these 13 killed and 37 seriously injured occurred in the two raids on Eastbourne.
Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages lost by enemy action during the month of May 1943.Table I.The following table shows the division of losses into cause and nationality : -Flag.	Submarine.		Mine.		Surface Craft.		Aircraft.		Other Causes and  Cause Unknown.		Total.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.British Allied-Dutch ......... Greek   ...       ... Norwegian Panamanian United States ...       ... Other Allies Total of Allied losses Neutral countries Total	24	119,194	1	1,568 1 ...			4	20,296	1		-.....29	141,058	2 3 7 2 7 1	11,371 14,310 33,470 17,446 45,189 1,983				...					2 3 ; 7 2 7 1	11,371 14,310 33,470 17,446 45,189 1,983	22	123,769		...	...	...					22	123,769	1	1,633									1	1,633	47	244,596 1   1		1,568 i ... i			4	20,296			52	266,460
Table II.The following table shows the division of losses into cause and area: Area.	Submarine.		Mine.		Surface Craft.		Aircraft.		Other Causes and Cause Unknown.		Total.		No. 1	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.Atlantic  North   ...... South   .,....... Indian Ocean Pacific Areas......... Mediterranean United Kingdom Coastal Waters ... Elsewhere       (including North Sea and Barents Sea\ Total    ...	30 7 4 5 1	144,730 41,711 18,704 33,472 5,979	1	1,568	...		2 2	6,687 13,609			32 7 4 5 3 1 ...	151,417 41,711 18,704 33,472 19,588 1,568	47	244,596	1	1,568			4	20,296			52	266,460Table III.The following table shows the losses inflicted on Ocean, United kingdom coastal and Western Atlantic and Caribbean Convoys arriving at their destinations during May 1943.Convoys.	Number Convoyed.	Number Lost r(all by;S/M).	Percentage Lost.Ocean United Kingdom Coastal ____ Western Atlantic and Caribbean	1,155 2,976 1,774	21 1	1-8 0-1	5,905	22	0-4This table refers to losses while in Escorted Convoys.
(A. Losses from all Causes.(Tonnage in Thousand Gross Tons.)Period.British.Allied.Neutral.Total.No.Gr. Tons, i    No.Gr. Tons.      No.Gr. Tons.No.Gr. Tons.1939-September-November(3 months)December 1939-F ebruary1940 ............(3 months)1940-March-May(3 months)June-August        ...       ...(3 months)September-November(3 months)December 1940-F ebruary1941...(3 months)1941- :March-May(3 months)June-August(3 months)September-November(3 months)Totals-&apos; September 1939-November1941       ......110129110202255232282152160369419256-8511,034876i i,i3i1   501:   5321,6325,9691512367064741315141494821612962393285082011361,989197- 969953424945517102054482232691378113457902033382423713723484622482521,6442,8366566401,4161,4101,2851,7737597589,602(In Thousand Gross Tons.)Period.British Flag andBritish Controlled.No.Gr. Tons.American Flag andAmericanControlled.No.Gr. Tons.Others.&quot;No.Gr. Tons.Total.No.December 1941-F ebruary1942 (3 months)   ...1942-March-May (3 months)June-August (3 months)September ...       ...\jctoberNovember ...December  ...1943-january february march april may...&apos;Totals: December 1941-^_May 1943   ...33030324778841157950468949461,5161,1541,3161,2518664966553352072175042502106,96191158161432735172326421712652407759816197149182651211642279475437643145658129753,256233116191116321028102121222012464537451135116156101818414073.635992,401Gr. Tons.1,6772,2662,18359565586541034940275336429710,816Total Losses by  Enemy Action and Marine Causes of Merchant Ships outside enemy control, including Tankers but excluding Merchant Ships commissioned for Naval Service,Fleet Auxiliaries and American Merchant Ships employed in the Armed Services.(Including vessels of all tonnages for losses by enemy action and vessels of 100 gross tonsand over for losses by marine causes.)
3$. Losses analysed by cause.(In Thousand Gross Tons.)Period.Enemy Action.Marine Risk.Sub-marine.1939-September-November ..December    1939-February1940        .........1940-March-may june-AugustSeptember-November   ...December    1940-February1941        ...       ......1941-March-May        ...June-AugustSeptember-November   ..December   1941-February1942 ...       .....1942-March-may june-AugustSeptemberOctoberNovember...December...1943-JanuaryFebruaryMarchAprilMay3493171267367875128094694248801,5711,689479603712337203351613324245Mine.12,536160229105133868872243081513116141511,133Sur-Surface draft.3522122052452442194836101701341471120Air-craft.1,439Other jCausesjor    iCause jun- ;known.Total.Over-due,pre-sumedlost.*other non-EnemyCauses,t291672181311805389999191178198576604257663202,2763258436212434315295188107*297955476224941,3281,2701,0481,6726715941,4572,1582,062557621&apos; 81336124437768033726618,1793716281638151631381075&quot;727810324613060124199867213318298114382952421042173.2728Total109283146881402371018816422010812138345249105257327311,961 I 2,23920,418* Some of these losses may eventually be held to be due to enemy action.* Including losses due to vessels running on British orAUied mines.
Appendix III (1) will be inserted in a subsequent Resume.(2) Merchant ships (100 gross tons and over) under construction in the UnitedKingdom as at 31st May, 1943.(Tonnage figures in thousand tons.)	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross tons.	No.	Gross tons.Coasting ships and colliers Other ships Total in the United Kingdom	7 30	4 244	21 152*	26 920	37	248	173	946* Including 4 ships (2,000 gross tons) of Merchant type building for the Navy.In addition, the following merchant ships have been ordered in tJhe UnitedKingdom:  No.      Gross tons....... 23 182............ 46TankersCoasting tankers other Vessels135f17614204 813f Including 3 vessels (3,000 gross tons) of Merchant type to be built for the Navy.
Enemy Merchant Ship Losses are assessed to 15th May, 1953.Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously Damaged.		Damaged.     j        Total.				No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German Italian Other enemy ships  and ships useful to enemy Total     ......	528 785 284	2,173,031 2,827,937 465,291	190 170 30	431,470 732,282 63,123	360 227 52	949,740 879,742 183,923	1,078 1,182 366	3,554,241 4,439,961 712,337	1,597	5,466,259	390	1,226,875 j 639		2,013,405	2,626	8,706,539The table does not include losses inflicted on the enemy by our russian allies, which are estimated at about 1,500,000 gross tons sunk; nor does it include losses inflicted on Japanese shipping in the Far East and Pacific, which up to the15th May are estimated to number 317 ships sunk or about 1,771,000 gross tons.In addition there is about 146,000 gross tons of Axis shipping which has.been. taken over by South American countries not at war with the Axis.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and Naval Personnel.Qth June. H.M.S. Sargasso (dan-laying yacht) sunk by mine south-east of st. Alban&apos;s Head.7th June. M.G.Bs. 116 and 108 slightly damaged in action off Dunkirk.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 9 killed; 4 missing; 2 wounded; 1 killed and 2 prisonersof war, previously reported missing.Ratings: 39 killed; 11-missing; 5 wounded. .
APPENDIX VI.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports have been received during the week : Germany.Duisburg. Photographs taken on the 27th April and on the 13th, 14thand 15th May show the following damage resulting from the attacks on the26th/27th April and the 12th/13th May. By far the greater part of the damage has been caused by the second attack. The greatest concentration of damage isin the town centre of Duisburg, where 48 acres have been devastated, ruining the major part of the old town. Other incidents; which in the aggregate are considerable, are scattered over a wide area, but are largest in number andgreatest in severity in the neighbourhood of the main station and in the district of Meiderich.Many of the important industrial concerns in the suburbs of Duisburg have suffered damage. Pour factories of the Vereinigte Stahlwerke A.G. (AugustThyssen) have been affected, two of them very severely, and a coke and benzolpurifying plant apparently, put out of action. Extensive damage is seen also toa tar distillation plant, the largest in Germany. Beside munition-makingfactories other firms damaged include chemical works, zinc and sulphuric acidplant, ships&apos; boiler works, wire works, cotton and cellulose weaving mills, silkfabric factory, soap works, malt works and two collieries.Both docks and marshalling yards have suffered severely. Many ware-houses and store sheds on the quaysides have been destroyed and stores of timberburnt out. At least seven barges have been sunk, others damaged and a bargebuilding yard destroyed by fire. Besides many warehouses around the greatmarshalling yards in the dock area destroyed or damaged, railway tracks in the yards and sidings have been disrupted by many direct hits and rolling-stockscattered. Communications have been further interrupted by direct hits onbranch lines, by severe damage to a lock-gate on the Rhein-Herne Canal, bydamage to two railway viaducts and especially by severe damage to the mainpassenger and goods stations.Apart from the old town and Papendell, where over 600 buildings, mostlyof the large city-block type consisting of shops, offices, hotels and blocks of flats,have been destroyed or damaged, the most severe damage to residential property is found in the districts of Meiderich and Hamborn, areas north-east of the docks, and in the district of Neudorf, south-east of the town centre. In theformer some 850 buildings and in the latter district some 300 have suffereddemolition or severe damage,, the greater part of them being of the workers&apos;dwelling type. Altogether, over 2,000 houses or other buildings are seen to havebeen destroyed by fire or H.E. or rendered uninhabitable.Wilhelmshaven. A final interpretation of photographs taken on the28th May, after the U.S.A.A.F. daylight attack on the 21st May, shows that some13 buildings in the Marine Werft have been damaged, most of them severely.These include : (1) The machine-shop north of Slip 2, where the roof has been stripped overan area of 900 sq. yds.(2) The North Electric Power Station, north-west corner of the Bauhafen,gutted over an area of 670 sq. yds. with considerable further roofdamage.(3) Lathe shop and joiner&apos;s shop and adjoining shed at north-west corner of the Bauhafen, 760 sq. yds. of building destroyed and severe damage to remainder.(4) Smithery and joiner&apos;s shop, at the west of the Bauhafen, gutted over an area of 2,000 sq. yds.(5) Boiler shops, at the south-western corner of Bauhafen, destroyed over an area of 230 sq. yds.About 42 business or residential buildings in the town area north and southof the Bauhafen have suffered, the majority being demolished.Essen. Photographs taken on the 29th, after the attacks on the 30th April/1st May and the 27th/28th May, show much fresh damage in Krupps Works andin the N.E. port of Essen.
In Krupps, six machine shops have been severely damaged, and five buildings of a power plant serving the steam-hammer sheds partially destroyed. A foundry,a rolling mill, the Diesel motor shop, the administrative offices and several otheroffices have all been more or less seriously damaged.Three collieries and a nut and bolt factory at Stoppenberg have been hit, andmany commercial buildings at Altenessen and in the city centre have been destroyed or damaged. A hutted camp and two flak positions have suffered damage, and the road bridge over the railway at Delwig has been broken. ^ Thereare also several direct hits on tracks. Two acres of Gasworks buildings atSegeroth have been destroyed and there is considerable further damage to residential property.Wuppertal. Fires were still raging at noon on the 30th May and were onlygot under control with the assistance of neighbouring brigades. The efficiency of the civil defences was considerably impeded by the fact that the higher officials were already absent in the countryside. In addition to the usual extra rations,more than a million tins of preserved fish were rushed into the district.The Mohne and Eder Dam-?. The water supply of Dortmund has been completely disorganised and the canal level considerably exceeds all previousrecords. The bursting of the dams is described as the greatest disaster in100 years.France.Bordeaux. A final interpretation of photographs taken on the 17th and25th May shows considerable damage in the area around Bassin 1. Warehouseand industrial buildings near the docks &quot;-have suffered severely, and in additionto the Matford aero-engine works, there is important damage to the St. Louisrailway station and to two chemical works on the east bank of the river. Thewrecks &apos;of several cranes which used to stand on the quay which has collapsedcan be seen half-submerged in the later photographs. These also reveal that atemporary caisson has been placed in position across the inner end of the lock.The main items of damage are : (1) The Matford Aero-Engine Works. The main workshop, six bay(580&apos; x 300&apos;) has been seriously damaged by at least six direct hitsand is about l/6th demolished. A four-bay building (250&apos; x 150&apos;)has been severely damaged as well as two smaller buildings.(2) Gobain Chemical Works. A large four-bay building (475&apos; x 210&apos;)&apos; hasbeen damaged, a seven-bay building (265&apos; x 275&apos;) and a two-baybuilding (460&apos; x 80&apos;) severely damaged, and a smaller, buildingdemolished.(3) The Gare St. Louis, which has received 12-14 direct hits, demolishing alarge area of one platform, and damaging station buildings andanother platform.   Sidings and trucks have also been damaged.In addition a number of unidentified industrial buildings, manyf. of them large, have been damaged and several of them severely.Caen Carpiquet. It is reported that as a result of one of our attacks inApril, the wireless telegraphy station and the wireless telegraphy tenders werepartially destroyed. Casualties amongst personnel amounted to 20, of whom six were officers. &apos;     -;.Holland.Flushing. Photographs taken during the attack on the 31st May show atleast one bomb bursting on two vessels berthed in the marine dock, and, threedirect hits on the engine shops on the north side of the clock. Four bombs havefallen across the oil storage tanks on the east side of the Verbreed canal, and 10amongst shipping berthed alongside the quays. Four other bursts are seen acrossthe asphalt plant in the town and four more on the south-west dispersal area ofVlissingen Airfield. -Italy.Naples.-Photographs of rather small scale taken on the 5th May after the attack of the 28th April show a number of items of fresh damage.   Several hits
have been obtained on the Quays, the Calata Vittorio Veneto being seriously damaged. Further damage has occurred to the Granili Barracks, and to the GasWorks, while the factory between the A.G.I.P. Oil Storage Depot and the RoyalArsenal on which repairs were in progress has again been hit.Sea-mining.The following mining results have been received : 1st May. The Dutch motor vessel Bertha (153 tons) was mined and sunk off Gjedser.6th May. Danish Oummo, 492 tons, was mined and sunk near KattegatSyd Lightship.7th May. Cutter No. 164 Bodil mined and sunk in the Fehmarn Belt.13th May. Motor ship Svalen mined and sunk north of Brandso (LittleBelt).15th May. German motor ship Arusa mined 15 miles off Hals. ^15th May. A German schooner was mined and sunk in the North Sea.Mid May. Press reports state that the Swedish Hanestrom V (515 tons)was mined and sunk off the German Baltic coast.28th May.-Swedish radio reports that the Swedish Gondul was mined and sunk.






</content>
</cab>
