<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/24 images: 220-231</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1942.SECRET,W.M. (42)24th Conclusions.Copy N6.    44TO&apos; BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may bei taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 24 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the. War Cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;s.Room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Wednesday, February 25, 1942, at12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. C: R. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Air   Chief   Marshal   Sir   Charles F. A. Portal, Chief of the Air Staff^   (Item 1).The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for the Colonies..Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Item 1).General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff (Item 1).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Contents.M minute no. Subject.1      Air Reinforcements for India and Burma2      U:S.S.R.........      ....[23508-1]Page128
*! Reinforce- l.   The War Cabinet had before them a Report by the Chiefsments for India Gf Staff Committee as to certain measures which were consequentialand Burma.      upon the steps taken to increase the number of fighter squadrons inIndia and Burma (W.P. (42) 95).   The Chiefs of Staff sought authority to borrow 72 Hurricane II aircraft from those, nowallotted to Russia, to be repaid in the next three months.The War Cabinet-(1) Decided that this recommendation could not be accepted,and that there must be no interference with supplies ofHurricane aircraft to Russia.(2) Invited the Minister of Labour and National Service, the&apos; Secretary of State for Air and the Minister of aircraft production to examine what could be done to increasethe output of Hurricane aircraft.U.S.S.R. 2.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (42) 96), covering an reference-        exchange of telegrams with Washington.W.M. (42) 18th The War Cabinet-Minute^T Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs toprepare, for consideration at a further Meeting to be heldat 7 p.m. that evening, a draft telegram to Washington,setting out the procedure which he suggested should beadopted for the next stage in the discussions.Great George Street, S.W. 1,February 25, 1942.
OUTWARD TELEGRAM.(CYPHER)DEPARTMENTAL NO. 1.FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO WASHINGTON.NOo 129126th February, 1942,Do 2.15 p.m. 26th February, 1942.IMMEDIATEMOST SECRETYour telegrams Nos. 971 and 1013 (of 20th and 21stFebruary:   Anglo-Soviet negotiations).I do not think that President can fully understanddifficulties of whole problem when he expresses confidence in being able to reach agreement with Stalin on lines indicated inparagraphs 4 and 5 of your telegram No. 1013.     It is alsodifficult for us, as you rightly pointed out to Welles, to stand aside while President takes up matter with Stalin since it,is With tis that latter wishes toi-conclude. a treaty and since we, not&apos;United States Government^ are principles in thesehe go t ia t i ons I2. I have consulted Mr. Winant who has suggested that since he is shortly proceeding to.Washington, the best course would befor me to give him memorandum for use with President.     This Ihave done and the text of the memorandum is contained in my telegram No. 1306.3.     I would suggest that pending Mr. Winanfs arrival, you should confine yourself to telling Mr. Welles that Mr. Winantis the bearer of His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s reply to the presidents proposal that he should intervene directly withStalin and that you hope that he will therefore take no step in this direction until he has received Mr. Winant*s report.4,       You will no doubt get in touch with Mr. Winantimmediately upon his arrival and concert with him how you can best participate in the discussion of our memorandum.5.     For your own guidance, we are anxious to establish the habit whereby all big political questions arising out of the warshall be dealt with by means of tripartite discussions and decisions.     The present offer of the President to enter intodiscussion with Stalin on the Baltic question seems to afford agood opportunity to get this tripartite system started.   If a tripartite discussion can be arranged in the present case andif the outcome is reasonably successful it ought to be possibleto repeat the experiment on future occasions and thus graduallycreate convenient precedents which would enable the procedure for joint consultation to evolve more or less spontaneously.The ideal form for such tripartite discussions would beinformal meetings between Mr. Winant, M. Maisky and myself.(Copies sent to Members of the War Cabinet)

CYPHER. DEPARTMENTAL NO.  1.PROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO WASHINGTON.No. 1506.February 26th, 1942. D.1O.40 p.m. February 26th, 1942.IMMEDIATE.MOST SECRET. *My telegram No. 1291 paragraph 2.   Following is text of memorandum.   Begins,Lord Halifax has told us that the President, after full consideration of the suggestions which His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave put forward for dealing with M. Stalin1s demand for the recognition of his 1941 frontiers in Finland, the Baltic Statesand Roumania, as a condition for signing an agreement for co-operation with us in post-war problems, did not feel able to approve either the acceptance of these demands or the two alternative proposals submitted to him.   We understood that thePresident felt that both of these alternative proposals were difficult to reconcile with the Atlantic Charter and that it waspremature to attempt detailed treatment of the problem.2,     Lord Halifax has also told us that the President feelsconfident of being able to reach agreement direct with M, Stalinand proposes to set about doing so, through M. Litvinov in thefirst instance, supporting his action later through AdmiralStandley.   We understand that the line the President might proposeto take is that he entirely recognises the justice of M. Stalin&apos;claim for security and that this can be met in a variety of ways in regard to which it is difficult for the moment to take a finaldecision.3.     As Lord Halifax stated to Mr. Sumner Welles, when thelatter informed him of the President&apos;s attitude, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would naturally feel nothing but satisfaction if thePresident could in fact reach agreement with M. Stalin.   At thesame time His Majesty&apos;s Government feel that they should, in thelight of their own experiences in the Moscow talks and elsewhere,put before the United States Government their own view of theproblem and some suggestions as to how it might be handled.Admittedly no easy solution is at hand.4.     It is true enough that one of the chief aims of soviet policy has been and no doubt still is to obtain the maximumguarantees of Russia&apos;s &quot;security&quot; so that the Soviet government can work out their own social and economic experiment withoutdanger of foreign intervention or war.    But this is by no means thechief motive which lies behind M. Stalin&apos;s present demand for the recognition of his 1941 frontiers.   We cannot therefore leLp feeling that the President is unduly optimistic in supposing that someother form of security in lieu of the reoccupation of the baltic states will prove acceptable to M. Stalin.     Since M. Stalin hasdecided that the Soviet union security requires that the baltic states should be in the Union, he will not be willing to discussthe rights and wrongs of this decision.

5.     M. Stalin&apos;s view -undoubtedly is that having takenthxs decision, he is merely asking us to assist him to recover these territories at the Peace Settlement, if the needarises - ancient Russian territories which had been regained bythe Soviet Union before Hitler&apos;s attack on   Russia.   As for the atlantic Charter, he would argue that the frontier which he wishes us to recognise in Finland was one that was settled in due form by a treaty between the Soviet and FinnishGovernments, that the Baltic States voted for inclusion inthe Soviet Union by means of plebiscites, thus fulfilling theprinciples of the Atlantic Charter, and that Bessarabia andNorthern Bukovina were handed back to Russia by Roumaniain accordance with the provisions of a treaty concluded betweenthe   Soviet and Roumanian Governments.   Moreover, M. Stalinsigned the Atlantic    Charter on the assumption that it onlybecame effective for the soviet Union on the basis of the frontiers of 1941.6.      It is true that we have suggested two alternative proposals to the President based on Russia&apos;s security needs,but we doubt whether they would satisfy M. Stalin even ifthey could be shown to have the support of the United Statesof America and were accepted as a contribution towards sincereco-operation between our three countries at the peacemakingand after the war.    But these alternative proposals containedconcrete offers, whereas the President would appear to be ofthe opinion that it is premature to attempt a detailedtreatment of the problem.7.     As to the procedure which should now be followed,clearly it would be to the common advantage if conversations between President Roosevelt and M. Stalin were to result inagreement being reached between all three powers.    The way would then be open for us to sign a treaty with M. Stalin.    V/ethink, however, that we should put to President Roosevelt someof the difficulties which we see in this procedure.     As it is with His Majesty&apos;s Government and not with the United StatesGovernment that M. Stalin wishes to conclude a treaty and asit is from His Majesty&apos;s Government that he wishes to obtainrecognition of his territorial claim, it would seem in-appropriate to him that we should not be a party to theseexchanges.     We fear that if the President were to argue thismatter alone with M. Stalin, the latter might suspect that wehad agreed to this procedure to bear upon him, and he mightresent it accordingly.,     Moreover, as we have not ourselvesexpressed any opinion to M. Stalin on this subject since the moscow meeting, if he were now to learn the result of ourexchanges of views with the United States Government throughthe President and not through us he might misinterpret this procedure as indicating that His Majesty&apos;s Government haddisinterested themselves in this European problem.8.     An alternative method has therefore occurred to us,and we should like to suggest it to President Roosevelt,M. Stalin, by putting forward his condition, has touched upon an issue which is of equal interst to the United States and ourselves, and therefore it would seem that all three powers should get together to discuss this difficulty.    The virtuein this procedure is that such consultation would not onlyhelp to overcome this particular difficulty but might lead inthe future to close co-operation, both for the conduct ofthe war and in the period after the war, between the threeprincipal Powers.   We believe that such a prospect would be welcomed by M. Stalin.    If the President would consider theproposal favourably we should therefore like to propose thattripartite conversations should ensue in London on Mr. Winanfsreturn.(Copies sent to Members of the War Cabinet.)

OUTWARD TELEGRAMo105H. 1104/86/G.(Cypher) DEPARTMENTAL NO. 1.FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO WASHINGTON.No. 1S0926th February, 1942.       D. 11.30 p.m. 26th February, 1942.IMMEDIATEMOST secret my telegrams Nos. 1291 and 1306 (of February 26th).I gave memorandum to United States Ambassador last night.     He read it through and said that it seemed to him a very good document.2.     I then made following points verbally which Ambassadorsaid he would bear in mind:-(a) Poles were apprehensive of consequences ofendorsing 1941 Russian frontiers in respect of Baltic States,but at the same time there was much to be said from Polishpoint of view for our reaching an agreement with Russia ifwe could.     If our treaty were signed Russia would be boundto consult us about frontiers of Poland as about all othermatters in $europe.     This must be to Polish advantage sincePoles were at present entirely dependent upon Stalin&apos;sexpressions of goodwill.(b) It did not seem to us possible to argue thatconception of Russian bases in the Baltic States ran contraryto Atlantic Charter.     Stalin could certainly argue that ifexistence of American bases in British West Indies did not conflict   with Charter, there was no reason why Russian bases in Baltic States should do. so.3.     Ambassador undertook to do his best to expound our point of view to President and to Mr. Surnner Welles.individual.




</content>
</cab>
