<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/60/41 images: 352-369</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/&quot;?Z* * ,       SeT-/       &apos;/-/ .- &quot;TY 3 &apos;    &apos;^w-    :THIS DOCUMENT IS THE! PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted&apos;for the War Cabinet.   January 1945. 1 U *)The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited,   it is issued a sie uiruusaiaun m ima paper mas men sinufor the personal use of . r^^^^^r^^t.WAR CABINET.THE WASHINGTON NEGOTIATIONS FOR LEND-LEASE IN STAGE II.Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.MY colleagues will be -interested to read the attached Report which lord Keynes made after returning from his recent stay in Washington.2. As will be seen, the &quot;document concerns matters of a highly delicatecharacter; no doubt my colleagues will ensure therefore that it is treatedaccordingly.J. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,9th January, 1945.THE WASHINGTON NEGOTIATIONS FOR LEND-LEASE IN STAGE II.Report by Lord Keynes.Chancellor of the Exchequer.I have sufficiently reported in telegrams the positive conclusions of theWashington negotiations in October and November 1944. But there remaincertain supplementary incidents and observations which may be worth furthercomment.2. Prior to the conversations between the Prime Minister and the Presidentat Quebec three dangerous tendencies, one newly emerging, the other two of oldstanding, were influencing the attitude of Washington towards the scope of lend-Lease in Stage II.3. The first of these was directed to a considerable curtailment of the scopeof Lend-Lease after the defeat of Germany. There were, we believe, various proposals passing during the summer in and between Washington Departments,more particularly in the War and Navy Departments, but also in F.E.A. (theForeign Economic Administration), lacking indeed any final authority butrepresenting what some service and civilian officials might be found pressing onfinal authority at a suitable opportunity.4.   In the field of munitions these proposals were for limiting assistance tothose of our needs required solely for the war against Japan and capable ofbeing produced only in the United States, without regard to our over-all require-ments or to our need to release man-power.   It is likely that the requirements of[29006] bTOP SECRET .        &apos; /    Copy No,   34W.P. (45) 24.9th January, 1945.r-.....mL
the Admiralty would in any event have been subjected to particular scrutiny andcurtailment. But if these proposals had been acted upon, only a part of our ground and air requirements would have been considered and the rest rejectedout of hand. In the field of non-munitions Lend-Lease would have been restricted,according to the more extreme school, to foodstuffs. I much doubt, however,whether the potential threat in this field was nearly so serious as in the case ofmunitions.5. These ideas were logically defensible up to a point, if the scale of lend-Lease in Stage II were to be restricted, as broadly speaking it has been in stage I, to our marginal requirements over and above what we could providefor ourselves when completely mobilised for war and drawing on all other sourcesto the maximum extent. They were also conformable to the fundamental principleof the Lend-Lease Act that aid under it must be &quot; for the defence of the UnitedStates &quot; which was held, and still is held, by some precisians to exclude theprovision of any dispensable easements for the inhabitants of the British Isles.During the brief visit of Sir Wilfrid Eady and myself to Washington in Augustafter Bretton Woods and Ottawa, it was made clear to us by the heads of theWashington missions that we must somehow secure that this limitation to merelymarginal aid should cease to apply in Stage II. It was also clear that so vital achange as this could only be secured and held fast by a decision reached by thePresident at the instance of the Prime Minister. The Prime Minister took theopportunity of the Quebec meeting in September to discuss and agree with thePresident a brief outline directive, sufficient for this purpose, and requiringF.E.A. to have in view the objectives of permitting after V-E Day some releaseof British man-power, some improvements in the standards of civilian consump-tion, and a broad resumption of the freedom to export. This directive wasentrusted to Mr. Morgenthau and Lord Cherwell for further discussion andimplementation with the United States departments concerned.6. Some difficulties and dangers remained. For this directive was of thebriefest character .and was capable of different interpretations, both in principle and in degree, when it came to working it out in detail and in practice. Never -theless, the Quebec decision plainly rejected the principles underlying theproposed curtailments which, as mentioned above, were previously floating aboutin some quarters in Washington, and gave us a firm basis of clearly expressed general intention upon which to work. In addition, Mr. Morgenthau, with whomLord Cherwell had established an intimate and very helpful understanding, had become a convinced advocate of a strengthening of our financial and economic position. Sir Robert Sinclair and I, wuth other officials (amongst whomMr. Austin Robinson of the Ministry of Production, Mr. Reader of the Ministryof Labour, and Mr. Bridgeman of the Ministry of Fuel and Power deserve par-ticular mention for their skilled help in essential details), joined Lord Cherwellin Washington. On the American side a committee of three was established under mr. Mqrgenthau&apos;s chairmanship, including Mr. Stettinius and Mr. Crowleythe Foreign Economic Administrator, with the addition of Mr. Pattersonand Mr. Lovett of the War Department and Mr. Gates of the Navy Department,where service questions were under discussion. On the technical sub-committee,as it was called, the principal American members, with whom all our detailed work was conducted on the non-munitions and export questions, were Mr. HarryWhite of the United States Treasury (in the chair), Mr. Dean Acheson an assistant Under-Secretary in the State Department, assisted by Mr. Taft, andMr. Oscar Cox and Mr. Currie, principal officers of F.E.A. On the Munitionsside, however, Sir R. Sinclair pressed from the outset, wisely and with success,that our Service representatives, General Weeks, Air Chief Marshal Courtneyand Admiral Waller, should be put into direct touch with their opposite numbers,and many difficult points were discussed in a preliminary way with the service departments in the week before the formal presentation of the case.7. It had been my original intention to depend to a much greater extent,as I had done in Canada, on oral exposition. But Sir Robert Sinclair favouredfrom the outset a full statement in writing and he proved correct. In view ofthe shortness of time, he had originally in view a document which would be mainlyan elaboration of WP. (44) 419. I felt, however, that if we were to have a writtenexposition, the only satisfactory solution would be a complete re-writing of the document. The preparation of this statement was a heavy task for all concerned,but in the end everyone accepted the advisability of attempting it and, after aweek&apos;s very intensive work, the task was accomplished.   There was never at any
time an opportunity for continuous or coherent oral exposition to the rightaudience. A Washington meeting has to be experienced to be believed. At themain Committee any continuous argument or indeed more than a dozen simplesentences were always out of place. At the technical and other sub-committeesthere would be twenty-five or more persons present at any one time, but theircomposition would be continually changing as they flocked in and out of the roomto attend telephone calls and other business, so that we were seldom addressingthe same audience for more than ten minutes together. One would suddenlydiscover that even the chairman had disappeared without explanation to returnhalf an hour later, and the actual spokesman on the American side would break off his remarks at any moment to answer a call from without. Indeed in washington the Ancient Mariner would have found it necessary to use the tele-phone to detain the wedding guest. For it is only on the telephone that one can obtain undivided attention. If you seek an interview, your American friend willspend half the time talking on the telephone to all the quarters of the compass,until in despair you return to your own office and yourself ring him up, when you can expect to secure his concentrated mind for as long as you like, whilstsomeone else wastes his time keeping a date with him in the chair which you have so wisely vacated. No! Sir Robert Sinclair was right that a writtendocument is best.8. Moreover, there is no place where ample documentation is more appre-ciated than in Washington. There is an unquenchable inquisitiveness whichquickly turns into suspicion if it is not satisfied. Nor is there, as a rule, any reason to fear dangerous purpose when a piece of information is pressed for.Attached to every Department in Washington there is a cohort of researchers,economists and statisticians, who will take unlimited trouble to understand yourcase and whose business it is to think objectively. If your case is a good one andif they feel that you have given them the material for a thorough unstanding of it, they will become your best friends and advocates. In the long run, their influence is considerable; most certainly their criticism can be dangerous. I am convinced t*hat in the past we have made a great mistake, and handicapped our representatives in Washington, by an economy of information. So-called &quot; reasons of security &quot; must be reckoned at least as one of the minor, if not sometimes a major, inefficiency of the machine of War. The Statement of our Position wonover to our support an army of honest thinkers and clever heads scattered allover the administrative area.9. The Munitions programme was given priority in our agenda. It was,in fact, agreed with remarkable ease and celerity. Sir R. Sinclair was able topresent and justify exact details of requirements over a wide field. GeneralWeeks and Colonel Sallitt from the War Office and Air Chief Marshal Courtneyand Mr. Hindley from the Air Ministry came over from London with full and up-to-date knowledge of all relevant matters and presented the military case to the United States War Department with unfailing authority and skill. Theyseemed soon to acquire an ascendancy over their American colleagues and werenever defeated on any matter to which they attached critical importance. the representation of the Supply Departments Mr. Willison from the Ministryof Production, and Mr. Devons and Mr. Taylor from Ministry of Aircraft Pro--duction were of the greatest assistance on the production side. With the navy department, on the other hand, there was much more difficulty, although ourAdmiralty requirements (apart from the fleet air arm programme which wasdealt with separately) were of a relatively unimportant character compared withthe rest of our needs and, being an insignificant proportion of total Americanoutput, could not present great difficulty on the supply side Early in the dis-cussions the United States Navy Department broke contact with Admiral Wallerand gave us to understand that we should be faced with a unilateral decisionpresented to the Main Committee without our experts having previous knowledgeof its content or an opportunity for explanation and discussion. We, therefore,judged it advisable to lay a formal complaint about this procedure before mr. Morgenthau. He immediately promised us redress, saying that he saw noreason why the Navy Department should not follow the excellent precedentwhich had been set by the War Department. We understand that, at a meetingof the American members of the Main Committee which was summonedimmediately, the Navy Department after an initial show of strong resistancewas in the end, and with some difficulty, brought to yield, after which fracasthe essential items of the Admiralty programme were accepted without much[29006] , &quot; B 2
further ado. Before sunset, as he had promised us, Mr. Morgenthau was asgood as his word. This opportunity may be taken to record that Mr. Morgenthauwas, throughout the discussions, as good as his word within the limits of his powers. On two occasions in particular, that just mentioned and the last-minuteattempt to withhold our export freedom he interposed on &quot;our behalf withvehemence and with success. Throughout the procedings he maintained with lord Cherwell (who had, however, left Washington before the turmoils of thelast fortnight recorded below) and with myself unbroken relations of confidence,cordiality and intimacy, and he never failed to give us all the support thathe could.10. In one respect, the discussions on the munitions programme were particularly satisfactory, namely that the American side accepted our require-ments with much less question than on previous occasions as being the properand necessary consequence of the strategic decisions of the Combined Chiefs ofStaff. Indeed, Sir R. Sinclair and the Service representatives did not haveto accept any curtailments of the demands we had brought from London except where they were themselves satisfied that a reduction could be made safely or where there were genuine supply difficulties at the American end:11. In another respect, however, we were defeated of our best hopes,inevitably in my opinion, though to Sir Robert Sinclair&apos;s disappointment. our original idea had been to secure, without using the word, something approachingprotocol validity for our requirements when once they had been passed byMr. Morgenthau&apos;s Committee. This proposal, however, aroused great wrath inthe United States War and Navy Departments. We should have quicklyexhausted our rather limited stock of goodwill in those Departments if we had pressed it. Moreover, there were sufficiently good arguments from futureinevitable changes in the strategical position and in supply conditions in Americawhy the Americans should reserve for themselves an ultimate discretion. the truth is that, not being at arm&apos;s length, as the Russians are, we have to sufferthe inconvenient familiarities of our proximity as well as its broad advantages.Nevertheless, so far as phrases are worth anything, they have in the covering-letters accepted the basis of our military needs; they have said they will do their best to make available the quantities accepted in the agreements; and they agreethat the production of our requirements will rank part passu with their own.This is better than anything we have had hitherto; though there remain,as before, not only the continuing supervision of the Combined Munitions Assign-men ts Board, which we readily accepted, but also all the usual -jokers by whichthere is very little on which they cannot run out on us hereafter on one pretextor another, if they are so minded. In practice, those who have had experienceof the system will, I think, agree that our failure to secure protocol procedure is not as bad as it sounds.12. There is, however, some reason for caution arising out of this. not too much attention should be attached to what follows, but it should not escapenotice altogether. We have reason to think that the War and Navy Depart-ments did not accept with any enthusiasm either the Quebec directive or theprocedure of the Morgenthau Committee on which they were not representedformally or as of right. Mr. Morgenthau was too clearly armed with thePresident&apos;s personal authority to make any overt resistance advisable. More-over, his position was undoubtedly strengthened and the whole course of our negotiations made less difficult by the preliminary understanding he was able toreach with Mr. Patterson, the Assistant Secretary of the War Department.Our case was presented to Mr. Morgenthau on the 17th October. Within thehour a copy was in the hands of the War Department. Discussions with our representatives began at once, and by the morning of the 23rd agreement onthe War Office and Ministry of Supply items had been reached and a report made to the Main Committee. The Air agreement did not lag far behind. all this undoubtedly gave great encouragement and reassurance to Mr. Morgenthauas well as to ourselves. Nevertheless, the dissident elements may find some later and more favourable opportunities for bringing the situation a little nearer to what they had been aiming at before Quebec. One is told that the service departments in Washington include certain less friendly elements such as arescarcely to be found, if at all, in the State Department, the Treasury or F.E.A.A certain number of quondam Isolationists dressed up in uniform are seatedthere. These Departments are admittedly the stronghold, not only (particularlyin the Navy) of service jealousies but also of the unco-operative imperialistic
ambitions and expansionisms into which the xenophobe passions of isolationismand America-first are suffering what can be literally called a sea-change. Theseminority and opposition elements are not strong, but they are capable of mischief;though it must be remembered that the discussions on the Munitions programmepreceded the Election, the outcome of which has served to diminish the practicalsignificance of these elements, at least for the time being. We had hoped atone time to obtain some security against later back-sliding by keeping theMorgentihau Committee in being with a measure of continuing authority. Inthe confusion iand habitual Washington disorder of our winding up it was notpossible to make any formal proposition to this effect. Nevertheless, I think we might proceed on the tacit assumption that the Morgenthau Committee still continues in existence, for all we know to the contrary; and if the occasion should arise (which is, one hopes, unlikely) when there is some clear case of back-slidingfrom what this Committee had approved, the notion of bringing the matterformally to the notice of Mr. Morgenthau and his colleagues should certainly beconsidered. If the Prime Minister decides to make any communication to thePresident, possibly there might be a suggestion along these lines; on the otherhand, the tacit assumption suggested above may be the safer line, since it is perhaps not very likely that any general agreement could be obtained in washington at the present time to put on a permanent footing a committee forthis purpose with Mr. Morgenthau in the chair.13. Our non-munitions programmes (apart from the extra new items tobe dealt with below) went through more slowly than the munitions but with no less ultimate success. They were handled entirely by the Washington missionson the spot dealing, under general direction, with their usual opposite numbers.We created a good impression by ourselves taking the initiative in cutting out anumber of items, more particularly steel and non-ferrous metals and a wide range of miscellaneous manufactured articles, which were likely to interfere with our export freedom. By distinguishing between items for consignment to this countryand items consigned direct to other areas, we found that we were able to effect this at a surprisingly low cost, perhaps $40 million. This also had the effect ofmaking our lists look a cleaner and more straightforward affair.14. We had to admit some compromises in the way of accepting aprospective reduction of our stocks, more particularly oil and certain foods,where, however, there was admittedly a good deal to be said for the Americanargument. The old question of the coastal vessels, which there had been pressure on us to agree in advance to take over for cash at the end of the war, was satis-factorily settled on the financial side, only to come unstuck on the allocation side a bad business, due to a blunder for which our Shipping Mission was not responsible, which will, I hope and believe, come right in the end. The provisionof the necessary Lend-Lease finance, which is all we could concern ourselves with at this stage, does not, it must be remembered, always guarantee a correspondingallocation of supply, for example in the case of meat where we may have difficultylater on in getting from the Combined Food Board the full amount for which, ifwe can get it, we made sure that a Lend-Lease appropriation would be available.Subject to these qualifications, in every case our Missions were sufficientlysatisfied with the treatment they received not to think it necessary to call in further assistance or appeal to the Main Committee.15. No doubt this was partly due to the better and more expansiveatmosphere which the Quebec directive and the statement of our case had created.But it should not be overlooked what great credit is due for the result to thequality and skill of our Washington Missions and the standing they have acquiredwith their American colleagues. After an intermittent experience of Washingtonextending over the whole of the Lend-Lease period, I venture to say that we havenever had a more brilliant and effective team than were assembled there this autumn under the captaincy of Mr. Ben Smith. There was not a weak spot. Ifit is not impertinent of me to say so, the present members of the British supply council have been serving the State in exhausting and exacting conditions witha mental and moral stamina which is beyond all praise. Without any doubt itis there that the credit is due. Mr. Harry White remarked to me one day :&quot;I think Whitehall has no conception of what the chaps you send out here areup against.&quot; Washington is a place frantic with frustration in every quarter.It is all very well to stick it for a few weeks, seeking daily comfort from the familiar adage of the British Ambassador three-quarters of a century ago (was it Lord Lyons?), who said, that in Washington it is not,a question of how much
you can do but how much you can stand. But a saintly patience and a strongcharacter are required to persist for months with a clear head and without lossof temper. Yet our fellows manage, not only to keep their heads above theencircling flood of personal and political and departmental jealousies andindecisions and uncertainties which never are and never can be resolved orfinalised, but also, so it seemed to me, to have gained, as time goes on, a genuinelyincreasing affection for those who torment them so, friendship and exasperationadvancing hand in hand So may a bird of passage record with particularadmiration and respect and grateful thanks the names of Halifax, Ben Smith,Macready,, Self, Brand, Lee, Goschen, Opie, Maclay, Hart, Hambro, Archer,Penson, Hutton, Roll, Helmore, Symon, Wilkinson and Stevens.16. The second of the influences mentioned in Section 2 was the objectiveaccepted in F.E.A. of the progressive contraction of Lend-Lease and the progressive expansion of Reciprocal Aid, which had its origin in the UnitedStates Treasury criterion that Lend-Lease aid was excessive if it led to our gold and dollar reserves rising from the figure of nil, at which they stood in April1941 (when Lend-Lease began) to anything materially above 1 billiondollars. This Treasury criterion, which was a unilateral pronouncement neveraccepted&apos;by us, ante-dated the entry of the United States into the war and thegrowth of our overseas liabilities. Nevertheless, it had been pressed for morethan three years, and it was only after Mr. Morgenthau&apos;s visit to London inthe late summer of 1944 and his conversations with the Prime Minister and theChancellor of the Exchequer, which greatly impressed him, that the United states treasury Department were of a mind to depart from it. This, however, was not enough.. For meanwhile the doctrines, originally based on the above criterion,had acquired an independent life of their own and a complicated but coherentbody of dogma had been built up, which, in matters of detail, remained to theend our greatest practical obstacle. Vice and virtue had to have their positionsreversed in the F.E.A. Commandments, a matter not to be accomplished in thetwinkling of an eye, and right up to our last sub-Committee Meeting in washington one was met by genuine well-wishers with the reply that that whatone was proposing would be all very well if the opposite principle had not beenestablished a year before. The very fact that this resistance was derived from what was in original purpose upright, being in mere accordance with instructions from above and in no way the child of ill-will or jealousy, made it all the more difficult to overcome.17. Nevertheless, we can fairly claim that by the end of the negotiationsthis heresy had been rooted out and that the avowed purpose of F.E.A. hence-forward is to increase, and not abate, the scope of Lend-Lease assistance, witha view to strengthening our general reserves so far as is possible within the legallimitations of the Act and without risk of giving rise to plausible (and, I would add, unplausible) criticisms in the press and in Congress, when, in the nearfuture, the Lend-Lease Act comes up for renewal and, a little later on, newappropriations under it have to be voted.18. Unfortunately the outcome of our negotiations measured in hard cashfell considerably short of the change of mind and heart, and must be deemed, tothis extent, unsuccessful. Mr. Morgenthau and Mr. Stettinius (Mr. Crowley,though quite well disposed in principle, never attained the same level of con-consciousness of what it was all about, his ear being so near the ground that he was out of range of persons speaking from an erect position) were fully convincedthat it was both advisable and desirable that new and special relief should begiven us to the extent of some $400 to $500 million. Mr. Morgentlmu was determined at the outset to secure for us something of this order; foughtvaliantly to the end; and, being only too conscious of defeat, was appreciative,I think, that no useless word was said to rub the disappointment in. He was always open to hear new suggestions which might meet the case; but, in the lightof your telegrams, I judged it better to refrain from any of the larger ideas whichmight trench on what is in hand for the purposes of Stage III.
19. In the end, our major proposals under this head fell through for thereasons explained below, and we had to be content with building up what wecould from a variety of minor items as follows : (i) New ridings on Lend-Lease eligibility [definite).Oil ................       ......Ocean freights    ...       ...       ...       ...Food items ...N.A.A.F.I. (including food)     ......Emergency housing Raw materialsEquipmentHousesSundry items for the Dominions and India (australian -lia 7, New Zealand 1, India 11)   ...Maize (in lieu of Argentine supplies) ...(ii) Reimbursement of old capital items (definite)Definite(iii) Contingency Lend-Lease Funds for Capital Equip-ment Contingency Funds for Dominions and IndiaUltimate Lend-Lease proportion of Indian rolling-stock   ...       ...       ...       ...       ...        perhaps(iv) New rulings on Lend-Lease eligibility (not yet finally determined and still problematical).Freights on non-Lend-Lease Government cargo      ...Sundry items for Crown Colonies     ...       ...Lend-Lease proportion of machine tools for United- &quot;  Kingdom(v) Reimbursement  of  old  capital  items   (still  under examination)(vi) Relief to Reciprocal Aid by taking food-stuffs off the list either by their action or by ours (still under examination)million.48147142810*50*1940t230512812815perhaps  worthwith    luck    amaximum     of20Very uncertain4611720. All this, however, is not worth its full face value. The direct cashrelief, excluding (vi) above, is likely to work out ultimately at about 1200 million more or less, against which we shall have sacrificed about $40 million by taking-items off Lend-Lease to secure export freedom (this, however, I reckon a cheapprice, which might have been much higher). Indirect financial aid (emergencyhousing, maize and deferred recoveries for capital goods) should be worthanother $100 million. If we can manage to get food-stuffs taken off reciprocal aid, which we understand Mr. Crowley and F.E.A. would welcome if a way canbe found, $46 million can be added to the direct cash relief. The right approach to this needs immediate and careful thought.21. The relaxation of Lend-Lease eligibility in favour of emergencyhousing deserves a special mention of grateful appreciation. We had noexpectation of this when we left London, but we managed to argue successfullythat no form of aid was likely to commend itself more sympathetically to the peoples of both our countries. It certainly represents a stretching on their partof the strict interpretation of the Lend-Lease Act, and we must be careful, inavailing ourselves of it, not to go beyond a reasonable gloss on what is properly* Not necessarily a relief to our reserves, since if we could not have obtained these itemson Lend-Leaae, we should probably have had to go without.f At United States Prices, excluding freight, but freight will also be lent-leased ifshipment is on American vessels. At Argentine prices 17 also excluding freight. Thisrelieves our Argentine liability but does not increase our dollars.
&quot;temporary&quot; or &quot;emergency&quot; or &quot;replacement of bombed-out houses.&quot; Itwas still uncertain when I left Washington how far suitable types of pre-fabricated structures would be obtainable. But I understand that the represen-tatives of the Ministry of Works have been successful in discovering a suitabletype and that we can now hope for the delivery of 30,000 houses in the course of1945, which should prove a very helpful supplement to our own programme. i suggest that the attention of the Minister of Education might be directed to obtaining under this provision second-hand temporary structures suitable for emergency schools, which may be available in large quantity from the surplusstocks of the United States Administration and would probably be reckoned up against the Lend-Lease appropriation at a very moderate price.22. Since several of the items catalogued above would have fallen outside,and have been additional to, Mr. Morgenthau&apos;s proposed relief of $400-500million, I feel that we have fallen f200 million short of our best and justifiablehopes.  The reasons for this are to be found in a chapter of bad luck as follows : 23. There were from the start two alternative means of giving us what we wanted, and in the end we fell between the two stools. The first expedient was to restore off-shore sugar and civilian tobacco to the Lend-Lease eligibility which hadbeen allowed to these items in the first phase of Lend-Lease. Sugar alwayspresented difficulties from our point of view as well as theirs. Existing contracts of ours in United States dollars, but in the Caribbean, not in the United States,were involved. But a further obstacle came, I think, from the current shortageand the prospective still greater shortage of sugar available for civilian con-sumption in United States. It was, moreover, this same obstacle, namely the reluctance to supply on Lend-Lease any article of civilian consumption where itcould be represented that Lend-Lease was operating to the disadvantage of theAmerican consumer, which stood in the way of our getting tobacco back into the list. This item presented no technical difficulties whatever. At the beginning ofour conversations both Mr. Morgenthau and Mr. Harry White expressly declaredthemselves in favour. At that moment, cigarettes mysteriously disappeared fromall the drugstores although supplies, perhaps falling slightly, remained at about60-70 per cent, above pre-war. I do not believe things went so far that anyonewas ever actually without a cigarette. Everyone, however, from the Presidentdownwards, immediately concluded that it became out of the question to lend-lease civilian tobacco. It was useless to argue that lend-leasing the tobacco wouldnot make the smallest difference to the volume of supplies we should receive, wdiichwere already contracted for and set aside. It was useless to point out that, ifthere was a shortage, it was a shortage not of leaf, of which there was eighteen months&apos; supply in stock, but of labour and packaging for cigarettes, aggravated by bad distribution, and that what we wanted was not cigarettes, but leaf. these were subtleties, we were told, far beyond the comprehension of Congress or thepossibility of explanation to the public. The unfriendly press was already showingpathetic cartoons of Uncle Sap reduced to a state of nervous breakdown throughbeing deprived by a leering Britisher of his daily pack of 20. There cannotbe any doubt that the unlucky synchronisation of our discussions with thisspontaneous and unheralded outbreak of cigarette hoarding cost us f 100,000,000.24. This is an unattractive aspect of American habit. But what is morealarming is the ea.se with which policy can be deflected by irresponsible commentwildly off any recognisable mark. This is partly a result of the extremesensitiveness of civil servants, right down the line, to unfounded and calumniouscriticism by columnists, of which they may be at any time the personal victimwithout effective redress. On my last clay Laughlin Currie, the civil service headof Lend-Lease, sought to explain and justify to me the difficulties he had beenputting in our way, some of which he knew I had thought unnecessary, by showingme an issue of The American, a weekly of Mr. Hearst&apos;s, about to appear withnumerous charges of alleged Lend-Lease abuses without a vestige of foundation,of a character which we should no more ask than the Americans would concede.This only shows, I replied, how vain it is to protect yourself by refusing reason-able measures when the grounds on which you are attacked invariably relate toalleged crude acts of quite a different order which neither you nor we have evercontemplated; to which he rejoined that the Lend-Lease Administration hadsurvived unscathed so far precisely because it had been able to show that everyplausible charge made against it was based on falsehood. Shortly before, I mayadd, in a nation-wide radio address during the campaign, Mr. Dewey himself had gone out of his w7ay to denounce Mr. Currie by name as a crypto-communist
who had been investigated by the Dies Committee, contrary to the facts andwithout a vestige of evidence, on no better ground than that he had been oneof the original group of New-Dealers, whose services the President had alwaysretained, and was also believed to be an intimate of the Vice-President,Mr. Wallace. I often had to complain, as a consequence of all this, that I wasturned down not only when there was a good reason, but also, just as likely, fora reason which everyone admitted to be bad; and that it was hard luck to becaught both ways.25. One certainly learnt the value of our excellent system of professionalscape-goats, known as Ministers, with skins thickened by experience or naturalendowment, whose duty it is to suffer vicariously for the sins of all the administra-tive tribe. American officials are open to press abuse and Congressional criticism.Yet they are without any real responsibility or adequate opportunity to reply;and it saps their nerve. This lesson was reinforced by another experience. Oneof the last matters, on which with characteristic willingness to take troubleField-Marshal Dill concerned himself very shortly before his death, was to arrange a meeting of the Combined Chiefs of Staff to give me an opportunity to explain the nature of the financial burdens we had assumed, so that the American ServiceChiefs might better understand that our requests for the relief of man-powerwere not made without good reason. General Marshall, who presided, followedmy remarks with a discourse, only indirectly relevant to what I had said, onthe theme that there was scarcely a General or an Admiral present who, with little or no experience of such a situation, might not find himself faced at any time with the task of defending his executive acts before a Congressional Committee,and that it was essential for us Britishers to understand that fact if we wereto appreciate rightly what might from time to time befall us.26. Escaping from this long digression, I return to the other alternativeby which we might have been given what we wanted. When the United Statesfirst came into the war they were, as is well known, fatally deficient in certain types of aircraft, which were coming forward to our order as a result of our havingspent about 2 billion dollars, which was almost the whole of our gold reserves,in building up the American Munitions Industries from small&apos;&apos;beginnings. Wetherefore agreed to transfer to them a useful quantity of the aircraft which wehad ordered and paid for. On the first occasion, when a matter of some$80 million was involved, they very properly reimbursed us. On the secondoccasion, which was arranged between Air Chiefs without waiting to formalisethe financial provisions (the Arnold-Portal Agreement), when aircraft, which hadcost us more than $200 million of our pre-Lend-Lease reserves, was transferred, we expected a similar reimbursement. This time, however, the United States war department decided just not to pay, and the United States Treasury did not pressthem to do so. Sir Frederick Phillips never accepted this position or agreed toit in any way. After he had vainly presented the bill on several occasions, it was put into cold storage with hope that a better opportunity might come later. Therewere also further similar but smaller items of later date, due to our agreeing, totransfer certain munitions which had cost us cash dollars to the United states at their request to help them fulfil their protocol obligations to Russia. Thesebrought - our total claims to the order of $250 million. The United Statescontention is, presumably, that we either should give them these munitions asreciprocal aid (which, however, did not exist as an agreed arrangement at thedate of the major transaction) or. should regard them as replaced in kind by aircraft and other supplies which we have received subsequently on Lend-Lease.Nevertheless, until we have agreed to one or other of these alternatives, the UnitedStates cannot put either of them into force by unilateral decision and, meanwhile,there can be little doubt that they owe us the money. They can, of course, at anytime force us to waive our claims by making this a condition of further Lend-Lease assistance; and, in all the circumstances, we could not object to this verystrenuously. If, on the other hand, they are looking for ways to help us, here,on the face of it, was an easy means.27. Mr. Morgenthau began by showing considerable irritation at the revival of a claim which reminded him unpleasantly of a phase of shabby behaviour, theoccasion of some friction at the time between Sir Frederick Phillips and himself,which he much preferred to forget. At a later stage, however, when it appeared that it would be very difficult to fulfil those hopes on our part which he hadencouraged,  he was, I understand,  sufficientlv magnanimous to change his[29006] - &quot; c
attitude (partly, I guess, under the influence of Mr. Harry White, who gave me the impression from the start that he thought this an easier way out than the alternatives). F.E.A. definitely favoured this solution which, from their point ofview, was much preferable to restoring difficult items to the Lend-Lease list. TheState Department was of the same opinion. Accordingly the United states members of the main Committee, namely, Mr. Morgenthau, Mr. Stettinius andMr. Crowley, referred-the claim, so we were informed, to the War Department,out of whose funds the claims would have to be met. We were not made privyto the American discussions behind the scenes, but I have reason to believe thatthe United States members of the Committee were genuinely disappointed at the outcome and felt quite bad about it. For the War Department referred the matter to their lawyers, who ruled that the appropriations out of which these claims mighthave been met had now expired, so that nothing could be done without askingCongress for a new and specific appropriation for the purpose. Mr. Lovett, the assistant Secretary of the War Department, informed the MorgenthauCommitttee that his Department did not think it opportune or politic to ask for:such an appropriation at the present time, a decision which was formally conveyed&apos;to us by Mr. Morgenthau. Mr. Harry Hopkins, in private conversation, expressed a doubt whether a certain lack of sympathy in the War Department (which we.never had the same opportunity to penetrate with the full force of our case aswe had with the civilian departments and which is, moreover, along with the navy department, the stronghold of the less friendly elements) did not play a part.But Mr. Oscar Cox, counsel to F.E.A. and lately Assistant Attorney-General, told me that he felt little doubt that the ruling was formally correct. Whether, allthe same,. there may not have been some way round, we shall never know. I have thought it advisable to put this incident on record to the best of my unstanding of what occurred; but, as will be seen, it is based, in part, on conjecture.28. This was not the only issue on which at the last moment we were defeated by the lawyers, with whom every American Department is infested. ASub-Committee, consisting mainly of lawyers, recommended that we should beallowed retrospective Lend-Lease facilities for certain oil and shipping itemsworth about $30,000,000, and this was approved by the main Committee. on my last day in Washington I was informed by Mr. Crowley that some additionallawyers had found this to be impossible on account of a principle of law, whichsounds very odd, that F.E.A. cannot take over an existing liability from anotherparty but can only assume a newly created liability. Surely the plague of1lawyers in Washington is a worse plague of Egypt than Pharaoh ever knew.It is only by a rare and lucky coincidence that what is administratively sensibleis also lawful. The late Lord Hewart should have visited Washington to discover what the substitution of administrative law for administrativediscretion means in practice. The place only carries on at all because of the widereserve of discretionary power which becomes vested in the President in time ofwar. and what will happen when peace returns, with all its complications, heavenonly knows.29. There was, however, a further contributory cause, in my opinion, for out failure to win the missing $200 million. The strengthening of our reserves hadnot entered into the Quebec conversation, and the force of our case under this head, and probably even its existence, never reached the President. He had, i feel sure, no effective word of our proceedings until we were almost at the lastlap of our course. Mr. Harry Hopkins, consulted at the outset, decided that itwould cause difficulties if Mr. Morgenthau were to find that any reports werereaching the President except from himself. Mr. Morgenthau has been criticised in some quarters for not keeping the President in closer touch with our discussionsfrom the beginning. But, in fact, the Presidents complete preoccupation withthe Election campaign and its immediate political consequences made thisinevitable; besides which, Mr. Morgenthau has easier access to his presence than to his mind. Anyhow, the necessary word, to Mr. Crowley to do his best tostrengthen our reserves and not to be unduly timid never came. On the contrary,an impression of the Presidents mind, which produced a quite opposite tendency,reached Mr. Crowley and ran right through F.E.A., namely, that the Presidentwished nothing to be done which could be represented in Congress as involvingany present change in the Lend-Lease set-up and practice. The consequences ofthis are dealt with further below.30. So, in the end, we were disappointed of our best hopes and duly fellbetween the two stools. But we put up a good fight and can claim as consolationthat the half-measures (or kittens) we brought home from what came to be known
as the Chapter III cats were all a-bonus over and above the expectations we setout with instructions to realise when we left Whitehall. I would like to mention the keenness and skilled aid of Mr. Lee and Mr. Goschen in the pursuit, without which tens of millions less dollars would have been recovered.31. There is also the thought that the atmosphere left behind is one inwhich our American friends feel that they have done less for us than they intended; which may be better for future discussions than if, in retrospect, therewas * a suspicion m their minds that they had allowed us to overreach them.Mr., Harry White and Mr. Oscar Cox, in particular, were emphatic in private conversation in attaching much more importance to a good settlement in stage III than to anything we could settle now. They were constantly urgingme to be content now with the least that would do, and not to press for anything which might have the effect, even indirectly, of prejudicing the later discussions.Their own policy throughout was dictated by this thought, acting, as they believed, in our interests. And the same lies, I think, behind the Presidentstactics, as, in what follows, I surmise them to have been. I never had reason to doubt the basic friendliness, the intention to help and the genuine frankness of advice of all the American officials with whom I was in touch. I would particu,-;larly mention Mr. Harry White for the unvarying fairness and helpfulness whichhe showed as Chairman in his own aloof and independent way, and the intimateadvice, the truest to be had in Washington, on which I could rely in case of need;and Mr. Dean Acheson for what I believe that he did, without confessing it orblabbing in the too frequent Washington way, behind the scenes.32. If there is one wrinkle worth handing on to my successors, which I havepicked up after spending nearly a year out of the last four stepping like a catover the hot tiles of Washington, it is this. Remember that, in.a negotiationlasting weeks, the situation is entirely fluid up to almost the last moment. Every-thing you are told, even with the greatest appearance of authority and decision,is provisional, without commitment, &quot; thinking out loud,&quot; a kite, a trial balloon.There is no orderly progression towards the final conclusion. Thus you mustnot believe that a man is not your loyal friend, merely because he has raisedfalse hopes, or run out on you, or even, from a strict point of view, double-crossedyou. Equally, do not become faint-hearted against opposition. You may beable, when things look worst, to gain a sudden reversal in your favour. AH thisis a process, unfamiliar to .us, of discovering by open trial and error what will go and what will not. I liken them to bees who for weeks will fly round in alldirections with no ascertainable destination, providing both the menace of stingsand the hope of honey; and at last, perhaps because the queen in the WhiteHive has emitted some faint, indistinguishable odour, suddenly swarm to a singlespot in a compact, impenetrable bunch.33. I come finally to the third of the dangerous tendencies of $ 2, namely the temptation to use Lend-Lease to satify trade rivalry by hampering our exporttrade. To avert this was our biggest political problem, yet the purpose mosteasily accepted on its merits by the officials with whom we were dealing. Wehad no difficulty in obtaining acceptance in the Treasury, in the State Depart-ment, in the F.E.A. and in the White House of the proposition that we oughtto receive the widest possible export freedom at the earliest possible date. Thetask was to find a formula to achieve this which would escape political criticism,and, above all, to find an agreed procedure for communicating the substance ofthis formula to our own exporters on the one hand and to the American public and pressure groups on the other.34. I affirm with emphasis that there is no ground for supposing any desireor policy on the part of the three departments with which we were dealing to hamper our export trade. On the contrary, they are as conscious as we are that our recovery of trade is the only way out and is almost as necessary to thesolution of their problems as of ours. We can safely assume this (with a reserve in respect of the Commerce Department of which I have no evidence either way)in all our future dealings. Indeed, the United States Treasury (as was also thecase in Canada) was much more inclined to complain that we were taking advan-tage of Lend-Lease (or Mutual Aid) to send less exports than we could to UnitedStates (or Canada). On the other hand, their political timidities in relationto pressure groups, other elements hostile to the Administration in and out of[29006] c 2
Congress, and the chatter of columnists was infuriating; and, m my privateopinion, largely unnecessary, as I think the final outcome went some way towardsproving. Surely this was a nettle, which, if it was grasped, would cease to stingand soon wither. Nothing of what I subsequently experienced, as related below,led me to change this conviction.35. As a result of their so easily accepting the main proposition, we begangaily enough. We, on our side, discarded and never produced the more timidproposals we had prepared beforehand during our first week (and we largelyowe our avoidance of a mistake here to the wise insistence of Sir Henry Self).They, on their side, bent their best wits to find words which would give us inpractice virtually complete freedom. Then silence and a veil descended, and wecould learn nothing for certain from our opposite numbers. We comfortedourselves that, if the Election turned out well, the mists would disappear. exactly the opposite happened. After the Election, timidities mysteriously multiplied(on other parts of our front also, as well as on this). From the best possible sourceI was warned that dark forces, of which I knew nothing, were bringing to bearin the neighbourhood of the White House. Mr. Morgenthau complained to methat advices from sources he could not identify were reaching the President. Inever learnt what the mysterious scare was which ran through every corridorof that Byzantine Court &quot;within a few days after their electoral triumph. Butthe result was that things began to slip.36. The President gave a press conference in which he pretended to beunaware that anything of the smallest importance or novelty was going on inour discussions. He even went so far as to maintain that he had no idea whatwas meant by Stage (or, as the Americans call it, Phase) II about which thejournalists were enquiring he had never heard the expression, so he said.Nothing whatever is happening, was the impression he sought to produce, weare all just churning along as usual; which was certainly a second-degree method,so to speak, of lulling suspicion in the minds of the well-informed sleuths present.Yet he did, in fact, get away with it.37. This gave the cue to Mr. Crowley; though the precise role which heplayed at this time, especially during a vital week when he purported to beabsent from Washington, I cannot say. After, as I gathered, considerable contro-versy with Mr. Acheson and Mr. Morgenthau, who, in face of this cloud on thehorizon, though no bigger than a man&apos;s hand, had to yield in the end, Mr. Crowleyannounced at our very last formal meeting that our whole programme whichhad been discussed hitherto on the basis or beginning on the 1st January was put back to the indeterminate date of V-E day. The same afternoon I was told on his authority that we must not even assume that the export arrangements could be considered as agreed after V-E day and that Mr. Crowley also consideredhimself free to revise, as he thought fit, any item in the non-munitions programme which had been already accepted at the official level. There was also trouble andinconclusive conversations about Ministers at home being allowed to make anyworthwhile statement to Parliament. In short, I was put on notice that theywere, or might be, running out on us all along the line.38. This was after the final meeting of the Main Committee from whichwe were entitled to suppose that we had had a decision. There was, therefore,nothing to be done except to see behind the scenes all our friends in high placesone after another and more than once, and beg them to rally round. (And even so I got in temporary trouble with Mr. Morgenthau at one point because, forthe excellent reason that he was (as usual) absent from Washington, I had not shown my draft of a statement to him first but had already cleared it withMr. Harry Hopkins and Mr. Stettinius!) Fortunately Mr. Crowley hadaltogether over-reached himself, and was compelled under severe pressure fromhis colleagues to recede back to the position which had been accepted by the main committee. It ended in a recommendation to the President signed by all three off them (Mr. Morgenthau, Mr. Stettinius and Mr. Crowley). the text of whichI have not seen, but which gave us, I was led to understand, the certainty of complete export freedom after V-E day and, by administrative action thesubstance of it from the 1st January next. In spite of this episode (and otherpeculiar information which I need not relate) I believe that our TammanyPolonius, Mr Crowley, neither meant nor wished us any harm, but conceivedthat he was playing the Presidents political game on the principle of ooliticalsafety first. 1 1
39. My own conversation with the President, whilst it convinced me thathe never intended things to go so far, nevertheless indicated how easily Poloniuscould have come to believe that he was doing what was wanted. The Presidentdeclared to me without qualification that we must have our export freedom. he made no objection to a public announcement and accepted the position that Parlia-ment must have this. But he also made it clear that it must all be so expressed that he would be free to confirm that there would be no change whatever in thegeneral conditions of Lend-Lease before V-E day. He told me thai it was essential to prevent any premature raising of Lend-Lease issues in the presentlame-duck Congress, with which, he said, he might have considerable trouble.With the new Congress, he added, it would be another matter. We all know thatin these matters the President attaches primary importance to timing and thathe is generally right. He put it clearly to, me that from his point of view thetime is not now, but he was ready to go as far as possible to meet the dilemmathat from the point of view of Ministers in London the time is now. I had to draft poised between these two horns and to warn you of the inadvisability of altering words Which had been agreed with so much difficulty. (I did not troublethe President with the actual text, but he particularly enquired whether mr. Harry Hopkins had approved the wording, which fortunately I had hadan opportunity to correct with his help immediately before I saw the President.)40. Quite apart from any special warnings of trouble brewing somewhere,I can see strong justification in our own interests (and I am sure he so intendedit) for the Presidents caution, provided it was not pushed too far. In the courseof next year he may have to go to Congress three times on our financial behalf,first to obtain a renewal of the Lend-Lease Act, next to seek fresh appropriationsunder it, and finally (if all goes well) in connection with Stage III. Naturally atthis moment he wants to play the issue down and keep the waters smooth. Butthere was also another and perhaps more compelling reason for extreme care. Infact reconversion is proceeding in the United States much too fast to suit W.P.B.Strong efforts were being made, whilst I was in Washington, to retard this tendency, which was beginning to interfere seriously with the output of munitions.If there were to be any suggestion that British exporters were to be released fromrestrictions as from the 1st January, whereas the official date for reconversion inthe United States is V-E day, there would be no holding American manufacturers and W.P.B.&apos;s task would be dangerously aggravated.41. In fact we were successful in straddling the position. It was, indeed,only on the last afternoon, and as the result of strong assaults, that it was agreedto issue fairly full statements on both sides. In the result all fears were falsified.The reaction in Congress and in the responsible press was excellent; whereas anattempt at concealment or a more partial statement would, I am convinced, havebred suspicion and a swarm of utterly false stories. The handsome way in whichthe Americans at the eleventh hour met our views and the success which resultedleft for all of us a pleasant flavour in the air, which in the turmoil of the last week was becoming sullied;&quot; and we parted better and more intimate friends all roundthan before it.42. I find that I have left to the end any mention of what I believe to havebeen the decisive factor in our favour. The Quebec conversation and LordCherwell&apos;s initial steps with Mr. Morgenthau played an essential part in startingthe business along the right lines and with the right general directive. The MainStatement of our case caused a much needed enlightenment all down the line. Butthe real underlying reason why the wicket was so much easier than on previousvisits to Washington and why a better measure of success than London, perhaps,anticipated, was certain from the start, is the ever increasing and ever deepeningconviction in the minds of all responsible Americans that a strong Britain afterthe war is a vital, indeed an indispensable, requirement of American policy. Ihave a very strong impression that the recent course of events has somehow hadthe effect of causing this old notion suddenly to hit the sub-consciousness of theAmerican people with the impact of certitude. It has become an unspokenpremiss, which, whatever the momentary, superficial reasons to the contrary, cannotbe questioned. Further acquaintance with Russia does not increase intimacy orconfidence. The illusion of China has faded. Central Europe is a dreaded cavernI of misery and chaos. The Governments of Western Europe are wished well butare doubtful quantities. The little Latin nephews are all very well but not whatUncle hoped. There is nothing to be found reliable or homely in the habitableglobe outside Britain and the British Commonwealth This, to-day, is America&apos;sdeepest, least alterable conviction a sure rock upon which, whatever may appear
on the surface, we can build with safety They want to be told, not that we havesacrificed more than we can afford, but that we are stable, healthy andcompetitively strong. If, therefore, we can control our suspicions, even though they have some foundation, and our exasperations, for which there will be everyexcuse in the world, if we can overlook their inevitable jealousies andunwarrantable aggrandisements and indefensible intrusions, and if they can dothe like, as I think they can, in respect of our not less objectionable faults, the onlybrotherhood by which civilisation can be held together, already sealed with blood,will become in due time a decent, commonplace, wnrkadav affair, which is taken for granted, as anything must be which is to be good and durable. On notemptation or provocation or pretext must we allow ourselves to stray, even inthought or hypothesis, along another path than this.43. And having said all that, I should like to return to earth and addsomething on a lower level which may look like the opposite of the above, but infact is the safe means to the same end; though it might be more pertinent to the separate report which I hope to make on the impressions I have formed aboutthe shape which the solution of our financial problem in Stage III might assume.44. . I have been designated this autumn to travel in North America seekinglarge-scale financial aid on the basis of a hard luck story about how we held the fort when we were almost alone, how we have conducted the war with the utmostfinancial imprudence, first to win it and then to shorten its duration in the interestsof all alike, with the result that we have not now very much left; and, moreover,apart from grounds of fairness requiring a more equal sharing of the burdens, itis in the general interest that the United Kingdom should emerge from thestruggle, not with a Pyrrhic victory, but economically and financially strong.This story can be based on vivid and unanswerable evidence; though I am not sure how far the story of our past effort would carry us if it were not supportedby the very strong conviction, upon which I have been dilating above, that our future, strength is an objective of major concern to the United States and to canada.45. Fortunately this same story, supported by the same underlyingconviction, will carry us up to a point through the financial difficulties of stage III up to a point exactly the same considerations apply as in Stage II.But only up to a point. There are enough hostile or critical elements in thecountries concerned to make it important that our friends, though in the majority,have a rock-bottom case to present. I notice already a tendency in the UnitedStates Treasury to enquire whether it is really necessary that we should continuesuch vast expenditures overseas after Germany has been defeated. I believe thatwe shall receive the support necessary to see us through those transitionaldifficulties which have been genuinely caused by what we suffered and accomplishedat the height of the danger and by the part which we shall be expected to play in the settlement; and that we shall receive it on terms which will not burdenthe future unduly. Our chief trouble will be to prevent the attachment of incon-venient strings. If once the suspicion gets abroad that the scale of the assistance we seek is partly caused by our undertaking, for reasons of power and prestige,new liabilities and responsibilities both beyond what we are able to support outof our own resources and also beyond what our Allies and Dominions are askingand expecting of us. these strings will multiply and toughen.46. Even to-day the United States Departments are on the brink of showingsigns of an implied right of interference into what we should wish&apos; to consider our own business. It was necessary to be continuously aware of this tendency andto take what precautions one could. A position can very easily arise when noprecautions will avail. In that case friction and ill-will are likely to occur betweenthe two countries which will undo the best hopes of the future. I am certainthat I shall have with me every British official who has any intimate experienceof &quot;Washington when I urge with vehemence that, in spite of their genuinegood-will and magnanimous aid to us, financial independence of the United states at the earliest possible opportunity should be a major aim of British policy. Thisis, indeed, ian indispensable condition of the right sort of workaday relationship.There are very few objects of policy beyond the demands of victory over the enemy to which that should be subordinated. A mighty Empire in financial leadingstrings to others will not be mighty at all, and we shall have sacrificed real powerto show and sham.
47. His Majesty&apos;s Ministers would, I think, do well to assume that we shallnot be freely or unconditionally assisted, except within a narrow field, to under-take foreign and imperial responsibilities at other people&apos;s expense for a sufficientlength of time to bring such policies to fruition. Because we have been able so tocontrive that we could wage the war as though money were no object, it will notbe safe to conclude that post-war policies or even Stage II policies can be safelyconducted that way. If the attempt is made, waste, ill-will and frustration areto be expected. There is a much more limited supply of cloth to cut our travellingcoat than what we wear at home.48. Following my previous precedent of getting one of our Statesman-orator-poets to provide me, Chancellor, with a peroration for the reports I write to you on board ship, I offer you, after the intensive experience of seeking propsdescribed above, a familiar line, written at a time of this country&apos;s adversity, butcontaining a moral very applicable to the next few years, especially for the holderof your office to enforce That we must stand unpropped, or be laid low.KEYNES.S.S. Nieuw Amsterdam.12th December, 1944.




</content>
</cab>
