<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/72/0 images: 2-32</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)) &quot;SECRET. COPY NO.C A B I N E T      41 (52).Meeting of the Cabinet to &quot;be held in.the Prime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons,to-day, Thursday, June 30th 1932, at 6.0 p.m.AGENDUM.STATEMENT BY THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER.(Signed) R.B. HOWORTH.Deputy Secretary,, Cabinet,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.50th June,  1932.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERN!0 EGRET. COPY NO.CABINET    41  (32)oCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held inthe Prime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons.,on Thursday, June 30 th, 1932, at p.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.    (in the Chair).The Right Hon. The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M. P., The Viscount Hailsham,Chancellor of the Exchequer. Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt. ,G.B.E. ,CM.G. ,M.P. ,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E.,M.C.,M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of LondonderryK.G.,M.V.O., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G0B0E0 ,DoSoOo ,D. S. C. ,M.P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O.,M.P., Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres-Monsell,G.B.E.,M.P.,First Lord ofthe Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,CB.E.,M.P. , Minister ofLaoour.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormshy-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.Mr. R.B. Howorth, C.B. ,CM.G., Deputy Secretary, Cahinet.
IRAQ.situation;.IN REGARD&apos;TO THEIRAQ LEVIES.ClixcL(PreviousReferenceCabinet37 (32)Conclusion3).1. With reference to the Conclusion mentionedin the margin, the SECRETARY OP STATE FOR THECOLONIES read to the Cabinet the following paraphrasetelegram which he had received from the HighCommissioner of Iraq.&quot;Dated 29th June, 1932.   Received in the&quot;Colonial Office at 8.55 p.m. on June 29th 1932,&quot;IMMEDIATE&quot;No. 241.&quot;Reference my telegram No. 239.    My advice&quot;has &quot;been accepted by Mar Shimun, who has issued&quot;instructions to Levies to continue in obedient&quot;and loyal service until receipt of League&apos;s&quot;reply to national petition of 17th June.    If,&quot;after League&apos;s reply had &quot;been received Levies&quot;wish to withdraw their service, their discharge&quot;is to he effected gradually and in accordance with&quot;the orders of Commanding Officer;    they are for-&quot;bidden to resign in a &quot;body.   At conference ofAssyrian leaders which he is summoning for 5th&apos;iJuly, Mar Shimun will advocate cancellation   of&quot;proposed national concentration and will advise that&quot;decision of League of Nations be calmly awaited.&quot;Majority of levies, many of whom have already &quot;been&quot;disarming, are expected to ohey Mar Shimun* s&quot;exhortation to remain in the service after suitable&quot;guarantees have been taken from them.   Those still&quot;(?wishing) to resign will be permitted to take their&quot;discharge gradually.
&quot;I do not think that this change of front,&quot;which has come just in time, would have &quot;been&quot;&quot;brought about without the presence of British&quot;troops.&quot;I was visited yesterday afternoon by the&quot;Acting Prime Minister and Minister of the Interior&quot;and the Iraqi Director General of Police, who were&quot;in a great state of perturbation.     They informed&quot;me that thirty-six Assyrian police in posts in the&quot;newly administered territories in the Worth had&quot;threatened to resign oh the 1st July;    their example&quot;would, it was feared be followed by nearly 300&quot;others occupying key positions in Kurdistan.&quot;It would be premature to say that the danger&quot;is passed;    I am, however, full of hope that&quot;situation is developing on the right lines,HUMPHRYS.&quot;The Cabinet noted, with satisfaction, the great-improvement in the situation with regard to the Iraq,Levies which had resulted from the action which had beentaken.
LAUSANNE 2. At the request of the Lord President of the CouncilERi:o!CEo the CHANCELLOR OS1 THE EXCHEQUER outlined to the Cabinet^us the proceedings of the Lausanne Conference to date,&quot;erenceIclusio^(2?^ The Conference had started with the customarygeneralities.    On June 17th the Conference adopted theDeclaration relative to the suspension of payments duringthe Conference? the credit for this achievement largelyrested with the British Delegation, which had initiatedthe proposal.The Conference then turned to real business, and difficulties at once began to shew themselves.    Conversationstook place between British and French Ministers, and theformer were greatly disappointed to find that the attitudeof France was much less in accord with British views thanthe British Delegation had assumed would be the case, fromthe hopeful and encouraging reports which had beenreceived from the British Embassy in Paris.   M. GermainMartin, the French Minister of Finance, was a professormuch given to oratory, but lacking any sense of reality:M. Herriot feigned ignorance of financial matters, but was quite sure that the French people would never assent to total cancellation of reparations.    Neither of the french ministers appeared to have any market sense at all.Day after day passed without any appreciable progress being made, and while close touch was kept with theGermans, it was felt that the real difficulties would be with the French rather than with the Germans.    The latter were very helpful and conciliatory than might have been expected from a German Government of the Right, and, indeed,were at least as forthcoming as Dr. Bruning*s Governmenthad been.
When it became clear that it would not &quot;be possible toshake the French in the Anglo-French conversations,  the.prime Minister decided that the time had come to adopta firm and vigorous line.    The French were accordinglytold that their proposals were not such as the Chancellorof the Exchequer could possibly entertain! that theConference had reached a critical point? that either asettlement must be made9 or all hope of any settlementmust be abandoned.    Influence was brought to bear on the belgians who were following their customary role of the&quot;honest broker&quot;i in the result the French Delegationbecame alarmed, and formulated their proposals in writing.They were then advised to enter into discussions withthe Germans, and, while great care was taken to avoid any definite commitment, an indication was given thatthe British Delegation would be prepared to givefavourable consideration to any arrangement   which theFrench might be .able to reach with the Germans.The Franco-German conversations   began with the usuallong general speeches.    The German Finance Minister, GrafSchwerin von Krosigk, opened with a speech of two hours&apos;duration, and M. Germain Martin desired a day in which toprepare his reply.    It became clear from the slow progress that was being made that the United kingdom delegation might have to leave for the Ottawa Conferencebefore any conclusions were reached.   Moreover, the FrenchDelegates were preparing to return home for financial discussions in the Chamber of Deputies.   Experience hadshewn that whenever a Delegation went home, it returned toLausanne with much stiffer views as a result of the homecontacts.
The Prime Minister had then interviewed&apos; hi. Herriotand Herr von Papen?  the former was much agitated at what he represented as the intransigent behavioux&apos; ofthe&apos; Germansi    Herr von Papon, on the other hand,adopted the attitude that he did not very much mindwhether the Conference failed or not.The United Kingdom Delegation had ascertained from a most reliable source that when M. Herriothad returned to Paris he had formed the definiteopinion that cancellation of reparations was inevitable and had persuaded the French Cabinet to give him a free hand,  subject to one or two conditions? namely,either that Germany should pay a lump sum for thereconstruction of Europe, or that France should obtain political and economic advantages to set against her lost reparations.   M. Herriot was understood to have returned to Lausanne preparedto do business with the Germans on this basis? butHerr von Papen had raised the question of&quot;compensation&quot; with reference to Austria and central Europe, and M. Herriot feared that france might be saddled with further obligations, withnothing to shew in return for her sacrifices.
- The British Delegation had, in the meantime,&quot;been at work on proposals, and had formulated a scheme,the &quot;basis of which was a lump sum payment by Germany towardsEuropean reconstruction.On Tuesday, June 28th. the Prime Minister had seen M. Herriot and he (the Chancellor of the Exchequer)had had a discussion with Freiherr von Neurath.     Thelatter had explained that there had been no change in theGerman attitude.    It was, however, difficult to do any real business at meetings when the French Delegates were accompanied by an army of Experts.    Germany was quite preparedto make a contribution towards a settlement.   The meetinglasted all day and in the discussions on the political andeconomic side, the difficulty was that both the Germans andthe French persisted in confining themselves to vaguegeneralities.Subsequently discussions took place in regard to political questions, such as security, between the PrimeMinisters;    in regard to the economic questions between theMinisters of Trade and Industry:    and in regard to the&quot;forfait&quot; between the Finance Ministers.    Practically no progress was made at these discussions, and ultimately itwas decided to appoint a Committee of six persons, one from each of the Inviting Powers.    This Committee included M.Bonnet,a.Deputy   of the French Left Wing Party, who was favourable to cancellation, Graf Schwerin von Krosigk,Dr. Pirelli, M. Francqui and himself (the Chancellor of theExchequer).     The first meeting of the Committee was heldat 6 p.m. on Wednesday, June 29th. and within an hour theCommittee had agreed to accept the British scheme in principle and had begun to discuss the amount of the lump sum
The Chancellor of the Exchequer read to the Cabinetextracts from the draft scheme, and explained that under itreparations and war debts as between the European countries would be completely wiped out.     The German Government woulddeposit bonds with the Bank of International Settlements,these bonds would however only become operative when theforeignGerman Government1    loans had got on to a 5% basis, and theywould bear no interest or sinking fund charge until issued tothe public      In the event of a general debt cancellationthree-quarters of the bonds would be cancelled and theremaining quarter would be available for European recon-struction.     With regard to the amount of the bonds, it .had been ascertained that M. Bonnet had authority in the last resort to agree.to a sum of 4 milliards of   gold francs, andthat the German Delegation had authority also in the last resort to go up to a sum of 4 milliards of gold francs.     TheFrench would claim,in addition, that the amount involved inthe Hoover Moratorium should be covered, but they wouldprobably be prepared to give way on this point.Early in the discussions the German Delegate had raised an entirely new point, and had demanded as an indispensable-sable condition &amp;f Germany1s agreement that some &quot;aid&quot; shouldbe given towards maintaining the value of the mark.    This &quot;aid&quot;might, he had suggested, be provided in various ways, e.g.by the provision of credits for the Reichbank.    The GermanDelegate had also raised other points, as, for example, theattitude of the United States and the finality of any settle-ment that might be reached.    In regard to the latter, M.Bonnet had said that the French were prepared to regard thesettlement as final and definitive.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer added thatwhen he left Lausanne,  the discussions were still proceeding in regard to the amount of the &quot;bonds.,These discussions had &quot;been adjourned on v/wednesday night and on their resumption on Thursday at 11 a.m.  somehitch had occurred, as a result of which the PrimeMinister had requested him (the Chancellor of theExchequer) to return to Lausanne as soon as possible^ it seemed probable that the hitch was in connection withthe German demand for &apos; &quot;aid&quot;*The Chancellor of the Exchequer concluded byexpressing his belief that in the end a settlement,which would be of great value in restoringconfidence, would be effected at Lausanne.THE,LORD &quot; RESIDENT: OF THE COUNCIL, on behalf ofthe Cabinet, thanked the Chancellor of the exchequer uerfor his report on the Lausanne negotiations.
3.      THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER   informed the Cabinet that at 9.30. p.m. that evening he woulannounce in the House of. Commons the Governmentplan for the conversion of the whole of the5 per cent. War Loan.    It was vitally important that no hint of what was contemplated should bepublished before the New York Stock Exchangeclosed that evening.    The most profound secrecymust be maintained until his statement in theHouse of Commons was made.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER then read to the cabinet the terms of the statement to bemade in the House of Commons.   For this statementsee Appendix I.      *In congratulating the Chancellor of theExchequer on behalf of the Cabinet, theLord President of the Council said that theseproposals and a successful outcome of the lausanne Conference would constitute a most-helpful introduction to the Ottawa Conference,The Cabinet agreed  To take note that the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer would make his statement in regard to the conversion of the 5 percent. War Loan in the House of commons at 9.30 p.m. that evening, and that theHouse of Lords would be informed of theterms of this statement by the Leader ofthe House at the same time.
4.     With reference to the conclusion mentionedin the margin, THE LORD PRESIDENT OP THE COUNCILread to the Cabinet a personal letter which hehad received from the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs enclosing a copy of theDraft Declaration of the British DisarmamentPolicy as settled by the Cabinet at their meeting on June 27th, with the alterations in red which- had been made at Lausanne.   For the text ef the Declaration as altered at Lausanne,see Appendix II    0THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER informed the Cabinet that the Prime Minister was most anxious that nothing should be done which wouldin any way disturb the cordial relations whichhad been established by the British and Americandelegates at Geneva.   The alterations which hadbeen made in the Draft Declaration were notalterations of substance but were alterationsdesigned to remove any ground for the suggestionthat the document contained anything savouringof disparagement of President Hoover*s proposals.THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL thoughtthat there could be no possible objection to accept-ance of the amendments which had been- suggested bythe Prime Minister and his colleagues.  &quot;While itmust be for the Ministers at Lausanne and Geneva todetermine the position in regard to the Americans,there could be no doubt that as regards the Houseof Commons and public opinion in this Country itwas imperatively necessary that the BritishDeclaration should be published with the least possible delay.
-fTHE CABINET AGREED:-(1) To request the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Secretary ofState for Air to convey to thePrime Minister and his colleagues * -at Lausanne the views of the cabinet as to the great desirability of theDeclaration of British DisarmamentPolicy being announced in Parliamentsimultaneously with its publicationat Geneva with the least possible delay.(2) To approve the Draft Declaration ofBritish Disarmament Policy in the formset out in Appendix Ilto these conclusions.(3) That there should be attached to theDeclaration of British DisarmamentPolicy, when published, the Tableprepared by the Admiralty showing the eventual reduction in tonnage at presentpermitted to the British Commonwealthby the Washington and London NavalTreaties which would result fromthe British proposals.11.
*THE ELECTIONS      5&quot; Tne attention of the Cabinet was drawn in MALTA,to the recent telegrams which had passed befweedthe Governor of Malta and the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies relative to a proposal of the maltese Ministry to send a Deputation to london to discuss with the Secretary of State the(Previous language and constitutional questions,     ForReferenceCabinet these telegrams see Appendix111*37 (32) &apos;Conclusion 8) * In kis reply to the Governor, theF.d.Secretary of State had instructed the governor to make it plain that there could be no questionof any alteration in the policy which had been laid down by His Majesty&apos;s Government that thewhole language question had been dealt with by theissue of the Letters Patent, and that noproposal to alter those provisions could be enter-tained, nor could the passage of the Bill be delayed or any of its provisions withdrawn.     Inthese circumstances Ministers should be informedthat no useful purpose would be served by theirsending a Deputation,The Cabinet took note of,and approved, the action whichhad been taken by theSecretary of State for theColonies in regard to thismatter., Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.30th June, 1932o
APPENDIX I.2T23        .j?ive Per Cent. WarQuestion put, and agreed to.Lords Amendments to be further con-sidered upon Monday next.FIVE PER CENT. WAR LOAN(CONVERSION),ME. CHAMBERLAIN&apos;S STATEMENT.Motion made, and Question proposed,&quot; That this House do now adjourn.&quot; [Captain Alargesson.]The CHANCELLOR Of the EX-CHEQUER (Mr. Chamberlain): The Ad-journment of the House has been moved in order that I may, with hon. Members&apos;permission, announce the Government&apos;splan for the conversion of the War Loan.1 offer my apologies for interrupting thenormal business of the House, but I haveno option. The House has the right tobe the first to hear an announcement olthis character, and the hour of the even-ing at which such an announcement mustbe made is precisely determined for me by a consideration, on the one hand, of the  hours of business in America, and,on the other hand, of the minimum time which must be at the disposal of thePress to enable them to make the schemeknown and understood in the countryupon the following day.Talk of conversion has been in the airfor a long time, and naturally so, for ithas been growing increasingly obviousthat the War Loan at 5 per cent, was outof relation to the yield of other Govern-ment securities, &apos;and, moreover, for themaintenance of that old War-time rateattaching to so vast a body of stock andhanging like a cloud over the capitalmarket is a source of depression and ahindrance to the expansion of trade.Nevertheless the choice of a propermoment at which to launch so vast anundertaking is one which demands most careful and anxious consideration, andthe final decision to make this announce-ment to-night was only arrived at after anumber of alternatives had been examined and rejected.I may, perhaps, give the House someof the reasons which convinced me of thenecessity for prompt action. In the firstplace economy is an urgent matter, andthis scheme, effecting so great a reductionin our interest charges, is an essential element in any economy proposals. Inthe second place I anticipate that fromLoan (Conversion).        - 2124a general reduction in the level of in-terest charges great benefits should flowto industry, which will be enabled more easily to obtain such capital as it needs and to secure that capital on better terms. There is a great consensus ofopinion that the continued existence ofa vast body of British Government stockyielding a 5 per cent, return is an arti-ficial obstacle to a fall in interest rates to a lower level at which they would otherwise naturally stand.Thirdly, we are in the fortunate posi-tion that the relative merits of BritishGovernment securities, by comparisonwith all other investments, British andforeign, have never been more amplyrecognised by the world at large thanat this moment. That, as the House will realise, is a vital factor in the successof such an operation.Fourthly, while we are in a position tosecure immediately such important re-results as I have indicated, I do not con-sider that further delay would9.30 p.m. be   justified   either   by   theprospect of small additional savings or by any hope that the operation would become any easier with the lapse of time.The final and the strongest argument for immediate action is to be found inthe spirit of the country. After a long period of depression we have recoveredour freedom in monetary matters. Wehave balanced our Budget in the face of the most formidable difficulties, andwe have shown the strongest resistance of any country to the general troublesaffecting world trade. I am convincedthat the country is in the mood fox greatenterprises, and is both able and deter-mined to carry them through to a successful conclusion.Before I come to the particulars ofthis scheme there is one personal matter to which I should like to make refer-ence. It is well known that my predecessors-cessor, Lord Snowden, had hoped to un-dertake this operation last year, hadconditions been favourable, and in theFinance Bill introduced by the firstNational Government in September lasthe embodied a series of Clauses prepar-ing the way. Lord Snowden was de-prived of the satisfaction of carryinghis plans into effect, but I propose toavail myself in every detail of the pro-cedure provided in the Finance Act of30 Jotte 1932
2125Five Per Cent. War    HOUSE OF COMMONS      Loan (Conversion).212G[Mr; Chamberlain.]last year, which has rendered my taskeasier and introduced conditions morefavourable than would otherwise havebeen possible.In a few moments&apos; time a specialedition of the &quot; London Gazette&quot; willbe published. - It will contain a noticeintimating that the Government intend to repay the War Loan in cash on the1st December next to those holders whodecide to apply for repayment within three months from this date, but thenotice will also intimate that holders ofthe Loan are invited to continue in theLoan on altered conditions.It is my confident hope that the great mass of the holders will respond to the invitation. I am arranging for copiesof documents to be available to hon. Meni-bers in the Vote Office immediately onthe conclusion of my statement, and, forthis reason, I shall for the moment omitminor alterations, and shall confine my-self to a statement of the principalchanges in the terms of the continuedLoan. The dividend of the 1st december next must be paid at the rate of 5 percent, per annum, the rate payable underthe original prospectus, until the notice to repay becomes effective. Thereafter,beginning with the dividend payable on1st June, 1933, the rate of interest willbe 3^ per cent, per annum. Up to the1st December, 1952, five years later thanthe latest date for the repayment of theLoan under the original prospectus, theGovernment forgo all right to redeemthe Loan. After that date the Govern-ment reserve to themselves the right to repay the Loan, at any time, either ina single operation or by instalments.The existing arrangement under whichthe interest is paid without deduction of Income Tax at the source a specialprivilege which has proved itself a greatconvenience to an enormous number ofsmall holders will continue unchanged.I am bound by the terms of the pros-pectus of the 5 per cent. War Loan togive at least three months&apos; notice to re-deem, but in an operation of this immensemagnitude it is very desirable that weshould know as quickly as possible where we stand, and that we should have ampletime to concert such remaining measures as may be necessary. For this reason,but also because we recognise that the inevitable reduction in the rate of inter-est may, when it first comes, be seriouslyfelt in a number of cases, we offer a cashbonus at the rate of  1 for every  100of stock to all those holders who not later than 31st July, assent to the offerio continue in the Loan : this cash bonuswhich in the case of the ordinary investorwill not be liable to Income Tax, will bepaid to each holder within 14 days fromthe date of receipt of his effective assent.The House will desire to know whatsaving would be effected by this scheme.The saving in interest charge at whichwe aim by this conversion scheme is inthe region of  30,000,000 per annum. Inthe nature of things none of the savingcan be realised in this financial year, thecurrent expenditure of which will be un-affected by this operation. But the wholeof the ^saving will be realised in the year1933. It must, however, be rememberedthat the reduction of interest carries with it a reduction in the yield of Income tax and Surtax and, taking this into account,the net budgetary saving may be put at about  23,000,000 per annum.There are nearly 3,000,000 people whohold War Loan. Many of these have, Iexpect, but little experience in construinga complicated prospectus, and they will therefore be glad to receive a simplestatement of the aims and policy whichunderlie this operation. For these reasons, I have thought it right toarrange that, when the prospectus andother relative documents are sent, as theywill be to every holder, a letter over mysignature should also be enclosed, ex-plaining&apos; the nature of the scheme andthe purpose behind it. I am makingcopies of this letter available to hon.Members in the Vote Office as soon as my statement is concluded.The letter will go, as I have said, toall holders, great and small. Large in-vestors to whom a conversion operation isa familiar process may well find in partsof it phrases more simple and less tech-nical than is customary on these occa-sions. I feel no doubt that, remember-ing the immensely wide circulation the message will have, they will appreciatemy object and will not regard the letteras superfluous,I am sure that anyone who may be con-contemplating the issue of new capital inthe market in the early future will fore-bear from coming forward for a fewweeks while this great operation is pro-ceeding and that the authorities in the
2127 Five Per Cent. WarCity of London will co-operate in this necessary object. I should add that thesale of Savings ^Certificates will be tem-temporarily suspended as from this evening,but, as we have -of course no intention of abandoning that valuable method of bor-rowing, a new certificate, details of whichwill appear in the Press to-morrow, willbe placed on sale after a short interval.I will mention one other matter whichmay be of some interest. My prepara-tions have been proceeding for manyweeks, but the essential need for secrecyin preparation has prevented me fromprinting any of the many (millions offorms which I require. With the willing-co-operation and assistance of the Bankof England, the Government propose toattempt the gigantic task of printing15,000,000 forms and despatching them by post in nearly 3,000,-000 envelopes withina space of 24 hours from now. these letters will not, of course, reach all the holders to whom they are addressed on saturday morning, for the holders live inall parts of the country and indeed ofthe world but they will all be on their way by to-morrow night. In this way we shall cover all the holdings at theBank of England and the Post Office. Inaddition, upwards of 500,000 letters con-taining supplementary notices in special cases will we hope, be posted early on(Saturday. I do not undertake that wecan completely fulfil this almost super-human programme, but we shall spare no effort, and I am sure that our endeavourto present our scheme with the leastdelay and in the most intelligible formwill be widely appreciated.For the response we must trust, andI am certain we shall not trust in vain, tothe good sense and patriotism of the3,000,000 holders to whom we shall appeal.Mr. LANSBURY: I am sure, Mr.Speaker, that the House will not expect-any discussion on the statement whichhas just been made, but I am sure also,that you and my fellow Members will allow me to say one or two things onthis occasion. First, may I say a personalword to the Chancellor of the Ex-chequer? On behalf of myself and myfriends I congratulate him on being in good health and able to come back andto make this statement to-night. we heard that he had been ill; we are very glad to see him, and we hope that hisLoan (Conversion). 2128health is as good as the clearness of his speech would lead us to imagine. Withregard to the statement itself, I onlywant to say on behalf of my friends thatwe welcome it most heartily. Everyoneknows our view on this subject, and weare delighted that, at long last, an effort is to be made to put this enormous debton a better footing. Although we havetremendous differences of opinion withthe noble Lord in another place andwith the right hon. Gentleman, we con-gratulate them both on having had apart in bringing this scheme to- fruition.We all agree that the step which theright hon. Gentleman is taking is thevery best form of economy. It is one ofthose steps which we think would enable us to have a better understanding withthe regard to the conditions of lifethroughout the length and breadth ofthe land. We also think that everyoneof the stockholders ought to be only toowilling to fall Jn with the right hon.Gentleman&apos;s proposals, and we hope thathis appeal to their patriotism will resultin accomplishing that which he has setout to do.Sir AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN : I hopethat my relationship with the Chancellorof the Exchequer will not be held to debarme from offering a few observations,, as a previous holder of that office. I join veryheartily in the congratulations which theright hon. Gentleman the Leader of theOpposition has felt able on this occasion to offer to my right hon. Friend and hiscolleague. I desire only to add that Ithink that the statement which the Chan-cellor has just made was as wise in the steps which he outlined as it was lucidin its exposition, and that I am confident that he will meet with the response fromthe country which he has a right to expect.Sir GODFREY COLLINS: I am sure that all sections of the House desire to congratulate the Chancellor on what Ithink is one of the most momentous state-ments made in this House since the War,for we have listened to-night to the com-plete vindication of British credit in the eyes of the world and, what is more, tothe complete vindication of the national government, for there was no chargemade more seriously than that while cutswere being made, the interest on the WarLoan was not being reduced. I am sure that all sections of the House desire tq30 Jtnsra 1932
2129  -      Five Per Gent. War    HOUSE OF[Sir G. Collins.]congratulate the Chancellor and hope thathis words may find a response in the minds of all investors, and that everyinvestor may convert at the lowered rateof interest.We have during the last nine monthswitnessed a most remarkable scene. Somenine months ago we saw British creditebbing. We witness to-night the rise ofBritish credit by nearly 25 per cent.,, andI am sure that I echo what is in the mindCOMMONS      Loan (Conversion). 2l3(5of every hon. Member when I say that we hope that the Chancellor, having dealtwith the War Loan, will deal with theSupply services, so that the Income Tax-payer in the coming year imay see hisrate reduced and, what is more, the rateof employment increased in this country.Question put, and agreed to.Adjourned accordingly atTwelve minutes before Teno&apos;clock.
EC RE T.- ---&apos; APPENDIX IITiKOLARAT I ON OF BRITISH PI SAPiMAMENT POLICY.Draft as settled by the Chancellor of theExchequer and the President of the Boardof Trade in consultation with the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs&quot; at Lausanneand approved by the Prime Minister on_ June 27th. 1932.1. The Government, of the United Kingdom welcomePresident Hoover&apos;s declaration, alike because it calls for a really substantial measure of actual disarmament and because it seeks to apply the two principlesof quantitative and of qualitative limitation.   as president Hoover says &quot;Reduction should be carried outnot only by broad general cuts in armaments but by increasing the comparative power of defence throughdecreases in the power of the attack&quot;.Success at Geneva depends upon general agreement,and the American delegation has made it plain that president HooverTs proposals are put forward as a contribution to an agreed general programme.    TheUnited Kingdom Government have already advanced widesuggestions of their own.   These, while theydiffer in some important respects as to method ormeasure, are inspired by the same purpose, and a comparison will stvovf that already there is asubstantial area of common ground.Without interrupting or anticipating detailed discussions which must take place with the other delegations represented at Geneva, it is convenient
at this moment to set out in broad outline themain characteristics of the British proposals.They in their turn should be regarded, not as adeclaration of isolated action,, but as a contributionto general agreement.3.     First, the Government of the United Kingdomdesire to put on record their agreement with president hoover on the further principle that the threeproblems of Military, Naval and Air disarmament areinter-connected.    International agreement cannot be attained without an adequate contribution from all three sources.    Inasmuch as Britain, like the UnitedStates, finds her strongest arm in the navy, the contribution which concerns her most is to be foundin this sphere, in which, as is well known,   contributions to disarmament on the largest scale have already beenmade in advance of the General Disarmament Conference.Nevertheless the British Government now offer afurther contribution as part of a general worldsettlement.3*     It is now proposed to set out under the threenecessary heads the manner in which the Governmentof the United Kingdom would suggest that these principlescould be applied.
Naval Proposals.4       These proposals cover all types of vessel - capital ships,aircraft carriers, cruisers, destroyers and submarines.It is essential that proposals that are intended to beadopted by general agreement should make due provision forvarying circumstances,,     Having regard to the widely-scatteredresponsibilities of the British Navy and to the conjoint interestsof the members of the British Commonwealth, it is not practicable to cut down the number of naval units beyond a certain point.But it is perfectly possible and in the highest degree desirableto adopt a mode of treatment which will secure by other means thelarge reductions at which we are all aiming..     The present Treatylimits of size and gun calibre are far too high, and the UnitedKingdom Government consider that a very large reduction, amountingto about one-third in the case both of capital ships and cruisers,can be made in future construction,,5,     As regards capital ships, the position under the existingNaval treaties is that the maximum size for future constructionhas been fixed at 35,000 tons and the gun at 16 inches.     Asbetween Britain, the United States and Japan, however, no further capital ship construction can be undertaken until the year 1937.The proportions of such ships as between these three Powers is inthe ratio 15 s 15 ; 9.     The total tonnage of a category of shipscan be reduced either by diminishing their number or by diminishingtheir size.      The American proposal is for a reduction in number,namely from 15 capital ships to 10;    it would thus leave the size of these enormously expensive vessels untouched.     Not only so butguns of 16 inch calibre would remain in any future constructionof capital ships.     Every figure involved in these huge dimensions- initial cost, upkeep, personnel, ammunition, stores, docks, -
would be maintained at the highest level.      The UnitedKingdom proposal, while securing no less reduction in total tonnage, avoids these consequences by (l) reducing the size of the gun, (2) reducing the size of the ship.For example,  if the calibre of the gun is reduced to12 inches the maximum size of the ship can be reduced from35,000 to 25,000 tons, and an immense saving is effectedunder both heads, both initially and consequentially,6.      But the Government of the United Kingdom are preparedto go beyond this.      They are ready to apply the same princi-ples to cruisers, and to reduce their maximum size and gun-calibre by international agreement from the present figureof 10,000 tons and 8 inches to 7,000 tons and 6,1 inches.It would then be possible to reduce the dimensions in thecase of capital ships still further and fix a maximum of22,000 tons with 11 inch guns.      This will nearly halve the initial cost of any future capital ship and greatly reducethe cost of maintenance.      Thus the whole scale would come,down together and there would be a definite return tosmaller dimensions.      On this basis the British proposal would effect an ultimate reduction in capital-ship tonnagealone of 195,000 tons;    the comparable figure under theUnited States proposal would appear to be about 175,000*7.     As regards aircraft carriers, the Government of theUnited Kingdom are in substantial agreement with president hoover&apos;s proposals.      They propose a reduction in the size of the Aircraft Carrier from 27,000 to 22,000 tons with consequent reduction in total tonnage from 135,000 to 110,000tons.
6       Special reference must &quot;be made to the Submarine.The British view has been, and is, that the submarineshould be entirely abolished.      If its abolition canbe secured, this will at once lead to a reduction ofapproximately one-third in destroyer tonnage.      Ifinternational agreement to abolish submarines is found impossible of attainment, ocean going submarines shouldbe got rid of by limiting the size to 250 tons, and thetotal tonnage to the lowest figure upon which agreement can be reached,9,     Consequently, the Government of the United Kingdomputs forward for immediate adoption by international agreement the following set of proposals relating to thenavies of the world:(l) Reduce the maximum size of any future capital ship to 22,000 tons, and the maximum calibre of the guns carried to 11 inches,(2) Reduce the maximum size of cruisers hereafterconstructed to 7,000 tons, and maximum calibre of guns to 6.1 inches.(3) If international agreement on point (2) cannotbe secured, the Government of the United kingdom would still urge that the maximum size of capital ships should be reduced to 25,000 tons and theirguns to 12 inches as a maximum.(4) Reduce the maxima for aircraft carriers to22,000 tons with 6.1 inch guns..(5) Abolish submarines,(6) If submarines cannot be completely abolished,fix their maximum surface displacement at 250 tons,with a strict limitation both of total tonnage and number of units.(7) Reduce destroyer tonnage by approximately one-third, this depending on the abolition of submarines.
J^AWJIJ^proposals .10. ^n ^e rea-^ Qf land disarmament His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom find themselves in fullaccord with the spirit which has inspired the latest proposals of President Hoover,   Naturally it will be necessary  carefully to examine the details of theAmerican proposals before expressing a final opinionon their suitability to the situation of each country.11.        To consider in turn the four categories to whichthese proposals relate:-(a) In regard to chemical and bacteriologicalwarfare His Majesty&apos;s Government have already joined inrejecting the use of these methods of warfare andtherefore cordially welcome the United States proposals under this head,,(b) In regard to land gunss His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave proposed the abolition of all mobile guns of a .calibre greater than 155 mm. (6.1 inches calibre).Considerable stress was laid in the discussion at Geneva,on the difficulties due to the problem of drawing anyclear line of demarcation between fixed and mobileartillery.    His Majesty&apos;s Government believe, however,that the difficulty is theoretical rather than practical.Under this head also His Majesty&apos;s Government find,themselves, therefore, in general agreement with theproposals of the United States government
(c) In regard to the strength of land armiess HisMajesty&apos;s Government have consistently placed in the forefront of their proposals for land disarmament the examination of measures for the reduction of effectivesto the lowest level compatible with national safety.So far as their own forces are concerned;, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have already reduced them to the minimumnumbers required for the preservation of internal order and for the defence of their overseas possessions andcommunicatIonsoThe United States proposal for a division of land forces into a &quot;police component&quot; and a &quot;defence component&quot;raises points of some difficulty and will require very careful examination;   but so far as His Majesty&apos;sGovernment understand the application of the suggestedbasis of calculationy it would appear that the Britishland forces have already been reduced substantially below the number recognised to be necessary for themaintenance of internal order s v/ithout making any allowance for the forces needed for the protection of linesof communication between the United Kingdom and the overseas territories.(d) In regard to tanks? His Majesty&apos;s Government havealready advocated the abolition of all tanks above aweight of 20 tonss which by&apos;their characteristics are specially suitable for offensive employment in battle.In the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Government the abolitionof all tanks would not contribute in the long run to thecause of disarmament.
Tanks of the lighter type cannot be regarded asspecifically offensive weapons.     Their comparativelylight armour and &apos;the&apos;irreduced capacity for crossingtrenches render them unsuitable for the assaxilt of highly organised defences.But as a means of saving the life of the soldiers,as well as of economising man power, tanks are invaluable.In a small voluntarily enlisted army like our o?m they constitute an essential compensation for lack of numbers which It would, be Impossible to surrender.     As faras this country is concerned, in view of its world-wideresponsibilities, any general prohibition would require an increase in our present land forces in terms of manpower, and thus, as a measure of disarmament would tendto defeat its own ends.12.     It would be seen therefore that in the realm ofland disarmament the proposals of the United StatesGovernment, so far as they relate to matters whichdirectly touch the land forces of the United King-dom and of the countries of the British Common-wealth,    approximate   very closely to thosefavoured by His Majesty&apos;s Government;    and that inthe total of their effectives His Majesty1s Governmenthave been able already to put into practice a measureof disarmament which more than conforms to the standards proposed by President Hoover.
Air Proposals^13,     There is no aspect of international disarmamentmore vitally urgent than the adoption without delay ofthe most effective measures to preserve the civilian population from the fearful horrors of bombardmentfrom the ,air.     The Government of the United kingdom would be prepared to go to any length, in agreementwith other Powers, to achieve this object, and if more drastic measures are proposed from any other quarterand are shown to be practicable, they will examinethem with the utmost sympathy.They propose that the High Contracting parties should agree between themselves in respect of theirair forces that there should be(1)     the complete prohibition of all bombingfrom the air save within limits to belaid down by an international convention.Attacks upon the civilian population would be prohibited.     The convention would define as precisely as possible thelimits of permissible military objectives;(2)     a strict limitation in the unladen weightof all military and naval aircraft (troop-carriers and flying boats excepted);,(3)     a restriction in the numbers- of all. kinds of military and naval aircraft.
14. It is essential to bear in mind, the extent ofBritish disarmament already effected both on sea and by measures, additional to the abolition of conscription, on land.     If a comparison is made with the year before theWar, it will be found that in complete vessels the capital ships of the British Commonwealth   have been reduced from69 to 15, its cruisers from 108 to 58, its destroyers from285 to 147, and its submarines from 74 to 52.The personnel of the British Army, including itscontingents   in    India, has been reduced in the same period from 259,000 to 207,000 and this has been effected by the disbandment of 9 regiments of cavalry, 61 batteries and companies of artillery, 21 companies of Royal Engineers,21 battalions of infantry and 6 battalions of colonial and troops locally enrolled.      (in addition there has beenduring the same period a net reduction of the personnel of theIndian Army of approximately 20,000 men).The air arm was in its infancy in 1913-1914 and nocomparison can be made with that date, but it must be mentioned that in the number of military and     naval aero-planes the United Kingdom stands only fifth in the list of states and that, of aircraft authorised for home defence in19S3 by the United Kingdom Government with the approval ofParliament, 20% have not in fact been constructed.15. Great and far-&apos; reaching as these reductions havebeen - beyond comparison greater than any which have been effected elsewhere (outside the countries disarmed by theTreaty of Versailles)- His Majesty*s Government in theUnited Kingdom are ready and eager to join in the further measures for which general agreement can be attained.The proposals which accordingly are now made constitute an-10-
additional contribution, practical and extensive, to the effort to relieve the heavy burdens which the maintenanceof existing standards imposes upon the world and which theworld expects us by a great common effort effectively to diminish.
TELEGRAM from the Governor of Malta to theSecretary of State for the Colonies.Dated 29th June. Received 11.14 a.m.  29th June.No. 99.The following minute submitted to me by Ministersis forwarded at their request begins.        Ministers havedecided to send a deputation to London to discuss withthe Secretary of State the language and constitutional questions as already explained by Head of Ministry tothe Governor. The deputation is to leave Malta thisY/eek. Pending arrival in London of this delegationv/hich is to be headed by Head of   Ministry it isrespectfully asked that in view of representations Y/hichthe deputation has to offer further stages of the malta constitution Bill novr before the House of Lords be notproceeded with     ends.PARAPHRASE telegram from the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies to the Governor of Malta.(Sent 2.5 p.m. 30th June, 1932).Immediate.Private and Personal.Your telegram No. 99.       You should make it plainto your Ministers that there can be no question of any alteration in the policy which has been laid down byHis Majesty&apos;s Government.     The whole language question has been dealt with by the issue of the Letters Patentand His Majesty&apos;a Government will entertain no proposal
to alter these provisions.     Nor can there be anyquestion of the passage of the Bill being delayed or ofany of its provisions being withdrawn.       The Bill- will pass its third reading in the House of lords to-day and will pass through all its stages in house of Commons before Parliament adjourns in middle of July.As the object of visit of Ministers is to suggestchanges in policy which cannot in any circumstances be entertained., you should convey to Ministers that no useful purpose could be served by their sending adeputation..For your private informations      I leave for Ottawaon July 13th;     so that if the departure of Ministerscan be delayed my absence will constitute an additionalreason for their not coming&quot;

</content>
</cab>
