<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/56/8 images: 94-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons during the following week.It was reported that Mrs Joyce Butler&apos;s Television Licensing(Elderly and Disabled People) Bill was due to receive its SecondReading on 21 February.    If it became law it would reduce theBritish Broadcasting Corporation^ revenue from licence fees by about 45 million a yea.r.    The Bill would therefore have to be opposed atSecond Reading.    It might however be carried, and in that eventevery effort would have to be made to block it at a later stage.The Cabinet discussed the handling of the Report Stage and third reading of the Trade Union and Labour Relations (Amendment) Bill,which were to be taken in the House of Commons on 12 February.Quer&apos;Jons would then be raised about the implications of the closed shop provisions of the Bill for Press freedom.The intention was that the Bill should substantially restore the legal position to what it had been prior to 1971,    It would legalise theclosed shop but would be neutral on whether or not it should beintroduced in individual cases.    Newspaper editors had expressedfears that the establishment of a closed shop by the National Union of journalists (NUJ) would imperil editorial freedom, and there was alsoanxiety that it might interfere with the access to the Press ofoccasional contributors who were not members of a trade union.Fears had also been expressed that the Bill might endanger thecontinued existence of the Institute of Journalists.    The Secretary ofState for Employment had argued during the Second Reading debate that these matters could not effectively be dealt with by means of statutory provisions and that the preferable course would be for allthe parties concerned (proprietors, editors and trade unions) to agreeamongst themselves on a general code of conduct.    A possible Charterhad been prepared by the editor of a national daily newspaper with aview to its signature by all the parties; and this general approach was understood to be supported by the NUJ.    There were prospects thatthere would shortly be a meeting of all concerned at which it was hopedthat the Charter would be agreed.    It was perhaps unfortunate that matters had not proceeded more rapidly, but they were not underMinisterial jurisdiction.It was argued that it was doubtful whether the Charter, even if accepted, could of itself provide an adequate long-term safeguard.The Press in Britain enjoyed greater freedom than in any other country, save perhaps the United States, and it was important to do
nothing which might imperil that freedom.    If at some future time theNUJ passed into the control of political extremists, it was unlikelythat the Charter would suffice to ensure editorial freedom or thecontinued ability of part-time journalists who did not belong to a tradeunion to get their work accepted.    A similar threat to Press freedomcould arise if the ownership of the Press became concentrated inundesirable hands.    The Secretary of State for Employment hadalready indicated in the course of discussions that if the Charter were agreed and all the parties to it asked that it be given some form of statutory backing, the Government would consider such a requestsympathetically.    But on a matter of such fundamental importance itwas undesirable to leave the initiative entirely to third parties;  andthe Government should therefore announce, during the following day&apos;sproceedings in the House of Commons, that they were seeking methodsof giving statutory protection to Press freedom and would beprepared to introduce any amendments to the Bill which might be foundnecessary at a later stage.    If this were not done, there was a realdangex&quot; that the House of Lords would refuse to accept the Bill in itspresent form;  and any ensuing conflict between the Lords and the commons would imperil the progress of other urgent government legislation in the Lords.On the other hand, it was argued that legislation to protect editorialfreedom and the right of access to the Press of contributors who didnot belong to trade unions would be a wholly new departure on which itwould be inappropriate to embark by means of last-minuteamendments to the Trade Union and Labour Relations (Amendment)Bill.    Moreover, it was improbable that any statutory provision could produce the desired result.    The fear was that the NUJ would secure a closed shop and use it to restrict Press freedom.    But allexperience showed that if a trade union was bent on securing a closed shop it could not be prevented from doing so by the law.    A better course was to seek to ensure that the NUJ did not come under thecontrol of extremist elements;  and the proposed Charter, which would establish a broad area of agreement as to the principles which should apply, would be much more likely to secure this than any form of regulation by statute,, which could only serve to exacerbate feelings.Moreover, while an NUJ closed shop could in theory prove a danger toeditorial freedom, it was by no means the only danger - many editorsalready felt themselves at least as much in need of protection againstproprietors as against trade unions.    Furthermore, trade unionsgenerally attached much importance to the closed shop provisions ofthe Bill and would be reluctant to see them diluted.    Statutory backingfor the Charter could however be considered if it were clear that allconcerned wanted it.    And whatever the immediate outcome, a suitable opportunity for reviewing the matter would arise before very long
following receipt of the Report of the Royal Commission on the Press,by which time it could be seen what effect the relevant provisions ofthe Trade Union and Labour Relations (Amendment) Bill were in facthaving.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were agreed about the importance of avoiding any action whichwould endanger the freedom of the Press.    During the following day&apos;sproceedings on the Trade Union and Labour Relations (Amendment)Bill in the House of Commons, the Secretary of State for employment should indicate that the Government welcomed the fact that discussions were going on about a possible Charter.    He should saythat they recognised that the Charter would not - and was not intendedto - provide an entire regime for the Press;  but if the parties to the charter joined in asking the Government for legislative or other action in support of it - for example, a statutory code of practice orsomething on the lines of the Fair Wages Resolution - such a requestwould be urgently and sympathetically examined.    He should add thatthe Government attached much importance to preserving the freedomof editors from improper pressure from either proprietors or tradeunions, and that they would consider whether any further legislative or other action was necessary in the light of the Report of the RoyalCommission on the Press.    The Royal Commission could of coursesubmit an interim report on any matter which it considered of urgentimportance.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister !summing up of their discussion and invited theSecretary of State for Employment to be guided accordingly.
2. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat there had been a period of heightened tension in Cyprus duringthe past week.    There had been indications that there would be adeclaration by the Turkish Cypriots of the independence of the zoneoccupied by the Turks, possibly accompanied by military action at various points, including Nicosia Airport.    The Prime Minister andthe President of the United States, Mr Ford, had therefore sentmessages to the Turkish Prime Minister and President respectively,drawing their attention to the grave consequences of a renewal of fighting and urging restraint.    Subsequently, on the night of8 February, there was evidence of troop movements in the Turkishoccupied zone and we and the Americans received appeals from theGreek Cypriot leaders to intervene again in Ankara.    Furthermessages were accordingly sent to the Turkish Government, andalthough they replied to the effect that the reports were unfoundedthere was evidence that military action had been in contemplationand was stopped at the eleventh hour.    Although the situation hadeased it remained uncertain and would have to be watched very carefully.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that he had visited Portugal on 6 and 7 February at the invitation of the PortuguesePrime Minister, Dr Soares.    There was concern about the influence of the Portuguese Communist Party and the possibility that they wouldtake over the government of the country.    The Communists did not enjoy strong support numerically, but they had achieved a strongminority influence within the Armed Forces Movement (afin).He thought there was a reasonable prospect, however, that the AFMwould retain its cohesion, and in that case the power of the Communistswould be limited.    He had been assured that the elections would beheld on 12 April.    The Portuguese Government were taking a helpfulline on the Rhodesia question;  the consulate which the illegal regime in Rhodesia had been allowed to establish in Lisbon would be closedin the near future.     It was important that we should do all that wecould to encourage the democratic movements in Portugal and he hopedthat further Ministerial visits to that country could be arranged.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the african leaders in Rhodesia had informed our High Commissioner inLusaka of their talks with Mr Ian Smith.    The question of a constitutional conference had been discussed and there was apossibility of progress although Mr Smith continued to say that theconference should be held in Salisbury, which was totally unacceptable to the Africans.    At this stage, Mr Smith appeared to be playing his hand alone; he had not yet involved any of his colleagues in the talks.
The Cabinet -Took note of the statements by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary
3. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Lord Chancellor(C(75) 16), to which was attached a report by the Ministerial Group onthe information policy to be carried out by the Government in relationto the referendum on United Kingdom membership of the european economic Community (e.c.);  and memoranda by the Lord Presidentof the Council on the possible arrangements for controlling theinformation activities of outside organisations (C(75) 17) and oh thequestion to be included on the referendum ballot paper (C(75) 18).THE LORD CHANCELLOR said that, following the cabinets discussion on 23 January, a Ministerial Group had met under his chairmanship to consider the practicability, form and control of any government information programme relating to the referendum,havmg regard to the extent of non-Government publicity.    The group had concluded that a Government information programme would be essential as a means of discharging a necessary part of theGovernments responsibilities in relation to the referendum.    Thereshould be an initial Government pamphlet, distributed to all house-holds in, say, April, containing basic factual material about the referendum itself, the composition of the European Community, theUnited Kingdom&apos;s accession, and the commitment to renegotiation.An interdepartmental unit should be established in the Cabinet office with the task of planning and preparing the Governments informationprogramme and should be directly responsible to the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.    The units first task should be to prepare the initial Government pamphlet, which should be approved beforeissue by the Ministerial Group, if the Group were kept in being.    TheCabinet were invited to endorse these agreed recommendations.The Group had also envisaged that the information programme should include a second pamphlet, for similar distribution about the end ofMay, dealing with the general issue of membership, in the light of therenegotiated terms,    But the Group had not reached an agreedconclusion on how the Governments recommendation or the cases forand against continued membership should be prepared and presented.It had been argued, on the one hand, that it would be contrary to the fair conduct of the referendum, and thus wrong in principle, for theGovernment to use the resources of the Government information services to present their view on an issue which they had decidedshould be left entirely to the decision of the electorate;  in any casethe Governments recommendation would presumably be presented ina White Paper, in Parliamentary debates, and in Ministerial speeches and broadcasts.    Other members of the Group took the view that,since the Government would take a decision, as a Government, on therecommendation to be put to the British people, it would be entirelyproper, and the Governments duty, to explain and justify the irrecommendation by using the Government information machine.    TheGroup were agreed that the Government had a responsibility to see
that the arguments for and against membership were presented to the electorate., but further study was needed of the appropriate means of presenting both sides of the case.    There were objections to inviting the two campaigning movements to contribute pieces, and also to theGovernment attempting, on their own, to produce an objective accountof both sides of the case.    On these further issues it was necessary to seek the guidance of the Cabinet,In discussion it was argued that a factual statement about the european economic Community would be either controversial or platitudinous,and the Government should not make the mistake of the conservative government and carry out an extensive distribution to Post Offices ofinformation material about the Community.    The campaigningorganisations would themselves publish far more material than thepublic could absorb.    The Governments primary duty would be topresent, in a pamphlet for general distribution by the Post Office, theterms secured in the renegotiation, with particular reference to the pledges in the Labour Party&apos;s Election Manifesto, and to say whetheror not the Government judged the terms to be satisfactory.    Thepamphlet could also explain the mechanics of the referendum.Different views were expressed about how far this pamphlet should goin presenting and justifying the Governments own position on thegeneral issue of membership.    It was argued, on the one hand, thatthe Government had a clear responsibility to explain and advocate their view on the basic question of membership in the light of the outcome of renegotiation, and that this was implicit in the Manifesto commit-ments.    This should be expressed in as balanced a way as possible,avoiding the most extreme form of presentation to which thecampaigning organisations were likely to be prone.    It was entirelyproper that the Government&apos;s own information effort and resources should be directed to supporting the Governments own recommen-dation.    Against this It was argued that the Government should confine their own information activities to a White Paper setting outthe new terms and the Governments recommendation.    It would be wrong for public money to be spent on stating one side of the case,when the issue of future membership of the Community went wider andhad to be decided by the British people as a whole in circumstances inwhich the media generally were slanted one way.It was also argued that it was unnecessary, and that it would weaken the impact of the Governments own recommendation, for theGovernment to distribute with their main pamphlet a statement of bothsides of the case, which would emerge strongly enough from other sources during the campaign.    It would be sufficient for bothcampaigning organisations to be allowed free delivery of theirstatements of case.    Against this, it was argued that the Governmenthad a responsibility for the presentation of both sides of the case; and
that, while it would be preferable to avoid a direct responsibility fordrafting the necessary texts, the Government should go some way tofollow the Australian referenda practice and should, at least,undertake the distribution of the material.    Government distribution would avoid the addressing of envelopes by volunteers, which could have a divisive effect in constituency organisations.    Thus the two cases could be included in the main Government pamphlet, on the basisof statements to be drafted as far as possible by the outsideorganisations, but in consultation with the Government.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that insufficient time remained for the Cabinet to reach conclusions onthese questions of information policy, or on the other referendumissues raised in C(75) 17 and 18.    The Lord President of the council should now circulate, for consideration by the Cabinet on20 February, a complete redraft of the proposed White Paper on thearrangements for the referendum, which it was proposed to publish on26 February.    The draft should propose alternative passages on thequestions which had not yet teen resolved.The Cabinet -Invited the Lord President of the Council to circulate a draft White Paper on the referendum arrangements,containing alternative passages on the issues examined in C(75) 16, 17 and 18.Cabinet Office11 February 19758


</content>
</cab>
