<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/82/0 images: 270-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tjgjTOniMICNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)C R E T. COPY NO.CABINET   47  (55).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street, S.W.I.,  on.WEDNESDAY, 16th OCTOBER, 1935,at 11.0 a.in.AGENDA.1.    THE ITALO-ABYSSINIAN DISPUTE.(Reference Cabinet 45 (35) Conclusion l).2.    THE ATLANTIC AIR ROUTE    -    (if ready).(Reference Cabinet 44 (35) Conclusion 2).Memoranda by the Secretary of State for Air.CP.  164 (35)    -   already circulated.CP.  182 (35)    -   already circulated.Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.CP.  184 (35)    -   already circulated.3.    GOVERNMENT OF INDIA ACT,  1955;    BILL TO REPRINT ASTWO SEPARATE ACTS,  ONE RELATING TO INDIA AND THEOTHER TO BURMA.(Reference Cabinet 43 (35) Conclusion 3).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India,covering draft Bill.CP.  191 (35)    -   to be circulated.4.    UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT ALLOWANCES FOR CHILDREN.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.CP.  190 (35)    -   to be circulated.5.    FUMIGATIONS WITH HYDROGEN CYANIDE.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.CP. 189 (35)    -   already circulated.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2* Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,12th October, 1935.
j^TR DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OT? HTS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).ggj^R E T. COPY NO.CABIN E T    47 (55).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.w. 1., on WEDNESDAY,16th OCTOBER, 1935, at 11.0 a.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (In the Chair).lie Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.m Eight Hon.Sir John Simon, CCS.I.,K.C.V.O., O.B.E., K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home-Affairs.He Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K.G. , M.V.O. , Lord Privy Seal.p Eight Hon.lj.H. Thomas, M.P. ,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.if Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,&amp;.C.S.T., G.C.I.E., Secretary[of State for India.If Eight Hon.I Malcolm MacDonald, M.P. ,f. Secretary of State for theI &quot;Colonies.(I Right Hon.\ Sir Bolton Eyres Monsell,; G.B.E., M.P. , First Lord of theAdmiralty.pRight Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P. ,Minister for Agriculture and- Fisheries.IlRight Hon.hfir Kingsley Wood, M.P. ,Hfinister of Health.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.G.B.E. , C.M.G., M.P. , Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G. ,G.C.S.I., G.CI.E. , Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E., M.C., M.P., Secretaryof State for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E. ,  -C.M.G., M.P., Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Walter Runicman, M.P.,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Labour.lel Sir M.P.A.  Hankey, G.C.B. , G.CM.G. , G.CV.C. Secretary.
- jrpftio- 1. The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsiSPtFP&apos;* said that at the last week-end he had. felt somewhatl&apos; ions perturbed at the attitude Of the Press in giving theth France.impression that the Minister for League of Nationspevious Affairs at Geneva was making all the proposals foreference:3,&apos;tinet 4-5 sanctions, and even that some were being made without35), Con-conclusion 1.) the approval of the British Government:    also that we and the French were constantly wrangling on thequestion.   Be had accordingly addressed a telegram to the Minister for League of Nations Affairs, andhad had several conversations with him by telephone,as the result of which it was quite clear that thePress reports were inaccurate.   Most of the work wasbeing carried on in Committees and Sub-Committees,meeting largely in private, and the recent reports had probably been put about by representatives ofother nations.   For example, the ... embargo on certain exports to Italy had been proposed   by theFrench.   The Minister for League of Nations affairs had taken towards it the same line as the Cabinet,undertaking to consider it but pointing out that therewere some difficulties,   ^he same was true in other cases.   The Greek Finance Minister, who was Chairmanof the Financial Su.b-committee, had taken a leading part in financial sanctions. 1 There had. been no particular difficulties with the French at Geneva.Even after his doubts had been removed on thispoint, however, the Secretary of State had feltdisturbed that no clear resolution had been accept-ed       that,if we were attacked as the -result of sanctions, other nations would come to our assistance.At his request, the Minister for League of nations affair had obtained a resolution from both theCommittees concerned to the effect that all the nations-1-
would carry out -Article XVI, paragraph. 3.   That was satisfactory so far as it went, but left in doubt whatwas meant &quot;by &quot;co-operation&quot;, particularly in the caseof France.    At that moment there had appeared in theFrench, paper &quot;Gringoire&quot; a most offensive articlesigned by the     uw-in-law of M. Chiappe, the Presi-dent of the Municipal Council of Paris .   this had. beendisquieting,  especial].y in connection with the doubt as to what French co-operation meant, so he had decided to clear the question up with. M. Laval, andhad sent a. telegram on Monday to the British ambassador in Paris.    M. Laval&apos;s reply (Paris melegram No.303, ofOctober 15th) was to the effect that France fullysubscribed to the undertaking in paragraph 3 ofArticle XVI of the Covenant, that&quot;The Members of the League will, mutuallysupport one another in resisting anyspecial measures aimed at one oftheir Members by the Covenant-breakingState&quot;,but had made a reservation that to justify thissolidarity it is necessary that the attack whichbrings it into play shall not be caused by a factoutside the application of Article XVI.   M. Lavalhad stated that -&quot;In the actual situation as presented by the British Government, the e ire tan-stances are such that they oblige theFrench Government to make a reservationas to the presence in the Mediterraneanof British, naval forces much in excessof the effectives normally stationed inthat Sea.    mhe Covenant-breaking State,actually Italy, could in effect allegethat it was justified, in seeing in this.  concentration a step ( hnesure&apos; ) going beyond the application of the stepactually agreed upon at Geneva forthe execution of ArtioIe XVI*.Added to this,  the French Admiralty had refused, todiscuss the question of co-operation with the british naval Attache.
would carry out Article XVI, paragraph 3.    That wassat is fact cry so far as it went, but left in doubt whatwas meant by &quot;co-operation&quot;, particularly in the caseof France.   At that moment there had appeared in theFrench paper &quot;Oringoire&quot; a most offensive articlesigned by the     aw-in-law of M. Ohiappe, the Presi-dent of the Municipal Council of Paris.&apos;   this had beendisquieting,  especial].y in connection with the doubt as to what French co-operation meant, so he had decided to clear the question up with M. Laval, andhad .sent a telegram on Monday to the British ambassador in Paris.   M. Laval,&apos;e reply (Paris Telegram wo.203, ofOctober 15th) was to the effect that France fullysubscribed, to the undertaking in paragraph 3 ofArticle XVI of the Covenant, that&quot;The Members of the League will mutuallysupport one another in resisting anyspecial measures aimed at one oftheir Members bv the Covenant-breakingState&quot;,but had made a reservation that to justify thissolidarity it is necessary that the attack whichbrings it into play shall not be caused by a factoutside the application of Article XVI.. M. Lavalhad stated that -&quot;In the actual situation as presented by the British Government, the circumstances-stances are such that they oblige theFrench Government to make a reservationas to the presence in the Mediterraneanof British naval forces much in excessof the effectives normally stationed inthat Sea.   mhe Covenant-breaking State,actually Italy, could in effect allege-that it was justified, in seeing in thisconcentration a step ( hmesure&apos;) going beyond the application of the stepactually agreed upon at Geneva forthe execution of Article XVI&quot;.Added to this, the French Admiralty had refused todiscuss the question of co-operation with the British.Naval Attache.
The Secretary of State recalled how, early inSeptember, he had told M. Laval of our reinforcements to the Mediterranean, in which M- Laval had concurred,expressing surprise that they had not been sent earlier  all of which was on record.      Signor Mussolini had said much the same thing, and that in our place hewould have done the same himself.      In these circumstancesM. Laval&apos;s reservation was quite unjustifiable and madea deplorable impression.     Moreover, he seemed to be constantly intriguing behind the back of the League ofNations and ourselves with a view to some accommodationwith Signor Mussolini.      His advice to the Cabinet,therefore, was that this question should be cleared up;that he should be authorised to send a telegram to M.Lavalrecalling the circumstances of our reinforcementsand the previous conversations in regard to them;describing the nature of the reinforcements as a condi-tion of elementary safety;    and making clear that unless we were satisfied as to the French attitude there couldbe no question of withdrawing any of them.      He also proposed to add that if earlier we had felt confidentof naval co-operation by France and of the availability of French ports in the event of an Italian aggressionwe should have sent fewer reinforcements to the Medit-mediterranean.      In view of the equivocal French attitudehe was not prepared to advise that we should take anyrisks by withdrawals from the Mediterranean.      If theFrench answer was satisfactory, we could consider any proposals that Signor G-randi might make on signor mussolini&apos;s behalf,  but he felt that we could notconsider them until after he had cleared mattersup with M. Laval and. discussed the question with theFirst Lord, of the Admiralty.
The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he wasprofoundly disquieted &quot;by what had happened.   Ferecalled that the Sub-Gcmmittee on. Defence Policyand Requirements had adopted various precautions tosafeguard our position in the event of sanctions.For example, on the 5th September they had agreed.  &quot;(b) That, in order to provide a safeguard against the risk of such an attack&quot;(i.e,, an attack by Italy)  &quot;the adop-tion of sanctions must be made conditional on a, clear understandingthat if Italy, as a consequence,should attack any of the nationsconcerned, all the participatingnations will declare war on Italy....-(c) That in particular, as a condition ofthe acceptance of sanctions, we musthave a clear understanding with france as to the action she will take in theevent&apos;of an Italian attack on theinterests of the united Kingdom:    also,if possible, with Yugoslavia and Greece&quot;.He also recalled that the Defence Policy and Require-arrangements Committee had examined the situation on theassumption that France would give us whole-hearted-operation and would play the principal r.ol.e in theWestern Mediterranean except the Gibraltar area, and  &apos;the principal air role in Northern Italy, in which,however, a contingent of the British. Air Force would co-operate:    the United Kingdom was to play theprincipal role in the Pastern Mediterranean  - all ofwhich, together with a good deal more, had beenreported to the Cabinet in 0 .P.-176 (65) and taken note of by them on September 24th (Cabinet 43 (35),Conclusion 2(a)).    He further recalled, that duringthose previous discussions the Cabinet and the defence policy and Requirements Sub-Committee had been considering the Reports from the Defence Services,in which the dangers of Malta and the absence of bases for the Fleet in the Mediterranean had been emphasised.
For some time past now he had felt profoundlydisquieted at the attitude of France, and that waswhy he had teen pressing to clear the matter up.In Paris our Naval Attache&apos;&apos;s overtures had beenrebuffed.    From the British Ambassador&apos;s telegramNo. 203 we now knew where we were, and that M. Lavalalleged that by strengthening the Mediterranean Fleetwe were causing a provocation to Italy.    From thepoint of view of the Navy this was a terriblyunsatisfactory position, and we ought to ask forcategorical assurances from M, Laval as to hisco-operation.   Referring to the remark of theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs that before considering any Italian proposals for mutual with-draws. 1 in the Mediterranean he would like to consult the Admiralty, he said the only possibility was thewithdrawal of the Battle Cruisers from Gibraltar.&apos;Fhe despatch of these Battle Cruisers had produced a very good effect and had resulted in bringing back the Italian main forces, including their largerCruisers, into the Western basin of the MediterraneanThe Admiralty would, however, be willing t.p. considerthe withdrawal of these Battle Cruisers if theFrench would provide a substitute and declare their willingness to fulfil their responsibilities and give us the use of bases.   At present we were nonearer getting our bases, though sanctions were making progress at 0 eneva*    Even though/the Ministerfor League of Nations Affairs was not taking the lead at.Geneva, all the world thought that he was.From the Admiralty&apos;s point of view even the situation at Geneva itself, as reported in Geneva telegramNo. 210 L.N., was not very satisfactory.   For example the suggestion that our anxieties were nsurely met bythe terms of Article XVI itself, which is, of course.
binding on every Member of the League and underwhich we are at present working&quot; -was not veryconvincing, especially in the light of M. Laval&apos;sattitu.de.In the course of the discussion M. Laval&apos;position was interpreted to mean that even if Italyattacked us in consequence of the imposition of sanctions under the aegis of the League of Nations,Prance might refuse co-operation on the ground thatthe movements of our Fleet had been provocative.It was urged that the British Ambassador in Parisshould be instructed to obtain an explicit withdrawalof M. Laval&apos;s reservation, and that in the absenceof such withdrawal it would be impossible to preventits becoming known that the whole scheme of sanctionshad broken down owing to the French, attitude.One feature which made the situation especiallyserious was that Italy was almost certain to learnof the French attitude.    It was suggested that itwas necessary in these circumstances to let theFrench know that if the Covenant were to break down for this reason the Locarno Treaty would, also breakdown and there would be left no effective obligationsIf it -was arguable that our reinforcement, of theMediterranean Fleet was so provocative as to enableItaly to attack us without bringing paragraph 3 ofArticle XVI into operation, it might be argued thatin the event of a German attack, on France the French,fortifications and other defensive preparations wereequ.a 1 ly provocative to a German attack.The Prime Minister reminded the Cabinet thatwe must be   careful not to be drawn into a quarrelwith France as -ell as with Italy as the result ofwhat was happening at Geneva.
Some doubts were expressed as to whether, even ifM. Laval gave the assurances we asked, we could rely on him in view       his equivocal attitude throughout.withdrawal fromthe French /    chanak was recalled.    It was urged,however, that if M. Laval should give the assuranceswe desired, conversations should take place immediatelybetween, the British -Attache and the French Ministry of marine.    If Italy could he made to Believe that france would stand behind us in the event of attack, thatwould be a sufficient deterrent.The First Lord of the Admiralty urged, that wemust be very explicit. If we were to withdraw&apos; the battle Cruisers, France must publicly announce thatshe would take over our responsibilities and take some concrete action to make this clear:    as, forexample, preparations in the Mediterranean ports.The question was raised as to how long theBritish Fleet could, remain in Alexandria and the Levantwithout returning to Malta.The First Lord reported that, apart from this,he was in great difficulties in maintaining the fleet at war strength, and was having to consider-paying offtwo Capital Ships .There was general agreement that until this situation was cleared up we must go slow at Geneva inthe matter of sanctions.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs saidthat if we were able to obtain completely satisfactory assurances from the French Government, the best wayof announcing than to the jworld would, probably be byry roth c0untr3.esmeans of     public statement at Geneva.   That wouldbe worth a good deal, even if we might feel somemisgivings in regard to whether in the last resortthe&quot;assuranees could, be relied on.-7-
In the course of the discussion the Cabinet were reminded that the policy had been to play the Genevahand to the full, but the question was raised as towhether it had not been played, as far as was safe.But the view of the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs was strongly supported that the moment hadnot yet come for a change in policy.    It was urged,however, that until the situation with France was cleared up we shotild not apply any new sanctions apartfrom the maintenance of the arms embargo to Italy,which involved no new action on our part, sincethe agreement reached at Geneva had only been tolift the existing embargo in the case of Abyssinia.The Cabinet agreed  fa) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should send instructions to theBritish Ambassador in Paris to insist on a categorical ana explicit withdrawal by M, Laval of his reservation to hisacknowledgment of the French obligation under Article XVI, paragraph 3, of theCovenant.   Fis telegram to the ambassador should, be drawn up in. the light of theCabinet discussion and should set out for v. Laval&apos;s information what were likely to be the consequences andreactions of adherence to his present attitude on the sanctity of inter-national engagements:ft.) That great caution must be exercised in the application of sanctions, andthat it would be well to postpone the application&apos;of any new sanctionsuntil&quot;the position with the FrenchGovernment had been cleared up, andthat until that time it would bedesirable not to press sanctionstoo actively at G eneva.
rriR ITALO-ftBYSSlNIAWDISPUTE.Sanctions.*__jrbe Attitude0f Non-member states .11 p-p ev i ou sI ReferencetI Cabinet 45(35), Oon-i conclusion ion 1.)2.   The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs raised the question of the attitude to be adopted, inthe matter of sanctions, towards States that were not members of the league of Nations.    Tn the case ofAmerica he had taken the line that the initiative had better come from the United states &quot;overnment.   Asregards other nations he thought that the League ofNations should reach its o-vn conclusions as to whatsanctions were to be applied before approaching them.Any resolutions that were taken in which non-member states v.-ere concerned should be provisional pendingtheir co-operation.fhe Cabinet agreed to the above proposals ,
3. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs reported, a suggestion that had reached him that theunratified Treaty of Financial Assistance might be invoked at Geneva.    Any assistance that could be rendered to Abyssinia In that way would be in thenature &quot;of a gift, owing to that country&apos;a lack of resources.   The propose,! was not being pressed..^he Cabinet agreed  That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should inform theTi/irlnister for league of nations affair that it would be prefer-able that the unratifled treatyof Financial Assistance shouldnot be raised at the present time.i1TAI.0-ySSTNTAN,PU^F.e TreatyFinancialsistance.deviouseference:binet 29SO), Con-us ion 2.)
IP ITALO- 4.      The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsfgySSlNIANigSEUTE. said that in the earlier discussions at Geneva thequestion had been raised of something in the natureUnctions.of compensation for States that would be adverselyfssistance affected by the reactions of the imposition ofto StatesIdversely sanctions.      Those proposals had now been modified and,ff ec ted.what seemed now to be contemplated was that if thedifficulties actually arose they should be consideredlater on their merits.     A formula was under discussion between the Foreign Office, Treasury and Board of Trade.The President of the Board of Trade entered acaveat that the Board of Trade was already receivingprotests, through Chambers of Commerce, from merchantsvrtio expected to be adversely affected by sanctions,and that a good deal of caution was necessary.The Cabinet agreed  To leave the responsibility for preparing an appropriate formula for use at Geneva to -The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The president of the Board of Trade.
if HE ITALO-AETSSTNIANDISPUTE.Continuanceof imperial airways.(previous reference:Cabinet 45(35), Con-clue ion 5.)i3I5. The Secretary of State for Air drew theattention of the Cabinet to ^elegraro No. 370, ofOctober 15th, from the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to the &quot;igh Commissioner in Egypt,and more particularly to paragraph 3, as follows:-&quot;I do not think it is necessary tohold that laws of neutralitynecessitate that passage of civil aircraft of belligerents carrying on ordinary peaceful service unconnected with war should be forbidden.    Italy has no treaty right applicable inpresent circumstances for any civil aircraft to fly over egypt or theSudan. ....... However, it is unlikelyin the present case that any Italiancivil aircraft which have nothing todo with the war will be flying overEgypt and the Sudan.   Therefore itis not considered necessary or desirable for Egypt or the Sudanto declare that they will neverpermit during present hostilitiesany flying over their territory by italian civil aircraft, though this can be reconsidered if Leaguerecommends any measures with regardto Italian civil aircraft.    egypt and Wudan should., however, make sure in connexion with any appliea-tion for any Italian civil aircraft to fly over their territory that the flight has nothing to do with the war&quot;.Re recalled that at the meeting referred to in the margin he had mentioned, that a large mail was shippedby the Italians by Imperial Airways&apos; to Khartoum,where there was an Italian spur line which carriedit to Eritrea.    It would not be right to assume thatthis mail was not connected with the war.   TheItalians had the right to run this spur line into their own colony.   To stop it would be most provoca-tive and would probably result in immediate retaliation-tion against Imperial A-irways, who always had twoflying-boats at Brindisi, the seizure or detention of which would completely dislocate their service.He hoped, therefore, that the natter might be further considered, and that in any- event a warning shouldbe sent to Sir Miles Lamps on to take no action atKhartoum for the moment.-12-
The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should, send, animmediate warning to Sir Mileslamps on to take steps to avoid any action on the telegram affectingthe Italian, air line from Khartoumto Eritrea:fb) That the question should be remitted to the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs and. the Secretary of Statefor Air, who should report to theCabinet if and when they should think any change of policy to berequired.
mpE TTAXO-DISPUTE.Broadcasting.PA6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,in reply to a- question as to why Baron Aloisi had been refused facilities for broadcasting to America, on a recent occasion, explained that only half an hourbefore the broadcast was    to&apos; take place he had been consulted, on the matter.    The break at Geneva hadtaken place that very day.   Be had felt- that thenotice given to him was much too short *   For example,if the broadcast was to take place it seemed that both sides should have the same facilities.   He had felt, therefore, that in the cireurastanr-es the onlydecision he could take was to veto facilities,mhe Cabinet approved the actionof the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.
flirp! ATLANTIC 7.    The Cabinet again had before them the followingaTR ROUTR.documents on the subject of the Atlantic Air Route:-(previous Memoranda by the Secretary of state or Air (C.P.-164 (35) and C.P.-18Stjg-e pr-ance:Cabinet 44 (35)) :(35)    Gon-elusion ?,.) A Memorandum bv the Lord Privv Seal(C.P.-184 (35)).These Papers had been considered at some length atthe Meeting referred to in the margin, when it wasagreed that the Prime Minister, the Secretary ofState for Air and other Ministers should see thePrime Minister of Wort-hern Ireland and discuss withhim the question of the site of the proposed base in Ireland at an early date.The Secretary of State for Air reportedthat the whole position of the Trans-AtlanticAir Route, including the international aspects,had been explained to uhe Prime Minister ofNorthern Ireland who had been most reasonable andhelpful, taking the line that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment must take whatever action was right.He had urged, however,  that if the decision shouldbe to establish the aerodrome in the Irish FreeState, it should be announced as having been taken on technical and not on political grounds.The next step was to carry out a technical surveyin both Northern Ireland and the Irish Free State.He himself proposed to keep in touch with lord craigavon who had suggested that if it was decidedto establish the aerodrome in the Irish Free State,it might be useful to have an alternativein Northern Ireland.The Lord Privy Seal, while accepting what-had been arranged, demurred to the suggestion-15-
that there were advantages in a landing place in theIrish Free State.      If the hest &quot;base technically wasin Galway he had nothing to say, hut he was not convinced by the argument that the aerodrome must besituated in the Irish Free State because otherwise the Government there would negotiate with France and .Germany.The Secretary of State for Air assured the Cabinet that he had evidence that France especiallywas anxious to establish a seaplane service for which theuse of an. Irish Free State base would be very valuable.The Cabinet agreed:(a) That the Secretary of State for air should arrange for a teclinical survey of alternative bases for aerodromes ofthe western terminus of the AtlanticAir Route to be carried out at once in the Irish Free State and NorthernIreland respectively.(b) That the Secretary of Statefor Air should keep in close touchv/ith the Prime Minister of NorthernIreland.(c) That the Irish Free State Governmentshould be informed that the survey was taking place in both territories.
loV?HNMBNT 0? 0.   In pursuance of the Conclusion mentioned in[*JBIA ACT,  1935.  the margin, the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum11 to Reprintt?.&apos;0 separate   by the Secretary of State for India (C.P.-I91 (-35))jets, one relat-Lag to India and covering a forma] -Rill for the purpose of re or in tingl&apos;ne other tothe Government of India. Act, 1935, as two-separate[BurmaActs, one relating to India and the other to Burma.In order to save time the Secretary of State sought(previous[Reference,[cabihet 43[(35), Con- authority to proceed with the Bill in the form to be[elusion 3.)approved by the Committee of Home Affairs withoutfurther sanction, from the Cabinet.The Cabinet approved the proposal of the Secretary of State forIndia as set forth above.
tfWEPIT A110W-flOFS FORHILDREN.previous reference:Cabinet 60 (33)Conclusion 3).dud-\io.9.      The Cabinet had before them a Note by theMinister of Labour (CP.-190 (55)) covering a Reportby the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committeecontaining a recommendation that the benefit- allow-ances for dependant children should be increased-from S/- to 3/- a we eh, to be met out of a disposablesurplus of about  lj millions a year in the possessionof the Unemployment Fund.   The Minister assumed thathis colleagues would agree that the Committee&apos;recommendation should be adopted, but, owing toreactions on the Unemployment Assistance Scheme, hesuggested that the actual operation of the increase should be postponed for a fe*? weeks by holding back the House of Commons Resolution necessary for putting the Order into effect.   mhe Report further recommendedthat there should be a maximum, of 41/- to the weeklyamount of benefit in any case, but the Minister ofLabour asked, his colleagues to aiithori.se him to settle-this point of detail with the Chancellor of theExchequer.A short discussion revealed considerable difficulties of a political character, and theCabinet agreed:(a) That the question should be referredto the Cabinet Committee on theRegulations of the unemployment assistance Board which would discuss it in a preliminary way the same afternoon.(b) That if the matter was not settledthat afternoon, the Committee should if possible hold a further meetingat which the Lord President of theCouncil (who was absent on public business) could be present.
HYDROGEN 10.     The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum byCYANIDE. , .     , s__ the Home Secretary (CP.-189 (35)) asking authorityproposedBill to to submit to the Committee of Feme Affairs a draftcontrol Useof   for Bill to confer power upon him to make, in consultationPuroos es ofFumigation,   with the Secretary of State for Scotland and theMinister of Health (and, where appropriate, any other minister specially interested), regulations governing the use of hydrogen cyanide for the purpose offumigation in enclosed spaces,   This gas was exceed-ingly lethal to human beings as well as to insectsand vermin:    its use in dwelling-houses appeared likely to become common:    and the desirability ofsome measure of control over its use had. for sometime been under examination.    It was also proposedto bring within the scope of the Bill one or two other dangerous gases which might be put to similarus e.The Cabinet agreed to the above proposal.
11.    The Cabinet agreed:That a Cabinet Committee composed asfollows:Mr. Neville Chamberlain(in the Chair),Sir John Simon,Mr.  J.H. Thomas,Mr. Malcolm MacDonald,Viscount Hailsham,Sir Kings ley v/ood,Mr. Ernest Brown,Mr. Walter Elliot,Lord Eustace Percy,should make recommendations as to items to be included in the Governmentselection programme.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,16th October, 1935.CABINETCOMMITTEE ONGOVERNMENTPOLICY.

</content>
</cab>
