<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/15/1 images: 10-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1941.SECEET. Copy No.W.P. (41) 28.February 8, 1941.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.THE &quot;ASAKA MARU.&quot;Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.THE case of the Asaka Maru presents His Majesty&apos;s Government, probably by design, with an awkward problem which, if mishandled, may have serious consequences.2. The ship is normally a cargo liner, but has been taken over by theJapanese Government, who are sending her to Lisbon manned by naval ratingsand flying the naval ensign. She is armed with two five-inch guns. She leftJapan on the 16th January and was due at the Panama Canal on the7th.February and at Lisbon on or about the 20th February. She was described by the Japanese Ministry of Marine in a communication to the naval attache atTokyo as &quot;a special service ship of the Imperial Japanese Navy sent to Lisbonon a Mission to protect Japanese residents in Europe and to transport changingmilitary and naval attaches to Embassies and Legations.&quot; It appears that shewill also be carrying about 30 members of the Japanese Naval Mission to Berlinas well as some &quot;observers&quot; to obtain technical information for the JapaneseNavy. In the communication to the naval attache referred to above the Ministryof Marine requested the &quot; whole-hearted co-operation of the Royal Navy in regardto the protection of the ship from any danger.&quot;3. In the words of Sir R. Craigie, this request for our protection for a shipbearing large numbers of officers going expressly to our enemies in Berlin toorganise a joint front against us &quot;is in itself impertinent.&quot; But apart fromthis, it is almost certain that the voyage of this ship is an attempt to breakthrough our blockade and that the excuse that the utilisation of the ship is dueto difficulty in obtaining facilities for the journey of the Naval Mission viaSiberia is a mere pretext. There is, in fact, evidence that the ship will be usedto take contraband, if not on her outward voyage to Lisbon, at any rate on. herreturn. The Japanese admit that the ship is &quot; taking some naval stores only toLisbon &quot; and that &quot; some cargo intended exclusively for the Japanese Navy willbe brought back, coming possibly, from France, Germany or Italy.&quot; Theseadmissions appear amply to confirm our reports that it is intended to ship fromLisbon 3,000 tons of machinery and some smaller items. It is also suspected thatit is intended to bring back in the same ship guns from the Oerlikon factory inSwitzerland.4.   Legal opinion has been sought as to the right of a belligerent to intercepta warship, and, broadly speaking, our view is that the normal immunity of awarship from contraband control is lost if she fails to confine herself to herfunctions as a vessel of war; and we should be the more justified in claiming the11288   [22212]
right of search in that in the recent case of the Nagora Mam, which we allowedto depart from Italy with certain German and Italian goods on board, we made it clear that this was the last occasion on which we could countenance enemyexports to Japan.5. From the point of view of economic warfare all the arguments are thus in favour of intercepting the ship. To allow her through would open the way toa new and serious leak in the blockade and, in Sir R. Craigie&apos;s view, if theJapanese succeed in this case they will resort to the same methods on an increasedscale. This in itself is perhaps of less importance than the effect which mightbe produced elsewhere if it became known that we had knowingly allowed theblockade to be evaded in this way. The Argentines are preparing to send a navalauxiliary to fetch some German war material which they desire, and we are onlyproposing to allow them to have it in return for concessions satisfactory to ourselves. The Brazilians are deeply dissatisfied with our refusal to allow themto have more German arms. The Chileans are pressing us for German arms andother goods. If we permit the Japanese to make this shipment it will be almost impossible to maintain our control of enemy exports to South America in anything approaching its present state of efficiency, and&apos; the way will be open to a floodof German exports with all the consequent benefit to the enemy and loss to ourselves. Indeed, it is probably not an exaggeration to say that a system couldbe rapidly organised which would practically stultify our control.6. The objections to interception are essentially political. Sir R. Craigiehas expressed the view that the strongest possible reaction is to be expected ifthis vessel flying the Japanese naval ensign is intercepted, and that, as the vesselmay be expected to resist, a first-class incident may be anticipated.7. The question turns largely on whether the Japanese are prepared, on grounds of major policy, to join Germany in the war against us in the immediatefuture. Unless they are so prepared we could no doubt afford, without unduerisk, to take a firm line towards any attempt such as this to break our blockade.But if they are ready for war with us action against the Asaka Maru mightclearly provide the necessary spark and we might thus be placed at a serious disadvantage vis-a-vis the United States. It is essential that, if we become involved in war with Japan, it shall be as the result of clear aggression by japan, and it would be disastrous, from the point of view of American sympathy and assistance, if it could be represented that we had provoked war on such an issue as the searching of the Asaka Maru, especially if the incident arose outof the control, not of enemy imports, but of enemy exports, the importance ofwhich is, unfortunately, not as yet fully appreciated in the United States.8. Viewed in this light it may be argued that the interception of a mere3,000 tons of machinery would certainly not be worth the risk, and that the best course would be to let the cargo pass and concentrate on so handling the matter that it did not become a dangerous precedent.9. Account must, however, be taken of the nature of the cargo. If theJapanese are bent on war the breaking of the blockade in itself will have no real value to them, and the explanation of their attempt to do so must in that case be sought in the intrinsic importance of the goods which they are endeavouring to bring away from Europe. It is possible, in fact, that themachinery may be of a type which is a vital necessity to the Japanese fleet.10. The request for protection is easily answered on the lines that, as theAsaka Maru is entering areas where our enemy is engaged in unrestricted seawarfare against us, we cannot undertake any responsibility for her safety. Ipropose, subject to the concurrence of the Cabinet, to instruct Sir R. Craigieaccordingly.11. To this it would be possible to add a communication on the following lines :  In view of the Japanese statement that the ship will be carrying cargofrom Lisbon, His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot regard her as immune from control and must insist on the normal proof that the cargo is not of enemy origin; that is to say, that it should be covered by certificates of origin and interest issued by His Majesty&apos;s consular officers.   As the Japanese Govern-
ment are aware, His Majesty&apos;s Government only permitted the shipment ofcertain goods in the Nagara Maru on condition that no further enemy exports were shipped. To this decision His Majesty&apos;s Government must adhere, andif goods of enemy origin are to be on board they will hold themselves free to intercept the ship, seize the goods and place them in prize.12. But to state our intention without attempting to carry it out, or to reserve a right without exercising it, seems likely to have every disadvantage. Mycolleagues will doubtless agree, therefore, that whether any communicationregarding interception is made must depend on whether we are in fact preparedto intercept the ship in the last resort. If we are not prepared to do so it may bebetter to blink the fact that cargo is being carried and to say nothing, at all eventsuntil interception is no longer physically practicable, when a protest might benecessary to save us from admitting an awkward precedent.13. When we first suspected that the Japanese were preparing to utilisethe Asaka Maru for the shipment of goods, Lord Halifax was instructed toexplain our suspicions to the United States authorities and to ask whether theywould be prepared to ascertain whether the vessel was carrying cargo when shepassed through the Panama Canal. I have not yet received any report on there actions of the United States authorities to this proposal. Before coming to adecision on the larger question, my colleagues may wish to try to ascertain howfar the United States Government and the President himself would consider itjustifiable to take the risk of war implicit in any attempt to subject the AsakaMaru to contraband control. If this is agreed I would propose to telegraphaccordingly to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington simultaneously withinstructing Sir R. Craigie to make a communication to the Japanese Governmentconfined solely to the question of protection on the lines of paragraph 10 above.I would also propose to inform His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Lisbon of theposition and to request him to institute all possible enquiries into the nature ofthe cargo which the A saka Maru intends to take on board there.A. E.February 8, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
