<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/83/36 images: 380-390</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   	CABINET

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet \\yij held at 10 Downing Street on      j/\THURSDAY 6 NOVEMBER 1986 at 9.30 am Y/yO PRESENT	

The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP Prime Minister	

L Rt Hon Viscount Whitelaw //&apos;~\\ lord President of the Council (a.	The Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St Marylebone Lord Chancellor

he Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC VZyVy [ecretary of State for Foreign anfry^jl jommonwealth Affairs ly1&apos;	The Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP Chancellor of the Exchequer

&lt;y the Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP ecretary of State for the Home Departnj	vyy The Rt Hon Peter Walker MP   t^j^^VSecretary of State for Energy Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MP yO^psetary of State for Wales

[he Rt Hon George Younger MP secretary of State for Defence	

[he Rt Hon John Biffen MP Lord Privy Seal the Rt Hon Norman Tebbit MP Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster	The^Xv.Hon Norman Fowler MP Sd&lt;?re^ry of State for Social Services The Rri^ipa-vTom King MP Secret5  ?^of State for Northern Ireland

the Rt Hon Michael Jopling MP Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and	The Rt HW^Nicholas Ridley MP Food SecretaryMf State for the Environment

the Rt Hon Lord Young of Graffham Secretary of State for Employment	The Rt Hon KennetlvBaker MP Secretary of Staifyior Education and Science

the Rt Hon Kenneth Clarke QC MP paymaster General	The Rt Hon John MaWirMor MP Chief Secretary,

the Rt Hon Malcolm Rifkind QC MP Secretary of State for Scotland	The Rt Hon Paul Channcvrr&gt;jfK Secretary of State for^fr&amp;N^ and Industry

The Rt Hon John Moore MP Secretary of State for Transport	

	ALSO PRESENT

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury	


   	SECRETARIAT		

%	Sir Robert Armstrong * Mr D F Williamson (Items 3 y\ Mr J B Unwin (Item 5)	and 4 )	

	sOv Mr A J Wiggins (Item 5) Mr A J Langdon (Items 1	and 2 )	

	Mr N H Nicholls (Items 3	and 4 )	

	Mr M J Eland (items 1	and 2 )	

	CONTENTS		

tem	Subject		Page

	PARLIAMENT^AFFAIRS		1

			

2.	HOME AFFAIR^/X?		

	Anniversary of the Anglo-Irish Agreement		1

	Teachers&apos; Pay, Duties and Conditions of Service		1

	Acquired lmmur^De(ficiency Syndrome (AIDS)		2

	Rate Support Graq^O)^ FOREIGN AFFAIRS [y^\		2

3.			

	United States Arms Control		2 3

	s-u		3

	Mozambique		4

	Ws  B  		/.

	Falkland Islands Fisheries /y		-T

	WgL		

4.	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS		c:

	Employment Initiative		j

	Fisheries		5

	Exports of Lamb to France /V*		5

1	PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEY 1986	III	6


   1. THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Cabinet would wish to congratulate i	the business managers in both Houses on the way in which a particularly

i A	heavy legislative programme had been brought to a successful conclusion.

The Cabinet -

j.	Congratulated the business managers on the ^^/   k.uccess ful completion of the legislative programme.

%

Lome affairs 2. thk^ecretary of state for northern Ireland said that the

[	__ anniversary of the signing of the Anglo-Irish Agreement fell on

[nniversary	15 November. A number of unionist protest rallies were being organised

L the	to mark the event. One event that had some disturbing overtones was a

Inelo-lrish &quot;service of dedi   a^4on&quot; in the Ulster Hall which was being organised [greement	under the auspices Uf the Free Presbyterian Church in which the

Democratic Uniorttki^PArty leadership were predominant. The meeting, which would be addj^e^wl by Mr Paisley, was being organised with great secrecy, and offic&apos;ira%^  /nionists were being excluded from attending. As far as wider action &lt;vafj^^ncerned, it was not thought that strikes were being planned althougb^treke would undoubtedly be sporadic attempts to set up road blocks and^tdk^pther disruptive action. Positive steps would be taken to counte^X^k and the Royal Ulster Constabulary were prepared to move in speed^y^y)

V/)

WMm |g mm

Teachers    Pay, THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EDUCA^iO^^D SCIENCE said that union Duties and	attitudes towards the Government    	on teachers    pay were now

Conditions of	crystallising. The National Union	hoOl Masters/Union of	Women

Services	Teachers had made it clear that thei&apos;c-^e^iand was for a 50 per	cent

increase in payj that would be widely ^ep^^as unreasonable and could Previous	only assist the Government in the pres^iation of their case. The

Reference:	National Association of Head Teachers	haw indicated general support	for

CC(86) 35.5	the offer, although at a meeting with	him later that day they	would	no

doubt wish to discuss further some points of detail. The Professional Association of Teachers were likely to indicat^^support for the offer. The other main unions had rejected it. The Conservative members of the management panel of the Burnham Committee werery^TSying that the Government offer should be brought into consider^t^pn/^t the forthcoming meeting of the Committee in Nottingham. This was	to be resisted

by Labour members and the main unions. It was too ea&apos;My/io predict how this conflict would end, although the Conservative meiM^&apos;^V^had threatened to walk out if the offer was not considered. ^JrOthe meantime he was making every effort to put across the terms of tb^^wprnment offer to the teachers themselves. He had written to all ^(  e^Utaachers asking them to draw the letter to the attention of their st^ftf^and all national newspapers that morning carried full page advertis^i^ewty^v explaining the terms of the Government offer in some detail,


   THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND said that in Scotland the union &apos;ywCx   reaction had concentrated on the phasing of the proposed increase, to

which they were hostile; public reaction had been more favourable. The key event now was the ballot of all teachers in Scotland, the results of //Which were expected in about two weeks&apos; time.

H9

L     ed	THIyj&amp;&apos;MlE MINISTER	informed the Cabinet that a Sub-Committee of the Home

fqU1	ancTSod^al Affairs	Committee had been set up, under the chairmanship of

p   	the ^^d^resident	of the Council, to consider and co-ordinate proposals

I! d^me	for me^Sur^A to limit the spread of the AIDS virus in the United Kingdom

f   Dg)	and to	with its effects. Although the question of AIDS was now

being gi^.n very extensive coverage by the media, much more would need to be done to make the public aware of the full extent of the problem.

(p)	   

(ate Support THE SECRETARY OF	FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that a difficult

|rant	situation was deve^ttwith a number of Government supporters in the

House of Commons whtf^ep^esented areas that did not do well under the Previous	rate support grant se^^^ent that he proposed to make for 1987-88. It

Reference:	was too early yet to d^^^^Jiow far these members might carry their

  CC(86) 14.1	protest, but anything thaZ^ede difficulties for the passage of the Bill

that would be needed in T^^iotthcoming Session to abolish local government grant recycling^w^^\clearly be a verY serious matter.

Under the formula embedded	Local Government Planning and Land Act

1980 it was inevitable that g^ap-t^vas diverted from the higher resource areas to the poorer ones and	of ingenuity could prevent that

effect, which was disproportiona  eiV&gt; suffered by local authority areas represented by Government support^^s^j^Overspending was also a factor in the situation:	if authorities spent/^efspons ibly there should generally

be no need for high rate increases.	local authorities commi11ed

themselves to large wage increases the&gt;yoyesrnment should not subsidise them. He was seeing every Government &apos;Mpfiorter in the House of Commons whose constituency was significantly afb^cted, and was explaining to them the background that he had described.

The Cabinet -	/x   n\

2. Took note.

I

IforEIGN	3. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thapublican

   AFFAIRS	Party in the United States had fared worse in the mid-t^m^lections

than had been expected:	the Democrats would enjoy a maji^itjnof eight

   United States or ten seats in the Senate and had increased their repres  NEwpd^Qti in the House of Representatives. This was a substantial setback	United

States President, who had campaiged hard; and, although he n^dxte^lared


   his intention to continue with his present policies, his position would be weakened. It was likely that the United Kingdom and European Community would encounter greater difficulties over trade. On the other hand, the results might strengthen United States perceptions of European concerns over defence and arms control. The expected assumption of the &apos;s&apos;^Vv&gt;chairmanship of the Senate Armed Services Committee by Senator Nunn, who \\V/  tas sensitive to the importance of the European link, would be helpful.

/orfWscussion, it was noted that the Republicans had achieved a better Tr^iyji in the gubernatorial elections, where personalities might have

for more. It was thought that agriculture had had an important ef    eC^2ti the election results.

X

Arms Control THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that, while in Vienna

earlier in the^H&amp;ek for the opening of the review of the Conference on Previous	Security and/Co-Aeration in Europe, he had met the United States

Reference:	Secretary of &apos;SEa^g^NMr Shultz, and the Soviet Foreign Minister,

CC(86) 34.3 Mr Shevardnadzelfa^/Lell as a number of his European Community

counterparts. Ti*e^  pyiet Union were in confident mood, taking the line that the recent m^^tfra^at Reykjavik had resulted in agreement to all elements of their n4g^   iwing position and that the Strategic Defence Initiative (SDl) conVirvuMd the sole obstacle to an accord on nuclear arms control. They we^^^^o beginning once again to criticise the United Kingdom and Fran^aj^fpv not being prepared to participate in discussions about reductrs^ioi nuclear weapons.

The United States position fcfeajJiwL^ed unclear. The Administration refused to accept that insistence on cMjib^8oI remained an obstacle to progress.

It was disconcerting that Mr SWulJ^Oaad given imprecise answers when questioned about Administration ifemrjJKkng on nuclear arms reductions.

His European counterparts were eq^^^y-disturbed at the apparent United States failure to perceive the impMsSjwicuis for deterrence of the elimination of strategic nuclear weapon^; an&lt;^ were making separate representations to the United States winrernment.

In discussion it was noted that there were welcome signs that the United States Secretary of Defense, Mr Weinberger, sljitced British concerns about the proposal to eliminate ballistic miAdTms. He was hoping to be present when the Prime Minister met the Unit^d^Sya&lt;es President later that month. If so, he would be a useful ally, (fj)

\

Syria	THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that he hacp&gt;jfc  ken to

Mr Shultz and to his European Community counterparts aiwriifjmossible Previous	action against Syria in the wake of the recent convictic$  ^1&gt;p/Mr Nezar

Reference:	Hindawi (for attempting to sabotage an El Al flight from Ift^aAnQow

CC(86) 35.3 Airport). He had also raised the question of Syrian and L^v^dOsupport for terrorism with Mr Shevardnadze. There were signs that, wyap^.

^yy^S


   Xfyl/OsK European Community Foreign Ministers met in London on 10 November,

agreement would be reached on wider measures against Syria. The United states Government, while supportive, were anxious not to jeopardise their current attempts to secure the release of United States hostages the Lebanon. They had not been forthcoming about the recent reports, ^^ivich had not been officially denied, that they had been in contact with Iranian Government. There were signs of a shift in United States &apos;^^7icy towards the supply of arms to Iran, which now seemed to be linked Iran&apos;s ceasing to support terrorism than to the Gulf War. The l^^yere being equally reticent about their reported contacts with SyHa\a^i Iran, designed to secure the release of their hostages in the

Lebafxjp^^)

In disdj^^yon, it was noted that there had been no change in the United KingdomV\policy of refusing to supply arms to either Iraq or Iran which would enhance their offensive capability. It was noted also that the two British hostages believed still to be held in the Lebanon were in the hands of one^-af the more intractable groups.

||||

iozambique THE FOREIGN AND Coi^^ALTH SECRETARY said that Mr Joaquim Chissano, previously the Foreigif^J&amp;vister, had been appointed President of Previous	Mozambique. This was&lt;  ^bly the least bad outcome for the West.

Seference:	//sK

fcc(86) 34.3	Yyj)

%

Falkland	THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SEGR^TAkY said that Argentina was

Islands	predictably mounting an extens ive^^tpmat ic campaign against the

Fisheries	planned establishment of a fisherir&apos;es^onservation zone around the

Falkland Islands; Argentina would pu^ughthe matter at the meeting of previous	the Organisation of American States Tlw/r&lt;jllowing week. He had raised

Reference:	the matter with Mr Shultz. Although Mte^donservation arguments were

fcc(86) 35.3 generally understood, the United Kingdoms action had not been welcomed internationally. British diplomatic posts would continue to explain the reasons for the action, laying stress on the United Kingdom&apos;s preference for and efforts to achieve a multilateral fisheries arrangement in the South Atlantic.	^

The Cabinet -

Took note.	  //


   4.	THE PAYMASTER GENERAL said that there was a concerted effort by the AFFiCHwCv European Trade Union Confederation (ETUC), assisted by some of those responsible for social policy within the Commission, to derail the Employtftw^M United Kingdom&apos;s initiative on creating the conditions for employment lnitiat:SexyV\growth. This initiative had been put forward jointly by the United

^&apos;^XYKingdom, Italy and the Republic of Ireland, and at the informal meeting vTv^xff Social Affairs Ministers in Edinburgh it had obtained the broad &apos;,^/^u  port of all member states. The Trades Union Congress and the ETUC, /irowsVer, did not like the stress which was now being placed on de^Mlation, on facilitating small businesses and on other aspects of tne/MW approach. At least some members of the Social Affairs Dir&amp;erpttkte of the European Commission were identified with trade union viewsvon/Chese matters; the President of the Commission, Monsieur Delors^vtiowever, was supportive of the new ideas. It was the United Kingdom^residency&apos; s objective to keep the other member states on course and to seek to minimise the difficulties which the ETUC might raise in the period up to the European Council on 5-6 December and the Social Affairs Councid^Zbater in December.

mk

Fisheries	THE MINISTER OF AdftM&amp;J&amp;JRE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that at the

Fisheries Council on^yN^rember agreement had been reached on a regulation providing T&gt;evti2$ control over the operation of the common fisheries policy, incli^mi^the closing of a fishery when the total allowable catch was exhc&amp;gt^a and an increase in Commission inspectors&apos; powers. He considered thhrs^  ^tep forward which would be of value in checking over-fishing. Th^re^n^d been no discussion in the Council of the United Kingdom&apos;s dec is	declare a fisheries conservation zone

for the Falkland Islands, but   r^d&amp;scuss ions in the margins of the Council there had been support&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;rojJ^W  e British action.

HI

1f&gt;	: h

Exports of THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIESXAND FOOD said that excessive Lamb to	French inspections of British lamb seemed now to have been stopped. He

I France	would maintain the pressure in order to ensure that the improved

situation was maintained. Pressure from Fren^h^heep farmers might be I Previous	reduced if there were a decision in BrusselsZ/tfilan week to make an

I Reference:	advance payment of premium. He was considering	separately whether

ICC (86) 33.4 the United Kingdom should step up its inspections^! imports of Golden Delicious apples.

The Cabinet -

Took note.


   I i&gt;/\	5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Lord President of the

   pEN^S^&gt; Council (C(86) 22) about the 1986 Public Expenditure Survey.

JURVEY	the LorD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that at their meeting on 17 July

I . g &apos;\^/^he Cabinet had agreed that the Chief Secretary, Treasury and spending I leviou ^	in carrying forward discussions of the 1986 Survey, should

MafiWS 7	within the published planning totals of   144 billion for 1987-88

&apos;C   b &apos;	&lt;^rtX^149 billion for 1988-89, and within a newly set planning total of

rb6) 32 2   J^&gt;lllion for 1989-90. Settlements had been reached bilaterally [	&quot;	beb^i^the Chief Secretary, Treasury and the responsible spending

Minisi^s covering a considerable number of programmes, but there had remai^f^ight programmes on which it had not proved possible for bilatera/\8   ttleraents to be reached. The Ministerial Group on Public Expenditure (MISC 130) which he had chaired had therefore been establish^! to tackle these remaining programmes, which by definition were the most difficult ones, with the objectives of reaching settlements and reducing the amounts of the additions. Following some very difficult cHSfcussions, the Group had agreed settlements on all the outstanding prc/graityies; but they had had less success in containing the additions to prbgfc^S&amp;ss. In practice they had had very little room for manoeuvre; the laffeept) elements in the upward pressures for additions to programmes came frb^^al authority current spending, which was outside Government1 s di^kd^p^^pntrol, and froro demand   led social security programmes, about whi^jK^vk Group could do practically nothing. Leaving aside previously agreeucui^a^f ions for demand   led social security expenditure, the Group ha^0Xminated nearly half the additional bids on the programmes they had c^ris^ia^red for 1987   88, about 70 per cent for 1988-89, and about 60 per Pa^^Vr 1989-90. It had not been an easy task, and spending MinisterSy^g^een pressed to the limit of what was politically sustainable. Thk^di^fAculties Qf containing additional bids had increased in each success iVe    ^rVey, and future years would be no easier. He was grateful to his iroU^gues on the Group for the work they had done, and to the spending^Min^ters concerned for their goodwill and forbearance. He commep^k^Lp the Cabinet the settlements reached by the Group, and those previ^oi^ concluded bilaterally by the Chief Secretary, Treasury.	  /V/

THE CHIEF SECRETARY, TREASURY expressed wis gratitude to the Lord President of the Council and the other members of the Group for the help they had given, and to his colleagues responsible for spending programmes for the substantial reductions they/^a^\accepted in their additional bids. He endorsed the Lord PresiddWt dfthe Council&apos;s comments about the difficulties presented by loi^i/^u&apos;^hority expenditure and the social security programme. Difficulties (ui^t/i^se areas were also affecting expenditure in the current year; heT^j^/expected a planning total outturn of   140.4 billion, as against^/i^^^published planning total of   139.1 billion. He had had to acce^i^^^itions of   5.8 billion to programmes, as against the available Reskpv^of   4.5 billion; the main factors were local authority current agwjepwiture (an excess of   2.8 billion, or 9 per cent), local authority	(  0.5

billion) and social security (  1.5 billion). Colleagues slwjH^^do their utmost to avoid any further claims on the Reserve, which wa^^^rpedy far


   overspent; indeed, all possibilities for savings should be energetically pursued, whether or not there was any question of the programmes concerned of further claims on the Reserve.

A. THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the outcome of the Survey

fvyepresented a serious problem for the Government, not least in the

^^Lnancial markets. He was grateful to the Lord President of the Council the other members of MISC 130, and agreed that the settlements they /^rad^keached were at the limits of political feasibility. But there was n^^  aping the fact that the additions to programmes exceeded the ava^^Dle Reserves in all three Survey years. Moreover it was essential titute credible Reserves which had to be added to the revised prog  immgOtotals. The privatisation programme was going well, and it would&lt;berreasonable to assume a small increase in projected receipts in each Sup/ey year from   4.75 billion to   5.0 billion. Given that the revised programme totals now incorporated realistic provision for local authority current expenditure, and an adequate allowance for demand-led expenditure oa^Sbcial security benefits, rather lower Reserve figures could be c on tiemp lilted than were shown in the 1986 White Paper; on this basis an approp^ib^v allowance might be   3.5 billion for 1987-88,   5.5 billion for 198^\8j)/imd   7.5 billion for 1989-90. This meant that the planning totals wojwi/need to be increased by   4.7 billion for 1987-88,   5.5 billion for nf&amp;^^^vand   8.3 billion for 1989-90.

Great care would be neeifed^in presenting these increases in the planning totals, and in rebuttin^idixyisations of pre-Election laxity. He would make clear that realistrc^_fjramres had been included for programmes which the Government were not ih   ^rriVsition to control; that continuing restraint had been shown onAowu^K programmes, and where there were increases these represented	iterate recognition of priorities; that

public expenditure would contiaa^vts steady fall since 1982-83 as a proportion of Gross Domestic Prodypt^GDP); and that there would be no relaxation in the Government&apos;s fxsc^d/stance as set out in the Medium Term Financial Strategy:	additiorfai-^fi&amp;nding would have to be fully

covered by additional tax receipts/Yiiieyitably this would have implications for the changes in taxa&amp;Ld^rto be made in the 1987 Budget, but it was too soon to assess the sizeOof any fiscal adjustment. The credibility of the Government&apos;s position on borrowing would be strengthened by economic developments during the current year; although the public expenditure outturn would be h ighej^-bh an projected in the 1986 Budget, increases in revenues (mainly Va^ue^Rdded Tax and Corporation Tax, offset by some reductions in^m/fc^evenues) should be sufficient to offset both the expenditure increaseland also the early repayment of   300 million of Advance Petroleum	Tax (APRT) during

the current year, so confirming the   7 billion foMOM^ for the Public Sector Borrowing Requirement made at the time of th^^^Vv Budget. In addition to the earlier repayment of APRT, which wouYif^^of particular help to smaller independent British oil companies and wK&amp;HiXwould require a short Bill to be introduced early in the new Be^s^on, the Autumn Statement would confirm national insurance contribufr^iiKrates at their present levels for 1987-88 and adjust the lower and ^  f^r^ancome limits in line with inflation.


   More generally, Che wider economic outlook was reasonably encouraging. y Although growth during the current year would be a little slower than forecast at the time of the Budget, the Autumn Statement would show /m per cent growth of the GDP in 1987, with manufacturing production, ^  fen-oil exports and investment all going ahead at a reasonable rate //vStengside continuing strong growth of consumers&apos; expenditure (growth \\d&lt;iring 1986 was particularly heavily dependent on consumers&apos;

&lt;^wWe^Liture). Exports should over time respond to the fall in the efccliapge rate in recent months, but in the short term, before these eff^isSworked through, the immediate impact of the exchange rate moveme^OI9uld be a deterioration in the trade balance. A current accouifTdipicit of   1.5 billion was thus forecast for 1987, as against a positiod%^%road balance during the current year. Despite the fall in the exchMp rate, however, only a small upward movement in inflation was in prafepect, to about 3.75 per cent in the fourth quarter of 1987.

In accordance with established practice, no forecast would be given of unemployment; but the measures taken by the Department of Employment, together with tbf^^celeration in economic growth, offered the prospect of some downwammdi^ement.

In discussion the^^^^cjwing main points were made    

a. The behavrouj^f local authorities was a continuing problem. Two-thirds of thVd^Skrrent expenditure was on pay, and of that expenditure two-tnir^^as on employees other than teachers, where local authorities h^^wn themselves all too ready to concede unjustified large in^eai^s, particularly to manual workers. Although they complaihe^^h&amp;ut increases in rates, or in fees and charges, they were unwi^Mfc^g^to accept the need for effective financial discipline; tlrttiU^sponse to financial pressures was to demand more assistance from p^iral Government rather than put ^ their own house in order.   tin^Jfhe less, given the Government s recognition of the need to giCs  e higher priority to education and housing, which were the responsK0pJJ-ty of local authorities, care would need to be taken in critiCi^^g their activities.

b.	In those areas where the Gove^rfment exerted the primary

authority, priority had been given w expenditure on health, housing, roads and law and order programmes. Expenditure on housing   would be sustained by the recent large increase in the flow of receipts from sales of local authority/jien&amp;es, new town assets and other properties.	^.

c.	The factors behind the rising trend of	expenditure

would produce continuing problems in future yS^W. Where programmes (eg the Department of Trade and Indus^^Kcould readily cut back, this had already been achieved in the	of recent

Surveys. If significant reductions were to be made^^future, these would need to be concentrated on the main soo;^W/sJecurity, health, defence and housing programmes, where the l^te^^amounts of money were at stake.


   /\ THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up Che discussion, said that the Cabinet

thanked the Lord President of the Council and the other members of MISC 130 most warmly for their work. The 1986 Survey had been difficult for X^/v\all Ministers concerned. The Cabinet approved the settlements of all \\V/phe individual programmes, both those concluded bilaterally with the /^T&lt;iK^,ef Secretary, Treasury and those arrived at in the course of the work NX/o^/MISC 130. They recognised that much of the difficulty faced by the &lt;  ^4poment resulted from local authority current expenditure, over which tney&apos;r&amp;d no direct control, and from demand-led social security progj^flwes. Where the Government were in a position to make clear policy/^ioices, the settlements had been tough, and such increases as had b^&amp;nr^^reed were carefully directed towards specific purposes to which th^/G&lt;yyernment attached priority. The Cabinet also accepted the need to&apos;&apos;P^e&apos;onstitute the Reserves for each of the Survey years, and thereforevagreed the additions to the planning totals proposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer:	the programme figures were realistic,

particularly bearing in mind the pressures arising on the local authority curreirb   expenditure and social security programmes; for the rest; and the Government&apos;s decisions were responsible and carefully costed, and dire&lt;$  dl3*pwards clearly identified priorities. The Cabinet agreed that the Cli^nc^jLlor of the Exchequer should make his Autumn Statement that aftWinxin, covering the results of the Survey, the forecast for 1987 aiwm^ 1 imited fiscal measures he had outlined. The printed version of th^^^wtnent, together with the appropriate supporting material, wodT^Ka published when Parliament resumed on 12 November; meanwhile pre^f/frotices would be issued that afternoon by the responsible Departmen^v/se)t)ting out the main elements in their programmes over the three tHffyp^Nyears. In order to ensure consistency of presentation, the Chanceli^f\vv the Exchequer should circulate the text of his Statement to Cabin^,t/^olleagues in time for them to draw on it in presenting their own progdaam^Ss that afternoon.

The Cabinet -

1.	Endorsed the Prime Ministeri3c5?*Pression   f thanks to the Lord President of the Coun&lt;yjA^Sd the other members of the Ministerial Group oini&apos;ublic Expenditure.

2.	Approved the settlements of the individual programmes as set out in paragraphs 8 to 16 of C(86) 22 and in Annex B to that paper.

3.	Agreed the revised planning totals or^lwSTyi billion

for 1987-88,   154.2 billion for 1988-89 and	bill ion

for 1989-90, as proposed by the Chancellor or&apos;Ci^ Exchequer.

4.	Agreed that the results of the Survey, togecfr^Cyj.th the economic forecast for 1987, should be announced^

Parliament in the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s AutdajH/&apos;VN,

Statement that afternoon, the printed text of which,\vy/A together with appropriate supporting material, would published on 12 November.	V

Cabinet Office

6 November 1986



</content>
</cab>
