<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/55/0 images: 154-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AGENDA.1,      REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS -THE NAVAL CONFERENCE.   &apos;   (If required).(Reference Cabinet 40 (27) Conclusion 3).&apos;Extract from iviinutes of 229th Meeting ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence.(CP. 204 (27)    -    circulated herewith).See also Telegram to the First Lord of the- Admiralty from the Prime Minister, No. 125of 15th July, 1927.2.      EGYPT.(Question to be raised by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs).3.       MILITARY CONTRIBUTIONS BY COLONIAL AND OTHERGOVERNMENTS. &apos;Memorandum by the Secretary of State forWar.(CP, 197 (27)    *   already circulated).4.   .   THE POLITICAL SITUATION IN CYPRUS.Memorandum by the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.(CP. 198 (27)    -   already circulated).REPRESENTATION IN THE DOMINIONS OF HIS MAJESTY&apos;SGOVERNMENT  IN GREAT BRITAIN.(Reference Cabinet 31 (27) Conclusion 3).Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP%. 202 &quot;(27)    -   circulated herewith).6.      THE EMPIRE MARKETING BOARD.(Question to be raised by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer).(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC i-iaJESTY TS GOVERNMENT) .SEC RET. Copy No,ICABINET    41  (27),Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, -20th July,  1927, at 11.30 a.m.
150f78      THE POSITION  OP THE IRON AND STEEL INDUSTRY.Memorandum &quot;by the President of the Boardof Trade.(CP,  201 (27)    -   already circulated).8&quot;      THE ISLE OF MAN CUSTOMS BILL.Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury covering draft Bill.(CP. 199  (27 )    -   already circulated).9o      ROAD CONVEYANCE  OF PASSENGERS AND GOODS BYR&quot;A I Eg aT&quot;&quot;C&quot;QMPANIES .Memorandum by the Minister of Transport.(CP.  200 (27)    -   already circulated).10.      WASHINGTON HOURS CONVENTION..Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP. 206 (27)    -    circulated herewith).TO TAKE NOTE OF :-11.      AIR RAIDS PRECAUTIONS.Extract from the 229th Minutes of theCommittee of Imperial Defence togetherwith interim Report of Sub-Committee.(CP.  205 (27)    -    circulated herewith)..  (Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.18th July,  1927.   .
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S govern-aENT)S E C R E T. Copy No.CABINET    41 (27).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10,Downing Street, S.W.I., on &quot;WEDNESDAY,July 20th, 1927, at 11.30 a,m.ADDENDUM TO THE AGENDA.PREPARATION OF THE ARMY FOR WAR.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War(CP. 207 (27)    -   circulated herewith).(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet,.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.19th July,  1927.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIJ MAJESTYfb GOVERNMENT).RET,copy no,C A B I HJ T    41 (27).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, ..-.S.W.1., on WEDNESDAY,20th July, 1927, at 11.30 a.m.PRESENT;-The Right Hon. -Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in.the Chair).he Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P., Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.he Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K. G .., G . C. V. Q .., C . Bc fLord Privy Seal.Ihe Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary of Statefor Home Affairs.fhe Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bt.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.phe Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,C.M.G.,MoPo, Secretary of Statefor Air.[The Right,Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E. ,M.C.,M.P. , Presidentof the Bo a:--d of Trade.[The Right Hon.W.E. Guinness, D.S.0 ,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.pie Right ,Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Viscount Cave, G-.C.M.G..,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C .H.,, M. P..,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.L.S. Apery, M.P.., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.Sir&quot; John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S. 0.,,ift.P., Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon,Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,First Commissioner of Works.mThe Right Hon..Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.. ,M.P.,Attorney-General.*   .*   wSir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.secretary.
1. The Cabinet had before them the following documents on the subject of Reduction and limitation of Naval Armaments:-An Extract from the Minutesof the 229th Meeting of theCommittee of Imperial Defence(Paper C.P.-204 (27)):The Prime Minister informed his colleagues that the Cabinet Committee had held a number ofanxious deliberations in regard to the proceedings at Geneva, and had on the previous day come tothe conclusion that it was desirable to bringthe British Delegates home for consultation.Ke thought it would be necessary to hold aSpecial Meeting of the Cabinet on FRIDAY afternoon.The Secretary of State for War asked thathe might be excused from attendance at thisMeeting of the Cabinet, as he was due that day at Tidworth in connection with the MechanisedBrigade.The Secretary of State for Dominion affairs said he also would be unable to be present, ashis ship was due to sail from Southampton at p.m- for his visit to the Dominions.The Cabinet agreed  )That a Special Meeting should beheld for the consideration of thequestion of REDUCTION AND LIMITA-TION OF NAVAL ARMAMENTS on FRIDAY,July 22nd, 1927, at 2-30 p.nu atTHE HOUSE OP COMMONS.
2. The Cabinet had before them a   Memorandumby the Minister of Labour on the subject of theY/ashington Hours Convention (Paper CP.-206 (27)).In his Memorandum the Minister of Labourexplained that on May 4th, 1927 (Cabinet 30 (27),Conclusion 3), the Cabinet had authorised him to consult the Employers1 representatives privatelyin order to ascertain their views upon the way inwhich the Government proposed to deal with theHours question.    He had accordingly been in communication with the President of the Employers1Confederation, and had received lengthy documentsstating their grounds for opposition to ratifica-tion.     The main reasons wh.v the Confederationconcentrated upon opposition to the WashingtonConvention appeared to be -(i) They fear that although a &quot;sensible&quot;Hours Act might be passed now, theWashington Convention would still bein existence and might be used later on as a reason for mod if modifications inthe law;   and(ii) They do not regard the WashingtonConvention as a suitable basis foran attempt at securing internationaluniformity of Hours.The Minister of Labour therefore proposed tcr theCabinet that he should see the Employers and tell them.that the view of the Cabinet was that, having;regard to the. history of sthe.matter since 1919,the Hours question must be dealt with and that theGovernment   invite the Employers to co-operate inthe framing of proposals which will be governed by two main considerations:-&apos;     -Cl) That, while embodying the principle ofthe 48-hour week, they should follow in the main the existing industrial conditions in this country and shouldbe calculated to interfere as little as possible with those conditions:
C2) That the proposals should form asuitable basis for a Conventiondesigned to secure greater inter-national uniformity of hours.The Minister of Labour made&quot;a statement tothe Cabinet in amplification of his Memorandum..The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Minister of Labour shouldcontinue his negotiations with theEmployers on the lines proposed inhis Memorandum:(b) That he should keep in close touchwith the Home Secretary on thesubject, since the Factories Bill,to be introduced next February,would be affected by the result ofhis negotiations:(c) To take&apos; note that the negotiations in their present stage were entirelyconfidential and that no statement could be made in Parliament.
3. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs reminded the Cabinet that at the previous meeting he had informed them of a preliminary conversa-tion he had had with Sarwat Pasha with a viewto exploring the possibilities of an Agreementwith Egypt, and had told them that it was too early as yet to say whether anything would result.He had since circulated a full account of the conversation (F.O., Egypt and Sudan. Oonfiden-tial. J.1934/8/16, of July 13th). SubsequentlySarwat Pasha had lunched with Sir austen chamberlain&quot; s Private Secretary (Mr Selby)to meet Sir William Tyrrell.   The latter had told Sarwat that the Secretary of State had inmind more particularly three questions on whicha settlement was desired:-(l) The Army.(2) The British advisers.(3) The responsibility of GreatBritain to see that foreignersand their property were safe-guarded.Sarwat Pasha had promised to think the matter over and to tr,y and produce the heads of anAgreement which might be acceptable to HisMajesty&apos;s Government.    If he could achieve this result he would return to Egypt for consultation and would subsequently join KingFuad on His Majesty1s visit to Rome, whencehe would come back to London.    Two days agoSarwat had called on Mr Selby and had handed him the heads of a possible Treaty of Alliance.Before doing so he had stated that he had, communicated the draft to King Fuad, who had approved the general idea.
Sir Austen Chamberlain said that he had hadSarwat Pasha&apos;s draft translated, and theoriginal, together * ith the translation, was now in the printer1s hands and would be circu-lated at once.    It was not a document which,in its present form, we could accept, but itmarked a great advance on the attitude of any previous Egyptian Government since 1922.    it seemed to show that Sarwat Pasha had beenattracted b:-/ Sir Austen&apos;s idea, and that he hoped to do business.    He himself had appointed a Committee in the Foreign Office, with whichhe had associated Lord Lloyd, with a view tothe examination of Sarwat&apos;s draft and the- preparation of alternative clauses where necessary.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs then gave the Cabinet the substance of the 12Articles of Sarwat&apos;s draft.    (As these areto be circulated the;/ are not reproduced in -these Minutes.)    Summing up, he emphasized thesigns which this draft gave of an intention,tomake a very serious overture, and laid stress on the immense advance it was on the attitudeof any previous Egyptian Government.    Sir Austenalso made clear that Sarwat Pasha was not in aposition to put it forward as an offer, as he did not yet know whether he could carry itin Egypt, but if he could reach some kind ofbasis of agreement here he would go back to egypt and try to obtain its acceptance. It, was most important that we should , go forward and discuss the heads of the Agreement, since
either its rejection or refusal to discuss itwould, when it became known, create a very strongadverse feeling in this country.    The foreign secretary asked that, before he resumed negotia-tions with Sarwat Pasha, the Cabinet should either themselves consider the proposal or, ifthey preferred,, appoint a Cabinet Committee toreport to them in the first instance-In the course of a short discussion theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs was askedto bear in mind the importance of securing an expert Adviser in the Ministry of the Interiorin Egypt;    of doing anything he could to safeguard the position of British officials engaged by theEgyptian Government;     and of our interest in Egyptfrom the point of view of communications, includingair communications and civil aviation.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,informed the Cabinet that, in reply to a question in Parliament, he was going to state that he hadnaturally taken advantage of Sarwat Pasha&apos;s presenoin this country to discuss-Anglo-Egyptian relationwith him, but that it was not Sarwat&apos;s intention,or his own, to conclude any Agreement during his visit.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the policy of an alliance with Egypt, provided that suitable terms could be agreed, while reservingabsolute freedom in regard to thedetails of Sarwat Pasha1 s scheme,which they had not yet seen in full:(b) That the Draft Agreement, with the comments of the Foreign Office thereon,should- be considered in the firstinstance by the following CabinetCommittee:-
The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (In the Chair),The Lord Privy Seal,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Home Secretary,The Secretary of State for War,The Secretary of State for India,The Secretary of State for Air,The First Lord of the Admiralty,The Attorney-General,Sir Maurice Hankey, G.C.B.(Secretary).-7-
4. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for War on the subjectof Military Contributions by Colonial and otherGovernments (Paper CP.-197 (27)).The Cabinet agreed  That a Committee, composed asfollows  The First Commissioner of Works(In the Chair) ,The Chancellor of the Exchequer(or Financial Secretary tothe Treasury),The Secretary of State for Scotland,The Parliamentary Under-Secretary,Colonial    Office,The Financial Secretary,War Office.Mr R. B.Howorth, CB.  (Secretary)should examine and report on theproposals of the Secretary of Statefor war, on the understanding thatthe present moment was not favourable for raising the question of a contri-bution from Egypt.
5.     The Cabinet had under consideration aMemorandum by the Secretary of State for theColonies on the subject of the PoliticalSituation in Cyprus (Paper C.P.-198(27)).After some discussion the Cabinet agreedThat the Secretary of State forthe Colonies should be placed in aposition to negotiate with the cyprus Government on the basis that(i) The British Government willrelieve Cyprus of the Tribute(92,800 per annum) applied to theservice of the Turkish GuaranteedLoan of 1855-, so long as it continues,by means of a grant-in-aid of an equivalent amount, Vyprus renouncingany claim on the invested surplusof the Tribute account:    and(ii) Cyprus will contribute 10,000 per annum as a contribution towards the cost of defence:so that the net additionalcharge on British funds shall notexceed  32,800 per annum as a maximumover and above the present grant-In-aid of  50,000.The above agreement was reached onthe understanding that the Secretary ofState for the colonies would do his best to maske reductions in the ColonialServices Estimates to compensate for the expenditure on Cyprus?
6.. The cabinet had before them the Report of aCabinet committee on the Representation in theDominions of His Majesty&apos;s Government in GreatBritain (Paper C*P. -202 (27)).    In their Reportthe Committee stated that they were generally infavour of proposals of the character put forward by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and submitted the following recommendations to theCabinet, bearing in mind that the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer had asked that it should be recordedthat his assent thereto was subject to the condi-tion that the total cost of a soheme of british representation in the Dominions as a whole, inclu-sive of establishments and other expenses, shouldnot exceed  10,000 per annum in the aggregate:-(a) That the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs should be authorised to sendforthwith an official reply to theGovernor-General of New Zealand&apos;telegram of June 2, 1927, to theeffect that the British Governmentconcur in the proposals contained therein and will accordingly arrangefor the appointment of a junior memberof the staff of the Foreign Office tothe Prime Minister&apos;s Department in few-Zealand in a consultative or informa-tive capacity but with no executive or administrative functions , and in no wayrepresentative of the British Govern-ment in a diplomatic sense;    and thatthe British Government are preparedto pa7/ his emoluments.(b) -That the Prime Minister should beinvited to take the opportunity ofhis forthcoming visit to Canada toconfer informally with the Governor-General and the Priie Minister ofCanada on the specific proposalsrespecting British Representation inthat Dominion outlined in paragraph6 of the Report of the Committee(Paper C.P.-202 (27)), viz:- Thatan Officer be appointed at Ottawarepresenting the British Government.The kind of arrangement discussed was .(i)-An Officer with status and emolu-ments equivalent to those of a minister or Senior Counsellor in the Diplomatic
Service ? and (ii) a junior withstatus and emoluments equivalentto those of a Second Secretary Inthe Diplomatic Service;   the BritishGovernment hope that the canadian government will be willing- to provideoffice accommodation for the british representative in one of their departments at Ottawa.   &quot;(c) That the financial bearing of theproposals (a) and (b) above shouldbe further examined by the Treasury,the Dominions Office and the ForeignOffice, in consultation.(d) That as regards the Union of SouthAfrica, the best arrangement would befor the Imperial Secretary to act asthe Representative of the EritishGovernment in South Africa, thedetails to be left for discussion between the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and the South Africanauthorities.(e) That, for the present, no further action should be taken regardingBritish representation in theCommonwealth of Australia, the Unionof South Africa (subject to (d) above)or the Irish Free State, but that theSecretary of State for DominionAffairs should be at liberty to examinethe question of British representationwith the Australian and South Africanauthorities respectively should befind it necessary or desirable to do&apos;so during his forthcoming visits tothose Doininions, and report to theCabinet.In giving their approval to the above proposals the Cabinet were in general agreement that the British representative in Canada shouldnot be regarded as being there to balance therepresentative of the United States of America,and inclined to the view that the representative should be placed on the Vote of the Cabinet office which, they were reminded, is a sub-head of the vote for the&apos;Treasury and Sub Departments.
7. The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed the Cabinet that the Cabinet Committee on Experdi-ture had been considering reductions in Depart-mental expenditure in order to cover the excessof expenditure over Estimates involved by the shanghai Defence Force.    There had already been .a considerable response to their recommendationsfrom the Minister of Health, the Secretary ofState for Air and the Secretary of State for War.One recommendation had been that a saving of 600,000 should be effected by reducing the grant to the Empire Marketing Board for 1927-28 from&quot; 1,000,000 to  400,000.    The Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs, however, had demurred to thisproposal.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer asked the Cabinet to approve the proposal and to authorisethe despatch of a telegram from the Prime Ministerof Or eat Britain to the Prime Ministers of theDominions in some such terms as the following: -&quot;We have been considering with someanxiet,y the financial position duringthe current year..   The Budget made provision for a balance of  1,400,000,but included nothing for the cost ofthe Shanghai Defence Force.    Themeasures which we have felt bound totake in the interests not merely ofGreat Britain but of the Empire as awhole in order to safeguaxd ourposition in China are likely to costnot less than  6,000,000 in&apos;all inextra expenditure, of which about 4,000,000 will fall in the current year, and the whole cost has to be met by the British taxpayer.We have been considering what economieson other Estimates can be made in orderto meet the Shanghai expenditure without involving a deficit for the thirdsuccessive year, which we feel wouldbe damaging to the country&apos;s interests.Among possible economies is a suggestion in regard to the funds of the empire marketing Board.    A million pounds isvoted as a grant in aid to the Board
this year, and this sum in additionto  350,000 carried forward unspentfrom last year would make the avail-able funds of the Board  1,350,000.The Board do not however, we areinformed, expect to spend this yearmore than three quarters of a million.If the actual issue from the vote forthis year were abated by  600,000 itwould give us a most sensible relief on our Budget, and at the same time would not restrict the execution ofthe Board&apos;s programme this year inany way.    To call upon the taxpayerto provide money before it can in fact be used to advantage is an obviousextravagance.   Having regard to thenature of the emergency which gives rise to this request, we trust&quot;youwill raise no objection to the pro-posal.  (Next year the full sum of one million pounds would be voted andwould be ample to meet any probableexpenditure by the Board.)We feel the less hesitation in askingyour concurrence in this requestbecause of the growing extension and effectiveness of our preferentialsystem.    Prom 4.7 million in 1925-6,the loss to Revenue which Preferencehas involved has amounted to no lessthan 6.2 million last year and isestimated to reach 6.5 million thisyear&quot;.In the course of the discussion it was explained that the Empire Marketing Board had only expended  150,000 out of the  500,000voted in 1926.     350,000 therefore had beencarried over to the present year, and the board would nominally have  1,350,000 to spend in1927.    The Board did not expeot to spend morethan  750,000 this year, so that the effect ofMr Churchill&apos;s proposal would be that the board would not carry forward a balance of  600,000to the financial year 1928-29.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explainedthat he only made this proposal as applicableto the present year and without prejudice.tothe general policy of carrying forward sums
unexpended by the Empire marketing Board in any year to the next financial year.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,while quite willing that the Exchequer should securethe relief Involved in withdrawing  600,000 fromthe carry forward account this year, providing that the Dominions could be informed that this money would ultimately be available, said thathe could not agree to the proposal in a form whichwas in fact making a request,which could not wellbe refused whatever might be thought, for release from our explicit pledge.     Such a step, he felt,would to a great extent stultify the work alreadyaccomplished by the Empii e Marketing Board;would create great Ill-feeling in the Dominions;and would achieve no economy in the presentyear or in the near future as compared with hisalternative.The subject was adjourned until the same afternoon.
BASIS OP ARMY 8. The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumESTIMATES.by the Se ore tar;/ of State for War in regard to(Previous the basis of the preparation of the Army for war,Reference:War Cab ins t (Paper CP. -207 (27)) in which he asked for an616A (1919).)* r early renewal of the decision taken by the WarCabinet in 1919, which was as follows:-&quot;It should be assumed, for framingrevised Estimates, that the BritishEmpire will not be engaged in any great war during the next ten years,and that no Expeditionary Porce isrequired for this purpose&quot;.The Secretary of State foruWar said hewould like to leave out the words after &quot;tenyears&quot;.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said that he had had little warning of thisquestion, and would like more tine to considerthe precise wording of any basis which was given.The Cabinet agreed -That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs and the Secretaryof State for War should concertthe precise wording to be given toa renewal of the decision of 1919,and that the. question should then bereferred to the Committee of ImperialDefence.    If the formula was approvedby the Committee of Imperial defence the Secretary of State for War shouldbe authorised to adopt it as the basis.of the Army Estimates.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I,July 20, 1927, ,

</content>
</cab>
