<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/55/0 images: 429-443</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANN10 MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)- SECRET - OOFf No.CABINET      60    (27).MEETING OF THE CABINET to be held at No.10, downing street,   S.-AM,  on WEDNESDAY, DECEMBER 7th,  1927, at11.30 a.m.AGENDA.1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS    (If required).2.    UNEMPLOYMENT IN THE COAL TRADE.(Reference:  Cabinet 59 (27), Conclusion 4).Interim Report of Cabinet Committee(CP.-302 (27) - To be circulated).3.    COMPETITION OF BEAM WIRELESS AND CABLE SERVICES.   [(Reference:  Cabinet 57   (27),  Conclusion 15).Interim Report of Cabinet Committee,(0.P.-303 (27) - Circulated herewith).4.    THE IRISH FREE STATE.    COMPENSATION CLAIMS UNDERARTICLE 10 OP THE ARTICLES OF AGREEMENT OF 1921.-Joint Memorandum by the Treasury and dominions office,(CP.-307 (27) - Circulated herewith).5.    NEGOTIATIONS FOR REVISION OF THE ANGLO-IRAQ, TREATY.Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of Statefor the Colonies,(C.P.-304 (27) - Circulated herewith).6.    MILITARY CONTRIBUTIONS OF COLONIAL AND OTHER GOVERNMENTS.(References:  Cabinet ^1 (27), Conclusion 4, and cabinet 45 (27), Conclusion 6.)Report of Cabinet Committee,(CP.-298 (27) -   Already circulated) .7 .   MALTING BARLEY TAX.Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries f(C.P.-301 (27) - Already circulated).(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,December 6, 1927. ...
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAWWTO MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT).SECRET.Copy No.CABINET    60 (27).CONCLUSIONS Of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10,Downing Street, S.V7.1., on WEDNESDAY, 7thDecember, 1927, at 11.30 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (In the Chair).The Right Hon.The Earl of Balfour, K.G.,0..M., Lord President ofthe Council.The Right Hon.The Viscount Cave, G.C.M.Gv,Lord Chancellor.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C.B., lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill,  C.H.,M.P.,Chancellor of the exchequer.The Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.,C .M..G. ,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O.,MwP.,  Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Ri ght Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board of-Education.The Right Hon.The Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,First Commissioner of works the Right Hon.W.E.&quot;Guinness, D.S.0.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland,Bt.,M.P.,  Minister of labour our.The Right Hon.Lord Cushendun,  Chancellorof the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.p.-JAttorney-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT: -fae -Right Hon.Sir W. Mitchell-Thomson, Bt.,K;B.E,M.P.,  Postmaster-General.(For Conclusion 2).Lord Lovat, K.T. ,K.C .M.G. ,K.C .V.0.,C.B. ,D.S . 0. ,. Parliamentary - Under-Secretary, Dominions Office.(For Conclusions 2 and 4).Colonel The Right Hon.G.R. Lane-Fox,  M.P.,Secretary for Mines.(For Conclusion 1).The right.Hon.W.G.A.  Ormsby-Gore,  M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary.Colonial Office.(For conclusions,  3,  and 5).
THE COAL 1. The Cabinet had before their, an Interim ReportSITUATION.  by the Cabinet Committee on Unemployment in theUnemploymentin the Coal Coal Trade (Paper C.P.-302 (27)), containing theTrade.following recommendations:-(Previous (i)  That the Minister of Labour should reference: schedule mining areas to which it-Cabinet 59 is thought necessary to apply(27), Con- emergency measures for the transferelusion 4.) of surplus labour.(ii)  That for the purpose of facilitating the transfer of labour from areas orindustries with contracted opportunities -ties for employment, a Board be setup to recommend the executive actionto be taken by the Departments con-cerned and to secure the co-operationof other areas and Industries at home or overseas.(iii) That the Minister of Labour shouldbe responsible to Parliament for thework of the Board.The above Report had only been circulatedlate on the previous evening, so that several members of the Cabinet had not had time to studyit.    In these circumstances the Lord Privy Sealand the Minister of Health were asked to explain the recommendations of the Report to the Cabinetin some detail,It was represented to the Cabinet that it-would not be right to take a final decision without taking more time to consider the matter, moreespecially in its financial aspects.   As yet no authoritative estimate had been made of thecost of the Committee&apos;s proposals, and the roughestimates suggested at the meeting were found to vary very considerably.    The urgency of taking adecision the same day, it was represented, was on grounds of Parliamentary expediency rather than on merits.    Even from, a Parliamentary point of view it was suggested that an Immediate decision was unnecessary.   The Cabinet were reminded of the   -danger, more particularly in a very difficult
financial situation such as exists at the presenttime,  of setting -up independent bodies with authority to expend money, as illustrated by theIrish Grants Committee, which had recommendedclaims amounting to  1,200,000 as compared withthe  400,000 originally allotted.The Cabinet were informed, however,  that,while the operations of the proposed Eoard would undoubtedly involve additional expenditure,this would be borne   by existing departments and be subject to Parliamentary approval in theusual way.After a discussion extending over thegreater part of the Meeting, the Cabinet agreed  (a) That the President of the Board ofTraOe, in the course of a speechthe saire afternoon presenting thepolicy of the Government in regardto miners&apos; unemployment as a whole,and after explaining the various measures already adopted for alls-viating the situation,  should have authority to state that the Govern-ment had decided to stimulate theoperation o^ the existing machinery and  that the Minister of Labour would set up a Eoard (as proposed by theCabinet Committee) with that specialobject.    He should make it clearthat the Eoard was not to have funds to expend on its own account, andthat the policy was designed to stimulate in certain districts theexisting machinery o^ Governmentfor these purposes and not for theexpenditure of money.    He should beauthorised to indicate that (as atthe present time) where unemployedminers had not the means to move in order to take up vacant postselsewhere, they would be helped,but he should be careful to avoid committing the Government to thoseforms of expenditure recommended bythe Cabinet Committee   which are noti authorised by existing legislation.He should also avoid mention of any? particular sum which might be made &apos;available for expenditure on this s ervlce:(b) That not more than  100,000 in the   .present financial year should be expended on the Cabinet Committee&apos;s
proposals, and that this figure should he kept secret for thepresent.
BEAM WXRELESS 2. The Cabinet had before them the Interim report and cable companies. of a Cabinet Committee on the subject of thecompetition of Beam Wireless and Cable Services(previous reference: (Paper C.P.-303 (27)), containing the followingCabinet 57(27), Con- recommendations:-elusion 15.)(a) To approve the proposals -(i) That an Inter-Imperial conference should be held in London as soonas possible, composed of repre-sentatlves of the Governmentsconcerned, namely -Great Britain,Canada,The Commonwealth of Australia,New Zealand,The Union of South Africa,India,and also of representatives of the  ,,Colonies and Protectorates.(ii) That the terms of reference ofthe proposed Inter-Imperial Con-ferenoe should be -&quot;To examine the situation whichhas arisen as a result of thecompetition of the Beam Wirelesswith the Cable Services, toreport thereon and to make recommendations with a viewto a common policy being adopted by the various Govern-ments concerned&quot;.(b)   To settle the representation of theBritish Government at the proposed conference.The Cabinet agreed  (i) To approve the recommendations in (a)above:(ii) As regards (b) above, that the repre-sentative of the British Governmentshould be of the highest calibre:(iii) That the invitation to the Conferenceand any announcement in regard to itshould be so worded as to make itclear that representation was limited  &apos;to those Governments which are inter-ested in cables, that is to say, the   .Governments mentioned in (a)(i) above(iv) That, with a view, if possible, to avoiding the early initiation of separately-cutting competition between the-A-
interests concerned, the Postraster-General should he authorised toinforn Sir John Denis on Fenderconfidentially that an Inter-Imperial Conference will probablyhe held in London at an earlydate.
IRAQ,Negotiationsfor Revisionof Treaty.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 57(27),  Con-clusion 10.)3. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Acting Secretary of State for the Colonies(Paper CP.-304 (27)) giving the results of the resumed negotiations with King Peisal, attachingthe draft of an Anglo-Iraq Treaty to which theCabinet were asked to give their approval, and explaining that King Peisal had left Londonbut that the Prime Minister of Iraq (ja&apos;far Pasha)Is on his way back to England and will findawaiting him on his arrival written instructions from King Peisal authorising him to sign theTreaty in its present form.The Cabinet congratulated the Acting Secretaryof State for the Colonies on the success of his negotiations, and authorised the signature of thedraft Anglo-Iraq Treaty.
4 . The Cabinet had before them a Joint Memo-randum by the Treasury and Dominions Office (paper cp.-307 (27)) in regard to the compensation claims of Civil Servants transferred to theservice of the Provisional Government of the IrishFree State on April 1, 1922 and, later, of theIrish Free State Government,  for compensationdue to them under Article 10 of the Articles ofAgreement of 1921.    The Irish Free State Govern-ment had decided to apply to such awards certain provisions of a Treasury Minute of March 22, 1922,which dealt with the reckoning of bonus for super-annuation.    The transferred Civil Servants hadcontested this, and eventually the JudicialCommittee of the Privy Council had decided againstthe Free State Government.   The Irish Free StateGovernment had then sent a letter to the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs stating that they/ere considering early legislation in theOireachtas with the object of setting up aCommittee constituted on the lines of the defunctCivil Service Committee (Compensation) whosedecision should be final, and to provide thatawards made on the recommendation of thisAdvisory Committee should be binding in law.As a matter of law this proposal would involvemodification of Article 10 of the Articles ofAgreement and also concurrent legislation &quot;bythe British Parliament.The Memorandum prepared by the Treasury andthe Dominions . Of fice explains th - case,,, and setsforth a number of relevant circumstances,including (Para.7) pledges given in 1921 and 1922by members of the Coalition and Conservative
Governments in connection with Article 10 of theArticles of Agreement of 1921,     Attached to theMemorandum are the following documents:-A copy of the despatch (referredto above) from the Government ofthe Irish Free State to theSecretary of State for DominionAffairs, dated November 9, 1927:The Judgment of the JudicialCommittee of the Privy Councildelivered on May 3, 1927:The treasury Minute of March 20,1922:A Statement by the Irish TreatyPensioners Association, handed to Lord Lovat on November 19,1927.The Cabinet were advised of the view of theTreasury that the arguments are decisive in favourof giving support to the action proposed by theFree State Government and of co-operating withthe Fr*e State Government in securing the necessary legislation to put the matter right.The Cabinet were asked to be careful to avoidexpressing any view reflecting on the Judgment ofthe Judicial Committee of the Privy Council, andwere warned of the danger of establishing a preCe-dent whbh would enable the Free State Government,whenever a Judc/ment was given against them by theJudicial Committee, to avoid its consequences by legislation.The Cabinet e-greed  (a) To support the action proposed bythe Free-State Government, and thatthe necessary legislation should beintroduced in due cotirss:(b) That the cases of two transferredCivil Servants:, in regard to whicha decision had already been made,should be discussed between theDominions Office and the Treasury.
MILITARY CON- 5.The Cabinet had before them the Report of aTRIBUTIONS BYCOLONIAL AND Cabinet Committee on Military--fkrnt&quot;rTbiTtions ofOTHER GOVERN-MENTS . Colonial and other Governments&apos; (Paper C.P.-298(27)), containing th.&apos;&quot; following recommendations:-(previous reference: (l)  THE STRAITS SETTLEMENTS.Cabinet 45(27), Con- (a) That the following proposals shouldelusion 6.) be adopted in final settlement ofall outstanding questions respect-lng the amount and method of calculation of the future annualmilitary contributions of theStraits Settlements:-(i) That all military expenditure(land works, armaments, etc.)on the initial formation ofthe Singapore Base should beborne    finally by Army Votes,i.e,, should be excluded fromthe &quot;cost of the garrison&quot; forthe purpose of arriving at theColonial contribution.(ii) That for all other military expenditure the existing arrangements should stand,i.e.,  the Colony should paythe full ordinary ourrent costof the garrison X subject always to the limit of 20 per cent,of the assessable revenue),including any military personneladded to the garrison as thenew defences are graduallymanned, and including the costof maintenance of the defences,old and new.(iii) That the statutory maximumpercentage of its revenue tobe contributed by the Colonyshould not be reduced, but should regain at the long-established figure of 20 percent, of the assessable revenue.(b) That the Secretary of State for theColonies should be invited to cornmu-communicate the proposals to the Govern-ment of the Straits Settlements after further consultation with the WarOffice respecting details as may benecessary.(c) That the annual contribution of theOpium Revenue Fund should be excludedfrom the revemie of the Colony assess-able to military contribution, butthat any sums drawn from the Fund,either in the form of interest orof capital drawings, and used as
income for revenue purposes,should be included in the assess-able revenue of the Colony.U)  CEYLON.That the Government of GeyIonshould be invited to contribute infuture the whole of- the cost of thegarrison (and not three-quarters ofthe cost as heretofore), subject tca maxi?rrum of 9-g per cent, of assese-able revenue, and that this invitationshould b? accompanied b;/ a statementof the intentions  of the War Officerespecting the future size of thegarrison,(3) MALTA.That the Government of Malta shouldbe invited to accept as a charge on local funds 51 per cent, of the full cost,  equal to  37,500 of the localunits, as a contribution towards thedefence of Malta.(4)  BERMUDA.That the Goveirrurent of Berrudashor &apos;.d be invited to make a military contribution of  12,500 per annumtowards the cost of its garrison,  this contribution being additional to the 3,450 per annum no&apos;.&apos; paid by the Colonyas a war contribution.(5)  JAMAICA.That the Government of Jamaicashould be invited to make a contribu-tion towards, the cost of the garrison of P-25,000 per annum, this contributionbeing additional to the annual amounts of  60 000 (war contribution) and about 14,000 (cost of local forces)  atpresent paid by the Colony.( 6 )  SIERRA LEONE.That when a final decision has beenreached as to the garrison to be main-tained in Sierra Leone for Imperialdefence purposes, the cost of the care and rraintenance units at Freetown shouldbe borne collectively by the West african colonies in. such proportions as may bedetermined by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.(?)   ^HE CHANNEL ISLANDS .That the present arrangements regardingthe Militia should be examined, with aview to seeing whether such alterationcan be made as would permit of theapplication to Jersey and Guernsey of .the usual principle that local funds should bear the full cost of local units.-IS-
The Acting Secretary of State for trie Colonieswarned the Cabinet that the proposals of theCabinet Committee presented considerable diffi-culties and would involve negotiations with anumber of Colonies.   He hoped, therefore, thatthe recommendations would, for the moment, betreated as tentative and as a basis for negotia-tion.    In particular, he warned the Cabinet thatthere was little hope of obtaining anything from malta or Bermuda.    In reply to a question,Mr Ormsby-Gore did not think that the recommenda-tions of the Committee would necessarily destroyall chance of obtaining contributions from theColonies towards the cost of Imperial defence as a whole if at some later date the Cabinetdesired to take up this question.The Cabinet agreed  -    (a) To approve the above recommendations as a basis for negotiation by theColonial Office:(b) That the Acting Secretary of Statefor the Colonies should do his utmost to induce the Colonies concerned toadopt these proposals, and should indue course report progress to theCabinet.
6. The Cabinet bad before their a Memorandum bythe Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries (PaperC0P.-301 (87)) in regard to a proposed tax on imported malting barley which had been rejected by the Cabinet on April 15s 1926.    In this Noteit was explained that, in view of the continuedagitation among a section of farmers on thissubject,, the question had been re-examined bythe Agricultural Policy Sab-Committee, who had decided against the tax and had asxed that the irrecommendation should be reported to the cabinet with a suggestion that, if the Cabinet concur inthe recommendation, a White Paper should be issuedsetting out the objections to the proposed Duty.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries hadattached to hie Memorandum the draft of a white paper which he recommended for the approval ofthe Cabinet.The question was reserved forconsideration at the next meeting of the Cabinet.
THE prorogation of PARLIAMENT.The King7sS oeeeho(previous reference:Cabinet 8(27), Con-elusion lo)7.    Immediately after the Meeting the PrimeMinister instructed the Secretary to inviteMinisters to furnish material for the King&apos;sSpeech on the prorogation of&quot;Parliament, with aview to consideration of the question by theCabinet at an early Meeting.2, Whitehall Gardens, S .E&apos;,1,December 7, 1927.

</content>
</cab>
