<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/21/0 images: 8-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS, 1X)CUMBNT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS   - ,11- :SLl &apos;1VW?,$TIJJ5 ^JI-j\W:W^lCABINET 19  (SO) conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet ihet held        I ,at lo, Downing Street..  S.W., on Monday,  12th.April 1920 at 12 HOON.PRESENT.The Rtm Hon. A.Chamberlain, M.P,(ihancellor of ti e Exchequer/The Hti -Hon. A. Bon ax haw, M.P.,)(in the Ghairj.lord Privy Seal. &apos;The lit. Hon. EiShortt, E.C . ,t,!.P.,Secretary of State for Homo AffairsThe fit. Hon. Sir L.WorthirigtonEvans,  Bart., M.P.The Rt. Bon\ IS.S.Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of -State for India.: The ;tt. Hon.; the viscount Milne-r,,O.G C B .,G.C.M.G., Seoretary ofState for the Colonies.The Rt. Hon., Sir E.Ceddes,  G.CB.,Gr,&apos;B-.E.?  .P., Minister of Transport,,The   (t.  Hon. R. Munro, K.G.,M.P.secretary for Scotland.The Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Horna,G.B-.E. IC. 0., M.P, , Pre sident ofthe Board of Trade.The Rt. Hon. c addison, M.P.,Minister of Health.   1THE FOLLOWING WERE -ALSO PRESENT: -Sir Eyre Crowe, &apos;G.CM.G., K.C.B., Mr P. Kerr.Assistant Under Seoretary ofState, Foreign Office.Mr Thoma a J one s.....................................Acting Secret ary.
THE RUHR   (1)    &apos;..&apos;ith reference to Minute 1 of Cabinet 18 [20)  theVALIiEYCabinet further consider.d the exchange of Notes with theFrench Government.       The folXovrinfr telegrams were read tothe Cabins t:-Note handed to Lord Derby by iresident of CouncilF.O.  Telegram lic. 1449 dated april 1 9th 19BONote from H.IvI. Govern  tent lor lu. hi lie randP.0. Telegram Ho&apos;. 1^6 dated April 10th 19  note handed to Lore; Dorby by i...1-111 lerandP.0. Telegram 1:0.458 dated April 11th 1920X% was- pointed out that the Prerch reply received that morning (No. 450) d ! ii n o t it a k e a b c o lu tely cle a r(li whether the French troops would evacuate all the german towns occupied or only j?ra;ikf ort and Darmstadt and( ) whether the evacuation was conditional on the withdrawalof only the extra German troops in the Ihihr Valley.and not also of the 17,500 whose presence had been permitted by theformer agreement.      The Cabinet were informed that lord derby had been asked by telephone to have these arsfe iguitiesremoved.   . On the assumption that lord Derby1 s reply wouldbe satisfactory the Cabinet proceeded to consider the text of a draft reply to the .. reneh Government and of the state-ment which the Lord privy oeal should make in the House ofCommons that afternoon.    These were agreed to in the formset forth in the Appendix.
load DERBY&apos;S (2)    The Cabinet consider-ed. the mestion of LordATTENDANCE ATTHE CONNER- Derby*-s att-endanuee at the Conf ere.no e-of Jimbas-sa&amp;orsENCE of ambassadors, in Paris and were generally agreed that in view ofthe discussions which would take place at San Remobe authorisod toLord Derby should/jreoume attendance * but that no reference should be made to the matter in the reply to the Drench Government crin the House of Commons.The Acting Secretary was instructed, whensending an account of the meeting to the PrimeMinister, to direct hie attention to the viewsof the Cabinet on this mat tor.Q
IDISTBIBUTI OH.     (3)    Sir Eyre Crowe was requested $0 Investigatejbi FOREIGN      vOFFICE complaints,made as to the failure of. the Foreign&apos;&apos;TELEGRAMS.Office to ciroulaio^eartain.dJiiport^urt^diagrams to&quot;Cabinet Ministers.
(4)    At-&apos;^e--&apos;reiju^sir-c.f &quot;the Secretary of State fcrIjxdxa, the Cabljae&quot;t---&apos;appol^to consider and adArise on the Report of the Pi^orrLefrs*Enquiry--Xk)miait&quot;tee (India) received from Lord&apos;&quot;Hunter.The secretary-e-tary of State for India( Chairman)The Lord chancellor the Home  SacretaryThe Secretary of State for the colonies the Secretary of State for ParThe President  of the Board of education the Attorney GeneralMr T. St. v-uintin Hill .   ,   .  Secretary2/Phitehall Gardens, S.P.April 12th 19 20DISORDERSEiKEIRYCOivililTTEE(INDIA)^ -
iAH EPLLX(Minute l)Prop o-sed^r^ply bo^a^es^tio s- in Eouse-, of&quot; Ccmmons-:&apos;As the House &amp;s aware a difference, which- HisMajesty&apos;s Government gr.e&amp; tly deplore, had aim sen betweenthe British and French Governments, but the exchangeof notes which has taken place between London and. Parisjustifies the belief that both Governments recognisemore than ever the necessity of maintaining intimate andcordial agreement for the  settlement of the grave questionsconfronting them in Gerr- . :ry and elsewhere.The approaching Conference of the heads of the AlliedGovernments will no doubt serve to confirm and. consolidatea complete understanding between the Governments.In these circumstances I venture to suggest that itwould be very undesirable to have any disc-as si on of thesubject in this House either in debate or by way of question and Answer. iIt is hardly necessary to add that- there is no truth,whatever,  in the statement made in a certain section ofthe Press that there has teen any difference of opinion inthe Cabinet and my Ht.Hon. Priond the Chancellor of the-Exchequer, whose name has been specially mentioned in thisconnection, has requested, me to take this opportunity Dfexplicitly denying it on his behalf.The reply sent to the French Government will be circulated as a lor sign Office telegram.

</content>
</cab>
