<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/21/0 images: 266-271</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINFW 35  (SO) .CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet, heldat 10, Downing Street,  S.V.1,  on WEDNESDAY,JUNE 16,  19Si0, at 11-30 a.in.The Prime Minister  (in the Chair),hfl Rirbt  Hon. A. Ponar Law, P.P,m    The Right Hon. A.. J.Ea&quot;? for&apos;&quot;   0Lord Privy Seal.Ibe Right, Hon. A. Chamberlain,M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer.Ike Right Hon. E. Shortt, K.C.,Li.P.,  Secretary of State for home Affairs.fhe Risrl-w Hon. w. Lonp, K.P.,First Led of the Admiralty,Right Hon.  Sir E. Geddes,G.C.E.,G.B.K.,M.P,,  Ministerof Transport.fhe Right Hon. T.J. Maenaroara,LL.D.,M.P., Minister of labour our.[he Right Hon. H.A.L. Fisher,M.P., President of the Boardof Education.M.P.,  Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Lord Birkenhead,Lord Ghance11or.The Right Hon. 07.S. Churchill,M.Pv.  Secretary of State forWar and Air.The Right Hon.  R. Munro,  K.C.,M.P.,Secretary for Scotland.The Right hon. C. Addison, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Sir Robert Home,&amp;.I -E.,K.C .,M.P. ,  Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. the Lord Lee ofPare ha/a, G.B.E. ,K.C .3., Ministerof Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. Sir L. Worthington Evans, Bart.,M.P.The following were also present:-N Right Hon. Sir A. Mond, M.B.,  \ The Right Hon. J.I.Macpherson, E.CFirst Coinraissione r of K.M. M..P., Minister of Pensions .Office of Works. !Sir D.J. Shackle ton, LCJoint permanent secretary, Ministry of Labour.Lieut.-Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.O.B., Secretary.Mr Thoraas Jones, Principal Assistant Secretary.(IIVlg.Po:,n:?:g;it,. is... t he. P r o re rty of His BritanniaI j- MiLhMb?.Ihhg Government.)pli? R M  1 &quot; PI HA I. COPY No.
(1) With reference to w*a- Cabinet 630, Conclusions 4 and5. and to Cabinet 33 (so), Appendix IV (4), the Cabinetrailwayman&apos;s wages  , and had before them two Memoranda bythe Minister of Transport  (Papers CP.-1408 and CP.-1458),and Memoranda by the Minister of Labour on the present fend-eric y of Wages (Papers CP.-806 and CP.-1233), -with commentsthereon by the Minister of Transport (Paper CP.-1465).The immediate question for decision before the Cabinet was whether or not the Government should adopt the Conclusionsof the Rational Wages Board respecting the claims referredto them on May 6,  1920,    The cost of the railway/men&apos;s demands,if granted, would have amounted to an annual charge of 2,8,000,000.    The findings of the National Wages Board Awardto the rallvaymen would cost nearly  10,000,000,  this sumincluding the increase due to the cost of living.It wao explained to the Cabinet that, since the lastincrease of rates, unforeseen additional charges, due to increased cost of coal and materials as well as increasedcoot of labour, had caused a further deficit in working,which in total might be  40,000,066 to  50,000,003 per annum.It was realised that the decision involved very largequestions of principle which in part were raised by theReport of the National Wages Board, such as the danger ofadvancing wages beyond the economic power of industries tomaintain them, and the probability of starting, a new cycleof wage   demands.After disceission of these and related questions,  itwag agreed -authorised,  on behalf of the Government,to adopt the Conclusions of the national wages Board of June S, I9g0, and shouldtake the necessary action to give effect-to them:considered, as a question ef great urgency, t)the subject of(a) That the Klnistof Transport should be
(b)(o)That the Minister of Transport, should beauthorised to increase the railway ratesand charges so as to provide foo the in-crease in wages and to meet&apos; the existingdeficit on their operations due to other causes :That the above decisions should apply toIreland,   and that fo- this purpose&quot;theIrish railways should be treated as a unit:That in announcing the foregoing decisionsthe Minister of Transport should state thatthe Government view with concern many points in the Renort,  and should drawp a -1 i o u 1 a v a ft e n * ion to p a r a map ha 4 5and 4b  of the Report;    he should emphasised-slse the risk that,  owing to these wage:,advances, the economic limits of theindustry were being approached, and heshould warn the public that if in prac-tice It is found that the consequent in-creases of traffic rates do not increasethe revenue to a corresponding extent,  thewhole situation will have to be reviewed inorder to safeguard the economic stability of the industry:That an Enquiry should be established with a view to meeting the suggestion in the second part of paragraph 45 ofMinisters should submit tc the cabinet proposals as to the scope and nemos othe Enquirv, and suggest suitablemendersnho Minister of Transport,The president of the Boa-dof Trade,The Minisbe- of Labour.
(S) With reference to Cabinet 3? (SO), Appendix I,  theCabinet had before them the following documents in regard tothe present Housing situation, and more particularlyits financial aeoeetsA Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Bxohequer(Paper C.P.-1330),A Memorandum by Si? M Worthington Evans(Pane:-- CP.-1348),A Memorandum by the Minister of Health(Paper CP.-1395),A Memorandum by the Secretary  fo&quot; Scotland(Pane&quot; CP.-1347),A Memorandum by the First commissioners aione ^* of Wo-As(Paper CP.-1455),A Memorandum by the Minister .of Labour(Papar C.p.-1466) .In view of the number and importance of the questions involved,  if&apos;was agreed  (a) -That, the whole situation should be- examined at once, from the point -of - view &quot;both, ofhastening the erection of houses and of thefinancial burdens on the State *. by .a Commit-tee of the following Ministers:-The President of the Board of Trade (in&apos;&quot;the ChadThe Minister cf Health,&apos;    .The Minister of Labour,The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries,The Secretary for Scotland,PThe First Commissioner &quot;of Works,,   -Sir L, &quot;Worthing!on- Evans,-The Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasury,Mr T. Jones (Secretary)..-&quot;-The Ministers should consider the desima-bility of consulting acme&apos;prominent&apos;builderaand look-into the question of building work by Government Departments, including theprovision of certain building materials- and administration of houses by the Minister ofMunitiona, which would require to be trans-ferrea elsewhere on the termination of that ministry,&apos; and the &apos;.work undertaken by theOffice bf Works on behalf of the CamberwellBorough Council (Paper CP.-1455) :-(b) That after the forthcoming interview withM. Millerand and.M. Ma--sal, the Prime Ministerand the Chancellor of the Exchequer should,if possible, associate themselves with theCommittee.
OYMENT(3) With.. reference---to.-Cabinet 22 (20). Conclusions, theCabinet had before then: a Memorandom...by-the Minister of Labourdealing with three important amendments to the UnemploymentInsurance Bill, which had been carried against the Governmentin Committee (Paper 0.P.-1303).    By these amendments,(i) The right to pay out State UnemploymentBenefit is specifically given to approved societies:(ii) Benefit is made payable from the first day(Instead of the seventh day) of unemploy-ment if unemployment lasts as long as awe eh:(iii) The weekly rates of benefit have been raised from 15/- to 20/- for men, and from 12/- tp16/- for women.It was pointed out that the first amendment commandeda large amount of support In the House of Commons, but thatthere were serious administrative objections to investingthe Approved Societies with the work, except under strictsafeguards.    The amendment was strongly resisted by the TradeUnions, and it was suggested that their resistance might be weakened by raking certain concessions to them under the othert v/ o am a nd me nt s, v iz,:-(i) A wait-ins? period of three days:(ii)  Rates of benefit,  18/- for men and 15/-for women:(iii) Weekly contributions on the following scaleEmployers.       M l22  ,.      State.,Men . .Women.5d.5d.4do3d,d.The cost of these-proposals to the Exchequer would be about 1,897,000, and the total cost to the Exchequer of-thisscheme, including amendments made or accepted by the Govern-ment, would be about  5,500,000.After considerable discussion the Cabinet agreed - -That the Minister of Labour should -(a) Accept the amendment dealing with the? r i e nd 1 y S o c i e t i e s :(b) Agree to a waiting period of three days,
only if absolutely necessary to so !ureTrade Union consent to the other aiend-nie nt a :(c) Agree to weekly rates of IS/- for menand 15/- for women:on condition that the rates of con-tribution of employers and employedshould be adjusted to bear the extraexpense and that no additional charge should fall upon the Treasury.It was suggested that this could bo doneby makirmr the contributions as fellows:-Employer.      Employed..    gtftte.Men .........    5d. 5d&quot;. 3d.Women .......    5d. 4d. 1 /gd.S, Whitehall Gardens * S.W.1,June 16,  1920.-5-

</content>
</cab>
