<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/189/4 images: 35-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TH]S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT81CP(76) 4 COpY no. 8 April 1976CABINETCHILD BENEFIT RATESNote by the Secretary of State for Social Servicesand the Chief Secretary, TreasuryWe attach a factual paper prepared by our officials setting out five possiblerates of child benefit.D EJ BDepartment of Health and Social Security8 April 1976
CHILD BBTKFIT (CB) RATKNote by Treasury and DHSSr.&apos;fi ts a universal tax-free benefit to replace family allowance (?AM) and childtax- allowances (CTA).   Initially only the under-11 rate of CTA will be subsumed,with residual rates continuing for older children.The attached Tables show the net Exchequer cost in 1977-78 (at 1975 survey prices), and cash, and percentage gains or losses for families of differenttymporofionB, oi&apos; 5 possible CB rates.    Brief comments on each rate are set outbislow.   It should also be noted that:(i)    Tin? Tables and cotnment3 on rates are concerned with families who payt:ix - the great majority.   families with earnings below the tax thresholdwill pain up to the full value of C:5 for the first child and up to theJiff erence- between       and 1fAM for each second and subsequent child.   ButVpJitilios in receipt of social security benefits etc will not gain 3ince therates of these benefits will be adjusted,    Aa a very rou^h estimate perhaps300,000 families below the tax threshold will gain substantially from CB.( I i.) fi^urr;n for onr- parent fpiiYiilip-B in the Tublfa show the; poaLtion oftho^c who ;.-iy tax, have CTAs and have claimed child interim bfmem (CUTS).On..-par-Tit  \anul.u s who do not pay tax, or -io not have CTAs (because theoth.;r partner&apos; has them) or have not claiaed CHI3 will gain more.(lii) 3y n.&apos;t Exchequer cost is meant the gross public expenditure cost of child benefit less the cost of FAM and child interim benefit, of certainsocial security savings, and of the tax * transfer&apos; arising from the abolitionof the 1976-77 child tax allowances for under-Us at the basic rate.(iv) If,  as S3 Committee have recommended,  there were a transitional taxconcession for non-resident children, the net Kxchequer cost of this wouldha 3orae &apos;3f5 million,(v) The 197 ^ Survey took illustrative CB rates of  2.16 and  2.22 a week and estimated that, at the 1975-76 CTA of 221+0, the net Exchequer costs would be&apos;U &apos;) mill ion and million respectively.   More recent demographicprojection;; require a revision of these figures to  85 million and &amp;15 million respectively.
(vi&apos;    Tn th-   &apos;u.ia&apos;L  !      ^ .-..r. r&apos;iv.1 by &quot;oO       .  :r v.&apos;&apos;-i;:h  iequiv l-ir,.  l-o.,r&apos; r/&apos;. oi&apos; .iNp .&apos;   v:&apos;&quot;&apos;V an-! ooi-its &quot;2X1 million ayi\ar (a&apos;  \&apos;)7C) -urvoy prLC&apos;) *i ;&apos; &apos; irj1&apos;.    !   . i L L O&apos;.&apos;.&apos; &apos;J Ci:    i \.VM\i\   -\;   -&apos;,\ &apos;/0 p rn V i. B I OI I; illy   ) 11*0 pOfi&apos;&apos; tl,   thf&apos;n. t vlKchcuvr oor.1, of each rata will bo increased by some  Jj.1. million.(vii)    In re.--.! tcms,  the value of find CTA.S has been falling over ramy/rars.    A:j  the tax threshold has fallen this has affected more and morefamilies:    since the mid sixties families on average earnings have beennaying &quot;tax at the standard rate.    To return family support to the positionin April 197L, between the two elections at which the Government pledgee itselfIntroduce an improved ay.-,tern, would  require rates of  2.1+8 and  2.58 for thetwo and three child families respectively.The pi-or have, however, been partly protected by means-testod benefits whichhave bo coma much more Lupartrmt in iu-mort for -working families than theywar- a fW years ago.    Something lite LOO,000 out of 6.6 million workingfamilies an; receiving such benefits (chiefly rent and rate rebates,  freeschool meal:; and family Income Supplements),  though take-up varies ranging from about 251&quot; for rent allowances for private tenants to for FI5.(vifi.) ?hf premium shown in the Tabl-? would be paid for the fourth and sub-.&apos;.&apos;-nuent children of two-parent f ami Lias and for all children of one-parentf aid.! ies.-;.      ^ho following uifi brief comnents on the rates in tte  Tables:-.,.;t,c 1   (-\ .Kb * cp\i premium - cost  59.; million)T!iis rat.-,   vhich is the lowest rounded rate which could in practice replace the^resent system of support at    minimum cost, would give cash gains to aLlfamilies,  with rains of 3Ip a week to ono-parent families for each of their children,  and to two-parent families for each fourth and subsequent child.date 2    (TJ.50 * :&apos;0n premium - cost C6L..9 million)This rate,  at the coct of a further  25 million, would make two-parent families:.&apos;iti-, 1, 2 and 3 children LBp, 3ivp and 20p better off respectively; and wouldrive an extra % . to one-parent families for each of their children, and to two-parent families for each fourth and subssquent child.
CONFIDENTIALxntc 3 - cost 290.5 million)A flat rate of   &quot;-.60 would on sure; that rio two-parent family of any likely sizewould bi&apos; worst; ofi&apos;*    The two-parent family with 1 child would be 5Hp better off,1; 1 -1 the &quot;alun -/-mid f&apos;ill by only 4p ?or each child as the family size increased.On(&apos;-;!ar(!nt families with CHT3 would be 4p worse off for each child but whenCabinet agreed to the introduction of CI13 in January 1975, they recognised thatone-parent ;\iroi.! i&quot;s drawing CHIB night lose on transition to CB; they agreed thatthis snould not be used as an argument for setting the rate for C3 higher thanthe level envisaged during their recent discussions of public expenditure.Rate I,    ( 2.6n - co^t  C115.9 million)&apos;&quot;!Ir. ir, the lowest rounded flat rate of CB that would ensure that no family wasivorjp off.    All tv;o-paront families would gain about the 3ame amount (63p for a family with on n child) and one-parent families would break even.    At the start ofthe scIioiti&quot; in 1977 tro-parent families with 2 or 3 children would get lltfi and %aore than in 197o-77 In cash terms and in real terms 7?; and % above the level inApril 197.V (the    ud(;et date between the two elections when the Government pledgeditself to introduce the new arrangements).state 5    (--2.70 - cost Q41.3 million)This rate would contain an improvement element for everyone.    At the cost of afurther ^5 million over Rate 4, it would makp the two-parent family with 1 child&apos;V-.p bettor off and .;ivo a further ^ain of 6p for each subsequent child.    Similarly,&apos;.vitimut a prouuuH, ono-paront families would get an extra 6p for each child.    Two-pa r-nt familirr. .-/ith 1 or J children would get 1$- ^d U?T more than in 1976-77 inc,r,h trnan and in re.a terras 9,- and 5f above the level in April 1974.
TA6i  1CQS-fS   OF   Vf\r\lO\)S ^ 5   OF CHILD BfMCFlT   AMP   PRGmiflRftre of 1      CHILV Li	COST   million		s  cosr op f million	1*073* (. Cosr or rats fiirip2-4-5				3*1-5I j 2- 50	3^ -7		25-2	^-9------      - - -i a- bo			 		M5 -9		 	JI5 ^2-yo _1	J4-/-3	 	 	1. PrtrMia ire Ptid ^or Hie tfrsJ- 3 children in I ^flrC^ft/ntiies  and. -for        feurWi W Suose^yen/- children.2. A$ Q rov^k yvtdt, Ga^ increase of 1 p on fhe basicC6 rate Costs abooh f&amp; m\\Uon.  ad, lp of premiumcosts abour  o-S rnll/ibfl.
II OF          ^	SiZS   OF m m          -_ n                   y*                 H			2	3	1 i			5	b	i t        \	iti 1^77/78   &apos;             \		i			1		-face		- o3	.0,    1% !	--    &apos;-----				3r---.-r.-_j ;r.--.	-A	 	...-------			li	&quot;Two    Pfldf NT	1	T    4-3 f		t- S&quot;p	1		t 3fcp	1- t7p	.^P	I      ^(i- 5t3p premium) ; i		1 i 1 -1		* 62p	^3p			f 1-2.4-p	i    M-S5p i___		j_-1 r	&quot;Two   PftA6pJT	1		1	i * 2op 1				1 +		1 1 * 3tr$Op prem&apos;(ijfrt) .	owe PflAfnir i		t-3bp	i I      * 72 p	i 1 */i?ep			t Itfp	&apos;    f-J-Sop		4--- ii	1      TnfC   ff*K  NT		t 5$p	1 i         4-5lfp	!    f- 5op			f- &quot;Hp	I		1 t i      -V	1		-iff	! ?f			 -	- /6p	j  -ior		1i 2-bS				r					i     f b7p	f bgp		!	j	* &apos;r					-V    1    *5p		t- bp	2-70 I ----....   JI		i		t 7f-p	^ S&quot;op	!		?fep	*&quot;^f     i	M8p			1	-t- bp		f i9p	i i		t- 24-p	4- 3op	f 3bp	4- &amp;p
nOzTl5mZHS1W levei-    j OP            1	Fam/i./	1	2	3		5	6CHlLp %6n FiT 1 *              1	PftffnfiCtf OF FAmu S M   KJ77/78 fnttlJiwtf)	3-OM-	2-7o		-3b	-10	03a- h-5	&quot;TWO   P/SR NT FAMILIES	rJLl-3	4- 5-2.	1-0,-7				0K6   PftR.er4T		f u-7	11-7	f 11-7	t- II 7	*- ii-7		113-S	t7-3	f^-7		t7-3	*- 8-4-		*-13 fc	*-&apos;3-fc	* (3-fa		f 13 -fa	* &apos;3-fa2 bO	&quot;TWO   PAA NT	*-*8-7				*3-3		f   &quot;           &quot;      -	-/-$		-J-5		-J-S	-l-S2-65	-TWO   Pfl fl.fi		i-13-7	t M	f	f 5-3 L. .-.		0N    PftKfrtT	f- -0-4--i    ii     mi   i	*- o*4-	* OH-	* 0-H-	4- OH-	1 j	TWO   PflA6(^T	h33-7		t- II-0	+ S -fa		--	0fl6   PftR NT	f 2-3	t a	f 2-3	* 2-3	*2-3	fi -3    1 i i -a-.-n-r 1oOzz

</content>
</cab>
