<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/197/16 images: 399-402</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77)86 COPY NO     8225 July 1977CABINETMINISTRY OF DEFENCE DISPERSAL TO GLASGOWMemorandum by the Secretary of State for defence. In CP(77) 85 the Lord Privy Seal and the Secretary of State forScotland have proposed a detailed dispersal of my Department as aningredient cf a proposed announcement of the Government&apos;s dispersalprogramme.    In this paper I recommend an alternative form of announce-ment of the dispersal of Ministry of Defence (MOD) posts to Glasgow whichwill credibly reconcile the Government&apos;s continuing commitment to theprogramme announced in 1974 with the realities of present circumstances.background. The recommended solution for the MOD in the Hardman Report(Cmnd 5322) was 11, 000 posts to be dispersed to Milton Keynes;  the&quot;regional&quot; solution recommended 6,218 posts for Cardiff and 4, 672 posts forMilton Keynes.   The plan which the Government finally adopted and announced on 30 July 1974 was for 5, 000 MOD posts to go to Cardiff and, 000 to Glasgow:  subject to discounting due to the Defence Review.    Thedispersals took their timing from the estimated completion of purpose-builtaccommodation at the two locations (1980-82 for Cardiff; 1982-84 forGlasgow).REDUCTIONS IN MOD NUMBERS3. All this was announced at a time when the London headquarters ofthe Ministry totalled some 19, 000 civilian and military staff.    But theDefence Review and successive manpower cuts will have trimmed this figureby about 20 per cent by the mid-1980s and, at the same time, &quot;minidispersals&quot; will take over 2, 000 staff from London to existing Defencelocations in the provinces in the interests of economy and more efficient management.    Thus, by 1983-84 the MOD baseline figure will only be some13, 000 posts, out of which the earlier decision placed 11, 000 at risk.    Yet Istill have to maintain an efficient unified administrative and operationalDepartment in order to control nearly three-quarters of a million Service-men and civilians and an expenditure of over  7 billion a year.
THE GLASGOW PACKAGE4. In the light of these changed circumstances, in May 1977 the ministerial Committee on Economic and Industrial Policy (El) agreed that theCardiff commitment should be reduced from 5, 000 to &quot;not less than 4, 000posts&quot;.    No comparable reduction has yet been agreed for Glasgow, but Eldid decide that MOD should look beyond its London headquarters to make upthe Glasgow package.    This did not extend my range of choice by very much.Most major defence establishments are either t.ed to their location by their nature, eg dockyards, or by the extent of their capital facilities, egresearch and development establishments.    But I have identified a packageof 4, 450 posts set out in d. , e. , f. and g. of Annex A to the joint paper bythe Lord Privy Seal and the Secretary of State for Scotland.    It is a complexone, beinging together computer-orientated functions from nine separatelocations involving Service pay, manning and records, and civilianindustrial and non-industrial pny services.    I am still studying itsfeasibility in view of both the technical risks and the problems in industrial relations it may involve.    However, from my standpoint it offers a potential solution better than any previously examined;  it promises toprovide substantially the number of posts required for the St Enoch site;and it would include good quality management work.5. There are a few additional blocks of work which, from my point ofview, could be dispersed to Glasgow, such as the Defence CodificationAuthority which is included in the option recommended by the Lord privy seal.    Others are all or some of the Quality Assurance staff at Woolwichor Bromley.6. The feature of the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s recommendation which istotally objectionable to me is the inclusion of 970 Service personnel management staff.    This proposal has on closer examination beenspecifically rejected by me on the grounds that it would be incompatible withthe efficient management of the Department, the administration of the armed Services and the conduct of military operations.PROPOSED MOD SOLUTION7. I propose that we should settle for a total MOD commitment of up to4, 500 jobs on the St Enoch site.    If this is not enough, the dispersal of quality Assurance staff must come back into the reckoning.    They could go into purpose-built accommodation on the Glasgow periphery well in advanceof the time scale cow proposed by the Property Services Agency for the st Enoch building.    I recognise the force of the objections to their dispersal,but there are likely to be at least as strong objections to any solution to whichI may be driven by the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s recommendation that I may go for adifferent mix for the Anderston site.    Nor could my choice be reasonablyconfined to the limitations of a building on that site.
IMMEDIATE NEED FOR AN ANNOUNCEMENT8. It is the main plank of the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s proposal that a reviseddispersal planning timetable must be announced before the Summer Recess.But it was the view of the Secretary of State for Scotland as recently as his letter of 18 July to the Lord Privy Seal that he &quot;could not agree that any announcement should be made until the feasibility study related to Option 9has been completed and it has been clearly established and accepted thatthis particular package will go ahead without impediment or furtherreconsideration.    To do otherwise and risk having to change our publicposition yet again would be completely unacceptable&quot;.9. For the reasons I have given in this paper, the Secretary of State forScotland&apos;s conditions cannot yet be met.    Thus the questions which would immediately follow an announcement in the form now recommended by theLord Privy Seal would quickly arouse doubt on the veracity of the announce-ment as regards Glasgow, with consequential major embarrassment with our supporters.RECOMMENDATION10.        In the light of a situation which has manifestly changed since 1974, i recommend that our announcement should relate to a policy we have some prospect of implementing.    Accordingly, I propose:-a. That the MOD entry in the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s proposed announcement in Annex B of his papor should read as follows:&quot;Ministry of Defence    4,000-5,000. Cardiff       1983-84Up to 6,000^ &apos; Glasgow     1985-86 to(1) 1987-88&apos;These numbers will be affected by the reductions in the defence programme since 1974.b. That a decision on the nature of the MOD Glasgow packageshould be deferred until the outcome of the current feasibility studyinto the computer-based option is completed.F MMinistry of Defence25 July 1977


</content>
</cab>
