<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 12-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
.:-   SECRETOf Idf-:&apos;. *******Secretary,War Cabinet;I attach for the information of the War Cabinet a Memorandum regarding the recent brea&amp;down on the French Railway System, based on communications received from the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief and prepared by the General Staff in conjunction with Major-General Sir E.Geddes, for transmission to the French Government, If approved^ with such observations as the War Cabinet may decide to forward.(sd)   W.R.RobertsonGeneral18th February 1917.   Chief of the Imperial General Staff.
Copy vxlo. 10,MEMORANDUM OH THE RAILWAY SITUATION IN THE BRITISH ZONE IIA FAAHCEA1.     The PieId-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief has drawn attention to the serious situation which has arisen in A   connection with the transportation facilities placed at the disposal of the British Armios in France, and to the effect &quot;which the failure of the Railways may have upon the conduct of the forthcoming operations in so far as those Armies are co-operating in i;Wro. It must be remembered that while the British Authorities have assisted the French pLailways by supplies of rolling stock and in other ways, the general understanding throughout the war has been that the responsibility for the management and operation of those Railways, and for the-adequate;service of the British Armies in France by rail has rested with the French Military -      Authorities. * &apos;*2.     From time to-time.discussions have taken place between representatives of the British and French Armies and.Far Offices At those.Conferences the former have endeavoured to meet as       -far as circumstances permitted the demands for assistance, and in July last at the conclusion of a series of Conferences General Bolin, who presided, made the following statement as .    reported in the proces verbal &quot;   Goneral Belin declares that the agreement is complete as regards rolling stock, &quot;both on numher and type to  . .    be supplied, as well as the time within which, deliverios- aro:* to he made. tt&quot; This.
This dool^ration was understood by tho British Authorities to conclude tho matter as it stood at that time, and sinco thon they havo taken every possible step to meet their obligations accordingly.3.     After tho Somme offensive, when the railway situation began to cause some unoasinons, further conferences wero arranged which took place in Paris In November and December last, attendod by ropresontatives of tint Staffs of the two Armies.     It was at this time, and as a consequence of a communication by Marshal Joffre, then General Commanding-in-Chiof of the French Armies, that it was first formally brought to the notice of the British Oommander-in-Chief that the French Railways required more extensive and general assistance Steps were immediately taken to rondor that assistanco as fully as circumstances permitted, and the withdrawal of locomotivos and rolling stock from tho British Railways and their transfer to Franco was authorised, and is being carried out as rapidly as circumstances, permit.     These measures havo-only been mado possible by drastic restrictions of Railway facilities to the public in this Country, and by the curtailment of imports of various kinds to set froo shipping for the conveyance of rolling stock on its wheels to France. At. the same Conforences a programme of Railway construction to be undertaken by both British and French on the Railway system serving tho British Armies was agreed to, and complete figures of tonnages to be carried were placed at the disposal of the appropriate French Officials.     The French Authorities have, therefore, since November last been fully aware of the foregoing circumstances, and the matter has also been the subject of representation both verbal and written between Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig and General Hivelie from the 26th December until the present time.
. -5-4.     It may bo argued that Britiah dclivorios of rolling stock in Prance have not fulfilled expectations owing partly to failure of Contractors and also to the difficulties of cross-Channel shipping, including danger from onomy submarines, but against this there is evidence that the breakdown in January was mainly duo to the lack of capacity of the linos, and exhaustion of the operating personnel and locomotives on the $ord systom.5.     It 7; a a not until the 23rd January that the impending failure of the French Railways to cope with tho situation was dofinitoly though verbally admitted at a Conference on othor matters between the Directour do 1fArriorc and the Director-General of Transportation, and this informal intimation was immediately followed by drastic restrictions in traffic facilities afforded to the British Armies which are still partly in foroo with most sorious consequences.6.     On the 29th January the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief arranged a Conference at Grand Quartier General with the Gonoral Commanding-in-Chicf of the French Armies, and tho situation was discussed as a whole.     General Nivelle expressed to Sir Douglas Haig the ability of the Fronch Railways by special efforts to handlo British traffic on a scale of 200,000 tons import per week, in addition to the necessary local traffic, such as^ roadstone and timber, required for the operations, and with this assurance Sir Douglas Haig hopod even with the limited resources available to be able to carry out the agreed plan of operations.
7.     The following are the approximate figures of tonnages to be handled :-(a) Total weekly demands of tho British Armies -Import. 250,000 tons.Local traffic     100,000 tons,350,000 tons.(b) Actual weekly traffic handled at end of January -Import. 150,000 tons.&apos;1 Local-traffic.      60,000 tons.; 210,000 tons.(c) Weekly traffic which General Mvelle at mooting on&quot;89th January expressed the ability of the French Railways to Carry by special efforts -Import. 300,000 tons.Local traffic.     All required. From correspondence subsequently received by the Secretary of State for War from Sir Douglas Haig, however, it appoars that the understanding reached at the Conforenco on the 29th January between himself and General Nivelle can only be realised gradually and after an indefinite period of time, and that oven so it is only thought possible by the French if considerable British assistance is given to execute works now proposed for the. first time, or which; the French had previous1y undertaken; to construct themselves.8.     It is obvious that the situation which has arisen is an extremely serious one, and justifies any stops, howevor drastic, that may be practicable to ameliorate it *   It is, therefore&apos;, recommended - ;
(i)   That tho French Govornmont he requested to furnish a full statement of tho import and local traffic sbparatbly, which they are prepared to guarantee to carry weok by week until their capacity shall have reached the full requirements of the British Armies as notifiod at the Conferences in November last.(ii)   That civilian traffic of all kinds in tho zone serving the British Armies shall bo restricted to an absolute minimum.     There are grounds for believing that a very considerable civilian traffic is now passing on the Railways and that this is by no means confinod to the absolute essentials of life,(ill)    That stops be taken to evacuate from the zone of the British Armies such civilian and refugee population as is necessary to-relieve the Railways of thp excessivo demands for tho support of this population.(iv)   That tho French Government uhould immediately takesteps to provide all the labour that can bo usofully employed on the works which their officers consider necessary for the proper working of the full notified traffic of the British Armies, and, further, to withdraw from other parts of France such rolling stock, locomotives, and personnel, as may be required from time to time to deal adequately with the British traffic on the linos serving those Armies.(v) That the British Authorities should be kept fullyadvised from time to time of the progress of such works.
9.     So far as the British Authorities themselves aro concerned, arrangements aro being mado to augment still further the labour on roads and railways for the construction and maintenance of which the British Armies aro now taking responsibility, and to expedite as much as possible the dospatch of locomotives, rolling stock and permanent way for Franco.     If thoroaftor it is found possible to place labour at the disposal of tho French Authorities for new-construction or for. works for which thoy undortook the responsibility, this can be done.     It is satisfactory to note that at the recent Conferences between Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Kaig and General Mvelle it was agreed that experienced technical Railway officers of the British Forces should collaborate with the Officials of the Ford Railway in obtaining the best use of tho Railway facilities available, and thore arc good grounds for the hope that considerable improvement can be obtained by this means provided such co-opcratlon is encouraged to the fullest extent.10.     In a communication to tho Chiof of tho Imperial General Staff, dated 9th February, the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief reports that the construction programme undertaken in the British area by his Transportation Department is making satisfactory progress.     He points out, however, that the hoavy calls on the fighting troops for labour have seriously interfered with training, and continue to do so.11.     As regards the effect of tho Railway situation on the plan of operation decided upon at the London Conference on the 15th and 16th January, ho makes the following remarks&quot;I have no means of knowing to what extent the railway situation has delayed preparations for the French offensive, nor do I know what proportion of the Railway facilities has been retained by the French for their own use.,ttIn
MIn the absence of full and reliable information as to future Railway proBpocts it is not in my power te give a date by which it will bo possible to &apos; carry out my attack on tho scale I had intended,&quot;At my meeting with General Nivolle on the 29th. January, 1917, it was agreed that my Transportation Department should be brought into closer touch with the French railway oxports, and I hope that this will lead to a fuller knowledge of what facilities I can roly on and whon they will be available.&quot;Meanwhile, if tho French commence their . operations on the 1st April - and still more, if V thoy commence earlier than that .-, I can only comply with the War Cabinet1s instructions, as to , / a combination with them, to the extent of a very ..   modified attack.     This course, so far as theBritish Armies in Franco are concerned, could have no more than a very local and temporary effect on the enemy, and would use up resources which would    . prejudice the success of subsequent operations.w,    12.    From the foregoing review of the situation, it is apparent that, whon the plan of operations was decided on at the London Cenforonco on 15th and 16th January, the whole situation both as to railway capacity and the demands of the British Armies was befere the competent French authorities, who had oven allotted to the British Armies, at considerable inconvenience to themselves, adequate Port accommodation to deal with the total forecast tonnage which their railways are now unable to carry. : Nevertheless within;ten days of that Conference the French Authorities were compelled to put into force drastic restrictions of the Railway traffic at the disposal of the British Armies in France, which have not yet been wholly removed.   It is, therefore, essential to tho effective conduct of the projected operations, whether in a modified form or at a later date than that originally mentioned, that the French authorities should definitely state, for the information and guidance of the British Commandor, to what extent they can be responsible for carrying the traffic of the British Armies, as communicated to them in November lastAImperial General Staff,War Office. February 12th. 1917, &apos;

</content>
</cab>
