<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 54-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. &apos;G.T.-12 WAR   CABIFET,/ ::V: PRODUCTION OF MUNITIONS BY AMERICA.HANKER VI WHICH U.S.A. CAIT BEST RENDER ASSISTANCE IH EVEITT - OE THEIR ENTRY INTO THE WAR.(Memo by the. Minister of Munitions, circulated to War Cabinet in reference to War Cabinet 54, Minute 3).The following Memorandum has been prepared by the Ministry of Munitions in response to the minute from the War Cabinet extracted below:-. . . &quot;The War Cabinet desire to be informed at the &quot;earlieet possible moment what further assistance &quot;can be rendered to the Ministry of Munitions by &quot;the United States of America in the event of their &quot;breaking off relations with Germany&quot;(I) It is assumed that special consideration will in any case be given to such important matters as the following:-(a) The Financial assistance the U.S.A. can give to the Allied Governments:(b) The release of the interned enemy shipping to make them available for ocean freight.(c) The use of the American Navy for convoy purposes.(II) Outside these points, the Ministry of Munitions are of opinion that the following considerations should form the subject of negotiations with the United States Government, should that country declare War.with Germany:-(a) The first necessity is that the U.S.A. Government should not in any way interfere with the production of munitions at present being made to the orders of the Allies.     Conferences should be held betweenthe U.S..A. Government and the Ministry&apos;s Organisation in America and also with the various Allies1 Commiss-Ions, and arrangements should be made by whioh the works in the States which have completed or are completing the Allies&apos; contracts should be utilised in the first case for meeting the demands of the United States.     Further, it is considered that the fullest use should be made of knowledge possessed by the Ministry!s Organisation in America of the resources of the country for the manufacture of munitions.(b) Great congestion exists .at present on the railways and-at the ports and depots in the U.S.A.   The Federal: and-States governments should at once take all steps they can to improve this situation. ,&apos;(c)     In the United Kingdom it has been necessary to:regulate prices by State act in certain cases, e.g. :-;Steel;. and Iron, and also to restrict the supply of materials and labour in certain industries in order
that they may be made available for the production of munitions.If the United States enter into the War they will     . probably, find it necessary to ,take similar action. This would relieve the position with regard to the supply of materials,.and would facilitate the -supply of munitions for the Allies generally.(d)     Owing to the shortage of propellants and the fact v ; that a very large proportion of the total supply comes from the U.S.A,   the:Ministry are constructing a large nitro-cellulose factory in Great Britain.   If there were no fear of the stoppage of the supply from America owing to political reasons, it would undoubtedly be more advantageous from the freight and labour view points if this new factory were to be constructed in America. &apos;Moreover, output/would probably be obtained at an earlier date if this were done.(It should be noted that in view of the fact that certain commitments have already been entered v into with regard to the new nitro-cellulose factory at Henbury, and in view also of the desirability of . having a National nitro-cellulose factory in this country, it would probably be advisable that the construction of this factory on perhaps a smaller scale .. (say one-half) should in any case be continued with a view to completion at the earliest possible date.   If this were done it would not, appear to be necessary to sanction the extensions to private factories now being considered by the Explosives Supply -Department) .&apos; (e)      The   greatest assistance could be afforded at once - / if the U.S.A., Government were to assist in the provision of essential materials, such as copper, brass, zinc, oil, steel and other raw products, so as to enable the Allies to possess sufficient - /    working stocks.(Sgd)     Cv ADDISON.13th February 1917.

</content>
</cab>
