<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 143-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of Eis.. Britannic Majesty ^Government]   ..; Printed for ike use of the Cabinet.   February 1917.CONFIDENTIAL. jULBg.t.- 26. ; v;v^SSKI think the Cabinet may like to see Mr. MontgomeryV views on Mr. Buchan&apos;s Memorandum about Propaganda. Mr. Montgomery has a most intimate knowledge of the practical working of the existing system.A. J. B.\ February 15, 1917.I HAVE read MivBuchanV memorandum of the 3rd February, and, while I think that the efficiency of propaganda work might he considerably increased by carrying out some of his recommendations, I do not think that there is anv need to uproot the existing organisation in order to put them into effect; moreover, for the reasons stated in the memorandum circulated to tho Cabinet bv Mr. Balfour on the 3rd February, I am strongly of opinion that the setting up of a separate office for propaganda is very undesirable. The objects aimed at in Mr. Buchan&apos;s memorandum, in so far as they are not in fact covered by existing arrangements, could all bo achieved by carrying out the recommendations contained in the last paragraph of the memorandum circulated by Mr. Balfour.Mr. Buchan is not quite accurate in all his statements; as to the existing propaganda work, and owing to this his memorandum gives an impression of confusion and inefficiency in that work which, in my opinion, is not justified by the facts. &apos;. For instance, Mr. Buchan says there is a good deal of confusion in the matter of finance. The Foreign Office and Wellington House (working under its direction) are, I understand, the only two Departments spending money for propaganda purposes on any considerable scale. At the Foreign Office all the financial side of the work, including the expenditure entailed by the work carried out by Mr. Mair and his staff, passes through my hands, and I have heard of no complaints of confusion at all: I know of the arrangements under which the funds at Wellington House are administered, and there is no confusion there.In the matter of cables and wireless, Mr. Buchan says &quot; a great deal is done badly.&quot; He adds that there is delay, and that much unsuitable matter is sent. I do -not know on what evidence this is based. Considering the difficulty, of catering for the different countries concerned, there has been very little criticism from the people who are responsible! for receiving and distributing the. messages at the other end, and we are largely guided by them as to the nature of the . matter sent; moreover,&apos; papers abroad are taking up our wireless messages and cables more every day.The memorandum is also very misleading in another respect as regards the matter of ,cables, because Mr. Buchan makes no reference to the fact that the cables actually sent by those who work directly under the Foreign Office are only intended to be supplementary to the very large service of news sent out for the Foreign Office by Keuter&apos;s. (They send, instance, for than 20,000 words a month for us to Holland.) Reuters have, of course, a large staff of experts for the purpose and they daily consult the Foreign Office and receive suggestions as to any particular points to which that Office consider, it desirable to pay attention. There is, of course, no point in establishing a service which would in any way compete with this, and our object has been merely to supplement the service sent by EeuterV on our behalf in any places where it does not cover all the ground.Mr. Buchan ignores the large amount of propaganda work of various kinds whicli we do through our Embassies, legations, and consulates abroad, this could not conveniently be done from a separate office havinsr no direct authority over our representatives abroad.It is not correct to say that publications, books, pamphlets, and:magazines are &quot; the staple of the whole propaganda business.&quot; This is certainly an important.part of the business, and the fact that there is an increasing spontaneous demand for such matter from America and other neutral countries presents a situation which we must
continue to meet. &quot;But cables: (through Reuter&apos;s and otherwise) and. information and facilities to foreign journalists in London have long ago taken: a position of far more importance that these things in the daily conduct of propaganda. In this connection, I should like to emphasise the point tliat.it.will he quite impracticable to supply the correspondents with the information that they want (fully 75 per cent: of which .concerns foreign affairs), except by having a staff: for the purpose at the Foreign Office; it is.proposed to use the staff, which now exists fjjr the purpose, in the new Department. There would, therefore, either, be no si aft at the Foreign Office to attend to the wants of the correspondents,, which now.take up a considerable portion . of the day of several people, or a fresh &apos; staff would have to be, set up. there which would largely duplicate the work which, I. understand, the people in charge of special areas in the new Department are intended to do.There are other points which are, in my opinion, open to criticism, but the above \&quot; are the most important.   -- I would urge strongly that such improvements as are: necessary can be made without the expenditure of money, effort, time, and housing room, and the disorgani-sation of existing arrangements which the establishment of a new Department would involve. . - -&apos;.^V^yyy^yy^fy.&quot;,-&apos;&quot;&apos;;-,- &apos;. - H. M.February 14, 1917. -

</content>
</cab>
