<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 233-234</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Col. Jones

SECRET.

G.T. 45

WAR CABINET

CONVEYANCE OF IRON ORE FROM SPAIN

(Memorandum by Sir Guy Granet)

Referring to Minute 8 of War Cabinet meeting (W.C.63) held on February 13th, x the result of enquiries made in Spain through the F.O. and in France through D.C.T. are not yet to hand. Meanwhile, however, it may be well to set out certain facts as regards the provision of locomotives and rolling stock for the consideration of the War Cabinet.

1. The amount of ore ordinarily shipped to this country from Bilbao is ? 3,400,000 tons per annum. Assuming that only half of this amount is required to be transported overland, and that work is carried out on 365 days per annum, this amounts to about 4,600 tons per day. This would necessitate the provision of 460 10-ton trucks or 12 trains and 12 locomotives per day. It is impossible for me to make an accurate calculation as to the number of wagons and locomotives required for the full service absence of exact knowledge as the length and grades of the routes to be followed.

NOTE. Extract from War Cabinet 63.

Iron Ore from Spain.

8. In regard to the conveyance of iron ore overland from Spain to France (War Cabinet, 58, Minute 3), the Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that ?there was a break of gauge between the French and Spanish railways on the West side on the Spanish frontier. He undertook to make further enquiries into the matter of the possibility of rail transport, and, in conjunction with Lord Hardinge, to draw up a draft telegram to our Minister in Spain, asking if Spain is in a position to furnish the necessary rolling stock to carry the ore from the frontier. He also undertook to ascertain whether France could provide rail transport from the frontier.

NOTE. At a conference on the question of the allocation of supplies of steel to various Government Departments held at the Admiralty on 3rd February, Mr. Hunter representing the Ministry of Munitions, stated that 600,000 tons of Spanish Ore are required per month.
But the calculations agreed with the French as to the locomotives-&quot;and-v.rolling stock, necessary - for the.--journey.:.; between Cherbourg and -iiloFane in eoirnoctiori with, the Faranto project; enable me to&apos; make &apos;a rough guecs.    ihe distance between Cherbourg- and Kodane is 1,110 idiomstres and the number of locomotives re-uiredvper daily train &quot;was .22.-: - fhe. distance. b e twe en t he Spanish&apos; F&apos;r one ier. and, Cher hour is about 550 miles or. 800 kilometres., I assume.--therefore: only 17 engines &quot;per: daily train.   mllowin;; for 8 cays round:trip and...: allowi-ig 10;-.. for spares - this would involve the provision of at . least 4,000. wagons, and on the /assumption of 17 engines per daily train, 221 locomotives would be reonireF.2, .Prom tho Minutes 01 the meeting: at the -ministry oftransport in Paris.,0111st February to discuss : the faranto scheme, it&apos;is clear that the Trench will be unable to assist by the provision of either locomotives or wagons.3.  .     :,:: .&quot;.s owing..to: the. uiiieronce : in gauge it will be impossible:to :obtain assistance with Opain,hit will be necessary for this country, to iind these - 224.locomotives and 4,000 wagons.      &apos;4. ht the present moment this country isproviding 370looomotives from the 2.:itish ralIways. and 300 irom 0ther . sources, -and...20,.000.: wagons from the British &quot;railways (in addition to -; out standing: order s; f or ab out 20,000; 10- ton units) to; assist; the: French railways to &quot;serve she British Frmy In Prance.;fhese locomotives and wagons have only been; provided after great Fiiiieulty and after cutting down services on   h British railways, in a very drastic manner,     - he extia locomotives and wagons necessary for this: service: could no doubt be iound, but 01-6bably only c t the &apos;-;:- price of ; re Fixcing ; the; efficiency 0f the Br it ish railways. Moreover the shipping difficulty is great       fhe Frsnch ports;: are: eohcongested /that /the-shibmentsh of locomotives;/ and- wagonsVpromised- to the French for the/Pord-system-are very much behindhand.7 ;::. h&apos;&apos;.:. Even if,extra shipping were provided so as 10 convey h:the necessary stock&quot;withowt retarding -the shipments promised for the IT or d system;;; it. is doubtful whether the- French ports could receive it except in driblets.. .-     (Signed)  :&apos; h&quot;.&apos; GUFF CfLUCf.  2nd February, 1917. &apos;-/-     ,-;&apos; .- .

</content>
</cab>
