<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 273-278</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MEMORANDUMBY THEMINISTER OF LABOUR.
PRELIMINARY STEPS TO BE TAKEN IMMEDIATELY WITH A VIEW TO REDISTRIBUTION OF LABOUR AFTER THE WAR.1. In view of the fact that a very great deal of preliminary work will be necessary to prepare the measures essential to ensure the smooth and efficient working of the arrangements for the redistribution of labour after the war, it is, in my opinion, necessary that certain steps should be taken at once.2. It is true that the machinery of the Employment Exchanges, which is to&apos; be utilised for this purpose, is already in existence, but it is necessary that this should be strengthened and extended in various directions.3. The matter, solar as it relates to demobilisation, has been under the careful consideration of the Recon-struction Committee, who came to certain conclusions. They have not yet dealt with the question of munition workers, but I have no reason to suppose that their conclusions in this respect will be materially different from those at which they have arrived in connection with the demobilisation of soldiers and sailors.4. The following conclusion, amongst others, was adopted by the Reconstruction Committee on 1st December 19.16, viz.: &quot; That a Central Demobilisation Committee should be appointed, as soon as its exact composition can be settled with the Departments concerned, to work in conjunction with the Employment Department of the Board of Trade; that there should be a system of local Demobilisation Committees covering the whole of the country to work in conjunction with the local Exchanges-both the Central and local Committees to consist mainly of representatives of employers and workmen in equal numbers ; and that the Central Committee should have an opportunity of seeing and discussing the scheme proposed, before it is finally adopted and put in operation.&quot;5. Central Demobilisation Committee. The Employ-ment Department of the Board of Trade has now been transferred to the Ministry of Labour,, upon which, therefore, devolves the task of appointing the Central Demobilisation Committee as the first step in carrying into effect the conclusion of the Reconstruction Com-mittee. This should be done as soon as possible, in order that there may be no delay in proceeding with the scheme of local Demobilisation Committees, which has to be submitted to the Central Committee in accordance with the conclusion of the Reconstruction Committee.6. It is proposed that tho representatives of employers and workpeople on the Central Demobilisation Committee shall be nominated, inmost cases, by the principal Federations of Employers and Workpeople respectively; in a few cases, Owing, e.g., to the non-existence of an association covering the trade, it will be necessary for me to nominate the representative.o   2461 a
; 7. It is. also proposed to add two women represen- $&amp;as j$$jtjie:&apos;.JQo^tmfttee,&apos; since,-even-if the Committee 4eals; solely jijpiestion of the return to civil lifeof i(iemobilLseci soldiers and sailors, it is possible that the interests&apos; ,0!. WQiBfiP- ^e seriously affected in caseswhere men&apos;s places have been taken, during their absence on active service, by women.-8. If it should be decided thot this Committee is to deal \vith munition workers and substitutes, upon which at present no,decision has been taken, it would probably be&apos;desirable to appoint two more women on the Com--mitteel There would be no difficulty about doing this after the Committee had been set up.9. The Composition of the Central DemobilisationCommittee, if appointed on these lines, would be as follows :-Chairman -     -     -     -     -     -     - 1Vice-Chairman -     -     -     -     -     - 1Representatives of Employers   -     -     - 17,,         ,,      Workpeople -      - 17,,      Women       -    - - .    - 2,,      Government Departments 8&apos;    46..An appendix is attached to this memorandum, giving full details of the proposed composition of the Committee.10. Chairman and Vice-Chairman. As the Ministry must keep in the closest touch with the work of the Committee, it is proposed that the Chairman should be the Minister of Labour ex officio, and that there also be a Vice-Chairman, for which post I should propose Sir George Murray or some public man cf similar standing.11. Local Demobilisation Committees. It is proposed that, the local Demobilisation Committees should be formed by enlarging the new Advisory Employment Ex-change Committees which it is proposed to set up at once. It is intended that practically every town with its own Employment Exchange will have a local Advisory Committee appointed to assist and advise the Exchange in its work.12. These Committees are to consist of represen-tatives of employers and workpeople in equal numbers and of representatives of women; they will be so con-stituted as to be easily susceptible of development into local Demobilisation Committees by the addition of representatives of local Recruiting Bodies and Terri-torial Force Associations.13. Local Agents. The extension of Unemployment Insurance to discharged soldiers and sailors will entail a considerable increase in the number of Local Agencies in rural districts. In accordance with the recommenda-tions of the Sub-Committee of the Reconstruction Committee, of which Sir Clarendon Hyde was Chairman, the number required will be about 670. Preliminary steps with a view to the appointment of these Agents ought to be taken at once.14. Extension of Employment Exchange Premises.  It will also be necessary, in order to carry out the planso (33)2461   Pk 126  50   2/17   K&amp;S A2
recommended by the Reconstruction Committee, to provide existing Employment Exchanges with additional accommodation, and in certain towns it will be necessary to open new Exchanges, whilst in other places Local Agencies already existing must be converted into Employment Exchanges with a whole-time staff. The requirements of the Department have been carefully estimated, and it is proposed to press forward with this work as soon as it is sanctioned. The opening of new-Exchanges, and additions to existing premises, will of course necessitate a proportionate increase of staff, most of which will be engaged on a temporary basis.JOHN HODGE.
APPENDIX.1. Chairman and Vice-Chairman.2. Representatives of Employers : The National Federation of Building TradesEmployers of Great Britain and Ireland - 1The Mining Association of Great Britain - IThe Iron and Steel Industry -      -     - - 1The Engineering Employers&apos; Federation 1Shipbuilding Employers&apos; Federations    - - 1Federation of Master Cotton Spinners&apos; Associa-tion, Ltd.  -      - -Cotton, Spinners&apos; and Manufacturers&apos; Associa-tion . -      -      -      -      -      -      -      -The Woollen and Worsted Industry      -      - 1 Incorporated Federated Associations of Bootand Shoe Manufacturers of Great Britainand Ireland      -      -      -      -      -      -   1Wholesale Clothing Manufacturers&apos; Federationof Great Britain and Ireland     -     -      -   1The Shipping Industry -      -     -     -      - 1The Central Association of Chambers of Agri-    . */culture     -      -      -      -      -      -      - 1Federation of Master Printers, &amp;c.        -     -   1Federation of British Industries    -     -      - 1Railways Companies Association   -     -     - 1 Representative of Financial and BankingInterests   -      -      -      - - 1Associated Chambers of Commerce - -1 Representatives of Women    -      -      -      -13. Representatives of Labour: The Amalgamated Society of Engineers -     - 1 United Society of Boilermakers and Iron andSteel Shipbuilders    -     -      -      -     - 1 The National Union of Gas Workers andLabourers of Great Britain and Ireland     - 1Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain      -      - 1National Union of Railwaymen     -      -      - 1 National Agricultural Labourers and RuralWorkers&apos; Union-     -     - .-     - 1National Building Trades Council -      -      - 1 The   Ship Constructors   and   Shipwrights&apos;Association       -     -     - -     - 1British Steel Smelters, Mill, Iron, Tinplate,and Kindred Trades Association -     -     -&apos; 1United Textile Factory Workers&apos;Association - 1 Printing and Kindred Trades Federation ofthe United Kingdom -      -      -      -      - 1National Transport Federation      -      -      - 1National Union of Boot*and Shoe Operatives - 1Yorkshire Textile Workers&apos;Federation -     - 1 The Parliamentary Committee of the TradeUnion Congress -     -     -     -     -     - 1The General Federation of Trade Unions      - 1Representatives of Women Employees   -     - 1
Official Representatives:--Ministry of Labour (including one woman) Ministry of Munitions   -      -Ministry of Pensions (Statutory Committee) War Office   -     -     -     -     -     -Admiralty    - -

</content>
</cab>
