<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 286-287</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
O       ;.&apos;      Iff * :      / A    .SECRET &apos;G.T.-59 FAR^CABIITFiT 231STATE OF TKF AIR SERVICE WITH BRITISH EZPFDITIOffART FORCE.Copy of a letter from 2?.M. , C-in-C to the C.I.G.S. dated 15th February 191?(Circulated at the r equest of the C.I.C-.S.)Thi Chief of theImperial General Staff,It appears to me necessary to bring to the notice of the War Cabinet the state of the Air Service in France.   On the 15th, January I informed the War:Cabinet, at the Conference in London, that this service would probably not be fully ready for an offensive; by the 1st: April.     To-day the situation appears to be worse than I had hoped.&apos; , ::: On the 50th \ September -1916, I called the attention ofthe Army Council ;to&apos; the urgent necessity of an early increase In the number and-efficiency of fighting aeroplanes, and, after., some correspondence on the subject of our estimated requirements, I was informed offieially by the War CfPice on the 15th November -1916, that the establishment of 56 squadrons r:;as approved in principle, and I was furnished with a forecast of the estimated rate of supply.Since that; date continual short postponements of the arrival of new squadrons and:machines for replacement have been notified to the G.0.C,, R.F.C in France by&apos; the Director or Air Organisation and I am informed that the situation is now as followst-Promised by March 7th. Probable arrivals by March ?th.5 new type Corps: Squadrons.; 3 new type Corps Squadrons5 replacements F; . 8 replacements (1 doubtful)11 new type fighting Souadrons 7 new type fighting squadrons 3 replacements (new type (2 of these doubtful), fighting squadrons) Uo replacements.   ;- Ff-&apos;\       The result m^y;be - summarised as under:-(i) There will be no reserve of Corps Squadrons, and five squadrons which should have been new type will be old-\- Ff-Vf- type.(ii) There will be a shortage of From four to seven fighting v  F squadrons below what was promised, and of seven to tenF   below what I asked for, and in addition two squadrons v     F  which should have been new type will not have been con-verted from old type.The position as regards fighting squadrons in particular is most serious.     Our fighting:machinesFwiir almost certainly fre ^flferioPin number and quite certainly in performance to those of the enemy.   In view, therefore, of the marked increase-in the number and efficiency of the German aeroplanes, it arrears that
we cannot expect to gain supremacy in the air in April, a is even possible that it may pass to the enemy.The seriousness of this situation cannot he ov-jr-r and its possible effect on the results of our operations no doubt be fully realised by the War Cabinet.(Sgd)      D.HAIG.Field-Marshal Ootiiuander-in-Chief, British Amies in France.

</content>
</cab>
