<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 293-296</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S E 0. g g T. r 62vHots by the Shipping Controller)Dear Sir Maurico Hankey,referenoe to your,letter of the 21st instant and the War cabinet o2 Minute 4 (0) as to the average profits of Shipowners for 2,3,4 and 5 years respectively before the Tfor, I understand that the Inland Kcvenuo have furnished a report to the Chancellor of the Sxchoquor in which the results are given as follows--2 years avorago 16,203    &quot;        &quot; i4:o 4     11 &quot; 13,605:    &quot; &quot; 12,50I have not the same facilities as the Inland Revenue for obtaining complete information as to Shipowners profits in different years and am not in a position to suggest any correction of those figuros,   Thoy are, ho?/evor, tho average for passenger and cargo vessels together, as pointed out in the memorandum, and this is a consideration of the utmost importance.   Passenger vessels generally earn much loss than cargo vessels in good years and mere in bad years, The profits of cargo vossols separately would thereforo shew a very much wider variation from year to year.   As any datum decided upon whether for 2,3,4 or 5 years, would,&quot; I presume, then bo taken for tho actual earnings of the individual Owner, this iDcint Is clearly of the first importance in considering the subject.,   I have not made any original investigations as to the profits of cargo vessels generally as distinct from passenger vessels, but I enclose for your information a paper showing(1)   an extract from Jpairplay1 of December 24th 1914, giving a table of cargo boat earnings for tho 11 years 1904 to 1914;(2)   a simple calculation showing on the values and profits thore.given what was tho not profit as a percentage on book value in each year, and(3)   a calculation on tho same basis of the average profits for cargo vessels for tho four periods named by tho Cabinet.You will see that this result which, as stated above, is only based on the figures collected from ^airplay1 gives for cargo vossols the follor/ing results;-     &apos;%2 years average 10 &quot;,9803     &quot;          n 13;9504   &quot;       &quot; io;7i05     lt          &quot; 8.54$This letter only deals with tho actual question of profits. The application of the provisions of tho Railway Agreement, and the necessary notifications in view of the very difficult conditions of shipping, requires further a very careful consideration and I will write te you again as soon as possible.Yours faithfully, (Signed)     J* MACLAY,Sir Maurice Eankey,2 Vlhitehall Gardens,S.Wa

: :     -V;:&apos;.;:&apos;fsff; &apos;y;:-7,&apos;*&apos;.,v-   &apos; ^ - \ cargo jo(1) The is sue of &quot;^airplay&quot; for Decentof cargo-hoat earnings *,Year1904 1905 1906 1907 1908 1909 1910 1911 1912 1913 1914Paid-up capitalDebenturesBooh valueloans; etc;      of steamors 7;549 3,577;8;081 9,167 9,6229,517 9,457 9,883 10,559 10;964 10,842,278,424;800,259,401,011,650,584,843,108:,026 3.157 3,775; 3;669 4,448 4,409 4,985 5,548 6,261 6,050 5,490 4,677,128 ,681 ,142 ,905 ,343;osi,999 ,588 ,067 ,388 ,571 10,753 12,353 12,130 13,732 14,338 13;915 14,610 15,717 16,477 16,682 15,587,752 ,849 ,265 ,754 ,652 ,494 ,877 ,739 ,354 ,965 ,708Ho. of. vessels393 464 433 490 533 508 522 535 561 598 569Tons gross.1,184,358 1,362,049 1,336-, 823 1,516,401 1,6-95; 837 1,603,341 1,725,335 1,833,360 1,981,209 2,121,427 2,067,403?j478,8524,771,07814,209,221509     1,675,211(2) Deducting depreciation at 5$ froc on the booh value of the steamers: : with the corres^ondhiYear1904 1906-1907 1908 1909 1910 1911 1912 1913 1914Net Profit a percentage booh value. , ;    &apos;       -   cf?:.: - :-J--;;- 1*.17 .17 2.04 1.79 1.87 loss103&amp;3.36 11.28 26.50 .   18.10.(3) Aye rag c Prof its of Cargo-boats fcr*age p profit 1912-15 &quot; &apos;   ,T        1911-12&quot; A&apos;      1910-13;&quot; &quot;V     1909-1$
[I2TGS.191.4 gives the following table I a years,.1904-1914. -rofit on a&amp;es11;,6985,5453,857;5,5877,9972,5111,5415,5165,8503,093Dividend	:   per	Depreciation	Depreciationon capital	cent	written off	at 5% 277,139	3.64	 216,154	 622,725286,005	o, o3	238,505	740,901    - ;,327,445	4.05-	348,651	&quot; 731,971385,077	4.17	.413,390 -	632,716!;-535,165.	3.40	395,696	.876,170179,886    -	1.89	189,043	837,890217,681	:   2.30	290,115	864,187370,061  .	.&apos;   3.73	506,040	943,088720,558	6.82	1,463,919	1,011,0281,377,615	12.56	3,544,643:	1,073,6651,126,069	10.38	1,944,463	1,003,349509,153	5.57 -_r............	-859,874	867,0627,539fit on voyages, the ^ net profit /;.&apos;--m in the following table/together fit per gross ton. .Profit per GrossTons.rr &apos;.&apos;oi o.5.18.o -    i1.   7.d. 4.S,rto 2.9. 9. 9.&quot; rroI, 4 &amp; 5 years before War18.98 15.95 10,71 8.54

</content>
</cab>
