<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/6/0 images: 407-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;EH -CA3IH3T.    /(Memorandinn by Sir. Alfred Mond. Mrst Commissioner of Works) *grime Minister.It has been;suggested to&quot; me that, it would be of great value, for the future to begin collecting material for a national: War LIuseum which is now; being done in Prance;; such material:would:include.(1)   Naval and Military trophies and specimens.;(2).   3ooks, Pamphlets, maps,- posters, pictures dealing with; the war.Tho collection would be formed partly by purchases from fimds placed by the Treasury at the disposal of the Committee in charge Of this object, and secondly by gifts from private persons.I understand that there are a number of people who are collecting various objects relating to the war which they will probably bo pleased;to hand over to some permanent national collection. &apos;,&apos;I propose that a small honorary Coiamittee should be formed of which the;&apos;First Commissioner of Works .should be Ex officio:Chairman, and.which should consist also of;a Director General of the Collection, a representative of the Admiralty, a representative of the War Office, representa-  . tives of the literary and art sides and an Honorary ... Secretary.-&apos; I believe; there would be no difficulty in obtaining * gentlemen of position who; would gladly undertake-this work. &apos;The question of where the Qollection can be finally housed need -not be dealt with at the present time.     The immediate necessity and the important matter is the collection of the material which can be stored, if necessary, until the.end of the war.If the scheme ;is;approved, I would suggest that;a small, grant&apos; of. -.. say-.-  3,000v.be -.- ma de by the Treasury to cover the purchases, wherevgifts are not available and any. running expenses for.secretarial and record.work,(Initialled)   AoH.27th February, 1917,i- j    &quot;   1   1 ; 1  11       j     &apos; &quot; &quot;  -rc   rn   V. p ^

</content>
</cab>
