<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 9-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] Printed for the Cabinet. July 1924.SECRET.- i 39CP. 401 (24).CABINET.SPECIAL REPORT ON  UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 106.   Period ended June 23, 1924.THE unemployment figures given in the Table in Part I (A) of this report show a decrease since the 26th May of 1,844, as compared with 32,154 during the period covered by the previous report. It will be observed from the Table that the Registers for the 9th June and the 16th June both recorded a large increase in unemployed persons. This increase appears to have been due in a large measure to the fact that in a number of cases firms extended the period of the &quot;Whitsuntide holidays, and does not signify any violent fluctuation in trade. A similar increase in unemployment occurred during the corresponding weeks following &quot;Whitsuntide of last year.The steady decrease in unemployment which has been a noticeable feature of the position since the beginning of the year has been retarded during the past month owing to the depression in the coal-mining industry, which has almost neutralised the slight improvement in the shipbuilding and engineering trades and other industries.T. SHAW.Ministry of Labour, July 16, 1924.I.(A.) Live Register of Unemployed at the Employment Exchanges in Great Britain. 	1922.	1923.	1924.						June 26.	June! 25.	May 26.	June 2.	June 9.	June 16.	June 23.	Increase (-I-) or Decrease (-) since May 26.Men Boys Women Girls Total	1,196,551 42,413 167,173 29,963	927,658 36,695 225,183 33,616	754,553 33,669 194,893 32,511	754,661 31,961 185,731 30,562	764,321 31,559 200,705 30,930	786,469 ! 766,960 31,013 1   29,580 205,284 ! 189,357 29,875 i    27,885		-1-12,407 - 4,089 - 5,536 - 4,626	1,436,100	1,223,152	1,015,626	1,002,915	1,027,515	1,052,641 1,013,782		-  1,844The above figures represent the number of persons recorded as not at work and claiming&apos; unemployment benefit on the dates given, whether they were totally unemployed, suspended or stood off, &amp;c, or working&apos; systematic short time.Percentage of unemployment in the insured industries at the end of May 1922       ....        ....        ........   13&apos;8,,    1923       .... .... .... .....  10-8,,   1924      ....        ............    93The above percentage figures include some, but not all, of the workpeople on &quot; short time.&quot;[11859] B
(B.) Important Changes in the Live Registers of Employment Exchangesduring the Period.London and South-Eastern Division.Luton. Increase 563 (30 men, 533 women) due to the termination of the straw hat manufacturing, season.South-Western Division.Gloucester. Increase 863 (857 men, 6 women) due to depression in the coal-mining industry.Southampton. Decrease 893 (decrease 918 men, increase 25 women)-due to increased employment in ship-repairing yards and docks.Midlands Division.Coventry.-Increase 504 (principally men) due mainly to seasonal decline in the cycle and motor-cycle trades.BasforcP.-Increase 1,388 (chiefly men)Ilkeston-Increase 3,551 (chiefly men)      Ldue \0 seasonal, depression in thev      J      &apos;      [    coal-mmmg industry.Nottingham.-Increase 3,044 (chiefly men)due to depression in the coal-mining industry.North-Eastern Division.BIyth. Increase 1,095(increase 1,099 men, decrease 4 women)Pontefract. Increase 635(increase 641 men, decrease 6 women)Bradford. Increase 1,420 (908 men, 512 women) due to depression in the wool-combing section of the textile industry.Hull. Decrease 883 (749 men, 134 women) due to increased employment on the docks and amongst fishing workers.Leeds. Decrease 611 (424 men, 187 women)- due to increased employment in the engineering, building and wholesale clothing industries.Middlesbrough.-Increase 845 -y(increase &quot;910 men, decrease 65 women) I due to depression in the iron andScunthorpe.-Increase 397                        I steel industry.    ,(increase 416 men, decrease 19 women) J ;Newcastle-on-Tyne. Decrease 1,182 (1,175 men, 7 women) due to general trade . improvement.North Shields. Decrease 513 (decrease 539 men, increase 26 women) due to improvement in the shipbuilding and engineering trades. - &apos;North-Western Division.Burnley. Increase 1,100 (300 men, 800 women) due to depression in the engineering and cotton-spinning and weaving trades.Farnworth. Increase 500 (men) due to depression in the coalmining industry.Glossop. Decrease 2,050 (650 men, 1,400 women) due to several cotton mills restarting work.Rochdale. Decrease 1,100 (women) due to increased employment in the cotton industry.Scotland Division.Glasgow Exchanges.-Decrease 1,8&apos;18 (1,153 men, 665 women)-due to increased employment in shipbuilding and public works for men and to seasonal work so far as women are concerned.
m ,&apos;due to intermittent working of collieries.Port Talbot-Increase 842II.-POSITION IN CHIEF INDUSTRIES.Coal Mines. The depression in this industry, which occurred during May has continued and employment has shown a further decline. Employment in the Bristol pits decreased considerably, and much short time&apos; was worked in the Forest of Dean. Short time was worked in most centres in the Midlands. In the Nottingham district 20,000 workers were so affected. In the North Staffordshire area the position was steadier and full time was worked in some centres. In the South Staffordshire area employment showed a decline in most districts. In the North-Eastern Counties, the depression previously reported as confined to Durham and Northumberland became deeper, and there are signs of its spreading to the South Yorkshire area. Discharges of men or irregular working are reported in many places. This position is largely due to a diminished export trade. In the Lancashire and Cumberland districts employment has declined, and in many collieries working hours have been curtailed. In Scotland it has been found necessary to resort to unsystematic short-time working at various centres. Sixteen thousand men are affected: In the South Wales.coal-field the situation was not satisfactory, and periodical stoppages or intermittent working occurred during the period in a number of instances. The principal pits remained fairly busy, but stoppages due to depression or shortage of trucks took place in many cases. Some of the less important collieries are stated to have closed down.Stone Quarries. There is no change to report.China Clay. This industry still continues active. The Cornish pits are still busy, but the surplus of labourers continues.Iron Mines.--Employment in this industry showed a further decline.Tin Mines. The slow improvement in Cornwall continued.IRON AND STEEL PRODUCTION.This industry remained depressed, and the employment position on the whole showed little or no improvement. In the Cleveland and Scunthorpe districts there was less activity and new orders are lacking. The export trade is equally as bad as the home trade, and shipments were about 20,000 tons less than for the previous period. The position is similar in the heavy steel trade in the Sheffield area, and a number of furnaces may close down in the absence of further orders. Rolling mills, however, were fairly busy and forges were well employed. The haematite steel and iron works at Barrow has reopened, but slackness of trade is reported from Bolton and Workington, where the steel works have been closed. In the Midland Counties unemployment &quot;remained heavy and there is little change to report. Whilst trade showed a slight improvement in North Staffordshire, employment in the South Staffordshire area continued to be very bad. At Bilston a large steel works is practically closed down. There has been an increase of short-time working at Brierley Hill, and the position at Wellingborough was less favourable. At Willenhall trade was good, and all firms were fully employed. In Scotland trade was very quiet and. showed no signs of improvement. The pig-iron trade at Coatbridge in particular was bad, only eight out of thirty-five furnaces being in blast, and only half the[11859] \\\ B 2Aberdeen. Decrease 771 (509 men, 262 women)-due to. improvement in the shipbuilding and allied trades and to the opening of the herring fishing season.Greenock. Increase 694 (571 men, 123 women) due to a decline in employment at the docks and at sugar refineries.HamiltonMotherwell V Increase 1,809-due to depression in the coal-mining industry. Rutherglen jWales Division.Blaina. Increase 989
normal number of men employed. The position in &quot;Wales was fairly satisfactory. In the pig-iron trade at Ebbw Vale full time was worked.TIN-PLATE TRADE.Continued activity was reported from Wales, and exports continued to increase.SHIPBUILDING AND SHIP-REPAIRING.The slight improvement previously reported has been maintained and a further small improvement was reported. Additional men have been taken on in many of the North-East coast shipyards. At Barrow and at Birkenhead employment was good. There was a slow but steady improvement on the Clyde. A slight improvement in ship-repairing work is reported from Deptford and Poplar. In the South-Western Counties, while there has been no general improvement, no serious diminution of activity has been reported. Employment in the Bristol yards remained steady, but was slack at Avonmouth. Work at Cowes continued in full swing, and employment at Woolston was good, but the position at Portsmouth outside the Dockyard remained bad. In the North and South Wales ports the position generally as regards ship-repairing was not satisfactory. At Swansea, however, employment was good, and the outlook at Cardiff is better.ENGINEERING.Motor and Cycle Engineering.-The employment position in this branch of the industry remained good. In the South-Eastern Counties the Leyland Motors (Limited) ahd A.C. Cars (Limited), at Kingston, increased their staff, and increased activity was displayed at Acton, Tottenham, Hendon, Maidstone and Aylesbury. In the South-Western Counties the motor-body building trade was very busy. Many of the men discharged from the Morris Works have been re-engaged. In the Midland Counties much unemployment still exists, chiefly among semi-skilled workers. In the Birmingham district, however, most firms were busy, and workers at Redditch were also fully employed. The usual seasonal slackness in trade has not yet become pronounced.  In Lancashire this branch of the industry continued to show activity.General Engineering. This branch of the industry continued to show improvement. In the North-Eastern Counties the improvement is mainly reflected in marine engineering, but more activity in other sections is also apparent. At Sheffield the saw trade was fully employed. Piles and general tools were also in demand, and outputs are slowly increasing. Improvement is also reported from Leeds and Bradford. Employment in iron and brass foundries in Lancashire has improved. Employment in the electrical and constructional engineering trades was well maintained. The locomotive works at Horwich were slack, and short time was instituted. At Crewe the carriage and permanent way sections were on short time. In textile engineering there is little improvement to report. In the Midlands unemployment is still heavy, but the slow improvement continued. 1 Little change occurred in the Birmingham area, and employment was intermittent at Smethwick and West Bromwich. Trade at Beeston and Nottingham was good, and at Newark and Stamford an improvement is apparent in the agricultural engineering section. In the South-Eastern Counties activity in most sections continued slightly to increase. At Deptford there has been an improvement in marine work. Messrs. Vickers of Weybridge worked night shifts on aeroplane and general work in several depart-ments, and overtime on agricultural machinery was worked at Bedford. Improvement has been shown at Dartford, Enfield and Chatham. The position at Ipswich was less acute, though not good. In the South-Western Counties there is no change to report. Employment was best in agricultural engineering and in the railway shops. Iron foundries provided good employment, but trade with brass founders and manufacturers of textile and other industrial machinery was slack. In Scotland little change occurred, but an improvement should follow the better position in the shipbuilding industry.TEXTILES.Cotton. Employment in the Egyptian (fine-spinning) section of the industry was maintained at a high level, but there was a considerable amount of unemploy-ment in the American cotton-spinning section, and, not only was organised short time still worked, but in a number of cases extended holidays were given. In the Weaving section of the industry the position is somewhat uncertain, and there has
been a slight falling off in trade in places where trade has hitherto been steady. Increased unemployment occurred at Burnley, and trade was poor at Blackburn, Bury and other centres. In the higher-grade goods the position is better, and additional looms were started at Preston and Ashton-under-Lyne. Employment was irregular in the Yorkshire cotton towns.Woollens and Worsteds. A slight depression has occurred in this industry, and short time was worked in many places. Employment has declined further in the wool-combing section at Bradford, and the shoddy and mungo trade has also suffered a set-back. At Witney the blanket trade remained normal, but short time was worked at Bath and Wellington (Somerset). Tweed manufacturers in Scotland were fairly well employed.Hosiery. The improvement previously reported has hardly been maintained. Short time was still&apos; worked at Basford, Derby, Sutton-in-Ashfield and Rugby. At Nottingham and Ilkeston there has been an increase in the demand for sports wear, and several overseas orders have been received.   In Scotland trade was fairly good.Lace. Unemployment in this industry is still heavy, and prospects of improvement seem remote. In the Midland Counties, the position at Basford, Beeston, Derby and Ilkeston continued to be very depressed, especially in the Levers section. A slight improvement is reported from Long Eaton. In the South-Western Counties no change occurred.Silk. Employment in this industry generally remained good, and there was an increasing demand for artificial silk. Full time was worked by most firms in Leek. At Macclesfield the number of unemployed has been reduced. Two cotton mills at Glossop, which have been closed since 1914 and 1916 respectively, have been taken over for the manufacture of artificial silk and the weaving of silk goods.Jute, The jute trade at Dundee remained steady, and two firms in this area are employing increased hands. No increase of unemployment has occurred in Forfarshire.Carpets. The industry is somewhat quieter, and the tendency seems to be towards lessened activity. A flood which occurred at Kidderminster, submerging the ground floors and basements of several carpet factories, caused much damage to materials and plant, and some 900 workpeople were thrown out of employment temporarily. In the South-Western Counties the factories at Salisbury and Stroud continued to be busy.BUILDING AND BRICK AND TILE MANUFACTURE.This report relates to the position prior to the stoppage of work due to the present dispute in the industry. Employment was reported as very good, with a steady demand for skilled labour. Employment amongst painters, however, diminished slightly. A shortage of bricks was reported at Redhill, where a contract is being undertaken, and at Walthamstow, where a housing scheme is in progress. In the brick and tile industry employment was generally good. At Peterborough, firms engaged in the making of Fletton bricks have many orders to execute, and con-siderable activity prevailed.  Pull time is being worked in most centres.CLOTHING.Trade in this industry continued to be fairly good, and most firms were busy. The wholesale tailoring trade in East London slackened as far as ladies&apos; tailoring is concerned, but in the West End firms engaged in tailoring and dressmaking were very busy. In the West Riding of Yorkshire there is still a good demand for experienced workers, and at Leeds unemployment among women is now lower than at any time since the trade depression of 1921. In the North-Western Counties trade is brisk, and employment is good in the underclothing trades. In the Midland Counties employment was good. In the shirt and collar trade there is no change to report. In the glove trade firms engaged in the making of fabric gloves at Barnstaple were busy, but short time was worked in leather glove factories.BOOT AND SHOE.This industry was slightly less active during the period. Unemployment remained heavy at Wellingborough and Kettering. Trade at Leicester was quieter and was slack at Stafford, but at Northampton employment was fairly good.
Employment remained poor at Bristol and Eastville, and with the smaller firms at Kingswood; the larger firms at Kingswood were, however, busy on advance orders. The trade shows a tendency to become slacker at Norwich.POTTERY.There is little change to report in this industry, and unemployment continued to be heavy. At Hanley, trade was fairly good in the sanitary section, and short-time working decreased in the earthenware and china branches. At Stoke-on-Trent the position was fairly good. The china trade at Derby remained busy, but the porcelain trade at Worcester was only moderate. In the South-Eastern and South-Western Counties trade was generally good.TRANSPORT.There has been no material change in this industry. Among dock workers employment has been better, owing to the increase in the arrivals of timber cargoes. A decline in employment was reported from Swansea.
III. OVERSEAS SETTLEMENT. (Colonial Office.)Under the Empire Settlement Act, 1922, assisted passage schemes for Australia, New Zealand, Canada and Ontario have been agreed with the Dominion Authorities concerned. In addition, schemes for the settlement of immigrants on the land have been agreed with the Governments of New South Wales, Victoria and Western Australia. A number of organisations, having as their object the provision of facilities for the settlement of immigrants in certain of the Dominions, have also been assisted. An extension of this, assistance to other organisations is under consideration.The number of persons approved for assistance and the number of departures during the month of May (with the corresponding figure for May of last year) and for the two months ended the 31st May, 1924 and 1923 respectively, are set out in the following Table : Monthly Progress Return relating to Schemes approved under &quot; The empire settlement Act, 1922.&quot;Approval and Departure Figures.Dominion.	Number of Approvals.				Number of Departures.				Month of May.		Two months ended May 31.		Month of May.		Two months ended May 31.		1924.	1923.	1924.	1923.	1924.	1923.	1924.	1923.(1.) Australia  (a.) Assisted passage scheme (J.) Land Settlement Schemes  NWaleSs0Uth 1 Approval and de- f (ii.) Victoria .. \-. P^ture &quot;gores . (iii. Western          included under Australia]   ^above . Total Australia under Government schemes (2.) Canada  (a.) Dominion assisted passage schemes-(i.) Nominated (ii.) Female household workers (iii.) Children (b.) Ontario assisted passage scheme Total Canada under Government schemes   .. (3.) New Zealand assisted passage scheme (4.) Minor schemes -(a.) Society for the Oversea Settlement of British Women (b.) British      Dominions      Emigration Society (Canada) (o.) Salvation   Army   (excluding   those coming   under  agreements   with Canada) -(i.) Women (Canada) (ii.) Boys (Canada) (iii.) Widows     with      families (Canada) (iv.) Families (Canada) (d.) Craigieliim Farm (Canada and A.us-tralia) (e.) Dr. Barnado&apos;s Homes (Australia) (/.) British Red Cross Society (Canada) .. (ff.) Fellowship of the Maple Leaf (Canada) (A.) Canadian National Railways (Canada) Total minor schemes Total	2,221 1 35	2,711 245	3,823* 11 48 53	5,383 384	1,947 1 30 29	1,674 107	4,004 1 63 514	3,556 107	2,221	2,711	3,823 2,073* 656* 438	5,383	1,947	1,674	4,004	3,556	1,127 350 171	14 189		291 106 190 493	1,039 331 171	192 237 174	1,984 656 469	291 298. 413 642	1,648	203	3,167	1,080	1,541	603	3,109	1,644	744	559	1,521	969	684	520	1,368	748	79 88 51 20	27 114 .   20 42	198 88 136 51 SI	48 153 70 51 12	75 88 36 20	7 114 20 42	123 88 136 36 31	23 153 -70 51 12	238 4,851	203 3,676	504	334	219	183:	414	309			9,015	7,766	4,391	2,980	8,895	6,257* These figures have been reduced ou account of cancellations during May.Note. In addition, free passages for ex-service men and dependents were granted during March, April and May in respect of S3 persons, making a total of 89,718 up to the end of May, 1924.    Wj
IY. STATISTICS RELATING TO FINANCIAL PROVISION FOR RELIEF OF UNEMPLOYMENT (including Post-War Resettlement of ex-Members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces), from the Armistice.Schemes of which the Whole Cost is Borne by the Exchequer  Table 1. Out-of-Work Donation, Training Schemes, &amp;c.Schemes of which Part of the Cost is Borne by the Exchequer  Table 2. Unemployment Insurance.Table 3. Unemployment Grants Committee, Ministry of transport schemes, &amp;c. Table 4. Land Settlement.Table 5.-Schemes for Training Women and Juveniles.Schemes involving Exchequer Guarantees Table 6. Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes.Other Schemes Table 7. Expenditure by Poor Law Authorities, A.(England and Wales), B (Scotland).These Statistical Tables have been compiled with a view to showing the extent of the effort from public sources since the Armistice to meet the problems of Post-War Resettlement and Unemployment, and to indicate the measure of assistance provided by the Exchequer. With regard to the latter, the methods of financial co-operation are so diverse that it is impracticable to give an aggregated figure of Exchequer Assistance. For this reason, the accompanying Summary is only indicative of the extent to which the Exchequer is involved, and must be regarded as supplementary to, and not in substitution of, the detailed information given in the Tables themselves.Summary. (A.)Schemes.	Table.	Total Approximate Value of Schemes Assisted.	Approximate Exchequer Contribution from Armistice to March 31, 1925 (excluding Loans).Training, &amp;c. Unemployment Insurance Unemployment Grants Committee Ministry of Transport Programmes Resettlement Acceleration of Road Schemes Miscellaneous Land Settlement Womon&apos;s Training, &amp;c.	1 3 3 3 4 5	  million. 103 190* 671 20 51;-H 20* 1	  million. 103 5j &apos;** 12 (including Road Fund) 4 !Total		4551	189* Note. The increased expenditure which will result from proposals now before Parliament is not included.
(B.) Additional Future Exchequer Liabilities under Schemes already Approved.Scheme,	Table.	Grants.	Guarantees.		  million.	  million.Training, &amp;c. Schemes	1	.. 1.	Unemployment ( rants Committee Loan			Schemes	CO	Hi	Ministry of Transport Schemes	3	n	Land Settlement	4	10	Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes	6		531Total   ..		34i	53j		87f	(C.) Further Exchequer Liabilities in respect of Schemes which the Government have offered to assist if undertaken, or if the necessity arises.Scheme.	Table.	Grants..	Guarantees.Unemployment Insurance Unemployment; Grants Committee Loan Schemes .. Ministry of Transport Schemes Trade Facilities.Guaranteed. Schemes	2 3 3 6	  million. Si-Hi	 , million. i3 37$Total   ..		171	60f		.   7i	[11859]
Schemes of Post-War Resettlement, mainly of ex-Service Men.Scheme. (The Appropriate Vote of the Estimates is given in Brackets.)	Approximate Net Expendi-ture from Armistice to March 31, 1924.	Provision in 1924/25 Estimates.	Estimated Total Expenditure to March 81,1925 (Approximate Net Expenditure to end of Month stated is given in Brackets).(1)	&apos;  (2)	(3)	W1. Out-of-work donation.. (His Majesty&apos;s Forces and Merchant Seamen (see No. 4 below as to civilians).)	  40,722,846	 	  40,722,846 (40,722,846 June)2. Grants for resettlement in civil life (Class VII, Vote 3.)	3,791,400	165,000	3.956.400 (3,820,000 June)8. Training of demobilised officers and men of His Majesty&apos;s Forces, also ex-Service nurses and war widows  (a.) Ministry of Labour (Class VII, Vote 3.)	23,208,633	. 1,369,911	24,578,544 (23,635,000 June)(6.) Ministry of Pensions (Class VI, Vote 4.)	1,192,000	68,000	1,260,000 (1,221,000 June)ic.) Board of Education (England and Wales).. (Class IV, Vote 1.)	7,675,775	64,500	7.740,275 (7,705,775 June)(d.) Scottish Education Department (Class IV, Vote 11.)	1,303,310	20,640	1,323,950 (1,312,414 June)(e.) Ministry of  Agriculture and  Fisheries (England and Wales) &quot;    (Class 11, Vote 14.)	1,498,868	4,850	1,503,718 (1,498,794 June)(/.) Board of Agriculture (Scotland) (Class II, Vote 36.)	53,899	150	54,049 (53,914 June)Total for training        ..	34,932,485	1,528,051	36,460,536 (35,426,897 June)Totals (1 to 3 inclusive)	79,446,731	1,693,051	81,139,782 (79,969,743 June)4. Out-of-work donation : civilian men and women ..	21,725,395		21,725,395 (21,725,395 June)Totals (1 to 4 inclusive) ..	101,172,126	1,693,051	102,865,177 (101,695,138 June)Note. (i.) The costs of administration and &quot;allied Services&quot; are not included in this table.  -(ii) The cost of the Overseas settlement free passage scheme for ex-Service men and women and their dependants (now rapidly approaching termination), which up to 31st March, 1924, had amounted to approximately  2,400,000, is not included in this table.
Statement of Income and Expenditure from Armistice to June 28, 1924.Expenditure     Benefit paid........ ....   165,386,000Appropriation for Administration ....    15,052,000 Miscellaneous Refunds, &amp;c.....        .... ....     2,002,000Income.  .     ?Contributions i Employers         ....        ....        .... 60,549,000; Employed          ....        ....        .... 55,077,000Exchequer          ....         ......... 39,732,000Exchequer (for ex-Service Men)      .... 2,923,000182,440,000158,281,000Interest (Net)................ 1,204,000Balance of Old Fund at Armistice (excludingInterest accrued) * Employers ....        ....        .... 5,825,000Employed .........        .... 5,825,000Exchequer       ..... .... .... 3,884,00015,534,000Loans from Treasury (Net)....        ....        .... 7,130,000Miscellaneous Mainly Deposits in respect  of   futureContributions      ....        ....        .... 291,000182,440,000Note.-The old Fund at November 8th, 1920, had reached a total of  22,210,000.[11 859]Unemployment Insurance.(Estimates, Class VII, Vote 3.)The National Insurance Act of 1911 provided Insurance against unemployment in certain selected industries. It was followed by the Act of 1916, which increased the numbers of persons insured, and, in 1920, by an Act of general scope which applied compulsory Insurance against unemployment to 12,000,000 persons. Subsequent amending Acts modified the conditions of receipt of benefit, increased contributions, provided benefit in respect of dependants, and authorised the Treasury to make advances out of the Consolidated Fund up to a limit of  30,000,000.
Totals to July 3, 1924.	No. of Schemes.		No. of Local	Estimated	Grant* allocated. (6)	Grants paid. (7)Financial Years. (1)	Submitted. (2)	Approved. (3)	Authorities whose Schemes were approved. (4)	cost of Schemes approved. (5)		1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1923/24 1924/25	964 2,045 992 1,086 198	640 1,168 688 795 119	219 235 . 244 301 39	  4,666,484 5,567,837 1,646,835 2,259,487 254,999	  1,206,925 1,601,307 459,800   -688,18&quot; 87,669	  26,636 1,816,715 486,593 544,671 80,353 (to May 31, 1924)* For various reasons it is found that the total amount of grant allocated exceeds the total amount which the Committee will be called upon to pay; the latter will not in the four years, 1921/22,1922/23, 1923/24 and 1924/25, exceed  3.650.000.(B.) Unemployment Grants Committee : Grants in respect of Interest or Interest and Sinking Fund Charges. (Estimates, Class VII, Vote 1, and Class II, Vote 35.)_Totals to July 3, 1924._Financial Years. (1)	No. of Schemes.		No. of Local Authorities whose Schemes were approved. (4)	Estimated cost of Schemes.		Amount of loan approved for Grant.* (7)	Submitted. (2)	Approved. (3)		Submitted. (5)	Approved. (6)					 	 	 1920/21	Nil	Nil	Nil	Nil  .	Nil	Nil1921/22	2,540	1,650	520	24,651,083	17,609,747	16,579,1071922/23	2,601	1,773	489	17,839,410	11,868,414	11,059,0801923/24	2,277-	1,648	462	24,698,480	19,404,680	18,416,151*1924/25	380	284	61	5,089,461	2,629,390	2,370.722*Notes.-(1.) Provisional approval has also been given to six schemes estimated to cost  808,456.* (2.) In addition, schemes promoted by Public Utility Companies have been approved to the extent of  1,734,561 for 1923/24 and  111,933 for 1924/25.Estimated Exchequer Liability in respect of Loans Approved.Payments by Exchequer towards interest, &amp;c, charges on Loans.		Estimated Exchequer liability 1924/25 onwards (Capital-ised) (3)	* Approximate annual charges on Exchequer in reBpeet of-															From [June 12, 1924, to July 3, 1924. (1)	Armistice to july&apos;s, 1924. 00		1924/25 (4)	1925/26 (5)	1926/27 and 1927/28 (6)	1928/29 to 1932/33 (7	1933/34 (8)   .	1934/35 to 1937/38 (9)	1938/39 (IP)  2 7,457	  R33.91T	  15,900,000	  1,600,000	  2,000,000	  1,900,000	  1,770,000	  1,120,000	  850,000	.    480,000* Note. The years given are financial years.(C.) Ministry of Transport Schemes. (i.) Road and Bridge Programme, 1919/20.To assist in the provision of employment for demobilised members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces until such time as they could be re-absorbed into industry, the Government after the Armistice inaugurated a special fund for the purpose of making grants on certain conditions to Highway Authorities for road work. The total of such grants has amounted to approximately  9,328,000 for Great Britain, and it is estimated that the works carried out by Local Authorities in order to earn a grant aggregated in cost approximately  20,000,000.(A.) Unemployment Grants Committee : Grants made on the Basis of BO per cent.of the Wages Costs.   (Estimates, Unclassified Services, Vote 1.)
(ii.) Unemployment Works assisted out of the Road Fund.The first &quot;Unemployment Programme &quot; proper was initiated by the Ministry of Transport in the Winter of 1920/21, and the following statement shows the total estimated expenditure by the contributing parties during 1920/21, 1921/22, 1922/23, 1923/24, and a forecast of expenditure during subsequent years, against the three programmes instituted in those years.Payments during Year.	Road Fund.	Exchequer.	Unemployment Grants Committee.	Local Authorities. (Estimated.)	Total.(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	(6)1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1928/24 1924/25 1925&apos;26 1926/27	  395,200 1,305.800 2,042,268 2,884.031 4,267,94.8 1,490,306 736,304	  118,600 387,700 539,232 89,500	  11,400 141,600 22,000 19,842 65,158	  502,400 1,492,600 1,871.700 2.219,760 3,055.476 1,150,587 736,304	  1,027,600 3,327.700 4,475.200 5,213,133 7,388,58* 2,640,893 1,472,608Totals	13,121,857	1,135,032	260,000	11,028,827	25,545.716		1,3 9?	(ion			14,516.889				Mote. Ofthe total Government contribution provided, amounting to  14,516,889- (a.) Grants formally made amount to  12,562,439.(b.) Grants promised but not formally made to  1,083,746.(o.) Leaving a balance which has been partly hypothecated of  870,704.An additional programme was authorised by the Government in October last. This contemplates a Government contribution to a maximum of  8,050,000 towards a total estimated expenditure of  11,750,000, excluding the possible construction of a new road connecting Liverpool and Manchester, the inclusion of which brings the total programme up to approximately  14,000,000.While there are not yet sufficient data upon which to base a forecast of the rate of expenditure on these schemes, the grants promised represent a Government contribution of  7,100,000, and the whole of the balance has been hypothecated to definite schemes.A further additional programme estimated to cost  13,500,000 has been authorised by the present Government, towards which the Road Fund will contribute a maximum of  10,400,000. This programme includes the construction of&apos; the Liverpool-Oldham (formerly Manchester) road.(D.) Miscellaneous.   (Estimates, Unclassified Services, Vote 2.)	Past Expenditure.				Total Expenditure 1921/22 to 1923/24.		Provision for 1924/25.	Schemes.	Exchequer.		Other Sources.			Other Sources.	Exchequer.	Other Sources.	1921/22 and 1922/23.	1923/24.	1921/22 and 1922/28.	1923/24.	Exchequer.			(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	(6)	(7)	(8)	(9)(a.) Land Drainage (J.) Water Supply (c.) Forestry   .. (cl.) Light Railways (e.) Scottish Schemes	  403,110 11,617 300,000 70,000 53,242	  180.376 11,031 100.000 65,744 44,513	&apos;   . 97,340 28,596 67,474 31,208	  101,209 18,000 72,335 47,076	  583,486 22,648 400,000 135,744 97,755	  198,549 46,596 139,809 78,284	  1300,000 30,000 25,000 75,000	  -100,000 20,965 81,500Totals	-				1,239,633	-463,238	430,000	202,465					1,702,901		632,465	Note. The figures given in this Table relate to &quot; Financial Years.&quot; [11859] IJJD ii
Table 4. Land Settlement.In England and Wales the provision under the Land Settlement (Facilities) Act, 1919, of small holdings and other Land Settlement Schemes for the benefit primarily of ex-Service men, are carried out (a) through the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, and (b) through the agency of County Councils and Councils of County Boroughs.Settlement through Local Authorities. These schemes are financed by the Exchequer in three ways : (1) by providing through the Public Works Loan Board the necessary capital; (2) by paying each year up to the 31st March, 1926, the loss on Councils&apos; small holdings account (e.g., due to charging a fair, as opposed to an economic, rent) so far as such loss has been reasonably and necessarily incurred; (3) by writing-off the difference between outstanding liabilities and the then value of the undertakings at the 31st March, 1926.In Scotland land settlement is not conducted through the agency of County Councils.Ministry&apos;s Settlements. Since the Armistice a number of properties have been acquired, the capital expenditure thereon and the difference, if any, between the annual cost of maintaining and administering them and the rents received from small, holders being borne by the Exchequer. No further properties are being acquired, and it is anticipated that for the future cash receipts will suffice to meet cash outgoings.Land Settlement.(A.) England and &quot;Wales.   (Estimates, Class II, Vote 14.)- &apos;	Amounts from Armistice to March 31, 1924.	Amounts from April 1, 1924, to end of June, 1924.	Totals.(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)Advances by Public Works Loan Board Oommis-sioners to County Councils, &amp;c. Borrowed locally by Councils (estimated) Payments to Councils for losses Expenditure on farm settlements by Ministry direct	  13,664,278 900,000 2,250,979 780,163	  236,731 50,000 672,821 (-4,071)	  13,901,009 950.000 2,923,800 776,092Total gross expenditure Less advances repaid by Councils	17,595,420 708,751	955,481 68,889	18,550,901 777,640Net expenditure ..         ..         ..       ...	16,386,669	886,592	17,773,261(B.) Scotland.   (Estimates, Class II, Vote 36.)			;	Amount from Armistice to March 31, 1924.	Approximate Amounts from April 1, 1924, to end of June, 1924.	Total.(i)	(2)	(3)	(4)Net expenditure by Board of Agriculture for Scotland   ..         ..         ..         ...	f 1,559,751	  63,241	  1,622,992*These figures include : Expenditure on (a) Public Works in Congested Districts . and (J) Rural Housing    ..        &apos;.. 54,708 95.353
Approximate Net Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 19JJ4.			Proposed Provision for 1924/25.	Estimated Total Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 1925. (Approximate Net Expenditure to end of Month stated is given in brackets.) (5)Exchequer. (1)	Other Sources. (2)	Total. (3)	Exchequer. (4)	 	 	 	 	 255,219	206,432	461,651	90,000	569,651				(501,769 June)(b.) Juveniles.After the Armistice, Juvenile Unemployment Centres were opened in certain localities to deal with the problem of unemployed juveniles. After a period of closure centres were again established, and the cost, which was originally shared by the Board of Education and Local Authorities, was, from the 1st April, 1923, to the 31st March, 1924, partly met out of Relief of Unemployment Vote by grants up to 75 per cent, in respect of approved schemes, the Local Authority providing the remaining 25 per cent. From the 1st April, 1924, the Exchequer Grant will, as an emergency measure, so long as unemployment amongst juveniles remains at its present scale, be raised to 100 per cent, of the approved out-of-pocket expenses of Local Education Authorities.Approximate Net Expenditure from Armistice to March 31,1924.			Proposed Provision for 1924/25.	Estimated Total Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 1925.Exchequer.	Other Sources.4	Total.	Exchequer.	(1)		(3)	(4)	(5)  125,000t	  22,000	  147,000	  200,000	  - 347,000* In addition, a scheme of Juvenile War Scholarships met from sources other than Government Grants was administered through the Board of Education, and cost approximately  18,380.f Includes certain imprests to Local Education Authorities against expenditure incurred in 1923/24.Table 6.Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes. (Estimates, Unclassified Services, Vote 3.)(a.) Export Credits.Under the Export Credits Scheme, which is intended to facilitate the resumption of the ordinary means whereby traders can obtain facilities from their bankers to enable them to finance their export trade, the Government guarantee drafts drawn against shipments of goods exported from Great Britain to approved countries abroad.Schemes for Training Women and Juveniles.(Estimates, Unclassified Services, Vote 2.)(a.) Women.The following table aggregates: (i) the expenditure incurred wholly by the Ministry of Labour in connection with the Registered Unemployed Women&apos;s Scheme which operated from 1919 to 1921; (ii) the expenditure, met partly from Exchequer Grants and partly from other sources on schemes for training women in Domestic-Service, &amp;c, under the auspices of the Central Committee for Women&apos;s Training.
Originally a system of Cash Advances against Bills of Exchange was adopted, but has been discontinued and superseded - by two systems of &quot;Guarantees,&quot; viz.: (a) general credits which do not involve a separate reference to the Export Credits Department in respect&apos; of - each; specific transaction: (b) credits ir aspect of each specific transaction.Position at June 30, 1924.Type.	Total Sanctions.	Sanctions Cancelled.	A mounts taken up.	Kepayments of Advances, Bills Paid and Guarantees Cancelled.	Amounts in use or Earmarked.(1)	(2)	(3)		(5)	(6)Advances Specific Sanctions General Credits -	  3,164,257 18,767,383 6,132,037	  1,412,107 10,283,259 3,955,271	  1,752,150 8,132,845 717,838	  396,502 5,592,052 627,759	  1,355,648 2,892,072 1,549,007 Maximum Exchequer contingent liability      . . ..  .      ..      26,000,000Amount in use or earmarked .. ... ..        5,796,727Balance available.. .. .. .. .. ..      20,203,273(b.) Guarantees under Trade Facilities Acts, 1921 to 1924.Under these Acts the Treasury is empowered, on the advice of an Advisory Committee, to guarantee the payment of interest and principal, or either interest or principal, of loans raised in connection with capital undertakings, provided the loans are expended in such a way as to relieve unemployment in Great Britain.Position at June 30, 1924.Exchequer contingent liability authorised by Trade Facilities Acts, 1921 to 1924, in respect of capitalTotal amount.in respect of which Treasury have stated their willingness to give guarantees up to.9th November, 1923Additional guarantees in period 10th November, 1923, to 30th June, 1924, which the Treasury have stated their willingness to give....Table 7.Expenditure by Poor Law Authorities on the Relief of the Poor and Purposesconnected therewith.(A.) England and Wales.As from the 1st April, 1922, special returns have been obtained of the expenditure on Poor Law Relief given in their own homes to persons ordinarily engaged in some regular; occupation, but these figures- must necessarily be accepted with caution. Prior to this date no comparable figure is obtainable, but it is estimated that similar expenditure amounted to approximately  500,000 in 1920/21 and to  8,000,000 in 1921/22. 65,000,000 38,205.645 9,499,000
Period. (1)	Total Approximate Expenditure in respect of all classes of Poor (including the Sick, Aged, Widows, &amp;c.) other than Capital Expenditure out of Loans. (2)	Domiciliary Relief in Money or Kind to persons ordin-aiily engaged in some Regular Occupation and their Dependants (included in column 2).				Persons Insured under the Dnem-ployment Insurance Acts and their Dependants. (3)	Persons not so Insured and their Dependants. (4)	Approximate Total. (5)	f	 	 	 Armistice to March 31, 1920	30,567,241	Not	separately ascerta	ined.1920/21 ..	31,924,954		Do.      do.	500,000				(estimated)1921/22 ..	42.272,555		Do.      do.	8,000,000				(estimated)1922/23 (estimated)	42,020,039	9.414.708	949,126	10,363,8341923/24	38,000,000	6,409,265	793,705	7,202,970	(estimated)			1924/25, April (4 weeks)   ..	Not yet ascertained	384,455	57,629	442,084May ,(5 weeks)   ..		453.832	67,532	521,364Total: Armistice to May 31, 192427,030,252(B.)-Scotland.The Poor Law Emergency Provisions (Scotland) Act, 1921, conferred on Parish Councils in Scotland, for the first time, power to grant poor relief to the able-bodied poor. - Particulars are not available regarding the number of unemployed persons in receipt of poor relief who were insured under the Unemployment Insurance Acts.Period.	Total Approximate Expenditure other than Capital Expenditure out of Loans.	*Approximate Expendi-ture on Outdoor Relief to the Destitute Able-bodied Unemployed (included in column 2).	(1)	(2)	(3)	Armistice to May 15, 1920 1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1923/24f May      (2 weeks)   .. June     (5 weeks)   .. July      (4 weeks)   .. August (4 weeks)   .. Sept.     (5 weeks)   .. October (4 weeks)  .. Nov.     (4 weeks)  .. Dec.      (5 weeks)  .. Jan.      (4 weeks)   .. Feb.      (4 weeks)   .. March   (5 weeks)  .. April     (4 weeks)   .. May      (5 weeks)   ..	  2,945,591 2,797,695 3,775,462 4,538,127 1 )*Not yet ascertained.	  500 (estimated) 659,925 1,352,170 46,000       ,,&quot;) 112,000       ,, 92,500 90,000 116,500           o 132,500             81,500         J-;g 93,000 93,100            86,300 80,800 60.000 72,300        j	&apos;Total: Armistice to May 31, 1924		3,169,095	* The figures exclude expenditure on interest and wages of extra staff  43,240 in 1921/22 and  102,000 in 1922/23.t From May 16, 1923. The cost for four weeks in April was  133,000, and for the first two weeks in JVfay  46,000.O

</content>
</cab>
