<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 45-47</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cabinet&quot;ho more war&quot; pmomstbationWSMBLSST/^BlTHM^ SEPT^OSB gist. 1924&apos;.Copy of letter from the Parliamentary Private Secretary to the Chancellor of tho Exchequer ta the Secretary to the Cabinet.Treasury Chambers, (Whitehall, S;.-$. 18th July, 19 84.Dear Sir Maurice Hankey,The enclosed is a Memorandum of a proposal whichI have placed before the Chancellor of the Exchequer   (with a view, if he agreed, to his bringing it beforethe attention of the Cabinet.Mr. Snowden, I think, intended to bring the matter up last week but he was not able to de so and he hasrequested me to ask if it will be possible for you toput it down on the Cabinet Agenda for the next meeting.I am,Yours faithfully,(Signed) J.H. HUDSON.Parliamentary Private Secretary to the Chancellor of the Exchequer.Sir Maurice Hankey, Cabinet Offices,Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.OOMDBHTIAL O.P. 407 (34)(THIS DOCUMENT IS TILS PROPERTY OP HIS- BRITAH&amp;IC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERMSHI)
u (3 national CQUJlCIh FOR HSLS^WEIQS Off WAR (formerly the Natjojofll ^geo.^^ouaqijj.Millbsnk House, 2 Wood Street,Westminster, 3.W.1,MEMORANDUM re NO MORE WAR DSMOHSTRATIOM AT WSMBDffY, en Zjr 1924.    .The.National Council for the Prevention of War (late National&apos;Peace Council) is organising throughout the country the No More War Demonstrations on Saturday and Sunday   Sept, 80th and 2lst.   Several Committees arid Lscal Councils are already formed in the provinces to run the Demonstrations.,  Generally these have secured the co-operation of the Trades Union and Cooperative Movement on the one hand and the league ,, of Nations Union on the other, as well ai a large number of peace and religious bodies.The H.D.p.ff.. proposes to ebtain the Stadium at Wembley for the great Centre! Demonstration on SUNDAY AFTERNOON. Sent. 21st.   The Authorities are prepared to let it only on the assumption that the DeaoHBtration has offioial sanction.   Thay point out that the great Etepire Sunday was permitted oeoauae the former Conservative Government gave to it ita offioial recognition, which the present Government maintained.The No Mare War Demonstration has already become a great national annual event.   The demonstrations are eelebrated in every country.   This year the International Federation of Trades Unions has arranged to secure universal oo-operatien for the dates, Sept, 20th and 2lst.The N.C.P.W. therefore appeals as a non-party organisation to the Government to offer its offioial recognition to the holding cf a great Demonstration for Peaoe at the Stadium on Sunday, September 2lat.   If this recognition is granted it is proposed:(l)   Ts ash the Prime Minister to speak (or if this is impossible a leading Member of the Government),(2) To invite the oo-operation .sf Mr. Baldwin and Mr. Agquith (or some leading substitute drawn from their respective parties).(3)   T(j secure an address from one of the Arohbishops or ether leading Anglican, and also from a .  . leading Non-csnformist.
(4)   To submit as resolution either the following or some other resolution which might commend itself to the Government.   The fallowing lias already secured the assent of the many organ!satlens affiliated to the H:C.P.W. as well as cf the League of Nations&apos; Union: &quot;This mass meeting cf citizens sends fraternal greetings to the similar gatherings now being held throughout Europe and America, joins with them in declaring its hatred of war. and militarism, and pledges itself to co-eperate with them in working for conditions which will guarantee that there shall be no more war by(a) Perfecting international organisation for the removal of the causes sf war, the peaceful settlemont of disputes and the promotion of international co-operation,(b) Securing the whole-hearted and organised co-operation of peoples working through a perfected ana all-inclusive League of Nations.(0) Developing an international sense cfsolidarity which shall make war impossible.:T(5)   To obtain with the oe-operation of the many religious bodies now affiliated large massed choirs and bancs for a musical programme(6)   To utilise amplifiers and apparatus for broadcasting.(7).   To raise  2S000 for the expenses (the Stadium will cest  500 at least) and to ask the Government subsequently far financial supports-2-

</content>
</cab>
