<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 100-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Q10 aS E G R E T.CAB HE T,UNEMPLOYMENT COMMITTEE.RELIEF   OP   UNEMPLOYMENT. PROGRESS OP SCHEMES AUTHORISED BY THE GOVERNMENT,Notes for the rise of Ministers in connection with the forthcoming Debate on Unemployment,(Paper No. CP. 411(24)).The attached Memorandum (CP. 411.A(24)) should be attached to the above-mentioned Paper (See page 28) circulated on the 25th instant2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, July 26th, 1924.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 government cabinet.Secret Copy No.   Q-.GC/-Jf // $ fetyj-        Unemployment Committee.Housing    and    Unemployment. Memorandum by the Minister of Health.1. The carrying out of the Government housing programme and the further development of building work which will be rendered possible by the augmentation of the ranks of the building Industry will make &apos;a very large contribution towards the alleviation of unemployment.There is at present a great shortage of skilled labour in the building trade especially in the bricklayer, plasterer and slater branches.   The result is that schemes already   in hand do not progress so quickly as they should,    while the development of new work is hindered.2, Tho present position of the building Industry inrelation to house building and tho future prospects have at the request of the Governmont been considered by a Committee representative of all sections of the Building Industry and cf the-manufacturers and suppliers of materials.This  committee has emphasised that the essential condition to ensure augmentation of tho resources of tho industry is stability and an ensured demand for a long period. The Government in their Housing Bill are aiming at a programme of approximately 1\ million houses in 15 years.      Such a programme will in the opinion of the Building Industry produce the necessary confidence to enable large proposals of augmentation both by skilled men and materials to be carried out.
0 oThe building Industry proper propose to put in force a large extension of their apprenticeship system, which will result in tho taking in of largely increased numbers of apprentices, in the acceptance of adult apprentices and in the shortening of the apprenticeship period.3. It will be appreciated that the development of housing schemes on a large scale benefits not only the skilled men, but finds work for large additional numbers of the -unskillod.4. Moreover, building gives employment not only tothose engaged on the structures, but also to those engaged in the prodvtotion and manufacture of building materials, and in the manufacture and fitting of equipment for the bxiildings.    A. very large proportion of the trades concerned are home trades, a fact which Increases the importance at this time of building work.    The oarrying out of the Government housing scheme will, therefore, create employment in 8 large number of trades outside the building trade itself.(Initialled.)      J.W.Ministry of Haalth.July 25th, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
