<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 109-110</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.CP. 413 (24).INTER-ALLIED CONFERENCE.REPRESENTATION OP DOMINIONS AND INDIA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.MY colleagues will remember that the question of the representation of the Dominions and India at the Inter-Allied Conference was mentioned at the meeting of the Cabinet on Tuesday, the 22nd July.The Memorandum attached gives the history of the negotiations and summarises the arrangements finally made.J. EL T.Colonial Office, July 24, 1924.Memorandum.The suggestion originally made to the Dominion Governments (in a message from the Prime Minister of the 28th June) was that a preliminary meeting should be held in London of Dominion and Indian representatives to discuss with His . Majesty&apos;s Government the policy to be adopted at the Conference and to make arrangements for representation.In their reply, the Canadian Government, while concurring in this suggestion, asked whether they were right in assuming that the governing principles in this matter would be those regarding treaties negotiated at International Conferences referred to in the Resolution of the Imperial Conference of 1923 on the subject of the Negotiation, Signature and Ratification of Treaties (which alludes to &quot; Inter-national Conferences, where there is a British Empire Delegation, on which, in accordance with the now established practice, the Dominions and India are separately represented &quot;).This message was considered by the Cabinet on the 2nd July, and, as a result, the Prime Minister sent a telegram to the Prime Minister of Canada on the 3rd July explaining that it was difficult to give a definite answer to this enquiry, and that it had been contemplated that the question of representation would be discussed and settled at the preliminary Conference referred to in his message of the 28th June. At the same time he alluded to the difficulties in arranging for the separate representation of all the Dominions and India. Two possible courses were mentioned in the telegram, viz., (a) the application of the panel system as arranged at Paris in 1919; or (b) representation of the Dominions and India by a single representative, but doubt was expressed as to the possibility of adopting either.The Canadian Government in reply strongly affirmed the view that, under the Imperial Conference Resolution, the Dominions and India should be separately represented, and that any instrument negotiated should be signed on behalf of Canada by a Canadian plenipotentiary. They nominated the High Commissioner for Canada in London to attend the preliminary Conference with instructions to present their point of view.In the meantime the Governments of the Commonwealth of Australia (which supported the attitude of Canada), New Zealand and the Irish Free State had also nominated their High Commissioners in London to attend the preliminary Conference.[11896]IThi^Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.
The Government of the Union of South Africa did not desire to nominate a representative, as they had only, just assumed office. They reserved the question of the appointment of a special South African delegate at the main Conference.As a result of the preliminary Conference with the High Commissioners and the Secretary of State for India, which was held on the 11th July, the Prime Minister sent to the Dominion Prime Ministers on the same day a message sum-marising the position and the attitude of the various Governments, and indicating that the following arrangements seemed likely to meet the situation best: (a.) The British representatives to keep in continuous consultation with the High Commissioners or other representatives of the Dominions and India during the sittings of the Conference.(6.) The Dominion Governments to be kept fully informed by telegraph of the proceedings.He also repeated the following assurance which he had- given at the meeting: &quot;Whatever is agreed to now, under the exceptional character of this Conference, will not be regarded or quoted as a precedent, and a statement to that effect will be made by me to the Conference.&quot;These proposals were accepted by the Government of the Commonwealth of Australia (in view of the difficulties of the position and the assurance quoted above) and by the Government of New Zealand, but the Canadian Government adhered to their previous view. They were, however, prepared to agree, if a rule of procedure of the Inter-Allied Conference did not permit the entire British Empire Delegation to be present at its sessions, that representation at any such session should be determined from time to time by the Delegation.The position was then discussed at a further meeting with the High Commis-sioners on the 15th July, and a telegram was sent on the same day to Canada, expressing gratitude for the suggestion of the Canadian Government, which was interpreted as meaning that the panel system (which would enable one Dominion representative to be present at the Conference each dayj offered a way out of the difficulty. This system (after a further exchange of telegrams intended to make its precise scope clear) was accepted by Canada,, with the result that it was arranged that representatives of any of the Dominions so desiring, and of India, should become members of the British Empire Delegation at the Conference on the panel system and also that the representatives so appointed could attend the meetings of the Conference on days when it was not their turn to sit as members of the Delegation.The plan adopted has been accepted by the Governments of the Common-wealth of Australia, New Zealand and the Union of South Africa, as well as by the Government of Canada, and also on behalf of India. The Irish Free State Government have, however, expressed their inability to participate in the Conference on the panel system.When the arrangement was announced in the House of Commons, and at the Inter-Allied Conference itself, it was made clear, in accordance with the Prime Ministers assurance, that the plan was a special one for the present Conference and was not to be regarded or quoted as a precedent.Colonial Office, July 24, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
