<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 270-271</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PROPOSED MARCH OF OFFICERS AND MEN .THROUGH london memorandum &quot;by the&apos;&quot;First Lord of the Admiralty.On the 21st July Viscount Curzon asked In the House of. Commons whether, on the return of the special service squadron from their world cruise, a march of the officers and men through London can take place on the same lines as those which have taken place through the great cities of the Dominions, in order to give the people of London the best possible opportunity of seeing the men and welcoming them on their return.The answer given was that it iS not proposed to adopt the sugges/tion and it was explained that to do so would, interfere with the menls leave and with the refitting of the ships0   At the same time the Parliamentary Secretary intimated that if there were any general expression of opinion in favour of such a march the question would have to be re-considered.   A memorial has now been received signed by  50 members of Parliament from both sides of the Housro urging reconsideration of this proposal.The view of the Admiralty has been that, the considerable expense1 of such a scheme would not be justified In the absence of an occasion of greater national Importance and that to carry it out would involve an undesirable delay In the&apos;arrangements for Setting the men away on the long leave which will be due&apos;to them on return and in the preparation cf the ships for refitting.MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)&apos; SECRET CABINETCP. Ho, 431/24RETURN OP THE SPECIAL SERVICE SQUADRON.
Admiralty, 1. 8. fi4.It is estimated that the expense, based on a march of approximately 2,000 men; would be from  2,500 to  3,000 or for 1,000 men half that amount.    It would be somewhat less if the men were entertained, for instance by the Lord Mayor and ,. Corporation of the City of London, and if the Cabinsi decide that we should adopt this proposal,&apos; I would as a first step endeavour tactfully to ascertain whether an invitation might&apos;be forthcoming from the City.(ltd.)     C.

</content>
</cab>
