<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 301-323</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.RET S Q,442 (24) CABINET 0 /THE TRADE POSITION AND PROSPECTS. Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate, for the information of the Cabinet, a note of the views as to the Trade Outlook, given to me in confidence by the members of the Board cf Trade Advisory Council at the meeting on August 6th,   I am also circulating a note of the meeting of the Advisory Committee to the Department of Overseas Trade, held In July.The reports at these meetings were somewhat less favourable than those given at the preceding onos.   More steel is being produced now than in 1913j nevertheless the industry is in a very depressed condition:   Complaints are made of the high costs which hamper It in the struggle with foreign competitors, but the essential difficulty lies in the fact that its productive capacity, so greatly increased - especially in this country during the war, exceeds demand.The coal trade is also quiet, both in the export end home markets.   Short time working in the American seotion of the cotton trade is expected to continue, and there is anxiety as to the prospeots of the growing American crop.   The Egyptian section, however, ia well employed.   In woollens, French competition Is severe and said to be increasing.Certain branches of engineering are prospering; and a small success for our trade is to be found in the introduction of British-made shoes into the United States,(Intld.)   S.W,BOARD OF TRADE,11th August, 1924,
The Trade Outlook.Index.Subject.  S l*Shipping and Shipbuilding ...................... engineering - (General Trade) .................... 2Engineering...................................... iron and Steel................................... 5Coal ............................................. VTextiles - (Cotton).............................. 8Textiles (Worsteds etc.).......................... 9Textiles (Wool)................................... 10Leather ..................&apos;!....................... 11Boots and Shoes .................................. 12Co-operative Societies........................... 12Banking .......................................... 13New Zealand Trade................................ 14Leading Statistical Data................,....... Annex.
CONFIDENTIAL.gripping and ShJ.pbrilld.ing.Sir Alan Anderson said that shipping freights for July were a fraction below those for July last year.   Laid-up tonnage was, however, 50$ less than at the corresponding date last year.   Probably there was relatively more shipbuilding in the United Kingdom than abroad, but the amount of tonnage commenced abroad had recently increased.The decline in coal exports was a large factor contributing to shipping inactivity.Complaints were being made by shipowners that assistance was given by the Trade Facilities Committee, not only to British, but also to foreign owners, where the ships were to be built in this country.   This practice he looked upon as open to objection, since it probably meant that foreign owners, who would otherwise have ships built in this country without assistance, would not do so unless they were given the benefit of a grant under the Trado Facilities Act. His own Company had three large vessels building without assistance from the Act, but owners of tramp steamers were not building;   and he thought that so long as such assistance was granted, they would be deterred by the idea that the cost of building could come down further.   The President said he would mention the point to the Treasury.Continuing, Sir Alan Anderson said that representations had been made to the President of the United States through the United States Chambers of Commerce, on the subject of the proposed preferential railway rates:   the President had accepted the Chambers of Commerce view that these discriminations would have        a bad effect on international trade.and relations.    It was understood that the demand
CONFIDENTIAL.Shipping and Shipbuilding.for these preferential rates had been withdrawn at the President&apos;3 Instance, but there was a possibility that the proposal might be brought forward again.The League of Nations had called into council   British and foreign ship owners at a meeting held a month since in London, when a number of League proposals on shipping matters had been considered.   Into certain questions   such as Life Saving Appliances Regulations, it had been decided that there was no occasion for the League to enter but various resolutions on other topics were passed.Sir Arthur Balfour said that the Sheffield Steel and engineering tool trade continued in much the same position aalast month: there had, however, been some increase in unemployment   i1and shortening of hours worked. .   j.)Trade with Japan had &quot;shown a heavy fall; that with South&apos;     IrAmerica and India had, however, improved! while trade with China continued quite good.   It was also satisfactory to note that Sheffield was now taking.,out of the United States&apos; hands someIPtrade in flies, twist drills, etc.   Empire trade was keeping up well, except for some falling off in Canada: this was probablyconneoted with the decline in trade in the United States.Business with France was bad, and fears were felt that the contemplated changes in the French Tariff would be to our detriment.)!The situation In regard to Chinese trade marks was becoming increasingly complicated.   Three separate registration offices had now been set up, one in Pekin, one in Canton and one in Manchuria: the fees for registration had also been practically trebled, and other difficulties were being met with, such as  .that no noticeEngineering - General Trade.
CONFIDENTIAL. 970- Ill U  \JEngineerings general Trade.was given of the arrival of British traders&apos; applications. There was no country in the world in which our trade marks were of greater importance to us.The President replied that the situation was being carefully watched by the Foreign Office, but remedial aotion was difficult, since the underlying cause of much of the trouble lay in the lack of authority of the Central Government,With regard to trade conditions in general,Sir Arthur Balfour said there seemed to be a widespread lack of confidence.The President, referring &quot;to the new Japanese luxury Tariff, said that very short notice of its introduction had been given, but as a result of representations made through the Foreign Office a concession had been secured as regards goods en route, and&apos;an endeavour was being made to obtain some exception in favour of goods already contracted for,   though perhaps not much could be hoped for in this direction.Engineering.Colonel Armstrong   said that manufacturers at home were not ordering new plant.   Engineering firms in this country were constantly receiving requests to tender from abroad, but orders did not generally mature, and went to Germany or even to Prance.   Many firms in the industry were living from hand to mouth.With regard to Sir Alan Anderson&apos;s remarks as to the application of the Trade Facilities Act to
CONFIDENTIAL. Engineering,shipbuilding for foreign owners, he expressed the hope that the sugges t ion made rajuld not be treated as extending to Engineering in general, since orders for foreign users were very much needed.The general   outlook In the industry was gloomy.The President ^remarked that steel output was still at a higher level than in 1913.   He suggested that the real source of the trouble lay in the post-war excess of the world&apos;s productive capacity.Colonel Armstrong agreed but said that, so far as the immediate position was concerned, the British industry was suffering from excessive costs of production.Sir Glynn west stated that steel was being produced in this country actually below cost price in order to keep steel works   going!   if they were once allowed to run oold, heavy expense would be incurred in getting them to work again. On his return from abroad, he was disagreeably surprised at the state of the engineering trade and the coal trade.   The General engineering had not Improved at all, he thought, except as the result of the orders for the new cruisers.The position in the heavy iron and 3teel trade might almost be described as disastrous.   It would be worse still but for the fact that deliveries from the Continent could not always be relied on. Depression in the iron and steel industry    reacted on the coal trade.
CONFIDENTIAL.Iron &amp; steel.Mr. Baker said that the heavy steel industry wao at present in a bad way, but he did not feel altogether so pessimistic as the employers&apos; representatives, and had some hope that the present aoute depression was only temporary.   It was to be noticed that a similar drop was being experienced in the United States of Amerioa where the steel Corporations works were employed only up to 45$ of their capacity, as against 90$ in the spring, while the Bethlehem Steel Company was occupied only up to 30$$ yet the oommon stock of these two concerns oontinued to rise.   This would hardly be the case unless some hope of improvement was seen.In this country less iron and steel had been produced in June than in May or June of last year, but more than in June, 1913) and the same was true of the output for the first six months of the year.   In other words, we were now producing and selling more steel than we did in 1913.     It seemed inevitable, however, that small and out-of-date firms should be put out of bueineaB by the large and progressive ones.Although according to the employers&apos; figures, 1,000 persons less had been employed in June than in May, prices had hardened-to the extent of about 2/6 a ton: this gave a 1^ advance in wages to workpeople covered by the sliding scale, the second advanoe of 1^$ whioh had taken place this year.The employees&apos; organisation maintained that output per head was not less now than in 1913,   The basis of pleoe-work rates continued to be that fixed in 1886, and if wages were high, this represented not high wage rates but actual earnings.Sir Glynn West said that, as regards wages oosts, he didnot regard these as being excessively high in the ateel tradeitselfj but as a large element in the cost of coal, ore, etc.,they contributed to the industry&apos;a difficulties.   The realtrouble lay, he thought, in the relatively high wages paid in sheltered trades such as the Railways.M-5-
2 0. confidential. Iron &amp; steel (Oontd.)Mr. Gallaoher remarked that, aa regards the ooal industry, miners&apos; wages in Scotland were not now more than 50$ above the 1913 basis, while the cost of living was some 59$ higher. A large proportion of the cost of ooal was, he thought, attributable to wages, and it seemed that cheaper ooal could, in the raaini only be secured at the expense of the miners.Sir Glynn West observed that there was also the element of transport oosts to be oonsidered.&apos;Mr. Dorman wrote:-&quot;The Iron &amp; Steel Trade oontinues in a depressed state. &quot;At the end of June the number of furnaces in blast had fallen &quot;to 190 out of a total built of 481.     The home demand for &quot;heavy steel is quiet, and there is no improvement to report &quot;in export.&quot;Shipyards are specifying regularly in moderate &quot;quantities, but orders for new ships are soaroe.&quot;The lower prioe of ooal and coke will give some relief &quot;to the manufacturers of Iron &amp; Steel, but at the present &quot;time all markets are lifeless.&quot;Continental competition is becoming more acute; semi-finished material is offered at  6.0.0 per ton, or even less, &quot;o.i,f. British ports, and finished material, such as joists, &quot;seotions, and plates, can be obtained at 30/- to  3 per ton &quot;below the British cost of production.&quot;The most disquieting feature of reoent statistics is &quot;the increase of imports into this oountry, and the decrease &quot;of British exports, together with the large increase in
fii 0 t)CONFIDENTIAL. Iron &amp; steel (Contd.)&quot;exports from Belgium and Franoe.   The figures are as nfollows:-United KingdomtImports Exports Monthly Average.    Monthly Average. Tons. Tons.&quot;1912............... 166,400 400,600&quot;1913............... 185,900 414,100&quot;First six months1924.............. 195,300 337,440&quot; Imports show an inorease of 10.8$ and Exports a deorease&quot;of 17$.Exporta of iron and steel from Belgium and France.Franoe Belgium Monthly Average.    Monthly Average.Tons. Tons.&quot;1912............... 41,500 124,500&quot;1913............... 51,600 129,200&quot;First five months1924.............. 263,300 271,200Increase = 465.8$    Inorease = 113,8$&quot; Generally, In the heavy iron and steel trade, production&quot;is deoreasing, and it seems as if makers must he content&quot;with the leavings of our Continental competitors.&quot;Coal,Mr.. Evan Williams wrote8-&quot;The serious position in the Coal Trade whioh I outlined at the last meeting has heoome more and more accentuated. There is no demand for export either for the present or the immediate future.   German coal is being sent to Franoe and Italy in inoreasing quantities as well as to Scandinavian oountries.   Many collieries are being olosed down completely and muoh time is being lost at those whioh are kept open. There is likely to be muoh unemployment and under-employment in the Industry generally, as the Inland demand has also
CONFIDENTIAL. Goal (Oontd.)fallen off.   The high rates of wages provided &quot;by the reoent Agreement will oertainly mean lower earnings and their insistence upon these high rates is going to be disastrous to the miners as well as to the owners..&quot;Textiles: Cotton.Mtjd Judson said that in the Egyptian section of the ootton trade business oontinued fairly good, and full time was being worked.   The American section had however experienced a very disappointing month.   The United States crop had failed again, in spite of an increase in the aoreage under oottonj the bollweevil had consumed something like a third of it.Employers were meeting this week to consider a proposal to go on working short time till the end of Decembers usually such decisions were taken over short periods at a time only. This meant a black outlook for the operatives, who could only look for half-wages for the next five months, and that after passing through several bad years.   An ample supply of cotton could not be looked for until the Empire was in a position to produce our requirements.Sir Edwin stookton wrotes-&quot;The position in regard to cotton pieoe goods had changed very little during the last month.   The advance in prioe of raw ootton has made it more difficult to seoure orders for future delivery, and the high oosts for the various finishing prooeeses still act as a serious deterrent to securing a substantial revival in demand for the finished article.   While the prices are at such a high level for ootton textiles, one oan hardly expect the Foreign buyer to purohase extensively.     The majority of buyers are somewhat impoverished, and those who can
OOKFIDEHTIAL. Textiles; Ootton (Oontd.)afford to buy are naturally not anxious to run the somewhat dangerous risk at the present abnormally high values.   I am hoping that we may get an improved position when the question of the growing orop in the states oan be more olearly estimated.&quot;Textiles: Worsted, &amp;o.Mr. sutoliffe Smith said that the position-in the textile trade was even worse than last month.   Three thousand more persons were drawing unemployment benefit on the 38th of July than on the same date in May.   It was doubtful whether 50$ of looms were running.   The spinning trade also continued very bad.     Export of yarns to   Germany had praotioally ceased, on account of the diffioulty in getting payment.    Most of the spinners were only working about three days a week.The French were now sending yarns to Leicester, Bradford being put out of competition by three faotors, the exchange position, and the lower wages and longer hours obtaining in France.The export trade to Araerioa in Mohair yarns had also been interrupted, with serious effects on some large firms engaged in this trade,Speaking broadly, Jiily had been one of the worst months known in the trade for a number of years.In the home trade, diffioulty was b^ing met with in selling pieoe goods, on aooount of the more favourable prices offered by the French (some 2/- per yard less).   Sellers found trade conditions in general very difficult, though probably the trade had never covered a wider field or shown more handsome productions than at present,
&amp; c -JTextiles; Worsted,&amp;c.,(Oontd.)The export trade was also unsatisfactory: no Improvement was shown in Chinas the Japanese trade also was not good, as there had been over-buying in that market.   The Italians were now making textile goods to a large extent for their home consumption as well as export.     There had, however, been a revival of demand from India.If, however, an agreement was reaohed at the present oonferenoe on Reparations, there seemed no doubt that much-needed oonfidenoe would be inspired, and the trade would benefit considerably.The ^resident refers,red to the proposed agreement in regard to dyestuffs- between the British Dyestuffs Corporation and the German Interessen Gemeinschaftt there now seemed no chance of this being made.   Mr, Sutcliffe Smith said that the colour Users did not desire to see concluded an agreement of the type which had been put forward.Textiles: Wool.Mr. Andrews said that he oould confirm Mr. sutoliffe smith&apos;a remarks generally; the situation in the raw material end of the trade, which was only employed up to some 50$ of its capacity, was as bad as that of manufacturers and spinners.   A shortage of wool was beginning to be felt in Merinos, though not yet in the commoner grades.   In the meantime, the French, assisted by lower wages, longer hours of work and depredated currency, were buying up   raw material in this country whioh we ought to retain, and sending it baok in the form of manufactured goods to London.     Their competition had praotioally doubled during the last six months.Bradford appreciated the efforts being made by the Australian Government to remedy the exohange difficulties whioh had reoently been experienced, hut felt some doubt whether the
9Q9CONFIDENTIAL. 6 O ITextiles: Wool (Contd.)benefit oould be felt by September next, when the new buying season would begin.Reverting to the subject of French competition, Mr. Beaumont Pease suggested that this was probably due rather to the differenoe in wages and hours than to the exchange, sinoe this had somewhat appreciated of late,Mr. Andrews said that Frenoh wages were only some 60$ to 65$ of ours.   As to hours, the Frenoh employers oould, he thought, obtain permission to work overtime whenever desired, and the Washington Convention was not being observed.The President observed that the Frenoh Minister of Labour had said at Geneva that they were oarrying out the Convention striotly.   Possibly the overtime whioh was being worked was within the limits permitted by the Convention. Mr. sutcliffe Smith.said that he thought precise information oould be obtained of the supposed infringements of the Convention.Leather. Sir Percy Densham wrote:-&quot;With regard to the Heavy Leather trade I have not muoh change to report.   The Heavy Leather Tanners during the past month have been putting a certain quantity of leather into stock owing to laok of demand.   This however is usual at this time of the year, and everything points to absorption of this extra stock  .so soon as the holidays are over.   We are very puzzled to find that there is a general advanoe in the price of our raw material, hides, all over the world, whereas at the same time we are reoeiving reports from various countries that the leather trade Is bad.   From this it would appear that the supply of our raw material is somewhat short and should oonsumptive demand improve there is likely to be a considerable
9 q 0CONFIDENTIAL. - . fo 0 0Leather (Oontd.) advance in prioe.    Production, I understand is continuing at about the same rate as for the last 5 months.&quot;Boots &amp; Shoes.Mr, Poulton said that, while output in the boot and shoe trade was not up to that of 1913, business was better than last year, especially in light shoes for ladies&apos; wear.   In this department they had been able to take away some trade from the Continent, and in Norwioh there was an actual shortage of labour in this branch.One large British firm had opened retail shops in the United States, with good prospects of sucoess.In Germany the trade was reported to be very bad, owing to lack of capital and oredit.A faotor which contributed to keep up the prioe of leather was the ease with whioh bubble firms oould set up in the manufacturing side of the boot trade; many such concerns had failed and paid only very small dividends to their creditors! leather sellers required a large margin of profit to meet this risk.     It was to be hoped that the Committee of Enquiry on the Bankruptcy Law now sitting could devise means to tighten up the law against people who failed after entering business without any reasonable prospect of meeting their liabilities.Co-operative SooleM.es (Scotland). Mr, Gallaoher said that in the last half-year the Scottish Co-operative Wholesale Society^ grocery business showed an increase of 2j$ over the corresponding period of 1923, while the drapery department showed an Increase of 4.9$ and the boot and shoe department of 3.9$; the furnish-ing business had decreased by 1.9$.   The increase as a whole
Co-operative. Societies (Scotland) (Oontd.)amounted to 2.7$ in money value, and as prices had fallen, this probably indicated an increase in the volume of trade.Industry in Scotland was not favourably situated, however, as regards any of its principal branohes, ooal, iron and steel, and shipbuilding.   There appeared to be a good deal of speculation at the present time in essential food supplies, and he suggested it would be well if the Trade Enquiry Committee on some other body could go into this question of speculation and the margins of profit in producers1, j wholesales&apos; and retailers1 price.In reply to a question by Colonel Armstrong as to how he would explain the paradox of an apparent increase in general buying power in Scotland coinciding with a falling off in trade, Mr. Gallacher said that up to 10 months ago the coal trade in Scotland had been exceptionally good, but a considerable decline had taken place latterly.   Bad trade, however, took some time to reast on wholesale business such as the Society1s.   If present tendencies continued, they would probably experience a falling off in business within the next six months.The President observed that it was so far satisfactory that, in spite of unfavourable trade reports, there appeared to be no indication of special suffering among the greaj, mass of the people.   Unemployment, though bad, remained considerably better than at the corresponding time last year.finanoial situation was the stringency existing in the money market, and the increase in discount rates.   The market discountBankin,Mr. BeaumontPease said that the chief feature of therate, which stood six weeks ago at 2/L5/l6, bad now risen to 3f.
CONFIDENTIAL. Banking.The Treasury Bill rate last Friday ( 3.13,5) was the highest-, since January 1922.   The Clearing Banks&apos; rate for weekly money had risen from 2-1- to 2f-.   The market had been driven to the Bank, and the Bank Rate was now effective.   In consequence of this, and of the improvement in the United States exchange, the prospect of an increase in the Bank Rate had been postponed^ this should be welcome news to borrowers.There was a greater proportion of over-drafts to deposits held by banks, and comparative failure had attended a number of reoent issues of capital.The foreign exchange market was awaiting the results of the Reparation Conference, during the last few days optimism as to its outcome had resulted in an appreciation of the Frenoh and Belgian exchanges.Mr. Tennant noted the improvement in sterling on New York -..as a satisfactory feature,&quot; New Zealand Trade. Sir James Allen said that trade in New Zealand continued good, and a reduction of taxation was in prospect.   It might beoome possible to place larger orders in this country, espeoially under the Trade Facilities Aot.   One large contract had already been plaoed, and it was hoped also to utilise the facilities provided by the Act for speeding up a number of works.   The material required would largely consist of eleotrioal plant, but it might be possible to accelerate railway development also.
901k O confidential. Annex.Some leading statistical data indicating the trend of the Economic Situation in Great Britain. (Information received up to 2nd August, 1924).fcment!jployed on live Eater (including mons on short time Ifeiving benefit)...fction:output during3k ended..........pon, outputIng month........., output during fiith...............is: Wholesale:&quot; Is&quot; Index NumberBslOO) food .....Taterials. ptal.....Latest.21 July 1,041,80019E.3 laid up inffed Kingdom Ports:-British............Hd reign............1[lng Freights :-jjper of Shippingjf&amp;ex Number........120*100).31 31 31Tons July*4,903,600June     607,800June     651,500July 159.4 July 172.2 July    167.5Net tons July   447,622A month earlier.1,013,782Tons 5,173,400650,900809,700158.4 168.3 164.net tons lApl 391,337A year earlier.At corres-ponding date in 1913.July     22,451   lApl 19,028June     29.09Market:-hk Ratefrket rate 3. months&apos;lank Bills.......,discount (3 months&apos; Breasury Bills)...Jige Rates York on London-tbles............Aug. 4$ Aug. 3f1 11 Aug. 3.13s.5.41d  3.6s.5.43d30.104$1 Aug.   4.4104.3231,221,554)Tons 4,601,000692,900767,700157.9 154.3 155.6Net tons 667,527 41,57528.68/ 435/l6   3,4s.4,95d4.570No compara&apos; hie data.Tons t24,970,000**   855,000**   638,600)Average )for year )l913sl00tt 23.044.870* Provisional.t Estimate for the whole month July, 1913./ Changed from 9* July 5th, 1923. ** Monthly average for 1913. tt Approximate estimate for the year 1913,
FLUCTUATIONS DURING THE LAST TWELVE MONTHS
flonfidential.Statements regarding the Export Trade Position made at the Advisory Committee to the Department of OverseasTrade at the meeting held on the lSch  July, 1924.MR. GOODENOUGH, who was unable to attend, sent the following statement,&quot;Overseas business, as reflected in the transaction handled by the Banks, has recently shown some diminution, but this is mainly due to seasonal influences.    July and August are UBually the months during whioh fewest shipping credits are opened, and this year has been no exception to the general rule.    While, however, the number of credits opened has decreased, there has been little shrinkage in the individual amountB represented.     It is of some interest to note that the demand for finance for the shipment to this oountry of certain raw materials is well maintained, and were it not for the uncertainty whioh is undoubtedly affecting the confidence of traders throughout the country, the prospects of a steadily increasing volume of trade would not be diBoouraging.&quot;The position on the Continent is still retarding progress, but there are signs of improvement in some directions.. Applications from certain countries for credit are increasing, and this Beems to suggest that, as currency conditions abroad beoome more reliable, foreign importers are more willing to acquire stooks whioh involve sterling commitments. ,&quot;The. importance of a satisfactory solution of international difficulties can hardly be exaggerated, but even the settlement of the European problem will only be a commencement and not an ond In Itself.     The disparity of wages and profits in various industries is undoubtedly among the factors which are hindering efficient organisation and preventing economical production upon the most advantageous lines.&quot; The American exchange, relieved from the Immediate pressure of certain influences, has improved, but there is little doubt that it is still below the figure justified by the intrinsic value of sterling.     This continued disparity is evidence that confidence has not been fully restored.While/
-2-While the external value of our currency is below its internal value, any increase in oux export trade is only secured at the expense of accepting less real value for the goods shipped.   It is very desirable under existing conditions that oar financial policy should be such as will secure stability of prioe levels as far as possible, avoiding inflation or abnormal deflation.&quot;IRON AMD STBi&amp;, SHIPBUILDING, /METALS,SIR ARTHUR balfour said that, as regards the steel and engineering&quot;Tools trades, which were a very good guide to the situation, there had been a very considerable falling off in the last six weeks.   The Japanese market in particular, and the Colonial and South American markets as well, had fallen off,    A great number of smaller firms who had had a hard struggle during the last few years had come to the end of their tether, and unless there was a sharp improvement within the next few months, the firms he spoke of were going to be in great trouble.    The position was much less hopeful now than when ho had spoken in April and May, and there had been a sudden Bet back in general confidence,MR. HICHENS confirmed what Sir Arthur Balfour had ta say as regards the &quot;steel trade, which was in a very depressed condition.   It was impossible for British firms to get down to foreign quotations, and on top of this there was an insistent demand for increased wages in this country.   It was not a matter of economies of a few shillings; something drastic must be done if the industry was to be saved.As regards shipbuilding, the yards were probably better employed now than for some time paBt; but at miserable prices, which could not possibly pay.   There was increased foreign competition, so that the outlook was not good.   He agreed with Sir Arthur Balfour that the payment of taxes in April and May had been a very heavy strain on the industry, and added that the payment of heavy rates, which add about  2 to  3 to the price of steel, was an even greater burden.MR. GRAY BUCHANAN said that lower prices for coal have enabled pig-iren makers to deal with considerable business in pig-iron with both the East Coast and West Coast of America.Stocks in consuming countries, all over the world remain low, and with jute, shellac, etc., fetching full prices for Indian producers, and wool fetching prices that even frighten the Australian woel-grower, the natural sequence should be indents for British manufacturers in exchange.   As regards India, dealers continue to place considerable contracts for steel hoops, copper sheets and yellow metal sheets, etc.   In spite of the rapid advance in the price of galvanised sheets, fresh business continues to come to hand, and makers&apos; order-books have now business as far ahead as December,   Australia has placed considerable orders for pig-iron which have greatly strengthened the Cleveland Makers1 position, some of whom are now asking a premium for shipping iron as compared with home delivery.    There are also important enquiries in the market for structural steel which will in the end come to this country.Our/
2 O J&quot;The/Oor generosity in the matter of loans to Australia during recent months should lead to considerable business for our manufacturers.      RusBia has placed some considerable orders here for brick tea and also for spelter.ELECTRICAL INDUSTRY.MH^PYBUS .said that in the electrical industry there was a&quot;Tair amount of export work   The smaller firms were suffering a good deal, but the firms who had a large organisation and adequate representation abroad were able to do a fair trade.     The level of prices abroad was lowish and American firm3 had recently shown signs of cutting in.   Generally speaking, firma were getting back in foreign trade what they had lost during the last three or four years.   The colonial trade was more difficult,Japan, he observed, was still quite a good market,and the attitude of America towards Japan had not affected orders for American goods,   Generally speaking, there was no reason for depression,.    It was to be remarked that German firms were finding money to re-construct their selling organisations abroad, and competition was being experienced from them.   The trouble in Brazil had been a disappointment, and one could only hop9 that it would uettle down.   The electrical industry was in a favourable position, partly because all Governments were at present turning their mind3 to electric power as a solution of their economic problems,CHEMICAL INDUSTRY.SIR WILLIAM BEARCE said that the chemical export induetry&quot;was&quot;in a&quot;fairly eatiofactory condition.   The future of Germany was what interested the industry most. They were a little anxious as to what might happen if Germany got a loan and if the agreement with the German I.G. was signed0   The general impression was that British firms wero likely to meet with more competition in the future than they had in the past,COTTON INDUSTRYaMRj H.W. LEE said that the coarse section of the cotton industry,&quot;which was the.greatest part of it, was still vary slack,    Many mills were working half time now and wore expected to continue at this rate until September, and after that it was impossible to say what the position would be0    There might be an improvement if there was a really good American cotton crop and prices dropped.   But it was not only price that was handicapping bn3inoB3, The real reason was that a great part of this trade was in goods sold to people living on the proceeds of agriculture and the condition of the agriculturist was such that at the present time he was getting about 50^ increase for  .&apos;his produce while he was called upon to pay about 100% more than in pre-war days for what we S9ll him.
The consequence was that he had to curtail his purchases. It would probably he a considerable time before the course section got back to the amount whicjj it used to turn over. In the fine cotton trad a, in which Egyptian cotton was mostly used, the position was more cheerful.   The mills were running practically full time and reasonable profits were being made.    There was a slight falling off at the moment, because the prices of the present crop were 3d., 4d., or 4id, more than prices in futures.     There had been a serious falling off in June from Germany owing to the fall in credits   On the whole, prospects in the fine cotton trade were not bad, but th9 position of the heavy section of the trade was one of great difficulty,tip,, - BOOTHMAM confirmed what Mr0 ILW0 Lee had to say, He salaihTSFTihe&apos; American trade was In a deplorable condition and there was not much Lope of its emerging until the prospects of the new American crop were definitely known.WOOL AM) WORSTED INDUSTRY.SIR ALGERNON FIRTH said that the position of the wool and worsted industry was much the same.   Employment was very bad and he thought that a number of firms were going to find it hard to make ends meete    Firms making speciality goods were doing fairly well.    He observed that some foreign countries, and in particular Japan, levy an extra duty if there is a thread of silk in the worsted. This was grossly unfair to British exporters.   The silk threads added nothing to the value of the material and were there purely for decorative purposes.SOUTH WALES COAL.COLONEL WATTS-MORGAN had no improvement to report. Exports of South Wales coals were down again to a certain extent in May and June as against March and April.THE FAR BAST AND INDIA,MR.., DCPWBIIi   said that he had nothing favourable to report on China.   The exports of ,hic firm, chiefly in piece goods, were 25 per cent, worse than this time last year, and the same was true of metals.   Most of their business in metals was in continental goods handled by their Antwerp office, due to lower prices.     The state of disorder in China shopped the movement of goods and storage was being paid in some cases for periods as long as two years.SIR CHARLES MCLBQD observed that the monsoon had BtartecT&quot;very well and then eased off.   There had then been a drought all over India, but the mornoon had come on now ij i-wceased strength and there was ample rain in all districts, with every prospect of continuance.   This Bhould have a good effect on the crops aid consequently on the balance of trade and power to purchase goods in this country.   He referred to the forthcoming rupee&apos;loan, the amount of which has been reduced from SO to 15 crores.This/
This reduction had bean rendered possible by the large amount of money which the Post Office had received from the sale of savings certificates of small denominations. This was an encouraging sign.    Conditions generally were at present fair.    Credits for imports of raw materials from India had very greatly increased of late.     Stocks had been reduced to a very small margin, making room for new importa-tions.     It was encouraging that the Government had taken up the Sukkur Barrage scheme for supplying water to millions of acree of land, which would&quot;mean the placing of large orders.    fie understood that American firms were getting orders for the excavating plant, and British manufacturers most of the boiler work orders in connection with this scheme.

</content>
</cab>
