<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/168/0 images: 498-500</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T^ja Pooument ,ia. the Property of H1b Britannio Majesty&apos;s Government).0 A B I HE T.463(241&apos;INTERNATIONAL OPIUM CONFERENCE, NOVEMBER,  1924.Further Memorandum by the Home Secretary.It is urgently necessary for the Government to take a decision on the question of the policy to he followed by the British Delegation at the Conference on Opium Smoking in the Far East whioh opens on Monday, the 3rd November.     The Cabinet discussed the question before the holidays, 6th August, but decided to postpone a decision till after the meeting of the Assembly of the League of Nations in September.The question of opium smoking in the Far East was not touched upon in the Assembly as it was ^considered better not to anticipate the proceedings at the Conference in November, and the position remains much the same as at the time of its previous consideration by the Cabinet.In the interval, the report of the two Committees appointed by the Governments of Malay and Hong Kong, to whioh reference is-made in the Memoranda circulated by myBelf and the Colonial Secretary, (CP.414 and 425) have been published, though - so far as I am aware - copies have not yet reached this country and public attention has not yet been drawn to the oonclusions submitted by the two Committees.     A further Memorandum has also been circulated by the Colonial Secretary and a Memorandum, by the Secretary&apos;of State for India (CP. 459 &amp; 450).All the considerations bearing on the question of the policy to be adopted by the British Government are now fully before the Cabinet, and I hope it&apos; will be possible for them to take a decision without delay.     Unless this is done, the
British Delegation to the Conference will not be able to take any effective part in the proceedings of the Conference.I have again carefully reviewed the whole question and 1 find no reason for modifying the proposals which I submitted to the Cabinet in my previous Memorandum.     The Colonial Secretary admits in his Memorandum (paragraph 7) that the &quot;continuance of the present policy cannot lead to the total suppression of the smoking habit&quot;.     The British Government is pledged to that suppression by the Convention of 1912, and the Conference in November is being called (very largely at the instance of the British Government) to consider what measures can be taken by the various Powers concerned to carry out the obligation in the Convention more effectively.     If the policy indicated in the Colonial Secretary&apos;s Memorandum is adopted, the British will have nothing at all (apart from the abolition of the private retail shop) to propose for Hong Kong, and for Malaya only some very tentative measures which may or may not pave the way later for a system of registration and rationing.     Suppression is not even remotely in sight.     The British Government will in effeot be saying (see paragraph 43 of CP.425) that they cannot carry out their obligation until a stable Government has been established in China and opium production there has been stopped.I have not overlooked or minimized the difficulties of carrying out a policy of prohibition or the seriousness of its effects on the revenues of some of the Colonies.The question of the replacement of the opium revenues has got (as the Colonial Secretary agrees) to be faced at some time, and on this point we differ only in this, that under my proposal the replacement would have to be effected within a definite period.     I have not suggested in my Memorandum what the length of that period should be.     Ten years was in my mind, but I should see no objection to a longer period if there were good
grounds for thinking it necessary.The only other observation I wish to make is that the opinion of the Governors of the Colonies (paragraph 43 of the Colonial Secretary&apos;s Memorandum) that &quot;far more evil than good would result from trying to prohibit and penalise the practice amongst Chinese&quot; seems to me to be quite inconsistent both with the objects of the Convention and with the experience obtained in China itself where in at least one province (Shansi) at the present time the practice of opium smoking has been successfully suppressed with the best results by an honest and capableGovernor, notwithstanding that it is quite as unfavourably placed as Hong Kong, or even more so, being surrounded by opium using provinces.     It is an opinion whioh I hope my colleagues are not prepared to accept.A.H.11th October, 1924.9V.61-3

</content>
</cab>
