<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/71/0 images: 22-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1954SECRET Copy. No.    6 4C. (54) 3064th October, 1954CABINETCONSTITUTIONAL DEVELOPMENTS IN THE GOLD COASTMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesNo action is required on this paper but I would like to inform my colleagues of the likely timing of future developments.2. The proposals for constitutional change in the Gold Coast mentioned inC. (54) 62 of 18th February were given effect from the 18th June, by the gold coast (Constitution) Order in Council, 1954. Dr. Nkrumah&apos;s party won theelection with a comfortable majority.3. As my predecessor told the House of Commons the introduction of thenew Constitution was the last step before the attainment of full self-government within the Commonwealth (a Ministerial Committee will soon report to the Cabineton the question, which will arise when the Gold Coast approaches independence,of adding to the membership of the Commonwealth), and we should be well advised to prepare ourselves for future constitutional reform in advance of thedevelopment of political pressure.4. So far the Gold Coast Ministers, assisted by the Governor, have done wellin many fields. I have every hope that they will do as well in the future; there haverecently been some signs that they may have to face the kind of inter-regional and inter--tribal difficulties which have bedevilled Nigerian politics during recent years.They certainly need more experience and if they are to attain independence itwill be necessary for them to continue to demonstrate their ability to govern andto preserve the basic freedoms of democracy. They will also continue to need asubstantial cadre of European officers to keep the machinery of Government atthat level of efficiency which will guarantee the effective implementation of theVolta River Project and other plans for development.5. The timing of the grant of independence must therefore depend on anumber of factors. An essential pre-requisite is the consent of the general assembly of the United Nations to the termination of the Trusteeship Agreement.(This question was discussed in C. (54) 169.) This cannot be obtained until the1956 meeting, so that the earliest possible date for the grant of independence tothe Gold Coast would be about December 1956.6. The Governor has suggested that December 1956 should be taken as thedate to aim at, for if we delay unnecessarily we may forfeit the great goodwill which now exists there and drive the Gold Coast out of the Commonwealth. He hasbeen informed that, while I cannot enter into any commitment now, I shall beready to consider the matter further at the end of 1955, and that I consider it wisethat the necessary preparations for independence which are now in their initial stages should be based on the assumption that they might have to be implementedby the end of 1956 or very shortly thereafter.A. L.-B.Colonial Office, S.W.1,1st October, 1954.46913

</content>
</cab>
