<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/71/0 images: 170-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(54) 350 COPY NO. \ ^20th November, 1954CABINETREVIEW OF WAR PENSIONS AND NATIONAL insurance pensions AND benefits memorandum by the Minister of Pensionsand National insurance outlined my proposals for the review of pensions and benefits on 10th and 11th November when the time-table for the review was approved(G.C. (54) 74th Conclusions, Minute 8 and 75th Conclusions, Minute 2).I now submit my full proposals.general.        The following details of the services covered by the review will serve to give my colleagues some idea of the ground to be covered and thenumbers affected.(a) Yfar PensionsWar Pensions are being paid to about 650,000 disabled men and170,000 widows.    Over 95 per cent of the disabled men are in employment and those who cannot work get extra allowances,&apos;(b) Industrial Injury BenefitsThese include a special rate of benefit (well above the normalsickness benefit rate) payable for not more than six months to men andwomen unable to work through industrial injury or disease and disablementpensions or gratuities payable to the small proportion of men and women who do not completely recover from their injuries.    Many pensionersare at work and those who are not can get additional allowances.    At anyone time payments are made to something like 180,000 men and womenunder this scheme.(c) National Insurance Benefits and PensionsThese constitute the main subject of the review.    The chiefbenefits are retirement pensions, of which there are about 4  millions,and sickness and unemployment benefit which are being paid to upwards of1 million people.    The scheme also includes benefits for widows, formaternity, etc. , all of which have to be reconsidered.The total number of pensioners and other claimants benefiting under these schemes is of the order of 7 millions.     The annual expenditure involved is over  600 millions.
30        National Assistance must also be considered.    This is administered by the National Assistance Board and the initiative forproposing increases in the scales of assistance lies with them.    They areat present paying out about  100 millions a. year, of which about 43 millions goes to pensioners.    The existing rates have for some timeprovided a higher standard than ever before but their values have slippedback slightly since they were raised in 1952 and I am expecting theNational Assistance Board to put forward further proposals very shortly.Assistance is being paid to over if million people, of whom 1^ millionsare getting it in supplementation of retirement pensions or national insurance benefits.    Yfith dependants, the National Assistance Board islooking after the needs of about 2f million people.Statutory basis of Review of National Insurance Pensions4.        The review of rates of pensions and benefits payable under theNational Insurance Act is governed by a procedure laid down by that Actand is dependent on a Report by the Government Actuary on the first five years&apos; working of the scheme which has just been received,    I am now in a position to ask formal approval for the full proposals I have worked out with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.Proposed new rates of Pensions and Benefits5. The chief considerations I have had in mind in arriving at thenew rates of pensions and benefits have been the desirability of restoring the value which pensions and benefits had in 1946 when they were originally fixed;  of providing some margin so that if prices move up again the new rates will not immediately start falling behind;  the relation-ship between national assistance scales and national insurance benefits,and the importance of re-asserting our belief in national insurance as themain provision for old age and the main defence agaiiast poverty;  and finally the desire that people for whom these benefits and pensions are intended should have some small share in our growing prosperity.6.        The main national insurance benefit and pension rates of 40s.single and 65s. for a married couple mentioned to the Cabinet on10th November represent an increase of rather more than 50 per cent over the rates of 26s. and 42s. fised in 1946.    The increase of 7s, 6d.in the single rate is considerably more than seems generally to beexpected.70        The new basic rate of 67s. 6d. for war pensions for the100 per cent disabled is also 50 per cent over the 1946 rates.    I proposeto couple this with substantial increases in the allowances given to war pensioners who are incapable of work or require special care.    I think this double approach, of a substantial increase in the basic rate togetherwith generous increases in the special allowances paid to the more seriously disabled will be generally acceptable.    The British Legionhave been campaigning for a basic rate of  4 10s. , but I do not think we need take this seriously.8.        Industrial injury benefits will follow broadly the lines of thewar pensions scheme, with a new&apos; basic rate of 67s. 6d. for 100 per centdisablement, but some of the allowances payable in more serious cases
have always been slightly lower than the corresponding allowances forwar pensioners ai:d I propose to continue these differences as an indication of the priority we have always promised war pensioners.9.        Details of all my more important proposals for increased ratesof benefit are in Appendix A.Increments10.       There is one matter on which the Chancellor has reserved hisposition.     The scheme for retirement pensions enables a man to earn ahigher pension by continuing at work after 65.    At present the man canearn an extra 3s. for each year of work.    I would like to increase this to4s. so that the pension for the man who retires at 70 would become 60s.if single (or 100s. if married).    These figures are very attractive in themselves.    Moreover, it has hitherto always been claimed that broadly speaking the increments earned compensate a man for the pension heforegoes if he delays retirement and we shall not be able to maintain thisuxiless we put the increments up as I suggest.    The Chancellor on theother hand points to the considerable addition to the future cost of pensions which my proposal would involve, amounting to about  20 millions intwenty-five years&apos; time, and to the fact that it is almost certain that thePhillips Committee will recommend against increasing increments whenpensions are raised.    He would therefore prefer to leave the point over for further discussion and not include it in the present Bill.    I may wishto develop my arguments orally.New Rates for National Insurance Contributions11.       War pensions are payable directly out of the Exchequer.   national insurance benefits and industrial injury benefits are payable out of theNational Insurance Funds to which workers and employers and the Exchequerall contribute.    Any increase in these benefits and pensions should there-fore be matched by increased contributions.    On a strict actuarial basisan increase of benefit of the order I have suggested would of itself require an increase of soxne lOd. a side in the contribution payable by the workerand his employer with a smaller increase in the Exchequer contribution.The outstanding feature of the Government Actuary&apos;s Report is that, fora number of reasons, including experience in relation to sickness andmortality since the scheme started, the contributions now being paid bythe insured person and his employer exceed for a new entrant at age 16those which are required on a strict actuarial basis.    We are, however,approaching the stage when the number of retirement pensioners will risevery sharply and when the cost of benefits and pensions will begin to exceed the income the Fund derives from contributions and interest oninvestments.    In the next 15 years, the expenditure will grow by 50 per cent,and the income will not rise at all.    The deficiency falls on the taxpayer,and even on present rates of benefit this would mean an increased load on the Exchequer of over  250 millions a year.    It was for advice on this very serious emerging problem that the Phillips Committee was appointed.It is understood that the Committee will endorse the view that in principleit is right to require the worker and his employer to make a specialcontribution towards the emerging cost of pensions and on this ground topay appreciably more than the strict actuarial contribution:  there was some analogous provision in the 1925 and 1946 Acts.    The proposals I ammaking will, so far as I can judge, fall within what the Committee is expectedto recommend.
12.       In agreement with the Chancellor of the Exchequer I have come tothe conclusion that the contribution now being paid by the employer and the workman should be increased by lid. a side for national insurance benefits,and by a further Id. a side for industrial injury benefits, making anincrease of ls0 in alL    We must expect this proposal to be criticised inview of the Government Actuary&apos;s disclosure about the existing contributionsbut the increase in contributions is proportionately rather less than theincrease in benefits and the total contribution payable in future will represent a much smaller proportion of the average earnings than did the contribution charged when the scheme was launched in 1940.    Unless wedo increase the contribution by an amount of this order, we shall befailing in our duty of making proper provision for the future commitments of the Fund and throwing over the main recommendation of the PhillipsCommittee, besides greatly increasing the burden on the tax-payer nextyear and subsequently.    The self-employed and the non-employed will pay about the same additional contributions for the benefits to which theyare entitled013.       Details of the more important changes in rates of contributionare in Appendix BcFinance14.       The broad effect of these proposals is to increase the amountat present being paid in pensions and benefits to the various peoplecovered by the proposals by about  135 millions a year.    This represents an increase of over two-thirds over the amount paid to them in 1948/49,the first year&apos;s working of the full scheme.    Most of this extra expensewill be covered in the first year by the extra contributions from insuredpersons and their employers.    The additional cost to the Exchequer ofthe whole operation will be about  25 millions in 1955/56.    But theinsurance scheme alone - apart from war pensions and industrial injurybenefits - is expected to cost the Exchequer in supplement to contributions and deficiency grant some  750- 800 millions in the next five years,compared with this year&apos;s cost of  70 millions.    Details of the financialeffects of the proposals are in Appendix C0Matters not included in the Review15.       In conclusion I must draw my colleagues attention to the fact thatthere are certain payments which I do not intend to increase, either because there is, in my judgment, no demand for an increase, or because they areof a kind which are no longer regarded as appropriate to the general schemeof social security established in 1946.    These include non-contributory pensions payable on a means test for which a time limit was fixed by theoriginal Act, family allowances, the fixed 10s. pensions paid to certainwidows with vested rights under the earlier schemes who do not qualifyunder the present scheme, certain allowances payable under the Royal&quot;Warrant, of which the most important are those for wives and childrenpayable with basic war pensions where the man is in employment, the20s. pension for able bodied war widows and parents&apos; dependency orneeds pensions.Conclusion16.       I ask my colleagues to approve the proposals set out in thismemorandum.    The time-table for the legislation and other steps needed to bring the new rates into force has already been approved.O.P.Ministry of Pensions and NationalInsuremceg WoC0Zo19th November 1954. A.
The following increases are proposed in the principal benefit and pension rate s 2-National InsurancePresent rate    Proposed rateRetirement pension     )Married 54s. 65s.yj , . ,        ., \   Single 32s. 6d. 40s.Unemployment oenefrt )Sickness benefit )Widows allowance (13 weeks) 42s. 6d. 55s,Widows pension            ) n^.      .?                       \ 32s. 6d. 40s.Maternity allowance     ;Guardians allowance 15s. 10s.Allowance for adult dependants 21s. 6d, 25s.Allowance for dependent children - eldest 10s. 6d. 11s. 6d.others 2s. 6d. 3s. 6d.Maternity grant                                         .  9  10Home confinement grant  3  4Industrial InjuriesInjury benefit                                            ) G5Sb 67s. 6d,Disablement pension (100% assessment))Special hardship allowance 20s. 27s. 6d.Unemployability supplement 32s. 6d. 40s.Constant attendance allowance                      25s, and 50s, 30s. and 60s.Widows pension    ) 27s 4ggWidowers pension)Allowance for adult dependants 21s. 6d. 25s.Allowance for dependent children - eldest 10s, 6d. 11s. 6d.others 2s. 6d. 3s. 6d,War PensionsDisablement pension (100% assessment) 55s. 67s* 6d.Unemployability - supplement 35s. 45s.dependent wife allowance 21s. 6d. 25s.allowance for 1st or onlychild 10s, 6d0 11s. 6d.
War Pensions - Contd.Constant attendance allowance 25s. , 37s, 6d.and 50s.Allowance for lowered standard ofoccupation 20s.Widows pension )Widowers pension )42s.Widows children (each child) 11s.Orphans pension - up to age 15 15s.aged 15 and over 21s. 6d.aged 10 and over, ifinfirm 32s. 6d.30s. , 45s. and60s.27s. 6d.52s. 6d.16s. 6d.20s.30s.40s.
111Main rates of National Insurance contributions(including contribution to National health service - 1 Od. for men and 8d. for women)Present ratesProposed ratesClass 1  (employed persons)EmployerMen     Employed manExchequerMainSche me4s.7d.5s. 5d.Is.6d.EmployerWomen Employed womanExchequer3s. 8d.4s.3d.Is.1jd.IndustrialInjuries5d.4d.(see Note 13d.3d.(see Note 1)TotalStampMainScheme) 10s. 9d.)) 8s. 5d.)5s. 6d.6s. 4d.Is. 10d,4s.7d.5s. 3d.Is,6d.industrial injuries-6d.5d.(see Note 1)4d.3d.(see Note 1)!total&apos;iarapP 12s.9d.i))10s.5d.)Class 2 (Self-employed persons)MenInsured manExchequerWomenInsured womanExchequer7s. 5d.9ld.6s. 2d.7jd.7s. 5d.6s.2d,8s.5d.2s.6d.7s.2d.2s.2d.3s, 5d.7s.2d.ftIVIClass 3   (Non-employed persons)Insured man Men           , Exchequer	5s. 7d.		5s.7d.	6s. 6d.		6s,6d.	9d.			Is. lOd.		&quot;*w^^-^v. Insured woman W omen Exchequer	4s.5d. 7d.	-	4s.5d.	5s. 2d. Is. 6d,	-	5s. 2d. -I&quot;INote s1,      The Exchequer contribution to the Industrial Injuries Fund is assessed atl/5th of the annual income from contributions of employers and employees.2.      The above table gives the rates for insured persons over age 18;  lower rates are paid by persons under that age.
APPENDIX C1. Estimated net additional cost to Exchequer in first two years (i.e. additional toExchequer liability on the basis of existing benefits and contributions);-  Millions1955/56(See Note 1)1956/57Extra Exchequer liability on account ofNational Insurance (see Note 2)Extra Exchequer liability on account ofIndu str ial injury ie sDoss of tax receipts on account ofadditional employees contributionsTotal additional cost in respect ofNational InsuranceLess;  Net savings on National AssistanceMet additional cost of National Insurance proposalsSxtra cost of War Pensions proposals (see Note 3)Net additional cost to ExchequerNOTES:2119251114102424131114251.   The higher rates of National Insurance benefits and contributions will not operate for the full year 1955/56.2.   Include Exchequer supplement to contributions and estimateddeficiency payment.3.   The extra cost of War Pensions for the full year 1955/56 will beabout  15 millions but  5 millions of this will be paid inadvance, and will fall in the financial year 1954/55.
2,    Estimated future cost of. National Insurance proposals:  Millionslo   Additional benefit expehditui*e20   Additional contribution income(employers and insured persons)30   Additional Exchequer supplement to contributionFirst full year(1956/57)1129323In 15 years(1969/70)150OA24In 25 years(1979/00)17693234.   Additional excess of expenditure ;over income (to be met. by Exchequer)    (4 surplus)5c   Total extra burden on Exchequer(3 and 4)60   Exchequer charge with presentbenefits and contributions7.   Total Exchequer charge (5 and 6)197993406432538960434517The additional benefit expenditure from the Industrial Injuries Fund willbe about  7 millions in the first full year;  this will be covered by theincome from additional contributions together with the extra exchequer supplement of  ljf millions.

</content>
</cab>
