<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/27/45 images: 516-523</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
233-OUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 01? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY!S GOVERNMENT).(421,365 ^Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The War Cabinet&apos;, at its meeting on the 3rdAugust (W.M.(42) 102nd Conclusions, Minute l)decided that a draft White Paper on the above matter should be prepared by the Service Ministers andthe Chancellor of the Exchequer in consultation -and should be submitted in draft to the War Cabinet.By agreement with the Service Ministers, i submit herewith the draft of a White Paper forapproval by the Cabinet,      The consultations whichhave taken place have included not only the service ministers but the Minister of Labour and NationalService and the Minister of Pensions, who, fromtheir respective points of view, concur in the draftoI ,;IIGUST, 1942.COPY NO.WAR CABINETSERVICE PAY AND ALLOWANCES(int&amp;O&apos; K.W.Treasury Chambers,18th August, 1942.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTEMOLUMENTS OF THE ARMED FORCES.(1) GENERAL CONSIDERATIONS.Attempts are commonly nuide to compare the remuneration of the armed Forces with that of industrial workers and other civilians. the factors of which account must be taken before any fair comparison of thiskind can be made are, however, complex and difficult to assess one against another; the object of this Paper is to bring out some of the considerations which should be borne in mind in attempting to measure the real emolu-ments of all kinds which are received by members of the Services.A number of illustrations are included, and these are taken generally fromArmy rates. Conditions of service in the three Forces are, however, broadly similar, and, although, the illustrative figures quoted in this Paper are taken from Army examples, the general considerations to which reference is madeare much the same in the other two Forces.Any direct and immediate comparison of pay between the soldier andthe civilian is impossible, since their systems of remuneration are different in fundamentals. In the first place, while the civilian worker receives thewhole of his earnings in cash, the soldier normally receives a part of hisearnings in kind in the shape of clothing, food and accommodation. In thesecond place, the civilian worker&apos;s earnings depend generally on the job he does and on the hours for which he does it, and do not take account ofother factors such as marriage; the soldier&apos;s earnings, on the other hand,make no differentiation for long or short hours of duty, but they take accountof his personal domestic circumstances by including allowances for his family or other dependants; they also take account, in the application ofWar Service Grants, of his financial circumstances prior to service and ofhis commitments. Other differences exist in the provision for the Forcesof such benefits as medical treatment, cheap recreational facilities and free travel on leave which civilians as a general rule do not enjoy.There is one other difference in basic conditions which is of some importance, viz., the incidence of income tax. As a result of the reductionin income tax reliefs, large numbers of wage earners have come within thescope of the tax. In civilian life a single man is liable to tax if his weekly earnings exceed about  2 2s. 6;?., a married man if they exceed about  3and a married man with one child if they exceed about  4. The soldier,on the other hand, being taxable only on his pay and not on either thebenefits which he receives in cash or in kind or in family or dependants&apos;allowances, may enjoy a real income very substantially exceeding thesefigures before he begins to suffer income tax. For instance, wdnle the married civilian becomes liable to tax on earnings exceeding  3 per w^eek,a married Staff Sergeant in the Army is exempt, although he has a totalcasli income for himself and his wife of  4 3s. 6d. per week and receiveshis own keep and clothing in addition.The civilian earns a post-war credit in respect of the income tax he pays;and the soldier who pays income tax is in the same position. But, inaddition, all soldiers below commissioned rank have recently been granted a post-war credit as part of their Service emoluments. No account is taken ofthis post-war credit in the illustrative calculations which follow as it maybe regarded as broadly counter-balanced in the lower military ranks by the civilian income tax credit.In attempting to .m.ake comparisons with civilians it is convenient to treat unmarried men without dependants separately from others, since theirtreatment in the Fbrees differs considerably.(2) UNMARRIED MEN.The minimum Service rate of pay is 17s. 6d. per week and this normallyrises after six months by the grant of proficiency pay to 21s. In addition tothis pay,, the unmarried soldier receives generally in kind his food, accom-modation, clothing and certain other benefits. It is impossible to put a cash value on these issues in kind which could not be challenged as beingeither too high or too low. The conditions under which soldiers live neces-sarily vary widely and, in particular, it is impossible to assess in terms of cash the value of the many different kinds of accommodation which theyoccupy. It is necessary, therefore, to approach the matter from anotherangle, and it is perhaps useful to attempt to assess the expenditure of whichthe soldier is relieved by reason of the provisions in kind which are madefor him. In normal circumstances the unmarried industrial worker wouldhave to provide as a first charge on his earnings for his board, lodging,clothing, laundry, health and unemployment, insurance and in many cases[24238]
transport to and from his work. The male industrial worker in a typicalGovernment hostel pays 27s. 6cl. per week for board and lodging, excludingmidday meals. In view of this figure it seems reasonable to suppose that full board and lodging, together with the miscellaneous items set out above,will commonly involve an expenditure at any rate of 35s. per week. Ifthis figure is taken, not as a valuation of the issues in kind made to the soldier, &quot;but as a rough estimate of the minimum sum which many industrial workers are likely to spend on the items of living which make no call onthe soldier&apos;s pocket and the minimum rate of pay of 17s. 6d. is added to it,it gives a total valuation of 52s.&apos; 6d. per week as the minimum emolumentsof a private soldier; this sum represents approximately the net income,after payment of.tax, of the unmarried civilian earning  3 per week.The &quot;above figures refer to the man without dependants and at theminimum rate of pay. That minimum may be increased in a variety of ways.The soldier may be granted an allowance towards the support of a dependant.Proficiency pay adds 3s. Gd. per week very generally after six months&apos; service,which is equivalent to an increase of about 5s. in the hands of a civilianwho in comparable circumstances would pay tax on it. Various incrementsare added at the end of the first, second and third years of service; after three years&apos; service these increments, together with a further addition whichthe soldier may earn for special proficiency, amount to a further 8s. 9d. perweek, which is worth 13s. to a taxable civilian. If we take the sum of 35s.mentioned above as a typical instance of the civilian expenditure on thethings which the soldier has provided for him, we find thus that theunmarried private soldier with no dependants is, after three years&apos; service,in a financial position comparable with that of a civilian earning 78s. aweek.More important perhaps than the proficiency pay and increments whicha non-tradesman private soldier may receive are the widespread possibilitiesof his earning tradesmen&apos;s rates of pay or promotion or both. The Forcesemploy a considerable number of tradesmen covering a wide range of tradesfrom the Armament Artificer to the Baker or Clerk who are paid accordingto their trade and their individual qualifications at rates which for privatesbegin at from 19s. 8(7. to 38s. 6d. a week and carry increments for lengthof service during the first three years. Thus an unmarried Private TradesmanClerdc without dependants may receive after three years&apos; service 36s. 9d.in weekly pay and a Tradesman Fitter 43s. 9d.; if we add to these figuresthe 85s. taken above as a typical value for receipts in kind and adjust them also to take account of the lower incidence of income tax on the soldier&apos;sremuneration, they are equivalent to civilian rates of pay of  4 7s. and 4 16s. per week respectively.Prospects of promotion could not of course be held to justify undulylow rates of pay for the basic ranks. But in examining the pay of thicForces it is to be remembered that the opportunities of earning improvedpay by obtaining promotion are good; for instance in the Army as a whole the proportion of Warrant Officers and n.c.o.&apos;s is nearly 24 per cent. Inaddition there is promotion from the ranks to commissions. Promotionprospects are therefore one in four or even better, and the financial effects of even moderate promotion are considerable. A non-Tradesman CorporaFspay would normally be at least 35s. and a Sergeanfs 45s. Qd. as comparedwith the Private&apos;s basic 17s. 6d., while the pay of.the Tradesman Corporalranges from 36s. 9d. to 50s. 9d. and that of a Tradesman Sergeant is61s. 3d. At the level of Sergeant it would perhaps be reasonable to takea higher amount than 35s. as the sum which would be expended in civilianlife on the things which the Forces receive in kind; for the purpose ofthis memorandum however it is proposed to retain the figure of 35s. Ifthis addition is made and adjustment is also made for the differentincidence of income tax the total estimate of value of the remuneration of an unmarried Tradesman Sergeant becomes  5 13s. per week. IfDependants&apos; allowance is in issue the gross emoluments will be corres-correspondingly increased.(3) MARRIED  MEN.A different method must be employed in attempting to compare thevalue of the married Service man&apos;s emoluments with those of civilians.It may be assumed that in most instances the married man&apos;s home ismaintained while he is on service and that therefore there is no saving to him by reason of his being supplied at public cost with accommodation.But the cost of his own food, clothing, health and unemployment insurance,and in many cases transport to and from work no longer form a charge on&apos;the family income. It is difficult again to make a cash estimate of&apos; the amount of this saving, but expenditure on these items in the caseof many industrial workers is unlikely to be less than of the order of23s. to 25s. per week. The minimum pay and allowances drawn in cashby a Private Soldier and his wife amount to 39s. per week; but; if weadd to this figure lit sum of (say) 23s. as ii typical valuation of issues in kind, the minimum weekly rate of total reinuneratibn becomes  3 2s. Od.
per week, which is equivalent to  3 4s. Od. in the hands of a taxablecivilian. Under present conditions a wife without children whether her husband is serving in the Forces or is u civilian will normally undertakepaid war work and thus supplement the family income; indeed, it is inthe national interest that she should do so. If there are children, however,the mother will very often not be in a position to do this; but in such. cases where the husband is in the Forces the family income is increasedby children&apos;s allowances. Where, for instance, there are two children theaddition under this head is 15s. making the minimum of  3 2s. Od.mentioned above a minimum of  3 17s. Od. The exceptional ease of the numerous family is provided for by the addition of further children&apos;allowances.All the various factors which in the majority of cases make for paymentabove the minimum rates in the case of single men operate of course inthe case of married men, too.   Thus proficiency pay generally adds 3s. 6d.a week to basic pay after six months&apos; service; increments totalling 7s. Od.a week after three years are added at the end of each of the first threeyears of service and this addition may be increased to 8s. Qd. by thegrant of special proficiency pay; tradesmen&apos;s rates may add between Is. 9d.and 26s. 3d. a week to basic rates; and further increases may he obtained bypromotion to higher rank.  The effect of these various factors is appreciable;thus, a married Private with two children, after three years&apos; service, evenif he had gained no promotion and was not a tradesman, could, togetherwith his wife, receive in cash 66s. 3d. per week the equivalent, if we allowQ.3&apos;3*5&apos;s- I0r issues in kind to the man himself, of  4l^s. 3d. per week.   If he had become a Corporal in that time the cash receipts would be 73s. 3d. a week,representing a total value of  4 l p. 3d., and, if a Sergeant, cash receiptswrould be 82s., representing a total value, after taking account of the incometax which a civilian would pay, of  5 Ub. Od.   If, on the other hand, he had gained no promotion but had obtained a tradesman&apos;s qualifications, cashreceipts might have risen to SOs. 3d., representing a total value of some 518e. Od. a week,o-s.(4) HIGHER NON-COMMISSIONED RANKS.The illustrative figures so far given in this paper relate to the lowrerranks, from Private up to Sergeant. But the forces offer considerable&apos;opportunities of promotion to higher ranks. The Army Warrant Officer,Class 1, has a rate of pay for non-tradesmen of  4 7s. 6d. and the warrant officer, Class 2, of  3 3s. Od. If (taking the case of an unmarried man)these figures are adjusted for the purpose of comparison with civilians bythe addition taken above of 35s. per week, representing receipts in kind andby correction for the difference in income tax, they are comparable withgross civilian rates of pay of  5 16s. Od. and  7 6s. Od. respectively. Oppor-tunities also exist for earning special rates of pay for special duties; forinstance, in the Air Force rates are paid for flying duties which considerablyexceed basic rates for the ranks concerned.(5) COMMISSIONED OFFICERS.The total emoluments of officers, like those of other ranks, consist notonly of pay but of a variety of issues in kind or of cash allowances whichare drawn in lieu of those issues. In the case of officers these additionalissues are drawn in the shape of cash equivalents (instead of issues in kind)more frequently than is the case with other ranks. The instances which follow assume for purposes of illustration that all allowances are drawn in cash. It is to be remembered that, although the officer who in fact receivesrations or accommodation in kind does not receive the corresponding cashallowances, the incidence of income tax, which is an important factor, isunaffected, since neither the allowances nor the issues in kind are reckonedfor purposes of taxation.The pay of the lowest commissioned rank (Second Lieutenant) in theArmy is at the rate of  201 a year, and the cash allowances which may bedrawn by an unmarried.man in respect of rations, servant, lodging, fuel and light amount to approximately  147. Pay only is taxable, and the total sum left in the officer&apos;s hands after payment of tax is (inclusive of allowances)  322. This is the same as the net sum left after payment of tax in the hands of an unmarried civilian with a gross earned income of 462 a year. In the case of the married Second Lieutenant living withhis family who draws all pay and allowances in cash, net resources afterpayment of tax are equivalent to those of a civilian with a salary of  483a year, while the corresponding figure for a man with two children is  518a year. Where, however, as will normally be the case in war time, a marriedofficer is living away from home he receives higher allowances. The total value of the remuneration of a married Second Lieutenant so situated would amount to  578 a year,-&apos; or if he has two children  611 a year. &apos;
It is to be noted that at the officer level the position of the armed forces in respect of income tax is especially favourable. While the salaryearner and the industrial worker in civil life in the course of the war have suffered successive increases of income tax on the whole of their incomes,officers in the Forces have to a considerable extent been spared from theeffect of these increases by reason of the fact that they are taxed only onthat part of their total emoluments which ranks as pay. A comparison with pre-war figures will illustrate the extent of the changes which war taxationhas brought about. Before the war the total pay and allowances, afterpayment of tax. of an unmarried Second Lieutenant were equal to the net income of the civilian with a gross salary of  360 a year; they are nowequivalent, as stated above, to a gross civilian income of  462. In the caseof men with dependants the increase as measured by civilian standardsis even greater; the net cash income of a married Second Lieutenant livingwith his family and drawing allowances at the rates ruling just before theintroduction of the War Budget in September 1939 was equal to that of a civilian earning  391 a year; now the equivalent civilian level is  483. Forthe man with two children the corresponding figures are  400 inSeptember 1939 and  518 now.(6) WAR  SERVICE  GRANTS.The figures of Service pay and allowances quoted above representthe rates provided for the normal case pi-esenting no unusual features.Where a serving man or an officer, whether married or single hasobligations to dependants and/or liabilities in respect of standing chargessuch as rent, building society payments; insurance premiums, hire purchaseinstalments, &amp;c, which cannot reasonably be met out of his Service pay and allowances his remuneration may be increased by the award of a war service Grant. The maximum amount of War&quot; Service Grant that maybe given is  3 a week which sum is free of Income Tax. -3&apos;Larried officers separated from their families have similarly benefited,the value of the remuneration of a Second Lieutenant so situated beingequivalent in 1939 to that of a civilian earning  409 and now equivalentto  578-or for an officer with 2 children  441 in 1939 and   611 now.



</content>
</cab>
