<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/12/0 images: 2-2</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C. 14(54)								3rd March, 1954



		1.	Parliament.					[Enter B-H.



H.C.	Business for next week.

	Propose to announce this week tht. Budget will be opened on 6/4. Judges Bill : hope to get it on in week after next.



B.H.	Service pensions didn’t go v. well with loyal supporters, who now have to make volte-face.  Some fear there may be similar retreat on Teachers’ Superannuation.  Also some suspicion tht. Judges Bill may be part of a deal on M.P’s salaries.  Wd. be useful if something cd. be said to 1922 Cttee. on whole of this complex.



P.M.	Had assumed a free vote on Opposn. Motion, after wh. Govt. wd. make up their mind &amp; put fwd. proposals with Whips on.

	Wd. be good to get Judges Bill over before all this comes along.



Agreed.



B.H.	Opinion on that Bill is better : but anxiety over whole complex.



	

2.	Kenya : General China.



A.E.	Telegram from O.L.



Sw.	Suggest this shd. be given in reply to Pr. N. Ques in both Houses to-day.  viz., the offer and the commutation.

	We shall be asked wtr we intend to prosecute those who surrender.

	x/	We shall have to say “no” in answer to any supplementary.

			

		Agreed : Announce to-day – Minister in H/L. and Foster in H/C.



A.E.		Remember O.L. isn’t saying x/.  Can’t we stall.  We may embarrass him.



Sal.		Say “can’t add any more to-day”.  Adhere to what O.L. says.  Agreed.



		

		3.	Sudan.



A.E.	Have submitted minute to P.M. re powers of Govr-Genl.  Have told Howe tht. troops cd. be sent if needed.

		Long apprecn. fr. S. Lloyd.

	Can’t reach any definite decision to-day.  Tho’ I have to make a temporising statement in H/C to-day. – merely because one is demanded in H/L.

								[Enter D.S., A.L.B



	4.	Germany : Manufacture of Civil Aircraft.



A.E.	Memo. has support of Arms Export W. Party and C.O.S.

	May be public re-action here.  But we shall be better able to face that after last week’s debate.



D.S.	We are now getting worst of both worlds.  Not stopping G. fr. having an industry &amp; allowing U.S. manufacrs. to get their foot in.  We have types that wd. suit G. better than U.S. types.  Feeling of frustration in Br. aircraft industry.



A.L.B	Strongly support this.

	Co-opn. already with potential air-line operators.

		

Memo. approved.			[Exit D.S. ALB., BH.

							[Enter O.P.



	5.	War Disability Pensions.



O.P.	Only 20,000 unemployable pensioners.  No increase made in their unemployability allowance since we came in.  They are specially hard cases.  Wd. like to increase the allowance by 10/= a week.

	These men are all out of the labour market.



R.A.B.	This is best thing to do.  Cost £½M. to Exchequer.

	Only ques is one of timing.  I think it might come a little later.



H.C.	Cd. we link this with Budget.  Need a peg to hang in on.



R.A.B.	That cd. be discussed.  May I settle timing with O.P.



M.F.	Small no. of totally disabled police &amp; firemen who wd. rank for equal treatment.  Will discuss with O.P.

								[Exit O.P.



	6.	Valuation for Rating.



H.M.	Simultaneous announcement of new valuations &amp; new poundage will make it much easier for any Govt. to put new valuation into effect.  Legn. needed for that.  P’pone entry into force until April ’56, so that legn. can be passed m’while.



		Memo. approved.





	7.	Taxation : Methods of Financing Govt. Expenditure.



W.	Political &amp; social, as well as economic, problem.

	Time &amp; ingenuity devoted to tax-avoidance.  Undermining of business morality.

	Taxation is stripping industry of reserves wh. it shd. be accumulating.  I take grave view of our industrial &amp; commercial future if present levels of taxation continue.

	Nothing new or revolutionary in my ideas.

	Commercial accountancy methods are not based solely on need to show profits – it has a wider object &amp; basis.

	No real objn. to financing stock-piling otherwise than by revenue.  RAB says reduced taxn. wd. not bring increased savings.  But redn. in co. profits tax wd. certainly result in savings.  Large incomes : present posn. is inflationary because people are using capital for current needs.



P.M.	6.000 millionaires before 1939 have shrunk to less than 100.

		I have always had 15/- in my mind as target.



RAB.		Wd. lose £30 M. to the Exchequer.



P.M.		Ty. told me it wd be £11 M.



P.M.	Wd. increase natl. wealth, promote savings, &amp; give incentives to hard work if we reduced surtax.  Ques is wtr it wd. kill, politically, any Govt. which proposed it.  I had always hoped it might be done in the hour of victory.  But, on tactics, I wd. hesitate to recommend it to Tory Party now.



R.A.B.	15/= cd. be defended easily on economic grounds.  But it wd. be indefensible politically.

	Difficulty about borrowing is that it wd. weaken Budget because we shd. have to treat capital &amp; revenue differently – e.g. death duties etc.,

	Shall I circulate Crick Cttee. Rpt. on Govt. accounting?

	Have examined, as substitute for Cripps’ form of Budget, other methods. wh. wd. take into a/c all transactions of Govt. with outside world.  Alternative methods wd. however show a deficit much in the same way as the conventional methods: indeed, even worse.

	Borrowing.  Wd. not wish to borrow in period of relative prosperity as now.  Nor are we now in inflation.  Borrowing wd. lead us back into inflation.  Market is over-full anyway – e.g. we can’t sell the steel cos.  If there were to be borrowing, we shd. do it in recession.  My mind is not closed to it.

	But ques of public exp’re will become a major political issue for this Govt.  Defence/social services/farmers = more than country can bear.  Even if we get anything out of farmers, we shall be faced next year with choice betwn. reducing expn. or increasing taxation.  I prefer the first.  I wd. welcome some dramatic reduction in public expenditure.  My main concern is with the Budget after next.



Al.	Def.  Exp’re – only hope of redn. is thro’ redn. of overseas commitments wh. wd. permit of smaller Forces.



A.E.	F.O. duty to seek means of reducing commitments.  I see no hope of it in F/E.  Only chance is M/E.  We ought to cut there.  But how?

	Germany – will continue and may become more costly.

	If anything is available in Budget, it shd. benefit industry.  We can’t expect to go on being as lucky over that as now, with G. and J. competn. stiffening.



P.T.	Export diffies. increase.  Present taxation level is main obstacle to exports.  Policy decisions early will be needed if there is to be tax relief in Budget of 1955.

[Exit A.E.

						

R.A.B.	Exp’re reductions must be made early in ’54 if I am to have any scope for tax relief in 1955.



Sal.	Concerned on one aspect.  When is borrowing permissible? Principle tht. there shd. be no borrowing save when early prospect of cash revenue is cherished by Ty.  Is it wise?  Gas, electricity can borrow under that principle &amp; have raised £600M in recent years – propose now to go up to £1400M.  Roads, at least as beneficial to society, can’t qualify under this principle.  Don’t believe that can be defended.

	Strict appln. of Ty. principle will distort pattern of our revenue and capital expenditure.

	Not necessarily a ques of increasg. borrowing – rather its appln. w’in any given total.

	And there will be increasing agitation about roads.



R.A.B.	It’s a ques of inroads into total savings.  They don’t suffice to meet all our needs.



H.M.	That’s not Sal. point.  He isn’t on the ques of total.

	Steel – not because there isn’t money enough, but because risk is too high at the price.



R.A.B.	Will consider Sal.’s point.  H’to, need for investment in electricity has bn. over-riding.



H.M.	But most uneconomic method of providing power because it can’t be stored.

	whole ques is wtr young men will go on working hard and creating wealth w’out any greater incentive than they have now?



R.A.B.	Let us register need for reduction in Govt.-expenditure.



P.M.	Then we must start soon?

	Cd. we reduce C. Servants by 10% or 15%?



Sal.	Set a percentage target for redn. of Estimates.  Much easier for Ministers to comply with an order to secure a certain percentage of savings.



</content>
</cab>
