<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/12/0 images: 20-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C. 31(54)							3rd May, 1954



		1.	Indo.China.					[Enter S.Ll., B.H.



S.Ll.	A.E. havg. diffies. in Geneva with Dulles.

	Geneva tel. 113.  Para. 3.



P.M.	Awkward moment when D.B.Phu falls – as seems inevitable.

	Will encourage Communists – esp. at moment when greater rift appears betwn. W. Allies.

		Endorse A.E.’s policy.

		But, as soon as this crisis is over, we must follow up quickly 	with effective pact for collective defence of S.E.A.





		2.	Parliament : Members’ Expenses.



R.A.B.	If all-Party motion is tabled, I shd. not favour free vote.

	I wd. favour Govt. amendment to a Motion – wtr Opposn. Motion or all-party.



H.C.	Thurs. last we were pressed for a day. x/ Made it clear, anyhow, tht. all the pressure is coming fr. Opposn.  side. /  But pressure will be renewed this Thursday unless we decide to give time next week.  They asked, thro’ usual channels, for debate this week.  Thursday of next week is only Govt. day we cd. offer.



P.M.	Has the onus of x/ been clearly put on Opposn.?



H.C.	Certainly in H/Commons.



Sw.	Can’t make anything in country on ques who supplies the time for discussion.



P.M.	Suppose they offer Supply Day &amp; table motion approvg. Cttee.’s. report.

	Cd. we not allow free vote?  It wd. be carried.  We need do no more than expense scheme.



H.C.	If it were carried on a free vote, we wd. have to do Cttee’s report.

	Also : wd. it be proper for Ministers to speak or vote – they aren’t concerned.



P.M.	Doubt validity of second point.

	But on reflectn. : we have said it isn’t our policy to do Cttee’s report.

	If motion commanded that, we shd. have to table amendment.



B.H.	Debate on adjournment motion wd. be so much to our advantage tht. I

                  x|	wonder wtr it wdn’t be better to off Govt. time on condn. it was on 

        |	adjournment motion &amp; tht. they wdn’t vote – officially.

	Number of Tories favouring Rpt. is decreasing as constituency influences are brght to bear.



R.A.B.	Try for debate on Adjournment.



H.M.	Yes : abandon manoeuvre about “whose time” &amp; proceed as at x/



P.M.	Don’t want to eat all my words : cd. we not offer to share time?



B.H.	They wdn’t accept condns. on that basis.



M.F.	And, if that fails, &amp; they table motion – we shd. put down amendment.

 



</content>
</cab>
