<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/12/0 images: 21-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.32(54)						5th May, 1954



		1.	Geneva Conference.			[Enter BH., J.B.C., S.Ll.



P.M.	B. Smith’s forthcoming attitude to A.E.

	But when I spoke to him on tel. last night he said he was finished.

	V. disappointing – and bewildering.  A.E. agrees.





		2.	Parliament.



H.C.	Business for next week.

	Teachers’ Superannuation Bill – 2nd. Rdg. Monday.

	Time-table motion for Television Bill – Tuesday.

	Members’ Expenses – Thursday, on adjournment.



B.H.	Oppn. accepted. our proposal, on condn. we gave time in followg. wk. for a final decision.  I said Govt. spokesmen wd. be indicatg. intentn. at end of 1st. debate.  He admd. tht. if they disliked this &amp; wished for further debate, it wd. have to be on Supply Day.



H.C.	Need for Indemnity Bill for Neil Macpherson M.P. in respect of his acceptce. of posn. with Dried Fruit Corpn. Australia.



P.M.	Final apprecn. of chances on Educn. Bill?



B.H.	Proposing to spk. to 26 today, who are unreliable: &amp; of whom 8 are pledged to teachers not to vote for it.

	My opinion : more likely to be beaten than not.



P.M.	Is this a good moment?



S.Ll.	Co-inciding with possible fall of French Govt.



L.P.	If we are going to lose the Bill, why incur the disadv. of a defeat.

	

H.C.	Shall we p’pone for a week, so that BH can see all &amp; Geneva may clear?

	But there must be def. decn. to go on.



H.M.	Defeat wh. we ignore will be bad for future discipline in our Party.



B.H.	So will abandoning Bill, wh. majority of our supporters have defended.



F.H.	I can’t see how we shall get economies if we run away fr. our dissidents on this.

	Will also damage our prestige.



Sal.	Foreign situation is most important argument.  This is not the moment at wh. to risk Govt. defeat.

H.M.	Future economies.  This won’t prevent them if they are presented &amp; carried all together.  



Sw.  	I agree, on reflection.



B.C.	W’out the Bill, we shall need a supplementary.



J.S.	Abandonment of Bill will damage our prestige.  Cd. accept a weeks’ delay.  We have all justified Bill as right &amp; necessary.  How do we explain w’drawal.  Let us at least show we have courage of our convictions, even if we are beaten.



W.M.  P.T.	P’pone for a week.  



M.F. 	Driven to that view because of Geneva situation.



		Agreed :	P’pone announcemt. of date of 2nd. Rdg.

				Review it again next week.



		3.	Indo-China.



S.Ll.	Tel. 137-138.



P.M.	Overtaken by telephone message fr. Bedell?



S.Ll.	Specific suggn. of study of S.E.A. pact need not be affected

	Only poss. objn. is tht. group won’t include any Asian. But this is

            x/	met by 1st. para. on p 2 of Tel. 138.



P.M.	First aim after Geneva must be to repair breach betwn. U.K. &amp; U.S.

	Can hope to do this on basis of Ldn. Communiqué.



S.Ll.	This is consistent with that.



Al.	Para. 6 of 137.  Staff Agency will need pol. guidance         [Exit B.H.

	on our policy for Indo-China, if they are to get far.



S.Ll.	Recognise that, but will show we mean business.



Sw.	Safe fr. pt. of view of Asians because of x/.

	Telegram fr. P.M./Ceylon suggests contact will suffice.



		Agreed :	Authorise A.E. subject to Bedell S. developmt. 			having produced no change.



		4.	Goa.



Sw.	Portuguese &amp; India have approached us re Treaty posn.

	P. have right to claim our support under old Treaty and N.A.T.O.

	We can’t accede to Nehru’s suggn. of a decln. tht. these have no relevance to Goa.

	We propose therefore to make our posn. clear to both sides, as in paras. 7 and 8.



P.M.	Favour Portugal.  But base it on legalistic arguments &amp; make it all as involved as possible.

						[Enter ALB., I.McL., O.P., D.E.



		5.	Government Programme for 1954/55.



P.M.	Big theme must be pensions.  Humanity can turn the flank of economy.  Advantages of big gestures.  That shd. have first priority.



O.P.	Memo. on this will be available next week.



W.M.	Ready to agree tht. my plans for occupl. health and Gowers for rlways shd. be considered together with proposals for economy.



M.F.	Shops : closing hours.  Waiting since ’47 : being pressed for it.

	Non-industrial etc.,  Pressure fr. T.U.’s since Govt. took office.

	I have met 9 deputns. from T.U.C.  Ld. Chancellor promised legn. to employers.  On other side, Parly. time : restrictions on traders : cost to employers.

							                     [Exit Sw.



	Condns. are bad : T.U. requests are justified.  Labour wd. chide us at our Election with not having done it.



W.M.	Will be diff. to handle T.U.’s if we can’t say we are going on with this.



L.P.	Opinion on H.A. Cttee. evenly divided.

	The other side of the case shd. not be ignored – para. 3.  Remember Catering trade.  Won’t be popular with Tory Party.



P.T.	These reforms cost money – to employers.  Can’t get anyone to build a hotel now.  Cd. we ask rlways to spend more – means higher fares.



A.L.B.	Rlways have enough burdens already.  Any money for them shd. go on higher wages for more skilled men.  This is not moment to give benefits to all.

	Road Traffic Bill shd. be included.



P.T.	Also Par Shares.



M.F.	Emergency Powers.  Are we to try to end it all before Election?

	Arguments : we are pledged to it.

		a valuable instrument of Socialism.

H.C.	Tho’ there are diffies.  



T.D. 	Open-cast.  



W.M. 	Use of troops in strikes.



M.F.	Main point : are we to leave the powers.



P.M.	Favour the theme of dismantling structure of emergency powers.



		Agreed :  Shd. be a more detailed memo. for Cabinet.  H.O.



H.M.	In a final Session -	Lists A. &amp; B. Essential Bills.

				Emergency Powers.

				Legn. for Economy Measures

				O.A.P.

	Can we do more?  That wd. give us a good p’mme for Election.



W.M.	May be right.  But danger of affronting T.U.’s.  Occupl. Health &amp; Gowers shd. not be shut out altogether.



							            [Exit A.L.B.

		6.	Recruitment of Ukrainians.			          I.McL.  O.P.



		Memo. approved.





		7.	King George VI Memorial.



D.E.	As in memo.



P.M.	First ascertain wtr Queen &amp; Queen Mother approve – informally.

	I will, if you won’t.  Before Cab. tender formal advice.

 



</content>
</cab>
