<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/12/0 images: 40-40</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.51(54)							20th July, 1954



								[Enter B.H., Att.G. S.Ll.

		1.	Geneva Conference – Indo-China.



P.M.	Tel. 984 fr. Geneva.  Seeking authority to conclude agreemt. despite some procedural differences with U.S., if the alternative is no agreemt.



	Agreed – A.E. to be assured of Cabinet support on this.





		2.	Egypt.



S.Ll.	Tho’ E. are reasonable on both points, they are adamant on 7 years &amp; 15 mos. respectively.



P.M.	Don’t mind short evacuation period, 	subject to view of military. 

Prefer to insist on longer duration.	{S.Ll.   Pledged to give debate on 

					  	{heads of agreemt.  But about 3 

S.Ll.	A.E. thght we shd. press for 12 yrs.	{mos. betw. heads &amp; concln. of 

						{agreemt.  Therefore, cd. have 

P.M.	Hold firm on 20 yrs. until A.E.         	{debate on heads after recess – 

        	returns.				{unless these were concluded 

					         	{before 31/7.





		3.	Crichel Down.



P.M.	Regret to inform Cab. tht. M/Ag. has offered resignation.  I have agreed to submit it to Queen.  This can be announced at end of his speech.

	A becoming attitude, wh. will produce v. favourable re-action.

	Will unite Govt. supporters.  Your action will be applauded.

	Regret this end to yr. successful adminn. of M/Agric.

	Express Cab.’s regret at losing you as colleague.



T.D.	Only dignified way of ending this debate.



R.A.B.	Will cause slump in confidence among farmers – and this will re-act at once on agricultural Members, who shd. have done more to restrain hot-heads in Party.



P.M.	Ministers’ original statement caused the trouble – and Cab. were all involved in that.



Att.G.	On para. 36 of Minister’s speech.

	This point was considered by Cab., and suggd. tht. it was for considn. wtr public enquiry shd. not be held if owner had raised objn.

	M.F. said this was not excluded.  Surely the point shd. be left open.  Suggd. addl. words.

M.F.	Thght I wd. say this at end, if point were pressed.

	No objn. to its being said at outset.  Don’t commit ourselves to this – we don’t know wtr it is practicable.



Sal.	Para. 40-41.  Suggest deletion.  



T.D.  	Have done so.



P.M.	Report of enquiry by J. H. Woods etc., 

Shd. this be presented to H/C.?



M.F.	Yes.  Deals with particular cases.  Propounds some salutary general principles.  Will help the Minister.



P.M.	On reflection, I agree tht. Cabinet is not suitable body to enquire into such matters.  This enquiry doesn’t abrogate our responsibility.



		Agreed :	(Report to be presented.

				(Typed copy not to be given to first Opposn. 				(speaker.

				(Copies in Vote Office when Minister sits down.



							[Exit Att.G.  Enter O.P.

		4.	Old Age Pensions.



O.P.	Govt. amendment has bn. well-received this morning.



P.M.	How many realise tht. money will come from contributions?



O.P.	What shall I say on time-table?

	On 26/5 said rpts. likely to be in by end/year.  We now know

	Phillips Rpt. will be submd. by end Nov.  Shd. now like to promise (hope) to announce our policy by end/year.



H.C.	Plans rather than policy.



O.P.	Actuary’s Rpt. can be obtd. at our discretion.  Wd. aim to get both by end/Nov.



R.A.B.	Confident we can include announcemt. in Queen’s Speech.  Detail wd. come a little later.  Motion goes a long way.



H.M.	Avoid disappointment on the amount.



O.P.	Ll.G. has said 1946 purchasing power = only 4/=.  We can satisfy that.



P.M.	Emphasise increased contribution.



							[Exit O.P. B.H.



		5.	Civil Expenditure.			[Enter ALB., I.Mc., D.E.



Sw.	Target of £100 M. was raised to £125 because of increase in forecast exp’re.

	Our proposals wd. save £113 M.

	Only 3 wd. need legn.

	Doesn’t exhaust whole field – C.D., Strat. Reserves, M/S. civil &amp;can, if necessary, return to those on basis of D.P. Cttee. report.  Moreover, central/local Govt. finance – tho’ not immediate, it wd. enable rate of Govt. grant e.g. on educn. to be reduced.



W.M.		i)    Most concerned about proposal v. bread.

	Wd. it be wise to give this political cry to opponents before an  Election?

	In industry : will cause trouble on wage-claims.  Not because .29 of a point in c/living is so grave, but because psychological effect of 1d. on bread.  Can soon lose £10 M. in wage increases.

	Wd. also tend to worsen relations in industry.  T.U.C. rpt. on econ. sitn. is likely to stress importce. of avoiding increases in food prices.

ii)   10% cut in Dplt. Inf. staffs.  Can’t take that – in addn. to general staff cuts.  Sub.  para. o.

		iii)  Sub para p.  Have got about £900,000.  Shall find it hard to go 			further.



Sw.	On ii) don’t take 10% too seriously.  Will be a ques of cutting the those staffs which make least contn.



I.Mc	Accept cut in capital expenditure on hospitals.

	Prescriptions.  Diffy. is solely political.  Burden falls on those who are most ill.

	Most concerned about m’tenance exp’re. on hospitals.  Their claims will total much more than my estimate of £4 M.  It can be cut below that. But not to £1 M.  This includes pay and distinction awards wh. must be met.  When figures come in Nov., I will examine with aim of getting it below £4 M. : but can’t promise to go down to £1 M.



J.S.	Same is true in Scotland.  Ask for it to be open until returns are in – Nov.



Sw.	Impressed with case tht. may be room for false economy here.  Hope Ministers will do their best.



J.S.	Prescriptions.  Pity we didn’t do it when l/c charge was just imposed.

	Wd. cause political trouble.



P.M.	Increase in bread price – terrible result for Tory Party : wd. probably lead to Socialist victory and thus more expenditure.



R.A.B.		i)    Bread and Flour.

	Judge all this v. background of Budget.  Drain of agriculture on it threatens stability of agricultural policy because taxpayer will revolt v. it.  Only means are redns. in Annual Reviews or levies (wh. were Conservative instrument pre-war).  I advocate levy &amp; it has consequence of increase bread price.  W’out levy you must depend on annual tussles with farmers.  Answer to M/F is : we aren’t shirking bread price increase.

	Bread subsidy costs £40 M. A non-pol decn. wd. be to abolish it altogether.

	On M/L. objn. I don’t expect instability in c/living index.  I wd. risk small rise, for sake of reducg. unsound bread subsidy.

	Public don’t need £85 M. subsidy on milk &amp; bread.  They are spending much more on tobacco &amp; t.v.  Concealing real price of food is not sound social policy.  Working man won’t notice this rise.  Econ. price of bread wd. be 1/8 per 3½ lb. load.

	My preference is to do both – for saving of £18 M.

		ii)   Health Services.  Ready to seek agreement on figure for m’tenance 

		with the 2 Ministers.



Sal.	Education.  Technological educn., wh. recently has had a little encouragemt. is now to be slowed down.  Don’t jerk it up &amp; down.  Let us at least have a steady rate.  Otherwise Universities will go ahead &amp; then be jerked back.



RAB.	This is only a cut on a fwd. estimate.  Recurrent grants won’t be touched.  Shall save on some bldg., which is non-technology!

	Only means a little delay in starting bldg. projects.

	Wd. like to inform Cab. – circulate a note.



W.	Am satisfied with proposal.



F.H.	School meals (£4 M).  Cdn’t get it all in first year.  From Party angle it will be difficult.  The charge was 7d. when we came in : if we make it 1/=, it will be hard to m’tain there is no increase in c/living.



W.M.	I cd. not be associated with an increase in price of bread.  I cdn’t remain in Cabinet.



H.M.	Thght this was an exercise carried out unusually early in year – to see what we wd. have to do to secure a given economy.  We shan’t decide until we have balanced all the risks etc.,



R.A.B.	M’while expenditure rises &amp; commitments are accepted.



P.T.	Present level of taxn. threatens our power to m’tain exports.

	Unless we can find some means of saving about £100 M.

	Budget can give no comfort to industry.  Must face this soon.



Sw.	No good expecting us to find the money by easier means.  There aren’t any.



W.	Para 2 of Ll.G.’s memo.  He gives £25 M. without the levy on flour.



H.C.	Cd. you put ½d only on bread (vice 1d.) and increase sugar by 1d.  Defend it by undue consumption of sweets.



Sw.	Can you raise normal loaf by ¼d?  



W. 	No., not now.



P.M.	Cdn’t begin to clinch this discussion in absence of A.E.

	Let us reflect on this, in light of discussion.

	Must consider general background – which is one of prosperity, with lush exp’re on tobacco &amp; T.V.  No feeling of alarm or threatened bankruptcy.  High emplt., &amp; prodn.



Sw.	All of which provokes hope of reduced taxation.  Which can’t be realised because Govt. expenditure continues to rise.



R.A.B.	All these economies cd. be realised with little disturbance,

	save only bread/flour and prescriptns.

               x|	I will identify those items on wh. decns. must be taken before Recess &amp; put in a note w’in 2 or 3 days.

	Will consider bread.  But want also general blessing for approach in report.



P.M.	Suspend decision until we have report on defence exp’re – when A.E. will also be here.

	M’while let us do x/. by all means.



Sw.         *	Reserve A.E.’s posn. on O. Informn. Services and technical assistce.



A.L.B.	£1 M. on Tubes.  Work has bn. going on for 2 yrs : contract let : will complete next year.  Can’t stop it now.

							[Exit D.E., I.McL.



		6.	Gatwick Airport.



ALB.	Favour announcg. before Recess tht. we are going ahead.



H.M.	Difficult.  de. L. has views &amp; shd. be here.  He thinks Horne wd. be better.



ALB.	Cab. Cttee. considered &amp; rejected Horne.



H.M.	Supposing de L.’s view is again rejected, there are 2 views on ques wtr we shd. announce a decn. so rapidly.  We recd. it only on 24/6.

	Wd. local objectors think we had given it due attention.  Wd. be thght these enquiries are only a sham.

	Chairman, Surrey Co. Council has written : apprehendg. tht. M/C.A. will announce as soon as House is up tht. he is going ahead.



A.L.B.	I wd. have seen him anyway.



Sim.	Cab. Cttee. were clear tht. Gatwick was only practicable choice.



A.L.B.	Urgency about Ldn Airport – dangerous congestion demands alternate long before developmt. of helicopters.

	Agree prs. this is too hurried.  Ready to wait about a month &amp; announce in Recess.



H.M.	Let it be taken at a Cabinet in September.



A.L.B.	V. well – so long as it doesn’t wait until October.



		Agreed :	Consider at a Cabinet in recess (end of August) 			– de L. being present – and announce decision 			before House meets again.





 







 



</content>
</cab>
