<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/12/0 images: 57-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C. 75(54)							11th November, 1954







1.	Wireless Licences.			[Enter P.M.G., Gammans, 

						Att.G., P.B.H.



Att.G.	Posn. was righted by Act of ’49, which came into force this year; but it did not validate charges made earlier.



Sal.	Considered by H.A. Cttee.  Clear tht. legn. is best course open to us.



						[Exit PMG., Gamm., Att.G

		2.	Pensions.



P.M.	Why shd. we not pay larger sum on old warrant?



O.P.	Twice in 4 yrs. this has been done – by Labour Govt. and by this.

	On first occasion there was a b’down in admn. because attempt to do it too fast.

	This is insurance scheme.  Wd. cost £8 M. a month to pay benefits before increased contns.  Can’t collect those until June.  Ty. willing to bring benefits in earlier (April) at cost of £12 M.  But can’t stretch that too far.

	Y’day Soc. Services Cttee. (Tory) in H/C. met.  At end there was no support for Xmas box.  Also convinced tht. emerg. scheme wd. involve risk of confn. &amp; breach of insurance principle.  They asked for no more than passage of Bill (all stages) before Xmas.  Viz., they concentrate now on speed of legn.  I wd. be ready for that, if we cd. persuade Oppn.



H.M.	Diffy. therefore to bothe prepns. for paying in and paying out.

	Must be able to prove maximum expedition.

	When, in course of Bill, do you order the new stamps.?



O.P.	I shall start it, before amendmts. discussed in Cttee. stage : but I can’t say so.



W.M.	Wd. it not be better to tell Parlt. you can’t order until Bill is passed and use that as lever to get Bill passed before Xmas.



R.A.B.	I have offered to stand cost of beginning to pay as soon as books are ready, even tho’ stamps are not ready.



O.P.	The limit then is capacity of my offices to issue new books.  And Feb/Mar. is our heavy period for sickness.



H.A.	Pass legn. by Xmas : increase assce. rates in Jan : then we cd. hold pension posn. until end/April.

	Then we can claim we have not delayed a day.

	Ford.  Stats. show expre. by o.a.p. is rising beyond rise in its cost.

	E.g. milk : same as natl. average : and butter more : meat &amp; eggs less than nat. average : tea is down absolutely but still about nall. average.  Position of o.a.p. generally is surprisingly good.  But it includes those on assistce. and those who aren’t.



R.A.B.	Ready to consider further cost on contns. if O.P. cd. advance his date.



W.	No evce. tht. there is much hardship.  Fact tht. o.a.p. are buying butter vice margarine proves it.

	Politically, v. desirable to pass Bill before Xmas.

	Useful also if dates for assistance &amp; w. pensions cd. be advanced.



P.M.	My only fear is that we may lose pol. advantage of increase.



D.E.	Poorest will benefit only by increased Assce.  Easier to hold posn. if theirs comes in earlier.  Any chance of expediting that?



O.P.	Can’t put pressure on Bd.  They don’t want to yield to clamour &amp; don’t wish to consider it before next normal mtg.

	When their decn. is taken, I can press them for earliest possible introdn. of new rates.



H.C.	Caveat on Phillips Rpt.  To get this thro’ before Xmas, will have to do it in 3 days in each House.  Can we go on saying : “wait for P. Rpt” – if that is not going to be available until early December.



O.P.	Will be signed : we cd. say we have considered it.



RAB.	We shall get it before announcemt.  Have told St. Office it must then have 1st. priority.  Mght get it printed before 2nd. Rdg.



H.C.	Can’t be sure this Bill will go thro’ w’out Oppn. obstruction.



P.M.	That wd. let us out, on the political argument.



	P.M.	Record Cab. desire tht. Bill be passed before Xmas.

                   *		Let Leaders of Houses report next week wtr that wd. be 	possible &amp; what wd. be involved.



Sal.	Avoid impn. of hysterical hurry, wh. wd. imply tht. Govt. were unduly influenced by political motives.



                   *	Agreed :	M/N.I. authorised to proceed with prepn. of Bill.



K.	On time-table : operation shd. be at earliest moment administly. possible.  Discard argument tht. later opern. wd. be better because nearest. G. Election.



O.P.	My earliest safe date is 27/4.



		Time-table approved, subject to earlier passage of Bill.  Admve. 	measures to proceed at greatest speed consistent with avoiding 	adminve. breakdown.





		3.	Defence Programme.



H.M.	As Def. Wh. Paper won’t be publd. until Feby., must have earlier announcemt. on AA Command, infantry battns., R.A.A.F.

	Sooner done, more money saved.  But if we announce may invite demands for debate, on adjournment or otherwise.  L.P.S. therefore suggests tht., instead, a phrase be inserted in Queen’s Speech, &amp; announce it in Debate on Address.  Wd. only involve 10 days’ delay, from R.A.B.’s point of view.



 



</content>
</cab>
