<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/12/18 images: 320-323</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC Mil JEST Y&apos;8 GOVERNMENTTO i8E 1JMBISR LOOK AKIB KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this doonment.MOST   SECRET.COPY NO.(40) 84th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 5,Confidential Annexe(8th April, 1940).SUPREME WARCOUNCIL -6TH MEETING.Royal marine operation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 82ndConclusions,Minute 6.)THE SECRETARY OP STATE POP FOREIGN affairs read to the War Cabinet a letter from His Majesty&apos;ambassador, Paris, in which Sir Ronald Campbell gavefurther particulars regarding the circumstances inwhich the proposal relating to the Royal marine operation had been shelved at the request of theFrench Government.     This letter might be summarisedas follows:-M. Daladier had at first shown signs ofplaying the game,   but it was not long before his vindictiveness had gained theupper hand.      It was clear that he was nowdetermined to embarrass M. Reynaud in every possible way.     His refusal of M. Reynaud:invitation to dine with him to meet theFirst Lord of the Admiralty had been bad;but still worse had been his action inputting about the rumour that M. reynaud had agreed at the meeting of the supreme war Council in London to a course of actiondangerous to France.       It was generally believed that the leakage in the french press regarding the Royal Marine Operation-was due either to M* Daladier or to a memberof his entourage.     The Royal marine operation was now being freely spoken of inthe lobbies of the French Chamber.     It mustbe remembered that M. Daladier was a peasant,and that he had all the bad, as well as allthe good qualities of the stock from which hehad sprung.Sir Ronald Campbell added that it did not much matter what Government was in power inFrance,provided that M. Daladier and M.Reynaud were both members of it.     He could see no possibility * however? of any permanentreconciliation between these men, who were divided not only by acute differences ofpolitical questions, but also on privatepersonal matters.




</content>
</cab>
