<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/38/12 images: 106-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Jo,SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 262.23rd June, 1943.WAR CABINET.POST-WAR CIVILIAN AIR TRANSPORT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.I am not sure that the proposed definition of &apos;&apos; Freedom of the Air &apos;&apos; asunderstood by the United Kingdom Government (W.P. (43) 251, Annex C,paragraph 4) is a practical one. It includes in freedom of the air&quot; the rightto land passengers and freight but not the right to pick them up, which is to be reserved to separate bilateral negotiation. But surely the right to land passengers and freight is worthless unless accompanied by the corresponding right to pickup and so maintain a full pay load. We are, in fact, proposing to concede nothingexcept innocent passage and the right to land for refuelling and repairs. If so,would it not be better to say so outright ? That would be a definite and intelligiblepolicy.2. On the other hand, I doubt whether so restrictive an interpretation of&quot; freedom of the air &quot; would appeal to the Americans or be to our own interest.The geographical distribution of the British Empire round the periphery of themain land mass of the Old World affords a wonderful opportunity for picking uptraffic on the way from one point of the Empire to another. I should have thoughtthat, so long as we can make certain of reserving the internal traffic of the Empireto Empire services, it was to our interest to secure the widest possibleinterpretation of &quot; freedom of the air,&quot; and to include in the proposed convention the right to discharge and pick up traffic from and for all destinations save thoseinternal to the territories of the signatory Power.3. This reservation of the right of &quot; cabotage &quot; will anyhow be insisted upon by America, Russia and most other countries. In our case we shall want to make certain that it covers the internal traffic of the Empire. This can be done, withoutemphasising it as a purely Empire policy, by stipulating that any two or morecountries shall be free to make arrangements for &quot; reciprocal cabotage,&quot; i.e., fortreating their territories jointly as a field for internal traffic. This would beanalogous to a customs union in matters of commerce. It would not only suitourselves, enabling us to bring countries like Norway, Egypt, Iraq, &amp;c, into ourEmpire traffic scheme, but would also leave the United States free to make similar arrangements with Mexico and other American countries, or France free to make arrangements with Belgium or Holland. It would not preclude Canada makingspecial arrangements with the United States for traffic across their commonborder or South Africa doing the same with the adjoining Portuguese or Belgiancolonies, or our making special arrangements with France or Belgium.4. I would therefore recommend that we should from the outset advocatea more extended definition of &quot; freedom of the air &quot; to cover, not only free transitand right of refuelling, but also the right to land and pick up cargo from andfor all foreign destinations subject only to the reservation of internal traffic,whether by an individual signatory Power or between any two or more signatoryPowers by joint agreement.L. S. A.India Offtce,.23rd June, 1943.[25610],Printed for the War Cabinet.  June 1943.






</content>
</cab>
