<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/187/10 images: 221-230</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THE POST-ENTRY UNION SHOPMemorandum by the Lord Privy seal. Following the repeal of the Industrial Relations Act 1971 and theintroduction of our own Industrial relations legislation, the National staff side are pressing for formal discussions on the application of the closed shop principle to the non-industrial Civil Service,    The attitude of theunions has not been formally disclosed; but it is understood to vary as tothe rigour with which they would want to apply closed shop arrangements,though all are thinking in terms of a post-entry arrangement and allprofess, as their main objective, the prevention of &apos;!free-riders&quot; (thosewho enjoy the benefits secured by unions without accepting the obligations of membership).    The attitude of the unions representing industrial civilservants is not known.2.        The annex to this paper sets out the views of officials.    Theyconsider that for the Civil Service the closed shop raises very seriousissues of 1 &quot;politic!sation&quot; and conflicting loyalties.    The majority ofPermanent Secretaries believe that the only way to avoid these dangers is torefuse to admit the principle from the outset.3.        My own view is that it would be difficult for the Government to refuseto negotiate since it is our legislation which has opened the way, and we havebeen taking a strong line In Parliament about editors.    It would, however,be essential for any arrangement to protect civil servants against conflictsof loyalties between their duty as civil servants and their obligations to theirunion.4.        On the other hand, it is clear that:i, A closed shop arrangement will increase the power and influence of the unions, some of which are political in outlook,ii. There will be strong feelings against compulsory unionmembership among many civil servants.C(76) 10 COPY NO 316 February 1976CABINET
iii. There will be strong and divided public opinion on the pointsiv. The 1bsue is one which is of considerable interest to theOpposition Parties.5.        I believe, therefore, that it would be right to open the subject to public debate.    The proposal to submit the issue of political activities ofcivil servants to an independent enquiry (see my memorandum C(76) 9)gives us the opportunity to do this by asking the Committee of Enquiry alsoto consider the closed shop issue in the Civil Service,    There is onedifference in the trade union position.    In the case of political activitiesthey want the enquiry, but this is unlikely to be so with the closed shop.They will probably object that a reference to the Committee will delaymatters and some are committed to report to their Conferences in the spring.    They will no doubt also express their willingness to give bindingundertakings not to use a closed shop for &quot;political&quot; purposes, though howfar such undertakings could be railed upon in practice may be open to question,    I consider that an independent look at the closed shop in theCivil Service is the best way of dealing with a contentious and very difficultissue of wide potential public interest.recommendation.        If my colleagues agree that an independent Committee of Enquiry beset up to look into the question of political activities of civil servants, i recommend that the issue of the post-entry union shop in the Civil Servicebe put to the same Committee.    If this is agreed, we shall have toconsider carefully the composition of the Committee.    It will need to be widely representative, and the trade union point of view will have to be reflected in the membership,civil Service Department5 February 19762
ANNEXPOST ENTRY UNION SHOPMemorandum by the Civil Service DepartmentIntroductionCurrent industrial relations legislation permits employers andtrade unions to agree that defined groups of employees must be members of a specified trade union.    Impending legislation willprovide that under such an agreement an employee can in law be fairly dismissed solely because he is not a member of the,specified trade union, unless he has an objection to joiningwhich is based on narrowly-defined religious grounds.   There isno legal compulsion on employers to enter into such agreements,and agreements of a less far-reaching nature are equallypermissible.The Union Position2.       The National Staff Side has approached the Official Sideabout the negotiation of a post entry union shop (PEUS)agreement in the non-industrial Civil Service, which wouldrequire civil servants (including those already serving) to joina specified union after being recruited to the Civil Service.The National Staff Side envisages a framework agreement withinwhich individual unions will be able to negotiate their owndetailed arrangements.3.       Within the Staff Side, the constituent unions are not entirely agreed on the precise nature of the PEUS arrangements to be applied.   The Civil and Public Services Association (CPSA)are committed by a Conference resolution to a full union shop,with exclusion only of religious objectors and requiring the dismissal of non-members.   Some other unions would be content with less far-reaching arrangements.   The National Staff Side,however, will expect to negotiate a framework agreement whichwould permit virtually all the various shades of PEUS.   It ispossible that at least the CPSA would be prepared to back itsclaim by some form of industrial action.1
The Staff Side Case4.       The main arguments likely to be deployed by the staff side are as follows&quot;:i. Civil Service unions primarily seek the elimination of &quot;free riders&quot; - those who enjoy the benefits secured&quot;by unions without making any financial or other contributionA BBtTS *is the only affective way of dealing with thisii. ; -the principle of the closed shop is increasinglywidely accepted and has been endorsed, at least: implicitly*, by the present Government in removing thelegal barriers to its introduction.   There is nothing:,aai /bite nature of the Civil Service which rules it out;iii. Civil Service unions are responsible and democraticbodies and would not abuse their power by deliberatelyexpelling individuals in order to secure their dismissalf!rGm&apos;the Service   (or by threatening to do so).j;^v Underlying the &quot;free rider&quot; argument is the fact that a jTclqs.ed ,shop would enable the unions to bring more effective :&apos;-pressure to bear on the Government in industrial disputes.   This.,..woyld be so however much the trade unions might disavow it as,,a. motive..-&apos;       it..The Issues for Governmentm6fUi &quot;In^ihinsidering these this paper is not concerned with the^iflS-lW Sf^he&apos;closed Shop as a general principle but only with&quot;%neaiitS!&amp;B^&amp;on9whether the Government aB employer and civilSM^vantliPemployees are different from other employers and^[pio^B%8 ^^a&amp; &apos;eirtent which makes a closed shop inappropriate&quot; ^* ^ &apos;^^3^s&quot; ^6SS^3i.y: a&amp;c^pt^a -that the. Civil Service should be,1 antTsfeiiTl tre^Veeif-Wtoe, completely non-political and should beM$$F&amp; &amp;&amp;fckfi&amp; &amp;\1&amp;(lgbtf&amp;im0Dto of the day.   These principles
CONFIDENTIALare fundamental to our system,of Government and must not becompromised.   Would a move to a union shop do so?   Unionisationas such is not a problem: it has long been official managementpolicy to encourage civil servants to join the appropriaterecognised union and this policy has been consistentlymaintained even though the unions themselves sometimes adoptpolitical attitudes and express opposition to the policies ofthe government of the day.   Most Civil Service unions areaffiliated to the TUC (which is identified, and identifiesitself, with one Party); it has been generally accepted thatthey should ,be free to play a part in the national trade union organisation as such, though some people already regardaffiliation as casting doubt on the political neutrality ofthe Civil Service generally, especially since some of the unions have begun to indulge in public criticism of government policies.8.      It could be argued that compulsory union membership wouldnot cast any more doubt on the political neutrality of theService than does the present widespread voluntary membership.   .But many would see a considerable difference between arrangements which leave the individual with a free choice and any form of compulsory membership agreed with the unions; and would regard the latter as seriously undermining the confidence of thepublic in the willingness of the Civil Service to carry out without question the policies of the government of the day.For civil servants loyalty to the government of the day andavoidance of conflict between public and all other interests are part of an essential code of conduct.   So long as staff aresimply encouraged to join trade unions, they retain full freedom to disagree with them on matters affecting the observance ofthat code.   But any form of closed shop, because it is bound to restrict the freedom to disagree, would create a potentialconflict between loyalty to the union and loyalty to theGovernment.9.      This difficulty would be greatly increased if the tradeunions sought to use a FEUS to secure the dismissal of individuals who remained loyal to the Government in an3.
r^fei^^ ^IS&amp;reme forms.   It is not inconceivable that some^toX^Sj    *otla c?uld o*w day try to bring pressureswajMnia through industrial action in order to influence broad political policies; or on individual civilM^eJTOp*l . ^trfcry to the interests of the Government.Zt \* ^P^l^d^t&quot;&quot;to impetus for a union shop comes^yfe &apos;(^:y^j^ most politically motivated trade^A&apos;imm^r9&amp;j created substantial problems in the DHSSindustrial dispute by expelling them from the union.   Moreover,the temptation to act in this way might extend beyond thenormal industrial dispute to matters of general policy onwhich the unions might want to challenge the Government.   Thedividing line between issues affecting working conditions and general policy is often very difficult to draw, eg inrelation to dispersal questions, or policy changes requiringsubstantial overtime.10.     Insofar as the purpose of a closed shop is to adjust thebalance of power between management and employees, it creates &apos;constitutional problems in the Civil Service because in a realsense it is ultimately Ministers who are the employers and allcivil servants, including the highest grades, the employees.In practice the power of Civil Service unions to representthe legitimate interests of their members through agreedprocedures is already very considerable and certainly greaterjthan that of many other unions.   There is no real imbalance of power to redreBs.   It is clear that some trade unions alreadydo, or will at some stage, aee PEUS as a means of bringingadditional pressure not so much on the management of the CivilService as on Government policies of all kinds and thereforedirectly on Ministers.   This could encroach unacceptably onTitiriisterial freedom and responsibilities.a 11.     Too much reliance should not be placed on theflit ^f^*^a*ively degree of responsibility and political,      da ac^*nt &quot;still &quot;characteristic of much of the Civil Servicetrade union movement.   There is a tendency towards greaterE^mi itBBfidr--*ta   political activism and this could in the future
12.     A consideration of a different order is that many civilservants would resent the element of coercion in a PBUS andthis feeling would be shared by important sections of publicopinion.   The result would almost certainly be a public debate in which the two issues of politicisation and &quot;freedom ofconscience&quot; could come together to the detriment of thepolitical impartiality, morale and efficiency of the Service.13.     There are also serious implications for management giventhe way Government Departments are organised.    In the private sector the dividing, line between workpeople and management is usually clear and the latter are hardly unionised.   In theCivil Service the dividing line is much less clear.   In practice it could be drawn at different levels in different situations.But the management category would normally begin at HEO levelwhere the unions have, of courset both effective representationand full negotiating rights.   This continues to apply up toAssistant Secretary, above which there is representation (but nonegotiating rights) on pay up to Permanent Secretary level.   at these higher levels a PEUS could create particularly acutedifficulties for both senior civil servants and their Ministers.14.     A PEUS could affect recruitment adversely by discouragingrecruits of good quality who might object to it.   It is alsoopen to the objection that for the first time it would imposeconditions on entry to Crown service which had nothing to do with the individual^ suitability for that service.Views of Permanent Secretaries15. Permanent Secretaries and Principal Establishment officers have been consulted on the issue.   A considerable majority feel*strongly that the considerations set out above mean that theproposal to introduce a PEUS into the Civil Service should be rejected in order to avoid jeopardising the whole tradition ofimpartiality and loyalty to the government of the day on whichthe British Civil Service is based and on which successive5
Governments have relied and should be able to continue to rely.   They also believe that a FEUS would add to the powerof the Civil Service trade unions to an extent and in a way that could significantly affect Ministerial freedom of actionin Government and in present circumstances add to the criticism that the Civil Service is an unduly privilegedbody which posseses too much power.16.     If Ministers agree, there remains the question whetherthis implies the outright rejection of any form of FEUS, orwhether there are alternative possibilities which would go some way to remove the difficulties foreseen.   The main onesare:i.    : a FEUS could be accepted subject to conditionsdesigned to reduce the difficulties over&quot;politicisation&quot; and conflicting loyalties.   For\       example, the trade unions might be required to give an undertaking not to affiliate to political parties and to refrain from particular types of politicalaction,   it might be possible, though there would be considerable difficulties of definition, to protect the individual against attempts to bring political pressure to bear on him and to act disloyally to the- Government.   Staff above a certain level, eg at leastwithin, the open structure (ie Under Secretary and above), and probably even below, would have to be excluded.   An appeals procedure to ensure the observance of these safeguards would no doubt benecessary.05&apos;  ^ &apos;less far-reaching scheme short of an actualjd? &amp;s:i FBUBvt;ould be offered which would go a long way towards^   ?  meeting the &quot;free rider&quot; point but would overcome manyTcirt of the objections of principle by dropping compulsoryunion membership and the resulting penalty of dismissal-of: non-membership.   There would be an arrangement under
m iT&quot;fr*T&quot;which, all civil servants would he required to pay dues tothe appropriate union but would be free to remain non-members if they wished.   But for serving civil servants,since there is no power to enforce payment of asubscription, some other effective sanction would benecessary.   It is difficult to see what this could be other than dismissal for non-payment.iii. Both these courses would in varying degree be criticised as requiring some individuals to act contraryto their beliefs or conscience.   This element could bereduced in each case if the arrangement was confined to new recruits (for whom the requirement to make a contribution would be a condition of service); though bythe same token it would take a very long time to solve the&quot;free rider&quot; problem; and the existence side by Bide of employees with differing obligations in relation to theunions would itself create problems.iv. A further possible course would be a variation of 11. above which would allow individuals the additionalfree choice of contributing the equivalent of their uniondues to a charity or any one of a series of charities,jointly designated by the Official Side&apos;and the union.Prom the point of view of many civil servants and perhapsfrom the broader stance too of outside opinion, there wouldbe considerable advantage in this course.   It wouldcompletely meet the criticism that individuals were gainingthe advantages brought about by the union for the CivilService without themselves being out of pocket to theextent of union subscription, while it would meet the criticism that would apply even to course ii. above aswell as to course i. about the element of eithercompulsory membership or compulsory contribution to a union, with the political implications that would be involved thereby.7
7which all civil servants would be required to pay dues tothe appropriate union but would be free to remain non-members if they wished.   But for serving civil servants,since there is no power to enforce payment of asubscription, some other effective sanction would benecessary.    It is difficult to see what this could be other than dismissal for non-payment.iii. Both these courses would in varying degree be criticised as requiring some individuals to act contraryto their beliefs or conscience.   This element could bereduced in each case if the arrangement was confined to new recruits (for whom the requirement to make a contribution would be a condition of service); though bythe same token it would take a very long time to solve the&quot;free rider&quot; problem; and the existence side by side of employees with differing obligations in relation to theunions would itself create problems.iv. A further possible course would be a variation of 11. above which would allow individuals the additionalfree choice of contributing the equivalent of their uniondues to a charity or any one of a series of charities,jointly designated by the Official Side and the union.From the point of view of many civil servants and perhapsfrom the broader stance too of outside opinion, there wouldbe considerable advantage in this course.   It wouldcompletely meet the criticism that individuals were gainingthe advantages brought about by the union for the CivilService without themselves being out of pocket to theextent of union subscription, while it would meet the criticism that would apply even to course ii. above aswell as to course i. about the element of eithercompulsory membership or compulsory contribution to a union, with the political implications that would heinvolved thereby.

</content>
</cab>
