<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/122/0 images: 250-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1965C. (65) 108 Copy No.23rd July, 1965CABINETSOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS AND INCOME GUARANTEEMemorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster i was invited by the Cabinet, in consultation with the Secretaryof State for Scotland, the Secretary of State for Wales, the Secretaryof State for Education and Science, the Minister of Housing, theMinister of Pensions and National Insurance and the Chief Secretaryto consider in the light of the Cabinefs discussion alternative policies in relation to benefits and assistance within the financial limits of the basic and additional programmes proposed in C. (65) 101.(C.C. (65) 38th Conclusions, Minute 3.)2. Introduction of graduated short-term benefits and income guarantee in October 1966 with periodical increases in benefits and assistance in line with the assumed increase in earnings (i.e.,fulfilment of all three pledges) would lead to expenditure in excessof the Ministry of Pensions&apos; basic and additional programmesproposed in C. (65) 101 as follows:1966-671967-681969-70Amounts by which expenditure would&quot;exceed basic programme  million20115\    140Amounts allowedas additional programme inC. (65) 101  million142560Amount by which expenditure would exceed additionaland basic programmestogether  million69080Not only would there be this substantial excess expenditure butthere would be nothing to meet the cost of other improvements which may be necessary in the period, e.g., for widows.The courses open to us n3. Discussion by ; the\ Committee of Ministers under my chairmanship has shown that&quot;&apos;there are only three courses open to
us if we are to keep within the limits of the basic and additionalprogrammes allocated in C. (65) 101.Course (A). To drop income guarantee; retain graduatedshort-term benefits; and increase benefits in relation to earnings.Course (B). To retain graduated short-term benefits and income guarantee, but to increase benefits on the nextoccasion by a substantially smaller amount than wouldbe required by the movement of earnings.Course (C). To defer graduated short-term benefits, while retaining income guarantee and increasing benefits on thenext occasion by a somewhat lower amount than wouldbe required by the movement of earnings.4. The Committee took the view the Chairman dissenting that it was not within their remit to reconsider the necessity of introducing wage-related unemployment, and therefore also of sickness, benefit in October 1966. Accordingly this Memorandumexamines the financial and other implications of Courses A and Bonly. The assumptions underlying the figures are given in the annex to the Memorandum.Implications of the alternative courses5.   Course (A).   This alternative involves:Wage-related short-term benefits introduced in October1966.NO income guarantee.Benefits and assistance rise with earnings:April 1966National assistance increased by 5s. in line with assumedincrease of money earnings.June 1967(a) Retirement pensions increased by 11s. in line withassumed increase of money earnings, and otherinsurance benefits and war pensions increasedcorrespondingly.(b) National assistance increased by further 6s. in line with assumed increase of money earnings.April 1969Insurance benefits, war pensions and national assistance in line with increase in money earningssince April 1965.Margin for further expenditure ( 4- ) as compared withannual limits specified in C. (65)101 :  million1966-671967-681969-70-f 5015-1- 20
6.  The principal considerations arising on this Course are:(a) Dropping the income guarantee would be a breach of an unconditional pledge in the Election Manifesto, whereit alone was specifically excepted from the proviso thatimprovements in social security benefits must depend onthe rate at which the economy could advance. Therehas been much Parliamentary probing on the income guarantee and the election pledge has been repeatedoften since. It was described as a &quot; must &quot; in a speech which I made in the House of Commons. In particular,heavy reliance was placed on the early introduction ofthe guarantee in opposing Mr. Airey Neave&apos;s Bill toprovide pensions for old people who had not contributed.The Minister of Pensions said income guarantee wouldbe introduced &quot; as quickly as possible &quot;.(b) On the other hand, the income guarantee scheme has turned out different from that held out at the time of the election and the level of guarantee may be less than was envisaged.This, however, is not only a question of finance. Thelevel could not be set much higher without endangeringthe objective of a half-pay pension scheme which wouldmake the income guarantee unnecessary. Thus, theproposed level of guarantee for a married couple with no children of about  7 plus rent, assuming a rent of 30s.,would, even without disregarded income, be more than half the take-home pay of a man on average earnings.(c) The Ministry&apos;s enquiry into the resources of old people willdraw public attention to the extent of &quot; hidden poverty &quot;among those eligible for national assistance but notclaiming it. This will bring fresh odium on national assistance as such. However, it should be possible toremodel national assistance so as to improve its image byimporting some of the administrative improvementsplanned for income guarantee, e.g., a change in the name,a written return of income, payment on a single orderbook with retirement pension, and some reduction ofvisiting. Possibly also some preferential rate might begiven to those who have been living or are likely to beliving for a long time on national assistance this couldbe afforded within the expenditure limit by a smallabatement in the general increase of national insurance benefits.(d) The contribution increase required for an increase in benefits of 11s. a week would be Is. lid. for the employed man with a similar extra amount from his employer if thewhole extra cost were met from the flat-rate contribution(apart from the normal Exchequer supplement). the increases in the flat-rate contribution would, however, be diminished to the extent that the extra expenditure couldbe financed from extra graduated contributions, and the
Committee concluded that, under this Course, it would benecessary to consider at the time the possibility of meetingthe cost of the benefit increase wholly or in part fromgraduated contributions.7.   Course (B).   This would involve:Wage-related short-term benefits introduced in October1966Income guarantee introduced in October 1966Benefit rates rise less than earnings:October 1966National assistance increased by 7s. in line withassumed increase in money earnings.June 1967(a) Retirement pensions increased by 5s. in line withassumed increase in prices and other insurance benefits and war pensions increased corre-correspondingly.(b) National assistance increased by further 4s. in line with money earnings.April 1969(c) Insurance benefits and war pensions increased in line with increase in money earnings since June1967 but ground lost up to then not made up.(d) National assistance in line with increase in moneyearnings since April 1965.Margin for further expenditure 1 + ) or excess of expenditure(-) as compared with annual limits specified inC. (65) 101:  million1966-67       ......      +101967-68       ......      -151969-70       ......      +208.   Considerations arising on this alternative are:(a) The Manifesto promised that &quot; Existing National insurance benefits will be raised and thereafter linked to average earnings &quot;. Now that the Government has raised benefits,people will expect that benefits will continue to go up atthe same rate as earnings. Between 1951 and 1964 benefitswent up rather faster than earnings, and especially soafter 1958. But the increase of benefits which could bemade in 1967 within the expenditure ceiling would, onthe assumed movement of prices and earnings, be limitedto 5s. a week which would compensate for the fall in thevalue of money only and would compare with theincrease of 11s. needed to keep benefits in line with the assumed movement of earnings. It is assumed so limited
a rise could not apply to assistance which would therefore have to go up in line with earnings. Apart from the somewhat derisory appearance of such a small increasein benefits, there would be criticism that the Governmentwere doing less than expected for such people as widows,the long-term sick, the lower-paid who become sick orunemployed, war pensioners and those injured at work,in order to give yet better benefits for old peoplequalifying for guarantee payments and for the betterpaid among the younger people who become unemployedor sick. An incidental consequence of this course wouldbe a continuing increase in the numbers on income guarantee and assistance.(b) A benefit increase of 5s. would, if financed solely on the flat-rate contribution with the proportionate exchequer supplement, necessitate an increase in the employedman&apos;s contribution of lOd. with a matching contribution from his employer, as compared with the Is. lid. a sideneeded on the same basis to finance a benefit increase of11s. related to the assumed movement of earnings. Therestriction on the increase in benefits under this Courseassumes that the limitation on expenditure is not affectedby the fact that benefit increases are mainly financed from contributions.Committee&apos;s conclusions . On the premise that graduated short-term benefits are anessential constituent of the programme, the Committee were agreed the Chairman dissenting in recommending Course A to theCabinet (which means discarding income guarantee; introducinggraduated short-term benefits in October 1966; and increasingbenefits in 1967 in line with the movement of earnings together witha remodelling of national assistance as far as may prove possible).10. The Chairman dissented both from the premise on whichthe Committee&apos;s recommendation was reached (that graduatedshort-term benefits were an essential part of the programme) andfrom the recommendation itself. He considers that income guaranteeis an essential constituent of the programme both because of theunqualified pledges given and because it would concentrate theavailable resources where they are most needed.D. H.70 Whitehall, S.W.1,23rd July, 1965.
AnnexAssumptions Underlying the Figures of Benefit Rates andExpenditure under the Alternative programmes.   It has been assumed that:(1) Real earnings rise by 3-6 per cent a year; money earningsrise by 6\ per cent in 1965-66, and by a further 6 per centin 1966-67; prices rise by nearly 3 per cent in 1965-66 andby 2-2- per cent in 1966-67.(2) Wage-related short-term benefits would cost about  55 million a year. The figure of  45 million given in C. (65) 101allowed for wage-related supplements to unemployment and sickness benefit only. A further  5 million is needed to accommodate wage-related supplements to injurybenefit, as proposed by the Minister of Pensions and national Insurance; and  2 million because of theproposal that the weekly earnings on which benefit isbased shall be one-fiftieth of the previous year&apos;s earningsto compensate for the time-lag since the reference period.The resulting figure has been rounded up to  55 million.(3) Income guarantee would entail an additional cost of about 100 million a year.2. The costings should not be taken as precise. For example,benefit increases cannot be accurately related to the movement of earnings, which cannot be precisely known when rates are fixed;and benefit rates must in any event be rounded amounts. A difference of Is. on the retirement pension with corresponding variations inother benefits makes a difference of nearly  25 million a year. the true cost of wage-related benefit may also be different from theestimate if earnings prove to have risen more than was allowed forin the estimate or if unemployment is running above the level (1-5per cent) assumed in the public expenditure exercise. Moreover the precise timing of benefit and assistance increases must be I.eft open.



</content>
</cab>
