<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/122/0 images: 356-381</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(65) 11223rd July, 1965COPY NO.59CABINETEARNINGS-RELATED SHORT-TERM 3ENEFITSMemorandum by the Minister of Pensions and national InsurancePART I - INTRODUCTORYIn February I was invited to submit to the Social services committee proposals for an interm scheme of earnings-related short-term benefits which could be brought into operation by the Autumn of1966 in advance of the general review of the national insurancescheme.    These proposals have been under consideration by theSocial Services Sub-Committee on Social Security Cash Benefits andalthough discussions are continuing on matters of detail the stagehas now been reached where it is both possible and, in view of the time factor, essential for me to seek the authority of the Cabinet to proceedwith the type of scheme which, in the light of the Sub-Committee&apos;discussion, I now propose.2.      The main features of the proposed scheme, which would coversickness as well as unemployment, are:-(i)   earnings-related supplements would be at the rate of onethird of average weekly earnings between  9 and  30(paragraph 10) j(ii)   the supplements would be paid in addition to the personalbenefit and dependency allowances payable under the flat-rate scheme up to a limit of 85 per cent of gross earnings(paragraph 10);(iii) average weekly earnings would be the gross earningsassessable to P. A. Y. E. tax in the tax year preceding the claim to benefit divided by 50 (paragraph 13);(iv) no allowances would be made for interruptions of earnings in the relevant tax year (paragraph 14);(v)   the maximum duration of earnings-related supplementswould be six months; for this purpose spells of sickness and unemployment separated by less than thirteen weekswould be aggregated (paragraph 15);(vi)   there would be twelve &quot;absolute&quot; waiting days forearnings-related supplements (paragraph 16);-1-

(vii)   contracted-out employees, and their employers, would be liable for graduated contributions for pensions and short-term benefits at the same rates as everyone else and theircontracted-out status would in future be recognised by anabatement of their flat-rate contributions and retirement pension (paragraph 23) j(viii)   the minimum cost of the scheme including administrationcosts would be of the order of  50 million (paragraph 24);(ix)   the scheme would be financed by additional graduated contributions but the proceeds of the flat-rate abatementplan for the contracted-out would be applied to reduceflat-rate contributions (paragraph 26);(x)   about 2, 000 extra staff may be needed in the Ministry ofPensions and National Insurance and about 800 in theMinistry of Labour (paragraph 27).PART II - AIMS AND ASSUMPTIONSGeneral3.      These proposals must be judged by reference to certainfundamental considerations of policy.    We made it clear in our election Manifesto that the rate at which we could carry out improve-ments in social security would have to depend on the progress of the economy.    The need to keep additional expenditure to the minimumconsistent with the provision of an acceptable and worthwhile schemeis borne out in the present proposals which fall short of those I shouldhave been making had the financial situation permitted more radical changes.    The scale of benefit is no better than that under discussionlast year by the previous Government with both sides of industry andthe proposals as they now stand represent in my view the bare minimumfor a worthwhile scheme.Timetable4.     If it is decided to go ahead with an interim scheme for operation from the Autumn of 1966 there is only just enough time available for the work to be done.    The Bill would have to be passedby the end of March 1966, not only to allow time for the subsequentstages (regulation-making, preparation of working procedures,printing, recruitment and training of staff, etc. ) but also to ensurethat employers and employees retain the tax documents relating tothe income tax year 1965/66 which will be needed to support claims under the new scheme when it starts.   The legislation will be complicated and Parliamentary Counsel should be instructed as soonss possible after the main outline of the scheme has been approved and concurrently with the discussions about the broad details of it which I shall need to hold with the Trades Union Congress, the confederation of British Industries and other interested bodies.Delay in any of these stages would prejudice the chance of startingthe scheme in the following Autumn.-2-

The need for simplificatiqr^5.       I am concerned about the complexity of the existing national insurance scheme, and the burden it imposes on the local officers ofboth my Department and the Ministry of Labour, on employers and onthe general public.     The introduction of earnings-related short-term benefits will add to the existing burden the task of working out a personal benefit rate for each claimant based on hie individualearnings.    Although the proposed scheme must inevitably causeemployers considerable additional work, it makes the minimumpossible disturbance to their existing pay and record arrangements.I feel this is important, not only to avoid saddling employers with agood deal of additional cost for work not directly related to their business, but also because we shall need the ready co-operation ofemployers to make the scheme work at all.    We can only expect this connection-operation if we can demonstrate that we have done our best to minimise the additional burdens on them.Implications of earnings-related benefits6.     Much of the criticism of flat-rate benefits relates to the levelof the personal rate of benefit (at present  4) in relation to the needsof the higher-paid worker faced with a sudden a.nd substantial drop in income during unemployment or sickness.    Critics of the present scheme do not always appreciate that, for the lower-paid workerwith a family, flat-rate benefit already provides a high proportion of normal earnings - at least as high as most earnings-related schemes in other countries.    For example, a married man with four children who is earning  12 a week can get a national insurance weeklybenefit (excluding family allowances) of  9. ,16s. - nearly 90 per cent of his take-home pay.    Clearly, the scope for giving additional help to such workers is limited and the larger benefits of the new scheme must inevitably go to those with relatively high earnings and relatively few family responsibilities.     This shift of emphasis isinseparable from earnings-relation and the aim must be to strike areasonable balance between the earnings-related element and the family-related element in the total benefit.7.     Li the long run, the answer may lie in radical changes in theprovision v/e make for children through family allowances and incometax so that more help is given to the low wage-earner with a largefamily whether he is at work or not.    Such changes could not,however, be contemplated as part of an interim scheme of earnings-related short-term benefits for operation next year, and the new scheme has had to be made to fit the existing structure.The problem of over-compensation8.      To create a situation where large numbers of sick andunemployed people could get as much, or even more, by way ofnational insurance benefits as they could get by working would be highly undesirable.    It would invite abuse and expose the scheme toridicule.    In extreme cases of low earners with very large familiesthe flat-rate scheme has already reached the point of over-compensa-tion and my colleagues and I v/ere all a.greed that the new scheme,particularly as it will be related to earnings, must not make such a situation widespread.

9.     It was clear from the start that in the absence of radical changes in family allowances a scheme such as proposed in &quot;IMewFrontiers&quot;, under which an earnings-related stipplernent equal toone-quarter of an individuals total earnings would be added to hisflat-rate benefit, would offend against this principle.     we considered the possibility of eliminating or reducing the weekly allowance for a dependent wife of  2. 10s. at present payable underthe flat-rate scheme but concluded that such a radical shift of emphasis from family responsibility to earnings-relation would be politically unacceptable.    I therefore find it necessary to propose a somewhat less generous scale of earnings-related benefit.    although this does not create such a serious over-compensation problem., some financial incentive to get a job is obviously required and it will stillbe necessary to incorporate in the scheme an over-riding benefitmaximum in order to ensure that the earnings-related supplementdoes not bring total benefit above something like 90 per cent of take-home pay (that is, gross earnings less income tax and national insurance contributions).    This will not, however, affect theexisting rights of those who can already get flat-rate benefit inexcess of 90 per cent of take-home pay.PART HI- DETAILS OF THE PROPOSED scheme the benefit formula10.     Within the limits imposed by the considerations referred to inthe first part of this memorandum my aim has been to devise a benefit formula which would give something like half-pay to the singleman on average earnings without producing an acute over-compensation problem for the lower-paid and without giving thehigher-paid a proportionately better benefit than the lower-paid.    Theformula proposed to meet this situation would give an earnings-related supplement of one-third of the amount of gross earnings between  9 and  30 subject to a ceiling where the total benefit(flat-rate personal benefit plus dependency allowances plus supplement)would otherwise exceed about 90 per cent of take-home pay.    (for practical purposes 90 per cent of take-home pay can be expressed as85 per cent of the gross earnings of those affected who pay little or noincome tax. )11.     For the single man on average earnings this formula would produce a total benefit of 51 per cent of take-home pay.    For the single man on higher or lower earnings the proportion would not be significantly different.    The married man with three children would get a proportion of take-home pay ranging from 90 per cent for the worker on  12 a week or less to 65 per cent at the earningsmaximum of  30 a week.    The effect of the benefit ceiling would bethat the  12 a week worker with more than three children would belimited to the rate appropriate to the three-child family.    A fullerrange of examples is given in Appendix A.-4-

12.     The minimum of the reckonable earnings range of  9 is that used for contributions and benefits in the existing graduated pension scheme.    The  13 maximum of the earnings range under that scheme would not, however, provide an acceptable level of benefit for the higher-paid worker.    Although it will probably be desirableeventually to have the same maximum for both short-term benefit and graduated pension purposes, I see no serious difficulty in having a different maximum for the two schemes for the time being.    A  30maximum would cover in full the earnings of well over 90 per cent of employed men and is likely to fit in with long-term developmentsfor pension.Reckonable Earnings13.     The earnings which would count for benefit (and contributions)would be the gross earnings assessable to P. A. Y. E. tax, as alreadydefined for the purpose of the graduated pension scheme.    benefit would be based on earnings in the tax year preceding the claim to benefit.   The benefit ceiling, where this applied, would also be related to the same earnings figure.    In recognition of the fact thatthe current level of earnings may be somewhat higher, I proposethat the amount of average weekly earnings should be arrived at bydividing this annual figure by 50 rather than 52. 18 - equivalent toabout a 4 per cent rise in earnings.    I should have liked to have beenable to base the benefit on earnings in the twelve months precedingeach claim, for benefit but after studying the possibilities in detail Iam convinced that the previous tax year is the only practicablereference period.    My colleagues in the Sub-Committee support thisview.    Any other basis would create an enormous amount ofadditional work for employers without necessarily producing betterresults. /14.     Only actual earnings in the previous tax year vould count for benefit.    Where earnings are reduced by sickness or unemployment(or any other interruption of earnings such as absence abroad or imprisonment) this would be reflected in a lower rate of earnings-related benefit.    This proposal may disappoint some of our supporters particularly as &quot;New Frontiers&quot; indicated that the scheme would make allowance for weeks of sickness and unemployment.The T. U. C. will certainly press for this.     There are three powerfulcounter -arguments: the first is that the principle of deeming earningsis questionable if it means that low wage-earners in regular employ -ment have to subsidise those with higher incomes but a greater riskof unemployment.    Secondly, the flat-rate system under whichcontributions are credited for weeks of sickness and unemploymentwill continue to provide the basic protection during periods of sick-ness and unemployment.    Thirdly - and in the context of an interimscheme this must, I think, be conclusive - a system of allowances for earnings lost as a result of sickness or unemployment in the relevant tax year would be a complication involving considerableextra work.    We shall have acute difficulties in some areas in recruiting sufficient staff to operate even the most straight-forwardscheme of earnings-related benefits by the Autumn of 1966.    Ishould be most reluctant to put the whole scheme in jeopardy for the sake of what is no more than a refinement of the benefit formulahowever desirable it might be if time and resources were not at apremium.    Eventually, with the increasing use of computers in myDepartment, it may be possible to cope with the additional v/orkinvolved should this be thought desirable.

Duration of earnings-related benefit15.     Earnings-related benefit would be paid for up to six months in a &quot;period of interruption of employment&quot; (a period which coversany spells of sickness or unemployment separated by less than13 v/eeks).    Sickness and unemployment would be aggregated for thispurpose so that there v/ould be no advantage to be gained fromdrawing one benefit rather than the other.    It was suggested in &quot;NewFrontiers&quot; that wage-related benefits should cover the first year ofabsence from work.    However,ray colleagues and I thought that a six-month period would be adequate, particularly in an interim scheme,and that to pay earnings-related unemployment benefit for longer than six months might have an adverse effect on the economy indiscouraging unemployed people from seeking or accepting new jobspromptly.    This may also provide the opportunity for some rational -isation of the duration of flat-rate unemployment benefit so that instead of the present variable period of seven to nineteen monthsbased on the claimant&apos;s insurance record these would be six monthsof earnings-related benefit followed by six months of flat-ratebenefit.    Twelve months would thus become the standard maximumdiration of unemployment benefit for everybody.Waiting days16.     For flat-rate benefits, there v/ould, as now, be three&quot;waiting days&quot; at the start of any period of interruption of employment.Benefit is paid for these days if the period of interruption ofemployment lasts for 12 days or more.    For earnings-relatedbenefit, it would be necessary to serve 12 waiting days at the start of a period of interruption of employment.    These waiting dayswould be &quot;absolute&quot;, that is, benefit would not be paid retrospectivelyfor them.    Thus earnings-related benefit would not normally be payable for spells of sickness or unemployment lasting less than a fortnight.17.     My original hope was to be able to treat the flat-rate and earnings-related elements as a single benefit with a standard waitingperiod but the only practicable way to do this would have been by imposing six absolute waiting days for both parts of both benefits.This would have meant a substantial reduction in existing rights toflat-rate benefits.    Most people would have made up on the earnings-related swings what they lost on the flat-rate roundabouts but therewould have been some claimants, especially those with low earnings and large families who would lose more than they gained.    Althoughthe proportion of cases would be relatively small they v/ould be the claimants in greatest need, and my colleagues and I concluded thatthis approach was politically unacceptable.    Without the substantialsaving of both cost and administrative resources which would haveaccrued from not paying flat-rate benefit for the first six days itwould not have been feasible to pay earnings-related benefitswithout a longer waiting period than six days.    It is highly desirable, in order to avoid s.nornaIies a.nd confusion to claimants,that the supplements to both benefits should be governed by thesame conditions, and we concluded that there should be a 12-daywaiting period  or the earnings-related element of both benefits.On this approach, the new scheme can be presented as appropriate to the more serious interruptions of earnings where sickness orunemployment lasts for more than a fortnight.-6-

Consequential Matters18.     There are many detailed aspects of the scheme which arestill under discussion and I should not wish to trouble the cabinet with these matters unless serious differences of opinion were to emerge in the Sub-Committee.    There are, however, two othershort-term benefits which may be affected by the introduction of ascheme of earnings-related sickness and unemployment benefit andthese are, I think, sufficiently important politically to meritconsideration at this stage.Injury Benefit19.     Injury benefit under the Industrial Injuries scheme is payableas an alternative to sickness benefit for the first six months of incapacity resulting from an accident at work or an industrial disease.    The rate has been maintained at about 70 per cent abovestandard sickness benefit since the start of the schemes, and is now 6. 15 s. a week.    Injury benefit is followed by a disablementbenefit in those cases (about 15 per cent) where some measurabledisability remains when injury benefit ceases.    Supplementation of sickness benefit as proposed would mean that sickness benefit wouldbe higher than injury benefit for everyone with earnings of  17. 5 s.or more - that is, on the estimated figures for April, 1965, some56 per cent of men and 1 per cent of women.20.     In my view it would not be sufficient merely to allow injuredpeople to draw the supplemented sickness benefit or injury benefit,whichever was the better.    This would effectively abolish for alarge part of the employed population a preference which hasexisted for very many years (and which is paralleled in nearly every other industrialised country), which wo^^ld be wrong, and would inany case stand no chance of acceptance by the T. U. C.    To my mind the right course, and administratively the simplest one, would be toallow the sickness benefit supplement, where payable, to be addedto flat-rate injury benefit.    The existing  2. 15 s. differentialwould thus be preserved, and this can be justified on the view that it represents the element of compensation for the injury.    It follows that the benefit ceiling for the industrial injury case should be 2. 15s. above that proposed for sickness benefit.    The levels ofbenefit produced by this proposal are shown in Appendix B.    Itwill be noticed that in the range where the benefit ceiling operatesmany beneficiaries are already receiving more by way of flat-rateinjury benefit tha.n the amount allowed by the proposed benefitceiling and this entitlement would be preserved.Widow^s Allowance21.     Widow&apos;s allowance is at present a flat-rate resettlementallowance paid for the first 13 weeks of widowhood  at a higher rate than the standard widow&apos;s benefit.    As &quot;New Frontiers&quot; recognised,there is a case for graduating this allowance by reference to the husband&apos;s earnings and for extending its duration to six months.This would do something positive for widows.    Furthermore, theOpposition^ 1964 Election Manifesto committed them to extending-7-

earnings-related benefit to the early months of widowhood and if ourscheme does not provide for this we can certainly expect an amendmenton Committee which would be difficult to resist.    For all these reasons I should like to include widow&apos;s allowance in the scheme fromthe outset but against this must be reckoned the additional cost - seeparagraph 24 below.    The Sub-Committee considered that theinclusion of widow&apos;s allowance was a desirable, but not essential,feature of the scheme and that the question of its inclusion should bereferred to the Cabinet for decision.C controls  actin g -Out22.     At present employees who are not contracted-out of thenational insurance graduated pension scheme, and their employers,pay both a flat-rate contribution and a graduated contribution(4-J; per cent a side) cn earnings between  9 and  18 a week.Additional graduated contributions will be needed to pay for the newearnings-related benefits but employees who are contracted-out of the graduated pension scheme by virtue of their rights to an occupational pension, and their employers   do not at present pay graduated contributions.    They are, however, required to pay a substantially higher flat-ra.te contribution than that paid by those who are note ont r a ct ed - out.23.   There is no question of excluding employees contracted-out ofthe graduated pension scheme from the new earnings-related short-term benefits but there are compelling reasons against super-Imposingon their flat-rate contribution a very small graduated contribution.Not only would the amount appear derisory and be costly to administerin relation to its yield but once people in contracted-out employment are   required to pay graduated contributions it would be indefensible tomake them go on paying their higher rate of flat-rate contribution which bears heavily and unfairly on the lower-paid contracted-outworker.    Accordingly my coU.ea.colleagues on the Sub-Committee agreed with me that the opportunity should be taken for reshaping the contracting-out arrangements so as to make the contracted-out liableto pay graduated contributions for pensions as well as short-term benefits.    This would have the following advantages:-(a) It would remove present inequities whereby the higher flate-rate contribution payable by the contracted-out imposes an ^^nfairburden on the lower-paid worker and his employer whereas the higher-paid worker is charged too litte.(b) It would ensure that the contracted-out employee enjoyedthe protection which the State scheme provides so far asgraduated retirement pension for widows is concerned(a point we made in our Election Manifesto).(c) It would pave the way for the later introduction of our ownearnings-related pension scheme or for the next generaluprating which is almost bound to require an increase inthe span, if not the rate, of graduated pension contributions.Under this plan the contracted-out would pay the same graduated contributions as everyone else and would earn graduated additions to pension accordingly.    They would, however, pay a lower flate-rate contribution than those not contracted-out and their total State pension-8-

(flat-rate plus graduated) would be abated to take account of this.Both these deductions would be related to the value of the occupational pension which the employer is required to provide as a condition for contracting-out of the State scheme.    The change would involve noalterations in the conditions which at present have to be satisfied byan occupational pension scheme to qualify for contracting-out and nofurther change v/ould be required in these conditions to match futurechanges in the State provisions.Finance24.     The basic cost of a scheme of earnings-related sickness and unemployment benefit on the lines proposed above is estimated at 44 million a year of which some  30 million is attributable to sickness benefit and  14 million to unemployment benefit (assuming 1. 5 per centunemployment).    To this must be added the cost of administration whichmight be of the order of   3 million a.nd a minimum of   l\ million toenable the industrially injured to draw earnings-related sickness benefit instead of injury benefit where this was to the claimantsadvantage.    A further  34 million would be needed to pay earnings -related supplements on top of injury benefit.    The minimum cost ofthe scheme v/ould therefore be of the order of  50 million.    Earnings-related widow&apos;s allowance payable for 6 months instead of the presentflat-rate allowance payable for 3 months would coot about a. further 7 million.25.     The change in the arrangements for contracting-out(paragraphs 22-23 above) v/ould produce additional contribution income of about  43 million a year most of which would come fromhigher-paid workers and their employers, raany of them in the public sector.    This amount is substantially a measure of the extent towhich the higher-paid contracted-out at present escape their fair share of the total cost of national insurance.    Ultimately this change-over will lead to some increased expenditure in the form of extragraduated retirement and widows1 pensions to which contracted-outemployees will become entitled; but in the next few years there willbe no significant expenditure involved.26.     Earnings-related short-term benefits, on the scale proposed,would require a graduated contribution of about 0. 4 per cent a sideof earnings between  9 and  30.    The principle that there should be additional graduated contributions to support the new scheme iscertainly one that we should wish to maintain and it is proposed thatwe should use the proceeds of the change in the contracting-outarrangements to reduce the flat-rate contribution payable by everyone.A reduction cf about 4d. a side should be possible.    These arrange-rnents are still to be worked out in detail.Administration27.     It is provisionally estimated that a scheme on these lines would require about 2, 000 additional staff in my Department, mainly to handle sickness benefit claims.    The number of additional staffneeded by the Ministry of Labour might be about 800.    The extensionof graduated contributions to the contracted-out and the wider spanof earnings attracting contributions will mean more work for the inland Revenue.    Some extra staff will be needed but it is not expected that the number will be large.-9-

PART IV - QUESTIONS FOR DECISION28.     I now invite the decision of the Cabinet whether I am to proceewith the preparation of a scheme of earnings-related short-term benefits on the lines I have described in this memorandum, includingconsultations with the T. U. C. , the C. B. L and other interested bodieiI should also welcome decisions on the following questions on whichthe Social Services Sub-Committee on Social Security Cash Benefitswas not able to reach final conclusions:-(i)   Should earnings-related widow&apos;s allowance beincluded in the scheme?    (paragraph 21).(ii)   Should  earnings-related supplements be paid on top of injury benefit?   (paragraphs 19 and 20).M. H.Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance, W. C. 2. ,23rd July, 1965-10-confidentiXl

vVS^weekly BKraFIT (rLAT-RATK FLU.S EAKI-XTTOS-KJ3LATED SUT PLK:     rl&apos;) AS A  FROPORTIOII OF TAK.K-?;0?vE F,OfEAJgllirGS-RKLATED SUPrLETEire    ^ 1/3RD OF GTIOSS RAT&quot;.inCS BSTj^T  % AT TP,  ?Qr	Gross earnings of  12 a week				r     &apos;      &quot;.....    Gross earnings of  15 a week					Gross earnings of  18 a week				Gross ea  25 a		rninga week	of		Gross earning  30    week			s of	(1) Total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (1) as ,. of take-home pay* plus f ariily allowances	(1) Total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (1) as ,   of take-home pay&quot; plus family allowances	(1) Total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (l) as ,   of take-home payr- plus family allowances	(1) Total benefit plus family allowances			(l) as     of take-home pay* plus family allowances		(1) Total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (l) as     of take-home pay* plus family allowances		 	s.	do		 	5 *	d.		 	s.			 	s.	d.			 	s.	d.		Single nan		0	0	51	6	0	0	51	7	0	0	51	9	6	8		51	11	0	0		50berried nan	7	10	0	71	8	10	0	67	9	10	0	65	11	16	8		61	13	10	0		59Married man 4- 1 child	8	12	6	78	9	12	6	72	10	12	6	69	12	19	2		64.	24	12	6		62Harried man * 2 childi-en	9	15	0	84	10	15	0	75	11	15	0	70	14	1	8		65	15	15	0		63Married man + 3 children	10	19	6	91	11	IS	6	80	12	19	6	74	15	6	2		67	16	19	r O		65Married man	12	4	(/	97*	13	4	0	86	14	4	0	78	16	10	8		69	18	4	0		66+ 4 children																						Married man + 5 children	13	8	&amp;	103^	14	8	6	91	15	8	6	82	17	15	2		71	19	8	r O		67Married man * 6 children	14	13	o/	108^	15	13	o/	95^	16	13	0	86	18	19	a o		73	20	13	0		69-Gross pay less income tax mid graduated and flat-rate contributions./In these cases the amount of earnings-related supplement would bereduced or extinguished by the operation cf a benefit ceiling of85..  of gross earnings, i.e., about 9Q   of take-home pay.coio?ide;;tial

V/KEKI.T INJTJE3T jpiSWEFTT&apos;RATE PLUS        l^JS;:^ j^^J^L^UgP^gMiSElE/..MING-S BELATED SUPPLEMENT e fol&apos; OF  ROSS KfJNINGSBETWEEN  9 and  30Gross weekly earnings of:		 12			 15				 18				 25						 30	Benefit celling 8j?j2 gross earning +  2 15s.			 12	19s.  -a.		 15		ios. -a.		 18		1s. -d.			 24	-s. -a.	 26			3a.   -a.Benefit for	Present flat rate plus family	(1) total benefit plus family allowances		(2) (1) as Jg of take-home pay&apos;:&apos; plus family allowances	O) total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (1) as g of take-home pay* plus family allowances	(1) total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (1) aa% of take-home pay^ plus family allowances	0) total benefit plus family allowances			(2) (1) as % of take-home pay* plus family allowances	(1) total benefit plus family allowances			(1) as f0 of take-home pay&apos; plus family allowances	allowances																				      S e      d.	 	s. a.		e	s.	a.	&apos;         -	 	s.	a.		Z	s.	a.		 	s.	a.	Single man	6   15   -	7	15  -	78.7	8	15	-	74.0	9	15	-	71.0	12.	1	8	65.5		15	**	63.0^Harriefi man	9    5  -	10	5  -	97.2	11	5		83,6	12	5	-	83.5	14 11		8	75.2	16	IT		71.4Married can * 1 child	10    7  6	n	7  6	102.8	12	7	6	92.6	13	7	6	86.2	15	14	2	77.5	17	7	6	73.4Marriednan * 2 ohildi^ai	11   10   -	12	10   -	108.0	13	10		94.2	14	10		07.2	16	16	8	77.5	18	10	-	73.8Married man 4- 3 children	12 14   6	13	14  6	113.7	14	14	6	98.6	15	14	6	89.4	18	1	2	78.7	I9	14	6	75.married man -s- 4 ohildren	13 19  -	14	19  -*	118.9	15	19	-	103.3	16	19	-	92.7	19	5	8	-79.7	a,	19	-	75.5Married man 4- 5 children	15 3    6	16	3	123.7	17	3	6	107.8	13	3	o	96.7	20	10	2	81.2	22		6	76.4.Married man 4- 6 ohildren	16 8    -	17	8    J*	128.2	18	8		112.0	19	8	-	100.6	21	14	8	1	23	o	-	77.7* Gross pay less income tax and graduated flat-rate contributionsx Benefit would be reduced to ceiling (at hear of column) plus family allowances  Benefit would be reduced to flat rate plus family allowances, as shown in first column.CONFIDENTIALAS A PROPOKTIOK Off TAKE HOME PAX




</content>
</cab>
