<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/122/0 images: 404-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COMPUTERSMemorandum by tha Minister of TechnologyAt their meeting on 3rd June (C. G. (65) 32nd Conclusions,Minute 4), the Cabinet invited me to circulate a further memorandum on assistance to the computer industry.2.      The Government are committed to policies which will ensure thatthere exists a flourishing British computer industry.    A number of measures to this end were announced in my Statement to the House on1st March.   They included -(i) the establishment of a Computer Advisory Unit;(ii) a 5 year programme designed to augment the computerresources of Universities, CATS and Research Councils;(iii) a programme of research and development;(iv) studies to explore the desirability of establiching a NationalComputer Programme Centre.3.      All these measures are in hand, but there are positive indications that they will not in themselves guarantee a viable British computer industry,    &quot;VThen I made my Statement on 1st March, the evidencesuggested that the price factor would not operate against British computers.The situation in this respect has changed.    United States competition is becoming more s eve re, partly as a result of economies of scale and partly because of the competition between the American companies themselves.Failing some degree of preference for the British computer industry, an unacceptable situation will arise.4.      The Government sector does not represent-a high proportion of themarket for British computers.    It is, however, a very significantproportion.    Much attention is focus sed on it and if a rising share ofGovernment orders is seen to be going to American companies, conclusionsunfavourable to the fixture of the British computer industry will be drawn.There have been a number of unfavourable developments recently, forexample, the large International Business Machines Limited (I. B. M.)order for Scotland.    Another problem is developing over requirements for the computer network for the Ministry of Pensions and national insurance.5.      To meet the situation, I have made the proposals set out in my paper of 31st May (C.(65) 79), but these were not adopted by the Cabinet.An alternative to the price preference which I then suggested would be toincrease the protective tariff.    But the present most-favoured-nationrate of 14 per cent is, I understand, bound.    Moreover, even if we couldnegotiate our freedom to raise it, we should still have to get over thedifficulty prenente^ by the combination of the GATT rule against new orCOPY NO.5 aJL. *J 0-1-CONFIDENTIALis DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HEB. BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)C.(65) 115ZGth July, 1965CABINET

CO WPinPMTI Alincreased preferences and Commonwealth free entry.    It is, of course,for the President of the Board of Trade to cay whether a higher tariff isa practicable course but it does not look promising and it would, at best,take an inordinate time.6.      I have explored the other possibilities put forward by the PrimeMinister in his summing up of our discussion on the .3rd June and as aresult I submit for the approval of the Cabinet the following alternative proposals in regard to the procurement of computers in the Governmentsector:-(i) It should be a matter of settled Government policy that computerneeds in the Government sector should be met by computers ofBritish manufacture except where either no British producedmodel can do the job or using a British produced model wouldinvolve more than 12 months additional delay.(ii) A British computer should be defined as including, in additionto those supplied by our own makers, any computermanufactured in the United Kingdom and having not less thana specified United Kingdom content by value.    The method ofcalculating the United Kingdom content and the level at whichthe qualifying figure should be set would require furtherconsideration but I am advised that neither should presentany technical difficulty.7.      The effect of such a policy v/ould be to admit computers made byBritish controlled companies, plus those made at the Honeywell factory in Scotland, plus the one computer model (a small one) to be made byI, B. M. in Scotland.    If I. B. M. or some other foreign controlled firmreacted by increasing the extent of their manufacture in the United Kingdomthe corresponding machines v/ould become admissible.C.      I accept that in the absence of open competitive tendering it wouldbe necessary to keep a check on the prices at which British computerswere offered so as to ensure that they were not excessive.     Allmanufacturers could be invited periodically to submit lists of the prices at which they were prepared to supply Government requirements.    Inaddition, it would not, in practice, be difficult to ascertain in sufficientinstances the prices being charged to commercial users.9.      A policy on these lines would have to be applied for a minimum period of 3 years in order to give the British industry a reasonablebreathing space.    It could be reviewed at the end of this period in thelight of developments.10,      Whether it would be practicable and advantageous to change overto a bulk ordering system of the kind proposed by the Prime Minister at cabinet on the 3rd June is being examined by the Departments concerned,I am myself attracted by such a system.    It is not, however, essential tothe implementation of the policy set out in paragraph 6 above and we neednot therefore at this stage decide for or against adopting it.    I propose that officials should work out and prepare a report on a batch ordering system on the following lines:--2-

EOI(i) there should be a 5 year rolling forecast of computer needs in the Government sector;(ii)  requirements should be aggregated and standard computerequipment should bo ordered as far as practicable;(iii) tenders should be invited for batches of computer equipmentafter any necessary discussion with manufacturers;(iv) invitation to tender would be restricted as in paragraph 6 above.There arrangements would not disturb the Treasury&apos;s present functions in regard to tho ordering of computers or the existing centralisedcontractual arrangements through the Stationery Office.    There would,however, be a central tendering policy and a central plan.11.      I would also ask the Cabinet tc invite Ministers responsible for nationalised industries to press those industries to follow the policiesoutlined in paragraph 6 as a matter of national policy.    1 would ask theMinister of Health to consider particularly the position of the hospitalorganisation where a vast expansion in computer use can be foreseenboth in administrative and in clinical practice.Structure of the Industry12.      I have continued with my attempts to persuade the computer industry to adopt a more rational pattern.    There have been manymeetings with the two principal companies concerned at which possibleforms of amalgamation have been discussed.    These efforts have, I fear,got nowhere and progress cannot be expected unless more powerfulmeasures are brought tc bear. /13. International Computers and Tabulators limited (I. C. T. ) are notprepared to subordinate their computer interests to English Electric and vice versa.    Neither firm welcomes the idea of a joint company.14.      The number of possible measures is very limited:-(i) we could apply a measure of coercion by threatening to call of four aid unless I. C. T. and English Electric pooled theircomputer interests;(ii) we could threaten to nationalise the computer industry.15.      I am not attracted by (i).    If the threat were ineffective we mightbe forced to abandon measures which are valuable in themselves eventhough they do not go far enough.16.      (ii) does not seem a promising candidate for the legislative programme as it exists at the moment.17.      It is, however, possible that the British companies&apos; negotiationswith French interests in computer development may lead to closer links between I. C, T. and English Electric.    I shall keep this point very muchin mind in assessing the joint proposals which they ha,ve just submittedto me for Government support in the development of a large Anglo-Frenchcomputer.-3-

Summary18.      I ask my colleagues to agree that:-(a) Government orders  or computer equipment should be usedto support the British industry;(b) to this end procurement of computers for GovernmentDepartments should be in accordance with paragraph 6;(c) officials should be instructed to examine and report cn abatch-ordering system on the lines set out in paragraph 10;(d) means of bringing together I. G. T. and English Electriccomputer interests should be considered further in the lightcf the outcome of the proposed Anglo-French project.tt   c.Ministry of Technology, 8.11.1,27th July, 1965




</content>
</cab>
