<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/122/0 images: 892-894</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  October 1965C. (65) 137 Copy No.    6 622nd October, 1965CABINETEARNINGS-RELATED SHORT-TERM benefits memorandum by the Minister of Pensions and NationalInsuranceOn 29th July the Cabinet authorised me (C.C. (65)43rd Conclusions, Minute 4) to consult various organisations aboutmy proposals for earnings-related short-term benefits and asked forfurther consideration to be given to the priority which should be accorded to the inclusion of earnings-related widow&apos;s allowance inthe scheme.2. I have not yet concluded my consultations. I have, however,given further consideration, in consultation with the Chief Secretary,to earnings-related widow&apos;s allowance, and I now ask my colleagues to agree that this should be included in the scheme, and that our intentions on it should be made clear in The Queen&apos;s Speech.3. There is a strong claim for better provision for the early months of widowhood. Part of the case for earnings-related unemployment and sickness benefit is that people need better provision against sudden and unexpected interruptions of their income in these contingencies. The argument applies with perhap seven greater force to widows who lose the support of a husband&apos;earnings, often with little warning and no opportunity to adjustfinancial commitments. The cost of this particular proposal is about 7 million a year.4. Apart from the very real merits of the case for improvingwidow&apos;s allowance, I have in mind that the previous administration had committed themselves in their manifesto to including this in their scheme for earnings-related benefits. If we do not do the same thereis every risk of an amendment which might well carry the day. i therefore think it realistic to recognise that earnings-related widow&apos;allowance is likely to come and ought to come, and to take the credit for including it in our Bill. If this is accepted, I think it important thatwe should declare our intention in The Queen&apos;s Speech and so avoid the appearance of being pushed into the improvement for widows bythe Opposition.CONFIDENTIAL6217 &apos;N
5. I am satisfied that the improved widow&apos;s allowances can befitted into my public expenditure limits, and that there are nocompeting claims which ought to displace it. There are always, ofcourse, major desirable improvements which might be made in social security. For instance, there is pressure from time to time to improvebenefits for the chronic sick, and this may well be renewed when weintroduce a Bill dealing with short-term sickness. But provision forthe chronic sick is to be examined in the context of our long-termreview of pensions and we should not attempt to anticipate the outcome of that examination. Similarly, there is criticism of thepresent age 50 rule for widows, but what we do about this againdepends very much on the shape of our long-term pension proposals.Under the agreed limits on expenditure any major innovation suchas an income guarantee could be financed only by cutting severely therise in benefit rates. I believe that cuts of the order required wouldbe politically unacceptable besides being unjust to the recipients ofthose benefits. Certainly the cost of my proposals for widow&apos;allowance would make very little difference here. I am, as mycolleagues know, working on some possible changes in national assistance but, again because of limits on expenditure, it is my intention that any improvements here which would otherwise takeexpenditure beyond the agreed limits should be met by positivesavings elsewhere.6. Among possible smaller improvements, I can think of nonecalling for a higher priority than my proposal for widow&apos;s allowance.I am content that other possible reforms should be judged in theknowledge of the money already committed for widows. If mycolleagues accept this, the proposal can be accommodated within mypublic expenditure programme on the assumptions that benefit rates will not rise faster than earnings and that the next uprating will not take place before June 1967.7. I therefore ask the Cabinet to agree that earnings-relatedwidow&apos;s allowance should be included in the scheme, and that thisshould be announced in The Queen&apos;s Speech.M. H.Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance, W.C.2,21st October, 1965.


</content>
</cab>
