<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/2/47 images: 642-645</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.W.P. (G.) (39) 96.Copy No.    13CHARTERING OF GERMAN SHIPPING.Note by the First Lord of the Admiralty.I AM well aware of the arguments which may be urged against thispolicy, but I feel that it should be considered by the Cabinet in the nearfuture, so that even if no decision or action is reached, the pros and consmay be constantly balanced as the character of the War defines itself.W. S. C.November 16, 1939.r[20320a]Printed for the War Cabinet. November 1939.

Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1939.SECRET. Copy No. 1 3W. P. (G.) (39) 96.WAR CABINET.NOTE ON THE CHARTERING OF GERMAN SHIPPING.THERE are about 1,500,000 tons of German shipping now lying in neutral ports. To charter this quantity at present rates would probably cost about 14 to  18 million a year. It is suggested that a reasonable price for thisshipping would be  36 million.Would it be wise for the British Government to agree to the transfer ofthese German ships to a neutral flag provided :  1. The transfer be effected within weeks.2. That as soon as the transfer is effected Britain be given an option tocharter the ships at pre-war (or at present British) rates for the duration of the war or any shorter period.3. That the purchase price be not transferred to Germany until after thewar.If these terms were accepted the effect would be that we should be able tocharter 1,500,000 tons of neutral shipping for about  9 million a year, ineHermans would acquire a credit amounting to the purchase price What tinswould be is difficult to forecast, but it would probably be considerably less than 36 million, if this is a fair price to purchasers free to charter their ships at thepresent swollen rate. ^    . ,,r- - . , ,The clanger emphasised by the Economic Pressure Section of the Ministryof Economic Warfare that Germany might borrow money on the strength of thesecredits, does not seem to be a very real one. People who believe Germany is goingto win will be ready to lend her money; those who are convinced she will lose are unlikely to trust that in the debacle she will ear-mark these credits to repay their special loans The obiection to this proposal is, of course, that the Germans mayrefuse to sell on these terms. On the other hand, there will be every incentive forthe neutrals to put pressure on the Germans to sell at a low rate, and it may wellhe that in many cases they will be able to make their wishes effective.If it is held that no ships will be transferred on these terms, the right to demand higher freights than the pre-war ones could be considered.The course to be recommended must depend upon the estimate formed aboutthe duration of the war. If the war lasts a long time it will pay us to get theshipping at cheap rates, even if Germany gets some credits, whatever they mayhe worth. On the other hand, in a short war the value of these credits to germany will lie greater and the advantage of the extra shipping to us will be less.[20320]
German Ships in Neutral Waters.(Not complete.)Large.JapanNetherlands East Indies.Portugal LisbonLobitoEast Africa ...Goa   ......IranItaly-TriesteWest CoastMassawaSpain &apos;East CoastWest CoastIslandsMedium.1517134311511513292221640117Small.121111228203157Panama A rea.Large. Medium.    Small.TJ.SA.     ...      ......... 4Mexico     .........        1 8Central America........      - - - 19Brazil      .........       2 17Argentina         ... 6              1Chile       ............. J*            *!3 62              1

</content>
</cab>
