<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/44A/0 images: 64-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Sir M. Hanhy.     31(This Document is the Property of SisBritannic Majesty&quot;s Government)*SECRET.IMPERIAL WAS CABINET 24 A.MEHUTES of a Meeting held at 10 Downing Street9S.W., on MONDAY, JULY 15, 1918, at 12. noono-   . nPresents- (/vThe Prime Minister of the United Kingdom fin the Chair)The Rt. Hon. MM A. Bonar Law, MoP..Chancellor of the Exchequer:The Rte hon G.NoBarnes, M*Po,The Bto Hon. Austen Chamberlain, MoP.,Lt.*.(Jen. The Rt. Hon. JoOoSmuts, E*C. *The Rt. Hon. Sir Robert L. Borden,.G.CoM.&amp;., K.C., Prime Minister of Canada?The Rt. hon a Yf.Mo Hughes, Prime Ministerof AustralianThe Rt. Hon. W.F.M&amp;ssey, Prime Ministerof Hew Zealand:The Rt. Hon. W.i.Lloyd, K.C. , PrimeMinister of Newfoundland:The following were also present-The Rt. Eon. A.J.Balfour, O.M., M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs:The Rto Hon. the Viscount Milner, G.CoB.,, G.G.M.S., Secretary of State for War;General Sir H.H.Wilson, K*C.B*, D.SoO*, -Chief of the Imperial General staff$Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M*P*A*Hanlcey, EoCB. *-Secretary,,War Cabinet.1.

BE WESTERNONE.BRICAN OG-ERATION.OMENTr^HWARD OFL.ISH RE-RYES.(1) With reference to Imperial war Cabinet 24, minute, the prime Minister reminded his colleagues that atthe Meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet on Friday somedissatisfaction had been expressed with the numbers ifAmerican troops training behind the British line, and ithad been agreed that the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff should make representations to General Foch on thesubject, and that he himself should write to MonsieurOlemenoeau inviting him to support General Wilson1s re-presentations to General Foch.    On Friday afternoon he himself had seen Field Marshal Sir Douglas Haig,and had found that he also was very anxious to get more Americanstraining behind his lines. The Field Marshal had notbeen very satisfied as to the position in rear of theBelgian lines, and considered that two good divisions should always be located in the region of Dunkirk to re-info roe in case of necessity,   sir Douglas Haig, whenpassed/ on the point, had explained that he had plenty ofroom for training purposes.   By the end of the monththere would be about 30 American divisions in France,and if the present distribution were maintained only 5ef these would be behind the British line and 25 behind the French line, of which 17 er 18 would be more or lessol^se to the line.The Prime Minister then gave a short summary of some0f the points in the letter which he had written to Mon-sieur Clemenoeau.   In explanation of the reasons for bring-ing more of the American troops behind the British frontfor training, the Prime Minister explained that we wereuncertain as to where the attack would oome.   There wasa good deal of evidence, however, to show that it mightoome on the British front.   In the event of a break at;any point, it would be very desirable to have even half\So

S3trained troops to push in to stera/fefe. and in this connection itshould &quot;be &quot;borne in mind that after an advance the enemy could&quot;bring no weight of artillery to hear for some time, s&amp; thatinexperienced troops were at a less disadvantagec^^t^j,On the previous day General foch had given orders that 4divisions from the British reserveswere to proceed far southof the Semme to the region of Vitry-le-Francois, south-east efChalons.   Thus, at the very moment when we were appealing for more American troops to &quot;be trained behind our lines as aujre-serve, Genera,! Foch had reduced, &quot;by 4 divisions, the reservebehind the British lines.   Moreover, General Foch had moved tothe southward the 6 French divisions of the D.A.H., which hadbeen in the region of Beauvais, whence they could have &quot;beentransported rapidly to reinforce the British front in case &amp; necessity.On the receipt of this information the Prime Minister, whothosehad been in the country, had taken steps to assemble ses/is&amp;b^: ofhis colleagues on the Imperial War Cabinet whom he knew to &quot;be within reach, and Sir Robert Borden, General Smuts, Lord Milner,the Chief of the imperial General staff, and the Director ofMilitary Operations had assembled.    The result of this informalconference had been that he had sent a telegram to Field marshal sir Douglas Haig, pointing out to him that all information re-leived up to the present had pointed to an attack on the british front by prince Bupprechtts forces, as well as an attack by theCrown Prince on the French front, and that, in these circum-stanoes, General Fochxs orders to British reserves to movesouthwards, gave the Imperial War Cabinet considerable anxiety.The Field Marshal had also been reminded that if he consideredthe British Army to be in danger he should exercise his judg-ment&apos; under the Beauvais Agreement to appeal.    It had also beeaagreed that General smuts should proceed, on behalf of the

Imperial War Cabinet, to (5.H.Q., to confer with Field MarshalHaig after the Field Marshal?s Conference with general Fooh,^The Prime Minister pointed out that everything depended upon whether the new attack was the main attack or not.    Qb-viously this latest attack was not a sham attack, and must betaken very seriously, particularly when it was remembered thatthe German divisions were larger than the French.   Up to thepresent time he did not know the Field Marshal&apos;s view,    pos-sibly he would not finally make up his mind until he had seenGeneral Fooh.   Nevertheless, he felt it was right for general smuts to be there.    If prince Buppreoht*s Army attacked, itwas conceivable, in the absence of proper dispositions, thatthe British Army might be overwhelmed, and it was, therefore,the duty of the Imperial War Cabinet to be clear that field marshal sir Douglas Haig was satisfied with the evidence inwhich General Foch was acting.A second point which General smuts would have to press was this.- Assuming that the decision to send 4 of the British re-serve divisions southwards was correct, even then, was it notthe more desirable that there should be additional Americantreops training behind our lines?   In faot, the points which general Smuts had to dear up could be summed up as follows.-(1) Is there any real danger of an attack by princeEuppreoht after the Crown prince1s attack has developed?(ii) in any case aught not we t$ have more american troops behind our lines? \In the course of the subsequent discussion, it was pointed$ut that the decision in regard to the reserves depended onthe evidence as to where the German troops were about toattack.   Consequently, if General Foch was satisfied that theenemy intended to attack in the Champagne, it was difficultto see what the British Government could do.    In this oonneo-tion the prime Minister explained that one of the primary

objects of General smutsr  visit was to ascertain definitely as to whether Field Marshal Haig was satisfied.    In any event,however, he was to insist on the importance of getting more American troops behind our lines.

Lord Milner said that he differed a little from the Prime Minister&apos;s view of the situation. He quite realised the force of what the Prime Minister had said, but if General Foch was right and the main attack was on the French front, he felt no doubt that the divisions asked for by the Gen. Foch ought to go, and to go at one. We should be open to very serious oriticism if this proved to be the great attack of the War and we had insisted on retaining 19 divisions in reserve behind our lines. Some days must elapse before the identifications of the enemy divisions engaged could be received, and until then we should probably not have definite evidence as to whether any of Prince Rupprecht&apos;s divisions were engaged. We could not refuse to allow General Foch to draw on our divisions until then.

The Prime Minister agreed generally with Lord Milner, but pointed out that if Field Marshal Haig, whose Intelligence Department under General Cox was a very efficient one, considered that the attack in the Champagne was only a part of a greater intended to withdraw the reserves from behind the British Army, and considered that the attack was coming on his front, it would be his duty, as Commander-in-Chief of the British Expeditionary Force, to exercise his right of appeal under the Beauvais Agreement.

It was generally admitted that if this should occur the Imperial War Cabinet would have a very difficult decision to take. In this connection it was pointed out that to oppose or over-ride the General-in-Chief on a military question would place great responsibility on the British Government, but it was also pointed out that if the Field Marshal Commanding the British Expeditionary Force appealed, it would be a 



ft f*.3 0Imperialgreat responsibility not to support him*   The/war Cabinet weresctecc reminded, however, that, in tbe event of a conflict ofopinion arising, tbe conditions were rather different from what they were before the appointment of a single General-in-Gbief.   Formerly, in the event of a difference arising betweenthe British and French Commanders-in-Chief, the presumption ifeach Government had been that their own Commander-in-Ghiefwas right,   low the presumption was that the Allied General-in-Ohief was right, and in any difference of opinion the onuswas on the British Commander-in-Ohief to show that GeneralFitch was wrong.   It was generally agreed that the fact thatthe attack had been made on a 50 mile  rent,within the preciselimits that General Foch had anticipated, was prima facie evi-dence that General Foch was right.    It was generally agreed,however, that it would, be undesirable to pre-judge an issuethat it was hoped would never arise.After the withdrawal of General Smuts/,&apos; there was some dis-discussion as to the time that it would take to bring the british divisions back from Vitry-le-Francois in case of necessity.The Chief of the Imperial General staff stated that no fore-oast of this could be made beoause so many elements in the pro-blem were uncertain, for example, the amount of rolling-stookimmediately available, the number of trains that could be run,the state of the roads, what other troops were moving, &amp;c.,The Secretary of State for War pointed out that the british divisions were not the only ones that could be used to rein-force the British Army in the event of an attack by prineeBupprecht.   If French divisions were more readily accessible,they would no doubt be employed.In reply to a cfuestion by Mr* Massey,, the secretary ofState for War said that from the point of view of man-power the British forces were probably not&quot; quite so strong today as

they had been on March 21, partly owing to the fact that someof the divisions had had to be filled up with Class B. men. Atthe present time we had 56 or 57 divisions in Prance, and or 2 divisions in the United Kingdom being filled up withClass B. men.    Of our 56 or 57 divisions in Prance, only 53were fully completed with Class A. men.    If the 5 american divisions training behind our lines were included, we werenumerically considerably stronger than on March 21.   Moreoverswe had a much shorter line to hold.   General Wilson said thatthe only point where we were really weaker than on March 21,was the extreme difficulty of ceding any ground.In the course of this discussion the Imperial War Cabinetmade the following decisions:-(a) The Secretary was instructed to circulate a copy ofthe letter written by the Prime Minister to MonsieurGlemenceau on March 13.(b) Those present should hold themselves in readiness fora meeting at short notioe at any time up to a latehour in the evenings(c) The discussion at the Imperial War Cabinet on War Aims,arranged for the following day, should be postponed:(d) The Chief of the imperial General Staff should arrangefor General Smuts to be accompanied by an Officer $fthe General Staff.T (2) The Prime Minister invited the views of Mr. Balfour oniI2JG*S.  .OH. ,, Count HertlingTs speech.   He suggested the possibility thatits object was to weaken the moral of the Belgian troops, witha view to an attack in the lorth, and, in his opinion, thiswas an important piece of evidence pointing towards an attacken our front.    Count Hertling, who had confessed^having disouss-ed the question at German Grand Headquarters, had practicallysaid to the Belgians: &quot;You will get your country whether youfight or note&quot;7. I

The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs,,while agreeing that the prime Minister1s explanation was a possible one,personally inclined to the view that^/it was merely a step ina &quot;big peace offensive on the part of the Germans, which he had&quot;been anticipating.   He pointed out that it would take some timefor a speech of this kind to penetrate to the rank and file of the Belgian Army.Whitehall Gardens, S*W.,Fitly 15, 1918,,




</content>
</cab>
