<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/44A/0 images: 132-177</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
, ft(This Document is the property of HisBri tannio Maj esty1s Government).B t.IMPERIAL WAR OABI1ET 27A.DRAFT MINUTES of a Meeting held at 10 Downing St.,S.W. , on WEDNESDAY,  JULY 21, 1918, at 11.30 a.m.P r e s an t:-The prime Minister of the united Kingdom (in the Ghair)jThe Rt. Hon. Sir Robert L. Borden,(J.0.M.G-., K.O., prime Minister ofCanada.The Rt. Hon. W.M.Hughes, primeMinister of Australia:The Rt. Hon. W.ff.Massey, prime Ministerof lew Zealand:Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.smuts,K.C,  (representing the prime Minister ofSouth Africa):The Rt. Hon. W.P.Lloyd, K.C., Prime Ministerof Newfoundland:The following ?/ere also present: -The Rt. Hon. the Viscount Milner, G.CB.,G. CM. 0. , Secretary of state for War:General Sir H.H.Wilson, E.C.B-, D.S.O.,Chief of the imperial General Staff:Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M.P.A.nanteey, K.G.B.,Secretary, war Cabinet.1.

3 WESTERS&quot; (1) The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reportedBIT.that on the previous day the Australians had taken Merris,a small village in the region of Hazebrouck.    One usefulresult of this operation had &quot;been that Rupprecht had &quot;been4 obliged to remove a German division from the line andreplace it from one of his reserve divisions.    This left a total of 21 divisions in RuppreohtTs reserve.    71 Ger-man divisions had now been identified in the presentbattle on the Crown prince1s front; of these 9 divisionscame from Bupprecht-s Army.    On the Grown princess frontthere seemed to be no doubt that the German resistancewas stiffening.   He did not know whether or not this was due to General Pooh perhaps having decided either to re-organise his front or to break off the pursuit,    she burn-ing of villages between soissons and Rheims gave the impres-sion that the Germans intended to retire to the line of.theVesle.LORD MILKER pointed out that the recent announcement ofthe German intentions to stand on their loresent line poi^fe-&apos;ed to no further retirement.    It would be a weak thing todo to announce that they were going to stand and then-&quot;&apos;again retire.m ,- . .... .     &quot;ITHE GHIEP OP THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF, continuing^-,said that Chalons and Epernay had been very heavily shelledwith long-range 15&quot; guns, with the result that many ofthe civilian population were evacuating these towns.   the range was very great, perhaps as much as 27 miles in thecase of Chalons, and 21 miles in the case of Epernay.    Thisno doubt was what the enemy had intended to do to paris ifhe had succeeded in his recent attack.   At Chalons last night a round had been fired every five minutes for threehours in succession, and the bombardment of Bpemay was even more rapid.    General Foch would, of course, wish,&quot;if &apos;

possible, to disengage the Chateau-Thierry-Epernay-Chalonsrailway, which was still under the fire of German 5.9&quot;guns, rendering the regular use of the railway impossible.To disengage the railway would involve an advance of about,000 yards, and this might give one of the reasons why theenemy was holding on to his present position.THE CHIEF OP THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF said that Brit-ish G.H.Q., still anticipated an attack on the Ypres-Mer-ville front, that is to say, on a front of perhaps 25kilos,  extending to about the junction of the British and belgian Armies,    He had himself examined the evidence which,as G.H.Q., admitted, was not very convincing; it consist-ed merely of the location of a few more dumps, a fev/ moresidings, hospitals, &amp;.&amp;.*, in the region indicated.    Theevidence of prisoners was conflicting, some saying thatthe attack was still intended, while others said&apos;that ithad been postponed.    The weather was,  of course, now more favourable for an attack.    He had had a letter fromGeneral plumer, ?/ho was quite satisfied with his situationand not at all afraid of an attack.LORD MILKER said that the position on the front of Gen-eral plumer*s Army was stronger than it had ever been be-fore, an opinion in which General Wilson agreed.(2) THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF reported .that the Italians had fallen back for a distance of lo or15 kilometres in Albania, in the direction of Herat.    He .had already reported the arrival of a fresh Austaian divi-sion, which appeared to have attacked rather heavily.(3) THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF reported thatthere was increasing evidence that the Germans were with-drawing their own troops, from Palestine in confirmatlonof information he had reported to the war Cabinet a few   )

weeks ago, that this move might be expected.    Reports hadbeen received from various places on the line of trainsgoing north containing nothing but German troops.In reply to questions he stated that the object of theGermans was no doubt to scrape up further man-power for theWestern front.(4) THE PRIME MINISTER drew, attention to a statement inthe Versailles summary of Weekly intelligence to the ef-fect that an additional /ffevarian division had been broken LORD MILNER pointed out that, according to the map inthe Cabinet Room, which was kept up to date daily by theGeneral Staff, the German divisions on the Western frontT/ere reduced to SoloSHE CHIEF OP THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF said that theDirector of Military Intelligence believed that the Ger-mans were breaking up some divisions, but that,- in somecases, they had never been complete divisions.    Neverthe-less, this evidence, in conjunction with the withdrawal from Palestine, pointed to a difficult man-power situationin Germany.(5] THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had received inform-ation to the effect that the Germans were not able to getmuch advantage from the Russian situation, and that theAllies were under a complete misapprehension as to Ger-many1s position and power there.   According to this report it appeared that Russia was so disorganised that the Ger-mans could do nothing with it.   Russia merely absorbedsome 30 German divisions, but they were in despair there and did not know quite what to do.In reply to MR LLOYD, he said that Germany did not ap-pear to be able to do much in Finland either.    Tbe Fir^tup.

Lord of the Admiralty had reported aa the result of a per-sona.1 visit that it was a most difficult country,LORD MILIEH, in reply to Mr, Hughes, said the germans were no doubt anxious to exploit the mineral and oil re-sour oes of Bussia.    She most important oilfields were atBaku, which was now threatened by the enemy.   We ourselveswere trying to push forward forces to enter Baku, hut theenemy1 s eommunications were much hotter than ours, whichran right across an inhospitable and undeveloped country in persia.   We should like to destroy the oil-wells before theenemy could reach them, &apos;but we probably were not in a posi-tion to do so.

JRE MI LI 3?-       (6) She Prime Ministers had &quot;before them a Report fey thePOLICY.CMef of the Imperial General staff entitled &quot;British Mil-itary Policy in 1918-1919&quot; (paper W.P.7Q).LORD MILKER said that his impression was that, as an alliance, we had not at present a sufficiently hopefulmilitary policy.   At present everything was still ooneen-trated upon the Western front.   At one time the idea ofour being able to achieve military victory on that front had &quot;been fading, but latterly it appeared to have revivedin great strength.    He did not know what, the view of theCommittee of Prime Ministers was, but he gathered the gen-eral impression abroad to be that the Germans would failthis year in the attempt they were making to gain a deci-sion on the Western front, but that next year the allies would sxicceed.there,    on this he personally felt the grav-est doubt.   In his view the Western front was a candle thatburned all the moths that entered it.    Shis year the Ger-mans had failed to accomplish anything in &quot;Palestine, andhad failed to do much with Russia; they had also failed, as yet, even to conquer Transcaucasia, though they were mak-ing good progress there; their failures had been due tothe fact that they had not employed sufficient forces forthe reason that they had concentrated everything in an at-tempt to break the Western front,   ifo one disputed for a mount that a decision on the Western front would end theWar, and consequently everyone was attracted by the ideaof taking the offensive there.    The Germans had made the attempt at Verdun, and had renewed it this year, while we ourselves had made the attempt to obtain a decision on theWestern front in 1916 and 1917.    So achieve success in-volved the employment of overwhelming force under modern conditions.    It was quite evident that in modern warfare the defence had an enormous advantage, particularly wherethe defences were of great depth.    Our defences possessed

considerable depth; the Germans possessed more.    He asked if we should have a sufficient superiority in the Westerntheatre nest year?   Would we, for example, have a superior-ity of 3 to 2?   from General Wilson1s paper he gathered that we should not *THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that General WilsonlsPaper was drawn up on the hypothesis that the americans would have 80 divisions. They had stated that this in-volved considerable further assistance in cargo steamersfrom us. He was extremely doubtful if we oould providesuch assistance.THE CHIBP OP THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAPP said that hehad only estimated for a force of 65 fighting American di-visions and 15 replacement divisions.    Our superioritywould amount to from 650,000 to 400,000 rifles, accordingto whether the Eastern front could be reconstituted or not.SIR ROBERT B0RDE1J drew attention to Conclusion 3 onpage 30 of W.P.70, where the assumed superiority was 400.000rifles.LORD MILKER, continuing, said that he had made an inde-pendent calculation in regard to the allied forces.    Asregards the British strength, he believed that 45 divisionswas an outside figure of the complete British forces, in-eluding the Dominions1 troopso   By complete divisions hemeant divisions of 9 battalions with a total of about15,000 men in them.   He admitted, however, that the 4Canadian divisions might be reckoned as the equivalent .,of6 British divisions, mxg which might add one or two mokve.a &quot;\Then we came to the great unknown quantity of the preno%divisions.   He did not think that it would be possible to

reckon on a French equivalent of more than 65 British di-visions.THE PRIME MINISTER remarked that the General Staff as-sumed the French divisions to be smaller than the British.LORD MILKER said that he reckoned upon 10 Belgian divi-sions, compared with the General staffs estimate of 5. Asregards the Americans, he assumed that they might reach a total of 80 divisions, each of whieh, he counted as the equivalent of 1-g- British divisions, making an Americanequivalent of ISO British divisions.On this extremely favourable calculation from the pointof view of the Allies,, he could not work up to more than24o divisions as our maximum effort next year.    against these it might he said that the Germans would he reducedto 190, ISO, or even 170 divisions.   Even on these assump-tions he was not satisfied that we could obtain a decisionon the Western front.    He pointed out that, in order toreach a total of 240 Allied divisions, we should be eom-pelled to strain to breaking point everything in the way ofshipping, man-po\i?er, &amp;c, and he doubted even then if itoould be done.   Every day he was receiving warnings fromthe United States of America about their difficulties in steel, coal, and manapower.   Moreover, the horse position was appalling, and horses were very expensive in tonnage.Our Armies could only hope for success if fully equipped with munitions, Tanks, &amp;c.   He had only recently heard that the Tank estimate must be cut down by a half.THE PRIME MI MS TEE said that he had received^very ser-ious Paper from Sir Tennyson D&apos;Eyncourt in the same sense.MR HUGHES said that, between Tanks and men he wouldasshave no hesitation in preferring the former,    - \LORD MILKER urged that before a decision was taken we ought to make sure that we had a reasonable prospect ofsuccess.   We should be certain that our basket could carry,8.

the eggs we wished to put into it.   After making this tre-mendous effort the Allies would he practically paralysed.In reply to a question by sir Robert Borden he saidthat the choice of another theatre in which to make our main effort involved a very &quot;big question,    nevertheless,even if we were not strong enough to obtain a decision onthe Western front we should be amply strong enough to con-tain the enemy on that front and create a reserve for ser-vice elsewhere.   By Ootober the enemy&apos;s chances of obtain-ing a decision on the Western front would be gone, and he believed General Wilson ?/ould agree with him that it would never occur again.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GEIERAL STAFF agreed,unlessthe Germans could enlist the man-power of Russia to help them. He pointed out that he had always held the viewthat we should be confronted with an anxious situationuntil the end of August, but that once the season of mudhad supervened on the Western front,all anxiety would beat an end.LORD MILKER,, ia. reply to Mr. Hughes, said that he him-self would like to see the French and the Americans provid-ing the bulk of the forces for the fifes tern front, with eon-sidarable assistance from us, leaving a margin of some loor 15 divisions with which we eould operate in other partsof the world.    If practically the whole of the German army was contained on the Western front, this reserve should beable to achieve a great deal.MR HUGHES asked his colleagues not to overlook the factthat the Powers that had the largest forces on the western front at the end of the War would probably exercise thegreatest influence on the terms of peace.   From this pointof view it was very undesirable to leave France and theUnited States to finish the War on the western front.

THE PRIME MINISTER expressed doubts as to the eorrect-ness of Mr. Hughes1 views.    He thought that the  ?ower thatwas obtaining a decision elsewhere might carry the mostweight.LORD MILIER said his point was that the French and Am-ericans would not be able to finish the War on the west-era front.    So far as we were concerned it was now outof the question that we could ever again play the greatrtJle on the Western front. The question arose, therefore,as to whether we were to continue to put all our forces on the Western front, where we must play a secondary partat best, or whether, by putting a portion of our forces there, we should continue to play the secondary part,while, with some 15 divisions in other theatres, we might perhaps obtain a decision.   His ideal distribution offorees on the Western front would be somewhat as follows;-America,..........60 divisions equivalent te   90France,.....................................    65/     British Empire..............................   35Belgium..............-.......................   10(TOTAL........ 200This force would be sufficient to keep the whole of theGermans employed, and we should have a balance of at least10 British divisions which could operate with any surplusef American divisions elsewhere.MB HUGHES asked where the Achilles1 heel of the enemyyy verywas to be found?   Was it in salonica, Sxsm large forces were looked up in this diversion, which had not proved afavourable one. \THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that, at least, the Sal-onica diversion had probably saved hundreds of thousan&amp;sN5fmen from being engulfed in the mud of the western front.&apos;-&apos;       fx &quot; - y d&apos;      &apos;(At this point MR MASSE? entered).

LORD MI LIES said it was much harder to decide where our effort should he made than to deeide that to continue the offensive on the Western front was not a business proposi-tion.MR HUGHES asked if Lord Milner had given enough eonsid-eration to the factor of the waning moral of the Germans?LORD MILKER was very sceptical about this.    As long asthey had no anxieties elsewhere he thought that the Ger-mans would always rally to the defence of their country.MR HUGHES put the question as to whether, by leaving 35divisions on the Western front, and endeavouring,, with 15British divisions,/with some surplus American troops,totake action elsewhere to induce the Germans to make peace,we should, in fact, be any better off than i  we were mere-ly to XBBBcfca maintain the whole of our forces on the West-em front without adopting any offensive role such as wehad done last year in Flanders, practically challengingthe Germans to turn us out.   Even if we achieved successeselsewhere, should we be better off at the Peace Conferenceif the Germans were still established in France and Belgium?LORD MILKER said it depended upon what the position wasin the rest of the world.SIR ROBERT BORBEK said that he felt in a very difficult position in this matter.   He could could lay claim to no military knowledge, and was dependent on using his common-sense.   He supposed that the question might be posed inthis way; Kext year, either we fight aggressively or we donot.   He assumed that we should fight aggressively.   Hence,we had to decide whether we would do so in one theatre orin several, and, if so, in v/hich.   ffeease ss-asg-HfJhe Italiantheatre^r^br exampl^taSe suggestion was that we might brjagthe War to an end successfully, not by a purely militaryandfront would iBmmm-]of very great importance.   Among the

I Doonsiderations that had occurred to him in this connectionwere the following:- ,      //-/,.     /(1) She possibility of increased efficiency? Ilf the&apos; AirServiee.    Germany in 1866 and 1870, ana in the pres-ent War, had always fought outside her own borders.If we could get at Germany in any other way than byactual invasion so as to make the German people feel the pressure of the War, we should be doing somethingtowards the object we aimed at.    He suggested this might be done by increased efficiency in the Air Ser-vine, and in this he felt sure the Americans wouldbe ready to help: &apos;(2) By increasing the recognition already given by Ger-man public opinion to the powers possessed by Ameri-ea and Great Britain to impose future restrictionson the economic activities of the German people.Henee, if it was impossible to smash Germany in a mil-itary sense, his suggestion vsould be that we might, by jud-iclous distribution, $eigfiB^ our forces on the Western andItalian fronts in such a way as to batter the Germans se-verely, /^^eai^^e^^^i^ds^aet smash tfejn^i *8 3&amp;s  $t the sametime we could knock them about and make them feel the pri-vations of war by means of aircraft., ^^^^^-^s^K^^ih- TSK7MpBaiSie the importance &quot;of the economic^factor after the War against an unregenerate Germany, /we might force them to concede the peace we desire.GENERAL SMEJSS said he wished to make some remarks aboutthe extremely able, interesting, a.nd brilliant report ofthe Chief of the imperial General Staff.   He agreed withthe forecast that General Wilson had given of the enemy&quot;transaction.   He agreed that, in all probability, the enemy would make another attack this year.    He still had substan-tial reserves intact, the number of which was not absol-utely certain,   she breaking off of the offensive would bea tremendous blow to the Military Party.    The. politicalsituation in Germany must be borne in mind.   Shere hadvforya long time been a tuasle between the politicians and theMilitary party, and only quite recently  unlmann had fall-&quot;en in this contest.    Consequently, the failure of the

Western offensive would be very fatal to the military party.   He also agreed with the view of the General staff that the nest stage would probably be an attaok on Italy,which might be expected to occur late in the autumn.    Gen-eral Smuts reminded the Prime Ministers that last year the Prime Minister had advocated the plan of an attack bythe Allies on the Italian front, which he himself believ-ed, if carried out, would have led to a great success.All last summer the Prime Minister worked very hard for it, but had eventually been blocked by the Italian HighOommand, who wished to wait until the present year.    Inthe sequel the Germans had themselves adopted identicallythe same plan and had made an attaok on the Italians just before the ?/inter, so that it was too late for us to re-taliate.   But for the great exertions of prance and our-selves, Italy might easily have been forced out of the warduring the last winter when the position had been very dif-difficult.   He would not be in the leas*t surprised if theenemy again repeated this plan, namely, to attack in Italyjust before the winter, and then in the winter to move hissurplus forces eastward to the Caucasus, and perhaps even to Transeaspia and towards India.    He fully believed that once the enemy saw that no decision could be obtained inthe West, they would go East, leaving sufficient forces on the.Western front to maintain a defensive position, just as they had done in 1916 and 1917.   This was a summary ofthe forecast of the Chief of the Imperial General staff,and he agreed in it.The first question that arose was: how were we to meet this?   This question must be answered before we oould oon-sider the question of 1919.    The General Staff Memorandumcontained certain suggestions, with which he himself didnot agree.The first of these was that minor operations should be13.

undertaken on the Western front in order to secure a &quot;bet-ter position from which to commence operations in 1919.It was considered necessary to drive the enemy furtherfrom certain important objectives, including the channel ports, the Bruay mines, and Amiens.    His $wn feeling wasthat this would he a fatal policy and to repeat the samemistake a,s was made in the Flanders offensive, last year.If we were to make a serious attempt to push the enemy hackit could only result in most bloody fighting.   Che eonse-quenoe would &quot;be that weshould reach the winter in the same conditions as last year when, after a series of continuoussmall advances, we found ourselves at the end. with no suf-fieient advantage to compensate our losses,    our men were(Atired and exhausted; our Army dessimated; our ranks de-pleted, so that proper training could not be carried out,aad in March we could not withstand the enemy&apos;s attack.If we are to enter upon a great offensive next year his advice would he to eonsdrve our Army for that purpose, togive it rest, to build up the American Army, and to bringour men to the highest possible piteh of training.    if general Ipoeh had decided on operations of this kind in thepresent year, he thought that the British Governmentshould have a very serious talk with him.Italy appeared to GMEBAL SMUAS to he the most promis-ing theatre,     he Allies had not achieved much there inthe past, mainly because General Cadorna*s judgment hadbeen wrong.   He thought it quite possible that conditionsnext year might be such that we should desire to selectthe Italian theatre for our big campaign,   $he position there, however, was that we could not move forward on tha.Piave, because the enemy was such a danger to our flank onthe mountain front.   His advances last year had brought

the enemy into an ideal position for threatening our flank,since, as General Cavan had explained, there was only avery short space &quot;between our defensive lines and the edge of the mountains.   Before any great operations could beundertaken on the Italian front, it was vitally necess-ary to widen the mountain front.   Hence, in the presentautumn, before winter sets in, we ought to secure thisflank and provide a good bastion to protect our flank inthe event of a future offensive.    She present proposal ofthe Chief of the Imperial General Staff was to send 3 or british divisions to train in Italy in winter.    She coursehe would recommend ?/ould be to press forward the develop-ment of the communications with Italy and to send divi-sions there, not in winter, but in the autumn^ in orderto clear this front, &quot;^hen we should be In a position tomake a big offensive on the Italian front next year if we wished to do so.    It was essential, however, to clear theflank this autumn.Shis brought him to the problem of 1919.    In regard tothis, he was in full agreement with Lord Milner,    He didnot question that the Western front was the decisive front,but from the beginning of the War it had always proved thefatal front.   She present War had shown that no one had a decisive superiority there.   Hence, what he feared wasthat even with the assistance of the Americans we shouldthrow away our strength on the Western front without ob-taining a decision.     What was necessary on the western front was to provide a defence which should be stable with-out seeking to take the offensive.    Shen we oould use oursurplus forces in some other theatre.    Shis had been theplan of the Germans in 1917.    Shey had held the western front with forces which they felt they oould rely on toprecent a break-through, even if they had to give some ground.    She balanoe of their forces had been transferred

to the East, where Russia had been knocked out.    Theyhad followed a similar course in 1916, when Roumania hadbeen knocked out, and 1^1915, when Serbia had been kneek-ed out.    Hence, the lesson was perfectly clear, that we ought to maintain a holding force on the Western front and create reserves for employment in other theatres,SIR ROBERT BORDM suggested that this plan of leaving a holding force on the western front would lead the Ger-mans to do exactly the same thing..GENERAL SMJ2S said this depended upon which side was able to make its preparations in secret.    She Germans wouldbe in an inferiority on the Western front, and would notbe in a position to&apos;take risks.   Moreover, we should re-main sufficiently active to compel them to leave their forces there,LORD MILNER said he wished to add one remark to what he himself had said.    Provided we could keep the whole of theGerman Army on the Western front, any margin of force we might have would.be of prodigious valuei   We might have a margin of strength on the Western front which,though not sufficient to obtain a decision, was ample to keep thewhole German force there.GENERAL SMUSS said he was inclined to agree with sir robert Borden that a purely military decision was notpossible in this war.   We ought, however, to bring ourweight to bear where the crust of the enemy1s resistancewa&quot;s thinnest.In reply to Mr. Massey he said that this point was noton the German front. Historically the Germans had alwaysproved &quot;frery .tough customers. The only way to break them,he believed, was to smash their Allies. Austria was in afeeble condition; the Bulgarian people, and possibly the: . &quot;;&apos;V&apos;: ;./-&apos;&apos;VvVV     -Bulgarian Army, were demoralised; Surkey had long been in

a miserable condition, and it was only the affair in theGaucasus that had revived her military spirit.&quot;   Hence, in-stead of pressing for a purely military decision we should use our military strength where we might exploit the eeon-omic and diplomatic position.MR MASSEY asked which of Germany^ Allies he would sel-ect?GENERAL SMUTS said that in this we must be guided large-ly by the General Staff.    But, as a matter of policy, weshould not mass the whole of our forces on the western front, where we might only smash ouriArmies to pieces, butwe should rather direct our efforts towards smashing Ger-manyls Allies,   When Germany saw her Allies being broken up she would probably make peace,    in short, he would de-pend as much on the moral and diplomatic as on the milit-ary factor.MR HUGHES said that what we desired was to reaeh a pos-ition where the Military power of Germany was broken.   Nomoral factor would give us the victory we desired,    sakethe ease of South Africa.    Supposing, at a peace Confer-ence, they said they wanted German East Africa; or suppos-ing Australia said they wanted the Islands in the Pacific;or if Great Britain said she wanted Palestine, or Mesopo-tamia^   What would the german s rqp ly if they were stillentrenched in France and Flanders?   we could only get what we wanted by giving them a thrashing. IGENERAL SMUTS said he also was for victory in the field.1  . V&quot;:;&apos; -      MtH*\--But he thought it was a great mistake to think that we VYcould get this by smashing the German Army on the Western / \front.   The Allies would only smash their own armies inx /.the attempt.   He wanted to get military victories else- V&apos;&quot;i&apos;      - &apos; &apos;      : &apos; &apos;&apos;t,&apos;d    !dv; &apos;\ivtS.,&apos;.   - :      -      -   - . viva -:&apos;^-s.Vwhere.MR HUGHES reminded his colleagues that he had asked LordOavan if we could smash Austria, and had not received a

very satisfactory reply.THE PHIME MINISTEE said that it would not he possibleto complete the discussion and reach decisions today pbut he would like to offer some observations for the con-sideration of his colleagues before they met again.    Thedecision on this question was the most important that the &apos;Imperial War Cabinet had to take, for on it would dependnot merely the question of ultimate vjietory, but the pos-ition of the British Empire when ultimate victory wasaohieved.   He himself had been engaged for four years eon--   tinuously in similar discussions.    He believed that hewas the only Minister in Europe amongst the Allies or their opponents who had been in the War from the start.He had listened to discussions of this kind for fouryears, to the same predictions, the same arguments, thesame so-called facts.    Hence, he was perhaps less impress-ed than others at what was said about German moral, num-bers, prospects of sweeping victories, the decisive thea-t$fre, &amp;c.   He himself was in agreement with Mr. Hughes that unless dsfes peace was preceded by military victory, theposition would be unsatisfactory.    He had been taken totask for a sporting expression that he had made use of ear-lier in the War, namely, the &quot;knock-out blow.&quot;   Neverthe-less, in substance he had not altered his opinion.    Tothis extent he disagreed with General smuts.    If we didnot achieve a military decision, military opinion in Ger-many would be always sayings &quot;We held them up all throughthe War; if only we had provided a proper stock of copperor cotton, or some other material, we should have woh.i:flConsequently, he believed that a military victory was evenmore important than the securing of the terms of peace ;,.iwedesired.    In the event of a military victory we could dV\afford to be more generous m- fWA- ^jh^- iS^A^vy^18. -  &apos;Y

He wished to invite the attention of his colleagues to two propositions:-(1) How to win without having our own Army, that is tosay, the Army of the British Empire, so beaten andshattered, that, in fact, at the end of the Warthe American Army would be the only one left:(2) How to win at all.I -1 LORD MIL1ER had said that we could only commence the campaign nest year with about 45 divisions,    in view of ourman-power situation he himself did not think we could im-prove on this estimate.    We were already in the greatest difficulty in regard to coal,    only that morning the Ship-ping Controller had called on him to say that our coal pos-ition was so serious that we were threatened with a eatas-trophe.   We could not supply our Allies or our munition works or our colliers, to say nothing of our households,which were a secondary consideration.If there was to be fighting on the western front itmust be on a gigantic scale, and we should be bound totake our share.    The fighting would be enormously costly.He would be extremely surprised if any one of the, 4 Brit-ish divisions that had lately been fighting with the Erenehand American Armies did not come out of the battle com-pletely shattered.    In fact, he ventured to predict thatthis would be the ease.    The great battle of next year would be precisely similar to the one now being fought,but on a larger scale.    The enemy would retire fightinginch by inch.    Their machine-guns would inflict enormouslosses.    The Germans were fighting their rearguard actioawith consummate skill.    Here among colleagues it would be  \a mistake to conceal the trutn, and we should&apos; speak     \n      &apos; ;&quot; Ifrankly, and we must admit that the Germans had a very&quot;  \. ,To AX&apos; s.fine Army, very highly trained and well led.   gsjk what  ; A....    :? \   \;did his remarks trend?   Y/e should begin the year with 45divisions.    How many should we have at the end? -Year after a-v A Ax - &apos;; x&apos;v    \-  - .19* s ;iA.

year the War Office had made demands on the Governmentfor such and such a number of men to replace losses.    Theyhad not feEss received all they asked for.    Broadly speakinghowever, the Government had given them 800,000 men a year.That was the number given last year.    Next year we couldnot supply them.    This year we had begun the campaign isi th58 divisions; we had poured in 500.000 men, now we only hacju53 first-class divisions left, notwithstanding that a di-vision had been brought from Palestine, and the Ex&amp;xa;equivalent of the infantry of a division had been brought from igsacEX&amp;tes: salonica.    This was the result of five months of defensive warfare.   Next year, we could not find500*000 men to replace casualties.   Consequently, next year if big fighting occurred, our Army would be reduced byhalf.    The same might be said of the Fraich.    The UnitedStates Army alone would be larger.   He ciid not believethat we could obtain a decision on the Western front nextyear.    We might batter them, fend possibly they might haveto sue for peace.    What would be the conditions when thatoccurred?   America would have an Army equivalent to 12qdivisions, Prance perhaps 40, and theBritish Empire per-haps 23.    When Australia said she wanted the Pacifie Is- -lands, or Palestine, President Wilson would look down hisnose and says That he had entered the War with quite dif-ferent ideas in view, he would say he had his 120 divi-sions ready to continue the War, and he would ask what assistance we could give.    Before we decided to put our army on the table next year and get it smashed to pieceshe thought that this consideration ought to be very care-fully weighed.He now came to the second question as to how the war was to be won at all.   He agreed with Lord Milner that itwas very doubtful if we could win by attacking on the west-em front,    in his experience of four years no Chiefof the Imperial General staff, and no Military Leader

had ever failed to make sanguine predictions as to opera-tions on the Western front.    He did not &quot;blame them.    Tjn-les&amp;they possessed a sanguine temperament they could not make War at all.    Sanguine predictions had been made lasttheyear in regard to/Passchendaele offensive.    We had been told that the German moral was falling, and that our troops were confident.   At the end of the year it was the moral of our troops that had been broken, while that ofthe enemy had been raised,   next year we should not havea superiority of 3 to 2 vihioh we had in 19.16 and 1917 with-out achieving success.   He could only see one thing thatwould make the necessary difference, namely, if Russiacould so far recover as to become a formidable menace andcompel the Germans to detach the necessary superiority, .composed of good fighting divisions, not the riff-raff now on the Eastern front, to crush it.   In three or four monthswe might know whether this was likely to occur.The cjuestion arose as to what we oould do in the con-trary event?   He agreed with General Smuts the fundamentalerror that had been made in this War was always to attackon the strongest Instead of on the weakest front.MR MASSBY remarked that the enemy never did this.TEE PRIME MINISTER said the enemy had enly done ittwice since the very first onslaught, namely, at Verdunand in the present year.    If the enemy had gone eastwardor made an attack on Italy in the present year we should now be in a most difficult position. y\He would now invite the Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff to consider some of the things that had been saidtoday, particularly in the light of certain information received by himself from a sure source under an obligation of secrecy.    SHE PRIME MINISTER then read an extract fromthe Report referred to, the gist of which was that, ac-eording to the writer, who was a person well placed to,Ttid*re, we rmcrht to hpve followed rw the Ttnlinn

Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 31, 1918.victory over the Austrians; that the state of Austria wascritical in the extreme; that &quot;by an advance on that frontwe might have turned the flank of the German Empire; thatthe Italian front was the vital spot; that Austria was&quot;A tal;&amp; that was told&quot; and a doomed Empire whose subject- 1        &quot; AApeoples would either obtain autonomy under the ea aegis of theAllies or remain in servitude under German oppression.(She Meeting was then adjournedtill 11 o*clock on the following day)




</content>
</cab>
