<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/18 images: 154-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT &quot;Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1943.SECRET- CopyW.P. (43) 418.23rd September, 1943. /o 9No. 0  war CABINET.AIRCRAFT CAPACITY FOR TROOPS&quot; MAILS.Joint Memorandum by the Chairman of Overseas Mails Committee and thePostmaster-General.THE weight of air mails to the Forces, including the Merchant Navy, in north Africa, the Central Mediterranean, the Middle East and beyond, has con-tinued to grow, and further aircraft capacity is urgently required if the airgraphand air letter services are to continue to function efficiently in their present form.The combined weight of the airgraph and the light-weight air letter mails hasnow reached a weekly figure of about 17.500 lb., as compared with the presentweekly allocation of 15,000 lb., and it is likely that the total weight of the traffic(apart from Christmas postings which will be augmented this year by the pro-posed suspension of the EFM service and for which special provision will have to tie made) will reach 20,000 lb. by the end of this year. It is, however, quite impossible to give any firm estimate of this traffic as postings vary with the numberof troops and no form of rationing (other than the cost) is possible for the outwardmail.2. The Air Ministry arranged, some four months ago. to increase the weeklyallocation from 12.000 lb. to 15,000 lb., which latter figure represents about 25 percent, of the passenger and freight capacity available for the purposes of all departments. The Air Ministry has been unable to make a further increase inthis allocation and the Overseas Mails Committee has therefore investigated thepossibility of reducing the load to be carried by modifying the existing mailfacilities. Of the various alternatives considered, the only one meriting considera-tion was a reduction in the size of air letters, which constitute 99 per cent, of the weight of the troop mails. The Admiralty and War Office, however, are notprepared to accept this proposal and the Committee, the Air Ministry dissenting,is satisfied that it would arouse public resentment and should not therefore be pursued.3. The Post Office, the War Office and the Admiralty are strongly of opinionthat it is of vital importance from the point of view of morale, both in this countryand among the Troops, and for the war effort generally, to avoid any deterioration-tion in the Troops&apos; mails service. This can be clone only if an immediate increase is made in the aircraft capacity provided for the Troops&apos; mails. The Air-Ministry assert that the world-wide air transport capacity at present availablefalls far short of requirements, that additional capacity is constantly requestedfor every theatre of war. and that an increase in the present allocation for troopmails can only be effected by decreasing the allotment for the other purposes, someof which are of a strategic nature. In these circumstances, they consider thatthere should be further efforts to achieve greater economy in the weight of airmails.4- It is the view of the Committee, the Air Ministry dissenting, that theadditional capacity required should be provided. An increase in the mailscapacity allocation from 15,000 lb. to 20,000 lb. would meet immediate require-nients and leave a small margin for increases in traffic, but this may not avoid therecurrence of difficulties clue to the failure of the mail capacity to keep pace with[26127]
increases in the volume of Troops&apos; mails and the necessity to trouble the WarCabinet from time to time about small additions of aircraft capacity. The WarCabinet is therefore invited (i) immediately to increase the allocation from 15,000 lb. to 20,000 lb.; and(ii) to rule that in future air capacity should automatically be provided forairgraphs and light-weight air letters step by step with any increasein the postings.5. The War Cabinet will wish to be informed of one other possibility whichmay later relieve the strain on the existing aircraft capacity on the route via theMediterranean, namely, the possibility of providing a fast surface service atweekly intervals between the United Kingdom and the Western Mediterraneanwhich would provide alternative transport for urgent traffic, including passengers and freight. The matter is at present being examined by the Admiralty, but,unless such a service could be provided forthwith, it would not solve the immediate problem created by the inability of the Air Ministry, having regard to their other commitments, to provide aircraft capacity sufficient to carry the actual weight ofair mails for the Troops.(Initialled) D. C.H. C.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,23rd September, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
