<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/49/29 images: 246-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S&apos;G0YERNMENTPrinted&apos;for the War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET.W.M. (45)29th Conclusions.Copy No. g2WAR CABINET 29 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet war room on Monday, 12th March, 1945, at 6 00 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the chair for Items 2-10).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council (inthe Chair for Item 1).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson.M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for foreign affairs.   .The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.Minister of Reconstruction.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., secretary&apos;s of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Lord   Woolton,The following were also present:The Right  Hon.  Viscount  SimonLord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland(Items 6-10).The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade(Item 5).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt, M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries (Items 6-7).The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State * for foreign affairs (Items 1-4).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.
WAR CABINET 29 (45).Contents.minute no.                                     Subject. * page 1      Greece........      ....     ------     .... - ....      ....      ....    175Future-of British Control.2      War Crimes    ......,.      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    1753      Supplies for Liberated Areas ....      ....      ....      .....    1774      Marriages between members of the Allied ExpeditionaryForces and Germans        ........      ....      ....      ....    1775      Man-power     ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    178Labour for the Cotton-Spinning Industry.-6      War Gratuities....      ........      ....      ....      ....      ....    178Boyal Observer Corps. &apos;7      Administration of Forestry Policy........      ....      ....    179Forestry Bill.8      Divorce!...      .........      ....      ..........&apos;..    1799      Disclosure of Scientific Information        ....     .....      ....    180, .   Proposed Visit of French Air Mission.10      Select Committee on National Expenditure       ....      .....   181Proposed Mission to the Middle East.
175W.M.29(45)1Greece.Future ofBritishControl.  ,(previous reference:w&quot;.M.(45)10thConclusions,Minute 3.-)1. The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (45) 138) recommend-ing acceptance of. the proposals, made&quot; by the Resident Minister,Central Mediterranean, for the future British organisation in greece once the immediate operational phase was over. Theproposals had been broadly accepted in discussions at Athens, a record of which had been circulated to the War Cabinet.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theseproposals resulted from conversations with Mr. Macmillan and field-Marshal Alexander in Athens. The Chiefs of Staff authorised him to say that they were in entire agreement with them. We were anxious to reduce our military commitment as far as possible, butGreece would need some assistance from us for a time. the increases in personnel that would be involved would not be substan-.tial and could be met by transfers from Ueneral Scobie&apos;s Head-quarters to the British -Embassy. If the scheme was approved inprinciple, the details would be worked out in consultation with theTreasury, War Office and other interested Departments. He was anxious that the United States Government should be informed ofour plans and invited to associate themselves with our policy : their co-operation would be specially welcome on the financial andeconomic side.The War Cabinet-Endorsed the proposals set out in W.P. (45) 138.War Crimes. 2.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous       Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W-P- (45) 121) reportingReference:      that the United Nations War Crimes Commission had prepared theW.M. (44) I52nd draft of a Convention on the surrender of war criminals which, theyConclusions,    recommended, should be concluded between the Governments of the minute 6i)      United Nations.   The Foreign Office and other interested Depart-ments considered that so formal a procedure was to be deprecated;that so far as this country was concerned the essential objects of thedraft Convention could be secured by executive action; and that theconclusion of such a Convention would in practice hinder ratherthan ,assist those objects.  The Foreign Secretary therefore recom-mended that His Majesty&apos;s Government should -address to theAllied Governments represented on the Commission a Note (thedraft of which was reproduced as Annex &quot;A&quot; to this Memo-randum) explaining their objections, but &quot;giving an assurance that,so far as His Majesty&apos;s Government were concerned, no serious difficulty was likely to arise in practice about the surrender of war criminals or of Quislings.  While the Soviet Government were not. represented on the Commission and could not be approached on thelines suggested, the general issue was to be discussed, at their request, in the European advisory commission, and.it might be thatin the result similar arrangements could be concluded with theSoviet Government.The Lord Chancellor agreed with the Foreign Secretary that,so far as concerned the surrender of persons in this country,.the objects of the draft Convention could be achieved more satis-factorily by executive action. We could also, in his view, be reasonably certain that, on the alternative procedure which we proposed ourselves to follow, we should be able to lay hands on the few individuals whom we might wish to bring to this country for trial.The Home &apos;Secretary supported the Foreign Secretary&apos;sproposals, but made the following&apos;points : (a) Great care would have to be taken in administration toensure that we could justify to the full the use of thepower of deportation in each individual case.  We must
be able to rebut any suggestion that this power was being used for the purpose of enabling foreign governments to get control of their political opponents. -(b) In peace-time the Home Secretary&apos;s power to deport an alien of his own initiative, and not in pursuance of a recommendation by a court, had been sparinglyexercised. The proposal in W.P. (45) 121 involved ^ amuch freer use of that power : but the circumstances inwhich it would be exercised were of course exeptional and related to war conditions.(c) Though the procedure proposed was that of deportation,not extradition, there might be criticism on the groundthat the Extradition Acts gave special protection againstsurrender for &quot;political&quot; offences. As against this,it could be claimed that war crimes were not&quot;political&quot; offences.Further points made in discussion were : *; (d) Would this proposal involve pledging the personaljudgment of future Home Secretaries ? The view of theWar Cabinet was that the decision of the Home Secre-tary to make a deportation order was an administrativediscretion which could be exercised in pursuance of, Government policy. It was not on the same footing ashis personal duty to advise the Crown on the exerciseof the prerogative of mercy. Moreover, the scheme proposed need not involve pledging the Home Secretaryto hand over any individual named. by any foreign government. As at present drafted, paragraph 6 of theproposed Note might imply that we would surrender anyperson in respect of whom the War Crimes commission had reported that a sufficient case existed to justify his being brought to trial. This might limit our discretionunduly; and The Prime Minister suggested that these words should be amended to read: &quot;His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would of course attach all due importanceto any report by the War Crimes Commission that asufficient case existed against any alien civilian tojustify his being brought to trial.&quot; t *(e) There was a risk that an individual who was about to be handed over under the proposed scheme might apply tothe Courts for a declaration of habeas corpus. Thatmight lead to public discussion. It was suggested (andthe War Cabinet agreed) that this was a further argument for the arrangements now under discussionbeing administered with great discretion, and that weshould hot hesitate to refuse to accede to a request ifwe were satisfied that it was insufficiently based.(/) It was suggested that the Home Secretary might * seeadvantage in establishing some special machinery toassist him in discharging, his duties under the scheme.(g) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs suggested,and the War Cabinet agreed, that it was unnecessary to consult the Dominions on the proposals in the foreign secretary&apos;s Memorandum.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposals of the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs as set out in W.P. (45) 121, and the draft note annexed thereto, subject to the amendment noted inparagraph (d) above.
177W.M.29(45).Supplies foeLiberatedAreas.(previous reference:W.M.(45)23rdConclusions,Minute 4.)3. At the request of the Prime Minister The Lord Presidentof the Council gave the War Cabinet an account of his recent visit to France, Belgium and Holland, and of his impressions of thefood&apos;situation in these countries.A full record of the Lord Presidents statement and subsequentdiscussion is attached as an Appendix to these Minutes.. The Prime-Ministerthanked the Lord President of the Council,on behalf of the War Cabinet, for making a personal visit to these areas and giving them his first-hand impressions of the presentconditions of the civil population.The War Cabinet-Invited the Lord President of the Council to review thesituation in consultation with the Ministers with whom he had considered the supply problems of these areasbefore his visit; and to consult&quot; with the Chiefs of Staffon the preparations to be made for bringing relief to thecivil population in occupied Holland on its liberation.Marriages 4.   The War Cabinet considered a report by the Lord Presi-between dent of the Council (W.P. (45) 147), as Chairman of the ArmisticeMembers of and Post-War Committee, on a proposal that S.C.A.E..F. shouldthe Allied promulgate a law in occupied Germany under which marriagesExpeditionary between members of the Allied Expeditionary Forces and GermansForces and would be prohibited, and, where performed in contravention of thisGermans. law, would be declared invalid.The Lord President of the Council said that his Committeewere in full agreement with the policy of non-fraternisation andfavoured the prohibition of marriages between Germans and members of the occupying Allied Forces. The majority of theCommittee felt, however, that great difficulty was likely to arisewith the Churches, with Parliament and with public opinion if\ such marriages were invalidated. Invalidation would be repugnantto public opinion : it would penalise the children of such marriages,rather than their parents: and, even if now approved, such asanction was unlikely to be maintained for long.The First Lord of the Admiralty and The Secretary of Statefor War said that in supporting the proposal- to invalidate thesemarriages they were influenced by the view of their military advisers that nothing short of invalidation would suffice to securethe effective enforcement of the non-fraternisation order. Further,the Supreme Commander, who was the competent authority for thispurpose, was anxious to legislate on these lines, and already hadthe support of the United States War Department for this course.The general view of the War Cabinet was that, while every -thing possible should be done to discourage marriages between members of the Allied Expeditionary Forces and Germans, and tosecure that severe penalties were imposed on persons contractingsuch marriages, they could not support the proposal that marriagescontracted in contravention of this law should be invalidated.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for War, toarrange for the -views of the War Cabinet as recordedabove to beGovernment.communicated   to   the   United   States
Man-Power.Labour forthe Cotton-SpinningIndustry.WarGratuities.RoyalObserverCorps. &apos; -(previous reference:W.M.(45)19thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum hy; theMinister of Production (W.P. (45) 144) on the man-power needs ofthe cotton-spinning industry.The Minister of Production explained that there was a seriousprospective deficiency in the supply of cotton textiles. He was seeking the maximum relief from the United States; but Our case for further assistance from them-must rest on proof that we were doing everything possible to help ourselves. Special measures were therefore required to increase the level of production in thiscountry, and the first step was to get back into the industry as manyformer cotton operatives as was possible. The Ministry of Labourand National Service estimated that, if they were free to withdrawthese from munitions and other work, they could restore about 2,450women to the spinning and doubling sections of the industry; andthis, coupled with the reopening of a few closed mills, might induceabout 1,000 non-directable women to return to those sections. these measures would involve some risk of marginal injury to munitions production, particularly in four firms in the Oldham area,particulars of which were given in paragraph 6 of his Memorandum.He recommended, however, that the Ministry of Labour and.National Service should be authorised to withdraw these cottonoperatives, without prior substitution.The War Cabinet were informed that the First Lord of theAdmiralty and the Minister of Supply were prepared to accept this risk of marginal injury to war production in this area. TheMinister of Aircraft Production had not felt able to accept the riskof some consequent shortfall in the aircraft production programme.The view of the War Cabinet was that, at the present stage ofthe war, this risk should be accepted. The types of aircraft affectedwould be heavy bombers; and the casualty rate for these types wasbelow the estimate on which production programmes had been based.The First Lord of the A dmiralty said that he assumed that his department would be given an opportunity for discussion before theMinistry of Labour and National Service withdrew from firms on admiralty work key workers whose transfer would throw a numberof other workers out of employment. He agreed that, in all other cases, these cotton operatives might be withdrawn without prior consulation.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposals set out in W.P. (45) 144 for thewithdrawal of ex-cotton operatives, without prior substi-tution, from munitions and other work.6. The War Cabinet had before them a report submitted bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of State for Air(W.P. (45) 140) in pursuance of the War Cabinefs request, made attheir meeting on the 13th February, for a detailed statement of thearguments for and against the grant of war gratuities to officers ofthe Royal Observer Corps.The report set out the arguments in favour of the view that officers of the Royal Observer Corps should be regarded as eligiblefor war gratuities; and examined the possibility that a decision inthis sense might have repercussions in other Services. The con-clusion reached was that officers of this Corps could be distinguished from other classes, such as R.A.F. Education Officers, who woreService uniform while paid on a Civil Service basis; and it was recommended that, in respect of eligibility for war gratuities,officers of the Royal Observer Corps should be treated like other civil Defence workers and not like Civil Servants.After a short discussion, the War Cabinets-Agreed that officers of the Royal Observer Corps shouldbe regarded as eligible for the Civil Defence war gratuity.
179 .     W.M.29(45).AdmMstvation 7, The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum by theof Forestry Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and the Secretary of StatePolicy. for Scotland (W.P^ (45) 148) covering the draft of a Bill designedForestry Bill, to giveeffect to the War Cabinets decision of the 31st August, 1944,(Previous that responsibility for forestry policy should be transferred to the reference: Agriculture Ministers, and that the Forestry Commission should beW.M. (44) 113th reconstituted as an expert body responsible to those Ministers for conclusions, advice on policy and for carrying out such functions as training,Minute 5.)      research and the management of forest holdings.- The War Cabinet were informed that the terms of the draftBill had been approved by the Legislation Committee on the27th February (H.P.C. (45) 8th Meeting). The proposed transfer&quot;of responsibility had been announced by the Chancellor of theExchequer in the House of Commons on the 15th February; and itwas unlikely that the Bill would give rise to serious-controversy inParliament. There might be some criticism of the proposed pro-cedure for the compulsory acquisition of land : the suggestion wouldprobably be made that the procedure should include some provision&apos; : for an appeal from the Ministers decision.  If this suggestion were pressed, it could be met by applying to these cases the new pro-cedure proposed under the Statutory Orders (Special Procedure)Bill.The War Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries andthe Secretary of State for Scotland to introduce the forestry Bill into the House of Commons &quot;in the terms ofthe draft annexed to W.P. (45) 148.Minute 2.)Divorce. 8. . The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum by the Lord(Previous Chancellor (W.P. (45) 127) drawing attention to the continuedReference: increase in the number of petitions for divorce.W.M. (43) 175th The L0r4 chancellor recalled that as a result of the WarConclusions, Cabinets review of the position at the end of 1943, three additional judges had been appointed to the Divorce Division and new arrange-ments had been made for taking all classes of divorce at Assizes.In the following twelve months, the increase in the number ofpetitions for divorce had far exceeded his expectations. In 1944,no less than 19,155 petitions were filed in England and Wales, ascompared with 10,350 in 1938 and 15,523 in 1943. As a result, alarge number of petitions remained outstanding at the close of theyear. In London, 2,992 cases had to be carried over to the new term.And, though the facilities for taking divorce at Assizes had not yetbeen available for a full year, he was satisfied that the divorce listsin the provinces were so heavy that special measures would be needed to deal with the arrears of work in the provinces as well asin London.There was no reason to suppose that the peak of the demandfor divorce had been reached: the number of petitions wouldprobably continue to rise until the year after the end of hostilities.He was satisfied that the Judges could not hope to deal with thevolume-of cases; and he suggested that steps should be taken tomeet the situation before public outcry developed.  -He therefore proposed that undefended divorce cases shouldbe tried by Registrars of the Divorce Court. The Registrars wouldsit in open court and would have all the powers of a Judge to dispose of undefended cases. They would have the right to refer difficultcases to a Judge, and they Would be under the direction and controlof the President of the Divorce Division. By concentrating on theundefended cases, the Registrars would give considerable relief tothe Judges, who would then be better able to devote their time tothe defended cases and to other cases of special difficulty.- Points in discussion were-(a) The Home Secretary asked whether the Lord chancellor was satisfied that there were conclusive reasons against
Disclosure ofScientificInformation.proposed visit ofFrench AirMission.(previous reference:W.M. (45)28thConclusions,Minute 4.)9. The War Cabinet resumed their discussion of theMemorandum (WP. (45) 153) in which the Minister of Productionand the Paymaster-General asked for guidance on the extent towhich soientific information should be disclosed to a Mission whichthe French were proposing to send to this country and to the UnitedStates to survey the field of aircraft production and development.Opinion was divided on this question. Some Ministers feltthat little or nothing should be disclosed to the French at this stage of the war. Information now could not result in production from france which would be available in time for use, in the european war. The French request ought therefore to be handled on the basis,not of assisting the war-time production of an Ally, but of helpinggiving divorce jurisdiction to the County Courts. this possibility had been mentioned by the WedgwoodCommittee; and it should be borne in mind that the workof the County Courts would decrease when the existing. system of workmen&apos;s compensation was replaced by thenew scheme of Industrial Injury Insurance.The Lord Chancellor said that he was satisfied thatit would be inexpedient to confer divorce jurisdiction-on the County Courts.  The Wedgwood Committee had- not recommended this course.     County Court Judgesdealt with a wide range of miscellaneous work and hadno special knowledge or experience of divorce law.   TheRegistrars&apos;of the Divorce Division, on the other hand,had special knowledge of divorce work.  Moreover, theywould work under the general direction of the Presidentof the Divorce Division, and this would secure thatmeasure of uniformity in divorce decisions which it was important to maintain.(b) Was it proposed that this jurisdiction should be given toRegistrars in the provinces as well as in London ?The Lord Chancellor said that he would propose to begin with a limited experiment in London. The&apos;President of the Divorce Division was, however, anxious that this system should be extended in the near future to some of the larger provincial centres, such asBirmingham and Manchester. It would be convenient,therefore, that the legislation should be so framed as to empower Registrars generally to exercise this jurisdic-tion. The extent to which particular Registrars were permitted to handle these cases could be determined laterby an administrative decision.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in someprovincial centres the Registrar acted also in the county court and could not be said to have the same specialisedknowledge of divorce procedure as had the Registrars ofthe Divorce Division in London. There might beobjections to allowing these Registrars to exercise thepowers of a Judge in undefended divorce cases; and itmight be preferable to arrange for London Registrars togo on circuit to the Assizes at which it was necessaryto relieve the Judges of this work.The Lord Chancellor undertook to consider thispoint.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposals in W.P. (45) 127, subject to thepoint noted at (b) above; and authorised the LordChancellor to discuss the details of his scheme with thePresident of the Divorce Division and to proceed with thepreparation of the legislation required.
181

W.M. 29 (45).

another country to establis its peace-time industry for the manufacture of aircraft. The concession of secret information for this purpose would be a valuable card in any negotiationsfor a military alliance.

On the other side it was argued that it would be difficult to justify a refusal to disclose any information of this kind. Over a large part of the field no question of military security arose. French pilots were already flying many of the British aircraft concerned, and were fully familiar with their equipment; and it was likely that full information about many of these aircraft was already available to the Germans. It was true that the French wanted this information for the purpose of establishing their peace-time aircraft industry; but from the long-term point of view we had much to gain by linking the French industry with our own, so that they would look to us for the supply of engines, instruments and other articles of equipment. If we declined to give them this information, they would turn for assistance to the United States, who would probably take this opportunity of building up firm commercial links between their aircraft industry and the aircraft industry which would in any event be established in France.

Discussion then turned on the terms of the telegram to the Joint Staff Mission at Washington, which was reproduced in the Annex to W.P. (45) 153. Some Ministers felt that it would be preferable not to give any lead at this stage to the United States Chiefs of Staff; but to open matters by a simple inquiry inviting their views on the extent to which scientific and technical information should be disclosed to this Mission. Other Ministers took the view that the United States authorities would be disposed to go further than we ourselves would wish to go in the direction of full disclosure to the French; and that, if we gave no lead at the outset,we were likely to be faced with proposals for a much more generous policy than that suggested in the Annex to W.P. (45) 153. We should then find it more difficult to persuade the United States authorities to adopt a more restrictive attitude.

After further discussion, the War Cabinet--

Invited the Minister of Production and the Paymaster-General, in consultation with the Chiefs of Staff and the Ministers directly concerned, to consider how the instructions contained in the Annex to W.P. (45) 153 could best be revised, in the light of the War Cabinet&apos;s discussion, so as to secure a more restrictive approach to this problem; and authorised them to despatch a further telegram to the Joint Staff Mission at Washington if agreement on its terms could be reached without further reference to the War Cabinet.

     ------------------------

Select Committee on National Expenditure.

Proposed Mission to the Middle East (Previous Reference: W.M. (45) 25th Conclusions, Minute 5.)

10. The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed the war Cabinet that the Chairman of the Select Committee on National Expenditure had discussed with him a proposal that a Mission of six or seven members of the Committee should visit the Middle East to enquire on the spot into such matters as the cost, use and possible disposal of constructional works, surplus stores and plant; the civil affairs organisation; and the civilianf staffs employed for war purposes. The Mission might also enquire into the work of U.N.R.R.A. and the British Council in the Middle East.

The Chancellor sought the views of the War Cabinet on this proposal. If facilities for such a Mission were granted, he thought that the Mission should be from enquiring into operational questions or questions of policy and should be required to furnish in advance a list of the subjects which they wished to investigate. In reply to enquirie, he said that the Select Committee had not previously undertaken any such investigations outside the United Kingdom.

[29799--3]
Discussion./showed that.it was the general view of the WarCabinet that it would be inexpedient that a Mission of Membersof Parliament should visit Egypt at this time to undertake an enquiry of this character.The War Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to inform theChairman of the Select Committee on National Expendi-ture that the War Cabinet would not favour the despatchof such a Mission to the Middle East.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,12th March, 1945.APPENDIX.-   France.The Lord President of the Council said that he had first gone to Paris andthat he had seen the United States Ambassador, whom he found fully alive*tothe need for assistance for France and Western Europe. He had met six or sevenFrench Ministers, and had-had a full discussion with them on questions connectedwith relief for the liberated areas transport, food, &amp;e.-From what he had seen of the situation during his visit, he derived theimpression that, save in regard to certain exceptional areas, France was beingfed reasonably well. He had visited some of the poorer parts Of Paris and theappearance of the people whom he had seen had not suggested either starvationor any serious privation. So long as supplies continued coming forward throughthe S.H.A.E.F. military programme on their present basis of a sufficiency toprevent disease and unrest, he thought that there was no reason for specialanxiety. The French were disturbed over the problem of transport, butMinisters and others whom he had seen, including General de Gaulle himself,had been most appreciative of the help that this country had given.He had seen S.H.A.E.F. and had long discussions on the transport and foodsituations. At present the general situation was that the supplies were coming forward, but danger lay ahead in the months before the harvest, viz., June&quot;to august, for which supplies had not yet been approved in the United States.France, like all other liberated countries, was living in a &quot; ship-to-mouth &apos;&apos; conrdition. There was nothing in the ground except vegetables, and in the comingsummer we might have a very serious position in both procurement and shipping.The French were quite ready to take over the handling of their own supplies inthe near future. He thought they were sufficiently well organised to Ibe ableto deal with this and S.H.A.E.F. were ready to hand, it over to them; but, if andwhen they took it over, they would still have to share the available transport withthe armies. The road and rail situation, and especially the rail situation,, had,however, very greatly improved. *His feeling was that the French were trying hard to get their country intoworking order again. The chief difficulty on the machinery side was m his view the complications that arose at the Washington end.As regards civil supplies, while we were now concentrating on the pro-vision of food, the French were very anxious to get some of their industriesgoing as soon as possible. In the normal way France had been self-supporting %in food, and even to some extent a country with a food surplus. Their existingdifficulties had been aggravated by abnormal climatic conditions, floods andfrosts, and by the destruction of communications in the course of the battle. Buthe felt that really good work had been done since the liberation of France, andthat matters were beginning to move in the right direction. The difficult problem was the deficit area of the South. The coal situation was much better. Parishad been cold because of the stoppage of transport. The coal was comingthrough now, and electricity based on water power was again; in running order.
183W.M. 29 (45).v     Belgium.&apos; In Belgium his impression was that-the general situation was quitereasonable at the present time. He had been at great pains to observe conditionsboth in Brussels and in Maastricht. The Belgian children whom he had seenhad looked well-fed and contented. In Belgium, as in all these countries, theproblem was of course primarily an urban one. The food ration on which thepopulation of Belgium were subsisting was a very narrow one, and here, as inFrance, they were living on a &apos;&apos; ship-to-mouth &quot; basis. He had noticed no foodqueues, and on the whole thought that the present situation was not too bad. Asin France, a dangerous time lay ahead unless food supplies could be secured inthe early summer, and here, too, transport was an acute problem. preparations were being made to sow, and there were more signs of life in some ways inBelgiuln than in France, thanks to the fact that it was an active base of operations. We should not, however, forget that there might be an extra strain on the Belgian transport situation the further we went east of the Rhine.He had discussed the situation with Belgian Ministers the Ministers ofFood and Transport, and the Prime Minister. They were all very anxious toget on with the reconstruction of their industrial life, and if certain rawmaterials could be supplied to them, their industrial machine might turn out some useful work for the Allies. He thought this point was worth looking into,since a very little might produce disproportionately large results. If we couldonly prime the pump they could make great progress.At one time there were very substantial losses by pilfering between the ports and inland destinations. This was largely because trains carrying civil supplieshad had to wait in sidings because of the higher priority granted to operationalmilitary traffic.  The position in this respect was now easier.Holland.In liberated Holland he had visited the Island of Walcheren. The floodsthere were most serious, but the people were in good heart, looked well and were clearly very happy to be freed. He had the impression that most of the farmershad put by a certain amount of supplies. There were four deep breaches in thesea dams on which the Dutch were already working; while they had engineersfor this purpose they needed pumping machinery, &amp;c, for which he understoodthey.had indented to us. They hoped to be. able to close these breaches byNovember or even sooner. If they could do this, they could then proceed todrain off the flooded areas, and thought they &quot;might be able to sow rye for 1946and get the land into good heart in say, two years&apos; time. It was most important that this work should be pressed forward without delay, since otherwise thebreaches would widen.He had also visited Flushing, where matters were well in hand. A 25,000-tonsteamer had been left there undamaged by the Germans. There was a good ship-yard at Flushing which was doing work for the Royal Navy. People both there and in the other islands looked very well. At Maastricht the good condition ofthe population might be due to the presence of occupying United States forces and to the indirect advantage which this represented in terms of food.On the other hand, a problem of the utmost gravity lay ahead in respect of occupied Holland.. . Germany. -He had paid a visit to Aachen but had nothing in particular to report asregards conditions in Germany.In general, he thought that the position as regards food had been prettygood until liberation, and had deteriorated after liberation, largely becausetinder the German Occupation the Germans had been at pains to feed the areasnow liberated in the interests of keeping their production going fof war purposes.He saw no immediate cause for anxiety over the next two months, but the period before the harvest would be a very serious one.The Prime Minister warmly thanked the Lord President on behalf of theWar Cabinet for making his journey to North-West Europe, and expressed theirsense of obligation to him for the first-hand information which he had brought back. In general, the Lord President&apos;s account confirmed what he had himselffelt for some time, that there was no very great shortage of food in these areas.He accepted, however, the potential seriousness of the position in occupied
Holland and the importance of providing-&quot;for immediate relief on its liberation.He thought we should arrange to have flying columns of food in readiness to tideover itssinhabitiants*aft6r the evacuation or expulsion i of the (oceupyihg Germanlf6rces; from ^Holland, -The -letter ffr6m the Dutch .Brime&apos;&apos;^idQaist^&apos;&apos;-vvlQi(^.-lie-I^circulated to %he War Cabinet under W.P. (45) 154 gaves a heartrending accountof conditions in that coiMtry. :      &quot;Occupied Holland. -&apos;The Prime Minister then4rivited the Lord^ifesidmt^to^iw^e War Cabinethis views as to our readiness to take adviantage-of any evacuation of occupiedHolland hy the Germans or of their expulsion from it.The Lord President df - the Council saia&apos;that  &apos;he was attxiohs to &quot;emphasiseto the War Cabinet the very grave nature of the problem that was&apos;likely to5 arise on the liberation of this part of Holland. It seemed quite likely&apos; that the germans would leave few, if any, reserves of food. The population would have1 been worndown by long privations. Immediate remedial action would be necessary. Itwas, in his, judgment, of the first importance that, in considering any-militaryoperations&apos;that might haye a bearing on the position in&apos;Hollaha,&quot;andsequally in considering - tJhe position that woulcT arise in the event of: German evacuation,we should give thought to the necessity for immediate action once circumstancesmade that possible. In particular, we should bear in mind the: possibility of sending in Dutch leaders to be dropped by parachute at a favourable moment;we should haveready prepared dumps of supplies of the appropriate&apos; kind to besent across the border; the troops on the Dutch borders should be fully trained in the roles that they were to. per form on the liberation of occupied Holland.The emergency was one&apos;that might arise at very short&apos; notice, and our respon-sibility would be heavy if we were not ready and prepared to deal with it. Hedeveloped in some detail the circumstances&apos;in which assistance might be givenoperationally or otherwise to the area at present occupied.&apos; The Prime Minister said that the Lord Presidents statement againemphasised the risk of further demands being made on our own very small stocksof fOod. There was a real risk that we should be pressed by the United states to. make concessions which in present circumstances it was impossible for us to afford, and he would feel bound to resist any such pressure. We would not bebehind the United States in sacrifices, but the sacrifices we had already madewere great and our level of food consumption was substantially below that stillprevailing in the United States. It might well be that if we were faced with ademand for an extra 30,000 or 40,000 tons of supplies to meet the critical needs,e.^., of occupied&apos;Holland&apos;over a short-period, we would have4o produce it, butwe could go no further. He suggested^ that the Lord President&quot; should himselfsee the Chiefs of Staff&apos; and- discuss with them what could usefully be done, andthat his ad hoc Committee,; possibly in consultation with the Chiefs of Staff,should, before being finally wound up, be reconvened and&apos; submit to the WarCabinet specific proposals for action.The lford:President of the Councilsaid; thatrhe^wphld-be^veryrready toreconvene the ad hoc. Committee as suggested by the Prime Minister. Hethought it fair1 to say that the members of me United States&apos;Forces whom he had met during his tour fully appreciated the demands that had been&apos;!madeJupon us and the need for a substantial contribution by the United States. The most effective method for keying up the situation would be that the operations forthe relief of occupied Holland on * its liberation should be given first priorityafter military operations, and in particular that arrangements should beTmadVthat the troops5 nearest the borders of occupied Holland should be detailed forthe work they were, to do in regard to relief as those areas ceased 1o be occupiedby the Germans. -He agreed entirely with the importance of.protecting theposition in this country. The danger was that, as there was nothing; in thenature of a- pipe-line in any of the occupied countries,; this country was used asa pipe-line. He desired in conclusion to emphasise the importance of reaching decisions as a matter of urgency in the course of the next few days.



</content>
</cab>
