<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 57-64</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet;  March 1962C. (62) 52 Copy No. 5 016th March, 1962CABINETECONOMIC SURVEY, 1962Note by the Chancellor of the exchequer circulate herewith for consideration by my colleagues a draft of Part Oneof the Economic Survey, 1962. An earlier version has been discussed by theEconomic Policy Committee and the present draft attempts to take account of the amendments which the Committee suggested.2. The draft follows the pattern adopted in the Economic Survey, 1961. Themain events of 1961 are summarised in the first half of Part One; and the secondgives tentative forecasts of economic developments in the remainder of 1962 andsuggests the main objectives of Government policy.3. Part Two of the Survey, which gives a detailed analysis of economic developments in 1961, is being prepared by officials separately and need not bediscussed by Ministers collectively.4.   I propose that the whole Survey should be published on 4th April.5. National income figures for the fourth quarter of 1961 will become available shortly and I wish to reserve the power to make minor amendments to the draft which these may require.S. L.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,15th March, 1962.60541SECRET
CONFIDENTIAL PROOFECONOMIC SURVEY, 1962&quot; PART one . THE UNITED KINGDOM ECONOMY IN 1961Introduction1. The year 1961 saw major developments in economic policy. Thedecision was made to apply for membership of the European economic community. New fiscal powers were asked for in the Budget Speech inApril to enable the level of demand to&apos; be regulated, if necessary, betweenBudgets. One of those was used in July. Another development was theintroduction of a policy explicitly designed to keep growth in incomes in line with the growth in output and so lessen ithe pressure on costs.2. Another, development of long-iterm importance during the year wasthe opening of discussions leading to the formation of the National economic development Council.The United Kingdom economy3. At the beginning of 1961 the ecj^economy faced two dangers, an increasing pressure of home demand upon resources and a loss of confidence in the pound because of domestic inflation and a continuing large deficit on thebalance of payments. Though there had heen little increase in economic activity at home during the previous year, shortages of labour, particularly of skilled labour, were becoming more widespread and, in most parts of the  country, more acute; and labour costs were rising rapidly.4. In April, 1961 the Budget accordingly provided for some net increasein taxation ; the borrowing requirement was reduced to an estimated  69million in 1961/62, compared with an estimate of  318 million for 1960/61 ;and powers were sought first to impose a surcharge or make a rebate of upto 10 per cent, on purchase tax and the other main customs and excise duties (excluding protective duties), and secondly to levy a surcharge of up to 4s. a week on employers&apos; national insurance contributions.5. In the period up to July, 1961 personal spending, investment in fixed assets and current expenditure by the Government and local authoritiesrose quite rapidly. At the beginning of the year these increases had beenoffset by a sharp fall in the rate at which stocks were built up but fromthe early spring industrial production started to rise quickly. Exports,however, which had risen towards the end of 1960, did not increase afterthe first quarter of 1961.6. In spite of an unusually large number of immigrants and school-leavers, the shortage of labour persisted in many parts of the country. Therewas little change in the number wholly unemployed (after allowance forseasonal variations and for normal fluctuations in the number of school-leavers) and short time working fell.   By the end of July the number in
civil employment had risen by 235,000, at least 150,000 more than theusual seasonal increase, and reached a record level. Nevertheless.,labour costs continued to rise ; by the end of July the index of hourly wage rateswas 3f per cent, higher than at the end of December and d\ per cent, higherthan a year earlier ; and average hourly earnings rose even faster. Havingchanged little between the first half of 1958 and the middle of 1960, pricesstarted to rise again: costs, however, rose even faster, so that profit marginsfell.7. Though the balance of payments improved in the first half of 1961,it remained in deficit as it had been for the two previous years. The poundwas therefore vulnerable, and it came under very heavy pressure in thewave of speculation which followed the revaluation of the German and dutch currencies in March, when there was a large-scale withdrawal fromsterling.8. To alleviate these immediate difficulties a number of central banks,at a meeting in March of the. Bank of International Settlements at Basle,agreed to co-operate closely in the foreign exchange markets. Short-termassistance, amounting in all to  323 million, was given under these arrange-ments in the following months. Nevertheless the withdrawal from sterlingwas so great that the gold and convertible currency reserves fell in thefirst half of the year by  164 million. There was a further fall of  114million in July.9. There was by the middle of the year excessive pressure of demand athome, with rising coats and prices, and a continuing deficit in the balanceof payments, accentuated by a heavy withdrawal from sterling. It was against this background that a series of measures was announced on 25thJuly designed in the short term to restore the strength of sterling and, inthe longer term, to increase the competitive strength of the economy. these measures included the imposition of the surcharge of 10 per cent, onpurchase tax and the other main customs and excise duties, a check inthe growth of Government expenditure, a special review of government expenditure overseas, an increase in Bank Rate from 5 per cent, to 7 percent, and further restrictions of credit. At the same time the Chancellorcalled for a pause in the increase of money incomes of all kinds in orderto bring the rise in incomes more into line with the growth of national productivity.10. In addition application was made for a substantial drawing from theInternational Monetary Fund. A drawing equivalent to  536 million anda stand-by arrangement equivalent to a further  178 million were sub-sequently arranged with the Fund.11. These measures rapidly restored confidence in sterling. The short-term outflow was stemmed and the reserves began to rise. By the endof 1961 the whole of the Basle assistance had been repaid,  150 million of the sterling held by the International Monetary Fund had beenrepurchased and the pound was again strong in the exchange markets.Bank rate was reduced from 7 per cent, to 6  per cent, on 5th october and to 6 per cent, on 2nd November, 1961. (It was further reduced to5$ per cent, on 8th March, 1962.)
12. The effect on the balance of payments as a whole was necessarilyslower. There was, nevertheless, a considerable improvement between thefirst and second half of the year. Domestic economic policy appears,therefore, to have begun to influence the current account. There was alarge inflow of capital, including the purchase of United Kingdom securitiesby overseas residents. This exceeded United Kingdom investment overseas,producing exceptionally a small net receipt on long-term capital account.The balancing item showed a slight net increase. There is no doubt thatthese movements were considerably influenced by the monetary policy.The external monetary position improved sufficiently to bring about a slightfavourable change for the year as a whole.13. At home the pressure of demand slackened between July and theend of the year. There was a fall in personal spending for several reasons ;the increase in personal incomes slowed down after the middle of the year ;there was a net reduction in hire purchase debt and in personal bankadvances in contrast to net increases earlier in the year; and pricescontinued to rise, partly because of the increase in indirect taxes inJuly and partly because of the rise in costs in the first half of the year.There were diverse movements among the other elements of demand.Current expenditure by the Government and local authorities continuedto rise. Investment in fixed assets reached a peak in the third quarterbut fell a little in the fourth. stock building diminished sharply in thethird quarter but recovered at the end of the year. The level of exportsremained unchanged.14. These changes together caused total production to fall a little and bythe end of the year there were some industries in which plant and labourwere under employed. The number of workers registered as unemployedwas slightly greater in December than it had been a year earlier.15. At the end of 1961 employment and output were both 2 per cent,higher than in the spring of 1960, so output per head had not grown.The failure of output per head to grow during the period may be attribut-able partly to the cuts in the standard working week negotiated in 1960and 1961 and to the consequent reduction of the hours worked. Thestandard working week was reduced on average from 44 to 42 hours in thetwo years ending in October, 1961, and average hours worked fell by nearly one hour twenty minutes. The stability of output per head does notappear to have been due to a decline in the pressure on demand, since,for example, unemployment was significantly lower at the end of the period.16. Largely as a result of agreements reached before July the index ofhourly rates rose by [2 per cent.] between July, 1961 and January, 1962,compared with [4J per cent.] in the corresponding period a year earlier.The prices of manufactured goods rose more slowly in the second half of1961. Profits continued to fall; in the second half of 1961 they were[4^ per cent.] lower than a year earlier and [13 per cent.] lower thanin the first half of 1960.
II.  THE PROSPECT IN 1962The World background17. In 1962 world industrial production may increase at a rate similarto that achieved last year. The expansion of the United States economyseems likely to continue for the time being. In Western Europe labourand productive capacity are very fully employed and a resumption of therates of growth of 1959 and 1960 is -therefore not to be expected ; but con-sumer demand is rising and the pause in the increase of production in!the middle of last year is unlikely to be more than temporary. As in previous years, trade between industrial countries seems likely to continueto rise faster than world trade as a whole ; but the (trade of primaryproducing countries, both exports and imports, will probably be morebuoyant (this year than last.The United Kingdom economy: demand, output and the balanceof payments18. The opportunities for the United Kingdom&apos;s exports are thereforegood; but they will be missed if export goods are not competitive andif the pressures of home demand on the economy become too great.19. The increase in personal spending is normally governed fairly closelyby the increase that takes place in total output and the corresponding increase in real personal incomes. In 1962 an additional stimulus topersonal spending is likely to come from an increase in borrowing on hire purchase credit, since it is expected -that a relatively large number&apos; of outstanding contracts will expire during 1962.20. In recent years current expenditure on goods and services by Govern-ment and local authorities has been increasing at about 3 per cent, a year in real terms. This rate of increase seems likely to continue in 1962,though for the central -Government alone it is expected to be little less.21. It seems probable that, in total, investment in fixed assets will risein 1962 but not perhaps by very much. Investment by the Government,the local authorities and the nationalised industries and public corporations-(together this accounts for nearly one-half of total investment), is expectedto rise by about 6 per cent, in real terms over the year. But investment in -the private sector may fall slightly.22. stock building increased at the end of last year despite a fall in production between the third and fourth quarters ; and there is reasonto believe that stocks were high in relation to current levels of outputat the end of the year. The rate at which stocks are built up may, therefore,be (relatively low for some time but there must eventually be a recovery.23. As -a result of these developments at home, -there should be some increase in the pressure of demand as the year progresses though it islikely to remain rather subdued in the first half of 1962. The growth ofproduction over -the year must largely depend on the timing and scale ofthe rise in exports. If this matches the opportunities available, produc-tion should expand at a rate that may be relatively slow at the beginningbut a good deal more rapid at the end of the year.
24. A further improvement in the balance of payments on current accountseems likely in 1962. Imports will build up again as output and stock-building rise but experience suggests that this may not start for some time.The terms of trade are expected to be favourable. Arrangements for exportfinance have been improved. The balance on long-term capital account islikely to be less favourable in 1962 than in 1961, since there were largereceipts, for example from the Ford transaction and advance repayment ofGovernment debt, in 1961 which are unlikely to recur on ithe same scalethis year. But on the whole the prospect seems to be of a stronger externalposition this year than last.Aims of economic policy25. The foremost aim of economic policy in 1962 must be to maintainconditions in which exporters in the United Kingdom can take advantageof the opportunities open to them to achieve a great expansion in theirsales.26. This cannot be brought about by Government action alone. But intwo important respects the Government can help. They can regulate the strength of total home demand which would otherwise compete withexport demand for the use of skilled labour and other scarce resources ;this has been the object of the Governmenfs policy in the last nine months.They can also influence the level of incomes and therefore the costs ofproduction.27. Throughout almost the whole of the post-war period our competitive&apos;strength in export markets has been persistently impaired by the tendency for money incomes in this country to rise much faster than national production, and consequently for our costs and prices to rise more rapidly than those of some of our chief competitors in export markets. The Govern-ment&apos;s incomes policy, if successful, will arrest this damaging trend. TheWhite Paper Incomes Policy: The Next Step (Cmnd. 1626) has set outthe considerations which in the Governmenfs view should affect the scale of increase of all forms of money income in 1962. If this policy is appliedand the rate of increase of money incomes in 1962 is kept within reasonable limits, our competitive strength will increase; and the nation as a whole will benefit from a more stable cost of living.28. In the longer iterm the aim must be to secure a satisfactory balanceof payments and to increase the resilience of the economy, its productivecapacity and the efficiency of its performance. It is essential that faster growth should be sought in this way. In this (task all have a part to play,both in Government and industry. The Government attach great value to the formation of the National Economic Development Council. The tasks of the Council have been defined by the Chancellor of the Exchequer asfollows:  -&quot; (a) to examine the economic performance of the nation with parti-cular concern for plans for the future in both the private and thepublic sectors of industry.(b) to consider together what are the obstacles to quicker growth,what can be done to improve efficiency, and whether the best use isbeing made of our resources.
(c) to seek agreement upon ways of improving economic performance,competitive power and efficiency, in other words to increase the rate&apos;of sound growth.&quot;29. Public opinion is increasingly aware of what these objectives mean;an example is the current concern about inadequate training of apprentices and of adult skilled labour. The impending reduction of tariffs, as wellas opening the way for exports, will help to stimulate industrial efficiencyat home, since ability to compete with imports will be as important as com-petitiveness in export markets. The Governmenifs plans for expandingscientific and technical education are producing results in the outstandingincreases in the number of scientists and engineers becoming qualified.30. This is the background against which we shall be working in 1962.Provided the pressure of demand is kept in check and the incomes policywidely applied, the country will be able to take advantage of the particularlyfavourable opportunities for exports in 1962. They may not remain so and itis essential to make the most of them. If we do, production could expandwithout a damaging increase in the pressure of demand upon resources andVithout renewed risk to the balance of payments. This is the only sound basis for sustaining economic growth.


</content>
</cab>
