<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 121-128</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government. (62) 689JiLMay^,1962CABINETAID TO UNDER-DEVELOPED countries memorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerIntroductionForecasts of aid expenditure over the next few years are now being prepared and are to be submitted in due course by the official Committeeon Development policy.     But this will take some weeks, and meanwhiledecisions will be required on at least two proposals for new aid commit-ments, to Egypt and to Nigeria, whose Finance Minister is about to arrive in London^    I have therefore felt it desirable, without anticipating the newforecasts, to set out in this memorandum the position about the current level of our aid expenditure, and to mention some other potential newaid commitments, so that this information can be taken into account in considering any particular proposals in this field which come forward inthe immediate future.The Current Level of Aid2.     Government expenditure on economic and technical assistance to under-developed countries (both bilateral and through multilateral agencies)has risen in each of the last five years and has more than doubled in thisperiod.    A further increase is expected in the current year under existing commitments.     The figures are as follows:-  million1956 - 57     ......................... 761957 - 58     .......................... 831958 - 59     .......................... 1101959 - 60     .......................... 131I960 - 61     .......................... 1521961 - 62 (provisional)............... 1601962 - 63 (estimate) .................. 183COPY NO.   &quot;j0
3.     In the memorandum on the Economic Situation which I circulated on 29th June, 1961, (C. (61) 89, paragraph 11), I proposed thataid expenditure should be held to  180 million a year.    I explained that&quot;on paper, existing commitments will result in expenditure of over 180 million both this year and next;  but I believe that this excess couldbe avoided by taking advantage of possible savings which may arise&quot;.In the event, this objective was achieved for 1961-62 with something to spare, but only because some of the recipients of our aid drewexceptionally slowly on sums available to them.     In particular, theGovernment of India drew only  17 million instead of  25 millionbecause, although they rapidly used up the loans available to financetheir general imports from the United Kingdom, there were delays inthe projects for which certain other loans were earmarked;  while theInternational Development Association used less than  1 million out ofour annual subscription of  9 million, again because the projects which they are financing take time to gather momentum, and we arenow holding altogether  16 million on call for the Association, apartfrom the further payment of  9 million which we will be making thisyear.4.    . The figure of  183 million for the current year comprises the budgetary provision  which has been made both above the line inDepartmental Estimates ( 89 million) and below-the-line ( 85 million)in respect of Exchequer loans to the Colonies, &quot;Section 3&quot; loans bythe Export Credits Guarantee Department and issues to the colonial development Corporation, together with  9 million in respect of thisyear&apos;s subscription to the International Development Association.This assumes that the Association will neither fall further into arrearsin using our subscription nor catch up on the existing arrears.    Asimilar assumption has been made about the rate at which India willmake use of the loans available to her.     Thus, leaving aside thequestion of new commitments, the estimate of  183 million must beregarded as subject to some variation in either direction, but there is obviously a distinct possibility of an excess over the figure of 180 million a year which we have had in mind.Future Commitmejitjs5.      What I have written above shows that this is a field in which itis particularly difficult to make precise forecasts of the out-turn ofexpenditure in a particular year, especially where aid is committedfor projects requiring several years for completion.     But sumsunspent in one year represent liabilities carried over into subsequent years, and a rising level of commitments entails a rising level ofexpenditure.     The level of our aid expenditure over the next few years is already to a substantial extent determined by commitments alreadyincurred, such as the independence settlements for Uganda and tanganyka, or the undertakings given to India and Fakistan, or by the moral commitment to continue the assistance which we provide from year to year for the Colonies and towards various United Nationsprogrammes.    Attached to this memorandum is an annex listing anumber of requests or proposals for new aid commitments, over and above our existing obligations or our normal continuing programme.-2-
These are all items to which specific consideration is being given now or will have to be given in the period ahead;  the list excludes variousmore speculative items, or proposals which we are in any eventdetermined to resist - such as the proposal for a new United NationsCapital Development Fund - though sooner or later events may forcesome of these other items upon our attention,6.      New commitments of this kind would obviously tend to increase our aid expenditure in future years.    In some cases, such as theIndus Basin Development Fund, an addition to this year&apos;s expenditure would be involved.    In some instances there is no problem of principle to be resolved - for instance it is accepted that, if we join theEuropean Economic Community, we will have to contribute to itsOverseas Development Fund as well as to its other institutions, suchas the European Investment Bank - but the question of amount is for negotiation.     In general, however, it is clear that only a continuedpolicy of stringency in this field can prevent a further and very substantial increase in our annual aid expenditure.    Moreover, a relaxation of this policy in one case is bound to make it very difficultto apply it in others.    For instance, if we take a lenient attitudetowards the request from Egypt, this would make it that much themore difficult to adopt a negative attitude towards the claims ofTurkey and Iran.S. Li.Treasury Chambers, S, W. 1.Sth May, 1962.
ANNEXA.__MULTILATERAL INSTITUTIONS(i)  Overseas Development Fund of the European EcononaicC ommun ityIf the Fund is continued at its present level, and we contributethe same amount as France and Germany, the United Kingdom contribution will be about  70 million over five years.    An increased level ofcontributions may be proposed,(ii)  International Development association the President of the International Bank for Reconstruction andDevelopment, Mr. Black, is campaigning for an increase in theAssociation^ initial resources.     This is likely to come to the foreat the Annual Meeting in Washington in September.    Our presentsubscription is  47 million over the five years 1960-1964.(iii)  United Nations Special Fund and Expanded Programme of technical assistance the Managing Director of the United Nations Special Fund,Mr. Paul Hoffman, has asked for an increase in the United Kingdom&apos;annual contribution from $8 million to $12 million a year.(*v) Iudus Basin Development FundOur existing commitment is  21 million, which was to be spreadover ten years.     We are likely to have both to accelerate payment ofthis amount (which may involve a Supplementary Estimate of over 2jr million this year) and to make an additional contribution of atleast SJ million (and possibly a good deal more) towards theincreased cost of the scheme.(v) European fund the United States authorities have proposed that the funds available for short-term balance of payments support under theEuropean Monetary Agreement should be called up and applied forlong-term development lending to countries such as Turkey and greece.    If adopted, this proposal would involve about  19 million from the United Kingdom over a period of years.B.       COMMONWEALTH AND colonial territories(i)  IndiaIndia and the United States are pressing us for an immediateadditional commitment of up to  17 million in the Indian consortium.(We have committed  90 million in the first two years of the Five-Year Plan, and intend to raise this to  125 million over the whole period. )
(ii) ^PakistanPakistan and the United States have made repeated representa-tions for a major increase in our commitments in the Pakistanconsortium ( 25 million for the whole Five-Year Plan).(iii)  NigeriaThe Nigerian Government are reported to hope for  50 million over six years from the United Kingdom.(iv) KenyaA proposal has been put to the Treasury for an increase of 29 million (making  42 million in all) in the amount to be spent ontransferring land from white settlers to Africans and settling the africans on ii.     This comes in advance of the independence settle-ment for Kenya, which remains for negotiation,(v) Central africa the Finance Minister of the Federation of Rhodesia and nyasaland may seek a further loan at the end of 1962.    A furtherworsening of the financial problem arising in Central Africa cannotbe ruled out.(vi) British HondurasIt has been agreed to offer  4 million over four years for reconstruction.     This may entail extra expenditure in the current year.C.    FOREIGN COUNTRIESWe have been asked for a ten-year loan of $30 million, pendingarrangements for long-term development finance.(ii)   TurkeyTurkey&apos;s development needs for 1963 and 1964 have been examined by a North Atlantic Alliance Mission.    A development plan, 1963-67, will be ready in the summer and the question offinance for it will soon be considered in the Organisation for economic Co-operation and Development (O. E. C. D. ).     We v/illbe under strong pressure to contribute.    (A somewhat similarposition may develop on Greece. )
SO(iii)   IranWe have said that we will consider whether we could join a consortium for Iran, if one is formed by the International Bank, andthat we will consider whether there is anything else which we could do to help.(iv) Latin america the TJnited States authorities have made a number of representa-tions about the need for aid for Latin America.    One of the countrieswhich they would like us to help is Colombia, and a ColombianEconomic Mission is now visiting Europe seeking short-term credits.(v) ^ThailandAt the request of the United States, a discussion of Thailand&apos;sneeds has been arranged in the Development assistance committee ofO. E.C.D..(v*) VietnamThe United States authorities are likely to promote a similardiscussion of Vietnam&apos;s needs,   but outside the O. E4 C.D. framework,for political reasons.May. 1962
(iii)  IranWe have said that we will consider whether we could join a consortium for Iran, if one is formed by the International Bank, andthat we will consider whether there is anything else which we could do to help.(iv) Latin america the United States authorities have made a number of representa-tions about the need for aid for Latin America.    One of the countrieswhich they would like us to help is Colombia, and a ColombianEconomic Mission is now visiting Europe seeking short-term credits,(v) ThailandAt the request of the United States, a discussion of Thailand&apos;sneeds has been arranged in the Development Assistance Committee ofO.E.C. D,(vi) VietnamThe United States authorities are likely to promote a similardiscussion of Vietnam&apos;s needs,   but outside the O. E* C,D, framework,for political reasons.1962


</content>
</cab>
