<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 153-160</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINETCOLONIAL ISSUES AT THE UNITED nations memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate, for the information of my colleagues and for discussion at some future date, an analysis, with which the Colonial Secretary and I are in agreement,of the situation at the United Nations as it affects British colonial issues.H.Foreign Office, S.W.1,29th May, 1962.60876aPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1962C. (62) 73 Copy No. .    5030th May, 1962
COLONIAL ISSUES AT THE UNITED nations the ProblemEvents in the United Nations have reached the stage at which we should consider whether our policy on the discussion of British colonial issues should be modified. We are entering a difficult period, which may last for some years,particularly in regard to debates on issues in Central and Southern Africa including the Rhodesias and the High Commission Territories which arouseintense feeling, especially amongst African members of the United Nations.The background. We comply fully with the Charter requirements regarding transmission of non-political information about our dependent territories to the United Nations.We now also supply ex gratia political and constitutional information. We have for many years sat on the United Nations Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories and joined in its discussion of colonial problems;these were conducted in general terms, the Committee being precluded from making recommendations about individual territories. We have consistently held the view that we are not accountable to the United Nations for our policies in thecolonial territories and that intervention in the affairs of individual territories is outside the competence of the United Nations. There is, however, no agreeddefinition of what intervention means in this context. It is possible at one extremeto take the view that even the discussion of individual territories is intervention.This view is not held by the majority of the members of the United Nations andwould be unlikely to be upheld by the International Court if it were ever referredto them. In the view of the majority, the United Nations can discuss individualterritories and even make recommendations on them in the form of resolutionswithout this amounting to intervention. In this view probably only an actualphysical attempt to intervene would constitute intervention.The Committee of Seventeen3. The General Assembly of 1960 (when many new African members wereadmitted) adopted its &quot; Declaration&quot; on independence for colonial territories.This Declaration, which we did not support, has become a basic text in the united nations and last November the Assembly established the Committee of Seventeento examine its application and report back to the next Session. We again abstained from voting when this proposal was adopted but said we would participate inthe Committee of Seventeen &quot; on the clear understanding that it will not attemptto intervene in the administration of the territories for which we are responsible &quot;.At the same time we said that &quot; if there were any attempts to intervene we shouldbe bound to withdraw our co-operation &quot;. We did not define what we meant by&quot; intervention &quot; but we had in mind the hearing of petitions, visiting missions and specific recommendations about particular territories but there is no agreed view on what constitutes intervention see paragraph 2 above.4. Although we tried to prevent it, the Committee of Seventeen embarked on a series of debates about individual territories in turn. They have so fardebated Southern and Northern Rhodesia, and they have on their agendaNyasaland, the High Commission Territories, Kenya and Zanzibar as well as thePortuguese territories. During each debate so far they have heard petitionersfrom the territories. During the debate on Southern Rhodesia a Sub-Committeeof Six visited London at our invitation. The Committee have just reported to theGeneral Assembly endorsing the Sub-Committee&apos;s report and making a numberof recommendations about Southern Rhodesia which we cannot accept and proposing that the question should be debated as a matter of urgency and gravityin the General Assembly which resumes in June. On Northern Rhodesia, theCommittee of Seventeen seem likely to recommend to the General Assembly adraft resolution making various demands which are also quite unacceptable.
608765. The Committee also decided to accept invitations to hold meetings inTangier. Addis Ababa and Dar-es-Salaam, and began their tour on 21st May. Themain purpose was to hear petitioners from African territories (including, nodoubt, Kenya and Zanzibar,!.British policy. During these debates our policy has been to say that we regard them asultra vires but to remain in our seat and state our case. We have, however, taken no part in the proceedings during the hearing of petitioners. Our immediatereasons for this policy have been:(a) We cannot stop the United Nations discussing our territories, hearingpetitioners from them or passing resolutions.ib) Our friends are only prepared to speak up for us if we speak up for ourselves; our case would therefore go by default if we do not state it.(c) If our case is not presented the tendency at the United Nations is towardsvirtually unanimous endorsement of extreme views.7. Debates on individual British territories, including the hearing ofpetitioners and the passing of resolutions, will continue. The heat will probablybe turned mainly on to Africa, particularly the Rhodesias and High commission territories and possibly Kenya, but the United Nations will probably get involvedalso in places like Aden, British Guiana and the Borneo territories, and- perhapsMalta. The pattern of the debate on the Rhodesias will be repeated and anyremaining inhibitions about passing specific resolutions about individual territorieswill be suppressed.8. Although our general colonial objectives are in line with those of mostof the African and Asian countries, many of the remaining territories are stilldependent precisely because there are difficult problems to be solved, and united nations intervention can only make these more difficult. Anyone with Afro-Asian backing can now try to use the United Nations as a court of appeal. Thisnaturally damages our authority and introduces a new element of confusion.9. However, these United Nations activities cannot be prevented. Thequestion is how in the circumstances we can best defend our position againstUnited Nations pressures, minimise the damage which may be done by the united nations and gain for ourselves the maximum freedom to follow the policies wethink right.  Two possibilities would be:(a) Withdrawal from all debates on individual British territories, including those in the General Assembly.(b) Withdrawal from the Committee of Seventeen.The extent of our participation in debates and discussion on resolutions if we decide not to withdraw has also to be considered.(a) Withdrawal from all Debates10.   In favour of this course it can be argued:(i) It is illogical to take part in proceedings which we regard as outside thecompetence of the United Nations (although we have done so in other cases).(ii) It is difficult to participate in debates and yet maintain with convictionthe view that the United Nations is not entitled to debate individualterritories or make recommendations about them. However much wemay say that we cannot share or shift our responsibilities, so long aswe are discussing our policies in particular territories with united nations bodies, we suggest both to other countries and to individuals in the territories that we are open to pressures through the united nations. This may restrict our freedom to follow policies we thinkright.(iii) Recent experience has shown that this is a slippery slope.   We have found that it is not really practicable to give information while refusing to discuss our policies and from discussing our policies it is a shortstep to negotiating on resolutions about them. The end of this processmay be that we shall have to submit to something like United Nationssupervision over the whole field of our colonial policies.
(iv) Although participation may bring short-term tactical gains for example moderate as against an extreme resolution the long-term effects are serious. In any case, from the point of view of preserving our freedom of action, extreme resolutions are sometimes to our advantagebecause we can more easily ignore them.11.   Against it may be argued:(i) Whether we participate in debates or not we are going to be subjected to pressures through the United Nations. When the United Nationshas passed a resolution about one of our territories this becomes a factor in the situation which cannot be ignored. Provided we have presented our case vigorously, the fact that we participate in debateneed not make it more difficult for us to reject United Nationsrecommendations.(ii) If we refuse to participate, the resolutions will certainly be more extremeand will be adopted by larger majorities, often almost unanimously.This will tend to increase the pressures on us.(hi) If we withdrew we should come under strong pressure from the UnitedStates and the old as well as the new Commonwealth, all of whom havemade it clear that they think we should accept United Nations discussionof our territories and that they can only help us if we defend ourselvesby stating our case. If we persist, the United States and old commonwealth would give us very little support.(iv) Our disengagement would be heavily criticised by large sections of domesticopinion and in Parliament.(v) We should probably find our non-participation snowballing so that weshould be excluding ourselves from other United Nations activities.(vi) Our general standing and influence at the United Nations even on issuesoutside the colonial field would be gravely undermined. This would leave the United States, broadly speaking, alone to face the uncommittedand the Soviet bloc with consequent damage to the Western position as a whole.(vii) It would estrange the sympathy of most of the African member States,whose friendship it is important to cultivate in the context of the cold war.12. A variant of the policy of a complete withdrawal would be, in the caseof the General Assembly, to remain in our seat but to refuse to participate in discussion, as the French have done over Algeria.13. Selective non-participation certainly served the French quite well overAlgeria. They were able to disregard the United Nations without incurring, e.g., a recommendation for sanctions against them and succeeded in concluding the Eviannegotiations without United Nations interference or even much attention from theUnited Nations. On the other hand they did not prevent acrimonious united nations discussion of Algeria and the adoption of resolutions which gave comfort and international standing to the Algerian rebels. Meanwhile their attitude, coupled with a general policy of disengagement at the United Nations, has greatly reduced their standing and influence at the United Nations.14. There are moreover special factors to be taken into account in anyassessment of the French example:(a) The French Government had no problem of domestic public opinion to face in treating Algeria as a problem for themselves alone.(b) The original French aim to maintain something like the status quo inAlgeria -was completely at variance with that of the United Nationsmajority and there was no advantage for them in buying time.(c) The Front de Liberation Nation ale were already rebels and not localleaders with whom a peaceful dialogue on the spot was beingattempted.id) France is not subject to strong diplomatic pressures to co-operate withthe United Nations, such as we have from the Commonwealth.(e) The French Government were prepared to disregard United States views and to see the United States voting against them.
15. The French did not carry through their own policy without loss to themselves and their allies. Western interests at the United Nations have undoubtedly suffered from the French policy of disengagement, and these effectshave been mitigated only to the extent that France&apos;s allies and notably the UnitedKingdom have stepped into the breach. The special factors listed above do notapply to the United Kingdom, and temporary withdrawal by the United kingdom would create very serious problems for Her Majesty&apos;s Government with the UnitedStates Government and the Commonwealth and with public opinion in the UnitedKingdom itself.(b) Withdrawal from the Committee of Seventeen16.   In favour of this course it may be argued:(i) When the Committee of Seventeen was set up we said that we would withdraw our co-operation if there were attempts to intervene and what we meant by intervention has certainly taken place in the case of the rhodesias. It can be suggested that if we do not now withdraw thiswould be inconsistent with our stated policy, and would lose us respect(although not necessarily goodwill).(ii) While it is important to remain in the Assembly as a permanent united nations organ of the greatest importance, it is reasonable to leave theCommittee of Seventeen, who are an ad hoc body, if we disagreealtogether with the manner in which they are doing their work.(iii) Withdrawal from the Seventeen would effectively demonstrate our determination not to accept their intervention in the affairs of ourterritories.(iv) Our withdrawal might make it easier for us to dismiss the Committee&apos;views as irresponsible and irrelevant.17. Against this, many of the arguments against a general withdrawal from colonial debates apply, although with rather less force. The points at (i)-(iv)in paragraph 11 would apply in a large measure, although the effect on our generalstanding in the United Nations would of course be less than if we withdrew fromAssembly debates also.  There are also the following arguments:(i) Withdrawal from the Committee would be a clear-cut and dramatic gesturewhich would create an atmosphere of crisis in our relations with theUnited Nations and be widely represented as meaning that we had moved to a policy of defiance and non-co-operation. This would makeit much more difficult for our friends to help us over both colonial andother issues at the United Nations and easier for the extremists tostampede the moderates.(ii) Probably as a result of the Prime Ministers recent conversation with president Kennedy, the Americans have recently begun to give us morehelp in the Committee of Seventeen and have shown a greater readiness to stand out against the Afro-Asian majority on our behalf. A suddenreversal of our policy would therefore seen to them ungracious andunreasonable and make them less ready to help us in future.(iii) We should still have to deal with the debate on the report of the Committeeof Seventeen in the Fourth Committee and the General Assembly. Apolicy of withdrawal from the Seventeen but of participation in similardebates in the Assembly could be regarded as illogical and, howeverthis may be, the feeling against us in the Assembly would be strongerif we had withdrawn from the Seventeen and our influencecorrespondingly less.(iv) We are giving some encouragement to a Canadian initiative against Sovietcolonialism which we hope may one day lead to debates on Sovietcolonies in the Committee of Seventeen (although at present this seemsa remote possibility). It would be unfortunate if we had lost the chance to hit back at the Russians in the Committee of Seventeen by walkingout beforehand.18. If withdrawal, whether total or partial, is rejected, what action can betaken to reduce the pressures upon us and to safeguard our freedom of action in
the colonial territories? Can this be done by taking part in debate to the extentof giving facts and correcting misapprehensions, but refusing to be drawn intodiscussion about our policies? Experience in the United Nations shows that itis extremely difficult in practice, not to say impossible, to maintain this distinctionunder heavy pressure, as in the case of Central African problems. Such pressuresinevitably lead us into explanations of our policies and thus into defence of them.Attitude to Resolutions19. The crux seems to be the attitude to be adopted towards resolutions aboutspecific issues in individual territories. This is the point at which pressure is put upon us and our attitude is consequently of importance politically both in new york and in the territories. We should in any case continue to maintain that suchresolutions are ultra vires; but we have a choice between complete detachment and leaving ourselves freedom to influence the wording of resolutions and the voting bydiscreet action behind the scenes.Complete Detachment in Relation to Resolutions20. This would mean conducting ourselves in such a way as to demonstrateconvincingly not only in the United Nations but in Africa and elsewhere that we regard all resolutions about individual territories as ultra vires and will not be influenced by them. For this purpose we would have to show that we are not greatly concerned whether a resolution is moderate or extreme, whether it conflictswith our policies or not, or how large the majority for it is. To achieve this weshould have to decline to be involved, either directly or indirectly, in any attemptto influence the outcome of negotiations about resolutions.21.   The arguments in favour of this are:(i) It would demonstrate our intention not to accept United Nationsintervention and so counter the pressures which local politicans in ourterritories may attempt to put on us through the United Nations.(ii) If we are involved in efforts to improve resolutions, even indirectly through our friends, it becomes more difficult for us to disregard the outcome.(iii) By making our intentions clearer, we should put our relations with theUnited Nations on a less ambiguous basis and reduce the risk that weshall afterwards be accused of duplicity.(iv) While it would tend to result in more extreme resolutions, this might not always be to our disadvantage because they might be easier to disregardthan more moderate ones.Freedom of Manoeuvre in Relation to Resolutions22. Our objections of principle to resolutions as such logically inhibit us from openly working for amendments to draft resolutions or to alternative draftsmore favourable to our point of view. Even with this inhibition, we could givediscreet encouragement to the Americans and our other close friends to introduceamendments to the more objectionable passages of draft resolutions or to producealternative drafts which take cognisance of the real facts and our views. We couldaim at reducing adverse majorities by splitting the vote. While still maintaining that resolutions are ultra vires, we could try to avoid a clear-cut dispute betweenthe United Nations and ourselves and avoid focusing attention on the fact thatwe are going ahead as we think best in the territories concerned. Out attitudemight be on the lines of the Home Secretary&apos;s statement in the House of commons on 8th May, 1962, when he said &quot; Her Majesty&apos;s Government are always ready togive proper consideration to resolutions of the United Nations, but we cannotsurrender or abdicate our responsibility.&quot;   (Hansard, Column 238.)23.   The arguments in favour of this are:(a) A policy based on a sharp distinction between discussions andrecommendations would not easily be understood in the United Nationswhere it is widely felt that, while we must remain responsible for our colonial territories, it is reasonable for the United Nations to expressviews and make recommendations.
(b) Partly for this reason it is often better to have a moderate resolutionthan a more extreme one (unless the extreme resolution is a Soviet onewithout much Afro-Asian support). If it is possible to get an Afro-Asian resolution amended to take some account of our views, this is again worth having because we can then say that the views of the united nations are not very different from our own policies.(c) Even if it is impossible to get a majority for a resolution approximatingto our own view, it is often worth while to confuse the issue and splitthe vote by having an alternative resolution on the table. In the absenceof any more moderate alternative the tendency in the General assembly is to give an overwhelming majority to the only available draft.Whether we like it or not, this then becomes widely regarded as a validexpression of world opinion and a factor in the situation.May 1962.


</content>
</cab>
