<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 161-166</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ITHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CJ62U4 COPY NO. ,jf6CABINETEGYPTMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer for some years Egypt&apos;s balance of payments has been deterioration-ting, largely as a result of an over-ambitious development programme and excessive internal credit.    Coming on top of this, the 35 per centfailure of last year&apos;s cotton crop has caused a foreign exchange crisis.Apart from  60 million of gold which provides the currency cover,Egypt&apos;s reserves have been exhausted, and a foreign exchange deficit of$130 million is expected in the calendar year 1962.2.      Dr. Kaissouni; the Egyptian Minister of Economy, thereforewent to Washington to seek assistance from the International monetary fund (I. M.F.) and the United States Government.    He reached agreementwith the I. M..F. on an economic stabilisation programme, which enabled the Fund to approve a stand-by credit of $42. 5 million, the maximum amount to which Egypt is entitled under its present quota.    A request by Dr. Kaissouni for an increase in this quota was deferred.     TheUnited States Government agreed to make a loan of $20 million, andundex&quot;took to lend up to a further $10 million to match whatever amount isprovided jointly by other Governments in excess of $20 million.    on instructions from Dr. Kaissouni the Egyptian Embassies then approached the British, West German and Italian Governments for similarassistance.    We were asked for $30 million, and were told that theFederal Government would probably be asked for $35 million and theItalian Government for $15 million.     Like the United States Governmentloan, any loans by other Governments could be spent on current importsfrom their countries.     The Egyptian Government hoped that the termsof these loans would not be more onerous than those offered by the ;United States Government:   repayment in ten years, with a grace periodof three years, and an interest rate of Z\ per cent.3.      Dr. Kaissouni then came to London, and re-stated his case tothe Lord Privy Seal and myself.    (He specified no figure for the loan from Her Majesty!s Government.    On his return to Cairo, he told our ambassador that he hoped to get an average of $25 million from theUnited Kingdom, Germany and Italy, but he also appeared to indicatethat his real expectation from us was about  5 million. )    The lord privy Seal emphasised the need for a satisfactory agreement on out-standing issues under the Anglo-Egyptian Financial Agreement before we could even consider a loan to Egypt, ,  I explained that our overseacommitments were already at a level which I was bound to regard asthe maximum;  that the improvement in our balance of payments fromthe past unsatisfactory state did not mean that we could afford more aid;that nevertheless many new claims were being urged upon us, all of-1-CONFiDENTIAL
high priority and substantial amount;  and that it was not thereforepossible to.give Dr. Kaissouni any assurance of a loan from her Majesty&apos;s Government.    I undertook, however, to consider his request with my colleagues, and assured him that we appreciated boththe importance of the Egyptian Government being able to surmount theirpresent difficulties, and the need for a quick decision to enable them to plan their import programme.4.     My Foreign Office colleagues believe that we may now be at thewatershed in political relations with Egypt.    If we follow the UnitedStates&apos; lead and help tide Egypt over this year, relations may showlasting improvement.    If we fail to do so, the reverse is likely to happen.    Apart from wider effects on political stability in the middle east, this would make it more than ever difficult to settle with Egyptthe problems arising from the Anglo-Egyptian Financial Agreement of1959, which are causing us so much embarrassment at home.    ForeignOffice Ministers are therefore in favour of offering a loan of $10 million,subject to a satisfactory settlement over the Financial Agreement.5.      The two outstanding difficulties arising from the Financial Agree-ment are, first, the delay in de-sequestration of British property and,secondly, the failure of the Egyptian Government to fulfil their obliga-tion to permit sterling transfers up to  E. 5, 000 a head of the liquidassets in Egypt of United Kingdom nationals.     The first Of these delaysis due to the inefficiency of the Egyptian bureaucratic machine;  theSecond is due to this, and to a shortage of foreign exchange.     Theconsequences of these difficulties are that British subjects cannotrecover or liquidate their assets and that the distribution of compensa-tion by the Foreign Compensation Commission is delayed because claims for damage during sequestration cannot be formulated.6.      A year ago we acquiesced, as a temporary measure, in an offer by the Egyptian Government to transfer the first  E. 1, 000 instead of thefirst  E.5, 000 of claimants1 liquid assets.    For 268 claims since dealtwith in this way, the Egyptian Government have transferred  140, 000and the balance remaining due is about  300, 000.    A further 1, 000 claimsare now with the Egyptian authorities awaiting adjudication.    assuming that the average amount of the claims is the same as for the 26S cases(this is an arbitrary assumption but we have no other means of calculation)these would place on the Egyptian Government a transfer liability of 500, 000 for the first  E. 1, 000 of each claim, or of  1, 500, 000 on thebasis of their full obligation up to  E.5, 000.     The Foreign Officebelieve that there may be up to a further 1, 700 claims not yet submittedto the Egyptian Government, which on the same reckoning would involvetransfers amounting to  900, 000 on the basis of the first  E. 1,000, orof  2, 500, 000 on the basis of the first  E. 5, 000.7.      Our other outstanding requests under the Financial agreement are that adequate compensation should be paid to the 1951 Officials,that there should be an Exchange of Notes fixing a terminal date forde-sequestration of British property, and a revision of Annex &apos;E&apos; ofthe Agreement to facilitate the identification of claimants.     There, arealso some other administrative matters on which we need the co-operation of the Egyptian authorities.    On the other hand, as part of-2-
a general settlement we could agree to withdraw our demand that &quot;pre-sale dividends&quot; dating from before Suez should be paid by the Egyptiansas an addition to their  27j million compensation payment.8.      If we were to make any loan to Egypt, Parliament and the public would demand that it be made conditional upon Egypt&apos;s full compliance with the terms of the Financial Agreement - Lord Killearn has already said so in a Parliamentary Question on 8th May.     This would mean that de-sequestration was completed expeditiously, and that transferrights were granted.    And more would be expected than that we shouldreceive a renewed assurance by the Egyptian Government, which wecould not enforce, that they will carry out their obligations.     We shouldbe expected to make Egyptian payment obligations a first charge on ourloan.    It will be seen from paragraph 6 above that the cost to theEgyptian Government of their full transfer obligations might eventuallyamount to as much as  4, 300,000.     The Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposalfor a loan of $10 million does not envisage any part of the loan being reserved for sterling transfers.    It is made on the assumption that wewould accept as a satisfactory settlement of the Financial Agreement apackage deal including all the matters referred to in paragraph 7 above,together with the proposal for dealing with sterling transfers which is described in the following paragraph, and would rely on the egyptian government to carry it out.9.      Some weeks ago we made a proposal to the Egyptian Governmentwhereby we would lend them  300, 000 sterling to pay off the balance due on past claims, if they would agree to meet claims approved from now on by transferring the first  E.1, 000 from their own resources as hitherto and the balance up to  E. 5, 000 from the sterling we providefor the costs of our Embassy in Cairo.    (These costs amount to about 30, 000 a month, and our proposal was that they should be met from theblocked Egyptian currency accounts of claimants, to whom we wouldissue simultaneously the sterling equivalent.)    This would have meant that some three years would be needed to settle the 1, 000 claims already under examination in Cairo, but it was thought that this was about therate at which they were likely in any case to be passed by the egyptian authorities.    (The proposal did not look so far ahead as the claims notyet submitted. )    Though the Egyptian Government refused to agree tothis proposal by itself, they would probably accept it if we were preparedto grant a sufficiently attractive loan for balance of payments assistance.There would however be no guarantee that they would carry it.out.10.    If we adhere to this proposal we should have to ask the egyptian government to agree to allow our Embassy costs to be met from blockedlocal currency for whatever length of time it took to dispose of all claims - not just, as under the proposal we have already made, for thethree years estimated to be required to deal with the claims now under examination, but perhaps for as long again, if not longer, to deal with new claims.    It seems very unlikely that the Egyptian Governmentwould agree to this, and even if they did there would be a considerabledanger that sooner or later they would refuse to fulfil their under-taking.-3-
1 1 &amp;11.     It seems therefore that, if we are to be able to say publicly thatwe have secured full compliance by the Egyptian Government with their obligations, we should have.to offer a loan of sufficient amount to covertheir full estimated liability for transfers up to  4. 3 million, or atleast this amount less the first  E.1, 000 of claims which they are atpresent meeting from their own resources, which would mean a loan of  2. 9 million ($8 million);  and that we should have to hold back this amount until claims had been met by the Egyptian authorities.12.    With even this lower figure of $8 million having to be set aside for transfers to claimants, a loan of $10 million, leaving only $2 millionfree for current imports, would not earn much thanks from the egyptian government if offered in the context of their appeal to We stern Govern-ments for balance of payments support.     This would be moreparticularly the case if, as is possible, the United States government accepted only the free $2 million as ranking for matching aid (paragraph above).     The International Eank, however, have said that they will be willing to promote an international consortium for long-term aidtowards Egypt&apos;s economic development plan, provided among other things that the Egyptian Government have honoured their international financial obligations.     To help them to do this, therefore, would be of real value to them.13;    Our loan would in any event be viewed in the world as aid to Egyptby Her Majesty&apos;s Government, and would lead to demands from allied countries like Turkey and Iran, and probably also from Greece, for atleaL.t an equal amount of assistance.    At present we are holding off thedemands from these countries, but any concession to Dr. Kais30uni&apos;s appeal would completely alter the situation and might well make itnecessary for us to lend in total several times the amount we offered to egypt. &apos;14.     Tnere appear therefore to be two main courses of action:-(i)   To rest upon the proposal which we have already madeto the Egyptian Government in connection with theFinancial Agreement, involving a loan of  300, 000,and an undertaking by them to use their sterlingincome from our Embassy&apos;s local expenditure, tomeet United Kingdom claims (see paragraph 9);  or(ii)   TO make a loan of $10 million as part of the inter-national rescue operation, but on the understandingthat sufficient (probably about $8 million) would be reserved to give us a reasonable assurance that theFinancial Agreement would now be honoured.15.    I am most reluctant to go beyond the proposal which we havealready made, and to which I only assented with misgiving.    Egyptis not a country which can claim a high priority for an additional aidcommitments that we may feel ourselves able to undertake.    Certainly,the claims of Turkey and of Iran, who are our allies, should rank Shigher.     In any case, as I made clear in my paper C. (62) 68, the-4-
1 1 1improvement in our financial position in no way justifies any relaxation of the policy of containment, and we have already before us a long listof proposals for further economic assistance, most of which are of higher intrinsic merit than that of Egypt.    Nothing but the. embarrasment in which the non-fulfilment of the Financial Agreement involves us couldjustify us in advancing Egypt to the head of the queue.16.    My colleagues may nevertheless feel that the political advantages of seizing this opportunity to dispose, if we can, of the long-standingembarrassment of the Financial Agreement, and the disadvantages fromthe point of view of our general relations with Egypt of not doing so, Iare such that we are bound (admitting that our proposal as it now standshas no chance of success) to make a further effort.    If they do so feel,I would be prepared to accept the second alternative.17.    If, however, we are to do this, it is in my view essential thatwe should make effective arrangements to ensure that the Egyptians doin fact use as much of the loan as is necessary to honour their obliga-tions.    This cculd be done by adopting a procedure somewhat analagousto that used for tied loans made under Section 3 of the Export GuaranteesActs, 1949-1961, i. e., within a certain total (which, on the assumptions madein paragraphs 6 and 11 above, would be $8 million) the loan would only bepaid over to the Egyptians against documents showing that they had metclaims for transfers by United Kingdom nationals.    The only possible alternative would be not to pay over the whole of the loan until the     \Egyptian Government had cleared off the backlog of claims, had made an adequate payment of compensation to the 1951 officials, and had inaddition dealt with the claims for transfers at present in the pipeline.This would, however, leave us at risk in respect of future claims fortransfers.18.    I understand that the Foreign Office agree that the only effective means of enforcing the condition that the Egyptians should honour their obligations is that part of the loan should be tied as suggested above.They point out, however, that if $8 million were to be tied in this way,this would leave only $2 million as support for the Egyptian balance ofpayments.    This would mean in their view that the loan would havealmost no value from a political standpoint.     They would thereforepress that the amount of the loan should be higher than $10 million.19.    I find great difficulty about this.     To lend even so much will initself be likely to have substantial repercussions on our policy ofcontaining our aid programme.    If we are to lend $10 million to egypt, we shall have to take an even more stringent view of claims for economic assistance by other countries.     The alternative of lending$10 million, but without adequate safeguards that the Egyptians will infact honour their obligations in the future, seems to me equallyunacceptable.S. Li.Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1.Uth May, 1962.-5-CONHDENTML


</content>
</cab>
