<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 169-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>

the entry of goods from abroad free of all kinds of tax. The effect of these Articlesis that a diplomatist purchasing on the open market in London goods the price ofwhich includes excise duty and purchase tax, is required to pay the full priceincluding these elements. If, however, he imports similar goods of British originwhich have been exported free of excise duty and tax in the normal course oftrade, he is not, under the Convention, required to pay those taxes on reimportingthe goods into the United Kingdom. In other words, no exemption from exciseduty or purchase tax is sought for goods bought in the United Kingdom. It is sought only for goods reimported from abroad. The British delegation at theConvention attempted to obtain an amendment to Article 36(1) to meet theTreasury&apos;s point that such goods should be subject to the special imposts but the attempt was very heavily voted down. The Foreign Office recommendation is basedupon the belief that it would be improper to seek to escape the effect of this voteby entering a reservation on the point.6. The second point at issue is contained in Article 37 (4) and this exemptsfrom United Kingdom income tax the wages of all private servants (not beinglocal nationals or permanent residents) in diplomatic households. The servants of Heads of Missions already enjoy this benefit. The number of servantsaccompanying diplomats other than Heads of Missions must be extremely small.The wish of the Treasury to subject them to income tax is not based upon therevenue to be derived from them so much as upon the point of principle that allresidents in the country should be taxed. On the other hand, there are arguablepoints in favour of exemption. In the first place, the emoluments of a ThirdSecretary are paid by his Government. If the Third Secretary&apos;s nursemaid wereto surrender part of her wages in tax, he would have to pay her higher wages andhis own emoluments would have to be increased accordingly. Thus indirectly theUnited Kingdom Government would be imposing a tax on the sending Governmentand inviting a reciprocal burden. At the same time the tax system depends upondeclarations by employers, and in the case of persons immune from process oflaw there is little chance of prosecuting an employer who fails to declare or makes a faulty declaration.7. Here again, however, the Foreign Office anxiety is based not so much uponthe merits of taxing these domestics or otherwise but upon the impropriety of seeking to avoid the universally adopted rule by reservation on a ratification.8.   I recommend therefore(i) that requisite steps be taken to amend the practice of the Customs andInland Revenue in order to bring it in line with Articles 36 (1) and 37 (4)of the Vienna Convention;(ii) that in order to support this practice by statutory law, the necessary stepsbe taken in the projected Diplomatic Privileges and Immunities Billto amend the law in the same sense.H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,17th May, 1962.
annex extract FROM VIENNA CONVENTION ON DIPLOMATIC RELATIONSjf: % ^ % H*Article 34A diplomatic agent shall be exempt from all dues and taxes, personal or real,national, regional or municipal, except(a) indirect taxes of a kind which are normally incorporated in the price ofgoods or services;(b) dues and taxes on private immovable property situated in the territory of the receiving State, unless he holds it on behalf of the sending Statefor the purposes of the mission;(c) estate, succession or inheritance duties levied by the receiving State, subjectto the provisions of paragraph 4 of Article 39;(d) dues and taxes on private income having its source in the receiving Stateand capital taxes on investments made in commercial undertakings inthe receiving State;(e) charges levied for specific services rendered;(/) registration, court or record fees, mortgage dues and stamp duty, withrespect to immovable property, subject to the provisions of Article 23.******Article 361. The receiving State shall, in accordance with such laws and regulations asit may adopt, permit entry of and grant exemption from all customs duties, taxes,and related charges other than charges for storage, cartage and similar services, on:(a) articles for the official use of the mission;(b) articles for the personal use of a diplomatic agent or members of his family forming part of his household, including articles intended forhis establishment.2. The personal baggage of a diplomatic agent shall be exempt frominspection, unless there are serious grounds for presuming that it contains articlesnot covered by the exemptions mentioned in paragraph 1 of this Article, or articlesthe import or export of which is prohibited by the law or controlled by thequarantine regulations of the receiving State. Such inspection shall be conductedonly in the presence of the diplomatic agent or of his authorized representative.Article 374. Private servants of members of the mission shall, if they are not nationals of or permanently resident in the receiving State, be exempt from dues and taxeson the emoluments they receive by reason of their employment. In other respects,they may enjoy privileges and immunities only to the extent admitted by the receiving State. However, the receiving State must exercise its jurisdiction over those persons in such a manner as not to interfere unduly with the performance ofthe functions of the mission.*H H* *fr *H


</content>
</cab>
