<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 185-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy.No..    50CABINETIMMUNITIES AND PRIVILEGESMemorandum by the Lord chancellor the Prime Minister recently asked me to carry out a comprehensive review ofthe problem raised by proposals for extension of diplomatic immunities and privileges. The Cabinet will recall that in December 1961 when they considered a proposal to extend these immunities and privileges to Commonwealth organisations(C.C. (61) 75th Conclusions, Minute 7), they asked for a report on four points; that report has been circulated separately under cover of C. (62) 79. In the paragraphsbelow I set out:I. The occasions on which the problem is likely to come before Parliamentthis Session and next Session.II. The general case in favour of granting immunities and privileges.III. The arguments for taking a restrictive line.IV. The course which I think it might be prudent and practicable to pursue.The Annex describes how immunities and privileges have grown up (Part I) andthe present state of play (Parts II and III).I. Occasions when the Problem will come before parliament . The problem arises mainly from the rapid growth of international organisations nearly always linked with proposals that immunities and privilegesshould be accorded to the organisations themselves and to their staffs. such proposals meet an unsympathetic response from a substantial number of membersof both Houses of Parliament, and in consequence the Government is involved inunpleasant argument every time a proposal comes before Parliament. There aresafeguards against abuse of the system; but the existence of these safeguards hasnot brought any abatement of the recurring criticism.3. If a place can be found for it in next Session&apos;s legislative programme, theForeign Secretary wishes to bring forward a Bill to enable the United kingdom to ratify a convention which was negotiated in Vienna last year on behalf of 81nations. This is likely to be mainly a consolidating measure. The Bill might run toabout 20 clauses but it would be limited to the treatment appropriate to foreign and Commonwealth envoys and their staffs. It would not affect the position ofinternational organisations, whether of foreign or of Commonwealth countries.4. If we join the three Communities of the Six (the European economic community, the European Coal and Steel Community and EURATOM) we shallbe expected to confer on these institutions and their officials the immunities and privileges they now enjoy in the other countries of the Six. There are at presentnearly 6,000 officials; and, although only a few of these would be in this countryand qualified for immunities at any one time, the number will grow. It might bepossible to provide for this extension of immunities and privileges by a series ofOrders in Council under the International Organisations (Immunities and Privileges)Act, 1950, but the better course will probably be to include provision in the general body of legislation to secure entry into the Common Market.C. (62) 8025th May, 196260848aPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1962
5. The Act of 1950 sets out a maximum scale of the immunities and privilegeswhich may by Order in Council be accorded to international organisations and their staffs. The Orders in Council require affirmative resolution in both Houses. orders in respect of the International Wheat Council and the Central Treaty organisation will come before the House during the current Session. At the present timedepartmental discussions are going on about two major organisations theEuropean Space Research Organisation (E.S-R.O.) and the European launcher development Organisation (E.L.D.O.) and it appears likely that draft Orders willbe presented, for these organisations and possibly for adjustments in the treatmentgiven to one other next Session. (Perhaps I may note at this stage that in May 1961,draft Orders for the European Free Trade Association and the Organisation for economic Co-operation and Development gave rise to no small debate in bothHouses.)6. If it were decided that Commonwealth organisations and their staffs shouldbe treated on the same footing as international organisations, it would be necessaryto legislate to set up for them a system broadly similar to that in the Act of 1950:in each case Orders in Council would have to be made to define their immunities and privileges. Depending on the criteria in the Act which an organisation wouldhave to satisfy before qualifying for immunities, at least two and possibly as many as eight Orders would be required.7. At worst, therefore, we may be faced with debates this Session on twoOrders in Council and next Session on two Bills if not three, plus ten or moreOrders in Council. That is a daunting prospect and quite apart from the questionsdiscussed in this paper some consideration may have to be given to Parliamentarytactics.II. The General Case in Favour of Granting Immunities and Privileges8. The principle known as &quot; sovereign immunity &quot; is fully and generally recognised as applying to diplomatic envoys and their immediate staffs. Derivedfrom the principle that an envoy, as representing his sovereign, could no more besubject to the jurisdiction of the receiving State than could that sovereign himself,this immunity was in less civilised times (and still is in less civilised countries) apractical necessity. Envoys must be independent of the jurisdiction and controlof the Governments to which they are accredited and for the proper fulfilment oftheir functions they must be accorded immunities and privileges which insulatethem from the domestic law of the receiving States. The same principle applies but with less universal acceptance to State bodies of one sort and another,such as Intourist and the trading organisations maintained by Soviet bloc countries.Although the complex duties of a professional diplomat may be said nowadays toinclude activities in commercial, economic, financial, cultural and other respectswhich call for the attachment to the staff of his Mission of a variety of specialistadvisers with their office personnel it does not necessarily follow that all these activities ought to attract immunities. In 1952 the United States Administrationissued an official declaration to the effect that they would not recognise commercial or quasi-commercial activities as covered by the general principle. The principlehas been subjected to even greater strain by the growing practice, over the past50 years or so, of extending immunities and privileges to organisations and personsmore and more remote from the immediate circle of diplomatic envoys and theirretinues. The organisations for which (or the officials of which) a greater or lesser degree of immunity has been sought range from the major international bodies(such as the United Nations and its specialised agencies and the institutions ofthe Common Market) whose main function may be said to be making policy oradvising on or co-ordinating the making of policy, to bodies which are mainlytechnical, executive or even quasi-industrial. Examples of this latter class areafforded by euro control (which has a limited degree of immunity) and E.S.R.O.and E.L.D.O., the question of whose immunities is at present being negotiated.It is not difficult to accept that the Secretary-General and other officials of theUnited Nations and its agencies should as a matter of general principle be accordedimmunities and privileges. The arguments applying to other cases owe less toprinciple than to political, economic and administrative considerations.9.   These considerations may be summarised:(a) Political. It can reasonably be argued that the immunities and privilegesaccorded by this country should be neither more nor less generous
than the treatment given by other countries. If, on whatever grounds,we appear to be dragging our feet about immunities in the international discussions which precede the signature of conventions or agreements,we may lose the goodwill of other countries and our political influencemay, in consequence, decline. In some cases the prospect of securingadditional influence through the establishment of a new organisationhere in preference to elsewhere would be lost. Considerations Of thiskind may be of special importance in connexion with commonwealth organisaitons which for reasons of policy we are anxious to promote.It may equally be in our national interest to award a privileged position to an international organisation and its officials where thiswill enhance its and their status, prestige and influence.(b) Economic. There would obviously be some advantage in attracting theforeign currency which would be brought in by having the headquarters of an international organisation in this country. Moreover,establishment here may.improve the prospect of orders being placed with British manufacturers for industrial equipment required by theorganisation. Our policy on immunities and privileges should therefore be as forthcoming as possible.(c) Administrative. There   are   obvious   difficulties   about   taxing   the organisations themselves. There is no general advantage in each ofthe member countries contributing to the revenue of the host country.So far as officials employed by these organisations are concerned, thereare advantages, where they are being switched from country to country,in having scales of salary that do not need to have regard to the varyingrates of tax of different countries. The criticism that officials ought not to be tax-free is met in some cases where organisations operatetheir own staff assessment schemes (based on sliding scales) and levya form of internartaxation on their officials.10. The hostile critic may see in these points a certain desire to keep up with the Joneses and perhaps a tendency to go in for horse trading. He may wellfeel that there is something improper in bartering immunities against foreign trade or currency: indeed, if this is a legitimate form of bargaining, it is difficultto see where a line is to be drawn. Nevertheless, it would be a mistake to discountthe points too heavily. It is a fact of international life that if we want to exerciseinfluence we must pay in some form or other to secure it. From enquiries whichhave been made by our representatives in Paris, Bonn, Brussels and The Hague Ihave the impression that the general tendency of the four Governments is towards a liberal interpretation of the obligations which they have assumed under treatiesrelating to privileges and immunities of international organisations.III. The Arguments for taking a Restrictive Line11. Although it is sometimes said that the objections to the grant ofimmunities are overstated and based on arguments which are emotional ratherthan strictly logical, I consider that among the objections frequently advancedthere are two which carry considerable weight.12. One argument is based on the fundamental principle of the rule oflaw. It is, particularly in the eyes of those brought up in the law, unsatisfactory,whether in civil or in criminal proceedings, that there should be any inequalitybefore the law between one person and another; and unsatisfactory that if a citizensuffers financial or other injury he should be unable to obtain proper remedy inthe courts. The need for envoys and their immediate staffs to have immunity fromsuit is recognised and (although the need in most parts of the world may. not nowbe so great as it once was) there are still areas where this and other immunitiesmay be important. But every extension of immunity means further exception tothe application of the rule of law and is, therefore, prima facie unacceptable,particularly when the extension is to the advantage of persons and Organisationswhose functions are not in the ordinary sense diplomatic. At present between250 and 270 persons connected with international organisations are resident inthis country and entitled to immunities and privileges. Other, in numbers whichare incapable of close estimation but must amount to a few hundred a year,come here on private or official ,visits or to attend meetings and conferences. Thenumbers resident in the United Kingdom would not be affected by the four orders
relating to international organisations referred to in paragraph 5 of thisMemorandum, but the Commonwealth organisations mentioned in paragraph 6would, depending on how widely the net is cast, add as few as two or as many as 600 persons.13. The other argument relates to social circumstances and is less easy tostate. There is a widespread awareness of the gap which has developed betweenthe original theory and modern practice. The modern practice is associated inthe minds of many people with the sharp difference between the standard of livingknown to be enjoyed by the diplomat or the international civil servant when heis in post abroad and when he is at home; and the difference is, perhaps rathervaguely, attributed in the main to immunities and privileges. The demand forimmunities and privileges is regarded (maybe with some envy) as a device forsecuring emoluments which are not really relevant to the job to be done. Thisodium which attaches to privilege may be unjust and regrettable, but the feeling is strong and in these egalitarian days it is a force to be reckoned with.IV. The Course we might pursue14. I believe that it is right to take the utmost care, in all our dealings withimmunities and privileges, to limit what is granted to what is required for the necessities of each case. This would involve the adoption of a definite principle and a stiffening of our attitude towards the granting of immunities and privileges.15. If my colleagues accept that broad approach, I would suggest somespecific points for consideration:(a) In determining whether a given international organisation should be eligible for immunities and privileges we should apply, as a general rule,the distinction indicated in paragraph 8 above, and should be disposed to admit bodies whose primary function is the making or co-ordinationof policy and to exclude others. I recognise that in the past we haveconferred immunities on organisations which might not qualify underthis test, but, although it may be difficult to decline to follow exactprecedents, I do not think this fact is, in itself, sufficient to deter us from aplying that test in future.(b) The particular immunities and privileges accorded to an organisation assuch should be those which appear to be required to enable its functions to be discharged effectively. That these immunities and privileges maybe limited, even in the case of major international bodies, isdemonstrated by the fact that the organisations of the Six may be sued(although their officials have a fairly high degree of immunity). Ifthese organisations are capable of functioning without completeimmunity, I think we should be very slow to conclude that other organisations require immunity merely because of their internationalcharacters.(c) Similarly, the scale of immunities to be accorded to persons within an organisation should be those required for the discharge of their functions. Refusal of immunity to the organisation may make thequestion of immunity of its officials less important, since an injuredparty will be able to obtain redress against the organisation. But theprinciple of equality before the law requires us (particularly in respectof criminal acts) not to grant to officials immunities beyond those required for the proper functioning of the organisations for which theywork. In deciding what is the proper scale, we shall have to examinecarefully the circumstances of each organisation.(d) In applying the general tests suggested at (a), (b) and (c) above, we shouldnot ignore the extraneous political and economic arguments for granting immunities and privileges to organisations and persons not otherwise eligible; but we should examine these arguments criticallyin each case and should not accept them unless we believe they would stand scrutiny in Parliament.(e) Having admitted immunities and privileges for Commonwealth diplomats,we should accept in principle that Commonwealth organisations whichwould qualify if the members were foreign countries should havetreatment comparable with that given to international organisations:
no more and no less. This means that agreements will have to be negotiated, reciprocity arrangements made and a Bill prepared. Inview of the large number of Commonwealth organisations which have operated for many years without immunities and privileges we should ensure, before taking on specific commitments, that all the requisitealterations in Constitution and finance have been or will be made.(/) Special care should be taken to ensure that the immunities and privilegesaccorded to United Kingdom citizens employed in this country donot go beyond the treatment which is now customary-immunity for official acts.16. Finally, it appears to me particularly important that United Kingdomnegotiators of international conventions should in every case receive clearinstructions at an early stage in the negotiations. It is very difficult for themto put forward proposals which other countries may consider restrictive if theyare required to do so for the first time at a stage in the negotiations when a more liberal draft has been under discussion for a long time and has not been adverselycriticised. It is, in my view, essential that there should be effective machineryfor inter-departmental consultations and that it should be set in motion at theearliest possible opportunity in each case.K.House of Lords, S.W. 1,22nd May, 1962.
ANNEXPart IHistory of Diplomatic Privileges and Immunities1. It has always been accepted that the Head of a foreign State is immune from the civil and criminal jurisdiction of the Courts of any other State. Thisdoctrine derives from the principle that jurisdiction cannot be exercised overan equal and, as between themselves, all Heads of State are equal. At common law the immunity of the Sovereign was extended to his representative and the ambassadors of foreign States could neither be sued nor prosecuted in theEnglish Courts. In the past it was certainly true that no Ambassador could havedischarged his duties properly if he had not been free from any risk of legalprocess. The necessity for diplomatic immunity is still very real in some countries.The extension of these immunities to the staff of the Ambassador is now generally accepted, although there have at times been doubts about this. Forexample, in 1653 the brother of the Portuguese Ambassador, who was also amember of his retinue, was tried, convicted and executed for murder. But atpresent most countries, including the United Kingdom, do not claim jurisdiction over any member of an Ambassador^ staff (unless, of course, the immunity iswaived by the Ambassador).2. The earliest legislation on this subject was the Diplomatic Privileges act of 1708, passed in consequence of the arrest for debt of the Russian Ambassador.It expressly provided than any process against a foreign Ambassador should benull and void and its issue a criminal offence. This Act did not extend thescope of diplomatic privileges or immunities since it was merely declaratory ofthe Common law.3. Until the end of the 19th century privileges and immunities wererestricted to foreign Sovereigns, their Ambassadors and staffs and their property.The first suggestion that immunities should be conferred on non-diplomatic personsis to be found in The Hague Convention of 1899 (which first provided for thesettlement of international disputes by arbitration): it provided for the Arbitratorsbeing accorded diplomatic privileges. The provision was also included in TheHague Convention of 1907 and in the Statute of the Permanent Court ofInternational Justice of 1920. At the same time as this Statute was enacted,privileges were conferred on the Officials of the League of Nations: Article 7of the Covenant provided that they should, when engaged on the business of theLeague, enjoy diplomatic privileges and immunities. It is to be noted that whennot so engaged they were not immune from process and in fact there is an example of the Secretary-General of the League being held to be amenable tothe jurisdiction of the French Courts in respect of a claim for maintenance byhis wife.4. The Second World War was the occasion of considerable extension of thepractice of conferring privileges and immunities. The presence of foreign AlliedGovernments in the United Kingdom made it necessary for Parliament to enactthe Diplomatic Privileges (Extension) Act of 1941, conferring certain privilegeson the members and officials of those Governments. The Diplomatic Privileges(Extension) Act of 1944 gave power to the Crown to confer privileges on international organisations and their officials and on the representatives of foreign states attending international conferences. This Act was passed in contemplationof the creation of the United Nations Organisation (U.N.O.) and in 1946 a thirdDiplomatic Privileges (Extension) Act gave the Crown the wider powers ofconferring the privileges required by the Convention adopted by the First general assembly of U.N.O. In 1947 the General Assembly adopted another Conventionproviding for the unification of privileges to be enjoyed by U.N.O. and the specialised Agencies, and two years later the Council of Europe also adopted ageneral agreement on privileges and immunities for the representatives of its members and the Secretariat. Effect was given to these Conventions by orders in Council made under the Acts referred to above.
5. The Act of 1944 was further amended by the Diplomatic Privileges(Extension) Act of 1950. Later in the same year the earlier legislation was repealedand replaced by the International Organisations (Immunities and Privileges) Act of1950, which prescribes the privileges and immunities which may be accorded to:(a) International organisations of which the United Kingdom is a member,their staffs and staffs&apos; families, and representatives from member countries of those organisations.(b) The Judges and members of the International Court of Justice and other persons having business there.(c) Foreign representatives and their staffs attending international conferencesin the United Kingdom.6. The next statutory development was the enactment of the DiplomaticImmunities (Commonwealth Countries and Republic of Ireland) Act of 1952, whichconferred diplomatic privileges and immunities on the High Commissioners ofthe Commonwealth countries and on the Irish Ambassador, to whom the earlierlegislation was not applicable.7. Finally, the Diplomatic Immunities Restriction Act of 1955 was enacted.This gave power to withdraw certain existing immunities from foreign diplomatsand excluded United Kingdom citizens from the enjoyment of those immunities.Part note on Immunities and Privileges Granted in the United Kingdom to international organisations and Persons connected with them. . Ordinarily international organisations of which Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the United Kingdom is a member would be accorded immunities and privilegesby means of Orders in Council made under the International Organisations(Immunities and Privileges) Act of 1950. The schedule to the 1950 Act lists themaximum scales of immunities and privileges which may be conferred. because a proviso to the Act restricts the extent of the immunities and privileges granted toany person by Order in Council to that required to be conferred by the appropriate international agreements, the immunities and privileges accorded in respect of individual organisations vary considerably. There are organisations whoseimmunities and privileges are minimal; for example, the Commission for technical co-operation in Africa South of the Sahara enjoys only the legal capacities of a body corporate.2. The great majority of the organisations enjoy immunity from suit and legalprocess in their corporate capacity. They are also granted exemption and relief from direct taxation and rates similar to that accorded to a foreign Governmentand exemption from taxes on the importation of goods directly imported by themfor official use in the United Kingdom.3. In so far as personal immunity from suit and legal process is concerned,with few exceptions only a limited number (usually not more than one or two) of high Officials of each of the organisations concerned are entitled to full immunity(similar to that accorded to the Head of a Diplomatic Mission) whereas the otherofficials are entitled to immunity in respect of official acts only. Similarly, in the few cases (for example the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation) where permanentnational delegations to the organisation are established, the principal permanent representative of each member Government and his official staff are entitled toimmunity to the same extent as the Head of a Diplomatic Mission and his staff; the clerical and menial personnel of the permanent delegation would receive immunityonly in respect of official acts. Apart from these special cases, representatives of member Governments to the majority of the organisations, their subsidiary organs,committees, &amp;c, enjoy together with their official staffs of specified limitedcategories immunity from suit or legal process in respect of official acts only.4. Exemption from United Kingdom income tax on their official salaries and emoluments is accorded to the officials (irrespective of nationality and rank) of mostinternational organisations. In addition High Officials (not being United kingdom citizens) enjoying full immunity are permitted to import free of customs charges,goods of foreign manufacture or origin intended for their personal use, and otherofficials are extended a similar privilege when taking up their posts.
5. Generally . speaking national representatives on constituent bodies or committees of the organisations and experts engaged on missions. for the organisations enjoy immunity in respect of their official acts. They cannot be arrested or detained in respect of acts committed by them in their personal capacity,nor may their papers be searched, but they may be sued after they have left theUnited Kingdom or if they return for any purpose other than the discharge of duties On behalf of the employing organisation.6. It is customary for the status agreement of an international organisation to contain a clause stating that immunities and privileges are accorded not for thebenefit of the individuals concerned but in order to safeguard the independentexercise of their functions in connexion with the organisation; and that there is a duty to waive immunities in any case, where it can be done without prejudice tothe interests of the organisations and the course of justice would otherwise beimpeded.7. If a High Officer is a United Kingdom national, Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentnormally accord him only the restricted privileges and immunities appropriate toofficers of a lower rank; that is to say, at the most, exemption from income tax onsalary and immunity in respect of his official acts, but no immunity in respect ofacts committed by him in his private capacity. Representatives of the organisationsor their committees who are United Kingdom nationals are not normally accordedany immunities.8. Special steps have been taken to mitigate the effect of immunity from civilliability in the case of the commonest cause of such liability, viz., motor accidents.Where a High Officer is involved in a motor accident or where any other official is so involved in the course of a journey undertaken as part of his duties, immunitycould in theory be claimed, but the Association of Insurance Companies have undertaken not to avail themselves of their clients&apos; title to immunity with a viewto avoiding payment of compensation to victims of the accident.Part IIITable  of   Privileges   and   Immunities   accorded   to   Existing   international organisations by United Kingdom Legislation or Orders in CouncilExplanatory note in the ensuing table the main privileges and immunities granted to international organisations are listed under 13 heads. The normal extent of the rights and immunities covered by each head may be summarised as shown below.In addition to the privileges and immunities listed below, international organisations normally enjoy the legal capacities of a body corporate. This means that they can own property, enter into contracts, appear in the courts, &amp;c.I. The organisation.   Immunity from Suit and Legal ProcessAn international organisation cannot be sued in the United Kingdomcourts, unless it waives its immunity.2.   Inviolability of Archives and PremisesOfficial documents of an international organisation, whether on thepremises of the organisation or in transit, may not be examined by any authority without the organisation^ consent. The offices of theorganisation may not be entered unless the consent of the organisation isfirst obtained.3.   Exemption from Rates and TaxesAn organisation cannot normally be called upon to pay the proportion(approximately one-third) of the local rates earmarked for services fromwhich it is not deemed to derive direct benefit, e.g., Public Baths andWash-houses. It is also exempted from all direct taxes on its income,assets and property, e.g., Schedule A,: but not from any indirect taxes suchas purchase tax.
4.   Exemption from Customs DutySubject to conditions imposed by the customs authorities, an organisation is not required to pay import or export duty on goodsintended for its official use in the United Kingdom.5.   Exemption from Import and Export Restrictions :No restrictions may be imposed on the import Or export of goodsintended for the organisation^ official use in the United Kingdom.6.   Press Communications RatesAn organisation may send Press and broadcasting material at lower rates.II.-Representatives (not being Citizens of the United Kingdom), Membersof Committees, High Officers, Persons on Missions7.   Immunity from Suit and Legal ProcessAny High Officer (normally the executive head of an organisation andhis deputy) and the principal permanent representative to the north atlantic Treaty Organisation and the Western European Union of anymember State (not being United Kingdom citizens) enjoys immunity fromjurisdiction in respect of his official and private activities. Immunity maybe waived by the authority designated under the appropriate agreement.On the other hand, national representatives (as opposed to principalpermanent representatives), members of committees and persons onmissions, normally enjoy immunity in respect of their official acts only.In their personal capacities they are generally granted only immunity fromdetention and arrest and seizure of their personal baggage. Immunitiesare not normally granted to national representatives who are UnitedKingdom nationals.8.   Inviolability of ResidenceThe premises occupied by these persons cannot be entered except withtheir consent.9.   Exemption from TaxesNo income tax is imposed on national representatives and members of committees who are in the United Kingdom for the discharge of their duties. They are, however, liable to pay indirect taxation, e.g., purchase tax. Persons on missions are not normally granted tax exemption.Principal permanent representatives and High Officers are entitled to taxexemption on their official emoluments.Ill-Other Officers and Servants10.   Immunity from Suit and Legal ProcessThe immunity is restricted to official acts and may be waived by theappropriate authority.,11.   Exemption from Income TaxThis exemption is limited to official emoluments.IV - Official Staffs, High Officers&apos; Families12.   Official Staffs of Representatives and Members of CommitteesAlternates, advisers, technical experts and secretaries of delegations,who are on the staffs of representatives or of members of committees,normally enjoy the same privileges as are enjoyed by the representativesor members of committees, i.e., exemption from taxation; immunity fromsuit and legal process in respect of their official acts and, in their personalcapacities, immunity from detention and arrest. The immunities may be; waived by the appropriate authority.   .13.   Families of High OfficersThese immunities are the same as the immunities enjoyed by highofficers (see 7 and 8 above).
Table of Privileges and Immunities Accorded to Existing International Organisations by United Kingdom Legislation or Orders in Council						United Nations							International	Food and	International	Educational,			International	World	Privileges and Immunities	United Nations	Labour	Agriculture	Civil	Scientific and	World Health	Universal	telecommunications-	Meteorological		Organisation	Organisation	Organisation	Aviation	Cultural	Organisation	Postal Union	cations Union	Organisation					Organisation	Organisation					The Organisation	(1947149)	(1949)	(1949)	(1949/54)	(1949)	(1949/55)	(1954)	(1954)	(1954)1.	Immunity from suit and legal	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes2.	process Inviolability of archives and	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	premises									Yes3.	Exemption from taxes and rates	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes &apos;	4.	Exemption from customs duty	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes5.	Exemption from import/export	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	restrictions									6.	Press communications rates ...	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes   .	Yes	-   No	YesanWo7.Representatives (reps.),Members of Committees,High Officers (H.Os.),Persons on MissionsImmunity from suit andprocessInviolability of residenceExemption from taxes ...05legalOther Officers and Servants10. Immunity from suit and legalprocess11. Exemption from income tax ...Staffs and Families12. Official   staff   of  reps,   and members   of Committees=Ambassadors family13. Family   of   High   Officials=Ambassadors familyYes H.Os.	Yes H.Os.	Yes ELOs.	Yes H.Os.	Yes H.Os.	Yes H.Os.	Yes (no missions) H.Os.	Yes (no missions) H.Os.	Yes (no missions) H.Os.Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and H.O.s)	Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and H.Os.)	Yes (reps., residence and HOs.)Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	yes yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	yes yes (reps.) Yes	Yes (reps.) Yes	Yes (reps.) Yes	Yes (reps.) Yes	Yes (reps.) Yes	Yes (reps.) Yes	Yes (reps.  limited) Yes	Yes (reps-limited) Yes	Yes (reps.  limited) Yes
Privileges and ImmunitiesThe organisation. Immunity from suit and legalprocess2; Inviolability of archives andpremises3. Exemption from taxes and rates4. Exemption from customs duty5. Exemption from import/exportrestrictions6. Press communications rates ...Representatives (reps.),Members of Committees,High Officers (H.Os.),Persons on Missions7. Immunity from suit and legalprocess  .Inter-GovernmentalMaritimeConsultativeOrganisation(1955/59)YesYesYesYesYesYesInternationalCourt ofJustice(1947/49)NoNoNoNoNoNoInternationalAtomic EnergyAgencyInternationalMonetary FundInternationalBank forReconstructionand DevelopmentInternationalFinanceCorporationInternationalDevelopmentAssociationCustomsCo-operationCouncilYesYes(reps, and h.Os.)yes yes(limited class)Yes(limited class)Yes(limited class)Yes8. Inviolability of residence	H.Os.	H.Os.            H.Os.	No	No	no. Exemption from taxes ...	Yes	Yes              Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	(reps.,	(agents, etc.,        (reps.,	(officials	(officials	(officials	residence and	residence and  residence and	other than	other than	other than	H.Os.)	H.Os.)          H.Os.)	United	United	UnitedOther Officers and Servants			Kingdom)	Kingdom)	Kingdom)					10. Immunity from suit and legal	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yesprocess					11. Exemption from income tax ...	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes  1	Yes			(other than	(other than	(other than			United	United	UnitedStaffs and Families			Kingdom)	Kingdom)	Kingdom)12. Official  staff  of  reps,   and	Yes	Yes	No .	No	Nomembers   of  Committees--	(reps. 	(reps-			Ambassadors family	limited)	limited)			13. Family   of  High   Officials=	Yes	Yes	No	No	NoAmbassadors family					H.Os.Yes(H.Os.)YesYesOrganisationfor economic co-operationandDevelopment(1961)	(1946)	(1955)	(1960)	(1954/61)	(1961)Yes	Yes	No	No	Yes	Yes		(with	(with		Yes		exceptions)	exceptions)			Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	yes yes	&apos;^Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	yes yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	yes yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	Yes	yes yes	No	No	No	Yes	YesCouncil ofEurope(1950/54/58/60)YesYesYesYesYesNoYesH.Os. andreps.Yes(reps, and h.Os.)YesYesYes(including mem-bers of european commission of human Rights no missions)Yes(permanentreps, and H.Os.)Yes(permanentreps, andHOs.)yes yes;Yes . Yes ,.....Yes(reps.  (reps.          (limited)limited) limited)(Secretary- (Secretary-          YesGeneral only) General only)to
Table of Privileges and Immunities Accorded to Existing Internationa! Organisations by United Kingdom Legislation or Orders in Council(continued)WEn50B						Commission					North Atlantic	Western	European Coal	.. European     &quot;..	for Technical				Privileges and Immunities	Treaty	European	and Steel	Free Trade	Co-operation in	International	International	International		Organisation	Union	Community	: Association	Africa, South	Tin Council	Sugar Council	Wheat Council						of the Sahara				:   The Organisation	(1954)	(1948/55/60)	. (1955)	(1961)	(1955)	(1956j 57 J61)	(1954/58)	(1953/59)1.	Immunity from suit and legal process	Yes	Yes	No	Yes	No	No	No	No2.	Inviolability of archives and premises	Yes	Yes	No	Yes	No	No	No	No &apos;3.	Exemption from taxes and rates	Yes	Yes	No	Yes	No	Yes	Yes	no.	Exemption from customs duty	Yes	Yes	No	Yes	No	No	No	no. 5.	Exemption from import/export restrictions   .	Yes	Yes	No	Yes	No	No	No	-no 6.	Press communications rates ...	No (H.Os.-limited if	No (H.Os.-limited if	No	Yes (chief rep.  limited if	No	No	No	No		United Kingdom) United Kingdom)			United Kingdom)				to representatives (reps.),Members of Committees,High Officers (H.Os.),Persons on Missions7. Immunity from suit andprocess8. Inviolability of residence9. Exemption from taxeslegalYesYesOther Officers and Servants10. Immunity from suit and legal        Yesprocess11. Exemption from income tax ...        YesStaffs and Families12. Official   staff  of  reps,   and        Yesmembers   of Committees=      (limited)Ambassadors family13. Family   of   High   Officials= YesAmbassadors familyYes Yes(permanent reps, (permanent reps,and H.Os.) and H.Os.)Yes Yes(permanent reps, (permanent reps,and H.Os.; other and H.Os.; otherreps., residence) reps., residence)Yes(chief rep. andcertain others)Yes(chief rep.)Yes(chief rep. andcertain others)yes yes(H.Os.)YesYesYes(reps., residenceand H.Os.)YesYesNoNoNoNoNoNoNoNoNoNoNoNo.NoNoNoNoNoono130Yes Yes Yes(other than        (other than        (other than united Kingdom) United Kingdom) United Kingdom under finance act)Yes(limited)yes yes(limited)Yes(chief rep.)Yes(limited)YesNoNoNoNoNoNoNoNo


</content>
</cab>
