<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 248-250</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BURMA: WAR DAMAGE CLAIMSMemorandum Jay the^Lqr^ chancellor am circulating this memorandum at the Prime Minister&apos;request to inform my colleagues of the conclusion reached by the HomeAffairs Committee on the handling of claims made by the Burmah oil company and other firms for compensation for war damage in Burma.2.        The claims relate to the damage done to the companies&apos;property under the scorched earth strategy pursued by our forces on leaving Burma in 1942.   Proceedings for compensation for this damagehave now been instituted against the Crown in the Scottish courts,and a total of nearly  40 million plus interest is involved.   If other british-Burma companies take similar proceedings, the potentialcost to the Exchequer would exceed  100 million.   The Court of;Session is expected to start hearing the claims about the middle of July.3.        The claims are being resisted on a number of solid legalgrounds:  that the acts of destruction on which they are based wereacts of the Government of Burma and not of the United Kingdom Govern-ment;  that the Burma legislation under which they were authorisedprecluded compensation;  that the destruction was done in the courseof necessary operations of war in the face of an advancing enemy.We have always denied any liability to compensate these firms directlyfor their war losses in Burma, and the Government of Burma havealso declined to pay any compensation for their losses.   In 1948 theTreasury distributed ex gratia the sum   of  10 million among theBritish-Burma companies, but this payment was made in the interestsof the national economy as a means of enabling British concerns torehabilitate their pre-war businesses.4.        The Home Affairs Committee were agreed that the companies&apos;claims are without merit and that it would be intolerable if the Govern-ment had to meet them.   The chances of the companies succeedingin the courts are only slight, but if the courts were to decide intheir favour, the Government could hardly avoid introducing a Billto set aside the decision, even though the legislation would be clearlyretrospective.   That being so, the Committee thought that there wouldbe advantage in warning the companies now of the governments intentions before they incurred further heavy expenditure on litigation.It is true that this course might expose the Government to criticismunnecessarily (since the courts might reject the claims) and would in a sense involve interfering with a case actually pending before the courts-1-confidential. (62) 91 copy NO.,^^!.30th May, 1962CABINET
(since summonses have already been served on the Lord Advocate);but if the companies proceed with their claims despite a warning,the Government will be in a stronger position to introduce legislation,and if as a result of the warning the claims are abandoned, no legis-lation will be necessary.   (The Committee recognised that, in any event, it. would be impracticable to introduce legislation this session. )5.        The Home Affairs Committee accordingly concluded thatthe claimants should be warned immediately that the Governmentwould introduce legislation to nullify their claims in the event ofthe courts deciding against the Crown.   A suitable letter is being prepared which will leave the companies in no doubt that the Goyern-ment remain confident that the claims will be rejected by the courts.If as a result of the warning the claims are withdrawn, there could bea case for making an ex-gratiau contribution to the legal costs whichthe companies have already incurred. -K.House of Lords, S.W.1,29th May, 1962-2-


</content>
</cab>
