<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/109/0 images: 259-261</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1962C. (62) 935 th June, 1962CABINETCOTTON TEXTILESMemorandum by the President of the Board of trade as I warned my colleagues might be the case, developments since my memorandum on cotton textiles was considered on 31st May (C.C. (62)39th Conclusions, Minute 8) have necessitated some modifications in the draft statement which was then approved.2. The Government of India wish the statement to say that the undertaking by the Indian industry is on the assumption that, in the event of our joining theCommon Market, Indian cotton goods will continue to enter the United Kingdomfree of import duty. We cannot be parties to such an assumption but a revisedparagraph has been put to the Government of India which I hope will be acceptable to them.3. Ministerial changes in Pakistan made it impossible for the PakistaniGovernment to settle the matter with their industry for some weeks to come. This,too, means that changes are required.4.   Two new factors have emerged:(a) Following consideration by the Cotton Board of the announcement of the hong Kong offer and the Governments favourable reception of it,Lord Rochdale, the Chairman of the Cotton Board, has asked that thestatement should refer to the very strong representations made by theCotton Board for a reduction m the ceilings for imports from HongKong, India and Pakistan. The Cotton Board is in a difficult positionin relation to the industry and I think we owe it to Lord Rochdale tomeet him on this point.(b) The trend of negotiations with the Six in Brussels makes it desirable tostate plainly that the proposed ceilings are in our view reasonable inall the circumstances.5. In view of the foregoing, paragraphs 2-5 of the statement have been modified and slightly re-arranged.   The revised text is annexed.6. I have discussed with the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster the date on which the statement is to be made and we have agreed on Wednesday, 6th June.F. J. E.Board of Trade, S.W. 1,4th June, 1962.Copy No.5060916
. ANNEXCOTTON TEXTILES: DRAFT STATEMENT(Revision of first six paragraphs)I wish to make a statement of Government policy concerning imports ofcotton textiles and other matters affecting the cotton industry.As the House may be aware, the Government .have received, through theGovernment of Hong Kong, an offer from the Hong Kong industry to continueup to the end of 1965 the present ceilings on their exports of cotton piece goods and made-ups for retention in this country and, in addition, to limit yarn exportsto the 1961 rate. The limitation of yarn exports is a new feature which would come into operation shortly.This offer is subject to the acceptance of similar arrangements on the partof India and Pakistan. The Government of India have informed us that asimilar offer is now forthcoming from the industry in India. Discussions arestill proceeding between the Government and industry in Pakistan.The Government are aware that the British industries concerned regardthese levels as excessive, and very strong representations have been made by theCotton Board to secure a reduction.On the one hand, the Government recognise the serious difficulties whicha large volume of imports cause to these industries; on the other hand, theGovernment are bound to take account of the importance of textile exports tothe economies of the Commonwealth countries concerned. Weighing both these considerations, they have decided that the proposed ceilings are reasonable inall the circumstances and that the offers should be accepted.Certain matters remain to be settled and the undertakings are on the basisof the present system whereby cotton textiles from Commonwealth countries, enterBritain duty free. If, as a result of the negotiations in Brussels, there were tobe any change in this system, the Governments and industries concerned naturallyreserve their right to reconsider the undertakings.The long-term Geneva Agreement is due to come into operation in Octobernext. The Government hope it will be accepted by many countries. They intend to accept it for the United Kingdom subject to a reservation exempting us from obligations under the Agreement to admit increased imports.These arrangements will ensure stability over a large part of the market.Supplies from all the major low-cost Asian producers are now regulated either by voluntary means or otherwise. Imports from Japan, Formosa, China andthe Eastern bloc countries are under licensing control. This will continue.Imports from Spain are limited by agreement with the Spanish industry. Allimports of cotton cloth from foreign countries, including the United States andthe countries of Western Europe, from which imports are continuing at a relatively high level, have to pay an import duty of 17^ per cent. I am circulating theOfficial Report Tables giving figures of imports from different areas since 1959.June, 1962.


</content>
</cab>
