<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/164/17 images: 265-270</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DHNTIALHOUSING (FINANCIAL PROVISIONS) (SCOTLAND) ACT 1972Memorandum by the Secretary of State for scotland. On 1 August the Cabinet invited me (CM(72) 39th Conclusions,Minute 5) to report early in September on -i.       the arrangements being made by Scottish local authorities for the implementation of the new Scottish Housing Act; and ii.       the steps which might be considered for dealing with anyauthorities who remained recalcitrant.I seek agreement to my proposed course of action which I believe should begin on 2 October.2. The Scottish Act places on local authorities two main requirements to be met by 1 October 1972 -i. Ihey must all operate rent rebate schemes for council tenantsconforming with the Act; and ii.       they must raise council house rents in accordance with thestatutory formula for Scotland.    (Those who have deferred makinga rent increase this year until 1 October, the last date, willrequire to make an average increase of 75p per week on that date;many have, however, anticipated the statutory requirements, andthe average increase required at the beginning of the localauthority financial year, May, was 46p per week.    The maximumpermitted increase this year for any individual tenant is  1 perweek. )These requirements come into force on 3 August. I have no power tomodify them and, under the Scottish arrangements, there has been nonegotiation with local authorities over them.3. There are 234 housing authorities in Scotland.    About 180 are believed to have taken the necessary decisions to comply with these requirements.    The others, whatever decisions may be taken between now and 1 October, are bound to come in default of the requirements, if only because there is another statutory requirement to give 4 weeks1 notice to tenants of any rent increase to be made and this notice will take them past1CP(72) 92 COPY NO  g g19 September 1972CABINET
the 1 October deadline.    I shall therefore be bound to considerinstituting default proceedings against most of these authorities.    they include some of the largest housing authorities with between them over half of all Scottish council houses.4. I have no doubt that action must be taken in relation at least toabout half these authorities which have   explicitly adopted formalcouncil resolutions not to implement the Act.5. The main default powers of the Secretary of State are outlined inthe Annex to this memorandum.    After discussion with the Lord Advocate,I propose to order local inquiries as rapidly as possible after 1 October:the Act requires a local inquiry in each case before I can decide whetherdefault has in fact occurred.    (This is the normal procedure in Scotland. )I therefore propose to write formally to all local authorities defying theAct on 2 October requiring them to supply me with specified information from which a prima facie case of default could be put to a local inquiry.Thereafter, with the normal 28 days&apos; notice of the holding of an inquiry,I plan to have 4 separate inquiries held more or less simultaneously in mid-November;  one of these would almost certainly deal with Glasgow.This is the maximum number which the resources of my Department andthe Scottish Bar are likely to be able to cope with at one time.    Assumingswift reports, and a favourable outcome, default orders would be madeearly in December, and the way would be clear for the holding of furtherinquiries at the turn of the year.6. Immediate action on 2 October is in my view essential, to demonstrate publicly that I am treating all defiance impartially and seriously and also to enable us to get through this major task as early aspossible before the end of the local authority financial year and the municipal elections in May.    I would not enter into any public commitment to hold local inquiries in relation to all authorities, or to proceed to anyparticular timetable: it would be desirable to keep options open.7.        It is difficult to assess the reaction of local authorities to what Ihave proposed.    One or more may try to fight a protracted legal battle.Others may take the line that they will not themselves implement the Act,or a first default order, but that they will not hinder the Secretary of state in exercising their powers under a second default order to raise rents bythe appropriate amount.    On the other hand, I believe that many will decide that, after they have made a gesture at a local inquiry, theinterests of their tenants and rate-payers would best be served by theauthority itself remedying its default in accordance with the terms of thefirst default order.8. The eventual outcome does not seem to me in doubt, but it could take some time to reach 100 per cent implementation.    Action on the linesI propose is widely expected in Scotland and I am sure it would be unwise to turn a blind eye to defiance.    There is nothing to be gained from delay.Indeed it might encourage opposition.    It would certainly be severely criticised by those who have observed the law.    By proceeding in thenormal way, by means of public inquiries held in as impartial a spirit as
possible, I would hope to emphasise on each occasion that failure to implement the Ac t meant a denial to citizens of statutory rights which parliament had conferred - for example the relief of the housing burden on the rates, and rent allowances for private tenants;  and that failure to operate the statutory rent rebate scheme for council tenants by1 October was just as much default as failure to increase rents.9. I seek the agreement of my colleagues to proceeding as proposed,starting with letters to some 25 local authorities on 2 October.G scottish Office18 September 1972
ANNEX TO CP(72)HOUSING (FINANCIAL PROVISIONS)  (SCOTLAND) ACT 1972MAIN DEFAULT POWERS OS THE SECRETARY OF state .     The principal statutory powers in cases of default by a localauthority are contained in section 356 of the Local Government(Scotland) Act 192+7 and section 195, of the Housing (Scotland)Act 1966 (both as amended by the new Act).     The Secretary of state has a discretion whether to take any action-     (In order to establish a .&apos;t .iiS.S facie case of default for further investigation, detailed information would need to be obtained from a local authority as toits estimated housing finances for 1972-73.)2-,     If the Secretary of State decides that further investigation of possible default is required, he must in each case apjioint a person(who would normally be Senior Counsel in the case of a majorauthority) to hold a public local inquiry.     28 days&apos; notice is normally given of the holding of an inquiry in Sootland.     an inquiry ought not to take more than 2 or 3 clays;    and the report would be asked for within a fortnight.3.     Thereafter, the Secretary of State could forthwith make a default order which would either -(1)    in general terms require the authority to remedy itsdefault;    or(2)   prescribe in details a rents scheme for the authorityto adopt in remedying its default.k-     If the authority failed to comply within 1h days, a furtherdefault order may -(3)    make such functions of the authority as were necessaryfor the purpose of remedying the default exercisable bythe Secretary of State.     (Following such an order, theDepartment would act for such purposes as if it werethe Council, and the authority&apos;s officials would adviseit and implement its instructions.     There is no provision in the Scottish Act for the appointment of a HousingCommissioner.)Alternatively, if the authority did not comply with the first defaultorder, the Secretary of State might -(k)    apply to the Court of Session for an order requiring themto comply with the default order/     (Defiance of a CourtOrder could lead to imprisonment for contempt of court.)5*     All three types of default order may make such variations of theprovision of the Act as the Secretary of State sees fit.     Variations -eg, to permit the maximum average rent increase to be more than (5vper week would be necessary if an order were to ensure that an authorityobtained no long-term advantage by default.
6c     At any stage the authority could seek to challenge theSecretary of State&apos;s actions in the Court cf Session.SUBSIDIES7.     In addition, section 58 of the Housing (Financial Provisions)(Scotland) Act 1968 as amended by section 73 of the 1972 Act gives the Secretary of State power to T*educe, suspend or discontinue thepayment of housing subsidies where he is satisfied that defaulthas occurredo     A local inquiry is not required before the secretary of State satisfies himself of default, but it is clear that this power cannot in practice be exercised before an inquiry is held under the other powers (as to do so would risk pre-judging the(,&apos;itcome of an inquiry) 0     In xDractice, the withholding of subsidies -except as a short-tex^m, tactical wea^jon (the use of which isunprecedented in this context   - would not contribute to solving the real problem of how to put a defaulting authority back on therails: it would either force an authority to borrow, or to increasethe rate burden, or bothoSURCHARGING OP COUNCILLORSBa     In cases of negligence or misconduct by councillors or officialsinvolving an illegal payment, or a loss or deficiency, the localauthority auditor- may make an interim report to the Secretary ofStatec      (The Secretary of State has no statutory authority to ask him to do so, .or to put inquiries in hand.)     Past experience - eg,school milk in 1970 - shows that it is difficult to establish awatertight case of negligence or misconduct in an interim report,and it might well not be possible to do so in the circumstances of housing default until after the end of the financial year 1972-73 -If an interim report is submitted, a statutory procedure is followed,for consulting those concerned.     The Secretary of State&apos;s discretion in the procedure and the eventual outcome (which may be challenged inthe Court of Session) is very limited:    he might find himself obligedto surcharge each councillor concerned for his share of the full amount of any illegal payment, or loss or deficiency - in the extreme case (Glasgow) the surcharge might be of the order of  5*000 per month on each Councillor who had voted not to implement the ActoFailure to pay such a surcharge would eventually lead to bankruptcyproceedings, following which a person is debarred from membership ofa local authority.      (Civil debt is not, in Scotland, punishableby inrprisonmento)     In practice, this audit procedure - likesuspension of payment of housing subsidies - is not really apt tothe solution of the problem of how to put a defaulting authority backon the rails0September 1972


</content>
</cab>
