<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/21/0 images: 2-2</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.34(62) 17th May 1962

1. Parliament. [Enter M.R.

I.M. Business for next week.

C. Market : Oppn. insistg. on debate on 6-7 June. V. awkward. Govt. spokesmen : L.P.S. C.S. and P.M. Avoid making any statements of substance and esp. giving any further assurances.

H. In H/L. will be continuing pressure for debate on substance before Parlt. rises.

2. Laos.

H. Purpose of U.S. troop movements : to deter R. from encouraging P. Lao in Laos &amp; to stiffen morale of Thais.

Shd. we act in support, if Thais request it? A. &amp; N.Z. have said publicly tht. they wd. Propose tht., if asked, we shd. send Hunter squadron back. This wd. be done under Manila Treaty but multi-laterally.

D.S. Will be regarded as S.E.A.T.O. action. Better give the Organn. this boost?

P.M. P.N. Ques. today. Read draft answer. This will make it clear tht. S.E.A.T.O. Council have discussed : that Art. 4(1) doesn‟t apply : but if request made under Art.4(3) by Thailand we shall be prepared to send fighter aircraft.

Substance : Summarised pressures to secure national Govt. in Laos.

Incident prob. designed to hurry us on – no more. Mr. K. is averse from mil. intervention in Laos : still urging the coalition. But now following 2 prong policy – short of strength in support of diplomatic pressures.

S.LI. If asked, we must do it. Otherwise we stultify S.E.A.T.O. Treaty and make ourselves cheap in the eyes of A. and N.Z.

K./D.S. Agree. x/ But C.R.O. shd. tell Tunku – send copy of answer at once.

H. Don‟t want to boost this as S.E.A.T.O. – which may upset Malaya and Laos.

Prefer to refer to Manila Treaty.

Agreed : inclding x/.

3. Education : Grants to Students.

H.B. Ty. do not challenge the arithmetic. But classic case showg. how not to proceed if we are to control expenditure. Cttee. on merits : then Cttee. on cost : then Govt. find result to be out of line with priorities elsewhere. We have cut £6 m. p.a. off U.G.C. estimate.

This wd. add £7 m. for a low priority need. Higher rate of grant already, for students, than in any other country. Equatg. red brick with Oxbridge not done in other Univ. subsidy?) – and CATS and other institutions are to follow.

See the diffy. of not acceptg. recommns. But not sensible priorities. And some risk of reaction on incomes policy (30%) – even if argument is invalid it will be raised.

Hence my suggn. of phasing this over 3 years.

D.E. Largest part of bill is for undergraduates. System of awards is built in to our practice. If we treble nos. in higher educn., we may have to look at this again – after Robbins. M‟while we are pledged to keep max. grant in line with an acceptable budget. Means test on parents starts at £700 p.a. When we legislated on that, we promised to look at figure for maximum grant, and to assimilate various Universities.

This was an objective survey and we declined on that a/c to put repves. of students on the Cttee. Recommn. was 30/= a week : Ministers cut it to 15/=. Over 4 yrs. this is 2½% to 3½% a year. Three rises of 5/= wd. be such a departure from pledges tht. one or both Cttees. will resign.

Must announce decision in debate today.

Hail. Post graduates - £136.000 only is involved. Issue is one of most important I have handled as M/Science. If grants are too low, in comparison with starting salaries of teachers (recently raised), it will be a disincentive to acquiring the higher qualifications we so badly need. These 3000 post graduate students are vital to future of scientific effort in U.K.

Research Council wd. prefer to have smaller nos. at higher rate.

P.M. Students : we have drifted into posn. in wh. all our students are State supported. Even in U.S. they work in vacs.

P.T. This surely is over the dam. Cttees. have recommended : Ministers have pared it down as much as possible.

Ch. H. You can‟t then spread it over 3 years.

H.B. I‟m open to persuasion that I am asking for the impossible. But this

underlines importance of Plowden principle tht. before accepting things in principle we shd. look at ultimate cost.

K. Worried about para.8 of H.B.‟s memo. But, even so, agree this is over the dam.

F.E. Must do this – with regret.

Agreed : as proposed by Education Ministers.

4. U.N. Chinese Representation.

H. Repn. on agencies has not yet come up. U.S. fear this device may be tried. But we voted for seating Red China in U.N. itself. Inconsistent for us to vote v. seating them in an agency. But we cd. argue tht. agencies are competent to determine their own composition. And our Ambassadors in W‟ton and N.York both support line suggested in memo.

P.M. Defensible, on basis tht. we were defeated on main issue and its logical therefore to conform with decision of U.N. on that issue.

Memo. approved.

5. Incomes Policy.

S.LI. E.P.C. discussion.

a) Alternative means of holding the line : -

i) Direction to natd. indies.

ii) Action v. employers who gave excessive increases – taxation,

prices, repns. to employers‟ organns.

iii) Presentatiion of diffies. of reconciling full emplt. inflation and free

collective bargaining.

iv) If we want to take tough line, must overhaul strike-breakg.

machinery.

b) Means of re-valuing particular classes. Memo. by M/L. needs

further examn.

Another mtg next week on b : while offls. consider a.

P.T. Urgency. i) if it is to be used wd. have to come before rlwaymen‟s claim.

K. On analysis of pp. circulated to E.P.C. seems to me tht. more thought is needed by Cttee. before Cab. can decide. We need a considered report from that Cttee.

I.M. Serious Press – seen last night – are concerned to know what action we

shall take in interim before NEDC comes in.

We can‟t influence private sector. We shd. now put more control on fringe – natd. indies. – to supplement what we have done on public service. This wd. make it easier to give concessions w‟in that field eg. for nurses.

H.W. First consider wthr. we are prepd. to fight a rlway strike – and how.

J.H. Hope we shall examine in detail ques. raised in E.P.C. discussion.

There are diffies. on i) Wd. Chairmen resign? Do Govt. want to become directly involved in wage fixing?

Hail. Don‟t abandon hope of influencing private employers. It is they who have undermined policy. T.U.‟s have shown some restraint.

We need collective penalty for wage increases beyond our policy.

M. Shd. be direction to treat this as matter of gt. urgency.

F.E. We cd. get nearer to private employers – explain our policy before claims come to a crunch.

E.H. Consider fundamentals – power balance betwn. T.U.‟s &amp; employers.

If we make things more rigid, less room for pol. handling of particular situation. That might be even more dangerous.

D.E. Tight control over public service, as means of influencing private sector, has bn. counter-productive. Extension to fringe might stiffen T.U.‟s even more v. Govt. intervention in wage negotiation.

May be better to address ourselves mainly to workers &amp; his wife who are more on our side than employers.

P.M. *Let me see a draft of the proposed directive to natd. indies.

Att. G. cd. consider it with Ministers concerned.

</content>
</cab>
