<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/21/0 images: 20-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.55(62) 22nd August 1962

1. Common Market. [Enter M.R.

a) The rest of the Commonwealth.

R.A.B. Summarised discn. at Ministerial Cttee.

Satisfactn. can be expd. as regards associates and Asians.

Old Doms. will be more difficult. On manufacture nothing better cd. have bn. expected. Temperate foodstuffs : can we rely on reasonable price policy &amp; world (or limited) agreemts on commodities. We can‟t expect to get radical improvements. Tho‟ some hope of special arrangement for N.Z. Chance that Menzies &amp; Holyoak may be persuaded tht. there is chance of reasonable settlement for them.

Raw materials – not much to be secured. Processed foods : concentrate on main items : fruit &amp; salmon.

U.K. agriculture can be considered separately.

Arguments for entering C.M. are v. strong. We must seek to persuade other C. countries that the price is not too high.

E.H. Negotns. at Brussels after last Cab. mtg. 5 days.

Secret mtg. of the 4 to produce amendmts to meet our case. French refused to accept any. U.K. met with Six in p.m. and even offered nil Spaak invited us to submit our amendments. I presented revised version of the document.

Detailed account of the discussions. Culminating at 7 a.m. w‟out final agreement. Settled that deputies shd. resume in Sept. and Ministers early in October. Not a break down – no ill feeling.

Inevitable adjournment.

French tactics – largely obstructive, tho‟ there is a real point of substance on the Financial Regulation.

E.H. Memo. C.M.N. 53.

Association. In general, satisfactory.

Outstanding ques. (i) Ghana – no diffy. expected. Fedn. of Rhodesia to be considered qua in dependent or qua dependent : failing that on lines of Morocco. Protocol. [Not to be discussed in Plenary at C.M.M.]

(ii) Form of association – no progress until Oct.

(iii) Can‟t settle figures until we know how many C‟wealth countries

become associates.

D.S. Don‟t press them to make up their minds now. Enough to demonstrate tht. we have secured good terms if they care to have them. They wd. be better off than now.

(iv) Different posns. on these particular territories : but no special diffies.

Agreed : v. satisfactory position.

Asian Countries.

E.H. x/ E.E.C. have undertaken to negotiate trade agreements before 1966.

Cotton textiles. Four stages of decalage India not quite content – for they under estimate value of promise of remedial action.

Other manufacture and foods. Even slower decalage . A better deal than we have secured for old Doms. or manufacturers.

Tea – great advantage to Asians : opportunity to sell w‟out any tariff in enlarged Community.

Unsettled – jute, Indian kips leather. Diff. for Dundee.

Hand loom goods – nil tariff.

F.E. V. satisfy. to Asians. Play up value of x/. Dundee will be difficult, but solution is inevitable.

Old Doms. : Manufacturers.

No new points – discussed before.

Temperate Foodstuffs.

P.M. New concept vice comparable outlets.

E.H. We originally asked for access up to existing tonnages on same competitive terms. This wd. have given more than they have now.

What we have got is - i) assurance tht. quantitative restns. will not be used except v. state trading and if market grossly disrupted.

This means in effect tht. we have secured the access.

ii) On terms of access, they will have benefit of Montant forfetaire : remedial action thro‟ adjustment of intra Community preference. They will therefore start with advantages over 3rd countries &amp; will retain it until 1970.

iii) Thereafter extent of access will turn on extent to which price policy leaves room for imports. We have on this the phrase “reasonable” opportunity. Unlimited in time &amp; applicable to enlarged Community. Canada e.g. sells 60% to Community of what she sells to U.K. Australia too. Thus, new approach safeguards that trade to Six as well as trade to U.K.

P.M. Let Cabinet have memo. explaining significance (technical) of confrontation and reasonable.

R.A.B. Best way of presenting this is to get A. &amp; N.Z. to say this is a fair &amp; reasonable approach. Some hope of this now. Cdn‟t do it on intellectual basis alone.

E.H. N.Z. Best means is acceptance of our proposals on butter &amp; lamb, which wd. also protect Australia. Failing that, we must try other means.

D.S. Yes : go for the best general plan we can get on these commodities – &amp; then ask for a stronger safety net for N.Z.

This offer of special protocol for N.Z. will greatly ease Holyoake‟s position at P.M.M.

R.M. Fr. have a serious domestic situation on butter.

C.S. Yes : big stocks in France. And smaller off take in U.K. as price rises.

Six will be judged by this – how much of the drop will France accept rather than thrusting it all on N.Z.

Pull between Articles 110 and 39.

Raw Materials – Nil Tariffs.

E.H. Six haven‟t agreed their own posn.. We may get better outcome, in negotns., than is suggested in memo.

Processed Foodstuffs.

E.H. Ditto.

No Ministerial negotn. so far.

Domestic agriculture – 2 main points similarly outstanding.

This will help in presentn. to P.M.M.

P.M. Blacks &amp; browns wd. do v. well out of this.

Whites wd. not do so well.

U.K. public opinion will be concerned mainly over A. and N.Z.

Thus Key figure for P.M.M. = Menzies. Heavy responsibility on him. His visit in summer was of gt. value. Truth is : he doesn‟t like new C‟wealth. A. &amp; N.Z. haven‟t shared in the excitement of C‟wealth developmt. – more desideritum for old “club”. Also fear tht. U.K. will be different if w‟in E.E.C.

R.A.B. He may switch his criticism to pol. consequences. That is easier to argue about. “Betrayal” on economic wd. be more dangerous line for us.

(b) U.K. Agriculture.

C.S. We first argued case for members to top up farmers‟ incomes if they fell behind. We failed to get this as unilateral right – and had to accept tht. this wd. be a Community decision.

Six have now evolved policy for cereals. This will be good for our growers of cereals, but means tht. foodstuffs prices will be higher. Also beef : this wd. be o.k. if we cd. retain calf subsidy. Pigment : costs will rise because of feed prices, but price will have to drop. Mutton : price will have to rise, to protect beef : can‟t estimate effect on consumption. (H. May be v. hard on Scotland). Eggs : price must fall by ⅓rd. p. doz. over 7 yrs. But trend twds. battery will look after

this. Horticulture : tariff protection will be w‟drawn : seekg. 5 years standstill + 5 yrs. decalage during wh. our competitive power can be improved.

On commodities where Six have still to frame policy, we shall be at disadvantage because not yet member with veto.

Excludg. cereals, picture of rising costs (£60 m) &amp; falling prices (60m) – and we may lose £100, on grants. As against that, opportunity to compete in larger market. N.F.U. seem likely to come out in opposition.

H.B. N.I. Govt. have told me their farmers will oppose this, as now foreseen.

E.H. After we had initialled, we shd. be in better posn. to put our views on agric. policy – even tho‟ we have not veto.

W.D. Presentation. On agric. (unlike C‟wealth) we shall have to argue on details, not on broad picture.

J.H. We shall have to say what farmers‟ posn. wd. be if we did not enter.

C.S. But pol. effect on Tory Party might be serious – if e.g. we said existg. prices support policy cd. not have bn. continued.

P.M. Cd. be put objectively, as facts of life – not as Party policy. Prs. by economists etc.

R.A.B. V. serious politically. Bye-elections at Chippenham etc.

N.F.U. Branches will be working v. us.

But (i) can‟t reach final decn. until commodity negotns. completed.

Emphasise final sentence of C.M.N.55.

(ii) For Aug : our policy on grants etc., + realisation tht. these depend on prosperous community. We must take E.E.C. as a fact.

If we are to be prosperous in future, we must enter E.E.C. And can‟t expect unlimited liabilities of existg. policy to continue.

Actually, E. Anglia shd. be o.k. Problem is pigs, eggs and horticulture.

(c) Procedure.

I.M. Party Conference. 27 resolns. on C.M. of which only 4 or 5 are hostile.

Debate on Thursday a.m. on emergency resoln. from platform.

R.A.B. and E.H. to speak.

Any 50 constituencies cd. demand special conference. Elderly people wd. be in majority. Must therefore reserve our right on timing. Might p‟pone it until Jan. &amp; hope that by then there will have bn. a debate and vote in H/C.

E.H. Don‟t mention any date. Don‟t know when we shall complete negotns.

2. Aden.

P.M. A good agreement. Safeguards for defence interests.

3. Congo.

H. Objective – constitl. settlement by agreement betwn. centre &amp; provinces. Ingredients as in para.3.

Plan of natl. reconciliation, agreed with U.S., B. and Fr., as in memo.

A. has accepted this. Gardiner is seeking T.‟s acceptance.

If we don‟t get this accepted, we face sanctions imposed by U.N. – followed, if they don‟t work, by mil. opns. by U.N. supported by U.S.

These are circs. in wh. I seek to offer short term aid ($2 m) + over 4 yrs. another $10 m. p.a. over 4 yrs. as inducement to agreed settlement.

If we want peace in Congo we can‟t get it for less.

B.C. We are £20 m. over aid ceiling. Demands from ex Colonies. Malta coming along. Also Egypt – Laos etc.

Accept short term proposn. But is long term offer to be made, in priority over the other demands.

F.E. No commercial credit likely to be f‟coming w‟out complete E.C.G.D. cover.

P.M. If sanction imposed on copper, we cd. say we wd. buy no more than normal : wd. not use our copper market to break the sanction.

Cd. we promise $2 m. at once &amp; promise to participate in larger

x/ scheme w‟out comitting ourselves to amount – in consultn. with other nations &amp; havg. regard to our commitments in Africa and elsewhere.

Agreed as at x/. F.O. &amp; Ty. to consult on words

for long term plan.

4. Berlin.

H. Dangerous daily situation over R. „bus‟ to Soviet War memorial.

W. Berliners in angry mood. But police seem to be getting it under control. Better leave this to local commandants.

Brandt has bn. sensible.

More generally, no new idea re W. initiative. Opinion on K.‟s next move is divided. But many think he may raise it at U.N. Might not be too bad. Settlements we cd. accept, tho‟ we cd. not have proposed them.

</content>
</cab>
