<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/21/0 images: 21-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.56(62) 13th September 1962

1. Congo. [Enter M.R.

H. U.N. proposals agreed with U.S., U.K., Belgians – French acquiescing.

Plan is reasonable – if A. &amp; T. can be kept sweet and U.N. don‟t bungle it.

We also agreed some parts of plan for appln. tho‟ dissociating ourselves from elements involving sanctions and U.N. force.

Unhappily, U.N. forces taken to ?K. as garrison. Also Indian troops have killed some Africans in Katanga.

For the moment, still some promise of success.

2. Berlin.

H. R. said officially they were willing to suspend conversns. until after U.S. elections. This indicates tht. they are playing for time – not anxious to sign treaty gives chance of talk with G. in N. York.

M‟while local trouble. Stopped R. soldiers using Friedrickstrasse crossing because unruly G. crowds cd. not be controlled there. We provided crossing nearer War memorial. But they have used armoured

y/ vehicles unescorted, contrary to rules applicable to all 4 Forces. U.S. think tht. if this passes w‟out comment, R. will use armoured vehicles

x/ all over city. We have agreed, with some misgivings, to tell R. tht. they can‟t use A.F.V.‟s No reply yet to our note. This was unanimous advice of Commandants &amp; Embassies because of provocation.

C.S. Not unreasonable for R. Better wait until x/.

D. Stress y/.

3. Meeting of Commonwealth P.M.‟s.

R.A.B. Genl. debate concluded – group discns. opened.

Attitude of P.M.‟s harder than expected. Reflected in Press – more than P.M.‟s own speech, for which we hope to get more publicity at week-end.

Menzies less helpful than we hoped – his domestic political situation.

Influenced by demarche of Oppn. Parties. Telling on federation.

Nehru‟s point on increased tension.

Betwn. pol. and econ. was recurring theme that Europe is imperialist cartel wh. wd. be content tht. others shd. confine themselves to primary products. This is aspect of neo. Colonialism. Much of this goes beyond E.E.C. – expectn. of more aid and acceptance of more of their exports.

This theme (followed even by Menzies) must be answered.

Makarios alone mentioned tht. Six exist.

Detailed discussion in groups.

Association. Can‟t improve existg. offer – wh. they are rejecting solely for prestige reasons.

Asians. Nehru v. grudging. Ceylon showed more appreciation.

No recognition of sacrifices we have made on textiles : jute.

All we can do for them is to bring fwd. opening of negotns. on t. agreemts.

Temperate Foods. Canada has nil to fear. Austr. has not shown enthusiasm for world agreements. N.Z., is worse case, put it rationally.

Shall not encourage D. to produce his alternative.

A : accelerate wheat agreement.

N.Z. : some special arrangemt. U.K. trying now to devise one e.g. bulk purchase of butter.

Our aim : series of general statements of purposes e.g. on less developed countries. Seek some improvement of terms in resumed negotiations. Don‟t encourage further P.M.M. – but possible some group mtgs. after Brussels concluded.

Cab. shd. be ready to meet next week e.g. Tuesday.

H. Small preference for manufactures from less developed countries wd. help if we cd. get it.

R.M. African objn. to association – India etc. excluded because too industrialised. Therefore they will be thrown out if they do industrialise.

Desai : if imposn. of tariffs cd. be delayed until trade agreemt. made, this wd. go far to meet them.

F.E. Too much comparison between present &amp; U.K. in. True comparison is betwn. U.K. in and U.K. out (1970). This shd. be stressed.

Dom. responsibility heavy if their statements make it impossible for us to join.

I.M. Opinion – Party &amp; country.

In July we feared effect of opinion moving against entry. It is still moving fast in that direction. Those who form opinion, the young &amp; the travelled are for : the man in the pub is fiercely against (wops begin at Calais). Viz., reverse of situation on Suez.

But because thinking people are with us, we ought to be able to turn it.

i) Party Conference. We shd. be able to carry that.

ii) P.M.M. Must avoid promise of another mtg.

iii) Shd. we now come out boldly in favour of entry – despite disadvantage to our negotiating position. To be considered after P.M.M.

H.B. P.M.‟s speech and content must be put across.

We haven‟t had enough time to put this across – here &amp; overseas.

As things are, we are heading for pol. suicide.

People must be made to realise how badly off we shall be if we are out.

Hope we may raise our bid (on terms) in the autumn. Even if it were refused, our pol. fortunes wd. rally.

W.D. P.M.M. re-action is not surprising.

On iii) are we sure our negotiating posn. wd. be undermined. This shd. be weighed again.

D. If we once say we are going in, shall we get improved terms?

Hail. Put the case more forcibly, but without saying now we are going in. Cd. now be done only on T.V. As soon as P.M.M. is over.

J.H. Remember that, save B‟brook whole Press is on our side.

E.P. Make as few promises to P.M.M. as possible. We shan‟t get much more from Brussels.

Remember, too, tht. by C‟wealth our public means only C., A. and N.Z. We must seem to have done our best for them.

Recent experience in my constituency confirms my view that we shd. state more boldly the case for entry.

R.A.B. We cdn‟t in any event decide to go in before negotns. carried further on commodities. esp. for our own agriculture.

C.S. Brussels deal on temperate foods is not good enough. On old Doms. and on agric. we cdn‟t get it thro‟ Parlt. unless we had a better deal. Worst of all is to find tht. having blown up advantages of getting in, we can‟t get in after all. Must avoid that posn.

I.M. Even so, it is indecision that is telling v. us.

We must simplify the issue. Can‟t rally our people until we take a stand.

H. French are still actively trying to keep us out. If we say now we must get in, we shd. get no more concessions.

4. Bank of England.

R.M. On Bank – increased resources of R.D.A. will increase our contn if our share is re-valued.

fund – discn. on world liquidity Problem : much available that can‟t be used – e.g. U.S. won‟t use gold or borrow from I.M.F. Recently dollar has strengthened. But danger of world deflation if U.S. turned down

next year &amp; commodity prices rose.

Special posn. of U.K. Use of £ as reserve currency by others causes us to retard our economy for no U.K. reason. Caution, however, in trying to extricate ourselves : popularity of “discipline” &amp; effect of I.M.F. discuns. on rates. B/E. have worked out a plan : I shall mention it tentatively. Can only move with co-opn. of U.S. &amp; other principal countries.

[Exit Devenshire, E.P.

5. Incomes Policy.

Railways Wages.

R.M. Beeching‟s case is based on comparability. He proposes another 6% - making 9% in all in ‟62. He wd. offer, &amp; refuse to negotiate. We doubt if that is possible. B. is relating it to cuts in man-power. &amp; l hope we cd. say this publicly. B. may insist on direction if we want a lower figure.

E.M. My main anxiety is to cut the man power. Wages is secondary to that.

B. must not resign. And on tactics B. will have to play it.

B.C. Money comes from Exchequer. Repercussions.

J.H. i) comparability : Guilleband : we are trying to get away from both.

ii) workshops. Yet engineering settled at 3%.

iii) rlwaymen are in no mood to strike. With redundancy staring them

in the face.

H.B. No objn. to early payment of smaller award.

Hail. Severance paymts. needed to secure redn. of man power. This will have to be added to cost.

E.M. Small in reln. to cost of wage award.

</content>
</cab>
