<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/180/20 images: 204-206</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S DOCUMENT IS THE jPROF*ERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT&quot;   - , &apos; &apos; 9 ; -V&apos;   - i,    &apos; &quot;   n &quot;    0C(74) 145 COPY NO     010 December 1974CABINETTOP SALARIES, HOSPITAL CONSULTANTS AND THESOCIAL CONTRACT uMemorandum by the Secretary of State for employment. We ehall without any doubt immensely increase our and the TradesUnion Congress&apos;s (TUC) present difficulties in sustaining the social contracton pay if we give 30-40 per cent increases to the Top Salaries Review Body(TSRB) posts and the hospital consultants,2, The TSRB recommendations are not consistent with the TUC payguidelines.    Nor are the proposed increases for consultants.    If we pretend that they are - by tal&amp;ing about cost of living compensation over several years or about restructuring - we shall not command conviction.    We shall only weaken respect for the guidelines among other groups,.3..        In any case people are not entitled to whatever the TUC guidelinesappear to justify.    Many low paid people are still not going to be able toreach the TUC  30 low pay target, while even a straight cost of livingincrease for the last year would yield gross increases of  40 a week andmore at these top salary levels - more than many people earn as a wholein a week.    It compares, for example, with the extra  3,43 a week thatthe local authority manuals have just secured in getting to the  30 minimum.4. Miners and others will not be slow to draw the moral.    If30-40 per cent is justified for people on five figure salaries, why not for those below?   If the TSRB groups can recoup their position since 1969 -even though they have had the highest level of settlement possible in eachof the last two years - why should others not look back beyond their lastsettlement and recoup what they regard as their losses from an earlier date?   And why should manual workers believe us when we tell them thatthe economy is in a grievous state calling for restraint by all if at the sametime we raise by thousands of pounds the salaries of some of the highestpaid people in the country?5.        I understand, of course, that the time is never ripe for large increases for the more highly paid public servants.    But they have theirstake too in seeing the social contract succeed and the pace of inflationchecked.    It will go hard with them as with the rest of our people if thesocial contract fails,1 IM
&quot;   &apos;&apos;&apos;&apos; \        &apos;:&apos;&apos;S&quot;^r6.        I believe therefore that we must reject the TSRB report.    Weshould allow sufficient increase to those earning less than  10, 000 to remove any acute differential problems with those below, but we should give no increase to those above  10, 000,    We should publicly recognise that these people will be making a special contribution and we should invite all others in the public and private sectors with incomes of  10, 000 or more to forgoany increase in their incomes in 1975.    The Royal Commission on theDistribution of Incomes will be reporting in the course of next year on top salaries generally and we can take stock then of our general policy in this field.7.        This approach willhave to apply to hospital consultants, as well,though I fully recognise the great difficulties involved there.    And it requires that Cabinet Ministers should accept a cut in their salaries.8.        This approach to their recommendations may lead the TSRB to resign.    I would hope not.    But if it did, I imagine that it would not beimpossible to provide for future changes in the higher salaries in the CivilService to be related in some way to pay movements lower down the scale,and for the link across to the judiciary and top posts in the Armed forces to continue.    No doubt there would be greater difficulty with the nationalised industries.9.        But such problems seem to me much less serious than those thatwould flow from acceptance of the present proposals on top salaries.    Weilshould then be playing right into the hands of those who are only too anxiousto break the TUC guidelines beyond repair,,10.       If my colleagues accept the principle of this approach, we should ask officials for detailed proposals for its application.M department of Employment10 December 19742


</content>
</cab>
