<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/19 images: 212-217</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.LORD STAMP:S PAPER,Note by the First Lord of the Admiralty.THE deeply interesting paper of Lord Stamp, sustained by the reports of messrs. Robinson and Jewkes, reminds us of the fact that we have reached amilestone in the war. If the view of the memorandum is accepted, we must now definitely curtail our war objective in men and material, and the impressionwill be spread in all quarters, including French quarters, that we are definitelyrecoiling from the task we set ourselves. This would have a most depressing effect, and would lead at once to relaxation at home, and reproach from abroad.2. It would seem that there are two standards of war effort which we are bound to try to achieve. First, we must equal mutatis mutandis our own effort of last time. Secondly, we must equal the effort of the French this time. To allow any lesser standards than these would be unworthy of our cause, and unequalto our dangers.8.   The following questions arise : (&quot;) Why is the rise in prices made applicable to imports and not to exports ?(b) Why has the income accruing to us from Oil Companies&apos; dividends notbeen assumed to rise agreeably with the assumed doubling of theexpenditure on imported oil ?(c) Why should we assume that the volume of exports cannot be maintained at the peace-time level of 1936-38 through seizing German markets,provided we take the necessary measures ?(d) Why should our shipping gains be reduced to zero ?(e) Why should nearly  20 millions be stricken from our interest and dividends in the face of the expected rise in prices, and the fall inthe  , Avhen the account is kept in sterling ?(/) Arising from the above, may not the net adverse balance of  369 millionsbe subject to marked reduction in our favour ? Could this reductionamount, for example, to  150 millions?(g) Why should it be assumed that, choosing our time advisedly we cannotmarket our assets in the United States at a quicker rate than 150 millions a year, without prejudicially affecting that vast market,which may well be buoyant upon European purchases and Americanimmunity from war?Printed for the War Cabinet.   February 1940.secret.Copy No.W.P. $fp- (30) 8BA. Money.[20780]b
B. Max Power.4. Here we come into direct contact with the French war effort. with only eight-ninths of our island population, with less than half our engineeringresources and two-thirds of our income, the French are maintaining over 100Divisions in the field, as well as a Navy comprising 160,000 men, and an AirForce which, at least in Squadrons formed for active service, is considerable.5. During the last War we ourselves made a much greater Army effort.Our troops went into battle from the eighteenth day. During the first twelvemonths we suffered 330.000 casualties and the severe wastage of munitionsattending constant fighting. Nevertheless, by the twelfth month we had, exclusive of the Indian garrison, 49 Divisions overseas, and were conducting an immensecampaign in the Mediterranean as well as fighting great battles in France. Inthose days, a British Division consisted of 13 battalions. By the twenty-fourthmonth we had suffered 900,000 casualties, and yet had 75 Divisions of 13 battalionseach in constant action. Our great effort, the Somme, was in full fury, and we also had large armies fighting constantly in the Dardanelles and later in the Balkans and in Mesopotamia. Why then should it be heldimpossible for us to achieve 20 Divisions by the twelfth and 55 Divisionsby the twenty-fourth month, when the first five months have already passedwithout any land fighting? I cannot believe that the Naval demand in manpower will exceed that of the last War. It certainly ought not to do so havingregard to the much smaller Fleet possessed by the enemy. The Cabinet shouldsatisfy themselves that the new factors of the Air Force with its super-priorityand of A.D.G.B. are sufficient explanations for the very great shrinkage fromlast time.. 6. The standard of the equipment of our Divisions, particularly in regardto the replacement of material, once they are actively engaged, may well befound to be excessive. We have no right to prescribe for ourselves standardsso high as to keep an undue proportion of our manhood, compared to Frame,out of the fighting line. Even with 55 Divisions at the twenty-fourth monthwe shall not be aiming at half the number of the Divisions already in the french army, although our Divisions are 13,000 strong and the French 16,500. Nodoubt with our Naval contribution, and our priority in the Air, we cannotattempt to rival the French in numbers. But to aim at an Army half as strongas that of France, by the twenty-fourth month, is surely the least we can offeras good comrades and Allies. We have already the heavy artillery of a greatArmy. For the rest, the standards of equipment good enough for the Frenchmust be good enough for us.7. So far as A.D.G.B. is concerned, we are working to a totalof 2.200 long-range A. A. guns, each equipped with 2,500 rounds. Itmay be pointed out that, even if only one enemy aeroplane is broughtclown for every thousand rounds fired, this would account for 5.500German planes; whereas if the guns cannot hit even once in a thousandtimes, the whole character of this defence is called in question, and shouldbe scaled down. Many of the standards worked out arithmetically by theService Departments lead to ridiculous conclusions. If such standards were applied to a German Army of over 200 Divisions, as it will soon be, the unrealityof such methods of calculation becomes obvious. Small armies often have tofight all at once, but, as their size grows, the number of Divisions that can bemaintained from a common pool is increased, and the proportion of divisions in action at any given time is diminished. The same applies to A.D.G.B.; for it is absurd to suppose that all the guns all over the country will be called uponto fire on the full scale.8. It is suggested, therefore, that the Army and A.D.G.B. standards otequipment and ammunition expenditure should be severely revised, and shouldnot be used as a bar to our putting our fair quota, of men into the fighting line.9. A second factor of easement may be noticed. The twenty-fourth monthbrings us to September 1941. This is approaching the end of the campaigningseason, and, even if we could not get the 55 Divisions by that date, they might beready by the thirtieth month (March), when the new campaign would normallyopen.
10. To sum up, nothing has been adduced upon money or man-power whichwould justify us in discarding the extremely modest standards of Army strength at which we are now aiming. We should try to equip our troops on the highestscale, but if this cannot be contrived, they must do their best wuth the kind of scale&apos; accepted in practice by our Allies or enforced by the rigour of the war.If we try our best and fail to realise 55 Divisions in action by the twenty-fourthmonth, we may be driven to accept the thirtieth month. If we were to agree tosuch a-retardation now, we should never realise it even then. It would seemindispensable to lay out all our plants upon the 55-Division scale, and concentrateour efforts on removing limiting factors as they appear.11. Finally, I must ask my colleagues to consider the very grave danger toour alliance with France if we do not do our fair share of the actual fighting on land, i.e., at least half of what they will be doing. There will be many hostilevoices to allege that the British are having a far easier time than the French.Millions of able-bodied men, it will be said, will be getting wages far higher thanin peace-time in all the home services of munitions, A.D.G.B. and A.R.P. It willbe said we are making ourselves comfortable at home, improving our Old age pensions, and our Workmen&apos;s Compensation scales; paying our men, civilians andsoldiers alike, far above the French scale, lavishing an inordinate proportion ofour resources upon home defence, having a far higher proportion of generals and senior officers, an enormous mass of non-fighting units, and only emerging in the battle-line with extremely small numbers.12. It is upon the forces actually brought to bear upon the enemy that oureves must be fixed. For all its vast expenditure, we have only added twenty orthirty Squadrons to the Air Force in the last two years. Out of a million andthree-quarter men, maintained at the most expensive rate and rationed on thehighest scale, we are only producing 10 Divisions by the sixth month and20 Divisions at the twelfth month. We aim only at 55 Divisions by the twenty-fourth month. Now it is argued that even this is too much for us. So far fi&apos;omaccepting any diminution of objective, we ought to hurl ourselves into the taskwith a new surge of impulse, and face all the sacrifices, hardships and exertionswhich this entails.W. S. c.IB 1940




</content>
</cab>
