<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/11/43 images: 426-431</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document,(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT).\ /secret.W.P.   (40) 363. COPY NO. 2?7th September. 1940.WAR   CABINET.DUTIES OF THE POLICE IN CASE OF INVASION.Memorandum by the Home.Secretary.In accordance with the decision of the War cabinet at their meeting on the 23rd August (W.M.(40) 233rd Conclusions;Item 4)^ I am circulating a revised print of the instructionsto the police in the event of invasion.     Paragraph 4 ofthese instructions has been redrafted in the light of thediscussion at the meeting of the War Cabinet referred toabove.J.A.HOME OFFICE.7th September, 1940.

Duties of the Police in Case of Invasion.1. The general principles governing the position of the police in the case of invasion are (a) that the police are not part of the armed forces of the Crown, and that therefore, in theevent of a landing and effective occupation of an area by the enemy in force, the police should not use arms, nor carry arms, in the occupied area ; but(6) that in the event of a landing by isolated parties who do not form part of an occupyingforce and whose object is, or must be assumed to be, to attack civilians, destroy property and cause confusion and devastation, neither the police nor civilians are debarred,either by international law or domestic law, from resisting and, if possible, destroying the enemy, in order to prevent him carrying out these objects.2. What has been said in paragraph (6) above applies to members of the enemy forces whether in the uniform of their units or in disguise, as well as to civilians, saboteurs or other agents, who might be landed, along with troops. In these cases, moreover, rules which might apply in caseof formal occupation of an area do not necessarily apply for the reason that civilians are not likely to be deterred from resistance by fear of possible reprisals, and the enemy&apos;s treatmentof the police or the civil population is not likely to depend greatly on the degree of resistancewhich is encountered or from where it comes.. 3. In some contingencies the distinction between the situations which have been indicatedin paragraph I would be clear : in others they might not be so easy to draw : but the general rules applicable to them may be summarised in general terms as set out below.&apos;   .&apos;&apos;    .       . ; ;&apos;:0;j   . &apos; &apos;   .        .      ..        .     &apos;     i &apos; \      ; /4. In the eventdf a landing and occupation by the enemy in force (a) if it is possible to evacuate some or all of the civil population from the threatened areabefore the landing takes place (i) the main body of the police should assist in controlling the movement and, if notrequired for any local duties, should withdraw, taking with them any arms whichmay have been provided for police use ; they should then place themselves atthe disposal of the military authorities ;(ii) a rear guard of police should be detailed to assist the civil authorities and the civilpopulation, if any remain, to ensure that all necessary measures have been carriedout and to guard against agents making contact with the enemy. When no longer required for these duties or to assist the military authorities this rear guard alsoshould withdraw by such route as may have been pre-arranged with the militaryauthorities.(b) if no measures have been taken for the evacuation of the civil population from the threatened area, or if any elements of the civil population remain in the area after themilitary forces withdraw (i) as many members of the police force as can be spared and are not required by themilitary authorities to stay should withdraw, taking with them any arms whichmay have been provided for police use ;(ii) a rear guard of police who should, so far as possible, be men who arc over military age and whose families have not been evacuated, should remain behind. their instructions should be to ensure that the civil population conform to any orders which may have been issued, e.g., as to remaining where they are, and generally to do everything in their power to assist the civil authorities and the civilians whoremain.5. In case of a landing by isolated parties of troops presumably for sabotage, etc., or the landing of other saboteurs . (a) the police should immediately inform the appropriate Military and Air Force Authorities,and on or near the coast also the Naval or Coastguard Authorities. The particularstation or stations to be informed should be ascertained and recorded at every policestation.(6) the police should do all in their power to overcome the enemy and prevent destructionof life or property. (In case of a landing by aeroplane its destruction should be preventedif possible).(c) as to the measures which may properly be taken for this purpose the following, whichare particularly mentioned in the Home Office circular of the 25th May last, shouldbe borne in mind : (i) the employment of armed patrols, especially in rural districts and the approaches to important towns ;(ii) armed police posts at bruises or other key points.   For purposes of this kind, the armed parties should mSle made up of police personnel, and, generally speaking-armed parties should not be formed partly of civil and partly of Home Guard orother military personnel. Where, however, both police and Home Guard personnel are employed on guard at vulnerable points, the former may retain their arms forthe present, pending further instructions.(d) great care must be taken, however, to distinguish landings in distress.   In any suchcase, whether the landing is from enemy or. friendly aircraft, first aid or any other necessary assistance must be rendered. If, however, there is no evidence of an aircrafthaving crashed, the possibility of treacherous behaviour by enemy personnel must beborne in mind.asjf.-21380/150   Sept./1940




</content>
</cab>
