<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/62/41 images: 374-377</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET. &apos;W.P. (45) 136.5th March, 1945.WAR CABINET.ORGANISATION OF CIVIL AVIATION.Memorandum by the Minister of Information.THE Plan presented by the Minister for Civil Aviation in his W.P. (45) 118proposes three companies for the operation of all British civil airlines. B.O.A.C.would share with the shipping and railway companies in this monopoly.2. An expanding and swiftly developing science, such as Air Transport,can never be served efficiently by monopolies in which healthy rivalry is eliminated.I ask the War Cabinet to approve a plan whereby the pre-war Air TransportLicensing Authority is reconstituted to license British airlines according to publicnecessity and convenience on the routes to be operated.. 3. British airline development should not be entrusted through monopoliesto railway and shipping companies, who could then strangle competition withtheir surface interests. At the best they would not countenance the undercuttingof their rail and shipping fares by their airlines.4. Lord Swinton proposes the inter-availability of tickets by sea, rail andair, thus tying air to surface charges. The organisation then becomes a cartel &quot;an agreement between operators to keep prices high.&quot;5. The proposal that types of civil aircraft should be ordered throughB.O.A.C. and serviced through a monopoly company would mean that the Govern-ment would : &apos;(i) specify and order the aircraft;(ii) superintend their design;(iii) oversee their development;(iv) operate them; and(v) control maintenance.6. I believe that such a plan, if accepted, would destroy British Civil aviation-tion.   It would throw open the world to domination by American airlines.7. I ask the War Cabinet, to approve instead a policy of public hearingsfor all those interests which wish to operate British air services. These hearingsshould be followed by the award of licences for regulated airline competition and the development and expansion of British Air Transport services.B. B.Ministry of Information, W.C. 1,5th March, 1945.Copy No[29359]&quot;




</content>
</cab>
