<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/73/0 images: 34-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i           Admiralty Memorandum for War Cabinet showing the                   proposed Disposal of Enemy Ships  of War.                               Enemy Submarines.    All German, Austrian, and  Turkish submarines surrendered under the terms of theArmistipe are to be sunk within three months of the signing of the Peace Treaty.  AllBulgarian submarines are to be  surrendered within the same period and sunk.    All submarines building, or unfit for sea, in Germany and Austria, to be destroyedunder Allied supervision within 3 months of the signing of the Peace Treaty.  german submarines interned in neutral countries are to be surrendered  to the Allies  and sunk.                                              *    The above  action will  be taken in order to prevent  the  Central Powers com-mencing another submarine  campaign  in the  near future; and while removing thepossibility of any disagreement among the  Allied and. Associated  Powers as to thedistribution of the submarines, it will be a judgment  on the enemy for the outragescommitted by his submarines during the war.                           Enemy Surface Warships.    Note. In all cases where it  is laid down that enemy vessels, built or building,should be destroyed the following reasons have dictated the policy:      (i) To reduce the Naval power of the enemy.     (ii) To prevent the enemy again acquiring the ships.    (iii) To avoid disagreement among the Allies and Associated Powers as regards           the distribution of  the Ships.Germany.    All  vessels  interned  under  the  terms  of the Armistice,   and the  nine  otherremaining &quot; Dreadnought&quot; battleships, are to be surrendered to the Allied and associated powers, and are to be  sunk in deep  water  within 3 months of the signing of thePeace Treaty.    In  addition, warships interned in  neutral ports are to be  surrendered and  sunkwithin 3 months of delivery.    *The vessels remaining, which are for the most part obsolescent, will leave germany with sufficient vessels for self-protection and police duties, while not giving her navalpredominance in the Baltic.Austria.    Battleships, cruisers, light cruisers, gunboats, destroyers and torpedo boats under allied supervision are to be sunk in deep water within  3 months of the signing ofthe Peace Treaty.Turkey.    All Turkish warships surrendered to the Allies are to be sunk in deep water within months of the signing of the Peace Treaty.     For self-protection and police purposes, Turkey will have those vessels which shewas allowed to retain under the terms of the Armistice.Bulgaria.    All vessels are to be surrendered  to the Allies and Associated Powers  and  sunkin deep water within 3 months of the signing of the Peace Treaty.Germany and  Austria.    Armed Merchant Cruisers, whether  in German or Austrian ports or  interned in neutral ports, and Fleet Auxiliaries  which are  capable  of being readily adapted for commercial purposes or which are converted merchant vessels,  are to be dealt with asmerchant  vessels through  the Allied  Maritime Transport   Council.  Any FleetAuxiliaries not considered suitable  for conversion, and all  local patrol  vessels andminesweepers, are to be retained by Germany and Austria.                          * For details, vide page 2.o (33) AS 6926 Pk      100  1/19 B&amp;S
Germany, Austria  and Turkey.     All vessels being built (torpedo boats and above)  which  are in a sufficiently advancedstate of construction to be launched are to be surrendered to the Allied and associated powers as  soon  as possible  after the  signing of the Peace Treaty and sunk;  theremainder are to be broken up under Allied supervision within 3 months of the signing of the Peace Treaty.      Approximate List of  Vessels of  War left  to Central  Powers when the                           above Terms have been Enforced.                                                                                   *                                         Germany.Type.Number.Remarks.Obsolete BattleshipsCoast defence shipsObsolete cruisers  -Light cruisers, modernLight cruisers, olderLight cruisers, obsoleteT.B.D.&apos;s, modo::.  -&apos;J .B.D.&apos;s, older   -T.B.D.&apos;s, old-T.B.&apos;s, modernT.B.&apos;s, old -  -16 disarmed and serving as accommodation or training ships.2 with machine guns only.  Prisoner-of-war hulks.3 with armament on board.All disarmed.1 disarmed.  1  training service.1 torpoio experimental ship.1905-6 and later.  All armed with 5-1896-7 1904-5.  All armed with 4-1 training service.  1 gunnery ship.All 4* 1-inch  guns.  22 possibly not  complete,  and would  therefore be surrendered or broken up under Peace Terms.All armed witit 22-pdrs.I Numbers are not definitely known, as several have been sunk.&apos; 9-inch guns.&apos; 1-inch guns. Others disarmed.Austria.Light cruisers, obsolete -T.B.D.&apos;s, modern -T.B.&apos;s  -    -    -    -    2    1About 12Built 1885.   Both disarmed.&quot;Lovcen,&quot; 787 tons.  2-3-9-inch, 6- 11-pdrs,,  4-21-inch  T.T.Number very doubtful.Turkey.GunboatsMotor craft -

</content>
</cab>
