<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/73/0 images: 111-117</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Thlc Doi&apos; MO E3 I f,-5;7th January 1919.           WAR CABINET.(Co.-ordination-of JDemobillsatIon Section)       WEEKLY APPRECIATION No.  1.          The following table shows the progress ofdemobilisation since the signing of the Armistice J-BRANCH	Strength at Numbers Demobilised. 11th November,1918.				Officers.	Other Ranks.	Officers.	Other Ranks.NAVY. AIR FORCE. TOTAL.	52,000 558,000 50,000	360,000 5,353,000 260,000	678 1,954 312	7,712 (a) 305,539 (a) 17,274 (b)	83&amp;r 30	5,973,000	2,944	330,525	(a) At 2nd January 1919. (b) At 30th December 1918.			It will be seen that the total number demobilised is333,469, the numbers demobilised during the seven daysended 2nd January amounting to .64,000 as &quot;compared withapproximately 50,000 in the preceding seven days.   Thetotal figures include 144,351 who were discharged fromthe Reserve, Class W etc., a large number of whom were already in olvil employment.     Naval demobilisationdiffers ^&apos;rom that of the Army and the Air  Force becauseof the comparatively large proportion of long service men now in the Navy.   These men have been sent on leaveprior to recommissioning the ships for foreign service.
On their return, the &quot;Hostilities Only&quot; men will be released.          Up to the present, including those demobilisedbefore the date of the Armistice, 115,000 Miners havebeen returned to civil employment, which is approximatelyhalf the number of Miners in the Army in all Theatres ofWar.   This number has enabled the Coal Controller toremove all restrictions on the extension of workingswhich had been prohibited during the War.   arrangements have been made for the release.of the remaining Miners.          It is not possible at the present time tostate the number of Pivotal men and Demobilisers whohave been released;  but information on this point hasbeen asked for and it is hoped can be included in laterissues of the Appreciation.    The applications forPivotal men must pass through the Head Office of theController-General of Demobilisation, and in many cases are certified by Trade Associations.   The rate atwhich these applications are dealt with has practicallydoubled during the past week, being now upwards of6,000 per day.   Up to the 1st January, the Controller- -General had applied by name to the Navy, Army, or AirForce for 43,542 Pivotal men and 30,000 Demobilisers.          The scheme under which Officers and men inthe Forces had to apply on Civil Employment forms forrelease5 is now beginning to work;  but there has notyet been time to secure the discharge of any appreciablenumbers by that procedure *   Up. to the 2nd January662,000 forms had&apos; been received from H*M0 Forces, and
they are being dealt with in the various labour exchanges.   As soon as there has been time for the forms to be linked up with offers of reinstatementor employment, the number of forms returned to theArmy for the release cf men will be reported.          The working of this procedure has no doubtbeen affected by the direct Contract system whichwas introduced with a view to speeding up the release.of men.   Some 200,000 applications from employers for the release of individual men have been receivedby the Labour Exchanges, and in many cases the formhas been vise&apos; and sent forward to the man who, if heaccepts the position, can hand the application to hisCommanding Officer.   The man is then registered for release when the necessary priority is reached.          The release of men by name is necessarily a somewhat slow procedure, and to ensure the demobllisa-tion of the Forces at a greatly accelerated rate, itwill be necessary to release large numbers by groups.To some extent this has already been resorted to, and groups, such as Students and Teachers, men over 41years of age, etc., may now be released in accordancewith the priority instruction from day to day.          I believe that at the present time the in-structions as to groups, coupled with the names whichhave gone forward, should enable the commanding officers of Units to supply their quota of the dailydraft for demobilisation.    These instructions will
be expended as necessary j   end the V.&apos;a.r Office havehad considerable negotiation with the French withthe result that arrangements have been made to trans-port after the 23rd January 17,000 men a day as wellas 1,500 Colonials.   In addition to this 18,500 menwho will be transported by the ordinary Cross-Channelroutes, it is hoped to be able to arrange for 4,000men per day to be shipped from Antwerp to an east coast port.    Arrangements have also been made whereby the whole of the white forces in Mesopotamiawill be brought through the Red Sea during the presenttrooping season.     Demobilisation of the Home Commandscan keep pace with the demobilisation of the forces overseas.          The cessation of hostilities has broughtabout unemployment in certain Trades;  but the extentof this unemployment is not yet sufficient to causeanxiety.   The total numbers unemployed at the end ofthe year may be given as roughly 350,000.  This has only been analysed by industry up to the SOth December,and a copy of this analysis is appended.   On thatdate the- total numbers unemployed in the Tradescovered by the 1911 and 1916 Acts represented 5.88$This is not a large percentage compared with pre-war experience.   Of the Trades covered by the 1911 Actunemployment on the 20th December only exceeded thefigures in 1913 and 1914 in one Trade, namely, En-gineerlng.   This Trade had an unemployment percentageon the 20th December 1918 of 5.90^ as against Z% inDecember 1913.These percentages do not. however, in my
opinion by any means represent the maximum percentageof unemployment which will be reached ,   I think itwill be some time before the numbers which can be absorbed -by Peace industry will even balance the num-bers which must of necessity be discharged from war industry;  and until that state of equilibrium isreached we shall have an accumulated balance of people discharged.   The quick release of Pivotal menand demobilised is  one of the most important keyfactors of the situation, and it is one which is beingstrongly impressed upon the Admiralty, &quot;War Office, andAir Ministry.   Until Employers of labour recoverthese men, they will not seriously consider launchingout into new enterprise.          Considerable progress has been made in thedevelopment of the schemes of Local Authorities forthe construction of Workmen&apos;s houses.   Subject to treasury approval, financial terms have been agreed with the Local Authorities, and steps have been takento secure an adeqaute output of bricks, windows, doors,etc..   The limiting factor at the present time isthe provision of the necessary road frontage;  and before the schemes can be completed, upwards of 500miles of new road will be required.          It will be remembered that in 1916 when thenecessity for improved roads in Prance became so urgent,the engineers and skilled roadmen of this Country were largely called upon for this work.   Road plant wasalso lent by the Local Authorities.   Until these men
t897th January 1919.and plant are returned,  no appreciable progress inroad construction is possible.   The l?ar office have agreed as a first step, to immediately return tothis Country one-third of the roadmen and plant nowin France, and this will enable a considerable amountof the preliminary work of the Housing schemes to beundertaken.          The whole position of industry is beingcarefully reviewed, and the various factors retardingdevelopment are being dealt with in detail.   N&quot;any questions affecting the rehabilitation of industry,which are either not strictly demobilisation questionsor of such great importance that Cabinet decision is called for, are being referred to the War Cabinet for decision - such as the War Pledges Bill, Excess Profits,Depreciation in Plant and Buildings, the Training ofDisabled Soldiers, etc.,  and until a definite policycan be announced on these questions, it seems im-possible to look for the development of industry whichis so much desired.                        (Signed) Eric Geddes.
Dumber of Civilian and        Out-of-  ork Donation nolicies  90 remaining lodged  at all  Local Offices on Friday  20th Dec. 1918, with the percentage  to  total  books Current.	rolicles Lodged. 20th Dec	% 20th Dec.	1 13th Dec.	% 6th Dec.Building Cons.of :orks Shipbuilding Eng. &amp; Ironfovnding Cons, of Vehicles Saw milling Other Industries	15,135 2,114 4,082 81,789 3,979 252 221	3.28 2.27 1.47 5.90 2,43 2,49 0.63	2.36 1.61 1.10 4.30 1.92 2.33 .&quot;*	1.98 1.67 0,79 2.99 0,66 9.20Total Industries under 1911 Act.	107,572	4,43	3.24	2,32Ammunition Chemicals Iron &amp; Steel Tinplate 1 ire Huts, Bolts, Screws Brass Copper, Tin, Lead Hardware k Hollow-ware Tools, Cutlery Clocks, Jewellery Needles, Pins Elec. &amp; Surg.Instruments Misc. Metal Vorfi: Leather Brick, Tile, etc Sawmilling Hubber pther^Insured 1 orkpeople	32,268 2,764 1.814 172 357 567 1.073 550 3.078 201 , 148 239 048 , 413 1,409 699 2,873 1.299 58,175	13,28 2.99 1.10 1.38 1.47 2,27 3.94 1.89 3.01 0.91 1.16 2.31 1.81 6,33 2.70 2.91 3.98 2,49 25.05..	11,85 1.95 1.09 1.11 1.43 1.63 3.94 1.73 2.42 0.80 0,80 1.58 1.58 4,44 1.80 1.79 3,19 2.24 17.44	9.05 1.46 0.60 0.60 1,17 1,03 2.04 3.11 0.63 0,36 0,45 0.78 2.01 4.32 1.06 0,79 1.80 1,40 8.49Total Industries wder 1916 Act	109,047	8,67	j 6,70	4.07totals Mi &amp; m$&quot;Ui$:	210,619 1	&apos;5.88	4,42	2.91Total Uninaurable Occupations	52.742	m	*	mt Grand Total ! 269.361		** 1, ...............		m 1 &apos; U------------------

</content>
</cab>
