<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/73/0 images: 130-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0149/6105.WAR  CABIIT:-1(7*THE SITUATION IH RUSSIA.Memorandum by the Secretary of. State for War.          I circulate for the information of my colleagues a letter which I have received from Mr.  Henry Pearson,  Chief Manager of  theAlexander Kevslcy (C.J.Pahl) Cotton Spinning and Weaving Hills,petrograd,MILNER.8th January,  1919.Shirley House, 52,Montpelicr Rd,    Brighton,January 2nd,  1919,The Right Honourable Viscount  Ivliln*r,  G.CB., G.C.M-G. Your Excellency,          Pardon  me  for  troubling you, &quot;&quot;-ut I wish to draw your attention to  the  question  of the Bolshevik menace to European civilization  and  liberty,  and principally to Russia and the  countries adjacent to Russia,   I only arrived  in England  from Petrograd about a month ago,  after a residence  in Russia of ^b  years, I was  arrested in the  British  Embassy in  Petrograd, when the Bolsheviks raided it* and murdered  Captain Cromie, was  sentenced to be shot, and subsequentl,imprisoned  in the Fortress of St. Peter and St,Paul for fifty days: and have witnessed the horrible brutalities practised upon their prisoners by  the  Bolsh;.boisheviks.  I hav  done my best since arriving in England to  enlighten my  fellow-countrymen and countrywomen as to the real  state  of affairs in Russia.  By invitation of Sir Henry Norman, and Commander Bean,  V,C,  I spoke at five big meetings in Blackburn (my native-..  town)  for the coalition candidat-s and against Philip  snowden, the  Bolshevik candidate, I also have an article appearing in  the  January number of the &quot;Nineteenth Century&quot;, I mention all this  to  show you how I feel on the  matter.          I wish  to  preee  upon  you the extreme  urgency of speedy British interference in  Russian affairs,  The Bolshevik array as a permanent fighting force is largely  a myth, and a hug;; Cluff on th-- part  of Trotsky (Bronstein),  The bulk of the army is composed of former  criminals, as you know that all the former criminal prisons  * are roofless, and thousands of  criminal prisoners have returned from  Siberia, and nearly all are  enrolled in the Red Army,   Thousands of officers and soldiers of the former army have been compelled, under threats and terrorism, to join the Red Army; and;, as the mills and works have  closed down, the workpeople have joined the army in order to get food, The -Red  Army  men have the first call  upon food supplies, and are promised sufficient food rations, 2 l&quot;bs of bread per day, sugar, tea,  etc., uniform,  and 400 roubles per month pay.  The rest of  the population are left to  starve.   No one;thinks
 i;:s that the ;-.\ed Arr^y will face an Allied force, and we should tainly see a stampede of the Bolshevik forces at the first ious engagement.   In fact, all the Russian former officers and men :I met in the Fortress and elsewhere openly declared that they id desert to the British lines at the first opportunity, f.tly or wrongly,  the intellectual Russians say the British made Revolution,  and it was through British influence that tcpo  off was overthrown,  and they look to us to rid them from tyrunny of the Bolsheviks..  The Red Army is only kept together promise of food and loot,  and if intervention had only taken   earlier, it would have  &quot;been a comparatively easy matter and  1 tin red delay only makes the task more difficult, especially if re ie a union with the German 33olshevik3*  We must not lose sight the fact that this movement is engineered and managed by  astute 3, many of them criminals, and nearly every commissary in Russia a Jew,  and I have noticed, since I camtto this country, that tings of protest against intervention are largely composed of en Jews, and that in constituencies where there is a large ish vote,  it has invariably gone to the extreme SocialistIlidate.  lo private telegrams or letters havo been allowed in mt of Russia and for at least a year no foreign nevspapors epting German) were allowed into Russia.  All the newspapers ised to the Bolsheviks have been closed long ago,  and their cos and machinery nationalized, and the editors either shot !ut into prisons.   3?or the sake of humanity it is imperative , something Bhould be done to put a-speedy end to this criminal, dthirsty and horrible combination misnamed  a &quot;peasants  andl!uiienTs Republic1&apos; I could go on indefinitely with tales of horrorpre witnessed in Russia under this terrible regime,  but I11 sure you know most of what is passing in Russia.  Hoping thatIsball soon see intervention of the Allies on a larger scale,I remain,Your sincerely,      (Sd).  E3ITKY PEARSON. &apos;

</content>
</cab>
