<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/73/0 images: 258-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ThH Document is the Property of                   ui,  ontannic Majesty&apos;s Govertynent^    SURPLUS GOVEHMBNT  PBOPBPvTY  IN P?jiHG3.   C^.(\ f&amp;memorandum &quot;by the  President of the Board of gradgU     With reference to War Cabinet Paper G.T.  6542,  I ha TOmade preliminary enquiries with  a view to ascertaining how muchof the transport material now  in Prance is  likely to be wantedin this country, and the  results are  shown in  the followingstatementsRailway 8*     The railY/ay companies  will want  their^rolling  sio-ok  JwHTurotfd(Dossibly with  some  small exceptions)  but nothing else.          !*They v/ill like  to offer for one  or  two items  of  War Otfioe etoakbut not for the bull.    precise  information as to &quot;their require-ments is being  obtained.Liffht Bailways.     Neither rails nor stock will be wanted here;   any lightagricultural lines that it may be decided to  build  can be.&quot;suppliedf om this country.Port Equipment.     Nearly all the cranes and- similar plant can be used in thiscountry.   A schedule of the cranes etc.  likely to  be  availablewill he circulated as soon as possible to the Port  Authorities.Inland Water Transport.     Some of the tugs and barges may be of use on  the  largerEnglish canals, and possibly a number for lightering purposes at-ports.   Steps will be taken to circulate schedules.Railway Engineering Plant.   /     It is unlikely that this will be wanted here.Bgad Plant.     The whole of this (which mostly belongs to the  local authorityleg)will be wanted in this country,and the Boad Board  are  in communication with the War Office.&apos;     I suggest that the French Government might be  informedgenerally in the above sense,  and to Id that further enquiries are /being made with all possible spee&amp;,  with a view to, decidingin detail which items of transportation plant can be offered  tothem.     It seems desirable that early steps should be  taken  toestablish the proposed organisation for supervising the &amp;iSposalVv-of surplus Government property, but I would suggest that  theWar Cabinet should consider whether the  sale of transportationmaterial to the French Government should not be placed in thehands oi a special committee or other body.A.H. STANLEY.Board, of Trade,     14th January,  1919.

</content>
</cab>
