<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/73/0 images: 275-287</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  November 1918.SECRET.(11040.)                      No.  1.                   [WITH&apos; MAP.]Mr. Lockhart to Mr. Balfour.-(Received November 8.)Sir,                                                  London, November 7, 1918.     I  HA VP] the honour to enclose herewith a memorandum dealing with the internal situation in Russia from the 28th January to the&apos;30th September, 1918.  For purposesof convenience I have divided this memorandum into three sections:          1. Bolshevism and the Bolshevik Government;         2. The Counter-Revolutionary Forces ;  and         3. Allied Intervention.     As Aliied intervention would seem to be the most important need of the moment,I have so arranged the memorandum so that the section dealing with intervention can betyped as a separate report.     In sending you this account of my activities in Russia I  have the honour to expressmy deep regret that, owing to circumstances over which I had no control, I was unableto leave Russia without falling into the hands  of the Bolsheviks.  I regret sincerelythe trouble and inconvenience thus  caused to His Majesty&apos;s Government.  At the sametimeT  venture most respectfully to  express to you  the warmest gratitude of myself andof the other members of my mission for your successful efforts in securing our release.     I feel that in many respects my mission has  not succeeded.   I trust, however, thatthe valuable material and information which we have  been able to obtain concerning a movement that constitutes a menace  to the whole civilised  world may redeem it from being considered altogether as a failure.                                                  I have, &amp;c.                                                      R. H. B. LOCHFART                                    Enclosure.              MEMORANDUM ON  THE&quot; INTEBNAL SITUATION IN RUSSIA.                 No. 1. Bolshevism and the Bolslievik Government.(a.) Internal Policy.    AT the present moment the Bolsheviks  have been in absolute power  for exactlyone year.   With reluctance I am forced to admit that their position is to-day perhapsstronger  and more consolidated  than  at  any previous period during  the  pasttwelve  months.&apos;  They  possess one  fundamental attribute of any real government:physical power to enforce their decrees.  By  methods, on which I shall dwell later,they have put down anarchy and  counter-revolution until  t6-day within the limits ofthat Russia which they rule  there  is more order of a kind than there  has been at any moment since the first revolution in February, 1-917.    As a proof of their virility,  1 would point out that since the 7th  November, 1917,their government has remained  practically unchanged, and in spite of many  trials theDu-umvirate of Lenin and Trotsky is still unchallenged.    It  is a mistake to imagine  that  the terrible measures of repression which  arebeing carried out almost daily in Petrograd and Moscow are the result  of anarchy or thework of an irresponsible  mob.  They are in reality part of a system which aims  at  thedestruction of all opponents of Bolshevism in general, and  of  all propertied  classes inparticular.   And for these measures  the Bolshevik  leaders alone must  bear the  full responsibility.      [996]                                                             B
  It is frequently pointed out in the foreign press that the Bolsheviks rule  by methods which for cruelty surpass the worst days of the old regime and  which are opposed  inevery sense to what we call democracy.  This is undeniably  true, and the  Bolsheviksthemselves admit these accusations quite frankly.     They point out that until capitalism is destroyed  the  mere fact that every manhas a vote does not in itself make for equality, and in  their struggle  lor this equalitythey consider any measures  justifiable.   They have therefore  restored  the death sentence which is generally enforced  without any further trial than the decision of the half-dozen  men  who compose the  Directorate  of  the  Commission  for  combatingCounter-Revolution and Speculation.  They have taken away the vote from all exceptworkmen and the poorer peasants.  They have suppressed all newspapers except thosewhich favour  their own  cause, and  they  have  so  far oppressed  and maltreated theRussian bourgeoisie as to render that unfortunate class almost entirely destitute.     It would seem at first sight that a regime  of this kind  would soon render  itselfhated to a large percentage of the population.  It has been stated and  not. untruly that the Bolshevik supporters  do not  number more than  10 per cent, of the entirepopulation.   Since November of last  year practically every Russian  politician, and certainly every English expert  on Russia, have  assured  us that the  Bolsheviks couldnot last for more than a few weeks.   There  have been moments when the  Bolsheviksbelieved themselves that their end was near; for example, after  the first Brest peace,after the Czeeho-Slovak  revolt, after  Count  Mirbach&apos;s murder, and  again on the5th  August,  when Dr. Helferich left Moscow  for Berlin with the avowed  purposeof  persuading  his  Government  to  suppress  the  Bolshevik  regime  in  Russia.In spite, however,  of numerous crises  the Bolshevik  Government has  maintainedits   position,  and  even  if one makes  the  wildest  allowances for  the terroristicmeasures by which  the  Bolsheviks rule,  it must be admitted that  the success  of bolshevism in Russia is due  to some more deep-rooted cause than the mere terrorism ofa band of workmen.   Indeed, although the Bolshevik  supporters may not number morethan 10 per cent, of the population, their worst enemies  cannot  deny their energy and party discipline.   Unfortunately, too, no other  party  can claim even half as large a percentage of supporters.   In  Russia the  aristocracy  and bourgeoisie  (including thepetite bourgeoisie) do not number more than 15 to 20 percent, of the entire population,and  this small percentage  is divided against itself  into  Monarchists,  ConstitutionalMonarchists,  Republicans, and Socialists.  Some 70 per cent,  of the population, i.e., themajority of the peasantry, remain amorphous and inactive.  But  this very inactivity isin itself a certain advantage  to the Bolsheviks whose influence amongst a non-Bolshevikpeasantry is to be ascribed almost entirely to the Brest peace  and the land reform.   at every congress, at every Soviet election, at every  meeting, the Brest peace has savedthe Bolsheviks time  and again.  Condemned as it was by  many of the  Bolsheviksthemselves, the  Brest peace from the  Bolshevik  point  of view is a further proof ofLenin&apos;s  clear-sightedness and  sagacity.   The peasant is  by instinct pel it  bourgeois,and  with certain reservations it seems probable that Russia will  become  a, land of smallholdings. The peasant, however, must have land.  He  really requires it to live, andfor   years  almost every party has encouraged  him to  expect  it.  The  Bolsheviksgave him   the   land not  exactly  as  he  desired it,  perhaps,  and without  anyvery great   security of tenure, but still  without any  restriction or delay.  Skilfullynursed  by  Bolshevik  propaganda,  and  warned by the  concrete example of theSkoropadsky regime in the Ukraine,  he believes  that  counter-revolution-means therestoration of the land to the landowners, and as all other  parties urge  him to break the-Brest treaty he prefers with his limited understanding a regime which gives himboth land and peace to a regime which he does not know, and which will send him backto the trenches.   The result of the German occupation in the  Ukraine is an example anda warning of what one may expect from a reactionary and  purely  military intervention in Russia.  The peasant, it is  true,  objects strongly to  the  Bolshevik  requisitions of grain and foodstuffs.   This may lead to  trouble  in  the  future,  but  in  his presentdisorganised state it is unwise to hope too much  from  the peasant  as an anti-Bolshevikelement.  He might welcome a deliverer who would relieve his wants, but he will, and can do  little on his  own account.   And  certainly he does not  want to  do any morefighting either for himself or for anyone else.     In  spite of all reports to the contrary the workmen are still  true to  their Bolshevikleaders.  This again,  is partly due to the  Bolshevik method  of  suppressing all  other parties, but chiefly to the fact that  under the  Bolshevik regime  the working man  isin a peculiarly favoured position.  Of such food as is  available  he has the first choice.He receives large wages, and his working hours  are short.  He  complains, it is true, of
the cost of liAing and of the dearth of food and manufactured goods.  He is, however,better educated  than the peasant,  has been brought  up on Socialistic doctrines, andreadily believes  that  his present difficulties  are  due  to the efforts of the capitalisticGovernments  of Germany and the  Allies to suppress the anti-capitalistic proletariatrevolution of Russia.  He is inspired  to a  certain extent  by the ideals of Bolshevismand class-warfare.    Finally, while the economic policy of the Bolsheviks, to which  1 shall refer  later,seems likely to bring their regime to ruin, the force of Bolshevism as an idea should notbe  under-estimated.  The Bolsheviks themselves may go,  but  Bolshevism and theSoviet idea have entered deeply  into  the  mind of the Russian people and may bedifficult to eradicate.   It is  impossible  to believe  that the Russian people will everaccept Tsardom  under its ancient form.  Much as we all like the educated Russian, wemust  not  close our eyes to the fact that when the British press makes use  of the phrase&quot; all the best-thinking Russians,&quot; it is referring  to a small minority amongst a vastand ignorant population.  Nor should it be  forgotten that it  is largely  owing to the inherent weakness and incapacity of this class that we owe the present chaotic conditionof Russia.(b.) Bolshevik Foreign Policy.    In an article in the  &quot;New Europe&quot; in  May of this year,  Professor Pares statesthat there are only two ideas in this war : one, the German idea  of world-domination,and, two, the  national idea of peopled rights and peopled frontiers.   There is, however,a third idea, which is certainly not novel but which has gained considerable popularityin  all countries  since the war, namely, the international idea of class warfare and anti-capitalism.   &quot;To turn  the first imperialistic war into  a  civil war,&quot; this  is the guiding principle which Lenin adopted years  before the  war, and  from which  he has never swerved.     It is  to the  dangers of this idea that  I venture  most respectfully to direct the-attention  of His Majesty&apos;s Government.  Whatever may be Lenin&apos;s policy as regardsRussia herself, it is clear that  he looks upon his  mother country merely  as  the mostfertile ground for his experiments.  A general European revolution  on a  class basis is,and always has been, his goal, and it is from this angle only that Bolshevism should be viewed.   I shall not enter here into the vexed  controversy  of the  Bolshevik relationswith the Imperial German Government.  As far as*the Bolshevik leaders are concerned and, in particular, Lenin, who is the brain and guiding force of the Avhole movement, Ihave never  believed  in such a combination, and the  documentary  evidence  which has&apos;recently  been  published  by  the U.S.A. Government only strengthens this  belief.Without further discussion,  however, it is obvious to-day first, that even if Lenin tookmoney from the  German Government, he used it for his own ends and not for Germanends,  and, secondly,  that Bolshevism has now gone far beyond the stage of any. outsidecontrol.   It is perhaps  no  exaggeration to say that Bolshevism  is now a far greaterdanger to Europe than German militarism.    At the present moment Lenin&apos;s eyes are focussed  on Central Europe.  He knowsand understands perfectly the weak and strong joints in  his armour.   He has  greathopes of a class revolution in Italy, Austria and Germany.  He  is certain of it in theUkraine and in Poland, and he admits quite openly  that such  a revolution  has leastchance of success in  England  and in America in  England, as he  says, because theworking-classes are too ignorant (ie., of Socialism) !  He knows that without the classrevolution in  other  countries his  own regime is  doomed because of the unreliablematerial upon  which he has to work in Russia.  His great  hope is fixed on the GermanSocialist party, which is strong and well-disciplined, and which might conceivably makea success of social revolution.  While his foreign policy has bc-en governed by playingoff  the Central  Powers and  the Allies against each other, he has never ceased toendeavour to strengthen his position with the German  Socialist party.  It was in orderto strengthen  his position with  that party that  he maintained such a bitter propaganda against the Allies, and his main task has been to  exist  until the  German Socialistsshould follow his example.   He  has done much propaganda in  Germany both  beforeand since the revolution, and  he has  many friends amongst the independent GermanSocialist  party.   In this connection it  is significant  to note how the  British  pressdenounces Lenin as a traitor and in the same breath lauds  Liebknecht to the skies as a genuine Socialist, and almost indeed as a hero.  It should  be recognised  at once thatLenin and Liebknecht represent one and the same thing, and that the latter is as great a danger to  Europe as the former.   We should  do well, too, to accept with caution the
assurance that there is no danger of Bolshevism in the new order which is springing upout of the ruins of the Empire  of Austria and Germany.    At the present moment Lenin belives that his hopes  with  regard to Austria andGermany are about to be realised.  For that reason he is ready to come to  almost any terms with the Allies in order to induce them to abandon intervention,  and to  leavehim a free hand  to support the revolution in Central Europe.   In this connection he isprepared to make important concessions, and to come to an agreement with the  Allies.It need hardly be said, however, that in the event of the success  of  his dreams  and  of trouble breaking out in any of the Allied  countries he would  be the  first to break hisword, and to throw  his whole weight into the scale against us.(c.) The Bolshevik  Army.    Partly, in order to maintain his position at  home,  but also  undoubtedly  with aneye to the future and with the intention of creating at least a greater Bolshevik Russia,Lenin has endeavoured to create an army.  This work was entrusted to Trotsky, a man of very different character to Lenin, but possessed of tremendous energy  and boundlessambition.  His  first efforts to  create  a.  volunteer army resulted in complete  failure.To-day, however, conscription has been restored, and several classes have been mobilised.(The soldiers are drawn exclusively from  the  working  classes, the  bourgeoisie beingdrafted into labour  battalions.)   Discipline has been established in the army  by the samemethods as in the towns, and the death  sentence  is  as  common  at the front  as  inPetrograd and Moscow.   In particular, the position of the officer in  the Red Army  ispainful in the extreme.   Mobilised  for  service  but  mistrusted (many  officers have entered the Red Army, some in  order  to gain their daily bread, others for  counter-revolutionary purposes), they are placed  at the  head of their  men find  shot  for theleast failure of their troops.  By a recent order of Trotsky&apos;s the wives and  children  ofofficers who desert to the Allies or the Czechs are thrown into prison.   Although the red army  in May   was an insignificant rabble,  to-day, thanks  to  a  certain enthusiasmcreated by its recent successes on the Volga front, it has  become a force which is not altogether  to be despised. This opinion is  supported by General Lavergne of theFrench Mission, and  by  the testimony of several, counter-revolutionary leaders  whohave been fighting against the Bolsheviks.  At the  end of September there were some two hundred thousand troops under arms, while  another three hundred thousand were receiving six hours&apos;  training per week.  On the  20th September the disposition of theregular troops was as follows :-                                                                    Men.         Screen on Her man front.       ..      ..      ..      ..      ..      15,000         Archangel and Northern front   ..      ..     ..      ..      ..       6,000         Ekateringburg front   ..      ..      ..     ..       ..      ..      12,000         Kazan to Samara front ..      ..      ..     ..       ..      &apos;..     105,000         Caucasus from Tsaritsin to Baku ..      ..     ..      ..      ..      75,000                       *                                           __                                 Total........     213,000    Of these troops some 23,000 are  Lettish.   These are excellent troops and consti-tute the backbone of the Bolshevik strength.  The  Commander-in-Chief  of theBolshevik armies is a Lettish Staff officer, as  is  also  the iiead of  the commission forcombating counter-revolution on the front.  There are also a certain number of troopsformed from enemy prisoners.   These  are mainly Hungarians.   They may be dividedinto two classes  : (1), those who are genuine Internationalists and (2). those who joined the Red Army to avoid going back to fight in the German  and Austrian Armies againstthe Allies.   From what I have seen of them they are certainly not acting on instruc-tions from the German or Austrian Governments.  There  are also a certain number of chinese coolies who have  been drafted into military service.  The stories about german officers and German troops in the Bolshevik  armies should  be received  with  caution.We shall never  understand  the Bolshevik movement or appreciate its danger if we continue to regard it merely as a toy of German  Imperialism..    The army is well provided with  some arms and ammunition.   There  is, however,a great shortage of artillery, especially  of heavy artillery.   As a  military force theRed Army is as yet unimportant.  But it is  increasing daily in  strength  aud  inefficiency, and, if, as  the  result of a  German withdrawal  from the Ukraine, or theabandonment of  intervention, it is allowed further triumphs in Russia it may become  aserious danger to the rest of Europe.
l!)H.1!)18.Bread (white), 1 lb.MilkSugarTeaMeatBread (black), 2 lb.FatsMealLodging&apos;LightPaperClothes, boots, washing     It is therefore in  their economic policy that the Bolsheviks are most vulnerable toattack.   The Bolsheviks realise this to the full, ainji on that account are most anxiousto conclude a commercial agreement with any foreign Power that might be willing  and able to  alleviate  their  financial and economic difficulties.   In this connection theyhave already  made many secret  overtures  to America.   To a  considerable extentthese difficulties are due to the fact that the richest parts of the former Russian Empireare in  the hands  of either Germany or  the  Allies [v. the  most interesting map inAppendix  I,  which  shows  the districts of  Russia  capable  of supporting  the local population).  It  is clear,  therefore,  that,   unless the  Bolsheviks can improve their position  by reconquering either the  Ukraine  or  Siberia,  they are  bound  sooner or later to go down before the anger of a starving population.  This is, in my opinion, thegreatest argument against our abandoning  our  intervention or  allowing the  fertiledistricts of the Ukraine to be handed over to the tender mercies of  the Bolsheviks.(e.) The Terror.    1 have thought it important to dwell at some length on this subject  because itsupplies our  best justification for  intervention.  The terror may be divided into two classes:  the  Red terror,  and the  Cold Terror.  The Bolsheviks have  been for  somemonths past  in the habit of summarily  executing  their active  opponents,  i.e., activecounter-revolutionaries.  Some of these sentences may be said to have been justified, as for example the shooting of the murderers of Uritsky, Mirbach, etc.  Executions  on  awholesale scale (i.e., systematic  murders  for which  the  Bolshevik Government can beheld responsible) first began after the murder  of Uritsky  and the attempt on Lenins       [996]                                                   ,          C(d.) Economic Situation.    While politically the power of the Bolsheviks seems undiminished, their  economic policy is likely to bring them  to  serious  disaster,  indeed, the economic  situation inRussia to-day is tragic  in the extreme.   In the Bolshevik budget the annual expen-ditnre exceeds the revenue by  hundreds of millions of  roubles.   Not only is there anappalling shortage of foodstuffs, but also  the almost complete dearth of manufactured articles has destroyed the exchange of goods for bread,  which is to-day in Russia the sole means of forcing the peasant to yield up his grain to the  starving towns.   Moneyhas almost lost all value, and in  Petrograd it  is practically  impossible to buy grainexcept by the primitive method of barter.  Where  money - still  has  a purchase value,prices are fantastic.  The following table, compiled by the Bolsheviks themselves, showsbetter than  any  words  the  appalling  state  to which Russia has  come under theBolshevik regime.    This table shows the maximum price  at  which a  working-man  can buy  the  barenecessaries of life.   It  should be borne in mind that this  is a table prepared by theBolsheviks for Bolsheviks, that the prices  here given are the &quot;fixed&quot; or &quot; normed &quot;prices  only obtainable by working men.  and that in spite of  this the increase in thecost of living since the war is still shown as thirty-seven  times.  For the bourgeois whohas not the advantages  of the workmen the cost is still greater.       Table showing  Average Minimum  Daily Budget  of Workmen, 1914-18.
Glife.   On that occasion some five hundred people were shot in Petrograd, some 120 in moscow, and a large number in tbe provinces, many of them innocent people, purely asa measure of revenge and in order to terrorise the opponents of Bolshevism.  In thisconnection, Major Ward well, of the American Red Cross, possesses an original documentof Chicherins which might be  published  throughout the civilised world.   In spite oftheir truculent answer to the Neutral Ministers, it appears certain that these executionswere not wholly approved of by the Bolshevik leaders, and in particular by Lenin himself.At any rate, soon after Lenin&apos;s recovery, this particular form of terror was  changed for another which is equally diabolical and  even more effective.   This terror  consists indepriving all opponents of Bolshevism  of  everything  they  possess, and  is indeed a systematic attempt to destroy every form of bourgeoisie in Russia.  In  Petrograd and moscow the bourgeoisie receives practically nothing to  eat.  (They are  placed  on thefourth and lowest category of food cards.)  Their houses and flats with the exception ofone or two rooms have been taken  away from them and  been given to the  workmen.Their money has long since been confiscated.  Now their very clothes, with  the excep-tion  of one suit, are to lie requisitioned.   Up to the present they have been enabled to live  by selling their art treasures, their furniture, and their jewellery.  Of this lastresource they have been now deprived by an official decree which is  only too likely tobe rigorously enforced.  At the present moment many bourgeois families are literallydying of starvation.   Indeed, their situation is  too deplorable for words, and what theirfate  will be  during  the coming winter defies  all  description.   The number of peoplearrested without the slightest reason must  be very large, and  the conditions of prisonlife under  the Bolsheviks regime are such that  they can only  fitly be compared  withthe horrors of India or China.  In this  connection I should like to point  out  that atthe present moment it is almost impossible for the  bourgeoisie to leave  Petrograd and moscow.  Even  if they succeed in obtaining a Bolshevik foreign passport, the swedish government  is now refusing visas  on the ground that  there is no food  in Sweden forthese unfortunates.   I venture to recommend that His Majesty&apos;s Government, in theinterests of humanity, and also friendship to a class who  did well by us at the beginningof the war, should immediately come to some arrangement with the Swedish Governmentwhereby this obstacle can  be overcome.                                   Conclusions.     In the above cursory and very incomplete review of Bolshevik activities, I have endeavoured to show that  the Bolsheviks are still the strongest political party in Russia,that in the Bolshevik idea there is a serious  danger to the rest of Europe, but that ifBolshevism can be confined to its present  limits it must fail,  sooner or later, owing tothe weakness of its economic policy.   Its strength is  difficult to gauge, as one cannothelp  feeling that the Bolsheviks are strong mainly  because of the weakness of all other parties in Russia.  At the same time most Russians,  and nearly all Allied experts on russia, seem to me to under-estitnate the strength  of the Bolshevik movement.  At thepresent moment, quite apart from Soviet Russia itself, the  Bolsheviks are  extremelypowerful in the Ukraine, which can hardly fail to turn Bolshevik  in the event of thewithdrawal of the German troops.  The position of Poland  and  Finland is also veryprecarious, while according to Bolshevik evidence both Italy and Roumania would seemto furnish  a fertile field  for  Bolshevik propaganda and Bolshevik ideas.   Finally, itshould be remembered that the Bolshevik  leaders are not working-men.   They are aband of intellectual?, some of them of great intelligence,  who have  been studyinginternational revolution for years, and who have a  dangerous knowledge of the best means of inspiring class-hatred.                      No. 2. The Counler-Bevolutionary Forces.      I arrived in Petrograd on January 29th in the  middle of the Brest negotiations. I wish to state that at this particular moment several of  the leading British representa- tives in Petrograd, including Mr. Bruce of His Majesty&apos;s Embassy, and General  Poole were in favour of recognising the Bolsheviks.  In a conversation, too, which I had with Sir George Buchanan on board a Norwegian  yacht oft&apos; Bergen,  the latter  was also inv favour of establishing relations with  the  Bolshevik  Government.   As the Bolsheviks were then by far the strongest  force  in  Russia, and as a  renewal  of  the  war with Germany seemed at any moment probable, my first efforts were directed mainly towards inducing the Bolsheviks  (1) to fight  Germany, and (2)  to accept Allied military  aid.
These efforts were continued after the  Brest  peace, and after my arrival  in Moscow,where  I worked in the closest  co-operation with General  Lavergne,  of the  french military Mission,&quot;General Romei of the Italian Military  Mission,  Captain Riggs of theAmerican Military Mission, and later with Mr. Poole, the American Consul.     When it was clear that owing  to conflicting ideals  no combination  was possiblebetween the  Allies and  the  Bolsheviks, and that the  Bolsheviks would not acceptAllied  intervention, I  began  to strengthen  my relations  with the various counter-revolutionary organisations in  Moscow.  Many of the leaders  of these organisationswere old personal friends.     Of the counter-revolutionary organisations at that moment the strongest were :      (1.) General Alexeiefsarmy, numbering then about 12,000 men.     (2.) The Right Centre--a  group of prominent  Russian statesmen, ranging from           ex-Ministers, such as Krivoschein, to the Right Wing of the Cadets.     (3.) The Left Centre a group of anti-Bolshevik  Liberals and (Socialists, ranging           from the Left Winsj of the Cadets to the Meusheviks.     (4.) Savinokofs League for the Regeneration and Freedom of Russia.     (f).) The Czech Council, which was not then openly anti-Bolshevik.     The  great  difficulty  with  all  these  organisations apart  from  their internalweakness&apos; was their inability and even unwillingness to co-operate with each other.     General Alexeief did not approve  of Savinokof, although finally he seems to havegiven a grudging approval to Savinokofs  work.  The politicians in the Bight Centrewere in constant dispute as to the respective values of a, pro-German  and a pro-Allyorientation.  During  the great German  offensive  in   March many  eminent Russiansmore or  less openly  advocated a  pro-German  policy, and most  wealthy Russianspreferred  the Germans to the Japanese.  Then, too, most  Russians at  that  time were of the opinion that the Bolsheviks could not last, and were not so willing  to  acceptoutside help as they are to-day.   Men like M.  Krivoschein, who carried with him mostof the  leading  Moscow  manufacturers, had  no illusions as to the further distress towhich   Allied intervention (the Allies at  that  time  not being in a position  tooffer serious military  help to Russia) would  expose  their country.   The mistrust ofthe Japanese was deeply rooted, and in May I received a deputation from the Moscowmanufacturers  to protest  against  any intervention  which would  be predominantlyJapanese,  and   whose only result  would  he  to  hand over Petrqgrad  and  moscow to  the Germans.   The   Right Centre,  too,  in   its  original composition,  refusedto have anything  to  do with  Socialists of  any kind.  M. Krivoschein,  for instance,blamed the French for supporting the Right  Social Revolutionaries, and stated that wewere treating (i).with a murderer (Saviukof), and  (2)  with a, thief (Chernof).  Finallythe  Right Centre dissolved over a question  of pro-Ally orientation, MM. Krivoschein,Gurko and other politicians refusing to bind  themselves  to an  anti-German  policy.What remained of the Right Centre,  including such men as  M. Fedorof, ex-assistantMinister  of Commerce under  Witte,; M.,  Stepanof,   also an  ex-assistant  Minister;Professor Struve, ex-assistant Minister of the Interior; M. Astrof, and  the MoscowCadets, now joined up with the Left Centre  and Savinkof s  League, and  entered intoregular relations with Alexeiefs army.  By the end of May this combination was  in fairworking order,  and seemed by far the most interesting and successful of all the counter-revolutionary movements.  It was essentially pro-Ally  in character.   The  Left  Centreincluded MM.  Kishkin,  Avksentief,  Filatof,  Potresof,  Orgunof, and  other  prominentmoderate Socialists.  Savinkof s organisation was mainly military.  His chief helper inthis connection  was  General  Boldyrief.   Savinkof also  had  a large  number  of hisadherents inside the Bolshevik organisations    The French  commenced to finance  and support these organisations before I  did.  In fact, the French led these.organisations to expect far more in the way of  military aid from the Allies than the latter  had been ableto give up to the present.   The recommendations sent home by the various Allied military representatives  in Russia  at  the beginning of the Czecho-Slovak  movement  were,I think,  at least  two  divisions for  Archangel,  and  a  large  Allied  force throughSiberia.  Although the American Ambassador did  not begin even to suggest  inter-vention until the middle of May, early  in  June M.  Noulens, the  French   Ambassador,read, through the  medium of the French  consul-general at Moscow, a note verbale tothe  various counter-revolutionary leaders at  Moscow, in  which it  was  stated thatAllied  intervention on a large  scale  would take place before the end of June. Bountifulpromises of both men and  money were  held  out to  the Russians.  There  is no  doubtthat the ill-fated adventure of the &quot; White  Guards &quot; at Yaroslavl was  directly  due tothis misleading information.
     The  plan of the Central Organisation  was to  hold the line  of the Volga and join up with the Allies in the North, and with General Alexeief in the South.  The latter was recommended to  proceed  via Tsaritsin to Samara, while  it  was hoped that  the Allies would he able to advance almost unopposed to Vologda and Viatka, thus cutting off Siberia completely  from the Bolsheviks.   I  am of the opinion that had  we been in a position, after the  Gzecho-Slovak outbreak, to  land  two  divisions  at  Archangel, together with an American-Japanese force  in Siberia, the Bolsheviks might  easily have collapsed.  In the chaotic state of Russia it was obvious (l) that the support we  would get from the Russians  themselves would  he in direct  proportion to the  number of troops we sent, and (2) that  if intervention was to be a success it  must  start well. The weakness of our operations in the  North has resulted in the  loss of the  Volga line, and the temporary collapse of the anti-Bolshevik movement in European Russia.   This has seriously harmed our prospects for intervention, and has had a depressing effect  on those elements in Russia who are most friendly to us     With reference  to the  actual strength of these various organisations the foliowioe details may be of interest:                              General Alexeief s Army.     During the winter months of 1918 General Alexeief, General Kaledin, and General Kornilof maintained a force consisting of (1) of ex-officers, and (2) of the Cossacks, of the Don, and of the Kuban district.  Neither  element was entirely  satisfactory, and quarrels between the generals themselves were  frequent.  The  Cossacks, too, were  not altogether free from Bolshevism.   After General  Kaledin&apos;s suicide the position became clearer.  General Krasnof became Ataman of the Don Cossacks, and, while maintaining friendly  relations  with  General  Alexeief,  adopted  a more or less pro-German, pro- Ukraine attitude.   He undoubtedly received arms and  munitions from the Germans. General Alexeief, ably  seconded by General Denikin, a man of great energy and ability, remained as head of the  Volunteer Army, and maintained  his position South  of the Don with the assistance of the Kuban Cossacks.  In June General Alexeiefs forces were not more than ten to twelve thousand men.  His position was  most desperate, and he was in dire straits for money.   Not only was lie surrounded by foes on three  fronts, but he was also in  serious danger  from the Germans.   In June  and July, however, as a result  of some  timely  victories over the  Bolsheviks, he  secured  a certain  amount  of guns and ammunition,  and  also a steady flow of new recruits.   Both  the French and we  ourselves  sent him  considerable financial  aid.   ft seems  clear also that  he also received certain  military  supplies through  General  Krasnof.   In  this  connection, M. Shulgin, at Kief, rendered valuable assistance, and  besides arranging for supplies he was also instrumental in sending  large batches  of officers to join  the Volunteer Army.  In August General Alexeiefs army  had swelled to 50,000  men.   Some  reports put his numbers as high  as a  hundred thousand, but  this figure should be accepted with caution.  Tt has been  a disappointment to many  that General Alexeief has been able to do so little.   His position, however, is  very  difficult.   Not only has he  three fronts to maintain, but  also many of his troops are.Cossacks  who will  not fight outside their own  territory.  Although he informed us  in July that he intended to  march against Tsaritsin with a view  to joining up with the  Czechs at Samara, he has clearly been unable to carry out his plans.     In July, when Miliukof went over to the Germans, the Allied representatives were very afraid that General  Alexeief would follow his example.  Both General Denikin and he, however, stood  fast by   their original  programme, and  were  bitter in  their condemnation of M. Miliukofs conduct.  Both General Alexeief and General Denikin are Monarchists, but the letters they have sent us are&apos;full of good  sense, and both generals realise the necessity of  proceeding with  caution.   Both generals favour  a military Dictatorship until order is restored in Russia and the country is in a fit state to choose a government for itself.  The discipline in the Volunteer Army is on the  old lines, and all the former salutes and titles of the old regime are retained.     General  Alexeief  is willing enough  to co-operate  with  almost  any  Russian Government which is against the Brest  peace  and the  Bolsheviks.  He is, however,bitterly anti-Kerensky, and one of his envoys  informed  us that the. Volunteer Army would  rather compromise with Lenin and Trotsky than deal with  Kerensky.                      Genertd Krasnof and the Don Cossacks.     General Krasnof should not be regarded as a pro-German.   Like most of the well-to-do class in Russia,  he is an opportunist, pro-German to-day, pro-Ally to-morrow..
 There  should  be no  difficulty whatsoever  in  winning  him  over  to our  side.   His supporters however, are not  strong, and he  has had rather the  worse of the recent fighting with the Bolsheviks.                                  The Bight Centre.     This organisation is now to all intents and purposes a Cadet organisation.  Its main aim was to create an All-Russian Government, around which the anti-Bolshevik forces might  rally.   It  has suffered much,  however,  from the defection  of such  men  as Krivoschein, Miliukof, &amp;e, and at Ufa  its programme was defeated by the  Left Centre. This programme favoured a military Dictatorship  under Alexeief, with a subservient Ministry, in which the main posts were to be divided among the Cadets and the Right Social Revolutionaries.  The Right Centre did  not even despair of bringing Miliukof back into the pro-Ally camp, and in their  programme had actually suggested him as Minister of the Interior.  The Right Centre is now breaking  up and  leaving Moscow. M. Pepilaef and M. Astrof left in July for Samara.   Professor Struve was to go to  the Allies  at  Archangel, while  MM.  Fedorof  and Stepanof  intended  to join General Alexeief.                                  The Left  Centre.     This organisation is mainly Socialist, and included  Right  Social Revolutionaries, Narodny Socialists, such as the ex-Minister Pieshekhonof, socialists of the Union group and Moderate  Mensheviks,  such   as  Potresof.    It   favours  the  calling  of  the Constituent Assembly, if only for  a few days, in  order to give a legal form to  the Directorate of five which it proposed as a counter-move to the Right  Centred military Directorship of Alexeief.     At the State Conference at Ufa the Left Centre triumphed completely.   Most of its leading members, with the exception of M. Kishkin, who is still  in prison, if  not shot, have now made their way to the other side  of the Volga.  The  Ufa Government is a direct result  of the  work of the two centres at Moscow  during the  spring and summer of 1918.                       t           Savinkofs League  for the Regeneration and Freedom of Russia.     This is a fighting organisation composed  mainly of officers.  It has provided most of the active opposition to the Bolsheviks, organised the operations at Yaroslavl and Kazan, has done much wrork in the way of blowing up  bridges, destroying Bolshevik military , trains, and supplies, and has been responsible for at least one assassination of Bolshevik Commissars.   Its strength is  difficult to gauge,  but cannot be placed  above 10,000 actives, although Savinkof himself claims to have many more names upon his list.  The organisation has suffered severely at the hands of the Bolsheviks, and a large percentage of the Bolshevik executions has fallen upon the  heads of the unfortunate members of this group.   The Leaders are Savinkof, Filonenko, and General  Boldyrief.     With regard to the Czecho-Slovaks, Dutofs Cossacks, the Samara Government, and the various  Siberian Governments, I need say little, as His Majesty&apos;s Government is probably in possession of more information on these  subjects than I know myself.  I can only repeat that the two great difficulties in connection with the anti-Bolshevik movement are (l), the  quarrels and bickerings  between  the various counter-revolutionary groups, and (2) the fact that the broad masses of the  people are, if not  against them, at  leastapathetic in supporting them.                            No. 3. Allied  Intervention.     With the defeat of Germany it  is clear  that  our intervention in Russia has nowentered upon a roost dangerous phase.     Our victories over Germany have removed our original pretext for intervention, andhave at the same time strengthened the position of the Bolsheviks (i.).by raising theirhopes for a revolution in Austria and  Germany; and  (ii.) by increasing their power inthe Ukraine, Poland and the other Russian districts at present  occupied by Germany.The Allies have now a choice of three plans:      ]. To abandon  our  intervention altogether, secure the  free and unhindered  exitof the Czecho-Slovak troops out of Russia, and come to a working arrangement with theBolsheviks.[996]D
      2.  To abandon our intervention  and secure the free  exit of the  Czecho-Slovak  troops,  should they so desire, but at the same time to support with arms and money the  anti-Bolshevik organisations in Russia such as the Ufa Government, General Alexeier&apos;s  forces, &amp;c, and at the same time to support in the same way a chain of national States  on Russia&apos;s western frontier,  such as  the Baltic  Provinces, Poland,  the  Ukraine and  Roumania,  with a view to creating- a strong economic barrier against the spread  of  Bolshevism.      3.  To intervene immediately on a proper scale, to strengthen our forces in Siberia and  in the north, and at the same time by  securing the elimination of Turkey from the war  to send an expeditionary  force through  the  Black  Sea to join General  Alexeief and  inarch immediately on Moscow in order to strike a blow at the very heart of Bolshevism.      Plan No. 1 has many objections, the  chief one perhaps being the fact that  it is the  combination which the Bolsheviks themselves most desire.   Its great advantage lies  in the fact that of all three plans this  is  the most easy of  attainment.   Advocates of  this combination  point out:   (1)  that  such a policy frees  us  from the charge of  suppressing an  anti-capitalistic revolution ;  (2) that  Bolshevism  cannot  be killed by  bayonets, but should be allowed to  die a natural death ; (3)  that we do not expose  ourselves to the risk  of labour and socialist troubles at home by sending  troops to  Russia  against the Bolsheviks alter the conclusion of an armistice or  peace, and finally  (4) that once  freed  from  the constant menace of outside  interference  the Bolshevik  regime  will become more moderate because, by not intervening, we shall be able to hold  threats of intervention over its head.   To most of these arguments serious objections  can be raised.   In the first place, before Bolshevism  dies a natural death it may spread  and cause the most appalling suffering in rich  and fertile districts of Europe, which will  thus be rendered sterile and incapable of supplying a, world population  already suffering  from the economic ravages of the war. Secondly, the Bolshevik regime, if given a free  hand, is more likely to lean towards extremism than  to moderation. If there is one lesson  to be learned from the Russian revolution, it seems to be the victory of the extreme Socialist  over the moderate Socialist.   This may not be true  in the long run, but in the present  state of Europe, and after the economic sufferings caused by the war, it seems to me to  hold good, at  any rate until the Socialistic experiment has been tried and  proved.      There  are, however,  still  more  serious  objections to  such a combination.  Our- withdrawal from Russia would be  regarded by the Bolsheviks as a sign of weakness, and  would  stimulate their revolutionary  energies and  activities  to an  alarming extent.  Further, although  the failure was  not entirely the fault of the Bolshevik Government  we have already made one attempt to  find a working (basis with the Bolsheviks.  Even  if a second attempt were more successful it could only be a temporary arrangement, and  would be broken by  the Bolsheviks as soon  as they felt themselves strong  enough.  Finally, if we have given pledges to the counter-revolutionary torces in Russia, we have  certainly led  them to expect help.  To  desert them now  at  the eleventh hour  would  gain us a very doubtful popularity with the Bolsheviks, and would  ruin our good name  with every other element in Russia.      Plan  No. 2 seems to  me  by far the weakest  of the three.   Without the  active&apos;  support of foreign troops  the  counter-revolutionary forces  in Russia are not strong  enough to  overcome the Bolsheviks.  &apos; By financing these organisations, and yet not  supporting them  actively, we  lay ourselves  open to the same charges as if we were  intervening in  force,  and  at  the same  time we are only prolonging civil war and  unnecessary bloodshed in Russia.   The results of our present  intervention would seem  to show the danger of half-measures against the Bolsheviks.  Finally,  nothing seems to  me more difficult of attainment than the  plan of erecting a ring of border-States  round  Bolshevism, unless these States are supported by  Allied forces.  Both Poland  and the  Ukraine, not  to mention the  Baltic  Provinces, will have  more than enough to do to  combat Bolshevism in their  own  territories.  All of  these States are far more likely  to  become Bolshevik themselves, than to be able  to  exert any  healthy influence  on  Bolshevism from outside.      Plan No. 3, in spite of its obvious difficulties, still seems to me the best solution  of  a very difficult problem.  Bolshevism, or rather the Bolshevik in Russia, can be destroyed,A  not, however, by gnawing at  the  outside of  Bolshevism, but by digging at  the core.  The objections to this plan are : (1) A  large number  of forces will have to be employed  not only to destroy the Bolshevik armies, but in  order  to restore  peace and  order in  Russia.  A successful intervention would probably  require  50;000 men  in the  South  via the Black  Sea, and at least the same number through  Siberia,   General Lavergne,  of the French Mission, puts the figure  even higher than this, and undoubtedly the more
 troops we send the more support we will get from the  Russians themselves.   (2) To maintain such  a force in Russia after  the  conclusion  of more than four years of war may be impossible, probably would be impossible without the  co-operation of America. (3) In the event of this plan being  more difficult of  attainment than would appear at present, our troops might have to  remain in Russia for a considerable period, and might themselves be exposed to Bolshevik propaganda.     The advantages of this plan, however, are far greater  than those offered by  any other policy.  Now that Turkey has concluded an armistice, we have the possibility of acting quickly and of beginning our operations before an  armistice is concluded with Germany.  Our victory over the Central Empires has probably increased our  prestige enormously amongst all anti-Bolshevik Russians, who now regard the Allies as  the only possible means of salvation.   By the time we are in a position to reach Moscow it may be  possible to  send a  relief expedition  to  Petrograd by sea.   With Petrograd  and Moscow in our  hands we should have no great difficulty  in  setting up  some form of Russian Government which will answer to the needs and wishes of the people.     Finally, in  connection   with  this  plan  I venture most  respectfully to make the following observations:     . 1.  That our intervention is justified on humanitarian grounds, and that we should do more by proceeding openly against the Bolsheviks than  by trying to  suppress them surreptitiously.     2.  That for the success of  such an intervention American co-operation is essential, and operations  should commence at once.  &quot;This is not possible in the north, but in  the south it is quite feasible.   If America would agree to send the bulk of the required troops it would  be possible to secure  the necessary complement  of French and British troops voluntarily.     3.  That whatsoever  Government  we  support should  make  immediately  some declaration which will  promise the land to the peasants not necessarily as a socialistic measure, but as an economic remedy which  is long overdue.   Without  a clear  pro- pronouncement on this subject we shall have the peasants against us.     4.  That however difficult it may seem, we should  proceed cautiously in supporting any one anti-Bolshevik  party as against another, and, in particular, we should beware of a renascence of  sentimentalism for the old regime, which is already manifest  in some sections of the English  press.     5.  No intervention in Russia can be really successful unless it is  accompanied by y large supplies of foodstuffs  and manufactured goods for the starving population, and no economic relief  can be given without a military occupation.     6.  A successful intervention will give the Allies a predominant economic position in Russia.  It will be more  than  paid for by economic concessions which will  in time repay us for some of the sums we have advanced to Piussia.     By restoring order  in Russia at  once not only are  we preventing  the spread of Bolshevism as a political danger, but we  are also saving for the rest of Europe  the richand fertile grain districts of the Ukraine, which in the  event of half-measures, or nomeasures at all  will be rendered sterile  by anarchy and revolution.   As  Europe willrequire after the war all the grain she can get the importance  of order in South Russiaand in Roumania is one of extreme importance.    Allied intervention is a guarantee of this order.  No other policy can  promise  thesame results, or the same security.                                                         R. H. B, LOCKHART.    November 1st, 1918.[996]E



</content>
</cab>
