<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/110/0 images: 66-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1962C. (62) 117 Copy No.   5 916th July, 1962CABINETFORECAST ESTIMATES, 1963-64Memorandum by the Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster general in his paper C. (62) 96, the Chancellor of the Exchequer gave some preliminaryfigures of the Forecast Estimates for 1963-64. It is now possible to give a betterconsidered estimate.2. We now put the Estimates for 1963-64 at  6,080 million, an increase of 470 million over the Budget Estimate for 1962-63.3.   The build-up is as follows:Forecast Estimates as submitted (see Annex)Increases in rates of payEffect of 1963 revaluation for ratingPublic Service pensions increaseIncreased National Assistance ...Sundry additions.........Contingencies     ...      ......  million+ 283802010*22550+ 470* Also a further  10 million expenditure not on Votes.4. My colleagues will note in the right-hand column of the Annex the verylarge figures for defence, external relations and education (both direct and via the general and rate deficiency grants).5. The pay (direct and indirect, via grant) has been included at 4 per cent,increase. In terms of total public expenditure (i.e., including local authorities),1 per cent, increase in public service remuneration is about  30 million.6. As regards contingencies, the largest is of course the possibility of national insurance benefits, with consequential repercussions on war pensions, etc. Evena 5s. increase in the retirement pension would mean additional public expenditureof over  100 million, and Exchequer expenditure of about  20 million.7. Last February, when we had been cutting hard, and had a pay pause,the Estimates turned out at about  162 million above the Forecast Estimates. the calculation above indicates  187 million above the Forecast Estimates; our expenditure calculations at this time of the year are usually pretty reliable.
8.  This adds up to the following comparisons:1960-61 (expenditure)1961-62 (expenditure)1962-63 (Budget Estimate) ...1963-64 (Forecast Estimate) saymillion4,9865,3685,6126,080Per cent, riseover previousyear7-87-78-4(comparingestimate withestimate)(comparingestimate withestimate)9. In other words, a faster rate of increase of expenditure than ever. this of course excludes the very large expansion of local authorities&apos; investment expenditure which is under discussion with the Ministers concerned; and it excludesthe very substantial increases of public expenditure (in addition to the charge on Votes) arising from increase in national insurance benefits.H. B.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,13th July, 1962.AnnexBudget Estimates Forecast EstimatesIncrease in Increase in	1961-62	1962-63	1962-63		1963-64	1963-64	  million	  million	  million		  million	  millioiDefence............	1,669	1,768	4	99	1,878	+ 110External relations      ......	170	185	4	15	220	4- 35Roads...........	135	151	%	16	167	4- 16British Transport Commission subsidy       ......	103	146	. ...H-	43	132	- 14Agricultural support......	273	339	4	66	325	- 14General and rate deficiency grant	633	715	4	82	755	4 40Education  (Departments  and University Grants Committee)	127	137	4	10	183	4 46National Health Service	633	661	4	28	684	4 23Other    ......      ......	1,485	1,510	. 4	25	1,551	4 41Total    ...      ......	5,228*	5,612	4384		5,895	4283* On comparable definition.July 1962.

</content>
</cab>
