<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/110/0 images: 68-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1962C. (62) 118 Copy No.      6 513th July, 1962CABINETLEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME, 1962-63Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Bills suggested by Ministers for inclusion in the legislative programme for 1962-63 have been considered by the Future Legislation Committee. The listannexed is a provisional classification which takes into account the Committee&apos;view that in preparing for what may be the last Session of the present Parliamentwe should have in mind the need: (a) to accommodate some major measures whichmust be counted as of special importance at this stage; and (b) to reserve to ourselvessome room for manoeuvre. From this point of view it is helpful that in termsof clauses and schedules the legislation required if we join the european communities is not likely to be so formidable as was at one time feared. On thebest estimate that can be made at present, the Bill would consist of a clause givingthe force of law to the Treaties, the text of which would be set out in a schedule of considerable length, and perhaps 70 additional clauses and three or four additionalSchedules. On the other hand, it will no doubt be necessary to take the committee stage on the floor of the House of Commons, so that this estimate still involves a substantial mortgage on the total time available. Indeed in some circumstances it might put at risk a large part of the programme.2.   The categories adopted in the list are:A.1 Essential. (I have included in this list a Pensions (Increase) Bill because we are now fully committed to an increase in Public Service pensions.)A.2 Contingent. (I have included here a National Insurance (Pensions)Bill; we have not yet taken a firm decision on National insurance pensions.)B.1 Main programme. (This includes the two measures Shops and offices and Weights and Measures which will be called for in connexion withthe new presentation of Incomes Policy.)B.2 Highly desirable. (These Bills have been set out in order of preference.The Criminal Justice (Scotland) Bill will include provisions on legal aid in criminal cases which have a special claim to inclusion in theprogramme.)C. Bills in reserve.D.-Other Bills.P. Bills suitable for a Private Member.3. On the best estimate that can be made at present the Essential,Contingent, Main Programme and &quot; Highly desirable&quot; lists would (makingallowances for some of the Contingent Bills not in the end being required) provideus with a full programme for the Session, and leave little or no room for manoeuvre.It follows that it may be impracticable to proceed with one or two of the &quot; Highly
desirable &quot; Bills. At present the only hope for the Bills in Lists C and D is thatone or two of them might on closer consideration be found suitable for handingto a Private Member successful in the ballot. I ask my colleagues to examine thatpossibility.4.  A feature of this suggested programme and one which could wellembarrass the programme is the number of major Bills which would have some. claim to have their Committee Stage on the floor of the House.- V 5. The programme will be further considered when the terms of The Queen&apos;sSpeech on the Opening of Parliament are being settled in the autumn. Meanwhile,I seek the approval of the Cabinet for the provisional programme I have described.I. M.Office of the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, S.W. 1,13th July, 1962.
AnnexPROVISIONAL CLASSIFICATION OF BILLS FOR 1962-63A.1 Bills EssentialFinanceExpiring Laws ContinuanceLocal Government (Finance) (Scotland)Agriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions)Pensions (Increase)Coal Industry (N.C.B. DeficitsBritish MuseumTowyn Trewan CommonA.2 Bills ContingentEuropean Communities (Membership)National Insurance (Pensions)Public Works LoansAir Corporations*Electricity (Borrowing) (Scotland)*Teachers (Remuneration)Egypt Supplementary CompensationColonial Development and Welfare (Amendment)British Guiana IndependenceZanzibar IndependenceKenya Independence and Kenya ProtectorateSingapore, Sarawak and North BorneoRhodesia and Nyasaland (Constitution Amendment)Ceylon (Consequential Provision)Tanganyika (Consequential Provision)Nigeria (Consequential Provision)B.1 Bills Main ProgrammeLondon Government .Safety, Health and Welfare in Shops, Offices and Railway PremisesEducation (Scotland)Weights and MeasuresB.2 Bills Highly Desirable Bills, from which two or three Additional ProgrammeBills might be SelectedTelevisionWater ConservationCriminal Justice (Scotland)Children and Young Persons and Employment of ChildrenAirports AuthorityC Bills Bills in ReservePublic LibrariesSeeds and Plant Breeders&apos; Rights (or possibly in List P)Administration of JusticeCompanies (Deposits)FinesWar DamageUnderground ParkingShipping and Oversea Trade (Counter-Measures)Radiological Health ServicesMagistrates&apos; Courts (Miscellaneous Provisions)Continental Shelf and Geneva Convention on the High SeasNuclear Installations (Amendment)Diplomatic Relations (Vienna Convention)* These three Bills might be combined in a single Bill.SECRET
D Bills OthersNaval EnlistmentWater Supply (Dental Health)Highways (Land)Overseas EducationCable and Wireless LimitedCountryside (Scotland)Land Powers (Defence)Teachers (Superannuation)Registration (Births, Deaths and Marriages)Affiliation Orders (Facilities for Enforcement)Electricity Supply (Amendment)Merchant Shipping (Conditions of Service and Discipline)Commons RegistrationLondon MuseumTaxes ManagementGas (Amendment)Permanent Aluminium BungalowsCommonwealth Scholarships (Amendment)Reserve ForcesPortsPoliceProbationTrustee Savings Banks ChequesMiscellaneous Administrative ReformsFactories and Rural AreasSevern Bridge TollsDistribution of German Enemy PropertyOffice Buildings (Amendment of Third Schedule to Planning Act, 1947)Employment AgenciesInternational Military HeadquartersMerchant Shipping (Safety Convention)Consular ConventionOil in Navigable Waters tDangerous DrugsP Bills Suitable for a Private MemberEmployment of Women after ChildbirthNursing and Residential HomesCriminal ProcedureLocal Authorities (Financial Powers)Local Authorities (Land)Metropolitan Police Act, 1839 (Amendment)Import of Rare AnimalsSheriff Courts (Limits of Jurisdiction) (Scotland)Dramatic and Musical Performers (Amendment)HovercraftStock and Share TransfersBuilding SocietiesCorn RentsForestry (Sale of Land) (Scotland)Divorce (Property Rights) (Scotland)Oaths and EvidenceWillsOld Metal DealersSiting of CrematoriaJuly 1962

</content>
</cab>
