<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/110/0 images: 95-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HSREl BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT)(62) 122COPY NO.21st Jul-19.62CABINETSALE OF CHXilSTCHURCH AIRCRAFT FACTORYMemorandum by the ^^Q^^J3^LSl^&amp;-S2^^;^ l^ ^i^We are in a dilemma over the sale by the Ministry of Aviationof an aircraft factory at Christchurch, vacated by the De HavillandAircraft Company, to the British Oxygen Company Limited.     TheDistribution of Industry Committee considered the problem on17th July and were unable to reach agreement.     This memorandumreflects the views which were expressed.2.      The Board of Trade have been negotiating with the BritishOxygen Company     persuade them to move their light engineeringproduction from Bs*ls*&amp;&quot;to Dumbarton, Scotland.    An industrialdevelopment certificate for expansion in the South of England hadbeen refused and we had offered to build and lease to them a factorycosting some  2 million and had also offered a Board of TradeAdvisory Committee grant of  300, 000 under the Local EmploymentAct, I960.     We had thought that these negotiations had been successful     and the plans for the factory had received wide publicity in Dumbarton, where the project would have made a majorcontribution towards relieving unemployment, which stands at, 7 per cent.    At the same time, however, the Company had beennegotiating the purchase of the vacant Ministry of Aviation factory at Christchurch.     They did not tell the Board of Trade of this until they had reached agreement with the Ministry of Aviation to buy the factor &quot;subject to contract&quot;.     We may need to make some change in our procedures in order to prevent this sort of thing fromhappening again, but the main issue is a different one.3.      I have discussed the position with the Chairman of theCompany.    He has now told me in writing (since the Distributionof Industry Committee met) that his Board have decided that theCompany will in no circumstances go to Dumbarton, about whichthey had apparently been ve ry doubtful even before the opportunityof the Christchurch factory had appeared;  neither are theyprepared to consider taking possession of the Admiralty enginerepair shop at Donibristle which we are converting for industrialuse.     They now say that if they are refused the Christchurch factorythey will continue in their existing premises and wait for an emptyfactory to come on to the market somewhere else (this could wellhappen before long at Portsmouth where De Havilland&apos;s are intend-ing to sell another aircraft factory which they own themselves).secret
4.      The question is whether we should allow the sale of theChristchurch factory to the British Oxygen Company to be completed.The Secretary of State for Scotland, supported by a majority of theDistribution of Industry Committee, takes the view that it would be disastrous to do so because of the political difficulties which arealready arising from the worsening employment situation inScotland.     This has been aggravated by present and future collieryclosures and by redundancies from the closure of the NorthBritish Locomotive Company Limited and the contraction of rolls Royce Limited.    Dumbarton itself has already been twicedisappointed by the failure of projects to bring new industry to thearea and the loss of the British Oxygen project ect is bound to be aserious blow to the area which will be deeply resented.     TheGhairman&apos;s letter expressing his Board&apos;s decision means that theblow will fall in any case.     But we should at least make the best of our position to face the resulting criticism if we could say notonly that we had made a generous offer of assistance to theCompany to move to Dumbarton, but also that we had refused tosell them the Christchurch factory.     To allow the sale to go through,on the other hand, might lead to the allegation that we had ourselvessabotaged our own attempt to bring alternative employment to scotland;    and, in reply,   the point that the Company1 s earliertentative thoughts  of moving to Dumbarton would have been abandoned anyway might avail us little.     This could causedifficulties for us, particularly at a time when we are trying to putover programmes of contraction in coalmining and the railways,for which the co-operation of the unions is of the first importance.5.      There are, however, serious objections to interfering withthe sale.     In the first place it would mean reversing a decision taken by the Distribution of Industry Committee in October, 1961,that our general policy should be to dispose of surplus government property at the highest price it would fetch on the open market andthat it would be indefensible to sell it for less than this for the sake of distribution of industry policies.     The main considerations under-lying this decision were that Departments in fact have no power tosell surplus property outside development districts at less than fullmarket value in order to further other departments  policies;and, furthermore, that there is no practical means of restricting the use of a factory when it is sold or of preventing a purchaserfrom re-selling it at its full industrial value.    Secondly, on whatgrounds could we refuse to sell to the British Oxygen Company and yet be prepared to sell at a lower price (the next offer - from an investment company - was  200, 000 lower) to some other firm?This could look like penalising a firm which at least contemplatedmoving to a development district, and favouring another that didnot even contemplate such a move.    If we do not sell to the BritishOxygen Company it would be difficult to sell to anyone else for a comparable industrial use.    Once we start upon a course of thiskind, we should give encouragement to those who argue that theGovernment should adopt a policy of sterilising industrial propertyoutside the development districts.
6.      Even  if such a policy were considered right, to apply it onlyto Government property would be ineffective, since the main weaknein the distribution of industry policy would still remain, namely thatthe Government have no power to prevent existing privately-ownedindustrial premises from being sold for industrial use even incongested areas.     To remedy this deficiency would require legisla-tion and effective control could prove extremely costly, since therewould have to be provision for compensation to property owners.The only benefit that it would be realistic to expect from a restriction applying to Government property alone would be theremoval of an appearance of inconsistency in our actions, judged from the particular point of view of our distribution of industrypolicy.7.      Moreover, it would not be easy to find publicly convincinggrounds for a change of mind over the Christchurch factory.There is no doubt that this factory would have great economic advantages for the Company; not only would it be much cheaper,but it would enable them to reach full production some two years earlier than if they had to move to a new factory in Scotland.    Andwe could not maintain that the price they had offered was inadequateor tha.t employment in Christchurch was already over-full:   the extra employment would be v/elcomed locally and a cancellationnow would certainly lead to protest.    Neither could we make a veryconvincing case on general distribution of industry grounds, sincethe Company are now resolved not to go to Scotland in any case and we have no power to stop them buying a privately-ownedfactory elsewhere.8.      To sum up, the alternatives are:-(a) To permit the sale to go through and accept the resulting embarrassment.(b) To refuse to sell to the British Oxygen company and face the charge of discrimination against that Company.(c) To make a change in our previously agreed policy for the disposal of Government-ownedfactories, which would entail substantiallosses to the Exchequer with only doubtfulpractical benefits to our distribution ofindustry policy,I should be grateful for my colleagues&apos; advice.F. J.E.Board of Trade, S. W. 1.ZOth July, 1962.

</content>
</cab>
