<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/110/0 images: 109-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1962C. (62) 128 Copy No.27th July, 1962CABINETTEACHER supply memorandum by the Minister of education on 13 th July the Committee on Education Policy considered a proposal by my predecessor for a crash programme to add a further 10,000 places to the training colleges.  They agreed to recommend to the Cabinet that:&quot; The Minister of Education would in the first place endeavour to obtain agreement with educational interests on reduction of the training period forinfant teachers from three to two years possibly with the promise of a thirdyear later but that he should have discretion to propose the provision of10,000 additional and mainly non-residential places in training colleges if this proved to be necessary to secure agreement.&quot;2. Teacher supply is so urgent and crucial an issue, both educationally and politically, that I have made it my first concern to examine it.3. There can be no doubt that the schools face a really serious problem, andthat action to deal with it is imperative. The core of Conservative education policy has been to reduce the size of classes. There is every prospect that, on present plans, the primary schools will have 2 million children in oversize classes in 1970 twice as many as at present and equal to the number in the worst days just after we took office at the end of 1.951. This prospect is bound to be contrasted very sharplywith the expectation which we held out at the time of the last General Election,namely that we hoped to be able to get rid of all oversize classes by the end of themiddle-1960s.4. Moreover, I foresee that unless we can expand opportunities, severalthousand qualified girls will be turned away from the training colleges in each ofthe next few years. We shall soon be under very heavy pressure to find room forthem.5. At the same time, I share my colleagues&apos; concern that &quot; wastage &quot; hasbeen taking away almost as many women teachers as we can train and that weseem to have gained so small a return from the very heavy expenditure we havealready incurred on expanding the training colleges.6. I therefore accept the essence of the Education Policy Committee&apos;conclusion, namely that, if we add more training college places, we must alsoincrease the &quot; throughput&quot; of the plant. But I think that I could make moreprogress in this direction if I could broaden a little the Committee&apos;s precise formula.7. This formula ties me to one specific solution cutting the training course for infant teachers to two years, possibly with the promise of a third year later. Ihave found on examination that the idea of a deferred third year, while at first sight attractive, is open to very serious objections. It would have either to be imposed as an obligation on all new two-year trained teachers, or offered as aright to any who wished to exercise it.
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1962C. (62) 12827th July, 1962Copy No.57CABINETTEACHER supply memorandum by the Minister of education on 13 th July the Committee on Education Policy considered a proposal by my predecessor for a crash programme to add a further 10.000 places to the training colleges.  They agreed to recommend to the Cabinet that:&quot; The Minister of Education would in the first place endeavour to obtain agreement with educational interests on reduction of the training period forinfant teachers from three to two years possibly with the promise of a thirdyear later but that he should have discretion to propose the provision of10,000 additional and mainly non-residential places in training colleges if this proved to be necessary to secure agreement.&quot;2. Teacher supply is so urgent and crucial an issue, both educationally and politically, that I have made it my first concern to examine it.3. There can be no doubt that the schools face a really serious problem, andthat action to deal with it is imperative. The core of Conservative education policy has been to reduce the size of classes. There is every prospect that, on present plans, the primary schools will have 2 million children in oversize classes in 1970-twice as many as at present and equal to the number in the worst days just after we took office at the end of 1951. This prospect is bound to be contrasted very sharplywith the expectation which we held out at the time of the last General Election,namely that we hoped to be able to get rid of all oversize classes by the end of themiddle-1960s.4. Moreover, I foresee that unless we can expand opportunities, severalthousand qualified girls will be turned away from the training colleges in each ofthe next few years. We shall soon be under very heavy pressure to find room forthem.5. At the same time, I share my colleagues&apos; concern that &quot; wastage &quot; hasbeen taking away almost as many women teachers as we can train and that weseem to have gained so small a return from the very heavy expenditure we havealready incurred on expanding the training colleges.6. I therefore accept the essence of the Education Policy Committee&apos;conclusion, namely that, if we add more training college places, we must alsoincrease the &quot; throughput &quot; of the plant. But I think that I could make moreprogress in this direction if I could broaden a little the Committee&apos;s precise formula.7. This formula ties me to one specific solution cutting the training course for infant teachers to two years, possibly with the promise of a third year later. Ihave found on examination that the idea of a deferred third year, while at first sight attractive, is open to very serious objections. It would have either to be imposed as an obligation on all new two-year trained teachers, or offered as aright to any who wished to exercise it.
8. If we were to opt for an obligatory scheme I should have, by regulation, to limit their appointment, as qualified teachers, to one particular type of school andfor a restricted period until they had taken a third year&apos;s training. I am certain&apos;that only a small minority would, in the event, be ready to break with a job, ahome and possibly a family, to return, even on full salary, to college for a whole year. Those who declined the obligation would have to leave service, even though they were ready to go on teaching and could be ill-spared, or alternatively acceptdemotion to unqualified status (as temporary teachers on a lower salary), despite-the fact that they would be more experienced teachers than when first appointed.iCfia these terms an obligatory scheme would, in my view, be publicly unenforceable.9. If on the other hand the return to training were optional, even fewer couldbe expected to take a third year and the scheme would quickly be seen to be athinly disguised return to two-year training. This was certainly the reaction when sir David Eccles floated a proposal broadly along these lines (&quot; short servicecommissions &quot;).10. I must therefore warn my colleagues that, of all the possible means ofincreasing the output of the colleges, an attempt to revert in this way to a two-yearcourse for infant teachers would meet with the strongest opposition not only fromthe teachers, who would regard this as an attack upon the unity and status of the profession, but also from the training colleges, and from the educational worldgenerally.11. The introduction of the three-year course was a Conservative reform andwidely regarded as evidence of our concern for educational advance. It will do usgreat harm in the country to go back on it.12. I have therefore considered closely other ways of getting more teachersthrough the colleges.  I believe the two best possibilities are:(i) the double use of accommodation, by alternating study and a higher proportion of teaching practice, i.e., the &quot;sandwich&quot; principle;(ii) the concentration of the course into a shorter calendar period by more&quot; intensive &quot; use of a college&apos;s facilities, i.e., longer terms or more terms in a year.Either of these would be easier to defend than the reversion to a two-year course that the Education Policy Committee had in mind, and would have the positive advantage of removing any obligation to use college places for a deferred third year.13. I have also been pursuing the proposed use in the schools of some formof sub-professional grade (&quot; auxiliaries &quot;) who would enable more efficient use tobe made of highly qualified teachers. It is clear that this proposal will need themost careful &quot; selling &quot;, but I intend none the less to push it.14. I should therefore like to be free to go for any one or any combination of these measures that promises success and I am prepared to push them hard.15. At the same time I am clear that these unconventional measures do not offer an alternative to the further expansion of the training colleges. 10,000additional places by themselves will not solve the teacher shortage, though theymay halve the gap between demand and supply by 1975. Equally, given the very heavy degree of overcrowding of the colleges we are already contemplating, wecannot expect these measures to go more than part way towards closing the restof the gap. I must therefore ask my colleagues to accept that a minimum supplypolicy requires expansion as well as these other measures: I cannot hope to securethe second without the first.16. I should propose to provide these 10,000 places on an &quot; economy &quot; basis and present it as a &quot; crash &quot; programme very largely in terms of day and lodgingplaces, with economies in the amount of teaching accommodation and such useof standardised planning and construction as may prove practicable. By thesemeans it should be possible to contain investment costs of building within about 8-  10 million (half the normal cost), spread over the period of 1963-67 (the great bulk falling in 1964-65 and 1965-66), with about  6 million running costs includingstudents&apos; maintenance when the programme is completed. It would be my intentionto make clear that we shall expect the educational world to accept emergency measures on the lines I have indicated in this paper as a quid pro quo for this expansion.
Ministry of Education, W. I.26th July, 1926.17. To sum up, I ask my colleagues to agree that I should authorise theexpansion of the training colleges by 10,000 places on the clear understanding:(i) that this should be regarded as an emergency programme an integral partof which would be:(a) a significantly greater output from the colleges than would result if all students were to take the conventional type of three-yearcourse;(b) the adoption of the economy measures described in paragraph 16;(c) the maximum tolerable degree of overcrowding in the colleges;(ii) that I should push further the proposal for the use of auxiliaries as suggested in paragraph 13.E. C. G. B.

</content>
</cab>
