<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/36/7 images: 112-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MflJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1943.5SSECRET. Copy No.    5W.M. (43)139th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 139 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at, 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, 12th October, 1943 at 6-15 P.M.Present:The Rt. Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador to theUnited States of America.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,President of the Board of Education.Captain the Right Hon. H. F. C.Crookshank, M.P., Postmaster-General.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell, Pay-master-General.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Major   the  Right   Hon.   G.   LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Fuel and -Power.The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of State.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury.The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.Contents.Minute T,No.                                       Subject. Pag?1      Coal        ................................ 862      Wage Earners&apos; Income Tax Bill................. 86[26253-2] B
1. The War Cabinet were informed of the course of the debate that day in the House of Commons on the coal situation.The Prim,e Minister said that he would intervene in the debate on the following day. Discussion ensued on the points raised in debate, and as to the line which the Prime Minister should take.It was agreed that this should consist, broadly, of a reaffirmationand re-emphasis of the line of policy set out in W.P. (43) 451 and approved by the War Cabinet on the previous day, against the background of the position of a Coalition Government, pledged tocarry out whatever measures might be necessary for the effectiveprosecution of the war.The War Cabinet was, however, informed that there was someapprehension that the present system of control over the operationof the mines might be brought to an end suddenly at the end of thewar (as had happened after the last war), notwithstanding theundertaking given in paragraph 13 of Cmd. 6364 that &quot;theorganisation now to be established will continue pending a finaldecision by Parliament on the future of the Industry.&quot;The War Cabinet agreed that this undertaking should be amended by an addition to the effect that the present system ofcontrol would, in any event, be continued for at least a year afterthe end of the war; and the Prime Minister should include this inhis speech.Coal.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 138thConclusions,Minute 5.)Wage-Earners&apos; 2.   The  Chancellor  of the  Exchequer  informed  the  WarIncome Tax Cabinet that, in his statement on the Second Reading of the Bill onBiJ1- Thursday, the 14th October, he proposed to indicate that he wouldgive sympathetic consideration to the possibility of includingwithin the scope of the Wage Earners&apos; Income Tax Bill salariedworkers in the lower income groups.He thought it right to report this to the War Cabinet as being a modification of the proposal previously approved.The War Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of this statement.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,13th October, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
