<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/16 images: 198-200</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1973CM (71) Copy No.   0 316th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Monday, 22 March, 1971,at 11.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,mp, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mp, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon, q c,mp, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the following were also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-general secretariat:Sir Burke trend . N. F. cairncross mr. P. J. Hudson
SubjectNorthern Ireland
northern ireland previous reference:CM (71) 15thConclusions,Minute 4The Cabinet resumed their discussion on Northern Ireland; theconclusions reached were separately recorded and circulated only toThe Queen, the Prime Minister and those Ministers who had totake action.The conclusions are recorded separately in the standard file heldby the Secretary of the Cabinet.

</content>
</cab>
