<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/97/6 images: 72-80</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL



THIS DOCUMENT IS IHE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



COPY NO



CABINET



CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet

held at 10 Dawning Street an



THURSDAY 12 JULY 1990



at 11.15 am



PRESENT



The Rt Han Margaret Thatcher MP

Prime Minister



_?e Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey How^^\MP

lord President of the Ctourxi^^-.



Ihe Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP ^!



Secretary of State for Foreign a$a///y

Commonwealth Affairs



The Rt Hon David Waddingtan QC MP

Secretary of State for the Heme

Department



The Rt Hon Kenneth Clarke QC MP

stary of State for Health



The Rt Hen The Lord Mackay of Clashfern

Lord Chancellor



The Rt Hon John Major MP

Chancellor of the Exchequer



The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker MP

Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster



Rt Hon Cecil Parkinson MP

Secretary of State for Transport



The Rt Hon The Lord Bel stead

Lord Privy Seal



Ihe Rt Hon Christopher Patten MP

Secretary of State for the Environment



Ihe Rt Hon John Gummer MP

Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries

and Food



Rt Hon John MaoGregor MP



of State for Education

ence



The John Wakeham MP



Seca? ^r^9  State for Energy



The Rt

Secret



Antony Newton MP

&apos;of State for Social Security



The Rt Han Pe?

Secretary of



The Rt Han. No:

Chief Secretary,



ike MP



or Northern Ireland



Ihe Rt Hon David Hunt MP

Secretary of State for Wales



CONFIDENTIAL


CONFIDENTIAL



AISO PRESENT



The Rt Hon Timothy Renton MP

Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury



SECRETARIAT



Sir Robin Butler

Mr L V Appleyard    (Items 3 and 4)



Mr D A Hadley

Mr A   Russell

Mrs J   Bailey



C           S



(Items 3 and 4)

(Items 1 and 2)

(Items 1 and 2)



era



Subject



PARLIAMENTARY



Carmuni



Statements



Registration



HCME AFFAIRS



The Maguires



FOREIGN AFFAIRS



North Atlantic



5-6 July



Houston



Soviet Union



in London



Kenya



OCMMUNITY AFFAIRS



a



Factortame (fishing vessels) case

Secretary of State for Trade and Industry



ii



CONFIDENTIAL


CONFIDENTIAL



Communx

Care



1.     The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in

the House of Cannons and the House of Lords in the following

week.



THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR HEALTH said that he had planned to

make an oral statement to the House of Camera on the phasing of

f/C^is canmunity care proposals immediately following the

//iWironment Secretary&apos;s statement on the local authority grant

^^tbtlement for 1991/92 on Thursday 19 July.   The Opposition had

&lt;/ ^S^ecided, hewever, to use the Opposition half day on 18 July

te community care, and he would therefore prefer to make

.tement either in that debate or immediately before it.

Thd\ lternative was a separate statement on 16 or 17 July, but

he was reluctant to agree to give the Opposition the opportunity

to discuss the matter on two separate days.



In discus(^iorO it was noted that, as the Opposition had

intentiona^^s^Lected this subject for debate to try to wrong

foot the Govrerppent, there was a strong case for announcing the

Government&apos;s p^ ?ssals either in the debate or by a separate



statement on

such an approa!

in the last days

possibilities for

possibility would

but this would make it

Government&apos;s business,

finish, none of which

it would be unfortunate to

until the spillover.   The p:

therefore be maintained and

negotiate with the Opposition

making the announcement on

Supply Debate.



day.   It might be possible to negotiate

the visual channels.   It was important

Summer Recess to minimise the

ition to disrupt the business. One

the Supply Day debate to Thursday,

sary to defer sane of the



were three Government Bills to

ject of a timetable motion, and

defer any of this business

arrangement of business should

iness Managers would seek to

le arrangement for

on the day of the



Statements

before the

Summer Recess



THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said

Ministers had indicated a wish to make an

the House rose for the Sunmer Recess. It

accommodate additional requests.   It would be

colleagues could wherever possible make

alternative ways, and give him notice as soon

further possible requests for statements over the

weeks.



of



.tement before

difficult to

if

in



le of any



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



.tion



Previoqs^vx

ReferenqKAV&gt;

CO (90) 17%%



    SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that the

Government had sustained a heavy defeat in the House of lords on

Thursday 5 July on an amendment to introduce a dog registration

scheme.   A substantial number of Conservative peers had voted

against the Government.   The amendment would place the

responsibility for dog registration on local authorities: the

clear intention of its promoters was that local authorities



required to operate such schemes but the terms of the

appeared to leave them with discretion whether or not

There appeared to be three options: to seek to

the defeat at Report Stage in the Lords, to aim for

L in the Commons, or to accept the amendment as drafted

improve it by providing more clearly for a discretionary

authority scheme.   The Government had secured only a small

majority against a registration scheme when the matter was last

considered in the Caimons.   The third option reflected what had,

at an earl^erx stage, been considered as a possible fallback as

an alternativ -to a national scheme.   He proposed that he should

explore witn^Slleagues how this approach might be developed in

more detail ^und^h particular how to ensure that the costs were



&apos; any irrpact on carmunity charges.   It would

irt too far frcm the Government&apos;s present

sing was unnecessary and unworkable, not

&quot;undermine the position of the



of whom had had to resist very

ituents on the matter.   But it might

which would avoid this risk while

kiently far to satisfy at least the

&quot; jon lobby.



ring-fenced

be undesirable

position that

least because this

Government&apos;s suppor

strong pressure f romx

be possible to devise

at the same time going

major part of the dog



In discussion the following



xirrts were made:-



a.    The arguments

as ever, and there was no

seeking straight reversal of&lt;

particularly inappropriate to



registration were as strong

^r anything other than



amendment.   It would be

Llow the !reposition of a



further task on local authorities at a time when the

Government&apos;s general approach was to avoid this.



b.    There was a risk that, faced w:

the amendment, the House of lords mi!

more unwelcome, such as a mandatory na

scheme.   This could lead to a dispute be

which might hold up the enactment of the

Protection Bill.   However, the lords might

incur the odium of delaying a popular and



c.    The recent consultation paper an the

contained much more practical proposals, desic

the real problems of dangerous dogs, and it was

that the Government should continue over the coming

to deploy its argument that an approach an these lines



ight reversal of

ite something

&gt;registration

Houses



ling to

Bill.



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



HCME AFFAIRS



Ihe Maguires

Case



;Previous



Reference:



CC(90)22.2



preferable to a registration scheme.   There was, however,

no need at this stage to give a public canmitment on what

action the Government proposed to take on the amendment in

the Commons, which need not be addressed until the Bill

returned to the Cannons in October.



ERIME MINISTER, sunming up the discussion, said that the

inet agreed that it would be wrong for the Government to

frcm its position that a dog registration scheme was

sary and unworkable, and that it should in due course



ersal of the lords&apos; amendment.   In the meantime every

should be made to deploy the Government&apos;s case against

istration scheme as strongly as possible but the

Government should reserve its position on the action it would

take in the Cannons until it was seen in what form the Bill

returned f^raXthe lords.



The



Took note,

up of their/



approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing

assion.



that he had recently received Sir

his inquiry into the circumstances

report reoaimended that the

for possessing explosives

should be referred back to

his view not just on the



which had been the basis

 s conclusion cn this

nature of the forensic

ion by the trial judge.

Secretary had announced



2.     THE HCME

John May&apos;s interim

of the Guildford Four

convictions of seven

were unsafe and unsatisfa

the Court of Appeal,

possibility of innocent

of the Director of Public

matter, but also because of the

evidence, and an unsatisfactory

now the Master of the Rolls. The



in a written Parliamentary answer the previous day that he

would be accepting Sir John May&apos;s reocnroendatuon, and he had



formally referred the case to the Court

The report would be made available to

by a motion for an unopposed Return, and

raised during Heme Office questions. NOw

been referred to the Appeal Court, the issue

The Business Managers were taking steps to

Speaker was advised of the position, to enable

clear as necessary that the Government could not

questions on the case.



The Cabinet -



Took note.



that morning,

that afternoon

y to be

matter had

judice.

the



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



North Atlc

Treaty



Organisation

Summit in

lorrion, 5-6

July 1990



Houston



Economic



Summit



3.     THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the

British Government&apos;s objectives had been achieved at the North

Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) Sunmit in London cn 5-6

July.   The right balance had been struck between reaffirming

the importance of NATO as the central collective defence

&quot;organisation of the Western Alliance  and demonstrating that it

adapting to change.   The essential elements of the Alliance

been preserved, including the integrated command structure,

&apos; States and Canadian stationed forces and an appropriate

nuclear and conventional weapons.   There had been a risk

Jerstanding in the original United States draft of the

ique over the reference to nuclear weapons as weapons of

last resort.   This had been countered by inserting language frcm

the Comprehensive Concept of Arms Control and Disarmament,

issued by/^Aio Heads of State and Government on 30 May 1989.

The NATO (suninit Communique had also sent a positive message to

the Sovier-^^^rship which had been well received by President

Gorbachev anaj^^hevadnardze at a critical time in the

political lif^^^^e Soviet Union.



THE CHANCELLOR OF

reached cn the points

Economic Sunmit in

impetus to the Uruguay

especially on agriculture

been deadlocked.

United States and

British Government

successful solution

the Second Montreal

June had been widely

Conference in November 1990 would

stabilising greenhouse gas emissions

of a Framework Convention on globed

also been a consensus on the need

assistance and know-how to the Soviet

introduction of genuine market policies

Government&apos;s position, that there

the problems and needs of the Soviet

for assistance, had been generally

this study wculd be led by the International

which had the greatest expertise in

organisations, including the EC, wculd



said that agreement had been

ipal importance discussed at the

9-11 July.   The Sunmit had given

world trade negotiations,



scussions had hitherto



the positions of the

(EC), which the

brought about a

the decisions taken at

London from 27-29

World Climate



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



    PRIME MINISTER said that it had not been easy to persuade

the united States Government to agree that reductions in the

overall level of agricultural support would bring about a

&gt;rresponding reduction in export subsidies.   In the end there

agreement that reductions in support should be

in terms of an aggregate measure, but that these

1 would cover internal regimes, market access and

subsidies.   ?Ihe President of the EC Commission,   Delors,

significant aside, had commented that work must new be put

a new agriculture system.   In the discussion on the

economy, she and other Government leaders had had to

President Bush that the key to sustainable growth was a

reduction in inflation.   This view had been accepted

final Ccmonunique.   There had also been evidence of an

ingly sharp united States reaction against the tendency

? member countries to assume that the United States

woulci simply align itself with positions already adopted by the

EC.   Overall, however, the Summit had taken place in an

excellent



people

the excel

Communique

secure



had been very well received by the

successful outcome was in part due to

r the Sherpas both in preparing the

working throughout the Summit to



In a brief discs,

agricultural

achievement. Ihe

positions of the EC

important positive

within the EC. Ihe

MacSharry, had been

the United Kingdom&apos;s role

to British farmers that,

Catnnunity, they should benef

!here might be some attempts

for small farmers on social,

which would bring little benefit

attempts should be resisted.



it was noted that the agreement an

Uruguay round had been a major

Kingdom&apos;s role in bridging the

other countries would be an



next round of negotiations

ioner for Agriculture, Mr

the outcome of the Summit and

d be important to point out

efficient producers in the

from the Summit conclusions,

the EC to maintain subsidies

and environmental grounds,

British farmer. Such



net Union        THE FOREIGN AND OCMCNWEAEIH SECRETARY

Congress, which began on 2 July, had so

&apos;ious successful from President Gorbachev



5ference: re-elected General Secretary with a



:(90) 25.3        the hard left traditionalists had failed to



perestroika.   Nevertheless, the Congress held il

extent to which the political system in the Sov:

disintegrating.   It had shown that while diehards

Party were resisting reform, the Party itself was

increasingly out of touch with the ordinary Russian

Although President Gorbachev had largely kept control

Party, he still faced formidable problems in the

large, including a miners&apos; strike.   The situation in the

Union would remain confused for the foreseeable future.



the 28th Party

reasonably

He had been

jority, and



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



prev



Fef&lt;

CC(90)



OCMMUNTIY

SAIRS



Factortame

(fishing

essels)



lous

Reference:

CC(90) 23.2



    FOREIGN AND CCMMDNWEAIIH SECRETARY said that the recent

unrest in Kenya was causing growing  concern.   The fact that

fatalities had occurred during the disturbances had changed the

situation.   Ihe British Government was under seme domestic

criticism for not publicly denouncing President Moi. Hewever,

the best way to influence President Moi was to convey the

Government&apos;s views privately.   The British Government was new

etly but firmly bringing heme to President Moi the need to

&gt;dy present grievances and to carry forward genuine reforms,

situation in Kenya remained disturbing.   The Kenyan



&apos;s attitude ran counter to the prevailing trend

democracy in Africa, which had been endorsed at the

Economic Summit.   President Ruanda faced a similar

ition in Zambia.   The key question was whether President Moi

would pay attention to the advice which he was new being given

by the British and other Governments.



In a bri

likely to

The right

meant a multi

majority of

point of view.



?ion, it was noted that this question was



in the House of Ccnroons in the coming days,

 ytake was that for Western countries democracy

and it was to be hoped that the

Ties would gradually ccme round to this



The Cabinet -



Took note.



4.     THE MINISTER OF AGRI

the House of lords had decided

granted to the applicants in the&lt;

they had been excluded from regi

directors or shareholders not bei



AND POOD said that

interim relief should be

brtame case, insofar as

ation by reason of their

? resident or domiciled in the



applic



ched on the

The plaintiffs

 rt for re-

Agriculture



ing the



Dhited Kingdom.   This judgement went further than had been

expected.   It would first be necessary toehold discussions with

the plaintiffs to see if agreement could

terms the order giving effect to the j

would then have to apply to the Department

registration, and subsequently to the

for licences to fish. It would be necessary,

terms of the judgement, to scrutinise the

carefully.   Ihe whole process might take between&apos;

months.   Uncertainty would persist until the

judgement in the case was given by the European

Justice, which was likely to take another six months

Ihe British fishing industry would inevitably be very

at the House of Lords decision, which created a situati

was not easy to defend, and there might be a risk of inci

arising in the fishing waters themselves.   It involved giv



CONFIDENTIAL




CONFIDENTIAL



Spanish interests the right to fish against quotas allocated to

the United Kingdom and it therefore struck at the basis of the

allocation of national quotas under the Ccnroon Fisheries Policy

of the European Ccrmunity.



-THE IRTME MINISTER said that the Secretary of State for Trade

Industry, who was in Czechoslovakia, had caused a statement

&gt;be issued that morning saying that, an reflection, he very

regretted remarks reported in The Spectator of that day and

redly withdrew them.   If questioned an the matter,

should draw attention to that statement.



The Cabinet -

Took



Cabinet Office

12 July 1990



CONFIDENTIAL





</content>
</cab>
