<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/9 images: 82-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;s GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (42)9th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 9 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, January 19, 1942, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Earle Page,Special Envoy from the Governmentof the Commonwealth of australia the Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade (Items 8-10).The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Leathers,Minister of War Transport (items-10).The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury (Items 9 and 10).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secre-tary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. J. T. C. Moore-Brabazon, M.P., Minister of Air-craft Production (Items 8-10).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.Lord Portal,  Parliamentary Secre-tary, (Raw Materials), Ministry ofSupply (Items 8-10).Admiral of  the Fleet  Sir  dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Sir Edward Bridges.Secretariat.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.[23362]
WAR CABINET 9 (42).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations ........ .... ;    43.Air Operations. &apos; ,&apos;-   &apos;. &apos;&quot;&apos;     &quot; &quot;Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations-Libva.U.S&apos;.S.R.    . : .;   :2      The Far East    ........................      ....      44Military situation.3      Finland   ..........................:.....      444      Free France      ....      .... ....      ....      ....      ....      .... 44General de Gaulle.5      St. Pierre and Miquelon ....      ....      ....      ....      .... 446      Timor     ............      .................... 447      Parliament        ................      ....      ....      ....      45Select Committee on National Expenditure.Proposed taking of evidence from Soviet Trade Union Delegation.8      The Allies............................      45Co-ordination of War effort:Munition assignments.Shipping.Raw Materials Board.9      Parliament        ....      ............      .... ....      47Suggested recording of the Prime Ministers statement.10      Parliament        .................... ....      47Debate on Aerodrome defence.
Naval, Military \. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following information in and Air          amplification of Cabinet War Room Records Nos. 863-869Operations. 0 .(Previous Summary of aircraft losses since the 12th January : Reference: Home Theatre W.M. (42) 4th Enemy-Conclusions, 3 destroyed.Minute 1) 2 probable.Air Operations. 3 damaged.Our Own 15 bombers (out of 423 sorties). ViMiddle East  1Enemy  ;i15 destroyed. /2 probable.7 damaged. r&quot;Our Own- 22 destroyed (including 2 on the ground).1)Far East -. ;:Enemy  &apos;18 destroyed. - . ... j14 probable.17 damaged (including 13 on the ground).Our Own 34 destroyed.22 damaged.Orders had been given that the attack carried out by coastal command on military objectives in Guernsey should not be repeated.At Malta there had been sixty-two alerts during the seven days&apos;period.Naval The total of shipping sunk during the previous week by enemyOperations.       action was estimated at 61,000 tons.   To this total must be addedShipping Losses. 47,000 tons of marine casualties, mainly due to bad weather.   Inaddition, about 31,000 tons had been damaged by enemy action and about 82,000 tons as a result of marine casualties.There had been some increase in the effectiveness of the enemy&apos;smining operations in Home Waters.Muitary The main developments were the fall of Sollum and of HalfayaOperations.        Pass.  At the latter some 5,500 prisoners had been taken, includingLibya. 48 German officers and about 1,770 German other ranks.IIS.S.R. The Russian forces had resumed their forward movement on several parts of the front, notably outside Leningrad and to the west of Moscow. Here both the northern and southern pincers were in;motion. It looked as though the southern pincer was moving towards Bryansk. In the Crimea the situation was less favourable,and the Germans had recaptured Feodosia.The War Cabinet-(i) Took note of the above statements. 1 1(ii) Asked the Chief of the Air Staff to report on the organicsation of the German Air Force lately in Cyrenaica, on!the basis of such evidence as had now come into our hands. Information was called for as to the number of&apos;aircraft which the German Air Force had maintainedoperationally fit, and the number of ground personnelemployed in servicing those aircraft, and whether suchL personnel were allocated to the servicing of individualaircraft.[23362] b 2
(iii) The Chief of the Air Staff sTloiifd MM&apos;report how manyof the former Italian aerodromes raCyrlenaica were nowbeing used. --ixxailim jhj? wb ;;(iv) Instructed the Chief of the Imperial General Staff roreport at what rate the rail-head in Cyrenaica could be moved forward. :, v:The Far East.MilitarySituation.(previous reference:&apos;-W&amp;f. (42) 4thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. A general discussion took placeon the present Militarysituation, and the future prospects, in the Far East.A record of the discussion, and of the Conclusions reached,is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Finland.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 124thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that therewas some indication that peace feelers might be made to Finland onbehalf of the Soviet Government. It was important, if any approach was made by the Finnish Government to Ministers in thiscountry, that they should not make any response, since this matter was best handled by the Soviet Government.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.b Free France. 4.   The Foreign Secretary said that a practice had been general established whereby representatives of foreign countries in thisde Gaulle.        country submitted to us, in advance, copies of broadcast speechesthey proposed to make.   General de Gaulle had recently proposed 1 to make a speech, but had submitted it only a very short time before it had been due to be delivered. He (the Foreign Secretary) had therefore stated that the speech could not be delivered : this wasnot the first time the General had so offended.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.St. Pierre andMiquelon.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 7thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. Arising out of the preceding Minute, the Prime ministers aid that he proposed to see General de Gaulle and explain to him that it was impossible to agree that, in addition to the communique,there should be a formal private agreement. The United StatesGovernment would not accept any such arrangement. Possibly,however, the United States Government might acquiesce tacitly insome of his points, provided that they were not raised formally.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Timor, 6.   The Prime Minister referred to a Minute which he had(Previous : , addressed to the Foreign Secretary, in which he had suggested that,Reference: v in view of the strategic importance of the island, we should notW.Mi (42) lsb.. commit ourselves now to withdrawing%ur forces from Timor whenConclusions,^ the Portuguese troops arrived. By that time the position mightMinute 3.) .     have changed. v-.-     y: .::.rd:j:- x, : The War Cabinet were informed&quot; that the negotiations whichhad taken place had certainly led the Portuguese Government tobelieve that we should withdraw bur11 forces as soon as: the portuguese-guese contingent arrived, provided that the Portuguese fulfilled
Parliament.SelectCommittee onNationalExpenditure.Proposed taking of evidence fromSovietTrade UnionDelegation,7. The Foreign Secretary said that a letter had been recefivedin the Foreign Office from the Clerk to the Select Committee; ionNational Expenditure asking whether arrangements could be madefor the Committee to hear evidence from the members of the soviet trade Union Delegation, now in this country, as to how : the munitions production which they had seen in this country comparedwith that in Russia.The War Cabinet- :&quot;iu!&quot;&apos;(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to reply that the letter hadbeen passed to the Secretary of the War Cabinet,, whowould bring the matter before the War Cabinet. ,... i(2) Authorised the Secretary of the War Cabinet to reply  $atthis request had been considered by the: War cabinet and adjudged unacceptable. , luUThe Allies.Co-ordination ofWar Effort.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 8thConclusions,Minute 1.)MunitionAssignments.(previous reference;,;-;1 W.M. (42.) ,7thConclusions,Minute 7,,)v i8. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the PrimeMinister (W.P. (42) 27), to which were appended three documentsinitialled by himself and the President dealing with (1) The establishment of Committees in Washington vandLondon for Munition Assignments.(2) The establishment of Anglo-American Shipping Adjust-ment Boards in Washington and London.(3) The establishment of a Combined Raw Materials Board.The Prime Minister said that the President was anxious, ifpossible, to make an announcement at an early date in regard to (2)and (3).The following were the main points made in discussion : (i) The Prime Minister pointed out that, while we should, ofcourse, help the United States to the fullest extent possible, that help would be far less than the help whichAmerica would give us. &apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;(ii) Sir Earle Page said that Australia was at present drawinghelp from both the United States aud this country.. ^Ilehoped that the machinery for co-ordinating in london the needs of the Dominions with those of the UriltedKingdom would be so framed as to take this fact intoaccount.(iii) Sir Earle Page also said that the Australian Govern-ment attached importance to some machinery being established for determining what munitions should bemade in which of the Allied countries and Dominions.It was explained that this matter would not come within the scope of the Committees in question, whichwould deal with the assignment of finished munitions.The Minister of Labour and National Service skidthat this point would be covered by the report whicfi hewart    had been asked by the War Cabinet to submit at their meeting on the ]15th  Jariuary.,. . ...., ^r..r!\^..;:.:;:rai^aw ;p^er-, conditions.   We were, in fact, so committed.   It., ..:,        seamed clear that they would be greatly affronted if in the event we did not withdraw our troops. \:,or i      : &apos;      The War Cabinet agreed- \That this question must for the present continue to be dealtwith on the lines already approved, but that the position should be reviewed in two or three weeks&apos; time.
(iv) The Minister of War Transport said that the scheme proposed was very satisfactory from his point of view.(v) The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the question hadbeen raised whether we would be prepared to sell to theUnited States fifty-four of the sixty ships now being built in the United States under contracts placed by this. country.The view taken was that we should not sell these ships and should retain our interest in them.  While theshipping resources of the two countries would be; deemedjto be pooled, it was important that these ships should...come into the pool as British, and not American, ships.  , *(vi) The Minister of War Transport added that some of the&apos;:Allied countries, e.g., Norway, would like, if possible^to be mentioned by name in the last paragraph of the.-,,document. &quot;.v..The Prime Minister said that it would be difficult;to do this, as the concluding paragraph was in common,form.(vii) Sir Earle Page said that it would be necessary to set up some machinery to co-ordinate the needs of theDominions with those of the United Kingdom. Thepresent machinery was not adequate for this purpose.He hoped that a statement as to the machinery proposed would be communicated to the Australian government at the same time as these three documents were communi-cated to them. &apos;: ...   -. . I-   j. ,v,        .--,)This was agreed to.(viii) The President of the Board of Trade said that he assumed,that oil was not regarded as a raw material.;The Minister of War Transport said that, having;regard  to the  dependence of oil questions on the&apos;iavailability of tanker tonnage, oil should be dealt withby a separate body affiliated to the Shipping Boards.The Prime Minister said that he would make thispoint clear when replying to the President.(ix) The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he assumed that the arrangements proposed in these,documents did not affect the arrangements for handling,production and shipping questions in this country.It was agreed that tbis was the case.The Prime Minister said that he thought there might be some advantage if Field-Marshal Sir John Dill were now to be appointedHead of our Joint Staff Mission in Washington. He proposed togive further consideration to this matter/ and would report to theWar Cabinet at a later Meeting.      .    -The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Prime Minister to send a telegram to president roosevelt, in the light of the discussion, suggestingcertain modifications on points of detail in the threedocuments.(2) Agreed that these three documents should be forwarded tothe Dominion Governments after the Prime minister had communicated with the President, and that the communications to the Dominions should be accompanied&apos;by an outline of the machinery proposed in London toensure the necessary consultation with the Dominions on&apos;these matters. &apos;      ;
Parliament.SuggestedEecording ofthe PrimeMinister&apos;sStatement.(PreviousHef erence:W.M. (42) 4thConclusions,Minute 9.)9. The War Cabinet gave further consideration to this matter,on which a Question had been put down for answer by the PrimeMinister on the following day.In discussion, all Ministers were strongly of opinion that thePrime Minister ought not to undergo the strain of making a state-ment in the House and also broadcasting on the same day. Further;,it was felt that the House would almost certainly grant this requestif the Prime Minister asked for it. Some doubts were, however,expressed as to whether a recording of a speech made in the Houseof Commons would not make it very difficult to refuse a request that other speeches should be broadcast.After discussion, the War Cabinet agreed as follows : That the Prime Minister should reply on the lines of thedraft which he read to the War Cabinet, proposing that,as an experiment, an electrical recording should be madeof the statement which he had been asked to make in thefollowing week on the present war situation. The pro-cedure contemplated was that a separate Motion would berequired on each individual recording and that the matter,should be left to a free vote of the House.Emphasis might be laid on the fact that this statement wasa very special occasion, since it was likely that the PrimeMinisters speech would be broadcast to the united nations, including, in particular, the United States andthe Dominions.Parliament. 10. After a short discussion, the War Cabinet agreed asDebate on follows :-Aerodrome (1) The Government reply in the Debate on this matter, whichDefence. was taking place in the House of Lords on the following(Previous day, should be made in very general terms by the reference: Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Air.W.M. (42) 7th (2) The Joint Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasury should conclusions, agree to the request that a Debate on aerodrome defenceMinute 3.) should take place on Thursday, the 22nd January, in theHouse of Commons.(3) If this debate was confined to matters of organisation, itcould take place in public, but, if the Members concerneddesired to deal with operational matters, this could onlybe done in Secret Session.(4) Some discussion took place as to whether the government spokesmen in the House of Commons should include a ministerial representative of the War Office as well as of the Air Ministry. Certain Ministers were strongly in favour of a reply being made by representatives of one department only (the Air Ministry). A decision on thismatter was deferred.Great George Street, S. W. 1,January 19, 1942.

W.M. (42) 9th CONCLUSIONS.19th January. 1943.PARLIAMENT. The War Cabinet were informed byProposed Visit       THE FOREIGN SECRETARY that a Member of by a Member ofparliamant to        Parliament wished to visit Turkey with a viewTurkey.to obtaining for his firm a contract which might otherwise be secured by the Germans.In view of the attitude taken by thisMember of Parliament, who had openly advocateda negotiated peace, it was undesirable that heshould pay a visit to Turkey, where a sectionof public opinion also favoured this view.After discussion, the War Cabinet:-(l)    Invited the Foreign Secretary toinform the Member of parliament in question, privately,  that itwas undesirable that he should visit Turkey:(2)    Agreed that,   if necessary,  thereason why a permit to visit-Turkey had been refused should be stated openly.




</content>
</cab>
