<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/131/0 images: 72-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/S DOCUM NT 13 THE PROPERTY OP HIS 3RITAHNIG MAJESTY1 S G.OVSR1&amp;ISINT).,Memorandum by the ChangelloT^-gt. the Exchequer,A decision must he taken at once on the Reparation question.   The financial situation cf Germany is critical. iThe German.Government are bound under the Schedule of Payments of May last tp pay on Reparation account in two instalments on &apos;15th January and 15th February next about  30 million of which seme two thirds is payable at the eadGier date.   Default is Inevitable.    Sir John Bradbury report that neither the -existing German Government nor ahy substitute could lay hands on the undoubtedly large amounts of foreign currencies held abroad belonging to German nationals, that the effort of the German Government to obtain short-dated advances from the German industrials will fail, and that there must be default unless advances can be obtained.in this country or in America. None will be obtainable here, except on condition of a mora^ sanatorium satisfactory to&apos; the lenders.In my view we should take action at once without waiting for the default, for the following reasons:-(l)    The financial situation will be worsened by each week&apos;s delay.,,.(2)   Further depreciation of the mark will threaten the.position of all those who have opened/Sommercial credits in favour of German firms and may lead to serious losses here and possibly a panic in Holland and Bwitzerland.E C: R E. T..C A B I ,N .E T.;v. 3512.GERMAN   REP.ARATI ON.It/
It will certainly prevent further private credits being granted and will stop german purchases of essential re-quiraments and so bring about a crash in Germany.(3) The atmosphere after default will be less favourable to a reasonable decision, and the alternative courses of action will be the same then as now-I propose that subject to payment of the January and February instalments we should grant the German Government a moratorium for two years renewable at the end of that period for a further two years subject to oon-ditions and determinable on three months&apos; notioe by the unanimous deoision of the Reparation Commission that there has been a wilful breach by the German government of the conditions.     Germany1s obligations during the moratorium to be limited to(a) the delivery of   million   tons a month of coal under the Treaty provisions(b) other deliveries in kind up to the value of 400-5;0O million gold marks *(o.) payment in cash of  40 million gold marks for the costs of the Armies of Occupation.Failure to make the stipulated deliveries in kind should carry liability to pay over in cash the cash Value of the deficitsThe conditions should be as follows (1) The abolition of all subsidies ( ) The provision )f a Budget surplus (3) Stoppage of note printing (4) Calculation of customs duties in gold
(5)     The reoonatltution of the Reiohsbarik bo ns to place it in relation to the ft em an Government somewhat in the position of the Bank of England to        Government in which it could adopt- a &quot;nagging&quot; attitude to demands for advances.(6)     The internal price of. coal to he raised so as to bring it into a reasonable relation to the world price.) - - .      The amount of the annual payments provided for bythe Schedule of- Payments which are postponed should bear interest during the moratorium period which should be added to the capital of the debteThe French Government will probably resist these proposals in favour of measures of force and it may be necessary to make some concession in regard to payments for deliveries during the moratorium.   But the Reparation Commission have power to   ostpone the instalments payable by Germany in. any year by a&apos;maiority vote.    To secure a majority both the It&amp;lian and Belgian votes are necessary, the French Chairman having a&apos; casting vote.   The Italian-Government is likely to, be favourable to postponement but will probably seek some consideration in return.   Belgium In view of her priority has the largest interest in the next payments by Germany.    In Belgium public opinion is likely to be more easily satisfied than in France of the German Government&apos;s &quot;inability to pay and of the&apos; disastrous consequences of violent measures.-  Ultimately the consent of both Italy and Belgium could probably be secured by a threat to withdraw our representative f^om.the Reparation Commission on the six months&apos; notice provided for by the treaty(Initialled)   \ ..S.H.T-FASURY, P:;-&apos;-;l.28th November, 1391-;

</content>
</cab>
