<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/131/0 images: 174-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
134SECRET.To &quot;be destroyed when roplaoed by a subsequent number.SECRlfl? ADMIRALTY WEEKLY   INTEXI.IG5N0E   Sim&amp;RY.No. 48,   Srti December.. 1921,Issued by the Naval Intelligence Division Naval Staff, Admiralty, for the Information of Recipients only.DISTRIBUTION Sent by All British; Route toCopiesCopies....... ........* . * *0 . * . ................ e . ecard of AdmiraltyIpiSoo.,Naval Sec. ,P.A.S. ,P.A.S(S)iity Captain . *...............le Odb inet . *..............*..joy.. Naval Board, Melbourne eoy., Naval Board, New Zealand beotor. Naval Service, Ottawa .. iA(NaA.0* ................... ....pain Segrave, R.N.,Naval Representative, League of Nations. inders^in^Chief, The Nore *.............. *PortsmouthPlymouth oa.................Sootland....................W.Approaches...............Atlantic Fleet.............N.Amerioa &amp; West Indies ....Medit mediterranean..............China......................East Indies&quot; *...............Africa.....................fA.C,, Reserve Fleet............&quot;\0*, 1st Battle Squadron ......it 1st Battle Squadron........, 4th Battle Squadron........, Battle Cruiser Squadron .... &apos;j 1st Light Cruiser Squadron.. . 2nd Li $it Cruiser Squadron,. .. 3rd Light Cruiser Squadron.. j&amp;*t Yangtse....................m ::::::::::::::::::::::::::ttnanding Offioer,H.M.S. 8Renown&quot;1 TOTAL (Distribution by Copying Branch)10 4 140 2 3 1 11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 185Adrniralty Naval StaffI.D.     ltiitltMlt*O.D.............P.D.T.D...........Intelligence Offloers S.I.OTg -mediterranean china .....East IndiesSeAmerioa . .  N.America .Ottawa .... D.I.01 s -Port smouthChatham ...DevonportRo sythHull.......Liverpool .*Queens town ,Gibraltar . *Malta......Colombo ....Singapore *.Shanghai .. * &apos; Wellington .Capo Town *.Bermuda ....Asoenaion D.N.T., Melbourne .. N.1.0,, Hong Kong ... N.V.O., Monte Video N. WO., Oallao ...... * . , .. *... d0 * Ia a o ...TOTAL   (I. D.Distribution)18 2 2 11 1 1 1 1 11 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 140
^pBI Jbe destroyed when replaced &quot;by a subsequent number.SSORET ADMIRALTY WB5KLY   INTELLIGENCE   SWARY. (W, 1.9)No. 48., ,.For the week ending, 3rd Deo. .,1921.PART    I.    NAVAL   INT ELLIG ENO S * GREAT BRITAIN.PROGRAMMES, of H. M. SHIPS.H.M.S. 11 Lowest oft&quot;, Leaves Simons town 29th December, Cape Town 29th*-31st December, St.Helena- 6th-llth January, Lagos 16th-20th January, Victoria 22nd-26th January, Accra 28th January - 1st February, Lago3 2nd-7th February, Elephant Bay 12th February, Great Fish Bay 13th-14th February, Walfisoh Bay 16th-l9th February, Gape Town 22nd February. &apos;K.M.S. &quot;Renown&quot;.   Programme between 17th January and 10th March Is        Colombo 20th January,-2nd March, Bombay 5th-8th March.Hi M. Ships &quot; Restle ss&quot;, 11 Rigorous&quot;, &quot; Romola&quot;, &quot; Rowena&quot;. Leave Gibraltar 2nd December. Leave Alters 8th December. Leave Oran 13th December for Gibraltar.H.K.S. &quot;Caroline&quot;.   Leaves Colombo 18th Deoember, Aden 26th Deoember, Suez 29th December, Part Said 1st January, Malta 5th January, Gibraltar 10th January.   (Dates are approx--. irnate).   Then proceeds to Portsmouth to pay off for disposal.E.M.S. &quot;Crocus&quot;.   Proceeds to Bombay in January.H.U.S. &quot;Comas&quot;.    Detailed to escort H.R.H.  Prince of Wales in R.I.M.S. &quot;Dufferin&quot;.   Leaves Calcutta 30th December, Rangoon 2nd-10th January, Madras 13th January.H.M.S. &quot;Crozier&quot;.   Programme should now read Gibraltar 29th November - 3rd;,December. Las Palms 5th-7th December, Sierra Leone 12th-14th Deoember, Lagos I9th-22nd December, St.Paul de Loanda 26th-29th December, tfalfisch Bay lst-3rd January, Cape Town 7th January.LATVIA.The Latvian Gunboat &quot;Virsaitis&quot; (ex-German &quot;M. 68&quot;) has been salved and repaired and will shortly be placed in commission as Senior officer s ship.of; the Latvian Navy.R U S S I A.The personnel of the Black Sea Fleet consists of men who have joined the Navy for their own convenience, and who have had no previous experience of naval work.     There
R U S 3 I A     (Oontd.)There are a j?oo&amp; many ex--soldiers, and quite a number who have neither served ashore or afloat *    Owing to la ok of specialists, res;ponsible posts have to be filled with Petty Officers, Mechanics, and even ordinary sailors. ViTomsn are employed as cooks and are treated in exactly the same way as the ordinary sailors.F BAN Q E.The sloop &quot;BethtineB had a boiler explosion whilst undergoing her trials off Port-de-Bouo (Marseille) *   Two men were dangerously burnt .Tho sloop &quot;3ellatrix.a has proceeded to Majunga to embark the Governor General of Madagascar for a tour of coast inspection and also to visit tho Comoro   Islands.The Government has refused an amnesty to the Black Sea mutineers*   The election of Marty as a Paris 1 Municipal Councillor, which was annulled, has been followed by the election of another Black Sea mutineer and Conmunist.
PART    II.    GENERAL   INTELLIGENCE.F I N L AN :OcFinland is sympathetic to the cause of the Karelians who have now risen against the Soviet, and has asked, the League of Nations to send a Co-mission to examine the rights&apos; of the Karelians as a national minority.   Finland has declared that she will maintain strict neutrality, hut will not interfere with any humanitarian enterprise.Petlura&apos;s returning toA U ST. R I A.Serious riots took place in Vienna on 1st December, when a considerable amount of damage was done to shops and hotels.   The riots started with workmen s demonstratiens to -protest against the high cost of living consequent on the further heavy fall of the value of the &quot;Krone&quot;.The Liinister of Finance promised to a deputation of workers a strong measure of State Control of the foreign exchange.U K R A I; N E.The insurrection in tho Ukraine under leadership has failed and the rebel staff are Poland,POL AN p,General Zeligowski left Vilna on 30th November for Cracow, where he is reported to intend to live in retirement *The Government has consented to the formation of an inter-allied oorairlssion to enquire into the treatment of prisoners taken in Upper Silesia.A R A B I A.Some Hedjaz troops have been attacked and defeated near El Taif during the past week.   Newspaper reports state that Ibn Saud was the aggressor.    It would,however, appear that Sheikh Kalid is the responsible party.,    The Headquarters of the latter are at &quot;Kurra, on the debatable land, between the dominions of Ibn Saud and Hussein, and he professes allegiance to neither of these chieftains.-lussein is taking steps to deal with Ha lid:A LThe alleged statement of - XBriand at the Washington Conference that tho reduction of the Italian array was brought about by moral disihtegration has been received with anger. At Turin, a mob -wrecked, the French Consulate, destroyed its furniture and archives and carried away the coat of arms which was paraded with contumely: in addition the French Consul was grossly insulted.
A R G 5 N T IN E,Insurgents in the Santa Cruz district have recently seized certain British subjects, one of whom, Herbert Robins has been put to death.-,    Representations have been made to the Argentine Government with a view to the safeguarding of British subjects in the disturbed area.0. H I N A.Macaoj.        The Chinese have accepted the principle of joint Investi-rrafion of the incident of September with the Portuguese as a preliminary to a discussion of the waters question.I. T A LY     (0 ontd,,)The Prefect of Turin lias apologiaed for these happenings, but tho French Ambassador is not satisfied,.Ariti.^B1f enoh feeling is very acute in Rome.Signor Tuozai has been recalled from Angora.,A general strike of railwaymen is threatened.The state of the Greek arm;/ in Anatolia is des-oribed as bad.    The men are poorly fed and insufficiently provided with winter olothincr.    In addition, they are tired of war and desertions are frequent.The Government has dealt severely with the workmen of the Athens Electric Power - Company/, who attempted a lightning strike on 22nd November, thus contravening the law .that three days1 notice must be piven.   Nine of the ringleaders have been sentenced to eight years, -and fifteen others to five years1 imprisonment .    Forty men who happened to be reservists have been drafted to the Anatolian front * These prompt and severe measures have been welcomed by the general public, who are tired of the pretensions of the over-paid artisans and unskilled labourers.T U R K E, Y.It is reported from Athens that Snver Pasha has sent a formal Note to the Angora Government in which he declares that, unless the Angora Government accepts the decisions of the Popular party of the Turkish Soviet, headed by himself and other ex-members of the CoU.P., he will raise an army in the Caucasus and enforce his terms by force.,       It is further stated that he has already begun to raise an army from, among the Turkish population of the Caucasus, and that the Angora Government have   sent an indignant protest to Mo so 07/oPerid Bey has arrived in Paris as Turkish Diplomatic representative *

</content>
</cab>
