<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/131/0 images: 283-283</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]SECRET.THE FRENCH BUDGET POSITION.THE French Budget is divided into three parts, the Ordinary Budget, the Extraordinary Budget, and the Budget of.expenses recoverable under the Peace Treaty. It is a point of principle that,- whatever may be done to-balance the two former, the French taxpayer shall contribute nothing to the last.M. Doumer&apos;s original budget proposals for 1922 amalgamated the ordinary and extraordinary budgets, showing a total expenditure of 24,932 millions and a total revenue of 22,470 millions, and proposed to meet the deficit of 2,462 millions by doubling the tax on business turnover. Of the expenditure 1,752 millions were of the classes usually termed &quot;extraordinary,&quot; and of the revenue 3,050 millions were non-recurrent (war profits tax and sale of stocks).The Budget Commission of the Chamber reported against the proposed doubling of the tax on business turnover, and pressed the Government to make further economies to secure a balance. Such economies as could be suggested both by the Government and the Commission themselves turned out to be no more than sufficient to balance the supplementary credits which became necessary and the expenditure remained at 24,C53 millions.On the other j*and M. Doumer was able to promise an increase of revenue. From an improvement in administration of the revenue departments he anticipated an increase of 377 millions over the original Estimate of the yield of the income tax and of 500 millions in that of the war profits tax. The deficit was reduced thereby to 1,626 millions, which M. Doumer proposed to meet by some minor increases of taxation amounting to 391 millions and a more moderate increase (50 per cent.) in the turnover tax.The Budget Commission have reported against the taxation proposals and have recommended that the deficit of 1,625 millions be allowed to stand. The justification adduced for this is that the expenditure includes a sum of 1,500 millions for redemption of debt (i.e., for paying off bonds surrendered in payment of the war profits tax). To borrow the money required for this purpose is merely to substitute a new debt for an old. The Budget Commission have also recommended the retention of the distinction between the ordinal and the extraordinary budgets, and the final result of their recommendations is the following (in millions of francs): -Ordinary. Extraordinary. TotalExpenditure         ... 21/753 3,200 24,953Receipts....... 19,777 3,550 23,327Surplus ... - 350 -Deficit ... 1,976 - 1,626The extraordinary expenditure includes the 1,500 millions for redemption of debt. Thus there is a deficit of nearly 2 milliards on the ordinary budget taken by itself.The budget of expenses recoverable under the peace treaty comprises war pensions together with all the outlay on the devastated area and similar expenditure. Hitherto it has been the practice to show the capital sums to be spent on reconstruc-tion, and apparently nearly 21 milliards had been spent up to 31st December, 1920, and 9 milliards more voted for 1921 should bring the total up to 30 milliards by the 31st December next. But for 1922 the &quot; recoverable &quot; budget shows, so far as most of the capital outlay on reconstruction is concerned, only the annual charge for interest. The total is thus reduced to 7,159 millions (of which 3,657 millions are for war pensions) as compared with 15,380 millions in 1921 and 21,265 millions in 1920 (though the latter figure was much underspent). The reduction is therefore wholly or partly fictitious.Deliveries in kind from Germany would of course go in relief of the capital requirements in question, while the cash payments would be applied to meet the budget charge of 7,159 millions. The cash receipt estimated for in the budget is 4,500 millions, leaving a deficit of 2,659 millions to be borrowed.*It may be added that the French claim for reparations, so far as the devastated regions and similar losses were concerned, amounted to 136 milliards, so that hardly a quarter has been dealt with yet, if that estimate can be accepted.* The real deficit seems to be from 9 to 12 milliards if allowance is made for some 6 to 9 milliards of new capital expenditure.[7404]

</content>
</cab>
