<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/131/0 images: 588-589</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property o  His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1921.SECRET CP. 3576.TURKISH PEACE.Memorandum by thr Secretary of State, for India.I did not consume the valuable time of the Conference of Ministers yesterday by re-argument of the case of Thrace. But in view of the decisions taken yesterday, which I most earnestly trust will lead to peace, I take this opportunity of putting on record the views that I hold.(1) I believe it to be in the interests of the British Empire that our friendly relations with the Turks, now more than justly punished for their share in the war, should be restored. 1 do not say this because I am a pro-Turk. It is true that most of those who have come in contact with the Turk I never have find him a likeable fellow, and he is probably a better fellow than the Greek ; but it is true that owing to the unfortunate escape of the &quot; Goeben&quot; and the &quot;Breslau,&quot; whose presence at Constantinople made it impossible for the Turk to make a separate peace, and owing to the admitted blunders of our pre-war diplomacy, the Turks were compelled to tight against us and to prolong the war, and must pay the penalty. My motive is what I conceive to he the interests of the British Empire.(2) I do not think that it is any act of friendship to the Greeks to permit them to acquire more territory than they are capable of admini-stering, and to remain in territory where their presence would be unwelcome. On the contrary, I believe that any outcome of the war if it were of this kind would lead not only to the arrest of Greek development, but possibly to revolution and chaos in Greece.(3) 1 think almost the most important consideration governing the distribution of Eastern Thrace is that the Prime Minister is honestly believed to have pledged himself, when he spoke on behalf of the British Empire in January 1918, so far as the British Empire was concerned, to leaving Thrace to Turkey, and I think it is most important that if such a pledge were made that pledge should be kept.(4) In 1919 the Prime Minister in the House of Commons stated that the pledge about Constantinople and Thrace was a pledge.(5) I admit that there is no religious question involved in the fate of Thrace as there is in the case of Constantinople, and the evacuation of Constantinople by the Allies, its freedom from allied control over its ndependenee, and the security which is being given by the proposed 4986      100   12.21
readjustment of the Chatalja frontier, are entirely satisfactory, and together with the proposals for municipal autonomy for Adrianople and the.minority clauses about the population of Thrace, would go far to solve the whole question, were it not for the bothersome pledge.(6) From the point of view of the pledge, therefore, and the real restoration of friendship with Turkey, I should of course prefer the restoration of the whole of pre-war Thrace to Turkey.(7) Failing that, and as a second best alternative, it would seem to me to be much the fairest solution to appoint a commission of enquiry into the wishes of the inhabitants and the arrangement of a frontier in conformity with the wishes of the inhabitants as nearly as such a commission could devise.   This seems to me the equitable solution.(8) Failing either of these, I would favour the suggestion which was rejected by the Conference of Ministers yesterday: to take a frontier which at its southern end came to the sea at the point on the map just east of Rhodesto, suggested by Lord Curzon, joined the Maritza River and joined the Bulgarian frontier after passing just south of Adrianople. This compromise would have the advantages of excluding the Turk from the Gallipoli peninsula, and including in Turkey the most ancient Turkish settlement in Europe Adrianople a town which is predominantly Moslem in population and containing places of veneration to Moslems generally. So far as I can see, it would roughly halve Eastern Thrace. We want both the Greeks and the Turks to live at peace. Both the Greeks and the Turks claim Thrace, and the Turks are supported by the Prime Ministers pledge; The compromise suggested is to split the difference !What I fear most of all is this, that the French will advocate, inside or outside the Conference, the restoration of at least far more of Thrace to the Turk than Lord Curzon suggests ; that the Italians will support them, and that the British will have the responsibility, as it was put yesterday, of doing their best to save Thrace. This is the aspect of the case most pre-judicial to the interests of the British Empire; the commission of enquiry, whatever be its results, would avoid this disaster.22nd December 1921.E. S. M.

</content>
</cab>
