<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/131/0 images: 620-623</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Dooument is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1921.SECRET.CP. 3582*CABINET.OVERSEA  SETTLEMENT.M EM Oil AND TJ .\1 BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE EOll THE COLONIES.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues the accompanying Memorandum which I have received from Mr. Amery, in his capacity as Chairman of tiie Oversea Settlement Committee.A decision will be sought from the Cabinet early in the New Year upon the financial provision and legislative measures required to implement the resolution passed by the Imperial Conference last summer regarding State-Aided Empire Settlement (copy attached).I invite the attention of my colleagues to this question, as it is important that a decision upon policj&apos; should be reached at an early date.w. s. c.Colonial Office, December 23, 1921.Resolution Passed by Imperial Conference, 1921, regarding 1 . State-Aided Empire Settlement.The Conference having satisfied itself that the proposals embodied in the Report of the Conference on State-Aided Empire Settlement are sound in principle, and that the several Dominions are prepared, subject to Parliamentary sanction and to the necessary financial arrangements being made, to co-operate effectively with the United Kingdom in the development of schemes based on these proposals, but adapted to the particular circumstances and conditions of each Dominion, approves the aforesaid Report.The South African representatives wish to make it clear that the limited field for white labour in South Africa will preclude co-operation by the Union Government on the lines contemplated by the other Dominions.2. The Conference expresses the hope that the Government of the United Kingdom will, at the earliest possible moment, secure the necessary powers to enable it to carry out its part in any schemes of co-operation which may subsequently be agreed on, preferably in the form of an Act which will make clear that the policy of co-operation now adopted is intended to be permanent.3. The Conference recommends to the Governments of the several Dominions that they should consider how far their existing legislation on the subject of land,settlement, soldier settlement and immigration, may require any modification or expansion in order to secure effective co-operation; and should work out, for discussion with the Government of the United Kingdom, such proposals as may appear to them most practicable and best suited to their interests and circumstances.Colonial Office, December 23, 19,21.Unemployment and Empire Settlement.The limits. within which emigration or Empire settlement could be regarded as effective remedies for the actual unemployment situation at the moment were discussed in a previous Memorandum (Oversea Settlement and Unemployment, 29.9.&apos;21)$*[7548]&amp;     CP 3532 * A.
But the most serious problems which the country has to face is not this year&apos;s unemployment, but the whole employment position for the next decade or more. Costly emergency measures of relief are inevitable in a crisis like the present. But they cannot be continued indefinitely, and if what confronts us is not a temporary adverse fluctuation but a permanent or prolonged shortage of employment, we must start at once and on an adequate scale - with our remedial policy.There are indications of an improvement in the state of trade, and possibly unemployment may be down to under a million in the course of the coming year. But there is nothing in the state of the world to suggest a permanent revival for a long time to come. There is no sign that Europe has begun to turn the corner. The disorganisation of the exchanges is still increasing. Even when the European markets begiu to improve the various Governments will be compelled for exchange and other reasons to keep out our manufactures by much higher tariffs than were in existence before the war. It is true that some of these markets, more particularly the German market, with which our trade was largely in the nature of an exchange of manufactures for manufactures, never represented a volume of employment in this country at all commensurate with the trade figures. But Russia as a producer of foodstuffs and raw materials was of immense consequence to the employment situation not only in this country, but in the rest of Europe. The best of our markets, those of the British Dominions, have been retarded in their normal growth not only by loss of population and indebtedness resulting from the war, but also by the cessation in the inflow of capital and population.On the other hand, as compared with weakened and disorganised markets, the population in this country, which depends on those markets for its existence, has increased abnormally. On the basis of the 1913 emigration figures (approximately the same as the average of the period 1909-13, though the principle on which the returns are based was changed in 1912), the normal emigration for the period 1914-20 inclusive would have been over 2,100,000. The actual total emigration for these years was 340,000. Allowing for nearly 750,000 who fell in the war, that still leaves an excess of .1,000,000 over the population which this country would normally have carried at the beginning of the present year. There is nothing in the condition of the world markets to encourage the idea that we can find employment for this additional population a population which, it is worth noting, is almost wholly industrial and provides no complementary home market.In all these respects France furnishes a striking contrast. Her population, even without any relief through emigration, has long been constant, and her war losses have barely been balanced by the accession of Alsace-Lorraine. More important still, half her population is agricultural her agricultural population is larger than the white agricultural population of the whole British Empire and provides a secure and steady market for her staple industries. Her exports, mainly of specialities, relieved of the necessity of securing foodstuffs, are sufficient to purchase such essential raw materials as she cannot produce at home and in her colonies. The continuity of her well-balanced scheme of employment is hardly affected by the condition of the outside world.The problem of employment is essentially a problem of the right distribution of population. In the British Empire to-day that population is wrongly distributed, firstly, as between industry and agriculture, and secondly, as between Great Britain and the Dominions. In Great Britain the population is over 400 to the square mile ; in the Dominions it is under 6 to the square mile. The only effective and permanent cure of the evils arising from a faulty distribution in the Empire as a whole, and most acutely in this country, is to secure a right distribution. In other words, the key to the employment situation is the shifting of British population from Great Britain to the Dominions, and from industry to agriculture. What is needed is a policy of Empire migration and Empire land settlement carried out on a large scale. The two must go hand in hand, for the capacity of the Dominions to absorb additional urban population is narrowly limited by the growth of their agricultural population, and by the inevitable objection of their own industrial workers to the influx of competitive labour. The figure to be aimed at over the next decade or so is an average transfer of something like 500,000 a year, a figure not more than just large enough to work off the surplus 1,000,000 and slow down the normal rate of increase.It may be suggested that the most obvious remedy, as far as Great Britain is concerned, is to settle her industrial population on her own land. But the efforts already made in that direction indicate that the process would be slow and costly, and, apart from the actual limitation of the land available, there can be little prospect of an
agricultural development in Great Britain, capable of supporting a large population, without a policy of direct subsidy or protection on a scale for which no Government would venture to make itself responsible.Such a policy of Empire settlement and migration would necessarily cost money. But it would secure a real and&apos; lasting improvement at far less cost than the present system of relief works and doles. It is necessary to remember, in this connection, that the national cost, the burden on industry, arising from unemployment relief is the same whether the actual payment is from national or from local funds. Even the contributions from employers and workers to the Unemployment Insurance Fund, once unemployment ceases to be occasional and becomes chronic, partake much more of the nature of an ordinary tax than of an insurance.At the present moment we are spending on outdoor relief at the rate of nearly  12,000,000 a year, of which at least  8,000,000 is due to unemployment, while the expenditure on unemployment benefit is at the rate of no less than  60,000,000 a year. On a rough estimate something like  25,000,000 has been spent in the last year on more or less productive relief work.The whole of this great expenditure affords a purely temporary relief, ft effects no permanent cure. On the contrary, unless other circumstances relieve the situation, it aggravates it by the crippling burden which it imposes on industry, and by the extent to which it prevents natural economic adjustments, and undermines energy and self-reliance. We are reproducing to-day on a gigantic scale the evils which the Poor Law Commission of 1833 found in the agricultural England of those days. The remedy then as it should be to-day was a drastic check on doles, and a systematic policy of Empire settlement.As regards the cost of Empire settlement it is one of which only a portion would fall upon this country. The Dominions need the population, and are prepared to pay in order to secure it. All they require from us is such contribution as will enable them to carry out the policy of settlement on an adequate scale. At the Imperial Conference last summer all the Dominions, except South Africa, agreed in principle to sharing equally with this country in any schemes for assisted passages, which may take the place of the present ex-service free passages, and Australia is, I believe, putting down  160,000 on next years estimates for this purpose. In respect of land settlement they are likely to be content with a much smaller contribution than one-half, in view of the fact that such settlement should be reproductive, and ultimately very profitable expenditure.Mr. Hughes has just submitted the outlines of a scheme for settling some 50,000 settlers in Australia at a cost of  50,000,000 raised in five annual instalments, and would apparently undertake raising this money himself if we contributed to the scheme sums equivalent to half the interest for the first five years on each instalment, Le., the years before settlers could begin to make any repayments. This would mean for this country a total contribution of about  7,500,000- 8,000,000. But the settlement of 50,000 workers on the land in Australia would mean, including families and secondary industries, a general addition to the population of Australia of at least 300,000 persons. Assuming that 150,000 of these would require assisted passages, at a cost to this country of about  1,800,000, the total cost of transferring 300,000 persons to Australia, as far as we are concerned, would be under  10,000,000, or very little over  30 per head. -This is without any provision, as there naturally would be for settlers&apos; repayments being used to provide for fresh settlement. Such a scheme would naturally require very careful examination and settling of details before it could be agreed to. But, on the face of it, the expenditure incurred by this country is small for the amount of permanent relief afforded to the economic situation.On a very rough estimate I reckon that an annual expenditure of about  5,000,000, of which about one-quarter would go to assisted passages, &amp;c, and the remainder to contributions to Dominion schemes of land settlements, whether in the form suggested by Australia or in the form of loans to Governments or private organisations in respect of the numbers of men settled by them, would give a sufficient stimulus to the movement of population to make a very material difference to the immediate unemployment situation, and, in a few years, to alter the whole character of our economic problem. As a matter of fact it would not, be poss&apos;ble, with advantage, to spend more than about  2,000,000 in the next year, and it would probably take three or four years to work up to an expenditure of  5,000,000.The immediate practical steps which would have to be taken are for the Cabinet to authorise the Secretary of State for the Colonies to go seriously into the proposals put
forward by Australia or by any other Oversea Government or private organisation, and, at the opening of the next session, to introduce a short Bill sanctioning a total expenditure on contributions to schemes of assisted passages, land settlement or development not exceeding a maximum of  5,000,000 in any one yeai\(Initialled) L. S. A.December 12, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
