<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/29/10 images: 66-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
32THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOYEFNMEN^^*v printed for the War Cabinet.  September 1942. M m4SECRET. Copy No.   g yW.P. (12) 430.September 26, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.SUPPLIES FOR TURKEY.Note by the Secretary.THE attached note of an interview between the Prime Minister and theTurkish Ambassador on the 24th September, 1942, together with a tabular state-ment of the equipment being supplied to Turkey, is circulated by direction ofthe Prime Minister for the information of members of the War Cabinet.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES, Secretary.Great George Street, S.W. 1,September 26, 1942.I read out the list of the supplies to Turkey, agreed upon with the War Office,to the Turkish Ambassador this afternoon. On account of the cypher difficulties,though these are not great as the cable only is used, I did not give the list tothe Ambassador to telegraph. I told him I wished Sir Hughe Knatchbull-Hugessen to have the honour of handing it to President Inonu, but that asM. Orbay had been instrumental in bringing this to my attention, I thought hewould like himself to telegraph that a substantial packet of several hundred tanks and A.A. and A.T. guns would be sent forthwith. The only thing that wouldstop them would be a disaster on the Egyptian front, of which I told him, in myopinion, there was no danger.The Ambassador expressed his thanks and his personal pleasure at being ableto transmit the news. He also promised not to state any precise numbers in his telegram.[24398][p.T.0.
List of the Main Items of Equipment to be provided for Turkey between now and the end of 1942.(Those items of equipment which are shown as to be provided from the middle east will be so provided unless there is a military disaster in the western desert.)Type-of Equipment.Total to end of1942includingalreadysupplied.AlreadyreachedTurkey.In Transitorawaitingshipment.Furthersuppliesnowpromised.Date of Supply andRemarks.Tanks-(a) Stuart     Light.Tanks(b) Valentines    orMatildasA.T. Guns 37-mm.3-7-in. A.&apos;A. Guns ..Bofors A.A. GunsA.A. SearchlightsField Guns   .....Medium GunsVickers&apos; GunsLight Machine GunsSub-machine Guns ...A/Tk. Rifles.....Mortars 81-mm.E.D.F. Light WarningSets (type now coming into pro-duction)41074621425111104561,1505,1507,500725308251428472548505,1505001004051072273223007,500225208401302001361002525Before the end of the year from the Middle East.In October, November and december from UnitedStates production in thosemonths.To be shipped from theMiddle East by the endof November.From India and the middle east as soon as they canbe shipped.From United Estates Sep-tember and October pro-duction.By the end of the year fromthe Middle East.To be shipped from theUnited Kingdom by theend of the year.



</content>
</cab>
