<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/20/38 images: 394-397</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1942.SECRET Copy No.W.P. (42) 7.WAR CABINET.THE ATTITUDE OF Mr. de VALERA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I THINK the War Cabinet should see the attached report by Sir John Maffeybased on a recent interview which he has had with Mr. de Valera. This seemsto supplement and confirm the impressions which I had formed on my recent visit to Dublin.I have sent a brief account of the position by telegram to the Prime minister in case the Irish question should come up in his discussions with president roosevelt.C.Dominions Office, january.ry 3, 1942.THE effect on the position in Eire of the entry of America into the war atEngland&apos;s side has long been a subject of speculation. Mr. de Valera long agodeclared to me and also to the American Minister that it would &quot; change theposition here overnight.&quot; But since he made that declaration the feeling infavour of neutrality has, in spite of economic hardships, undoubtedly grownstronger. &quot; Safety first &quot; is the general watchword and considerations of the moral issues at stake in the war are held at arm&apos;s length or cynically rejected.America and the American way of life have progressively come in for harshercriticism as the chances of American intervention have increased. Nevertheless,the fact that the number of people of Irish descent now involved in the war onour side greatly exceeds the population of Eire, and many obvious factors which need not be enumerated, render American participation in the war an event oftremendous significance for Eire. For the present I shall not attempt to assesspublic opinion. It will take time to develop. But I have been concerned toascertain what the effect of this tremendous fact has been upon the mind ofMr. de Valera and how he now plans to steer his ship in conditions so greatlyaltered. I had an interview with him on the 23rd December to discuss othermatters, and I took the opportunity, as we were on the threshold of a new year,to question him closely as to how he was adjusting his views to these new anddramatically altered conditions. The result was entirely negative. I should makeit clear that I did not raise the question of the ports or similar facilities, but was merely probing his mind to discover whether he was likely to be seeking a pathtowards some closer co-operation with our cause in any direction.I began by asking him what -he thought about the prospects of 1942, since itwas a year which must present him with the need for grave decisions. To-dayEire, largely owing to the Censorship, was mentally stagnant, and had hithertolacked leadership on the big issues now forcing themselves to the front. ireland was more than a geographical expression; here there was a trumpet which in[23308]
2history had never failed to sound on the great moral issues, and that trumpet wasin his hands to-day. I had read his Cork speech with interest. He had thenspoken on the occasion of America&apos;s entry into the war and had expressedsympathy with her, had spoken of her help to the cause of Ireland, of Ireland&apos;sgratitude and of the historical links. All this plainly indicated a speech whichcould only end with an offer of his right hand. But then there came an anti-climax : &quot;circumstances&quot; and &quot;history&quot; rendered it impossible for Eire todo anything. This had puzzled me. The &quot;circumstances&quot; of to-day seemedobviously to require Eire&apos;s help. The &quot;history&quot; which mattered to-day wasnot a chronicle of past frictions but the History being written all round us in theclash of world forces. Half the world was at war with the other half. It was quite plain to which half Eire belonged. Under his leadership was she to standaloof and do nothing ?This led to the usual disputation about Partition and the impossibility of eire being involved in the war while that injustice existed. Not that he would do a deal over Partition. It was too late for that. In fact, the position could not now be remedied; we must accept the unhappy fact. Eire&apos;s abstention from thewar might no doubt delay a favourable solution of the Partition question. Buttime would remedy that in any event.I said that I was not raising the question of Eire participating in the war as a British war nor in relation to any Anglo-Irish problem. I had alwaysappreciated and given full weight to these difficulties, as he well knew. But the partition trouble was no good excuse to offer to America when she looked acrossthe Atlantic for an Irish friend. Mr. de Valera then sought refuge in dis-paraging the influence of American opinion on Irish policy.I said that the Censorship had so starved the Irish mind that here there wasno knowledge of the tremendous issues vitally affecting the country. He saidthat the Censorship in the main had acted in our favour. Anti-British feeling was the dynamic of Irish opinion, always there though often latent. Pro-paganda produces counterTpropaganda, and the minds of the younger generation,brought up in an age and atmosphere of bitter hostility to England, wouldrespond far more readily to propaganda directed against us. He said that hecould not do more than once again emphasise his advice that the best course forus lay 1(a) in accepting such help as he could give within the limits of neutrality, aneutrality genuinely friendly to us;(b) arming his forces to make Eire secure against German invasion and toenable him to co-operate fully with us to that end.I said that the extension of a naval war to the Pacific might possibly bring up the question of the protection of Atlantic convoys in a form necessitatingsome joint approach by America to Eire. He would have to weigh his answer to that approach very carefully. At this point Mr. de Valera showed consider-able nervous excitement and exclaimed &quot;Let it be clearly understood that the answer to any such approach would be a plain &apos; No ! &apos; Eire has the right to choose her own way. She did not start the war, nor does she wish to get into it.The war was caused by the blunders of the Great Powers. I have seen oppor-tunities missed, but the little Powers could do nothing. Why should Eire suffer?If there is a conflagration, why should she be thrown into the fire? &quot;He added that any attempt by a Great Power to bring pressure on Eire orto force her into the war by making demands upon her which would lead to herbecoming involved would be a reprehensible act; it would be to commit a wrong.If such violence were perpetrated and here he rose to his feet in great agita-tion &quot; Then, then, my course would be clear.  Then I should know what to do.&quot;I said that the half of the world which really mattered looked to a very different answer from Ireland, and that it was my belief that Ireland would readily respond to a different lead. I had often wondered whether the name of de Valera would finally be associated with a vendetta or a Cause. He said thatif Ireland ever entered the war it would be as a reaction to external aggression.Comment-The fact is that, though Mr. de Valera might lead the countryin a different direction, he has now made it plain beyond all possibility of doubt.andl without need of further probings that he does not wish to do so and that american influence does not move him from his familiar technique or from Jus-old prejudices.
We must therefore go on persevering with the situation here, the plus factorsof which are &apos;(a) a genuinely friendly neutrality which shows itself in various usefulways;(b) denial of the coast and territory of Eire to Germany for serious activitiesinimical to us;(c) assurance that a German attempt at invasion will be resisted by theunited country in full liaison with our forces.In applying economic pressure to Eire we must always bear in mind its effecton these plus factors.The minus factors are : (a) Mr. de Valera&apos;s refusal to consider any suggestion of voluntarilyaffording strategic assistance;(b) Mr. de Valera&apos;s personal determination to resist any attempt to securefacilities by physical force or show of force.The problems to be considered in this latter connection are (a) the extent to which he could rally national forces behind him to opposeAmerica and England.(b) the opportunity which such a development would afford to the Germansfor coming to his assistance and making Eire a centre of sabotageand espionage, or even a base against us.Clearly, if the question of seizing strategic facilities by force comes to the forefront we must consider well beforehand the extent and leadership of the forces which would rally to us rather than to the de Valera standard, and also whether we should lose more by an upheaval in Ireland than we should gain from the possession of bases on the western seaboard.If we finally determine that facilities on the west coast of Ireland must bein our hands at all costs, the first step must be to lay before the Eire Governmentand people a clear proposal of what we will do for them. If we split the country by an offer first our position will not be so bad if later we have to split them by a threat.J. L. MAFFEY.December 24, 1941.


</content>
</cab>
