<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/165/23 images: 308-310</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CIVIL LIABILITY FOR PERSONAL INJURYMemorandum by the Lord Chancellor andthe Secretary of State for Social services. At its meeting on 7 July the Home and Social Affairs committee agreed that an inquiry should be instituted into the basis of liability for personal injury.2. The Robens Committee on Safety and Health at Work (Cmnd. 5034)had recommended an inquiry in the field of employers1 liability.     were recognised that any inquiry would at least have to extend to road accidentsand that it was questionable whether it would be possible to draw the linethere.    We were then concerned to ensure that the inquiry did not lead toa recommendation for a State scheme, which could prove very expensiveeven though the benefits to the injured person would probably be inadequate,and which might have to include provision for disablement resulting fromcongenital conditions or disease.    Departmental discussions proceededon this basis, but led to the conclusion that it would be difficult to defend a  proposal for an inquiry limited to accidents at work and on the road.3. Public and Parliamentary concern for the thalidomide victims hasled us to review the position.    We have concluded that in presentconditions we cannot avoid instituting an inquiry into the basis of liability for injury, caused in whatever way by the action of another person(eg by an accident at work or on the road, or by the administration of adrug or other dangerous thing).    We recognise that no change in the lawcan have any effect on the position of the thalidomide children, for whomany relief would have to be sought in other directions.    An additionaldifficulty in the thalidomide cases is that it is by no means clear whether there is any legal liability for injury caused to an unborn person.4. Although for the reasons already given we would not support aState insurance scheme, we believe that we have more to lose than gain bypreventing any inquiry from considering this possibility.    We are, however,reasonably confident that a well-chosen Royal Commission - for we thinkthat nothing else would do justice to the major problems involved - wouldbe satisfied by sound evidence that any scheme providing for compensationwithout the need to prove negligence should be supported by privateinsurance and not by the State.1C ftCP(72) 123 COPY NO     0 014 November 1972CABINET
5. The Committee agreed that a Royal Commission should beappointed to consider whether any changes are desirable in the basisof liability for personal injury caused by the action of another person and invited the Lord Chancellor in consultation with the ministers primarily concerned to consider terms of reference and membership of the Commission, as well as its staffing.6. We seek the Cabinet&apos;s agreement to the conclusions of the Homeand Social Affairs Committee.    There is strong all-Party support inthe House for Mr Jack Ashley&apos;s Motion which asks for a State insurancescheme to compensate for personal injury.    It is desirable that anannouncement of a decision should not be long delayed, although in announcing our decision to set up a Royal Commission we must, ofcourse, make it clear that this does not commit us to a State scheme.H. of St. M.K lord Chancellors Office13 November 1972


</content>
</cab>
