<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 102-107</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*nt Is the Property of      &quot;,/v  &quot;u  1  70           MINISTRY  OF  RECONSTRUCTION.           ADVISORY COUNCIL -SECTION II.  port upon the Second part of the Second reference.To the Rt. Ron. Sir Auckland Geddes, K.C.B., M.P.            Minister of Reconstruction.Sir,       A report has already been presented to your predecessorDr. Addison, on the first part of the second reference to thissection of the Advisory Council, in which report suggestions were given for framing legislation In prevention cf &quot;dumping&quot;.The Second part of the reference, which the Section consideredwould be best dealt with separately, was as follows&apos;&apos;To consider what steps,  if any,  should be taken to give  effect to the view of Lo?5d Balfour of Burleigh&apos;s Committee that the producers of this country  are entitled to  be protected in their home marked against the introduction of &quot;sweated goods&quot;, that is  to say goods produced by labour, which is not paid at Trade Union  rates of wages.,, where such exist in the country cf  origin of the goods, or current  rates of that country, if xhere are no Trade Union rates.11        The question involved in this second part of the reference has been examined by a small Committee of this Sectionof the Advisory Council, consisting of Sir Henry Birchenough,K.C.M.G., Chairman, Mr. E. Bevin, and Mr. J.J. Malion.   ThisCommittee has had the advantage of the collaboration of sir arthur steel-Iviaitland, M.P., Parliamentary Under-Secretaryfor the Department of Overseas Trade, who was invited by theChairman to assist the Committee in framing a workable schemeto give effect to the recommendation contained iyi the Reportof Lord Balfour of Burleigh&apos;s Committee.        The Committee after careful consideration of theproblem unanimously endorses the view expressed by lord balfour of BurleighJs Committee as to the desirability of
fxpreventing the^importation-ol^sweated -goods-in-tc this oountryfrom abroad.   The following suggestions are accordingly putforward for creating  a  simple machinery which,  in the view ofthe Committee, would  be of  the most  suitable kind to ensure the desired result and might also be made use  of for other similarpurposes.   It would  also help to give life and reality to the conception of a  League  of Nations in a sphere in which apractical application of that conception would  appear to be mostsuitably and easily begun.        To attain the objects in view we recommend  the appoint-ment of- Labour Attaches or  Commissioners,  who would be BritishGovernment officials  attached to British Embassies  andLegations in foreign  countries,, and  would  occupy in regard to labour questions an analogous position to  that  hold by theCommercial Attaches in  regard to questions of trade.   It wouldbe the duty of these  offloops to acquaint  themselves with labour movements and  conditions in -the country  to which theywere accredited, and  to supply the appropriate  Departments ofState with accurate general information relating to wages andother conditions in different trades, and  as  to labour legis-lation or experiments in dealing with&apos;industrial problems inforeign-countries.        In addition to  these regular officials,  specialCommissioners possessing high training and qualificationsmight from time  to time be  required  for particular  enquiriesje.g. into the conditions prevailing  in a particular tradesuspected of being a  &quot;sweated&apos;1 industry.    In this  connection the establishment of&apos;a  League of Nations ought  materially toassist in attaining the purposes we  have In view.   If such a league is&apos; established,  these  special Commissioners  might either be officials of  the British Government  or  of  the Central Bodyor Committee established by the League  of  Nations.
        We also recommend the establishment, of a strong AdvisoryCommittee of representatives of employers and workers includ-ing persons possessing knowledge of and able to give an authoritative opinion upon Labour conditions abroad.   ThisCommittee would be attached to the Department of Crovernmenton which the new machinery would be dependent, and it isconsidered that the future development of the scheme should be largely in the hands of this Committee.The manner in which this machinery would work,        In regard to the Restriction of the importation of&quot;sweated&quot; goods - which would be only one part of the functionsof the machinery.outlined above - the procedure would be asfollows         Some Interested persons or body in this country:-e.g. an Employers&apos; Association, Trade Council or Trade Union -would make a complaint to the Board of Trade (or otherDepartment) that &quot;sweated&quot; goods were being imported intothis country upon an appreciable scale, and would produceevidence that this was the case.   If a prlma facie casewere established, the Foreign Office would at the request of theBoard of Trade or other Department notify the Government of thecountry affected, and, if instituted, the appropriate Departmentof the League of Nations, that sweating was believed upon l.evidence to exist in a particular trade in a particular countryand that it was proposed either to exclude the goods in question or to impose a &quot;special&quot; duty upon them after the lapse of acertain period, e.g., six months, unless it were proved to the satisfaction of an investigating Commissionert preferably aCcnmissloner of the League of Nations, that tho conditions ofproduction were satisfactory.        The Government of the country complained against wouldthen be requested to afford every facility to the investigating
       Commissioner for making an accurate and full report upon the       facts of the case.   Facilities would either be given and after.       report -* and after el Vina the country comol&amp;ined against an       opportunity of reply in case of an adverse report - appropriate       action would be taken, or, if facilities were withheld, the case       would go by default against the country complained against, and       the importation of the goods in question would be subjected to       an appropriate regime of restriction or prohibition.               Vie reco amend that in any Convention laying down the       principles of international equality of commercial treatment?tant.                                &apos;    &apos;       an analogous provision be made to that introduced to meet the       case of &quot;dumping&apos;,&apos; so that discriminatlon in the circumstances       mentioned above may not be held to be an infraction of such       equality of treatment.       Advantages of action through a League of Nations,               .Among the advantages of dealing with the matter through a       Body set up by a League of Nations would be the following:-               The procedure would be more open and honest, and less       likely than any other to lead to international friction: the       case for        . excluding or taxing differentially the alleged       sweated goods would not be judged entirely by one of the parties       to the action, but in concern with an independent tribunal: the       matter could be discussed and considered in the light of world       conditions and in a broader and more generous spirit than would       be possible if it were merely a matter of negotiation between       country &quot;A&quot; and country &quot;B&quot;: the simultaneous or joint action       of several countries in excluding sweated goods in any established       case would be facilitated:and the machinery proposed would be       along tho most progressive and hopeful line of political       development.       The carrying out of the regime in details               In regard to the carrying out in. detail of the treatment       contemplated the Committee has considered the question as  to
whether it would be feasible to blacklist particular firmsproducing under &quot;sweating1 conditions, or whether it would benecessary to apply prohibition or restriction to the whole trade of a particular country in a specified article, if an appreciableproportion of the production of that trade could be shown to be&quot;sweated&quot;.   It was pointed cut in regard to this that ;&apos;sweatlng&quot;is essentially a thing of which individual firms arc guilty.Two firms may produce an article at tho same price, and one maypay good wages, and the other bad wages: the selling pricedepending largely on management and specialisation.   TheCommittee is of opinion that it is a matter for furtherconsideration whether a practically effective machinery crv ba ,devised for excluding the products of particular &quot;sweating&quot;firms by a system of blacklisting, or whether it would benecessary, if an appreciable proportion of the Importation of anyparticular article of a particular country is proved to beproduced, under &quot;sweating&quot; conditions, to apply the regimeadopted generally to all importations of that article from thecountry In question.   It might possibly be found that the lattermethod possess its advantages and that the threat of su^h ageneral prohibition would provide an effective inducement to theGovernment of the offending country to take action to remedy theconditions complained of by legislation or otherwise.        The Committee suggests that the proposals embodied inthis report might with advantage be included In the economicand industrial questions now being considered by the Paris PeaceConference with a view, to their discussion and to elicit theviews of our Allies in regard to them.   It Is thought that sucha favourable opportunity for at any rate a preliminary discussion of the scheme might not soon recur, and alsothat the suggestions contained in the report provide in
themselves, a contribution to the discussion of the directions in which a League &quot;of Nations may be made a political reality,providing a machinery for performing certain work of general interest more smoothly and efficiently than would be possible by previously existing methods of diplomatic action-.                                                   t                    We are, Sir,                      Your obedient Servant,HENRY BIRCHENOUGHy&apos; ChairmanRv BEVINJ. J. MA LLC N.Secretary  IB.  PERKYIQttu February, 1919,-6-

</content>
</cab>
