<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 303-304</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                    014/19.                                            Cpnfldential.                 BI3S1&apos;BIC5?I0MS ON CLU3S.Observations by the Central Control Board (Liquor raffle).                 It has &quot;boon a principle of the Board from the       first,in placing restrictions on  the sale and supply of       intoxicating liquor, to treat licensed premises and clubs       alike.   The limitation of hours  and other conditions       prescribed have been imposed upon both in identical terms.                 It has been universally recognised that the       unqualified application of this principle has served both       to make the system of control efficient and to prevent the       sense of grievance  which under differential treatment       would have been felt by frequenters of licensed premises on       the one hand or by the users of clubs on the other.                 It should therefore be. accepted as axiomatic, and       it should be plainly stated, that the removal or modifica-       tion of the drink restrictions as regards clubs must pro-       cee^ P&amp;ri passu with their removal or modification as       regards licensed premises.                 It has never been contemplated that the restriction-       tions imposed under the liquor Control Regulations should be       withdrawn immediately on the cessation of hostilities.   The       Defence of the Realm (Amendment)  (Mo. 3) Act, 1915, makes       provision for the continuance of those Regulations &quot;during       the continuance of the present war and such period not       exceeding twelve months thereafter as may be declared by       Order in Council to be necessary in view of conditions       connected with the termination of the present war&quot;,    he                                                         drink/
drink restrictions, whether those imposed by the central control Board or those imposed by the Pood Controller,cannot all be removed, simultaneously and immediately.Additions to the supply of beer and spirits have very recently been announced.   Modifications of the control board&apos;s Orders as regards hours of sale and other matterswill, it may be expected, be announced shortly, and theBoard believe that in this way, even though the cry forthe indiscriminate removal of restrictions may not be met,the best public opinion can be satisfied and the realinterests of national efficiency served.   The preferentialexemption of clubs would be resented not only by thelicensed trade, but by the vast mass of the population which relios for its intoxicating liquor on licensed pre-mises rather than on clubs, and would in fact produce morefriction and agitation than it would allay.5. R6. 19.

</content>
</cab>
