<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 401-408</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                      Colonel Dally  j0ne[This Dooixmeaafe is  he j^^f^ ^ Slis  Britannic  Majestys (^veiameatjPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1919.SECRET.G.T.-6951.6th Minutes.0WAR  CABINET.UNEMPLOYMENT AND STATE  OF TRADE CONFERENCES.Minutes of a Conference  of  Ministers held  at 2, Whitehall  Gardens, S.W., on                    Wednesday, March 5, 1919, at 1 P.M.                        Present:The Right Hon. Sir A. C. GEDDES, K.C.B., M.P. (in the Chair).The  Right  Hon.  The  Lord  EMMOTT,  G.C.M.G-., G.B.E., Director of War Trade  Department.Mr. H. T. BUTLER, War Trade Department.Mr.  C.  B.  HARMSWORTH,   M.P.,  Joint  Parliamentary Under-Secretary  to  the  Foreign Office.Mr. W. C. BRIDGEMAN, M.P., Parliamentary  Secretary to the Board of Trade.Mr. S. J. CHAPMAN, C.B.E., Board of Trade.Mr. G. J. HIGGINSON, Restriction of Enemy  Supplies Department.Mr. J. R. BROOKE, Ministry of Food.Mr. A. F. PAUL,  Royal Commission on  Wheat Supplies.Mr. J. B. LINDON, War Trade Intelligence - Department.Mr. W. J. GLENNY, Department of  Over-  seas Trade.Mr. G. C. UPCOTT, Treasury.Mr. G. W. CHRYSTAL,  Secretary, Ministry  of Reconstruction and National Service.Lieutenant-Colonel  G.  J.  S.  SCOVELL,  C.B.E., Ministry of  Reconstruction and  National Service.Lieutenant-Colonel L. STORR, C.B , Secretary.Mr. C. LITCHFIELD, Assistant Secretary.Captain A. L. SILVERWOOD-COPE, Assistant Secretary.Timber.               1. Mr. Chapman referred to the timber question, and said that the                 Board of Trade had announced that the control would be removed                 at the end of March, but they were not clear if this would  include                 import restrictions.                     The Chairman said that timber would come-under paragraph (a)                 of the decision in Minute 6 of the proceedings of the 4th Meeting,                 and therefore there would be no import restrictions on it.    2. The Chairman referred to a telegram that had been forwarded to him by the Prime Minister from the British Chamber of Commerce,complaining of the restrictions on British trade in the Near East.    Mr. Harmsworth, referring  particularly  to Roumania, said  thatsuch restrictions had been removed;  he understood, however,  thatPublicity regardingKe3trictions on trade in the NearLast.
Roumania, for the  purpose  of exercising control over the kinds of Icommnditii s  to  be  imported  was  proposing  to  impose  import Iregulations.     The  Chairman said that  the position was  that  the  British (IChamber of Commerce were objecting to the presence of restrictions Ithat had already been removed, and he asked Mr. Chapman whether, Ithe Board of Trade were carrying out the decision  arrived- at in minute 6 of the.proceedings of the 5th Meeting.    Mr. Chapman  said  that the question of publicity was beingcarefully considered, and announcements were being prepared.    At the request of the Chairman,  Mr. Chapman  undertook togive special attention to  seeing that the removal of the restrictionsreferred to in the telegram from  the British Chamber of Commercewere given full publicity, and  to expedite generally  the  carryingout of  the  policy of publicity.Restrictions on          3.  With reference  to Minute 5  of the  proceedings  of  the exports.           5th Meeting, the  Conference further considered the Report of the                  Sub-Committee on the subject.                      The  Chairman  said  that, leaving  blockade countries aside for                  the moment, the question which came before them was as to whether                  exports could be free except as regards :                       1.  Goods required for naval and military purposes.                      2.  Goods wtich are or will be required for home consumption or                             home manufactures.                      3.  Goods which are or have been directly or indirectly benefited                             by a subsidy or guarantee.                      He then read  to  the Conference extracts from letters which                  showed clearly that  there was considerable apprehension existing at                  the present time in British trade circles regarding the export of wool                  and cotton.   Large  stocks were at present held  by British traders of                  manufactured woollen goods, which they could not dispose of owing                  to the export  restrictions.    They were in danger  of having to                  sacrifice a large part of their  stocks on,a falling market in order to                  realise sufficient cash to pay what they owed.   If export restrictions                  were removed at once, toey could dispose of their high-priced goods                  abroad without loss, whereas,  if the restrictions  were maintained                  until the  autumn, many houses would  have to sell in this country at                  such a loss that they could not continue btisiness.                      Mr.  Harmsworth said that, about a month previously, a new                  Free List had been submitted to the Superior Council-of&quot;Blockade in                  Paris, and that he had no indication as to what had happened.  With                  regard  to the report of  Lord emmott&apos;s  Sub-Committee, he stated                  that he and  his advisors  had considered  it, and they agreed that a                  large number of articles referred to  should be  unrestricted, subject to                  the concurrence (in the  case  of  some  of  the  more important                  article^)  of  our  Allies,  and  the  naval  and  military authorities.                  They had  not considered  each  item scientifically.   Apart from the                  undesilability of ceasing  to  back up  our friends  and giving equal                  facilities  to  our enemies, one of the  results of taking independent                  action would be that our Allies would  prepare Free Lists  of their                  own, and so the blockade machinery would  rapidly be broken up.                  As an  example, he  said that if we removed the restrictions on the                  export  of manufactured  cotton goods,  there  was a danger  that                  America would immediately claim  the right to export raw cotton,                  which was one of  the ingredients of explosives.   He urged that the
removal of the blockade should not be hurried, seeing that it wayimprobable that  any great increase would be effected thereby in theBritish export trade, while, by so doing, we ran the risk of sacrificingthe attainment of some  of the objects for which the war had been undertaken.  So far as he knew, the ration allowed to neutrals underthe blockade was amply adequate  to meet their requirements.    Lord Emmott maintained  that  the ration allowed was, in somecases  at  any rate,  ridiculously small, and  that the effect  of ourpresent policy was that neutrals were  being compelled to  startmanufacturing articles which they had  formerly obtained from ua.He stated that  he believed that the ration  of cotton goods allowedto Holland at present was only one-third of their pre-war imports.He did not think  that if we removed  restrictions on the export of manufactured  cotton  goods,  America would  insist on being allowedto export  raw cotton.   He doubted whether Germany was dependenton raw cotton for the manufacture  of explosives, since that commodityhad not  been allowed to go  into Germany for the  last 3^ years ofthe war.   In any case, Germany  would be  quite unable to financeany large importation of raw cotton.   He  entirely  agreed that theproposals  of his  Sub-Committee must be laid before our Allies and before the naval and  military  authorities, but he felt that it was absolutely necessary for us to do something to steady Germany atthe present time, and he thought  that the best way of doing so wasto give her trade a chance.    Mr.  Higginson urged that if we too far relaxed our hold on goods  imported  by Germany, we might be faced with a state ofaffairs that Germany  might  refuse  to  accede to our peace  terms.The possibility of further bloodshed was unthinkable, and therefore we could only enforce our  terms by economic pressure, which  itwould be  almost impossible to exert if the blockade were lifted.  he further pointed out that it was extremely probable that large privateGerman  credits  had been established in neutral countries, and thatthese  credits  would be used  by Germany to obtain commoditiesplaced on the Free List.    Mr.  Harmsworth said that, once  we had removed the blockade,we could not possibly reimpose  it.   He hoped that the  blockadewould only last  for two  or three  months longer, and by removing it now  we  should only  achieve very small results, which could not justify tiie risks  which we should  be running.    Lord  Emmott  urged, on the contrary,  that something must hedone  to  get  our trade going, and s,iid that, so long as restrictions were  maintained  and  the   necessity for  obtaining licences were continued, trade would not be in a position to How freely.    Sir  A. King  pointed out  that it was  not proposed to abolishList &quot;C&quot; altogether; in any case, though reduced,  it would still bein existence, and therefore the machinery of blockade must  to someextent be kept going.    4. The Chairman raised the question whether it was desirableto trade with the Germans, in view of the fact that they were notin a position to pay.  He recalled  the  conclusion arrived at by theConference at a  previous meeting.   It  was advantageous  to thiscountry from a financial point of view to export articles to  neutral countries, who would pay us for them, and allow them to make whatterms they liked with the Germans on reselling  the goods.    Mr.  Higginson  deprecated  any  policy  of trading with theGermans through neutrals surreptitiously, but he agreed that, if the
blockade restrictions were withdrawn and articles were  transferredto a Free List, then it  was certainly  preferable to deal with  theGermans through a neutral market.     The Chairman expressed the view that whether we wished it ornot, the only method by which we could trade with Germany at  thepresent time, would be through neutrals.   During the past 4\ years,our traders had  severed  all connection with German  traders, and,even if they wanted to do so, months would elapse before they couldreopen direct  communication.   He  thought that,  if  the blockadewere withdrawn, and we thus entered into trading  communicationwith neutrals, it would be at least three months before  any goodsdespatched from this country would percolate into Germany.     Mr.  Chapman said that he thoroughly  agreed  with  this  view,and  added that  there was another consideration, namely, that,  byreopening trade with neutrals, we should &quot;enable our manufacturers to start work at once.                                   *  ,     Mr.  Lindmi, in connection with the question of the rapid perco-lation  of commodities  to Germany,  pointed out that America hadexported  ten years&apos;  supply of malt to Denmark in the  space of amonth, and  that,  no doubt, this large supply was destined, in due course, to go to  Germany.   It was conceivable that a similar situa-tion might arise in regard to other commodities.  He mentioned that america  now issued  their own export, licences against cable  advicesand  guarantees, and that we were handicapped in competing with america, inasmuch as we  made it a principle that the guarantee mustagree with the application.     Mr.  Broulte uaid that he thought lack  of shipping would prove to be a great obstacle in  the way of  reviving our export  trade.   Asregards  food,  he  thought  that  foodstuffs,  if we  exported them,would  reach  Germany  in  a much  shorter  period than  threemonths.     Lord Emmott raised the question of doing business with occupied territories.  It  had been mentioned to him that day, and he felt thatit was undesirable that this should be done through  the  machineryof the Netherlands Overseas Trust.     Mr.  Harmsworth agreed.     It was decided that      Goods destined for  the occupied parts of Germany should  not         necessarily be consigned through the Netherlands OverseasKecommendatioriB        5. The Conference then proceeded to consider the recommenda-by Lord Emmott&apos;s    tions put forward by Lord Emmott&apos;s Sub-Committee as regards theSub-Committee.     transference of certain commodities  from Lists &quot;A&quot;  and b &quot; to                  List &quot; C.&quot;(a.) Dyes.              In the course of a long general discussion, reference was made                  to a proposal to keep dyes on List &quot; A &quot;  at present,  because of the                  present shortage in this country.                      The  Chairman  said  that he  thought that, except in  so far as                  food was  concerned,  it should be accepted as a principle that the vague                  possibility of shortage at a future date should not be  considered a                  reason for maintaining restrictions on the export of a  commodity at                  the present time.   He considered that the dye  question  required                  further examination.   It  seemed most undesirable to  retain the                  products  of a new industry solely  for domestic  use and  so prevent                  them getting a footing in foreign  markets.
(b.) Oils.               The question of technical  oils  was  raised, and  Mr. Brooke                  explained that at the  present  time the  Government  is the sole                  importer of oil seed.   They supplied the seed to the mills by which                  the oil was extracted  and they again supplied the crude oil to  the                  refiners for preparation.   He said that at present we were supplying                  to manufacturers at prices below the cost price.   If oil were to  be                  transferred to List &quot; F,&quot; then  we must  charge a different price  on                  supplies intended for export from the price of supplies  intended for                  home  consumption, and  this would,involve elaborate machinery.                      Lord Emmott drew  attention to the fact that we  must beware                  of the possibility of the United States of America cutting in and                  offering supplies at a price below that at which we ourselves were                  offering.                      Mr.  Brooke  took  oil,  which  we  had  accumulated for   the                  manufacture of glycerine for explosives, as an example to show.that                  if we  liquidated  our  stocks below  tiie post-war normal price,  we                  should stop  importation.   He added  that  the Food Ministry found                  difficulty in  fixing  the  prices hi many cases, because  the proper                  prices could not  be discovered  without offering supplies  for auction                  in the market; and as this  procedure would  have to be applied to                  each several commodity, a lot of  time must necessarily elapse before                  such experiments could be completed.                      The Chairman drew Mr. Brookes attention to the  decision with                  regard to raw materials held by Government, and said  that it laid                  down  a clear policy as applicable to  ihe transactions of  the Ministry                ,  of Food as to those of the Ministry of Supply, for example.                      Mr. Brooke  said that he was working on the policy defined in                  that decision. c.) Fruit        -      rr^g question of the fruit trade was raised, and The Chairmari                  read  a letter from  the Chancellor  of the  Exchequer, in  which                  Mr. Chamberlain stated that, owing to the  state of the Spanish                  exchange at the  present time, we  should, in his opinion, hesitate                  before doing  anything which  would  tend  to  increase  our financial                  obligation to Spain.                      The Chairman, however, observed that this  objection need  not                  apply  to the entrepdt trade in fruit.                      Mr.  Brooke  said that  stocks, especially  of citrous  fruits, were                  being  held up iii  this country on  the chance of export being allowed.                  Sellers hoped that, if export were allowed,  they could obtain  better                  prices for their stocks in northern neutral markets.  He explained                  that whatever arrangement were made with regard to the import of                  Spanish oranges, must be applied in  the  case of the import of Italian                  oranges.  If we allowed Spanish  oranges to be re-exported from this                  country to Norway,  we must allow  Italy to export some of her                  oranges to Norway direct.  The effect of this would  be that  we                  should get a smaller supply of  Italian  oranges.                      Mr.  Chapman said  that he wished  especially to emphasise the                  fact that the whole question of the restoration of there-export trade                  required investigation.   This trade, he said, was at the  present time                  practically dead,  whereas it used  to be  a most important  trade,                  employing directly and indirectly numbers  of  people.  The present                  prohibition on  re-export did not i-elate  solely to restricted imports,                  but also  to others.   For instance,  the  prohibition  of  re-expurt  of                  cotton was retained to keep down purchases from United States of                  America (and so  protect United  States  of America exchanges).    It                  was presumed that the re-exports would  not have  a  beneficial effect                  on other exchanges  in  a  degree  that would make  up  for  the      [1205]-316                                                       C
detrimental effect on the United  States of America exchanges.  Ifthere was some gain from this purely as exchange  policy, there hadto be set up against it the great damage that was being done to theeconomic interests of this country.     The Chairman said his intention was to submit recommendationsof policy in regard to the restrictions on  exports with the followingends in view :      (a.)  1 o get the biggest possible Free List at once ;     (6.)  To get  as  many manufactures as possible transferred from           Lists &quot;A&quot; and &quot; 13 &quot; to List &quot; C.&quot;     It was agreed     That the possibility of  future shortage of manufactures should         not  be sufficient reason  for retaining restrictions on the         export of any particular commodity  at the present time.     6.  Mr Lindon raised the question as to what bearing the &quot; BlackList &quot; would  have on the matter.     Lord Emmott said it was part of the blockade machine.  Theremoval of it would, of course, help Germany to get her trade back;he couLI not say that there was any particular outstanding reasonfor retaining the &apos;; Black List,&quot; and it had to be remembered that theFrench and Italians were precluded by their laws from trading withGermany.     Mr. Harmsworth said that before removing the &quot; Black List&quot; itwould be necessary to consult  the Allies, and  he  thought that thequestion ought first  to be  considered as to whether those who hadbeen our enemies should have the same facilities for trading as thosewho had been iriendly to us.     Mr. Higginson thought that if trading were going to be allowedwith Germany, it would be  much better for the Allies to come to adecision upon that point immediately.   He  pointed out  that  the&quot; Black List&quot;  applied  not  only to German  traders  in  foreigncountries,  but that it had a direct  economic  effect on the firms inGermany who had established branch houses abroad.    Mr.  Butler said that the question  of the &quot;Black List&quot; had,been recently discussed in Paris, and that it was intended to  reducethe number of names on  the list  in South America to 150.  The&quot;Black. List&quot; in South America  existed  rather for economic reasonsthan  for blockade reasons, and thus was different to  some extent tothe &quot; Black  List&quot; in the Northern neutral countries, which includednames added both for economic and  blockade reasons.  He said thathe did not think we could abolish the  &quot; Bl*ck  List&quot;  in  SouthAmerica without abolishing also  the &quot; Black List&quot; in Europe.  TheFrench and.Italians were prevented by their laws from trading with persons or firms  of enemy nationality, and France and Italy looked to us not to let them down by removing restrictions which  could notbe removed in those countries until  peace was signed.   He addedthat the whole question  was  really a matter for the Foreign trade department of the Foreign Office.     The Chairman  asked  whether  maintenance  of the  &quot;BlackList &quot; was really hampering British  trade at the present time.     Mr.  Butler said that he thought it  was, but not to  any verygreat extent.  During the war British traders had broken off connec-tion with Black List firms, and, if the list were abolished, our traders
 would  not be  able,  even  if  they wished  to do so,  to  reopen.&apos; business at  once.   Whenever  British firms had  been advised  or compelled  to give up trade with undesirable neutral  firms, the names of desirable firms to take the place of the former customers had,  as far as possible, been supplied  by the Foreign Trade  Department and. the Department of Overseas Trade.  He said that American firms were anxious to reopen connection with foreign firms, and as they had been in touch with &quot; Black List&quot; firms more recently than British. firms had,  he thought-that the&apos; removal of the &quot; Black List&quot; would. help American  traders  more than ours.  The removal of the list would,  it  was  true, enable  a  certain  amount of  goods to go  to Scandinavia  which were at present held  up in this country, but  it had been the policy of his Department, prior to the imposition of the restrictions under the list,  to  recommend  our traders  to dispose elsewhere  of goods  sold  to  &quot; Black  List&quot;   firms,  so  that he thought that very  little stuff  was in fact  being  held up  on this account.     The Chairman  raised the question whether all American firms were as scrupulously avoiding trading with &quot; Black  List &quot; firms, and whether it was  possible, if they wished to do so, for American firms to export goods to &quot; Black List&quot; firms in South America.     Mr. Butler said that he  did not think this was the case, because, first of all,  licences  had  to  be obtained  from  the  American Government before the goods could be  exported, and the American Government had  agreed not  to issue  licences to export to &quot; Black. List&quot; firms; and, secondly, because if any cases had arisen of goods thus  being  illegitimately   exported,   we  should  have  received information  from  our consuls.   As  to the question whether the removal of  the &quot; Black List&quot; would  benefit  British  traders,  he remarked  that  if the List were removed, &quot;Black List&quot; firms  would now be in a  position to obtain  goods at the present prices, whereas other firms who had placed  their orders previously would probably have to pay the old price in force at the time of giving the  order, which would have been higher than the present price.  This might cause  trouble  with  British Exporters,  as firms who  were not formerly on the  &quot;Black List&quot; might wish to  cancel orders when they found &quot; Black List&quot; firms  getting goods at a lower price and at a not much better delivery date.     Mr. Chapman asked  if  a  decision  on this question could  be postponed to a  subsequent meeting, as he was anxious to consult the President  of the Board of Trade on the question.     The Chairman decided, in view of the facts stated by Mr. Butler as to the drastic reduction of the list for South America     . That it was not necessary for the Conference to take  action in.         this matter.General Policy          7- With regard to the general policy to be adopted in respect ofregarding Exports,   our export  trade, it was decided that                       (A.) In  the case of exports to  countries not included in the                  blockade area, there should be no restriction, except as regards                       (1.)  Goods required for naval and  military purposes.                      (i^.)  Goods which are, or will be, required  for home consumption                             or home manufactures.                      (3.)  Goods  which  are,  or have  been, directly  or  indirectly                             benefited by a subsidy or guarantee.
     (B.)  Subject to the above, the policy to be adopted by Depart- ments, with a view to the removal  of export  restrictions in the case of blockade countries, should be-     (a.) To  establish an efficient  contact  between  themselves for           purposes of preparing the  details of the  proposals to be           pressed by the  British delegates on the  appropriate           Inter-Allied bodies.     (b.) The  general policy which  is to guide them in preparing           details is                 (1.) The maximum  number of manufactured goods                      to be included in the Free List.                (2.) Of the remaining manufactured articles, as many                      as possible to be included in List &quot; C.&quot;                (3.) It is in the interest of  this country to have the                      restrictions on exports to neutral countries in                      the blockade areas removed, full consideration                      being given to the  fact that it will take at                      least  one month, and  possibly three months,                      for  any  manufactured  goods  ordered  by                      neutrals,  after   removal   of  the  blockade                      restriction, to reach  Germany in any material                      quantity.                (4.) All possible steps should be taken with a view                      to stimulation of the entrepot trade.     Mr. Chapman urged that, when making  any  announcement asregards the removal of restrictions, we should aim at saying what may not be exported rather than what may be exported.(Initialled)    A. C. G.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,       March 6, 1919.o

</content>
</cab>
