<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 414-429</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                     (d       /?-/-(&apos; This Document \s the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty^ Government         Z$          There was a decided improvement in the weather last week.In the Western and Korth Wsstern crunties and in Anglesey mild sunnydays with frosty nights weis expsnsucod throughout the week.   luother parts of the country. however,  the weather was changeable,mild dry days alternating with days of fog, rain, sleet or snow.A considerable area of low-lying land in lines, and Hotts, is still under water.   The floods in Hunts, have gone dfMyn rapidly owing to four breaks in the Pens, and much good fen land has been flooded.          Ploughiiog lias been possible on some days of the weekpractically in ail counties., and goed progress has been made in thedrier districts.   In Ncrthants and Leicestershire activepreparations are being made for spring planting, but in Derby andWarwickshire the land is net yet dry enough for this purpose.Parm work generally is very much behindhand;  tho Commissioner forLines., Rutland and Notts, reports that the arrears of work,especially in the potato growing districts, have probably not beenequalled for a generation.          A fair aoreage of wheat has been sown in Lanes, andCheshire.   Winter corn is looking well, but beans in the Hid landshave suffered from the frost.   In South Westmorland the corn hasbeen burnt off several fields to enable them to be ploughed.                      Local Organisation Division,                Work of Agricultural Executive Copimitteea.      bort.-Term,Credit Scheme.   The Treasury have authorised anextension&quot;of this &quot;scheme up to 31st Larch, 1919, after which datethey suggest that it should terminateTheir view is that having&apos;regard to the very trifling extent to which recourse has been hadto the guarantors, the Banks might well bo expected to undertake the provision cf credit facilities as part cf their ordinary business.   The Board are in communication with the Bankers1Clearing House on the subject.          Returns have been received from Agricultural ExecutiveCommittees for the period from tiie commencement of the credit scheme up to 31st December, 1910, as follows:-           Applications approved - llo, C65.  Amount   70,375.           Loans repaid                               24,458           Loans outstanding or not taken up          46,417           Loans in arroar on 31st December, 1918     10,212          In regard to tho last figure it must be pointed out that although leans may be granted for a maximum period of two years the&quot;Banks are net willing to allow overdrafts in the first instancefor longer than 9 months,   Practically the whole- of the loans &quot;in arrear&quot; have been or will be renewed for a further period, and sofar the Board have only been called upon to make good theirguarantee to the extent of about  270, part of which it  is expectedwill be eventually recovered.     CuItivation of in arms .    A farm at Ohudleigh in Devon isreported by the Committee to be in a shameful condition  cf neglect,the owner being described as an-entixely useless member  of society and a disgrace to Devon farmijig.   Various cultivation orders have
benn served u^on him by the Committee but  without  avail.   Authorityto take possession of the lands and buildings (with the exception ofthe dwelling-house and cider manufacturing premises)  has accordingly been granted and the Committee will start  the work of cultivation atonce.     Determination of Tenancies.   In January 1915 the ExecutiveCommittee were authorised to take possession of the Ccolhurst I!state(717 acres) in &apos;.?est.....bus sex with a view to  using it as a school forsoldier ploughmen and for teaching- inexperienced soldiers generalfarm work.   The Committee are continuing  the work of bringing the estate&apos; into cultivation and havo now applied to tho Board todetermine the tenancy of one of the farms  (ill acres) on the estatewhich is not being cultivated in a husbandlike manner and which, inthe opinion of the Committee , will never under the present tenantcontribute its full share to tho food supply of the country.   TheBortrd have accordingly determined tho tenancy in accordance with thousual procedure under the Corn Production  (Amendment) Act, 1918.     Allotments.   In Larch 1918 the Cheshiro Committee tookpossession with the consent of the Board of 3 acres of land in the parish of bhavington-cum-Gresty and let it to the  Parish Councilconcerned for the purpose of allotments.   Owing to the great demandfor allotments in that parish the Committee have now been authorisedto take possession of a further acre of land belonging to the  sameowner which was not, according to reports  received by theDepartment, being used in the national interest;  this piece of land has also been let to the Parish Council for allotments.          In January the Committee with the authority of  the Boardtook possession of 12 acres of allotments  at Chedworth inGloucester shire the majority of which were in a neglected or disusedcondition.   The Committee now report that they have made arrange-ments with two adjoining farmers to cultivate the greater portion  ofthe land, the remainder being left in the  hands of those allotment holders who wore already cultivating their plots in a satisfactorymanner.          Under the Cultivation Of Lands Order various LocalAuthorities are taking steps to acquire 32 acres of land which, will.provide 395 allotments.   Under the Small  Holdings and AllotmentsAct 96* acres of land are being acquired in order to provide  848additional allotments.     Land Drainage.   Cambridgeshire . Serious breaches and  slipshave occurred in banks, principally on the Cam and the Soham Lode.The latter is under the jurisdiction of the kiddle Fen Commissioners,who had had the unsafe state of the banks brought to their  noticeduring the past three months, but had taken no adequate steps  to  dealwith the position.   A report on the district was made by theDepartment&apos;9 Drainage Inspector on November 28th, and was forwarded to the Commissioners.   On February 21st  information was received  of serious breaches and  floods, with which tho drainage authoritieswen- incapable  of  dealing, and the Cambridge shir-- Executive Committeewere authorised to  take whatever action thy  found possible to assistthose authorities  and to pr vent further  damage.   They sent theirdrainagf officer to th. locality;  he found that further breacheshad occurred  and that the drainage authority s had taken no stepseither to  stop  the breaches or to prevent  their repetition.   Theyrequested  the drainage officer to take charge of the work;   theservices of prisoners of war were obtained,  and on 27th february the situation was  well in hand;  the drainage officer hoped to havosucceeded  in  Q  or  9 days in  filling  the breaches.
                        Horticultural Division.     Fruit  and Honey  Section.  . Spraying demonstrations have been given  during  the week at  Aylsham, Last Dereham, Fakenham, HarJe-ftcni and  Stow  (Norfolk), at which the interest which has boon aroused in; fie  country has been  well sustained, and many questions havo been asked.          Up  to the present 26 counties have adopted the Bee Re- stocking  scheme, and  applications have been received through the Horticultural Sub-Committee for 215 Dutch stacks and 450 Italian Queens.   The total number of  beekeepers who have registered with the. Horticultural Sub-Committees for bee sugar is 7,042, representing 25,600 stocks in frame hives and 3,500 stocks in skeps          During the  past fortnight resolutions passed by 10 Horticultural Sub-Committees have been forwarded to the BoarcLiirging &apos; immediate legislative action to prevent the spreading $f the Isle of 7ight bee  disease.  Two counties, Salop and &quot;Wiltshire, have refused to  adopt tho  re-stocking scheme until such action has been taken.          The Board1s exhibit  of dried and bottled fruit is being shovj-n  at  the  Disabled llx-service lien&apos;s Exhibition at St, George&apos;s Hall,  Liverpool.          It  is reported  that  6  tons of  empty baskets have arrived from Holland.     Small  Live Stock.  ,  Several officers and men have been inter- viewed regarding instruction in poultry keeping.   It is hoped  to be able to  place them on  suitable farms for instruction.     Instructionjand  Advice.    The need of advice among commercial growers has been shown in the  Fastern Counties, where after demonstrations had been given  to small holders and allotment holders the  Divisional Inspector  was invited to visit and to give further demonstrations to nurserymen.   The Inspector reports that there is most urgent need for  instruction and advice on Intensive Cultivation from the  commercial point of view, the average Horticultural Instructor  being considered lacking in the necessary experience.          Inspections  of nurseries and allotments in Yorkshire have been carried  out, and demonstrations given to  small commercial growers,  who  appeared to  be quite ignorant of  the existence cf  the Boards pamphlets on  pruning and cultivation generally.   These men are  losing  money by keeping to bad methods of  cultivation.          The same ignorance has been found in many districts in the  lidlands, where disease among fruit bushes is very prevalent.          V/hile making enquiries as  to the acreage under glass  in North  *7ales,  one man  in Denbigh was  found who  had about  5,500 square feet of glass nearly  all  in a  deplorable condition, with some of the tomato plants still in the ground with diseased fruit hanging on them.   He  had used the  same  soil under glass  for about  20 years.     Rural  Industries.    An  interesting example of rural industry is  shown  in a report  which has just  come to hand of  the  working of the  Upton-on-Severn Branch of  the North Wales  Fruit  and  Vegetable Society.    This  Branch has subscribed up to December 31st  shareI capital to  the amount of   1,441, made up of 5,764  shares.   The total  weight  of  fresh produce  handled during the year was  795 tons, v/hile  during  the autumn  contracts were made for 530  tons of
[Vegetables  for  drying  purposes.   Produce has been  ooliected from rjer  BOO  producer,  including  the largest market gardener, and thellmallest  cottager, 10y tons  of blackberries were collected.   TheI output of the Preserving  Department  was  1,362 dozens of canned and bottled fruit and vegetables,  lli cwt. of grain, and 170 dozens ofIpickles.    The  net profit for  the year amounted to   1,355.15.5.                          Technipa1 Pi vi si on.      Inspection of Land.   An  inspection was made of Didlington Farm,i Norfolk,  the home lUrm of a  shooting estate acquired by a wealthy[banker shortly  before  the war.  The farm, comprising  1,320 acres,[fas let until Michaelmas ,  1916, when  the  tenure was  given up;  con-I eiderable portions were subsequently let separately, but until March11917  the  farm,  now reduced to  some 700 to 000 acres,  was unoccupied,[and but for tho intervention of  the  Agricultural Executive CommitteeI might have  remained  so indefinitely.  An order requiring the cultiva- tion of a certain acreage was  served on  the owner;   the land was broken 1jup and sown, drought supervened, and the operations resulted in a  ccn*  I siderable financial  loss.   As regards 1918 the owner  agroed to continue  cultivation to the  best of  his  ability,  and seems  to have[tried honourably to  meet  the wishes  of the  Committee;   but the  seasoniwas again dry,  and  further lot;s was  sustained.    This  yeae the  owner[declines to carry out  in full  the  Committee&apos;s recommendations unless\ he is served with an order a3  a  safe-guard  against  undue  fi:o?,neiai,!loss.   The Committee  are unwilling  to  issue  an  order, and while they are not anxious to  take the  farm over,  they have  approached  the Board for advice on  the matter, as they  consider  that  in  the national&apos; interest ;and as an example to the  neighbourhood  it  should  be cultivated  to  the fullest extent.           The  farm  consists of 537 acres arable  land,  200 acres park ;iand, and 200-300 acres unreclaimed  heath.    Of the arable  land, 165 acres are classed as &quot;good&quot;, 202 acres  &quot;poor&quot;,  and  170 aores &quot;very poor&quot;.   The arable  land is generally  clean,  and the &quot;good&quot;  land has produced satisfactory coops of all  kinds;  the  rest  will require &quot;building up&quot;  for some years before  its cultivation can be made a paying proposition.    The farm buildings are  good,  if not quite as iconvenient as they  might be,   The  stock comprises   -14 horses;  44 red heifers, of which about 16 are in milk;   and  about  300 Useful  ewes in lamb,           As the best of the land Is in a satisfactory condition,  and a reasonable attempt  has been made tc  meet the  wishes of the  Committee, the  Inspector  suggests that the best course would probably be  for  the Committee to leave  the cultivation to  the owner,  talk the matter  ever with him, and provide him with a clear  and detailed statement  as to how  the  farm could best be worked in the interests of all concerned. Detailed suggestions on these lines are made in the report.      Plant Diseases,   A summary of the reports received for December and  January from Honorary Correspondents ef the Plant Diseases Sub- Committee of the Technical Committee has been prepared.   The summary deals with  insect and  fungus  pestB affecting all the main farm and garden crops,   and fruit.   In the case of frit fly. for example,  an examination of oats from seven fields on five farms in North Lines. showed infestations varying from    to 35  (the latter from a crap grown  on very light sandy soil), and the damage due to this attack works  out as equivalent to  tho total &apos;4.oso of crop  on 12 acres out of hhe  104  concerned.   Potatoes in the Bast of England, notably in bouth Lines, and Cambridgeshire, were reported tc be keeping badly, serious  losses in some cases  up to  80? being recorded.   Varieties most affected were British  Queen and Arran Chief,  closely followed by King Edward, Up-to-Date, Eclipse, Express and Royal Kidney, except in
Worcestershire,  where Xing Edward was said to  be  keeping well.potatoes lifted  early were keeping better  than those  left  long  in  theground.   Predisposing causes of the trouble were (l) bad  weatherresulting in the tubers being clamped in a wet, muddy  state,  (2) lack&apos;6f labour, resulting in large clamps (&amp;  foot base), faulty ventilation,  I0d subsequently failure to sort out^rotting tubers.    In  a  special report received  on Clover Sickness in the  Eastern Counties,  Tylenchus was stated to be widely distributed throughout the area,  beingespecially bad in Red Clover, and also found in Alsyke  and Kidney  Vetch. INo appreciable damage was noted on Sainfoin, Trefoil, &quot;White  Clover,  orLucerne.   Attacked plants were easily recognised by  their stuntedgrowth, and the  attack spread slowly outward in circular patches.     Seed Testing Station.   During the  month  of  February  approximately3,CO0 samples were received at the Seed  Testing Station, over 1,100being received in one week.   Tests are  well in hand, and  all sampleaare being reported with but little delay.   Clovers and grasses, whichare late^ than last year, are now coming to hand  in considerable numbers, 691 clovers having been received  during  the month.   223samples of flax were tested for the Flax Production Department  and 632samples of oats  for the Commercial Division, whilst over 1,000  samplesof oats have come to the Station from farmers  and the trade.     Miscellaneous Enquiries.   During February about 60 enquirieswere dealt with by correspondence, mainly  on subjects  relating  tocropping and manuring.   Six enquiries relative to tho  electrificationof seeds were received.                                                                        1                                                                        i                           Labour Division.     Demobilisation.   The rate of release of  agriculturists continuesat about 4,000 men per day, the total number cf agriculturistsreleased to date being 113,071.   In view of the  Army Order  retainingfor the Army of Occupation all men who joined  after  the 1st  January,1916, it is unlikely that the present rate will be maintained andthe whole position of the agricultural industry in connection withdemobilisation has been placed before the  Department of Demobilisation.A great deal of work will have to be compressed within tho few  Springweeks and the reports that the Beard are receiving from their county agricultural Executive Committees indicate that the  amount of labour at present on the land is insufficient to cope with  the work to bedone.   It has therefore been urged that tho precodent of the minersshould be followed and that, notwithstanding the  Army Order  as  to  theArmy of Occupation, all agriculturists who can show  that  they have adefinite offer of employment should be demobilised at  once.     Soldier Labour.   A further 3,573 soldiers cf AgriculturalCompanies were demobilised during the week, bringing tho  number ofsoldiers now on farms down to 39,016;  the number on farias early inJanuary was 72,051, so that the number of these men  demobilised to date is 33,035.          The question has arisen as to  the disposal of the  soldiersin or attached to Agricultural Companies and  now out  on farm work whoarc eligible for retention for the Armies cf  Occupation.    instructions have been i&amp;suod by the ^ar Office that  they  are  not  to bo withdrawnfrom farm work for the present, but enquiries  are being made as towhen they can bo spared.   The majority  of these  men have  been  on farmwork for many months and their withdrawal at  this stage would create avery serious situation and tho War Office have been asked to arrangefor their demobilisation or altornatively that they  remain in orattached to Agricultural Companies.El     Prisoners cf War.   Arrangements have been made to supply  gangsof German prisoners for field drainage,  oach gang including  twoprisoners who arc skilled land drainers  to act as foremen.    TheCommittees of Counties in which mole drainage  is practised havo bornurged to take full advantage of the availability of this  labour andorganise the work of clearing out ditches and the &quot;completion of themain drains compatible with the amount cf steam tackle available fcrEiole drainage.
                           Cult iyation pi v1 si on.          The arrangements for the liquidation of the tractor and horse ^schemes  are proceeding  satisfactorily.   The counties &quot;which haveIncepted  the new contract scheme, under which tractors are loaned toI engineers, are presenting some difficulty:  the Committees consider that  the  Department is under an obligation to the engineers tojcontlnue  their contracts until the end of September and it is to bejexpected  tluvt in the counties concerned the majority of the tractors will  have to be retained until that date.   In Norfolk, for example, 10  tractors only will be withdrawn by the end of liay and the rest (148) vail be in operation until the end of September.          Sales of  surplus implements and horses are proceeding. During  the past week particularly good prices were realised at Towcester, Northampton for whipple trees and horse drills:  whipple trees made an average of  2 a set, a price above cost, and drillF  32.10. each, a few pounds under cost.          The total number of horses sold to date is 3,400, at an average price of just under  60.   Seme very good prices were realised in  lilosex, Hampshire, Kent, and Norfolk, as some of the better class horses  which tho Committees were :.  holding back were disposed of; about 200 horses made an average of ftO guineas.   Committees are anxious to keep enough horses for the employment of the German prisoners, and they propose to take over&apos;at valuation the necessary(number  of animals which  they may require, with homes3 and implements, for farms in their  own hands.   In some cases Committees propose to keep  on these farms 10;.  or 20/* more horses and  implements than the farm  actually requires in order to help the small farmers in the neighbourhood, such work to be done on the basis ci the rates laid down  by the Depax-1me nt.          An instruction has been issued asking Executive Officers to  . notify the Deportment of any surplus stocks of fodder, especia ly hay in  the stack, which may not be required now their horse strength has. been.reduced.    On receipt of this information the Central Forage Committee will be advised of the Quantities, and the County Distributing Forage Committee will take it back from  the Agricultural Executive Committees at  the price originally paid for it.          Instructions have been issued to all Executive Officers tc notify  farmers through the Press, and otherwise, that pending the 3ale  of horse-drawn implements, these implements can be hired for the spring  cultivation, Committees reserving the right to withdraw them at  seven  days&apos; notice.      Steam Tackle .   The acreage dealt with during tho past week is as  follows:  ploughed 44, cultivated 16.  Total, 60 acres.                            Commercial Division.      Fertilisers.   The  Klnistry cf &quot;Munitions has nor/ agreed to the ir.suo.of  5,000 tons of Nitrate of Soda for agricultural purposes at  20 per ton.   The  applications received are being forwarded to the Ministry  of Iviunitions&apos; in order that the  supplies may  be despatched. It  is hoped that it will be possible to give delivery  in some cases this  week.          The Ministry of Munitions desires to  issue  a notification to  the  effect that  the Orders relating to fertilisers and  sulphuric acid  shall be withdrawn  as  from the 31st lay next .    In view of this the Treasury have refused to sanction an application  made  to them by the Eo  ird for permission to purchase 50,000 tons of FaciiicPhosphate Rock, which it was  proposed to buy on the understanding that if the Government did not  undertake the  importation of Phosphate Hock next season  this contract would  be transferred to the Trade without
viability  to  the Board.    If it is decided that the purchase of^plosphate  Rock next  season is to he left to the Trade, it will only lie  possible to regulate prices by voluntary agreement, and the Board bill  not be ab.;.e to  exercise any effective control.       Transport. , The Sub-Committee appointed by the Disposal Board to  consider the method  of selling motor lorries, has held several  meetings and has now decided on a number of recommendations v/hich it is  hoped will result in Burplus lorries being made available at an early date.  It is proposed that the new lorries, many of which have not teen  actually delivered, should be offered in the first instance to  the makers for sale  by them at a prescribed price ,   Old types ef lorries v/hich are not in running condition to the number of about 6,000  nil  be offered for  sale by auction.   Many of these are capable of  repair and will go some way to meeting the present need for transport [in  country districts.   Motor lorries which are in running ords  will [also  be offered for  sale without delay, while the remainder which are in  need  of repair will  either be sold in their present condition cr [Repaired before sale.   Tho urgent need for   placing surplus lorries Ion  the market without delay has been pressed on the Committee with a [view  to improving the conditions of agricultural transport.       Seed  Oats.   As a result of a careful scrutiny of the returns of [seed  oats  purchased  to meet the French Order it ,  has been found that fa sufficient quantity have now been obtained or are in sight. ;the average test on  the first cargo showed an average bushel weight Iof  over 41 lbs. and  an average gemination of 92^.   Further shipments [ire being  made from  Liverpool this week.       Wart  Disease.   The Board of Agriculture for Scotland has agreei Uo  the amended draft of the Wart Disease of Potatoes (Scottish Seed Potatoes)  Order of 1919, which will be issued at once. I;                                                  *
(                   Part 1,1 * ; Other Departments *                         Animals Division.I)    Swine Fever -  147 reports,  21  outbreaks.      A^tliraS -   -  13  reports, 2 outbreaks.      Sheep Scab  -  13  outbreaks.       gejjhjyynlicat ions for  licences  under the        Importation  of  Dogs Order -  79.      Rabies,   Three more cases  of  rabies have  unfortunately been confirmed, two of them in Devon  and one  in Cornwall.   Reports as to 5 suspected cases were received.     &quot;Soldiers&quot; Dogs.   A number  of  dogs  have arrived  at  the R.S.P.C.A. kennels  under the  arrangement made as  to  soldiers&apos; dogs, but in view of the  appeal to  the public  for funds to  defray the expenses of quarantining 1 Tommy&apos;B dog&apos; it seems a little  surprising that in a batch of  39  dogs recently landed under  the  scheme 27 are stated to be the property of  Commissioned Officers among  the owners being one Major General, and  8 Lieutenant Colonels.                            Rato Branch.      Local Authorities.   The meeting called by the  Birmingham Local Authority was attended by 1   several  hundred persons  including representatives of  other Local Authorities.   %ilst  no  definite action was decided  upon, the  discussion  and ventilation  of the subject will, it is hoped, have  a useful effect.   There  is evidence of an awakening interest and  activity on the part of the  general public and indications that  they and  their Local  Authorities are becoming more alive to the necessity  of  wider and combined effort.           Some Local Authorities, in  view of the  approaching Municipal and County Council  Elections, have  shown a disposition to shelve their responsibilities On to  the shoulders cf the new Councils. Northumberland have asked that before they commit themselves to appointing an adequate staff  in  formulating a  scheiae, they may have an assurance from the  Board  that their powers under  this temporary Order will be continued.      Poisons.   The trial arranged  with  the Clayton  Gas  Company was carried out at Reading on Friday and  Saturday of  last week. Sulphur-dioxide was generated in the  machines and applied to rat  holes on the premises of  a horse slaughterer and  the  railway banks adjoining. It is estimated that several hundred  rats were  asphyxiated, but the general conclusion  arrived at was that this method whilst satisfactory in enclosed places  cannot be advocated as a  practical method of destroying rats generally in Rural  Areas.                          Veterinary Department.      Swine fever material was examined in connection with 41 reported outbreaks, and the  disease was  found  to  exist  in  22  of them.      Anthrax material was examined  in 11 reported outbreaks and disease was found to exist  in 6.      Anti-abortion vaccine.    11,200  c.c. (224  doses) were manufac- tured, put up in suitable form and  despatched for use on infected farms.      kiseellaneous snecimens  -   post mortem exaniinations were  made  on 3 specimens.      Rabies,   During the week in question specimens were received from 6 suspected outbreaks.e.
                            Fisheries Division.                           Adniinistrative Section.     llFher leg.,.Qrgani sat Aon So clsty.   The financial position of the^jrk of  the Fisheries Organisation Society was discussed with two of the Governors of that hody -   The natter was also discussed with Mr.Vaughan  Nash.   Endeavour will be made to secure some subscriptions from fishermen and private persons, and it was suggested that difficulties in the way of obtaining subscriptions from fishermenmight be met by some scheme on a capitation basis, so that the larger Societies should contribute more than the small ones.     MPle^ManS&apos;   A Conference has been held with the Development Commissioners regarding the conditions under which loans should begranted.   The Commissioners were disposed to think that loans should now only be made to or through approved Fishermen&apos;s Societies; subject  to the undeistanding thai the Motor Loan Committee cculd stillbe free  to break new grounds and to make demonstrative installations in ports where motors had not yet found favour;  and further, that there must be some period of transition before adopting the new system.   It was agreed on the part of this Department that no exception need be taken to the request made &quot;by the Commissioners.     Pollution of Rittor Tees.-   The question of the serious injury to the fisheries of the River Tees due to the pollutions caused by theeffoment from chemical and other works was discussed with LordGainford who enquired whether the President would be prepared to introduce legislation to confer powers on Boards of Conservators to deal with pollution, or whether ho would favour the introduction of aPrivate member&apos;s Bill in the House of Lords.     Delays in trans-port of fish from Fleetwood.   Complaints are made of the serious delays in the transport of fish from Fleetwood by rail to Billingsgate and other markets.   The complaints have been dis- cussed with representative boat owners of Fleetwood and the Ministry of Food.   Detailed statements of the complaints are to be furnished, and the Ministry of Food will then take up the matter with theRailway Executive.     Destruction of Kines.   At the instance of this Department the Admiralty are instructing Senior Naval Officers to supply suitable fishermen applicants with rifle and ammunition on loan to enable then to attempt to sink mines whenever practicable.     Dump1 n^ at^sea of T,.N.T. and other explosive material.   The disposal of laige quantities of T.N.T., Amatol etc. by dumping  it in the sea  continues to engage the attention of the Division and of the Ministry of Munitions,   5he matter is receiving careful attention, with a view to prevent injury to fish life, but the latest proposals put forward by the Ministry were such as the Board could not possibly entertain.   Fortunately there is every indication of the willingness of the Authorities responsible for  dumping to consult the Board and to recognise the importance of safeguarding fishery interests.                  Pishermen&apos;s Registration and  Recruitinfl  Section.     I^9Nlii3 M.2ilI   The despatch of postcard enquiries is continuing, between four thousand and five thousand in all having been sent cut-   The submission of names for release has practically ceased,  except in cases where the particulars previously in  the Board&apos;s  hands were inadequate.   Some delays have occurred lately in the release cf pivotal men from the Navy owing  to the necessity ofJtobtaining suitable reliefs.                         Hotor ,Loan Committee.     JjiDtrJlatp^ons.   During February  the principal installations carried&apos;&quot;out&quot;ny the&quot; Committee were of a 110 H.P. engine at Brixham and a  twin-screw set of 6  PI.P. engines at Amiwch  in Anglesey.
                        Intelligence Division.    Education Branch.   The number of applications from ex-service  menfo:f agricultural training facilities increases as demobilisationproceeds.   The prospects of poultry farming, in particular,  forms the subject of many enquiries.         Efforts are being made to supplement the accommodation available at Agricultural Colleges by the use of Army hutments,where feasible.    gab lip at ionsBranch,   The number of applications for ordinaryssues of the^leaflete was 1,030, in response to which 4^235 copiessrere despatched.   In addition 13,600 copies of the leaflets were despatched to applicants for supplies in bulk for distribution.Applications were received for 495 copies of the three Bound Volumesof Leaflets, and 413 copies of the pamphlet &quot;How to Manage an allotment&quot; were sent out.         During the week Leaflet No, 326 (injurious Weed Seeda  inGrasses and Clovers harvested for Seed in Britain) was published,copies being despatched to 10,400 persons on the relative leaflet list.rue March issue of the Journal is in course of&apos;preparation, and  thework on this publication is much increased for the month by thepreparation of a supplement dealing with the Cultivation, Composition,ind Diseases of the Potato - a supplement ?/hich is likely to be  similar in size to an ordinary issue of the journal, while it will be illustratedidth a large number of excellent photographs.   A new departure  in thisconnection is that this Supplement is to contain advertisementsrelating to potatoes, in part to add to the interest of the publicationtnd in part to recoup expenditure.         Proofs of eleven of the series of &quot;Small Holders&apos; Guides&apos;  forthe use of Service men have now been reoeivei.   Further guides  are  inreparation.                                    *    Officers&apos; Training Branch.  Free, Government Scholarships:-     Applications recorded by Board........................  231       Considered by Departmental Selection Sub-Committee ...  139       Refused..........................,................   92       To be recommended to Utaln Committee.................    8       To be placed on &quot;Reserve List&quot;......................    0       Outstanding for references, interviews, etc.........   30  Residential Farm Training.     Applications referrtd by Board te  County Councils   ...... 272      (Applicants already demobilised - 134; not demobilised - 133).        Started  training..................................     2      ,  Preliminary training arrangements made   ............    31        Rejected by County Councils.......................     3        Withdrawn by applicant   ........,...................     1    Travelling^: expenses of applicants.   The question of payingravelling expenses of applicants who are asked to interview Sub-ommittees of County Councils etc., has been considered by the Inter-epartmental Conference ,   It has been decided that such expensesC uld not be paid, but that if pressure were brought to bear in theatter in any one of the Departments concerned in training ex-Servicefficers, the point should be reconsidered by the Conference.    Generalc   No real difficulties are reported by County Councilsn placing officers witrhv.^eudt^bJje--dTarmer-s for training.   One County
  Council raised the point  of placing  officers with near relatives.  This has &quot;been objected  to by the Board.,*           The number  *f enquiries  -  both verbal  and written -P regarding the Training  Scheme,  shows no  decrease.   The actual  demobilisation of officers appears to have  slowed down somewhat during  the past few weeks, but numerous officers contemplate making  application for training  shortly before  their  demobilisation.       Dairy nBranch*   The  latest information available concerning the  effect&quot;of the Co-operative Cheese  Schools which  were conducted at 10  centres distributed ever  England and Wales during last year is that  at 12 of the Centers  Farmers&apos;  Co-operative Societies have been  registered and factories  are being established which it is expected  will be in operation.during the coming season.            Of the remaining six centres one has definitely Joined  forces with a neighbouring Co-operative  Society.            Concerning  the  co-operative Societies  which weyo established  last year as a result of the co-operative schools  conducted in 1917,  a  report voluntarily submitted from  Cornwall claims  that the establish-  ment of these factories in the calf  rearing districts, has not had  the effect of reducing the number  cf calves reared  in  those areas;  and, with regard to the influence  of the factories  on  the keeping of  cows, the following is a quotation from the report  in  respect of  six  members of the Camelford Cooperative Cheese  Factory:-     Farmer No. 1 kept  in 1917  17 cows    1918   25  cows.       &quot;        2   &quot;   &quot; 1917  20   &quot;     1913   25    M       *        3   &quot;   &quot; 1917  10   &quot;     1913   20   &quot;  -       &quot;        4   &quot;   &quot; 1917  10   &quot;     1918   15   &quot;       &quot;        5   &quot;   &quot; 1917  12   M     1918   15   &quot;       &quot;        6   M   &quot; 1917  10   11     1918   15   &quot;            The above may be taken as a fairly general indication of  the effect of establishing cheeae factories in new districts.                                Land,Division.       Land Se111 eyrest,,throughn County,.Councils.   During the week the  following purchaeii by County Councils &quot;bT land!, under the Small  Holdings and Allotments Act, 1908, mainly for the purpose of  providing holdings for ex-Service men, were approved by the Board:-                                                              Piirchsse          County.           Parish.                Acreage.      priced.0    Bedfordshire    Boughton Conquest (part of                      Hewend Farm)                   27          1,300    Coamwall        St. Sampson&apos;s (Leyonne Farm)    156          4,6DO    Warwickshire    Wedding ton (Top Farm)           246          9,000    Worcester shire  St. John- j n-Eeciwardine           61          4,SCO    Anglesey        part Vaynol Estate                      (Trefarthen Farm)              57          3,575          The Board .,.also approved the leasing by the East SussexCounty Council of 29 acres of land at Jdimore for a period of 3years at an annual rent of  57. 16. 6.          Notifications were received ly the Board during the weekthat County Councils were considering the acquisition of 13 additionalproperties comprising a total ef 4,249 .vcres.               :          The total land acquired or egteed to be acquired by CountyCouncils with thg a^ard1s approval since the 20th December, 1913, Js
  5,-939 acres, of which vacant  possession of 480 acres has already  been obtained.   Vacant  possession of the  remainder will be obtained  in the ordinary course ao follows:-              Lady Day,  1919     -     755 acres.              6th April, 1919     -     178   &quot;              Michaelmas,  1919    -   1,452   &quot;              Candlemas, 1920     -   1,915   M              Lady Day,  1920     -     642   &quot;              6th April, 1920     -     305   &quot;              Michaelmas,  1920    -     139   &quot;                No information    -      73   &quot;            The Board  have under  consideration proposals by County   ouncils for the acquisition  of a  total area of 46,068 acres,   including land for  which it  is proposed to bid at auction and 2,403  acres which the Councils propose to acquire by the exercise of  compulsory powers).            A Land Settlement Egquiry Office has been Opened at 72,  Victoria Street, S.W.1., at which  sailors, soldiers and airmen oan  call and obtain information as  to  the scheme of the Government for  the provision of facilities to  enable ex-service men to settle on  the land in this country.Small Holding Colonies.            205 men are  now employed or settled on the Board&apos;s Colonies,  of whom 120 are civilians, 21 are  men belonging tt Agricultural  Companies, and 64 are  ex-service men.   14 more ex^Service men have  been accepted as probationers but  have  not yet started work.            Each Director  is being instructed to submit the names of 25$  of civilians now employed on  the Colonies  who will gradually be  replaced by ex-Service men willing to work for a probation period as  labourers.      Patrington.  Though the  weather has greatly improved the land is  Btill very waterlogged,  and ploughing has  been limited. The men have  been chiefly employed in hedging,  dyking,  and  clearing  roots.      Holbeach.   Horses have been employed  in ploughing so far as the  weather allowed, and in  oarting potatoes to the station.   Manual  labour has chiefly consisted  in riddling potatoes, and manure  spreading.      Heath Hill.  The  weather was  very wet at the beginning of the  week but improved towards the end.   Farming operations have chiefly  consisted in carting straw and  roots to the yards, hedging and  ditching.       Pembrey.   This Colony was visited during the week.   The land is  beginning to dry though  several.weeks of fine weather will be needed  before much can be worked, in view of the  almost unprecedented amount  of rain which has been experienced here during the last three months,  and which has seriously  affected the Colony owing to the bad ccn-  dition of the dykes  and  outfalls.    As much labour as possible has  been concentrated on digging  out the dykes, and prisoners have been  obtained to assist in the work  after a long controversy with the War  Office.            During the wet weather the men have been employed in  quarrying stone for  repairing the  roads.                    ^During the past month more stock has been purchased  and there are now 13 horses,  48-cows and heifers in calf and barren,  45 bullocks,  and 35  sheep.
            The great  shortage  of  labour, and no available cottages,  have proved a great  difficulty.    Steps are now being taken to  utilise one of the  farmhouses as a hostel  for single men.Kelham Estate.   The  present  moment is a difficult one as on April 6th^next the tenants on the Rolleston and Aver ham Sect ionsof the Estate  want to know definitely whether  their notices to quit are to be  adhered to,            The Society has agreed in principle to the sale of this part  of the estate to the Board  if the price be&apos;satisfactory, that is to  say if the price offered is equal to the present market value and thiB  decision was confirmed at the Annual Meeting of the Society held on  the 26th ult.   In  the meantime  the offer  of the Board is awaited as  the transaction must be settled  within the next few days in order  that the Rolleston  tenants  may be informed, as in future action with  regard to their holdings is a matter for the Board of Agriculture to  decide.   It is too  late for  the Society to attempt to farm this  area this year, and it will involve an immediate application from the  Estate Committee of Management for additional working capital.   On  the other hand, if  the tenants were allowed to remain (supposing the  transaction fell through) they would have  to be given a three years1  agreement in order  to secure  that the land would be properly farmed.  This it is understood would prejudice the  value of the land for future  sales as buyers at  the present time desire vacant possession in order  tc reap the present farming profits available.            It is impossible  for the Society (prior to 6th April) to make  the necessary preparations  to Bell the land by auction  to enable  buyers to have  vacant possession on 6th April, and in view of this  consideration, the  Estate Committee of Management are extremely anxious  to have a settlement.          The Board are invited to  take  over  contracts alreadyentered into for additional implements,  fertilisers  etc. beforecancellation of the orders take place.                           Live Stock Branch.  Work of Branch - Administration of Live  Stock and  Horse Breeding       Schemes.   Live Stock.Ho. of Grants approved for boars      do.       do.        bulls      do.       do.        heavy horses      do.       do.        milk recording  Milk Recording; Applications.No. of Certificates issued      do.  CCWB registered  Horse Breeding.Ho. of Stallions accepted for registration  Hi acellaneous,Duringaboveweek,  2  3 Nil  2Duringaboveweek.     397      1Duringaboveweek.76  Total  since 1 Apr .1918,     309     679     223      27  Total  since1 Oct. 1916.    1,962      201  Total  since  1 ttcv.1918,    1,668During above week. 0 applications for the export of 96  horses were  approved.11           do,          do.    137  cattle      do. 1           do.          do.      2  pigs was approved. 4           do           do.     50  poultry were approved 1           do.          dc.      1  dcg was approved.
                              S^at i^etica Iti Diy is ion.,( :   -Statistical Branch..   Except for the appointment  of new CropWporters, the worirhas &quot;been mostly of a routine  character.   Afurther 55 appointments have &quot;been made during the week,  making.thetotal number of Crop Reporters definitely appointed,  139,          A meeting of the Committee on Live Stock and Meat  Productiontos held en the 4th inst.    On tiie same day a conference-ofrepresentatives of the three Departments of Agriculture  was  held t$consider negotiations under *Part I Of the Corn Production Act,     Agricultural Wa^es Board.   A meeting of the Committee  on FarmingCosts and the&quot;&quot;Cost&quot;&quot;of*Living was held on Wednesday the 26th  Februarywhen the draft conclusions on the financial results  of farming were considered.          Mr. Padwick (in the absence of Mr. Rea) and Mr. Robbins  onbehalf of the Representatives of Employers, and Messrs.  Dallas andWalker on behalf of the Representatives of Workers on the Wages Boardattended the Industrial Conference arranged by the Ministry  of labour on the 27th February.   Sir Henry Raw also attended  on the invitation of the Ministry of Labour,   Mr. Padwick and Mr,  Walker  were nominatedcn the Joint Committee ajjpointed by the Conference.          The fourteenth issue of the Wages Board Gazette was publishedtin the 4th inst.   This issue contains a complete summary of theminimum rates of wages at present in force.          During the week 114 cases of complaint  of non-payment of theminimum rates were received, the largest number from a single county .being 35 in the case of Yorkshire;  12 cases were Bent england Inspectorsfor visit;  enquiries by correspondence were made in 292 cases;  and.31 cases were&quot; completed.&apos;   Reports were, received  from Inspectors in10 cases.   One additional whole-time InspectorMr. T.  Kemm, hasbeen appointed this week and will take up his duties cn  the  13thMarch.          Owing to delay in printing, the Report  on Wagas andConditions of Agriculture will not be published until the end of theweek.          Proceedings against an employer in Somerset for non-compliance with the Board&apos;s Orders was heard at Wells, on Mondaythe 3rd March.   The proceedings were taken in respect of the under-payment of an adult male worker.   The employer was visited by  an inspector in October last, and was found to have  underpaid two  ofher workers,   -fh: provisions of  the Act and of the Board&apos;s orders were clearly pointed out  t: the employer by the inspector, and  thecffer by lira fc.&apos;Ap:,over to pay the  arrears owing to the workers wasaccented as s. tistclement of the case.   On a second visit by the inspector in December it was found that one of the workers had continued to be underpaid since the date cf the first visit, and  theproceedings related to  the offence committed&apos; between the date  ofthe first and second visits.   The worker in Court went  back cn theevidence given to the Inspector and in his  signed proof, and on his evidence in Court, which was accepted by the Eench; nc underpaymenthad occurred.   The magistrate accordingly  dismissed the case.              Tithe, Cotyaone, Copyhold  and  Survey Branch.          The Board err1: uvc to receive many enquiries as to theprocedure in redemyi- ion&quot; tiidfcr the  Tithe Act, 1918, and among these is ore from e landcvvnor who oropcess  to raise  12,000 by  sellingpart of hib property with a view  to redeem  the tithe rentcharge on the remainder.
          Some County Councils are taking steps to redeem the  titherentcharge charged on land acquired by them for small holdings underthe Small Holdings and Allotments Act, 1900, as suggested in theBosrd1s circular letter of the 30th January last.   It appears,however, that certain of the Councils hare no detailed information as$o the tithe rentcharge charged upon their land,  and in order  tofbviate the expense which would be involved in obtaining suohparticulars from the tithe collectors,  it is proposed that  the board shall themselves supply these particulars after comparing the  plans of$he lands filed in this Department with the relative tithe  maps.          The number of documents inspected by the public in the  PublioInspection Room continues to increase.   Among the requisitionsreceived during the past week has been one for whole copies of sixdifferent tithe maps.             &quot;r.Ont. Joint, Committee of the Board Of Agriculture                          and the Ministry    flood.          Reports received show that tJ*9 exoeasive slaughter of calvesis. causing much anxiety and that there is a &quot;general demand for someorganised attempt to prevent,a continuation of such slaughter.          Weekly KsteB Nos. 30 and 31 have been issued.   There isstill a large demand from Local Authorities for the Leaflet $nParasitic Mange in Horses.                            Ordnance Survey.Maps were despatched as follows             War Office             Air Ministry             Admiralty             $the? Services             Overseas  ......... 3,084 2,661   34013,200Land Reclamation Branch,Progress of Schemes   ^silwllW,..J^qre.    A letter making formal application to theTreasury f5r an advance from the Development Fund to meet the oost ofthe proposed works in this area, has been despatched,   Borth.   The Director df Land Reclamation visited Berth Bog lastweek and decided on the limits of the area to be acquired.;.,, the survey by the Ordnance Survey levellers is still proceeding.   Sower by Wood, Barrow-in -Furness. ( janos.)   These areas were   liorecam.ee Ba/. gilrardale.. (Lanes.)      visited by the Chief   ----------------------,----.....------------------u      Engineer during the week   Me at h-i p, Flat s (Cum b 3 r land \.              and his reports are being                                            considered.                             Establishment Branch.          The Office of Works have now conditionally assigned to theBoard No. 6 St. James&apos;s Square, S.W.   Arrangements are being made forthe allocation of the rooms in that building for the information cfthe Office of Works.   The house is not very suitably adapted foroffices and much of the space cannot be utilised economically.          It is hoped, however, that this building may enable arrange-,ments to be ms-ie to afford some relief to the Fisheries Division bythe removal of a section of the Accounts Branch from  3. ParliamentStreet.   Besides which it should afford accommodation for ens or twoothe
 ( tions, and it may &quot;be possible to provide more permanent accommoda- ion for the Land Reclamation Branch now housed in Great College Street, Westminster.          The removal of Land Division this week from Whitehall Place fill enable relief to be given to the Officers&apos; Training, Education ,nd Dairy Branches, all of which are badly in need of better offices.          The housing of the Land Division at Victoria  Street will necessitate a further division of the General Registry, and a section \t the Registry staff at Whitehall Place must be transferred to fictoria Street,   This is extremely inconvenient as it is impossible jio exercise an efficient control and direction in the circumstances. Jut the whole Department.suffers by reason of the expedients which iave necessarily to be adopted for carrying on a large and important business with a staff distributed in numerous offices sepa&amp;ate and in some cases distant from one another,m5th March,  1919.                          Secretary.

</content>
</cab>
