<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 448-448</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^l^^SM^J^T^-^0^^ OF HIS  BRITAEfltTlC HAJEGTY*S GOVTOTTOTT.)                                                                  323- SECRET.                                WAR  CABI13ET. G.T.  foffl.                               &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;                                 FORESTRY:                          INTERIM FORESTRY  AUTHORITY.Memorandum &quot;by the Secretary for Scotland.      1*      With reference to the memoranda &quot;by the Treasury      (.G.T,  6833). by Mr.. A eland (G.T. 6893 and 6896), and &quot;by      Lord Ernie  (G.T.  6909). I think I should inform the War      Cabinet of  the ppsition from my point of view.      .2.      As  Mr. Acland states,-! hove endeavoured to come to&apos;      an arrangement with the Interim Forestry Authority on the      subject f)t  staff  and administration, in accordance with the      decision of the War Cabinet of the late Government.   There      has been considerable uncertainty as to the power of the      Interim Authority to employ any staff at all - an unoertain-      ty which is emphasised by tho considerations sot out by the      Treasury in their memorandum.   The suggestion was accord-      ingly  made  to the Interim Authority that, as they propose to      plaoe  thoir operations in Scotland under tho charge cf      Colonel Sutherland, who is a member of tho Scottish Board of      Agriculturej any  additional staff which they now desire to      appoint might be  appointed on Mr. Sutherland&apos;s advice, anrt      might  be temporarily attached to the Scottish Board, leaving      over in the meantime the question whether or no they should      ultimately  be attached to the Board or to a permanent      Forestry authority if and when established,      3* .       cannot, however, conceal my view that any arrange-      ment on the lines suggested is essentially unsatisfactory,      and is almost certain to lead to difficulties in working.      The statutory power to deal with Forestry in Scotland resides      in the Scottish Board, and as the Minister responsible, fer      that Board, I. am  unable to divest myself nf responsibility      for any Forestry  operations in which they have a hand.  I      therefore agree with the Treasury that the present posit ion      is entirely anomalous, and I  think that there should ba n?      delay  in regularising it.      4.      How it should be regularised is matter for serious      consideration.    I am unaware whether the far Cabinet ara in      entire, accord with the decision of the War Cabinet of&quot;t^      late Government.   I have endeavoured to give effect with      loyalty  to  that decision, but I am satisfled&apos;that the      proposal to centralise Forestry administration  in Whitehall      will prove  to be  a highly contentious one in the House of      Commons.    I am aware that a  comprehensive Forestry policy      has been promised in the King * s Speech, but such a policy       can well be carried out by the respective board a tff      Agriculture in  consultation with-the Development Commission,      and without constituting a Central Authority  in Whitehall,      My views on the subject were  fully expressed  in a memorandum       submitted to a War Cabinet Committee of which-Lord Curzon      and Mr.  Barnes were members,  and  I think I am entitled to       say they received partial acceptance in the report presented       by them  to  the War Cabinet.   I desiro to be heard upon tho       subject  in  tho War Cabinet beforo a final decision is       roa*hed.                               -  ,                             (Signed)  ROBERT KIOTO.Scottish Office.   9th March, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
