<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 450-452</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PROPOSED CLOSING  OF THE PRESS BUREAU,I  J   (Circulated by the Home Secretary),*****                12th February tho War  Cabinet  considered  the  proposal v/hich I        ^r the closing cf the Press Bureau (G.T.-6742) and decided that as the   censorship of telegrams and letters could not  yet  be abolished  it was necesa-   ary that the Press Bureau should continue.    Since then I  have  received the   attached letter from the Directors  of  the Press  Bureau ih  which they  give   strong reasons for a reconsideration cf  this  decision.   It  seems to  me that   the continuance of the Press Censorship  can be considered  apart from  the   censorship of telegrams and letters, and I  should  be glad  if the War  Cabinet   would now agree to my.previous recommendation.         I have also received a letter from the  Secretary of  State for India in   which he proposes that part of the  Press Bureau  organization should be retained   for the purpose of communicating official announcements to the  Press  and of   informing the Press on questions of Government policy.   A similar suggestion   was made in my previous paper ( G.T.-6742), but  I  have oome  to  the conclusion   that it is not practicable, mainly  because  an  I  have since learned it would   be ^uite unacceptable to the Frqss.   But apart  from this  reason the  Directors   point out that hitherto the Press Bureau has  afforded  a convenient channel of   communication to the Press because  every paper of  standing has  maintained a   representative in constant attendance  day and night in connection with ^hg   Press Censorship.    As soon as the Press Censorship is abandoned these re-   presentatives will no longer be in  attendance, and that means of  giving   information to the Press will be at an end, because it is  certain that news-   papers will not pay to keep a representative  at  the Press  Bureau for  the simple   purpose of passing on communiques from the  Departments.    In any  case no   official organization could probably become as effective as  the Press Associa-   tion and other newcagencies as a means of publication.         Where a Minister wishes to get into touch  with the Press  for special   purposes he can communicate either  with  individual newspapers or with the   Newspaper Proprietors Association,  and I understand that  this course, would meet   the wishes of the Press.                                              %10th March,&apos;1919.                                                    E.S,                        APPENDIX  1. &apos;              LETTER FROM DIRECTORS OF PRESS BUREAU.Dear Kr. Shortt,      The War Cabinet have decided that the censorship is to be maintained andthe Press Bureau must continue.   Evidently the censorship referred to is notthe Press Censorship, and we feel so strongly that a considerable number, ofmen are being paid for doing very little, and that that little is not reallynecessary, that V7c ask you to relieve us from our posts as Joint Directors ofthe Press Bureau.
      AB  long as  this, office remains open there will he something to do, but  in our  opinion it would maice no difference if the whole burden of responsibility rosted on  the Press..   In any case the small amount ef work we now get coats the country a. price out of all proportion to its &apos; value, while  it keeps the Directors and a number of Censors fir hours daily doing next  to nothing when their time might be better employed. .      Praotioally all the Departments except tho War Offios have aban-idoned press censorship&apos;and in  our opinion, the War Office itself oould quite wall  do whatever it wants.   It is a matter of opinion whether any censorship  done on behalf of that Department during the last two months has  made  the  slightest difference;   Tho&apos;Pro3s have practically ceased to refer  to us.   The Wireless messages from Germany, Russia, and elae- where, are  under  the control of tho War Offloe and they can deal with &apos; them as thoylike.   There remains only the censorship of Press telegrams and  we think  it would be  difficult to find any which have passed through  - this office during the last two months whioh might not have been safely left to the discretion of the  newspapers and agencies to whioh they were addressed&apos;    As to outward messages, the most objectionable was probably that from Mr, Bernard Shaw to  the Hearst press, and it was passed and has been published.                                                 *      The only other question  which might have arisen was in regard to the Paris Conference, but on  that  we were not consulted and&quot; the Government decided that everything which  oame from Paris on that subject should be passed,      Under these tircumstancos we feel that since the cessation of . hostilities the raison d^etro for a Press Censorship has either ceased altogether  or could be met fry  other and  simpler means.   It is our firm belief that up to the date of  tho armistice tho&quot;Press Bureau was of great value in  protecting the interests of the Allies and the lives of our fighting  forces,  hut since that date to keep the office in being is not only a waste  of,public money but a waste of intelligence and experience which can be  much better  employed.      As  we have  been here since tho beginning of tho war we.may, without affectation,oialm to know something about the Press Censorship, as it was and  as it.is, and we havo no idea what aro the reasons which have induced tho  War Cabinet to decide that it is necessary to continue the existence of an offite which, by reason  of the conclusion of hostilities and resulting circumstances has beoome somewhat of an anachronism,      Wo  trust therefore  that  you will allow us to give up &quot;our Directorship after the  lapse  of the usual  notioe or  earlier should that be more oon- yoniont to  tho Government.                  -               *  &apos; Yours very truly,                               (Signed)    F.A. SWETSJSNHAM.                                &quot;         B..T. COOK.
                        APPENDIX  331,             BETTER FROM SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.My dear Shortt,      I understand that the question of closing the Press Bureau has been postponed pending the cessation of cable oensorship.   When the time forfurther considering the closing of the Bureau arises, there are a couple of points whioh seom to me worthy of attention.   The Press Bureau presents by-far the most convenient and effective method of oommunioating offioialannouncements to the Press,   The institution ensures that announcements aremade available to all newspapers, and all possible chance of favouring somesection of the Press at the expense of another is avoided.      Again, from time to time it becomes necessary on grounds of policy toissue some general suggestions to the Press to help editors in the treatmentof Important questions.   Here again, the Press Bureau affords the best medium of reaching the right people.      In both these respects our pre*.war organisation seems to me to havebeen defective, and if you and other Heads  of Departments take the view thatthe existence of a Press Bureau hereafter could serve a useful purpose inthese matters, I think it would be worth considering whether some small Officeought not to be maintained to aot as a ohannel between Government departments and the newspapers.   It would only have to be quite a small affair, but ifits existence would bo  helpful; as I think  it would, it would be a pity-notto provide for it when the question of winding up the existing Press Bureauis under review.   If such an Office were maintained, I suppose the most con-venient arrangementsould be that it should be under the control of the HomeSeoretary,                                   Yours sincerely,                           (Signed)     E. MONTAGU,

</content>
</cab>
