<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/76/0 images: 555-556</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Department  of  Agriculture and  Technical Instruction for Ireland.    ^                    Thi   i-r-u-ient is the Property ofBritannic Majesty&apos;s government^&amp;M^       FOOD PRODUCTION SCHEMES,  IRELAND.       Memorandum prepared in compliance with Chief Secretary1y                     Minute cf l&apos;7th March, 1917,                     Week ended 13th March, 1919.               The following is a brief otatoment on the work of the department during the past week in furtherance of increaaod FoodProduction in Iroland:-                  LOANS FOR AGRICULTURAL IMPLEMENTS.               The number of applications received during the past  &apos;week is 52, and the total value of machinery ordered from the beginn-ing of the present yoar, to date, under the Sohemey amounts to 11,877.                       TILLAGE  SECTION.               The general inspection work was resumed in some districts  during the week, and arrangements wore also made for en-quiring into some specific caaes elsewhere in which complaints had beenmade to the Department that the occupiers wore not taking the necessary steps to comply with thic year&apos;o Tillage Order*               A considerable number of oases; inspected under theRegulations made by tho Department under the Third Schedule of theCorn Production A&amp;t, 1917, are now under consideration with a view to determining what action should be taken in the matter of exactingpenalties  where tho inspections already made show a default %ncomplying  with the&apos;1916 Tillage Orders,                     PROGRESS OF FARM TOR.               The weather during the week continued to bo favourable for tillage operations? although1in a few  eastern counties therewore anew  stermo and a heavy rainfall.   Ploughing was mm&amp;&amp;wfo&amp;*^proceeded  with, the condition  tf the ground permitting tractors to boueod for this operation on many farms.  Planting of potatoes  was infull swing in early districts,, and  sowing  of lea oats and  barley willbo general in another  week?               FWn one county it is reported that  farmer a weredissatisfied last  seaeon  with  the return from wheat crops, and are disposed to grow  oato  in  preference this  year012/5/19.
, ARTIFICIAL   MANURES.        Tho  supply of artificial manures has boon  more  satisfactorythan in previous seasons,  and it is  observer) that  this  has had  thooffoot of encouraging  email farmers to increase and maintain thoirtillage area,                   LABOUR  SITUATION,&apos;        The  labour situation continues to prove a  source of oerioueanxiety to farmers,-  Threats of strikes by farm labourers are saidto be making tho outlook for successful tillage very uncertain onlargo farms, while progress with ploughing is being retarded by existing labour troubles,  especially in southern counties, &apos;                     F  L  A  X,Flax Grading,        The complaints referred to in  last  week&apos;ereport as to the standard  of grading have been investigated by the&quot;Flax Supplies Committee.   It appears that cortain grounds for oom**plaint did exist, and the  Flax Supplies Committoe  have  intimated that immediate steps woro  taken to remedy the natter.  Roportsreceived from Inspectors this week indicate that the action taken ishaving effect.Demand for Flaxseod.  So far there is little improvement in the d&amp;fmand oy farmers for flaxseed.Labour,  Ho labour difficulties in soutchraills were reported to theDepartment during the week.Flax Growing in 1919,  Farmers are still showing some hesitancyIn&quot;makihg their plane for flax growing in 1919,MAINTENANCE  OF  LIVS  STOCK.             During ths period from 4th to 10th instant, inclusive,215 applications for licences to slaughter or export heifers,54 applications for licences to slaughter bulls or bullocks,&apos;andlb5 applications for licences to export milch powo, were receivedeEight applications wore roooiwod for licences to slaughter vealoalvoo.   One&apos;licence allowing of the exportation of a pure-bredHereford calf  was Issued during the period.

</content>
</cab>
