<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/182/4 images: 28-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government 1C(75) 29 COPY NO11 March 1975CABINETREFERENDUM:  EXTENSION OF FRANCHISE and additional VOTING FACILITIESMemorandum by the Lord President of the council. The proposals in C(75) 28 run counter to the views expressed by representatives of the Labour Party when I met them on 20 February,after our last discussion, and are likely to make more difficult with ourown side of the House the passage of the Referendum Bill through parliament,2o On the extension of the register to certain British subjects livingabroad, the practical difficulties are clear enough from the Home Secretary1paper.    There are also considerations of secrecy, and thus of confidence in the procedure, and of cost.    But to my mind the decisive argument ispolitical.    If we seek to legislate to extend the register in this way we shallbe departing from the principle enunciated in the preface to Command 5925that &quot;wherever appropriate the Government will use the well triedmachinery which serves for Parliamentary elections&quot;.    And we may wellbe accused of making such a departure in order to help one side in the referendum.3. Similar considerations apply to the proposal to give postal votes toholiday-makers and others away from home.    In addition it would represent a serious breach in the tradition that changes in the electoral law should be made only after careful consideration of them by the Speaker!conference, which has in the past rejected postal voting by holiday-makersin elections.    If those on holiday are allowed to vote by post in the referendum it will be very difficult to deny them the same right in elections.CONCLUSION4. I invite the Cabinet to agree that the electoral register (apart fromthe addition of peers) and the arrangements for absent voting in the referendum should be the same as in a General Election.E privy Council Office11 March 1975


</content>
</cab>
