<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/178/0 images: 170-179</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1926SECRET.CP. 22 (26).MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.Indians in South Africa.A crisis has been reached in the relations between South Africa and India owing to the introduction&apos;in the Union Parliament at the end of last session of the Areas Reservation and Immigration and Registration (Further Provisions) Bill known briefly as the &quot; Asiatic Bill.&quot; I circulate three telegrams from the Viceroy on the subject, in the first of which will be found a statement of the Indian case.This further piece of repressive legislation is based on the assumption that the Indian is an alien element in the population, and its avowed object, as stated by the Minister who introduced it, is to bring about a considerable reduction of Indians in South Africa. The Bill, if passed, would enable urban authorities to segregate Indians in towns both for trade and residence; it would prevent Indians from acquiring immovable property agricultural or urban-anywhere in Natal outside the coast belt, and even within the coast belt from acquiring such property except from other Indians, and would prohibit the entry into South Africa of the wives and minor children of domiciled Indians after 1st August 1930.This Bill, coming after other legislation which has, during recent years, gravely-prejudiced the position of Indians in South Africa, has naturally caused bitter resentment in India. The Government of India have addressed urgent representations to the Union Government, and in particular have asked them to agree to a conference between representatives of the two Governments. This the Union Government have refused, and the only concession they are willing to make has been to agree that a deputation from India, should be allowed to visit South Africa to collect information regarding the economic conditions of Indians, so that the Government of India may be in a position to put forward their own suggestions.The deputation left India towards the end of November. The Union Government have given an assurance that they will favour the fullest opportunity being given to the deputation to lay the Indian case before the Select Committee that will consider the Bill after its second reading. The Government of India, however, regard this offer as unsatisfactory, on the not unreasonable, ground that if a second reading were given to the Bill its principle would have been affirmed and the Select Committee would deal only with details.The Bill was formally introduced at the end of last session and would, in the ordinary course, come up for second reading during the present session, which was due to begin on 22nd January. The object of the telegrams which I am circulating was to secure, through the good offices of His Majesty&apos;s Government, a postponement of the second reading until the deputation had time to report, and until the Government of India could make suggestions for dealing with the situation on different lines. The Government of India have renewed their proposal that a conference should be held ; failing that, they ask for a further enquiry by the Union Government themselves before the Bill is proceeded with.With the Prime Ministers approval, a private telegram from the Secretary of State for Dominions Affairs to the Governor-General was sent on loth January, saying that if he felt that he could usefully bring his influence to bear on Ministers, any support that he could give to either of the requests made by the Government of India would be gratefully appreciated. I have just seen the Governor-General&apos;s reply. He has seen General Hertzog, who was not unsympathetic and consented to receive the Indian delegation and also to see the Minister in charge of the Bill. Lord Athlone, though promising to do all he can to promote a settlement, says that too much importance should not be attached to this, and that he is very doubtful whether there will be any outcome satisfactory to the Government of India.At the moment nothing further can be done. But should the Union Government refuse to listen to reason and pass this Bill, I fear that His Majesty&apos;s Government may be placed in a very embarrassing position.   The passage of the Bill would almost953      100      1.26 A
2certainly lead to a demand, however impracticable, that the Imperial Government should intervene to secure its disallowance, and we should thus be forced to choose between interfering unconstitutionally&apos; in the domestic affairs of a Dominion and facing the diversion against Great Britain of the flaming resentment now felt by all classes of Indians, including even the native Princes, against South Africa.I am told that in South. Africa the.Indian problem, is part of the native problem, and I know that the Union Government have their own difficulties, to contend against. But I earnestly trust that they will at least agree to postponement so that at the next , Imperial Conference another endeavour may be made to find a way out. Should, however, they persist with this legislation, a situation will arise the gravity of which, from the Imperial point of view, can scarcely be exaggerated, and it is for this reason that I have thought it well to take the first opportunity to inform my colleagues of the facts.BIRKENHEAD.ENCLOSURE.Telegram from Viceroy, Department of Education., Health and Lands, to Secretary ofState for India, 8th January J920.Indians in South Africa. We are constrained to address you regarding the situation which has arisen in this country as a result of the introduction in the Union Parliament of the Area Reservation and Immigration and Registration (Further Provisions) Bill. The matter has already been the subject of.correspondence between us, but we feel that the time has come when it is incumbent on us to lay the whole position as it presents itself to us before His Majesty&apos;s Government and to explain to them, in broad, outline, why it is that public opinion iti India is so deeply stirred by the progress of events in South Africa.2. At the outset we may mention that the total Indian population in South Africa likely to be affected by the proposed legislation is about .160,000, of whom approximately 102,000 are South African born. As His Majesty&apos;s Government, are aware, the Indian community in South Africa has its origin hi indentured labour, which was introduced by Natal between 1800 and 1911, for the development of her industries, and &apos;more especially for sugar and tea plantations. This indentured labour was recruited mainly from the agricultural labouring classes of Madras and Upper India, and the majority of the Indians who have settled in the country on the expiry of their indentures, and their descendants, are still connected with agriculture, being either employed by planters and farmers or settled on their own land as market gardeners. A considerable number, however, have taken to other occupations, such as household service, industrial labour, both skilled and unskilled, employment on railways and under municipalities, clerical work, trading, and even learned professions. The great bulk of the Indian community is resident in Natal. South Africa is now their home. Few of the colonial-born have seen India, and an ever increasing number can scarcely speak or understand any Indian language. It may be observed that there has never been any spontaneous emigration of the labouring classes from India to South Africa. Those who went there were recruited with difficulty.3. The intensity of Indian feeling on the question of the proposed legislation, will be understood if the various disabilities under which the Indian community in South Africa already labours are borne in mind. Apart from many extremely galling social disabilities, such as exclusion from theatres and. hotels, segregation in trains, and similar restrictions which, are not embodied in the Jaw, the main grievances of Indians, are as follows :  Political. In the Transvaal and Orange River Colony, Indians do not enjoy either political or municipal franchise. In Natal, Indians were. deprived of the right of acquiring political franchise in 189(1 The Boroughs Ordinance of 1925, while safeguarding the electoral privileges of Indians already on the roll, deprives the community of the right to acquire the borough franchise in future. Similarly, in April last, the Governor-General of Union of South Africa gave his assent to the Natal Townships Ordinance, which has the same effect in respect of Indian electoral rights in townships. Only in province of the Cape is the community in enjoyment of both political and municipal franchise.
certainly lead to a demand, however impracticable, that the Imperial Government should intervene to secure its disallowance, andwe should thus be forced to choose between Interfering unconstitutionally in the domestic affairs of a Dominion and facing the diversion against Great Britain of the flaming resentment now felt by all classes of Indians, including even the native Princes, against South Africa.I am told that in South. Africa the Indian problem is part of the native problem, and 1 know that the Union Government have their own difficulties to contend against. But 1 earnestly trust that they will at least agree to postponement so that at the next , Imperial Conference another endeavour may he made to find a way out. Should, however, they persist with this legislation, a situation will arise the gravity of which, from the Imperial point of view, can scarcely be exaggerated, and it is for this reason that I have thought it well to take the first opportunity to inform my colleagues of the facts.BIR.KENHEAD.ENCLOSURE.Telegram from Viceroy, Department of Education, Health and Lands, to Secretary ofState for India, Sth January 1926.Indians in South Africa. We are constrained to address you regarding the situation which has arisen in this country as a result of the introduction in the Union Parliament of the Area Reservation and Immigration and Registration (Further Provisions) 13i 11.. The matter has already been the subject of.correspondence between us, but we feel that the time has come when it is incumbent on us to lay the whole position as it presents itself to us before His.Majesty&apos;s Government and to explain to them, in broad outline, why it is that public opinion , iu India is so deeply stirred by the progress of events in South Africa.2. At the outset we may mention that the total Indian population in South Africa likely to be affected by the proposed legislation is about .160,000, of whom approximately 102,000 are South African born. As His Majesty&apos;s Government are aware, the Indian community in South Africa has its origin in indentured labour, which was introduced by Natal between 1860 and 1911, for the development of her industries, and more especially for sugar and tea plantations. This indentured labour was recruited mainly from the agricultural labouring classes of Madras and Upper India, and the majority of the Indians who have settled in the country on the expiry of their indentures,, and their descendants, are still connected with agriculture, being either employed by planters and farmers or settled on their own land as market gardeners. A considerable number, however,:have taken to other occupations, such as household service, industrial labour, both skilled and unskilled, employment on railways and under municipalities, clerical work, trading, and even learned professions. The great bulk of the Indian community is resident in Natal. South Africa is now their home. Few of the colonial-born have seen India, and an ever increasing number can scarcely speak or understand any Indian language. It may he observed that there has never been any spontaneous emigration of the labouring classes from India to South Africa. Those who went there were recruited with difficulty.3. The intensity of Indian feeling on the question of the proposed legislation will be understood if the various disabilities under which the Indian community in South Africa already labours are borne in mind. Apart from many extremely galling social disabilities, such as exclusion from theatres and hotels, segregation in trains, and similar restrictions which are not embodied in the law, the main grievances of Indians-are as follows :  Political. In the Transvaal and Orange River Colony, Indians do not enjoy either political or municipal franchise. In Natal, Indians were deprived of the right of acquiring political franchise in 1896. The Boroughs Ordinance of 1925, while safeguarding the electoral privileges of Indians already on the roll, deprives the community of the right to acquire, the borough franchise in future. Similarly, in April last, the Governor-General of Onion of South Africa gave his assent to the Natal Townships Ordinance, which has the same effect in respect of Indian electoral rights in townships. Only in province of the Cape is the community in enjoyment of both political and municipal franchise.
Entry and inter-provincial movement.- The Immigrant Regulation Act of 1913 is -utilised in conformity with the Imperial Conference Resolution of 1918 to prohibit entry of new immigrants from India into South Africa. The Act also incorporate^ provisions which have the effect of debarring Indians from moving from one province into another in which they do not possess rights of residence.Licensing daws.-JviiMfmB are handicapped in the pursuit of trade by the manner in which the licensing laws of the various pr-ovinces are administered. These laws are of general application and do not differentiate between European and coloured licence-holders, except in minor matters, but in practice, the powers vested in the issuing authority are frequently used to place difficulties in the way of Indian traders. Thus, in the Transvaal, the Asiatic communities complain that the municipal bodies refuse to grant licences to them purely on the ground of nationality. Although they have not yet felt the effect of the General Dealers (Control) Ordinance recently passed by the Provincial Council, they have good reason to fear that very few or no new-licences will be granted to Indians in future. In the Orange Free State Province, all Asiatics are, by the laws of the former Republic which are still in force, prohibited from trading or carrying on business of any description whatever. Even in the Cape Province, which has otherwise treated its Indian residents fairly, some municipalities have refused a much larger proportion of applications from Indians for trade licences than from persons of any other nationality. The same policy is pursued by the municipalities in Natal, where it was stated by the licensing officer of Durban municipality before the Asiatic Enquiry Commission that &quot;a European licence is granted always as a matter of course, whereas Indian licence is refused as a matter of course, if it is a new one.&quot; Outside the townships and boroughs, treatment of Indian applications is almost equally severe. The Rural Dealers Ordinance, 1923, empowers the Administrator to create a Licensing Board, from which Indians have been excluded on the ground that they do not possess parliamentary franchise. Their decisions on applications for new licences are subject to an appeal to Board of Appeal only when a new licence is refused on the ground that the applicant is not a fit and . proper person to hold licence applied for or to carry on the proposed business. The obstacles which, in these ways, have been placed in the way of Indians earning their livelihood by trade tend to place them at the mercy of their European rivals, and to prevent them from raising their social and economic position by an avenue for which many of them have shown special capacity.Restrictions on the acquisition of fixed property&apos;.-In the Transvaal, prohibitions against the acquisition of fixed property by Asiatics outside the locations date from the time of the Republic, and these have subsequently been made more stringent by Act 37 of 1919, which forbids the acquisition of immovable property by Indians outside the assigned wards or locations, either by the formation of companies or through nominal trustees. In proclaimed areas they cannot own fixed property; including stands, inside or outside townships and can only acquire leases, with respect to stands outside townships, which have been granted under mining laws prior to 1908. In Natal the Boroughs and Townships Land Ordinance empowers the town council of any borough or local hoard of any township, with the consent of the Administrator, to restrict to members of a particular j-aee occupation and ownership of immovable property sold or leased out by them. In Durban, so far as we are aware, only two sales of land have taken place since the Sims Harward Land Alienation Ordinance was passed in 1922, and in both cases right of purchase was confined to Europeans.Segregation. The Transvaal Law 3 of 18S5 recognised the principle of segregation, and although in practice it was not rigidly applied, separate locations for the Indians are to be found in the Transvaal, of some of &apos; which the Asiatic Enquiry Commission spoke in severe terms. Compulsory segregation was accordingly definite])7 rejected by that Commission which recommended that Indians should be attracted to separate areas by provision of special facilities. But the policy which has commended itself to the Union Government is one of enabling local bodies to provide for compulsory segregation of the Asiatic community in towns both for trade and residence. Indian sentiment has always been strenuously opposed to segregation as a racial stigma, and in Kenya His Majesty&apos;s Government have decided that the principle should not be accepted in townships. Objections to the system which led to this conclusion in Kenya apply equally in South Africa. Experience has shown that the power of segregation tends to be used in a spirit of racialism rather than
even-handed justice, and that the class segregated is usually given inferior locality, insufficient area or inadequate municipal conveniences. Traders dealing with the same class of customer are forced into different areas, and the Indian, as a rule, is prohibited from occupying premises in the more eligible quarters. We gravely fear that if the power of enforcing compulsory segregation on lines proposed by the Union Government is once embodied in the legislation it will be so used as to make conditions of life intolerable for all Indians resident in tzrban areas.4. The cumulative effect of these measures has been to rouse profound resentment ,in India and to deepen apprehension as to the future of the domiciled Indian community in the Union. We would like to point out that, in spite of our watchfulness and reiterated representations to Government, of the Union, both on general grounds and in regard to the special measures (of which your Lordship is already aware), there has been in recent years continuous progress in legislation directed to prejudicing the position of Indians and driving them from the Dominion. Late Government sought to relieve the situation by encouraging the voluntary repatriation of Indians, and this policy, which has been operative since 1920, is also favoured by the present Ministry, wdio have recently doubled the bonus payable to an Indian who may decide to return to India. , .   .5. Now, in addition, further anti-Asiatic legislation has recently been introduced, and is now pending before the Union Parliament, which is specially designed to impose new and even more serious disabilities upon Indians and to accelerate the pace of the Indian exodus. This was made clear in Dr. Malan&apos;s statement in introducing the Area Reservation and Immigration and Registration (Further Provisions) Bill in Union Assembly last -Inly, when he said, that the measures frankly start from the general supposition that the Indian is an alien element in population and that no solution of the question would be acceptable to the country, unless it resulted, in a very considerable reduction of the Indian population. From this standpoint he has introduced a Bill the j)urpose of which is to empower urban authorities compulsorily to segregate Indians, and to confine their rights of trading and of acquiring property to the areas assigned to them. Moreover, Indians may be restricted from acquiring or leasing land outside the coast-belt in Natal. Further restrictions are placed on their rights of immigration and of bringing into the country their wives and families and of inter-provincial migration.0. April last, with your approval, we addressed the Union Government direct and. suggested a conference on their general policy towards Indians, preferably in South Africa, but if that Government so desired, in India, or on neutral ground &quot;such as Geneva. In alternative, we asked the Union Government to make other suggestions to bring about a satisfactory and permanent settlement. Union Government replied, June last, that while they were quite ready to receive suggestions from us for making their policy of repatriation more effective, they regretted their inability to agree to a conference since the white population in South Africa, which was.determined that the Indian element should be brought down to an irreducible minimum, would view it with suspicion as an interference from outside. On 14th July, with your approval, we renewed suggestions for a conference on the ground that repatriation could not alone solve the problem, since nearly 63 per cent, of Indians in South Africa were born there, and that to secure a satisfactory settlement other methods of improving the situation must be explored. On 24th September, Union Government replied regretting their inability to agree to proposals for a conference unless its scope was restricted to the discussion of concrete questions. They seemed inclined to agree to a conference only if definitely restricted to the consideration of a more effective repatriation scheme, which j in their words, &quot; will result in considerable reduction of Indian population in South Africa,&quot; and of proposals for the mitigation of competition, between Indians and Europeans in South Africa, and they asked us to formulate concrete suggestions regarding the latter. We could not accept a conference whose main object would be considerable reduction of the numbers of Indians in South Africa. We were, however, prepared to help to smooth away difficulties in any scheme-for purely voluntary repatriation, and to make suggestions regarding vocational employment, when we had sufficient data. On 9th October, we replied accordingly to the Union Government that, before entering into a discussion of the repatriation, question or making suggestions regarding competition, we desired to send a deputation to South Africa to collect information regarding the economic condition, and general position of Indians residing in the Dominion.   On 10th November, Union
-Government acceded to this request and, as your Lordship is aware, a deputation was forthwith despatched and. is at present visiting South Africa, consisting of Mr. G. F. Paddison as leader and Sir Deva Prasad Sarvadhikari. and Honourable Saiyid Raza Ali as the members. Main purpose of the deputation is to enquire into and report on the economic condition and general position of the Indian community in South Africa, and to form an appreciation of the wishes and requirements of that -community, in order to assist us in connection with the discussions now proceeding. We have explained to Union Government in our telegram of 26th November last, which was repeated to you on 30th November, that in sending our deputation we have kept the possibility of conference in view, and have hope that proposals which., we may be in a position to put forward as the result of the deputation^ report may form acceptable basis for conversations between the Union Government and our representatives. We added that we trusted the Union&apos; Government on their part would not take any action in the meantime that might preclude the possibility of such conversations, if it is ultimately agreed that they are desirable.7. Our deputation, on its way to South Africa, crossed a deputation sent by the South African Indian Congress to India as a result of an interview with the Minister -of the Interior, at which they were unable to induce him in any way to alter the policy on which the Union Government have embarked. Their object is to represent the cause of Indians in Union to Government and people of this country. Their leader, Dr. Abdur Rahman, has addressed public meetings at Bombay and Calcutta, and also at the annual session of the Indian National Congress recently held at Cawnpore and of the Muslim League held at Aligarh. He has also presented a petition to the Viceroy, copy of which, together with His Excellency&apos;s reply, has been forwarded to the India Office with Mr. Ewbanfs letter 36I-OS, 24th December 1925. Main prayer of the deputation is that as good citizens of the Union, Indians demand, restoration to them in. the Cape Province and Natal of all political rights of which fchey have been deprived, and the grant of full political and civil rights in the Transvaal and the Orange Free State as enjoyed by other communities of the Union. Dr. Abdur Rahman and his colleagues impressed on His Excellency the urgent necessity of pressing the Union Government to agree to a round-table conference, and in the event of their not agreeing to this request and forcing their Bill through the coming session of the South African Parliament, they asked that the King-Emperor^ disallowance of the. Bill should be secured under the terms of section 65 of the South Africa Act. Failing this, they have requested that an appeal be made to the League of Nations as the Bill contravenes the spirit and intention of clause 23 of the Covenant of the League of Nations.8. It will, be seen from Governor-GeneraLs telegram dated 9th December, which was repeated to you on 10th December, that Union Ministers have, given us an assurance that they will favour the fullest opportunity being given to our deP&apos;-dation of laying the case of Indians, if so desired, before Select Committee after second reading of Bill has been taken. We have thanked them for. this offer, but as the second reading will affirm the principle of the Bill, and thereafter, in Select Committee, only points of detail can be considered, it is clear that the appearance of the deputation before the Select Committee cannot be regarded as adequate substitute for round-table conference. We are therefore faced with situation of extreme gravity because (1) of imminence of acceptance of the principle of the Bill, which will be introduced into the Union Assembly soon after 22nd January, and (2) we appear to have exhausted all means within our power to move the Union Government to reconsider their attitude on main principles of their policy,.9. Government and all parties in India are agreed regarding the reasonable basis and ethical justification of the case of the Indians in South Africa. We ma)7 leave aside for the moment numerous disabilities under which Indians are suffering in South Africa,- though we should desire, if a conference was agreed upon, to express our views in regard to them and make representations. The urgent&apos; question at the moment is the principle, pending legislation, which, if once accepted, will have the effect, as indeed it is designed to have, of driving Indians from the Dominion. Visit of Dr. Abdur RahmaiVs deputation and his public utterances have brought, this question more prominently than ever before the public. Much stress in the-press and in speeches is given to complaints of ineffectiveness of Imperial connection to help Indians in South Africa. Comments are freely made that representations made regarding Indians are persistently disregarded by Union Government and that Imperial Government have so far held out no hope of effective action on their behalf.-  -   &quot; &apos;:BBH!88nS; l ;-.v-;       - .-; --- ...... ..........-...r,.-:.r-- ,
It has been stated to us that persons not born in the Einpire and persons of races, recently opposed to the British Empire in the Great War are freely admitted to all privileges of citizenship in South Africa and are not subjected to the disabilities imposed on Indians, while Indians born in India or in South Africa are humiliated, and pressed - to remove, themselves from one of His Majesty&apos;s Dominions. These contentions lead to serious criticisms of the benefits of self-government within the Empire as the goal of Indian aspirations, and accentuate the importance of the issues, not only as a question of Indian feelings and susceptibilities, profoundly though these have been stirred up by them, but also as a matter of grave concsrn in Imperial , aspect. &apos; ;&apos;. 10. We have made a full and frank statement of our difficulties to you in the assxirance   that  you   will  consider what action can be taken   by the   Imperial, Government to remedy the situation.   It is obviously useless for us to press again for a round-table conference in direct communication with,the Union Government on the questions of Indians generally and the principles of this Bill,-because previous-correspondence on , the question of a conference with them leaves no doubt that complaints regarding the reply would again take unfavourable form.   We are now,, therefore, compelled to invoke  the  assistance of  His Majesty&apos;s Government in direction of perstiading the Union Government not at present to proceed further with the Bill pending discussion with His Majesty&apos;s Government upon the principles of the measure.   Statement of Dr. Malan in introducing the Bill, that Indians (many of whom have been born in South Africa or domiciled in that country for several generations) are regarded as alien element in country, and that no.solution will be acceptable to South Africa, which does not result in the substantial reduction of their numbers, has aroused widespread indignation in India, and it is noticeable that the public feeling here has now turned from considerations of a policy of retaliation, and has concentrated on the demand for assistance of the Imperial Government. If Imperial Government is unable to do anything to help us and the Bill becomes-Jaw, the deep and lasting resentment which will be aroused will be directed almost as much against His Majesty&apos;s Government as against the Union Government.   It wilL be urged by Indians that so-called partnership of India within the Einpire is evidently intended to be no partnership, but inclusion of Indians upon inferior&apos; status.   The situation, especially in its imperial aspect, is grave, and we therefore make an earnest appeal to Your Lordship to help us by any means that seem to hold some promise of effectual results.11. It might have been unnecessary for us to make this appeal to Your Lordship-at the moment if we had any hope of making effective representations to Union Government before the second reading of Bill begins and the principle of the Bill has been accepted. We sent our deputation to South Africa forthwith when the Union Government agreed to its visit, but the position which we shall occupy when we receive their report is obviously unsatisfactory. The Ministers have informed us&apos; that the session will begin on 22nd January, and that, in ordinary course, some time will elapse before the second reading stage of the Bill will be reached. This, they add, will probably give the deputation as much time as they require for making investigations and reporting to us. Government of Union intends to move after second reading that Bill be referred to a Select Committee and full opportunity be given to deputation to lay case of Indians before Select Committee. The latter concession, as we have explained, is obviously powerless &quot;to effect what we have in view, while very short time available before second reading stage is reached will clearly not suffice for us to make proper representations based on facts reported to us by our deputation, or for the Union Government to give our views a proper hearing and consideration. We have just received private information that the programme of parliamentary session,will be settled on 14th January, and it is vitally important to-press the Union Government forthwith to delay proceeding with the Bill.Telegram from Viceroy, Department of Education, Health, and Lands, to Secretary of State for India, dated 11th January 1926.Our telegram of Sth January. Indians in South Africa. Our deputation, after-inquiry in Natal, have telegraphed their interim and provisional conclusions and recommendations, which will be communicated to you by post. On the basis of this-interim report, and in view of the extreme urgency of the matter, and the fact that our deputation expects to see General Hertzog and Dr. Malan soon after their
arrival at Cape Town on 10th January, we decided to address further representations to Union Government in a telegram, dated 10th January, which is reproduced below : &quot;Our deputation, after enquiries in Natal, have . telegraphed their interim provisional conclusions and recommendations to us. In the first place they have been unable to find, any justification for the general opinion held by Europeans in Natal that Indian competition in trade is increasing and is closing fruitful avenues of employment to Europeans. Similarly, they are unable to obtain accurate or complete statistics to indicate how far, if at all, Indians have recently displaced Europeans in skilled or semi-skilled occupations. They suggest that, if a fresh survey of the situation were undertaken, it would probably prove the fears, so far at least as trade and commerce are concerned, to be unfounded, Their investigations tend to show that Indian penetration has during the last few years increased &apos; only in certain trades, such as tailoring and furniture, especially in Durban area, while in the sphere of business proper the Indian has not improved his position since the report of the Asiatic Enquiry Commission. Further expansion of Indian trade is barred by the action of municipalities, who refuse the issue of any licences to Indians, and frequently refuse the transfer of. old licences to new premises even in close proximity to old ones. Same policy is being followed by licensing,boards in rural areas. For these reasons they suggest fresh enquiry is advisable in order to verify the facts on which demand for Bill is based.&quot; 2. The second point our deputation lays stress on is that it is questionable whether the Bill will effect any mitigation in the economic competition between the two races, which European opinion in Natal regards as the crux of the whole Asiatic problem. Positive remedies contemplated by the Bill are (1) commercial separation, (2) residential separation, and (3) restrictions provided for in clause 10. As regards (1), our deputation finds that municipal administration of existing licensing laws has already resulted in Indian traders being concentrated in areas distinct from those occupied by Europeans, except certain old-established Indian firms which carry on business in European quarters. From European point of view, therefore, legislation now proposed appears unnecessary, while it will seriously aggravate the position of the Indian trading community. They assume that the elimination of Indians from trade is not aimed at, as such a policy would not be in accordance with the general standard of fairness, particularly since they report that aliens from Europe are monopolising the new opportunities for trade. If object aimed at is mitigation of -competition, other remedies seem more likely to be effective. Allegation of unfairness of Indian competition is said to be based on payment of lower wages to shop assistants, and evasion of regulations governing the terms of employment. They consider that means could be devised to prevent such evasion, and are strongly of opinion that the matter deserves investigation, especially as they have been told that, if the board -and lodging and other amenities allowed free to Indian assistants are included, the total wages of the latter equal those paid by European employers for the same class of work.&quot; 3. With regard to residential segregation, the enquiries of our deputation confirm the objection to this measure which we have consistently urged upon Your Excellency&apos;s Government. They- report that the condition of many localities occupied by Indians -around South Africa causes Indian community to be full of apprehensiou that class -area created for them will share similar fate. Any measure tending to depress, social and economic standards of Asiatics may be expected to intensify, rather than to mitigate, industrial and commercial competition between them and the white, population. 1 -&quot; -1. In the opinion of our deputation, clause 10 of the Bill will have most &quot;serious consequences. They point out, firstly, that Indian market gardeners, who tend to cluster in every township in Natal, and a large proportion of whom held land on monthly and yearly tenure from Europeans, will be driven into coast belt, where no fresh land is available for them, as area within that belt owned by Indians is small -and almost entirely taken, up; secondly, Indian market gardeners, who are now tenants of Europeans, will be deprived of their means of livelihood ; thirdly, Indian traders outside belt, who now carry on business in premises leased from Europeans, will be driven into belt on expiration of their lease. This will impose great hardship on Indians, and many Europeans will also suffer. Asiatic congestion around Durban is already great and will seriously (corrupt group) sanitary conditions. Asiatic suburbs of Durban are already regarded as a menace (corrupt group), becomes a great source -of danger to public health.   Indians shut olf from land will turn for a living to more
-or less skilled trades in which position of Europeans will be further threatened. Out-deputation state that Durban Corporation seems to be alive to the sanitary danger of this provision of the Bill, and they add that Europeans with whom they have discussed the question have also begun to realise its probable effects.&apos;&apos;5. These facts and considerations strengthen our conviction, which we have often pressed on Union Government, that a round-table conference would be most satisfactory method of dealing with the situation, and we hope that, as result of discussion during the last few months, and of the wider implication of the Bill, there&apos; may have been some such&apos;modification in the attitude of the European public, referred to in your telegram of 24th September, as to justify your Government in reconsidering the view they have taken of this proposal. We wish to make it clear that we are still willing and anxious to participate in a round-table conference in any place or-manner which may seem to them most convenient.&quot; 6. If for any reason the Government of South Africa hud themselves still unable to. agree to a round-table conference, we hope that the Union Government will agree there is a prima facie case for some fresh inquiry before the proposed legislation is proceeded with. Apart from other considerations the inquiry appears to be necessary,, firstly because exact facts regarding the extent of Indian competition in trade and industry do not seem to be fully known, and, secondly, because ultimate consequences of proposed legislation may be reverse of those which are expected and desired. We understand that our deputation will reach Cape Town on JLOfch January, and we should be grateful if a Minister of the Government, would consent to receive them informally and give them opportunity of explaining and illustrating more fully the arguments in favour of holding an inquiry which we have only been able to indicate in brief outline. We believe that there is a great deal to be said in favour of allowing representatives of the Indian community in South Africa and our representatives to-place their views before a committee of inquiry before proceeding any further with Bill.: The moral effect of holding the inquiry would be great. It. would convince-Indian opinion that the Union Government were not averse to hearing representations which can be urged against the policy embodied in the Bill, and that Parliament - will not allow Indian case to be prejudiced because they are not represented politically.&quot;Your Lordship will- observe that we have again pressed the Union Government to-agree to round-table conference as the most satisfactory method of dealing with situation, and, failing that, the institution of fresh enquiry into the economic position before legislation is proceeded with. Third course, which has been suggested by our deputation, after private conversations with the Governor-General, and which they understand is constitutionally feasible, is that the Union Government should be asked to agree to refer Bill to Select Committee before the second reading instead of after it, in order to allow the Indian community in South Africa and our representatives opportunity of representations before the Committee on question of principle as well as of detail. We quite realise that appearance of deputation before Select Committee, if Select Committee is granted before second reading, has advantage. It might result in some delay, which we would welcome. It would not commit us to principle of the Bill, which is one of our essential tactical requirements. But, at the same time, the Select Committee would consist of members of parties already committed to Bill, in principle, and if so, representations would probably not receive much consideration at their hands. For this reason, at this stage, we have preferred to take the stand, first and foremost, on round-table conference, and secondly, if that is refused, on an enquiry before any Parliamentary step is taken as regards the Bill. It is possible that both these requests will be rejected by the Union Government, who may then offer a Select Committee before second reading. If they -do so, offer can then be considered ; but we have made it clear to our deputation that it need not be suggested at this stage as a measure which is considered adequate by us.Private Telegram from Viceroy to Secretary of State for India, dated 8th January 1926.38 C. Private and personal. My Government are sending you an important telegram regarding Indians in South Africa and impending anti-Asiatic legislation. Situation is serious and there is urgent need for action. Principle of Bill has been repeatedly condemned and repudiated by us and by Lange Commission, but Union Government are forcing on the second reading stage. Dr. Malan has openly stated that the object of the Bill is to stifle Indians as an alien element in population of
Uniou and. reduce their numbers in the Union. Union Government have refused to confer with the Government of India on the position of Indians generally and the principle of the Bill, though they offered to confer on concrete questions if the purpose of conference was restricted to securing effective repatriation, which was defined as measures to secure considerable reduction of Indian population. We could not accept conference with the latter object. It seems unlikely that, in the short time left before second reading, we shall have opportunity to make further effective representations based on facts supplied by our deputation now in South Africa, or that if we do make representations they will receive proper hearing and consideration by Union Government. Only concession made by them is that after second reading of the Bill, Bill will be referred to Select Committee who will hear our deputation. This concession is useless because, once principle of the Bill has been affirmed by passing the second reading stage, no modifications of the details can really help Indians in South Africa. If the principle is accepted, the Bill will be used to drive Indians, already  subjected in all directions to special disabilities, out of the Dominion. Our only hope, though I realise the difficulties of His Majesty&apos;s Government, is that His Majesty&apos;s Government may secure the postponement of second reading while the principle is discussed.2. Imperial aspect of the Bill is the seriousness of Indian feeling that imperial connection is of no use in protecting them, as the Government of India&apos;s representations are ignored by the Union Government, and His Majesty&apos;s Government have not so far secured any alleviation of the hostile measure directed against them in the Union. It is further said that the present Government has not made any attempt in this direction. They feel that partnership of India in the Empire merely means inclusion of Indians in the Empire on inferior standing which offers no advantage or privilege. Gandhi has reminded them that we went to war with the Transvaal over similar question when it affected white people. Deputation from South Africa now in India have repeatedly alleged that it is better to be born outside the Empire as aliens, and even enemy subjects in the late war are admitted to privileges and excused from disabilities in the Union, while latter are heaped on Indians with a view to drive them from the Dominion.3. From interim reports received from our deputation I gather that the question of reducing the number of Indians is, at the moment, perhaps less racial than economic. Main difficulty is the competition of Indians in trades with the Dutch and poor whites. If the second reading of the Bill could be postponed wdrile the economic side of the question was investigated it would probably lead to some alleviation, of the Indian situation. Increasing influx of Italians and others from Eastern Europe, with low standards of wage and living, seems, in the end, at least as likely to threaten and extinguish the existing vested interests in a number of petty trades and occupations as Indian competition.4. The Metropolitan has decided to visit South Africa, with the assent of the Archbishop of Capetown, early in February, in order .to rouse feeling in the churches on behalf of Indians, and try to stimulate sense of justice in the public. In viewing the problem, he will represent the Indian Christians Council.953B

</content>
</cab>
