<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/178/0 images: 285-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY,(This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty1s Government)SECRET. CP.41  (26).119C A E I H E T.HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE. aliLEAD PAINTS BILL. Memorandum by the Home Secretary.The object of this Bill is to enable Regulations to be made for the protection of the health of painters using lead paint.      I circulated the Bill to the Cabinet in April last (C.P.202(25))   a,nd the Bill was introduced last  Session but made no progress.The Bill will be criticised by the Labour Party on the ground that it does not include any provision as to the prohibition of  lead paint for internal work,  but I believe there will be no serious objection to the proposal for Regulations.      A draft of the Regulations was in fact agreed upon between the Home Office and the industry three years ago,  but they cannot be brought into force until legislation is passed.This Bill might be introduced into the House of -Lords.W.J.H.5th February,   1926.
B  I LTOMake better provision for the protection against A.D. 1925. lead poisoning of persons employed in painting buildings.)E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the  advice  and  consent  of  the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of 5 the same, as follows : 1. (1) The Secretary of State may make regula- Regulations tions for preventing danger from the use of lead paint as to use of to  persons employed  in  painting buildings, and in lead paint, particular 10 (a) for prohibiting the use of any lead compound except in the form of paste or paint ready for use;(b) for the prevention of danger arising from theapplication   of   lead fpaint in the form   of 15 spray;(c) for the prevention so far as practicable of dangerarising from dust caused by dry rubbing down and scraping;(d) for providing for the medical examination of 20 persons employed in painting with lead paint,and for the suspension from such employment of persons whose health is or appears likely to be mjuriously affected thereby; (e); for securing that faculties for washing during, 25 and on cessation of, work are afforded to personsemployed in painting;[Bill 167] A
Lead Paint (Protection,        [15 Geo. 5.] against Poisoning).A.D. 1925. (/) fora the use of protective clothing by personsso employed and for preventing clothes left off during work from being soiled by paint;  and (g) for the distribution to persons so employed of instructions with regard to hygienic pre- 5 cautions to be taken.ij(     (2) The provisions of sections eighty, eighty-one and eighty-four of the Factory and Workshop Act, 1901 (which relate to procedure in connection with the making of regulations), shah apply as respects regulations made 10 under this section.2. On and after the nineteenth day of November, nineteen hundred and twenty-seven, it shall not be lawful to employ any woman or young person in pamting any part of a building with lead paint: 15Provided that this section shaU not apply to the employment of(a) persons employed as apprentices in the painting trade under   arrangements  approved  by an order of the Secretary of  State made after 20 consultation with  the  organisations, if any, representative of the employers and workers in the trade ; or (&amp;) women or young persons in such special decorated-tive or other work (not being work of an indus- 25 trial character) as may be excluded from the provisions of this section by an order of the Secretary of State.Prohibition of employ-ment of women and young per-sons in painting buildings with lead paint.Application of certain provisions of the Fac-tory and Workshop Act, 1901.3. The provisions of section seventy-three (which relates to notification of diseases in factories), sections 30 eighty-five and eighty-six (which relate respectively to breaches and publication of regulations), sections one hundred and nineteen to one hundred and twenty-one (which relate to powers and duties of inspectors), and Part IX. (which relates to legal proceedings) of the 35 Factory and Workshop Act, 1901, shall apply in any case where persons are employed in painting buildings as if the places where they are employed were factories, and as if the persons by whom they are employed were the occupiers of the factories, and with such further or 40 other modifications as may be made by order of the Secretary of State for the purpose of making those pro-visions applicable to the painting of buildings.
14. (1)  Every   person who by way of trade or A.D. 1925. business employs persons in painting buildings shall send      ,  to the Inspector of Factories for the district in which his ^ums^&amp;c office is situated a notice in writing stating his name and    .    &apos; 5 the address of Ms office, and shall keep at his office a register which shall be available for inspection by an inspector of factories at all reasonable times, containing such particulars as to the persons so employed by him, and as to the work on which they are employed as 10 may be prescribed,  and shall make such returns to the Inspector of Factories for the district as may be prescribed.(2) Any person failing to comply with the require-ments of this section shall be liable on summary convic-15 tion to a fine not exceeding three pounds.5.-(1) Where  an  inspector  under  the  Factory Power to and Workshop Act, 1901, suspects that any substance take sam&quot; used or intended for use in painting a building contains p es&apos; a lead compound, he may at any time take for analysis 2Q sufficient samples of that substance.(2) If any person who employs persons in painting buildings refuses to allow an inspector to take samples in pursuance of this section, or to give him facilities for the purpose, he shall be liable on summary conviction 125 to a fine not exceeding three pounds :Provided that any such person may, at the time when a sample is taken under this section, and on pro-viding the necessary appliances, require the inspector to divide the sample into two parts and to mark and seal 30 and deliver to him one such part.(3) A certificate purporting to be a certificate by the Government chemist at the Government Laboratory as to the result of an analysis of a sample under this section shall, in any proceedings under this Act, be evidence of J35 the matters stated therein, unless either party requires the person by whom the analysis was made to be called as a witness.(4) It shall not be lawful for any person, except in so far as is necessary for the purposes of a prosecution 1^0 for a contravention of this Act, to publish or disclose to airy person the results of an analysis made under this soction.[167] A 2
I1&quot;154. (1)  Every   person who by way of trade or A.D. 1925. business employs persons in painting buildings shall send      ;  to the Inspector of Factories for the district in which Ms ^turnslfc office is situated a notice in writing stating his name and    .    &apos; the address of his office, and shall keep at his office a register which shall be available for inspection by an inspector of factories at all reasonable times, containing such particulars as to the persons so employed by him, and as to the work on which they are employed as may be prescribed,   and shall make such returns to the Inspector of Factories for the district as may be prescribed.(2) Any person failing to comply with the require-ments of this section shall be liable on summary convic-tion to a fine not exceeding three pounds.5. (1) Where  an  inspector  under  the  Factory Power to and Workshop Act, 1901, suspects that any substance t^,ke sam&quot; used or intended for use in painting a building contains p es&quot; a lead compound, he may at any time take for analysis I20 sufficient samples of that substance.(2) If any person who employs persons in painting buildings refuses to allow an inspector to take samples in pursuance of this section, or to give him facilities for the purpose, he shall be liable on summary conviction 125 to a fine not exceeding three pounds :Provided that any such person may, at the time when a sample is taken under this section, and on pro-viding the necessary appliances, require the inspector to divide the sample into two parts and to mark and seal BO and deliver to him one such part.(3) A certificate purporting to be a certificate by the Government chemist at the Government Laboratory as to the result of an analysis of a sample under this section shall, in any proceedings under this Act, be evidence of 35 the matters stated therein, unless either party requires the person by whom the analysis was made to be called as a witness.(4) It shall not be lawful for any person, except in so far as is necessary for the purposes of a prosecution lO for a contravention of this Act, to publish or disclose to any person the results of an analysis made under this section.[167]A 2
&quot; Lead Paint (Protection      [15 Geo. 5.] against Poisoning).A.D. 1925.Application to employ -ment under the Crown.Definition.Short title, construc-tion, com-mencement and extent.If any person acts in contravention of the provisions of this subsection, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds.6. This Act shall apply where persons are employed in painting buildings by or under the Crown in like 5 manner as if the employers were private persons.7. In this Act the expression &quot; lead paint &quot; means any paint, filling, or painter&apos;s material which, when treated in a manner prescribed by rules made by the Secretary of State yields to an aqueous solution of 10 hydro-chloric acid, a quantity of soluble lead compound exceeding, when calculated as lead monoxide, five per cent, of the dry weight of the portion taken for analysis.9. (1) This Act may be cited as the Lead Paint (Protection against Poisoning) Act, 1925, and shall be 15 construed as one with the factory and Workshop Acts, 1901 to 1920.(2) This Act shall come into operation   on the first day of January, nineteen hundred and twenty-six.(3) This Act shall not extend to Northern Ireland.    20

against Poisoning).AB   ILLTo make better provision for theSecretary Sir William Joynson-Hicks.Ordered, by The House of Commons, to be Printed, 1 May 1925..LONDON:PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE.To be purchased directly from H.M. Stationery Office at the following addresses: Adaatral House, Kingsway, London, W.C. 2; 28, Abingdon Street, London, S.W. 1; York Street, Manchester: 1, St. Andrew&apos;8 CreBccnt, Cardiff; or 120, George Street, Edinburgh; or through any Bookseller.Presented byPrinted by Eyre and Spottiswoode, Ltd., East Harding Street, E.C. 4. Printers to the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty.[Price 2d. Net.][Bill 167]

</content>
</cab>
