<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/178/0 images: 630-666</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL&apos;LIBRARY0 A B I N E T.SECRET C.P.77(26).ELECTRICITY (SUPPLY) BILL.Memorandum for the Home Affairs Committee of the Cabinet by the Minister of Transport.I circulate herewith revised copies of the above Bill which I ask leave to introduce at a very early date.The Bill, as now drafted, contains certain alterations from that which was generally approved by the Cabinet last December (Cabinet 6l(25) 3).     These alterations have been made after consideration &amp;f the representations made by the various bodies concerned.     The Attorney-General proposes to explain the most important of these changes at the Committee.(SD.)   WILFRID ASHLEY.19/2/26.m
Electricity Supply bill arrangement OF CLAUSES.Constitution and General Powers oe Central Electricity Board.Clause.1.   Constitution of Central Electricity Board.2.   General powers and duties of Board.3.   Appointment of consultative technical committees.Provisions as to Scheme.4.   Duty of Board to prepare and carry out scheme. 5.   Existing selected stations. 6.   New selected stations.7.   Obligations and rights of owners of selected stations. 8.   Construction and acquisition of main transmission lines.9.   Standardisation of frequency.10.   Obligation of Board to supply electricity to autho-rised undertakers. 11.   Tariff for electricity supplied by Board. 12.   Price of indirect supply in bulk. 13.   Limitation on price to be charged to owners of selected stations. 14.   Power to reduce charges of undertakers who decline to take supply from Board. 15.   Compensation for deprivation of employment. 16.   Powers of authorised undertakers. 17.   Saving for necessity of obtaining certain consents.Subsidiary Provisions as to the Board. 18.   Application of Electricity (Supply) Acts to Board. 19.   Acquisition of land by the Board. 20.   Power of Board to use main transmission lines by agreement.21.   Power of Board to purchase surplus electricity. 22.   Annual report, statistics and returns.Financial Provisions.23.   Expenses of the Board. 24.   Power of Board to borrow.26-5 A
Clause.25,   Power to aiithorise issue of stock.26.   Power to Treasury to guarantee loans to Board.27.   Accounts and audit.&apos;  Miscellaneous Provisions.28.   Charges for electricity supplied by power companies.29.   Relation of charges to dividends.30.   Power to lop trees obstructing electric lines.31.   Schemes for constitution of electricity districts, andthe organisation of supply therein. 32.   Contents of schemes. 33.   Amendment of schemes.34.   Provisions as to companies with large  area  of supply.35.   Terms of purchase of a company taking a bulksupply. 36.   Methods of charge.37.   Amendment of Schedule to 62 &amp; 63 Viet. c. 12. 38.   Minor amendments.General.39.   Interpretation.40    Short title, construction, commencement and extent. Schedules.
DRAFTof aB   I   L LtoAmend the law with respect to the supply of     a.d. 192&amp; electricity.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows : Constitution and General Powers of Central Electricity Board.1. (1) For the purpose of this Act there shall be Constitution established as soon as may be after the passing of this 01 Central 10 Act a body to be called the Central Electricity Board, Electricity consisting of a chairman appointed by the Minister of   oar &apos; Transport after consultation with the Electricity Com-missioners, and seven other members of whom (a) five shall be appointed by the Minister of Trans-15 port, after consultation with the ElectricityCommissioners and such other bodies as he may think fit, two being persons of experience in local government, two being persons of experience in authorised electrical undertakings 20 ! carried on by companies, and one being a person of experience in railway business;(b) one shall be appointed by the Minister of Trans-port, after consultation with the  Board of Trade, as a representative of industry; 25        (c) one shall be appointed by the Minister of Trans-port after consultation with the Treasury.26-5 A 2
A-D. 1926.Alternative for subsection (1).(1) For the purposes of this Act there shall be established as soon as may be after the passing of this Act a body to be called the Central Electricity Board, consisting of a chairman and seven other members 5 appointed by the Minister of Transport after consultation with the Electricity Commissioners, and such other bodies representative of local government, the electrical industry, and large consumers of electricity, as the Minister thinks fit. 1(2) The Central Electricity Board (hereinafter re-ferred to as the Board) shall be a body corporate with power to hold land without licence in mortmain.(3) The Board may act notwithstanding a vacancy(4) A person appointed to be the chairman or to be a member of the Board shall hold office for such term not less than five years as may be determined by the Minister before his appointment.(5) The Board shall appoint a secretary and such 20 other officers and servants as the Board may determine, and there shall be paid out of the fund hereafter estab-lished to the members of the Board, or any of them, such salaries or fees and allowances for expenses as the Minister of Transport may determine, and to the secre- 25 tary, officers, and servants of the Board such salaries and remuneration, and, on retirement, such pensions and gratuities as the Board may determine; and any expenses incurred by the Board in the exercise and performance of their powers and duties under this Act  shall be 30 defrayed out of the said fund.(6) The Board shall have a common seal, and the seal of the Board shall be authenticated by the signature of the chairman of the Board or some other member of the Board authorised by the Board to act in that behalf, 35 and of the secretary, or some other person authorised by the Board to act in that behalf.(7) Every document purporting to be an order or other instrument issued by the Board and to be sealed with the seal of the Board authenticated in manner pro- 40 vided by this section, or to be signed by the secretary or any person authorised to act in that behalf, shall bein their number.15
received in evidence and be deemed to be such order or A.D. 1926. instrument without further proof unless the contrary is shown..2.-(1) The Board shall be charged with the duty of General 5 supplying electricity to authorised undertakers in ac- ^^QgS0f accordance with the provisions of this Act, but shall not, the u0ard. save as hereinafter expressly provided, themselves gene-rate electricity, and the Board shall have such further powers and duties as are provided by this Act.10 (2) It shall be lawful for the Board, with the approval of the Electricity Commissioners, to enter into arrangements with any authorised undertakers or other bodies for the exercise by such bodies on behalf of the Board of any of the powers of the Board under this Act15 which the Board think can more expediently be exercised locally.3. (1) The Board shall appoint one or more con- Appoint-consultative technical committees consisting of engineers ment of employed in connection with generating stations which  j^^chni20 are by virtue of this Act for the time being selected cai com. stations. mittees.(2) A consultative technical committee shall give advice and assistance on such matters as may be referred to the committee by the- Board, and for that purpose25 the committee shall meet from time to time as the Board may determine.Provisions as to Scheme.4. (1) The Board shall, as soon as practicable, Duty of prepare and submit to the Electricity Commissioners Board to 30 a scheme- prepare and carry out(a) determining what generating stations (whether scheme.existing stations or new stations) shall be the stations (in this Act referred to as selected stations) at Avhich electricity shall be generated 35 for the purposes of the Board;(b) providing for interconnection, by means of maintransmission lines to be constructed or acquired by the Board, of selected stations with one another and with the systems of authorised 40 undertakers;
A.D. 1926. (c) providing for such standardisation of frequency  as may be essential to the carrying out of theproposals for such interconnection as aforesaid;(d) enabling or requiring temporary arrangements(to be in force during the carrying out of the 5 scheme) to be made between the Board and owners of generating stations (whether autho-rised undertakers or not) with respect to the giving and taking to and by the Board of supplies of electricity, and with respect to the 10 working of generating stations (whether selected stations or not) by the owners thereof, upon such terms as in default of agreement may be determined by the Electricity Commissioners;(e) containing such  supplemental, incidental and 15consequential provisions as may appear necessary or expedient for any of the purposes aforesaid :Provided that a private generating station shall not without the consent of the owners thereof be included in the scheme as a selected station, nor shall the owners 20 of such a station be required to enter into any temporary arrangements under the scheme.(2) The Electricity Commissioners shall cause the scheme to be published, and shall give to authorised undertakers and to other persons who appear to the 25 Commissioners to be interested an opportunity of making representations thereon, and the Commissioners after considering the scheme and such representations, may confirm the scheme either without modifications, or subject to such modifications as th.ey think fit, and either 30 generally or as respects any specified area or areas, and Where the scheme has been confirmed as respects certain areas it may subsequently be confirmed as respects other areas.(3) As soon as the scheme is confirmed by the Elec- 35 tricity Commissioners, or is confirmed as respects any area, it shall be the duty of the Board to carry out and give effect to the scheme, or to carry out and give effect to the scheme within the area, as the case may be.(4) A scheme may from time to time be altered or 40 extended by a scheme made in like manner as the original scheme.Existing 5. (1) The Board shall make arrangements withselected       the owners of existing generating stations which by stations.
virtue of the scheme are to become selected stations A.D. 1926. for the stations being operated in accordance with the provisions of this Act, and for such extensions and alterations thereof as may be required by or under 5 the scheme and such additional extensions and alterations as the Board may from time to time direct: -Provided that if the owners of any such station consider that any directions of the Board requiring additional extensions or alterations are unreasonable, 10 they may appeal to the Electricity Commissioners, with a further right of appeal to the Railway and Canal Commission, against the decision of those Commissioners.(2) If the OAvners of any such station are unwilling to enter into or fail to carry out any such arrangements15 to the satisfaction of the Board, the Board shall be entitled to acquire the generating station at a price to be determined in accordance with the provisions of the First Schedule to this Act and on payment or tender of such price the Minister of Transport may make an order20 vesting the generating station in the Board.(3) Where the Board acquire a generating station under this section, they may carry out such extensions or alterations thereof as are required by the scheme or as they think fit, and may either operate it themselves 25 or make arrangements with any authorised undertakers or other company or person to operate it:Provided that the Board shall not themselves operate such a generating station unless, they satisfy the electrical -city Commissioners that i hey are unable to enter into an 30 arrangement with any authorised undertakers or other company or person to operate it on reasonable terms.6. (1) The Board may make arrangements with New se-any authorised undertakers or with any company or lected person not being authorised undertakers for the provision 8 a lons&quot;35 of such new stations as are required by the scheme.(2) If the Board satisfy the Electricity Commis-sioners that they are unable to enter into an arrange-ment with any authorised undertakers, company, or person for the provision of any such new station on40 reasonable terms, the Commissioners may by a special order under section twenty-six of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, authorise the Board to provide the station themselves.
A.D. 1926. (3) Where the Board themselves provide a newgenerating station, they may operate it themselves, or make arrangements with any authorised undertakers or other company or person to operate it:Provided that the Board shall not themselves 5 operate such a generating station unless they satisfy the Electricity Commissioners that they are unable to enter into an arrangement with any authorised undertakers or other company or person to operate it on reasonable terms. 10Obligations 7. (1) As from such date as may be fixed by theand rights    Board, the owners of a selected station shall be underselectT8 0f the obligation-stations (a) *G generate electricity and operate the station at such times and in such manner as the Board 15 may direct, and to conduct such operations with due regard to economy and efficiency; (b) to sell to the Board all electricity generated at the station at such price  as is hereinafter mentioned. &apos;        20(2) The owners of a selected station, if authorised undertakers, shall (subject to the provisions of this Act enabling the Board to require authorised undertakers to take the whole of their supply from the Board and without prejudice to the powers of such owners to 25 demand a supply under the other provisions of this Act) be entitled to be supplied by the Board from that station at such price as hereinafter mentioned with such amount of electricity as they may require for the purposes of their undertaking not exceeding the amount generated 30 at the station.(3) The price to be paid by the Board to the owners of a selected station for electricity generated thereat shall be the cost of production to be ascertained in accordance with the rules contained in the Second 35 Schedule to this Act.(4) The price at which electricity shall be supplied by the Board from a selected station to the owners of that station shall be either (a) the cost of production ascertained in manner 40 provided   by the  last   foregoing   subsection adjusted according to load factor, together with a proper proportion of the Board&apos;s expenses
other than those incurred by the Board in the A.D. 1926. purchase or generation of electricity; or , &apos; - (6) according to the tariff fixed under this Act for the supply of electricity by the Board; 5 whichever is the lower.(5) If any question between the Board and the owners of a selected station arises under this section, it shall be determined by the Electricity Commissioners : Provided that, pending the determination of the 10 question by the Commissioners,  the owners of the station shall comply with any requirements which may be made by the Board, and the price at which electricity is to be supplied by or to the owners of the station shall be such as may have been determined by the Board, 15 subject   to   such   subsequent   adjustment   as   may be necessary to give effect to the decision of the Commissioners.8. (1) As soon as may be after a scheme under Constmc-this Act has been confirmed as respects any area, the tion and20 Board shall construct and lay down the main trans- q^^1011 mission lines required for the interconnection of selected transmission stations with one  another and with the systems of mines. authorised undertakers in accordance with the scheme so far as it relates to that area.25 (2) Where a scheme provides for the acquisition by the Board of any main transmission lines belonging to any authorised undertakers, such transmission lines shall, on notice being given by the Board to the under-takers and on payment or tender to the undertakers of30 the price to be determined in accordance with the First Schedule to this Act, vest in the Board upon an order to that effect being made by the Minister of Transport.9e (1) The  Board may  require any authorised Standardi-undertakers or the owners of any selected station to sation of35 amend or alter the frequency employed in their under- frequency, taking or station, if and so far as such amendment or alteration is required to effect the standardisation of frequency provided by or under the scheme, or to effect such standardisation of frequency as the Board with40 the approval of the Electricity Commissioners may think expedient, subject to the payment to the authorised undertakers or owners of any expenses which they may properly incur in carrying such requirements into effect (including the cost of altering or replacing plant belonging26 B
A.D. 1926. to consumers); and it shall be the duty of the undertakers -       or owners to comply with such requirements and they are hereby authorised to do so notwithstanding anything in any special Act or Order relating to their undertaking.(2) The payment of any such expenses shall be a 5 purpose for which the Board may borrow under this Act, but such part of the revenue of the Board as is required to meet the interest on and sinking fund charges in respect of money so borrowed shall be excluded in any computation of receipts made in estimating the net 10 annual value of rateable hereditaments occupied by the Board for the purposes of their undertaking.(3) Any question of the amount of the expenses properly incurred by authorised undertakers or owners in  carrying  out any  such requirement  shall in  de- 15 fault of agreement be determined by the Electricity Commissioners.Obligation 10. (1) As soon as the Board notify that the carry-of Board to ing out of a scheme has been completed as respects any supply        area, the Board shall, subject to the provisions of this 20 toauthoy    ^c*&apos; ^e under an obligation to supply either directly or rised under- indirectly to any authorised undertakers in that area takers.        demanding such a supply such an amount of electricity as  they, require  for   their   undertaking  at   a   price ascertained in accordance with the provisions of this 25 Act :Provided that the Board shall not (a) supply electricity directly to authorised under-takers situatedv in the area of supply of a power company without the consent of the 30 power company unless the undertakers have an absolute right of veto on any right of the power company to supply electricity within the area of supply of those undertakers; (6) without the consent of the Electricity Com- 35 missioners, supply electricity directly to any authorised undertakers in the district of a joint electricity authority which the joint electricity authority are authorised to supply. (2) Where  any authorised undertakers  have de- 40 manded such a supply from the Board, and it appears to the Board that the outlay incurred in providing the transmission lines required for the supply would, having regard to  the  supply required,  entail  unreasonable
ISOexpense on the Board, they may represent the case to  A.D. 1926. the Electricity Commissioners, and the Commissioners        may, if it seems to them to be just, authorise the Board to impose such terms and conditions as the Commis-5 sioners think fit, on the giving of the supply.(3) Where any authorised undertakers owning a generating station, not being a selected station, demand a supply of electricity from the Board, the Board may make it a condition of furnishing such a supply that10 the undertakers shah take the whole quantity of electricity required for their undertaking, directly or indirectly, from the Board, and where any such authorised undertakers demand a siipply from any other undertakers who themselves receive a supply from the Board, the15 last-mentioned undertakers shall, if the Board so require, impose the like condition (which condition those under-takers are, if so required, authorised to impose notwith-standing anything in the special Act or order relating to the undertaking) :20       Provided that (a) The Board shall not impose or require theimposition of such a condition unless satisfied that the cost per unit to the undertakers of taking the whole of their supply directly25 or indirectly from the Board will be lessthan the cost per unit at which electricity is then being produced at the generating station of the undertakers, and in determining such cost of production no account shall be taken30 of interest or sinking fund charges in respectof capital expended on the station; and(b) where the authorised undertakers feel aggrievedby the imposition of such a condition as aforesaid, they may appeal to the Electricity 35 Commissioners, whose decision shall be final.(4) The Board may, before the carrying out of the scheme in any area is completed, if they think fit, enter into arrangements with any authorised undertakers in the area (being undertakers to whom the Board on the 40 completion of the scheme would be entitled to give a direct supply) for giving those undertakers, pending the completion of the scheme, a supply of electricity of such amount and upon such terms as may be agreed between them.26 B 2
A.D. 1926.Tariff for -electricity supplied directly by Board.Price of indirect supply in bulk.11. -(1) Subject to the provisions of this Act as to the sale of electricity to the owners of selected stations, the price to be charged by the Board for electricity supplied directly by them to authorised undertakers demanding such a supply shall be in accordance with 5 such tariff as may be fixed by the Board from time to time, and the tariff shall be fixed so that over a term of years to be approved by the Electricity Commissioners the receipts on income account shall be sufficient to cover the expenditure on income account, including interest and 10 sinking fund charges, with such margin as the Electricity Commissioners may allow.(2) The tariff shall be so framed as to include as part of the charge and show separately-(a) a fixed charges component;(6) a running charges component;and for this purpose the . fixed charges component and the running charges component shall be ascertained on the like principles as those set forth in the Seventh Schedule to this Act.1520(3) The tariff fixed under this section may, if the Board think fit, be different for different areas.12. Where   any  authorised  undertakers  take  a supply of electricity directly or indirectly  from  the Board, the price charged by them for the supply of 25 electricity in bulk to any other authorised undertakers shall, notwithstanding anything in the special Act or Order relating to their undertaking, be on the same terms as those on which the undertakers receive the supply directly or indirectly from the Board, together with such 30 charges and allowances in respect of any transmission line or part thereof belonging to the undertakers giving the supply in bulk and used for the purpose of that supply as are mentioned in the Third Schedule to this Act; and if any question arises as to the amount of the 35 price to be so charged, it shall be determined by the Electricity Commissioners.Limitation 13. Where any authorised undertakers being theon price to owners of a selected station who take  a supply of be charged electricity from the Board prove to the satisfaction of 40seized the Electricity Commissioners that the cost of takingstations. that supply from the Board on the terms provided by
this Act in any year during the period of seven years A.D. 1926. from the date when they commenced to take a supply   from the Board exceeds the cost which they would have incurred had this Act not been passed in themselves f. generating the like quantity of electricity, then the charges by the Board to those undertakers for the supplies of electricity furnished to them shall be so adjusted that the amount charged in that year does not exceed the cost which the undertakers would have 10 incurred in themselves generating the electricity.14. (1) Where in any year the Board notify to Power to any authorised undertakers owning a generating station, abate not being a selected station, that the Board are in a undertakers position to supply directly or indirectly to those under- w^0 decline15 takers the whole quantity of electricity required for to take their undertaking on specified terms, and are satisfied supply from that the cost of the supply on those terms is below Board-the then prevailing cost to those undertakers, and those undertakers refuse or within three months after such20 notification fail to agree to take such supply directly or indirectly from the Board, then, if the Electricity Commissioners are satisfied as respects the next subse-quent year that the cost of production of electricity generated by those undertakers substantially exceeded25 the cost they would have incurred had they purchased the like quantity of electricity directly or indirectly from the Board on the specified terms, the Electricity Commis-sioners shall by order require the authorised undertakers to make such abatement from the rates and charges30 for electricity for the ensuing year that the estimated aggregate amount of the abatements will be as near as may be equal to the amount of such excess as aforesaid.(2) Where any such undertakers have so refused or failed to agree to take a. supply directly or indirectly35 from the Board, then, notwithstanding anything in the special Act or order relating to the undertaking, it shall not be lawful for them subsequently to increase their then existing rates and charges for electricity without the consent of the Electricity Commissioners.40 (3) In calculating for the purposes of this section the cost of production of electricity generated by the authorised undertakers, no account shall be taken of interest or sinking fund charges in respect of capital expended on the generating station.
A.D. 1926. (4) For the purposes of this section, any authorised - undertakers owning a generating station not being a selected station shall on being so required by the Electricity Commissioners furnish them with a statement showing the cost of production of electricity at that 5 station for such period and certified in such manner as the Commissioners may direct.Compensa-tion for deprivation of employ-ment.Powers of authorised undertakers.15. Section sixteen of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, as amended by section twenty-one of the Elec-tricity (Supply) Act, 1922, shall, with the necessary adaptations, apply to any officer or servant of any autho-rised undertakers affected by the closing (permanent or temporary) or the acquisition of a generating station under or in consequence of this Act, and for that purpose that section as so amended shall have effect as set out and adapted in the Fourth Schedule to this Act.101516. (1) Where under this Act the Board is autho-rised or required to enter into arrangements with authorised undertakers for any purpose, then, notwith-standing anything in any Special Act or Order, or any 20 other instrument regulating the constitution or powers of the undertakers, it shall be lawful for the authorised undertakers, whether a joint electricity authority a local authority or a company, to enter into and carry out any such arrangements. 25(2) The carrying out of any such arrangements shall be a purpose for which authorised undertakers, being a local authority or a joint electricity authority may borrow under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922. 30(3) Where the carrying out of any such arrange-ment by authorised undertakers, being a company, involves capital expenditure, and owing to limitations on the powers of the company to raise capital the company cannot raise the necessary capital without the 35 authority of an Act of Parliament, the company may submit to the High Court (or in Scotland the Court of Session), a scheme providing for increasing all or any of the existing classes of loan or share capital of the company, or creating new classes of loan or share 40 capital, with such rights, priorities and conditions as may be specified in the scheme; and if the scheme is approved by the Court, then, notwithstanding anything
in any special Act affecting the company or the holders A.D. 1926. of any class of loan or share capital in the company,   the additional capital of each class shall form part and rank pari passu with the existing capital of that class, 5 and any new class of capital may with the consent of the majority in value of the holders of any class of security affected rank before any existing class of capital.17. Where the carrying out of any part of the Saving for 10 scheme, or any arrangement or requirement in connection necessity oi therewith, would involve any operation for which any ^ttin^ consent or approval of the Minister of Transport or the consents Electricity Commissioners would be necessary under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, nothing in the 15 foregoing provisions of this Act shall relieve the Board or any authorised undertakers or other persons con-cerned from the necessity of obtaining such consent or approval.Subsidiary Provisions as to the Board.20        18. (I) Subject to the provisions of this section, Application the Board shall be deemed to be undertakers and autho- of electrical -rised undertakers within the meaning of the Electricity ^cL to   y (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922,. and this Act in relation Board. to the Board shall be deemed to be a special Act for25 the purposes of those Acts, and for the purposes of this section there shall be incorporated with this Act the provisions of the Schedule to the Electric Lighting Clauses Act, 1899, subject to such exceptions and modifications as may be prescribed by  regulations  made  by the30 Electricity Commissioners :Provided that sections two and three of the Electric Lighting Act, 1888 (which relate to the purchase of undertakings by local authorities) shall not apply to the undertaking of the Board.35 (2) The Board shall not supply electricity to persons not being authorised undertakers except that with the consent of the Electricity Commissioners, they may furnish a supply to any company, body, or person requiring a supply for power purposes in any area not40 forming part of the area of supply of any authorised undertakers, but where electricity is supplied by the
A.D. 1926. Board, to a company, body or person requiring a supply        for power purposes it may be used by that company, body or person for lighting any premises in any part of which the power is utilised.Acquisition of land by the Board.Power of Board to use main transmis-sion lines by agree-ment.Power of Board to purchase surplus electricity.Annual report, statistics and re-turns.19. The Board may acquire land or any easements 5 or other rights in or over land voluntarily, or may be authorised to acquire land or any such right compulsorily, for the purpose of any of their powers and duties under this Act (including the construction of main transmission lines) in like manner as a local authority being authorised 10 undertakers may acquire or be authorised to acquire land under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, for the purpose of a generating station, and those Acts and the Acts incorporated therewith shall apply accord-ingly; and the Board shall be deemed to be a public 15 authority for the purposes of the Acquisition of Land (Assessment of Compensation) Act, 1919.20. The Board may, by agreement with any autho-rised undertakers or other persons, use, subject in the case of authorised, undertakers to the Acts and Orders 20 relating to the undertaking, any main transmission lines of those undertakers or persons for such time and upon such terms as may be agreed.21. (1) The Board and any company or person producing electricity by means of the utilisation of 25 water power, waste heat, or otherwise, may enter into arrangements for the purchase by the Board of any surplus electricity which the company or person may-be able to dispose of on such terms as may be agreed, and the Board may be authorised by order of 30 the Electricity Commissioners to exercise such powers (including the power to break up roads, railways, and tramways) as may be necessary for the purpose of conveying the electricity so purchased.(2) The  provisions  of  subsection (2)   of  section 35 fifteen of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, shall apply to the Board in like manner as they apply to a joint electricity authority.22. (1) The Board shall annually, at such date and in such form as the Minister of Transport may 40 prescribe, make to him a report of their proceedings under this Act during the preceding year.
(2) The Board shall furnish to the Electricity Com- A.D. 1926. missioners at such times and in such form and manner        as the Commissioners may direct such statistics and returns as they may require.5 Financial Provisions.23. All sums received by the Board shall be paid Expenses of into a separate fund, and out of that fund the fees tlie Board, and allowances of the members of the Board and the salaries, remuneration, pensions and gratuities of the 10 secretary officers and servants of the Board, and all expenses incurred by the Board, shall be paid.24.- (1) For the purposes hereinafter mentioned the Power of Board may with the consent of the Electricity Commis- Board to sioners and subject to regulations to be made by the borrow-15 Minister of Transport with the approval of the Treasury, borrow money, in such manner and subject to such provisions as to the repayment thereof, and with such powers as to reborrowing for the purpose of paying off a loan previously raised, as may be prescribed by the20 regulations, and the regulations may empower the Board to borrow temporarily by the issue of bonds or other-wise and to make arrangements with bankers, and may apply with or without modifications any enactments relating to borrowing by local authorities, including25 provisions as to the enforcement of the security by the appointment of a receiver or otherwise.(2) Such powers of borrowing as aforesaid may be exercised for all or any of the following purposes :-(a) the construction or  acquisition of  such main 30 transmission lines, generating stations, and other works as the Board are authorised by this Act to construct or acquire;(b) any other payment or any permanent work orother thing which the Board are authorised to 35 execute or do, the cost of which ought, in theopinion of the Electricity Commissioners, to be spread over a term of years (including the pay-ment of interest on money borrowed for capital expenditure for such period as may be deter-40 mined by the Electricity Commissioners afterconsultation with the Treasury to be the period26 C
16Electricity (Supply).[16 C4eo. 5.]A.D. 1926.Power to authorise issue of stock.during which the expenditure remains unre-remunerative);(c) the provision of working capital;(d) any other purpose for which the Board are underthis Act authorised to borrow. 5(3) Any money borrowed under this section, and the interest thereon, may be charged on the undertaking and all the revenues of the Board, or on any specific property forming part of that undertaking, and shall be repaid within such period not exceeding sixty years 10 as the Electricity Commissioners may determine.(4) The maximum amount which may be borrowed by the Board under this section shall be thirty-three and a half million pounds and the Board shall not have power to borrow any sums in excess of that amount, 15 otherwise than for the purpose of paying off loans pre-viously raised, unless authorised to do so by a special order under section twenty-six of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919.(5) It shall be lawful for any annual provision 20 required to be made by the Board for the repayment of money borrowed for any of the purposes of this Act, to be suspended whilst the expenditure out of such moneys remains unremunerative, for such period and subject to such conditions as the Electricity Commissioners after 25 consultation with the Treasury may determine :Provided that such suspension shall not be for a longer period than five years from the commencement of the financial year next after that in which such expenditure is incurred. 3025. (1) The Board may, for the purpose of raising money which they are authorised to borrow under this Act, issue stock (to be called &quot;Central electricity stock &quot;).(2) All such stock, and interest thereon, shall be charged on the undertaking, and on ail the revenues of 35 the Board.(3) Subject to the provisions of this Act, any stock created by the Board under the powers of this Act shall be issued, transferred, dealt with, and redeemed according to regulations made by the Minister of Transport with 40 the approval of the Treasury, and any such regulations may apply for the.purpose of this section, with or without
modifications, any provisions of. the Local Loans Act,  A,D. 1926. 1875, the Public/ Health Acts Amendment Act, 1890,        and the Acts amending those Acts, and of any Act relating to stock issued by any local authority.5        26. (1) Subject to the provisions of this section, Power tothe Treasury may guarantee in such manner as they Treasury tothink, fit, the payment of the interest and principal of f^^*eeany loan proposed to be raised by the Board or of either Boar(j the interest or the principal:10 Provided that the aggregate amount of the loans, the principal or interest of which may be so guaranteed, shall not exceed thirty-three and a half million pounds.(2) Such sums as may from time to time be recpuired by the Treasury for fulfilling any guarantees given under15 this section shall be charged on and issued out of the Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof.(3) The repayment to the Treasury of any sums so issued out of the Consolidated Fund, together with20 interest thereon at such rate as the, Treasury may fix, shall be a charge on the undertaking and all the revenues of the Board next after the principal and interest of the guaranteed loan, and any sinking fund payments for the repayment of the principal thereof, and in priority to25 any other charges not existing at the date on which the loan is raised.(4) All sums paid from time to time in or towards the repayment of any sum issued out of the Consolidated Fund under this section shall be paid into the Exchequer.30 (5) The Treasury shall so long as any such guaran-tees are in force, lay before both Houses of Parliament in every year within one month after the thirty-first day of March a statement of the guarantees (if any) given during the year ended on that date, and an account up to35 that date of the total sums (if any) which have been either issued out of the Consolidated Fund under this section or paid in or towards repayment of any money so issued.27. (1) The Board shall cause proper books of Accounts account and other books in relation thereto to be kept, and audlt-40 and shall prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form and containing such particulars as may be prescribed by the Minister of Transport.       &apos; ? 26 C 2
A.D. 1926. (2) The accounts of the Board and their officers  shall be audited by auditors appointed by the Minister of Transport, and the audit shall be conducted in accordance with such regulations as may be prescribed by the Minister of Transport. 5(3) As soon as the accounts of the Board have been audited the Board shall send a copy thereof to the Minister of Transport together with a copy of any report of the auditor thereon, and shall publish the accounts in such manner as the Minister of Transport may direct, 10 and shall place copies thereof on sale at a price not exceeding one shilling a copy.Miscellaneous Provisions.Charges for electricity supplied by power com-panies.Relation of charges to dividends.28. (1) On a power company commencing to receive a supply of electricity from the Board, the 15 Minister of Transport may revise the maximum prices authorised under the special Act of the company to be charged hy the company for supplies, other than supplies in bulk to authorised undertakers, and may revise the standard prices fixed by such Act and on 20 such revision in determining the maximum and standard prices regard shall be had to the benefit to the company of any reduction in the cost of electricity attributable to this Act.(2) So much of any special Act passed before the 25 passing of this Act as authorises such a power company to make good any deficiency in any previous dividends which have fallen below the prescribed standard rate of dividends shall cease to have effect and is hereby repealed. 3029. (1) Where any company, being authorised undertakers and not being a power company, receive a supply of electricity either directly or indirectly from the Board, the Electricity Commissioners may by a special order under section twenty-six of the Electricity (Supply) 35 Act, 1919, make provision as to the relation between the charges to be made for electricity and the dividends to be paid by the company, and the order shall have effect as if the provisions contained therein were in substitution for the provisions (if any) contained in the Act or order 40
relating to the undertaking of the company as to the a.D. 1926. relation of charges to dividend.  (2) The provisions of this section shall not apply to any company which is a London company within 5 the meaning of the London and Home Counties Elec-tricity District Order, 1925.SO. (1) Where any tree obstructs or interferes Power to with the working of any main transmission line or other lop trees electric line owned by any authorised undertakers, or obstructing10 will obstruct or interfere with the working of such a line, ^f10 the authorised undertakers may give notice to the owner or occupier of the land on which the tree is growing requiring the tree to be lopped so as to prevent the obstruction or interference.15 (2) If within one month from the service of the notice by the authorised undertakers the owner or occupier of the land on which the tree is growing gives a counter notice to the authorised undertakers objecting to the lopping of the tree, the matter shall be referred20 to the Minister of Transport who, after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, may make an order in that behalf, and the order may authorise the autho-rised undertakers to cause the tree to be lopped, and determine any question as to whether any and what25 compensation is to be paid.(3) The authorised undertakers shall issue instruc-tions to their officers and servants with a view to securing that trees shall be lopped in a woodmanlike manner and so as to avoid injury to their growth.30 (4) This section shall apply to main transmission lines owned by the Board in like manner as it applies to lines owned by authorised undertakers.Amendments of the Electricity Supply Acts.31, For section five of the Electricity (Supply) Act, Schemes for 35 1919, as amended by section nineteen of the Electricity constitution (Supply)  Act   1922,  the  following  section  shall  be of electricity substituted :- districts,and the(1) Where it appears to the Electricity Com- organisation missioners that with respect to any areas the of suPPly 40 existing organisation for the supply of electricity tlierem-therein should be improved, and. that a joint
A.D. 1926. electricity authority should be established there-for, the Commissioners shall give notice of their intention to constitute those areas a separate electricity district, and to formulate a scheme for effecting such improvement in the district, and for 5 the establishment of a joint electricity authority for the district:Provided that in considering what areas are to be included in a district, areas shall be grouped in such manner as may seem to the Commis- 10 sioners most conducive to the efficiency and economy of the Supply of electricity and the convenience of administration.(2) After such a notice has been published, the Electricity Commissioners, after consultation 15 with the authorised undertakers in the proposed district, shall formulate such a scheme as afore-said, and publish the scheme in such manner as they think best adapted for insuring its publicity, and hold a local inquiry thereon, and shall give 20 to authorised undertakers, county councils, local authorities, railway companies using or proposing to use electricity for traction purposes, large consumers of electricity, and other associations or bodies within the proposed district which appear 25 to the Commissioners to be interested, an oppor-tunity of making representations to the Commis-sioners on the proposed scheme, and with respect to the inclusion in or exclusion from the proposed district of any area. 30Contents of 32. A scheme constituting a joint electricity autho-schemes.      rity may, in addition to the matters for which provisionmay be made under section six of the Electricity (Supply)Act, 1919, contain provisions (a) for the carrying out  by the joint electricity 35authority of any works for the development of the supply of electricity within the district; and(b) for the subsequent alteration of the constitutionof the joint electricity authority ; and(c) for the appointment  by the  joint electricity 40authority of any particular committee or com-mittees, and for the delegation to any such committee or committees of any of the powers and duties of the authority.
33. The power under section seven of the Electricity  A.D. 1926. Supply Act, 1919, to make orders amending or altering        previous orders shall include power by such subsequent Amendment order to constitute a joint electricity authority in any    schemes-5 case where the original order did not provide for the constitution of such an authority.34. (1) Where after the commencement of this Act Provisions a special order is made authorising a company to supply as to electricity, and the area of supply consists of or includes companies 10 the whole of the districts of two or more local autho-       ^rge rities, the following provisions shall have effect with supply, respect to the right of purchasing their undertaking : (a) The   purchasing   authority   may  within   sixmonths after the expiration of  a period  of15 nfty years from the date of the confirmation of the special order, or such shorter period as may be specified in that behalf in the special order, and within six months after the expira-tion of every subsequent period of ten years,20 or such shorter period as may be specified inthat behalf in the Special Order, by notice in writing, require the company to sell, and thereupon the company shall sell to them their undertaking upon the terms of the payment25 to those undertakers of a sum equal to thecapital properly expended for the provision of the land, buildings, works, material, and plant of the undertakers in use or available and suitable for use at the time of the purchase30 for the purposes  of  their undertaking,  lessdepreciation according to such scale as may be approved by the Electricity Commissioners :(b) The Minister of Transport shall determine any questions which may arise in relation to such 35 purchase and may fix the date from which thepurchase is to take effect, and as from the date so fixed, or such other date as may be agreed, all land?., buildings, works, material or plant so purchased as authorised, shall vest in the 40 purchasing authority, freed from  the debts,mortgages, or similar obligations of the under-takers or attached to the undertaking, and the powers of the undertakers in relation to the supply   of   electricity  under  the  Electricity
A-D. 1926 (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1926, or such specialorder as aforesaid, shall absolutely cease and determine, and shall vest in the purchasing authority :(c) The purchasing authority  5(i) where the area of supply is situate wholly or mainly within the district of a joint electricity authority, shall be the joint electricity authority : Provided that if the area of supply is situate partly within the 10 district of one joint electricity authority and partly in that of another, the right of purchase shall be exerciseable by such oneof those authorities, or  shall  be divisible between them as the Electricity Commis- 15 sioners may determine(ii) in any other case, shall be the local authorities for the districts in which any part of the area of supply is situate, acting through a joint committee or joint board 20 constituted under section eight of the Electric Lighting Act, 1909.(d) Sections two and three of the Electric Lighting Act, 1888, shall not apply.(2) The Special Order in any case to which sub- 25 section (1) of this section applies may make provision as to   the relation  between the  price  charged   for electricity and the dividends paid by the company.Terms of 35. Where a company, being authorised undertakers,purchase of have ceased to generate electricity themselves, in lieu 30 a company  thereof are taking a supply of electricity in bulk directly *^^a j   or indirectly from the Board, or, with the approval of u isuppy.        Electricity Commissioners, from any other source, and the undertaking of the company is purchased by a local authority under section two of the Electric 35 Lighting Act, 1888, the following provisions shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in that Act: (1) In addition to the sum payable to the company by the local authority in respect  of plant and other assets under the said Act, or under 40 the said Act as varied by any order, there shall be paid a sum representing the capital properly expended upon plant and other assets
rendered unsuitable for use by reason of the A.D. 1926. taking of such bulk supply as aforesaid, after         deducting such amount as  the company,  in the opinion of the Electricity Commissioners, 5 ought properly to have written off in respectof such assets:(2) Any question arising under this provision shall be determined by the Electricity Commissioners, whose decision shall be final.10        36.- (1) The charge made by authorised undertakers Methods of to any ordinary consumer, may, if duly authorised, and charge, notwithstanding anything in any Act or Order to the contrary, consist of a periodical fixed or service charge and in addition a charge for the actual quantity of15 energy supplied to the consumer or for the electrical quantity contained in the supply.When the undertakers have power to provide meters, electric lines, fittings, apparatus and appliances, the periodical fixed or service charge may include a 20 rent, charge or remuneration in respect of any meter and any electric lines, fittings, apparatus and appliances provided by the undertakers in or upon the premises of the consumer whether let or hire on hire purchase terms to the consumer or otherwise.25 (2) A method of charge as aforesaid may be author-ised by Special Order or by an approval under the provisions of section thirty-one of the Schedule to the Electric Lighting (Clauses) Act, 1899, or corresponding provision contained in  any Act or Order, and such30 Special Order or approval may provide, where expe-dient, for an option to ordinary consumers to be charged by an authorised alternative method.37.- (1) The Schedule  to  the Electric Lighting Amendment Clauses Act, 1899, as incorporated with any special Act of Schedule 35 or Order passed or confirmed whether before or after the        * 63 commencement of this Act, shall have effect subject to the amendments specified in the Fifth Schedule to this Act.(2) Any special Act or Order relating to the supply 40 of electricity passed or confirmed before the commence-ment  of  this  Act  which  does  not  incorporate  the provisions  of  the  Schedule to the Electric Lighting Clauses Act, 1899, ;which are amended by the Fifth26 D
24Electricity Supply.[16 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1926.  Schedule to this Act, but contains corresponding provi----      sions, shall have effect as if the like amendments weremade in those corresponding provisions.Minorarnend-ments.38. The amendments specified in the second column of  the Sixth   Schedule to this Act (which relate to 5 minor details) shall be made in the provisions of the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, specified in the first column of that Schedule.Interpre-tation.General.39. (1) For the purposes of this Act, unless the 10 context otherwise requires The expression &quot; owners&quot; in relation to a generating station includes lessees or occupiers of the stationoperating the station; The expression &quot;authorised undertakers&quot; includes 15a joint electricity authority.(2) Where electricity is supplied to any authorised undertakers by other authorised undertakers who them-selves receive a supply from the Board, the first-mentioned undertakers shall for the purposes of this Act be deemed 20 to receive a supply indirectly from the Board, and references in this Act to an indirect supply from the Board shall be construed accordingly.(3) If and so far as the price for a supply of elec-tricity is under this Act to be adjusted according to 25 load factor, such price shall be the sum of the following items : (a) the number of kilowatts of maximum demand multiplied by the fixed charges component;(6) the number of units supplied to the undertakers 30 multiplied by the running charges component.For the purposes of this subsection, the &quot; number of kilowatts of maximum demand&quot; shall be deemed to be twice the largest number of units of electricity supplied to the undertakers during any consecutive 35 thirty minutes in the year &quot; fixed charges component &quot; component &quot; shall, in cases by  the: Board  is  applicable,the tariff, and -shall in other cases be ascertained in 40during any consecutive of account; and the and &quot; running charges where&apos; the tariff fixed be those specified in cases be ascertained - inaccordance with the Schedule to this Act.rules contained in the Seventh
40. (1) This Act may be cited as the Electricity A.D. 1926. (Supply) Act, 1926, and shall be construed as one with        the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and those consteuc 6&apos; Acts and this Act may be cited as the Electricity (Supply) tjon com. Acts, 1882 to 1926. mencement(2) This Act shall come into operation on the day of nineteen hundred and twenty-six.(3) This Act shall not extend to Northern Ireland.and extent.26D r
SCHEDULES.FIRST SCHEDULE.Provisions as to the Acquisition of Generating Stations and Main Transmission Lines.The price of a generating station or main transmission 5 line (a) in the case of a generating station or main transmissionline belonging to a joint electricity authority or a local authority, shall be one or more annuities of such amount or amounts and continuing for such period or 10 periods as an auditor appointed by the Electricity Com-missioners certifies to be required to indemnify the local authority against their liabilities for interest and sinking fund charges in respect of such sums borrowed for the purpose of providing the generating station or 15 main transmission line as are at the date of acquisition outstanding :Provided that if in any case it is proved to the satisfaction of the Electricity Commissioners that a substantial part of the cost of the generating station 20 or main transmission line has been defrayed otherwise than by means of loans, any such annuity may be increased by such amount as the Electricity Commis-sioners think just ;(b) in the case of a generating station or main transmission 25line belonging to a company or person, shall be such sum as may be certified by an auditor appointed by the Electricity Commissioners to have been tho amount . of the expenses incurred as and incidental to the pro-vision of the generating station or main transmission 30 line, less depreciation on a scale to be determined by the Electricity Commissioners :Provided that if the company or person or the Board are dissatisfied with the sum so certified, the matter in dispute shall, in default of agreement,  be  deter- 35 mined by an arbitrator appointed by the Minister of Transport.A.D. 1926.
SECOND SCHEDULE.A.D. 1926.Rules for Determining Cost oe Production of Electricity at Selected Stations.The cost  of  production  of  electricity  at  any  selected 5 station, shall be ascertained by calculating the following costs, charges and allowances for the year of account;(a) the sums expended for fuel, oil, water, and stores consumed, for salaries and wages, and for repairs and maintenance;10        (6) sums paid as rents, rates and taxes, other than taxes on profits, in respect of the station;(c) the  proper  proportion  of  management  and  generalestablishment charges (including compensation for loss of office payable under this Act) attributable to the 15 station;(d) interest (exclusive of interest payable out of capital),on capital properly expended and attributable to the generating station and the plant suitable to and used for the purpose of generating electricity thereon.20        The rate of interest for the purposes of this paragraph shall be-(i) where the owners of a selected station are a joint electricity authority or a local authority, the average rate payable on the money raised by the25 authority for the purpose;(ii) where the owners of the station are a company, the average rate of dividends and interest paid by the company on their share and loan capital during the preceding year ; so, however, that the rate shall in3Q no case be less than five nor more than six and a halfper cent, per annum.(e) an allowance for depreciation of the following amounts -(i) where the owners of the selected station are a joint electricity authority or a local authority an35 amount equal to the sinking fund charges properlyattributable to the station and the plant thereof;(ii) where the owners of the station are a company, an amount determined in accordance with a scale fixed by the Electricity Commissioners.
A.D. 1926. THIRD SCHEDULE.Authorised Charges and Allowances in respect oe Transmission Lines used eor giving Bulk Supply to Authorised Undertakers.The following are the charges and allowances which may 5 be made in respect of a main transmission line belonging to authorised undertakers used for giving supply in bulk to other authorised undertakers : (1) A proper proportion of management and general estab-lishment charges (including rent, rates, and taxes) : 10(2) The actual cost of the maintenance of the main trans-mission line :(3) The cost of units lost in transmission from the station or sub-station from which the supply is given to the station or sub-station at which the supply is taken : 15(4) Interest on the capital properly attributable to the main transmission line at the following rate, that is to say:(a) where the authorised undertakers owning the transmission line are a joint electricity authority or a local authority, the  average rate payable on the 20 money raised by the authority for the purpose of constructing the line ;(b) where the authorised undertakers owning the transmission line are a company, the average rate of dividends and interest paid by the company on their 25 share and loan capital during the preceding year ; so, however, that the rate shall in no case be less than five nor more than six and a half per cent, per annum.(5) An allowance for depreciation of the following amount: (a) where the authorised undertakers owning the 30 transmission line are a joint electricity authority ora local authority, an. amount equal to the sinking fund charges properly attributable to the line ;(b) where the authorised undertakers owning the transmission line are a company, an amount deter- 35 mined  in   accordance with  a  scale fixed by the Electricity Commissioners.If part only of a main transmission line is so used, or if a main transmission line is used partly for giving such a supply in bulk and partly for other purposes, the charges and allowances 40 shall be the proper proportion of such charges and allowances as aforesaid.
FOURTH SCHEDULE.Adaptation of Section 16 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, as amended by Section 21 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1922.5        If after the day of , and within five years from the date when under or in consequence of this Act a generating station has been closed or has been acquired by the Central Electricity Board, any officer or servant who had before the said day of been regularly employed10 in or about the generating station, proves to the satisfaction of a referee or board of referees appointed by the Minister of Labour that in consequence of such closing or acquisition he- (i) has suffered loss of employment, or diminution of salary,wages or emoluments, otherwise than on grounds of 15 misconduct, incapacity, or superannuation;  or(ii) has relinquished his employment in consequence  ofbeing required to perform duties such as were not analogous or were an unreasonable addition to those which before the said day of he20 had been required to perform; or(iii) had been placed in any worse position in respect to the conditions of his service (including tenure of office, remuneration, gratuities, pension, superannuation, sick or other fund, or any benefits or allowances, whether25 obtaining legally or by customary practice);and, in the case of the closing of a generating station, the authorised undertakers to whom the station belonged or belongs, or, in the case of the acquisition of a generating station, the Board, do not show to the satisfaction of the referee or board of referees that30 equivalent employment on the like conditions as those obtaining with respect to Mm at the date when the generating station was closed or acquired was available, there shall be paid to him by those undertakers, or the Board, such compensation as the referee or board of referees may award, including any expenses which35 the officer or servant necessarily incurs in removing to another locality :Provided that, except where the right arises in respect of the temporary closing of a station, such compensation shall, in the case of an officer employed on an annual salary, be based on, but not 40 exceed, the amount which would have been payable to a person on abolition of office under the Acts and rules relating to His Majesty&apos;s Civil Service in force at the date of the passing of the Local Government Act, 1888, but, in computing the period of service of any officer, service under any authorised undertakers
A.D. 1926.  shall be reckoned as service under the authorised undertaker in--       whose employment he is at the time that he suffers such loss or4th Sch. diminution as is mentioned in this section; and where any such officer or servant was temporarily absent from his employment whilst serving in or with His Majesty&apos;s Forces or the forces of the 5 Allied or Associated Powers, or in any other employment of national importance during the war, such service shall be reckoned as service under the authorised undertakers in whose employment he was immediately before and after such temporary absence. 10Any question whether a generating station has been closed under or in consequence of this Act shall be determined by the Electricity Commissioners.The Minister of Labour may make rules as to the procedure before the referee or board of referees under this section and \ft may by those rules provide (a) for Umiting the amount of costs and providing for the taxation thereof;(b) for fixing the fees to be paid to the referee or the member of the board of referees and for determining by whom 20 such fees are to be paid.FIFTH SCHEDULE.Amendments of Schedule to the Electric Lighting (Clauses) Act, 1899.8 7-      -   In subsection (1) for the words from &quot; The under- 25 &quot; takers shall carry &quot; to the words &quot; maximum &quot; rate of profit &quot; there shall be substituted the following words :&quot; The undertakers shall apply the net surplus remaining in any year and the annual proceeds 30 of the reserve fund when amounting to the prescribed limit &quot; (a) in reduction of  the charges for the supply of energy ; orC &quot; (6) in reduction  of  the capital moneys 35borrowed for electricity purposes ; or
&quot;(c) if the reserve fund amounts to more  A.D. 1926i than  one-twentieth of the  aggregate       -capital expenditure on the undertaking,    5^h scra* to the credit of the local rate: corit&apos;5 &quot; Provided that the amount whichmay be carried to the credit of the local rate in any year shall not exceed one-and-a-half per cent,  of  the out-standing debt of the undertaking.&quot; 10 S. 13-      -   In subsection (1) the proviso shall be omitted.SIXTH  SCHEDULE.Minor Amendments oe Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882-1922.15Enactment to be amended.Electric Lighting Act, 1882 (45 &amp; 46 Viet. c. 46) :-s. 3      -      -20Electricity (Supply) 25    Act, 1919 (9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 100) :-s. 13    -3035s. 21s. 32Nature of Amendment.In paragraph (5), the words &quot; until after &quot; the expiration of a period of three &quot; months from the date of the first &quot; publication of such advertisement &quot; nor &quot; shall be repealed.In subsection (2), after the words &quot;the &quot; area of the local authority&quot; there shall be inserted the words &quot; or by any &quot; amending order under section seven &quot; of this Act.&quot;After the words &quot; local authority &quot; where-ever they occur, there shall be inserted the words &quot; (including a county &quot; council).&quot;In subsection (3), the words &quot; unless it is &quot; an order made under section seven of &quot; this Act, shall be a special order and &quot; shall be omitted.26E
32Electricity (Supply).       [16 Geo; 5.]A.D. 1926. SEVENTH SCHEDULE.Rules eor determining the Fixed Charges Component, and the Running Charges Component.1. The total  cost of production shall be ascertained in accordance with the Second Schedule to this Act. 52. The total cost so ascertained shall be allocated as between fixed costs and running costs in accordance with such regulations as may be prescribed by the Electricity Commissioners for the purpose. , .... ,.. ,3. The amount of the fixed costs divided by the number of 10 kilowatts of maximum demand shall be the fixed charges oom-ponent.For the purposes of this provision the &quot; number of kilowatts &quot; of maximum demand &quot; shall be deemed to be twice the largest number of units of electricity supplied from the generating 15 station during any consecutive thirty minutes in the year of account.4. The amount of the running costs divided by the number of units supplied from the generating station during the year of account shall be the running charges component. 20

Electricity (Supply).DRAFTof aBILLTo amend the law with respect to the supply of electricity.XVII.   (4.)1M February 1926.26-5

</content>
</cab>
