<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/178/0 images: 670-672</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY,THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S&quot;GOVERNMENT.CAB IN E T.H OME    APFAIRS    C OMIvl.ITTEE .CRET. ELECTRICITY   SUPPLY   BILL-,p7&apos;79 (26)Memorandum by the Minister- of Labour.  -There are two points which the Committee o\tght to consider in connection with this Bill -(l) Ought the opportunity to be taken to strengthen the existing very inadeqiiate provisions for everting a stoppage in power stations generally?     Any such proposal would of coixrse be controversial but I think we ought to consider it seriously.The developments whioh the Bill contemplates will greatly increase the power of labour organisations to hold up the community through the power stations.     Not only will industry and the life of the community generally be more dependent upon the power stations, but the fact that existing stations will be more closely linked up will undoubtedly tend to produce greater unity of action over wider areas on the part of the labour employed in the stations, so that it will be much more difficult to prevent a dispute at any particular station extending over a wider area,     The Bill therefore increases the necessity for dealing with this problem^ and it would be less provocative to deal with it in the Bill which makes the extension than in a separate measure.The only statutory provision at present existing is the requirement in Section four of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875 as extended to electricity undertakings by Section 31 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, which in effect requires men employed in power stations (who are e\.istomarily on weekly contracts), to give a week&apos;s notice before ceasing work.    This period is Insufficient for effective/conciliation
conciliation or for arbitration.     There have in fact been numerous threats in recent years of sudden stoppage in power stations.One expedient which might be adopted is to make some express provision for (say) 28 days1 notice.An alternative method would be to follow the precedent of the Railway Service and make statutory provision for machinery of conciliation, the use of which should be compulsory before a stoppage takes place.    The existing machinery of the Joint Industrial Council for the Electricity Supply Industry does in effect as a rule secure in the majority of cases that no local stoppage should take place until there has been discussion both on the District and on the National Industrial Council,     There is, however, no provision for dealing with a dispute, if agreement is not reached on the National Council.     Machinery similar to the Central wages 3oard on the Railways might be built on this foundation, with a requirement that a dispute should be considered by such a Board within (say) 28 days In the event of agreement not having otherwise been reached.It was decider&quot; during the preliminary discussions on electrical development policy that the time .?as not ripe for dealing with this and kindred labour problems in the industry on compulsory lines.     My object at the moment is to bring the point to the notice of my colleagues and to ascertain their views on the general question whether we should attempt in this Bill to adopt some less drastic expedient,such as those which I have outlined.      If we decide to proceed the exact method would require further careful consideration.
IS?(2) It is very probable that the Opposition or individual Labour Members will move the insertion of a pair Wages Clause.I understand that the proposed Central Electricity Board is likely to employ very little labour direct, hut it will place many contracts, and it will he difficult to find any ground for resisting the demand that the Board should be required to include a Pair //ages Clause in its contracts.I do not suggest that the Bill should necessarily Include such a provision, but the Government ought to be ready with a caluse to this effect which they would be prepared to insert if necessary.   The clause would need careful drafting, and it would be better that the Government should bring forward a clause of their own on request than be faced with a Private Member&apos;s Clause which might very well be inconvenient, but might also be difficult to amend.(Intd.)   A.3,- M*Ministry of Labour. (February 22 nd, iya6.

</content>
</cab>
