<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/178/0 images: 798-803</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
VJFIDENTIA-L LIBRARY.HIS rmriUIviEHT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS 3PJTANKIO MAJESTY&apos;S GOVEHflLiENTSECRET. 0.90 (S3 ) ;CABINET. *Memorandum by the Min!ster of Labour -El? GI NEERI NG    INDUSTRY.1. The negotiations between the Engineering and Allied Employers&apos; National Federation and the engineering unions which have been taking place for two years on a claim by the unions for an increase in; wages of .30/- a week have now definitely broken down and a serious position has arisen.2. At a conference between the parties on 28th January,  1926, the unions informed the employers that, having regard to the length of time that had elapsed since they had made their application for a national increase of wages,  the negotiations would.be terminated if no advance was conceded and the unions would be free to take such action as they ploased, either nationally or locally.      This decision was considered by the Employers1 Federation, who informed the unions at a meeting ,held on 25th February, that in their view no action should be taken that might lead to a setback in the revival alleged to have set in, and that they were still prepared to discuss with the unions the position existing in tho industry.      The repre-sentatives of the unions re-affirmed the decision conveyed to the employers at the previous conference, whereupon the employers intimated to the unions that in the event of any action being taken by the unions, or a union,  to enforce an advance of wages either nationally, locally or seotionally, it would be re-si sted by the Employers&apos; Federation to the fullest extent.3. A number of applications for an increase in wages have already been made in certain districts and in/some
r s 9some instances joint conferences have &quot;been held.     Wo ol t-jprogress has, however, been made owing to the position of the national negotiations.      It was expected that as soon as the national negotiations definitely terminated the district claims would be pressed by the unions.      These claims will presumably still go forward but it is not possible to say at the present time whether they are now likely to be pressed to the point of a stoppage in view of the attitude adopted by the: employers.4.     A more immediate danger of a stoppage in the engineering industry arises from an unofficial strike in London of about 900 employees of Messrs. Hoe and Company Ltd., printing-machine manufacturers, a firm federated to the Engineering and Allied Employers&apos; National Federation.5.      The stoppage at Messrs. Hoe &amp; Companyrs works, which commenced on 13th January, 1926,  took place over the employment of five non-unionists.    The dispute, however, arose in the first instance over the refusal of the firm to discuss an application for an increase of wages of 20/- per week, with the result that the men refused to work overtime.      The dispute then developed into a question of the employment of non-unionists, and the men began a &quot;stay-in&quot; strike.    The firm thereupon locked out the night shift on 12th January and an unofficial stoppage of all the men took place the following day,6.      The stoppage has not been recognised by theExecutive Council of the Amalgamated Engineering Union, the chief union concerned, and the men are receiving no strike pay.    It is understood, however, that a levy is being made amongst the printing employees in the printing houses and that a considerable amount of money has been collected by the men in this and other ways./7.    The
7.     The unions concerned have made-repeated efforts to secure a resumption of work but their efforts have failed. At a meeting of the men held on 32nd February, a resolution was passed pledging the men not to return to work until recognition of their claims had been conceded and Informing the Executives of the unions concerned that they would not accept any Instructions from the Executives to return to work.     It will thus be seen that the men are thoroughly out of hand.   Even the fact that the London and District Association of Engineering Employers refused to meet the unions to discuss a claim for an increase of wages of 20/-a week for engineering employees in the London Hstrict until a resumption of work had taken place at Messrs.Hoe&apos;s had no influence on the ment   As a result of the refusal of the London Employers to meet the unions op their claim the London District Committee of the Amalgamated Engineering Union banned the working of overtime generally in the London district from 1st February.8.     Following the meeting between the Employers&apos; National Federation and the unions on 25th February, a special conference was held between the Employers&apos; Federation and the Amalgamated Engineering Union, the United Patternmakers&apos; Association, the Electrical Trades Union, the National Union of Brass and Metal Mechanics, the transport and General Workers&apos; Uniont  the National Union of General and Municipal   orkers and the workers&apos; Union, at which the Employers informed the unions that the agreement for avoiding disputes was being violated by the&apos;stoppage at Messrs.Hoe&apos;s and asked them to instruct their members who were on strike to return to work pending anyquestion at issue being dealt with In a ccnstitutional way*The Unions intimated that they were not in a position to/comply
Ministry of Labour, 26th February, 1926.comply with the request of the employers, who thereupon stated that they would have no alternative but to recommend their Federation to post look-out notices affecting the members of the unions concerned in all works of federated firms throughout the country until such time as the unions conformed to their obligations un3er the agreement.     At a meeting of the Federation held on 36th February it was decided to post look-out Notices on 6th March to take effect on 15th March.9,     I am arranging for informal discussions with the leaders on both sides with a view to seeing whether it is practicable to avoid the stoppage of work,(Intd)    A. S-M,
for Associations of Civil Servants. to employ as their secretary and representative in chief whole-time officials of their own., Two results have followed. In the first place, if only because these whole-time officials must justify their salaries, pressure to obtain better and still, better conditions of service has tended to become more and more persistent. By their -speeches and by their writings in the numerous Civil Service journals that are nowadays in circulation, leaders of Civil Service Associations do their utmost to prevent their con-stituents from resting content with things as they are and to inflame them with a desire for things that they have not got. It is noticeable, and natural enough, that the tendency to attack becomes more pronounced at times when Associations of Civil Servants fear that their existing conditions of service are in jeopardy.A further important consequence of the development of trade unionism in the Civil Service is the tendency towards affiliation with the Trade Union Congress and the Labour Party. Several Civil Service Associations, including the Union of Post Office Workers and the Civil Service Clerical Association, are affiliated to either or both of these bodies. In a number of cases their funds have been used to promote the candidature for Parliament of their own nominees. Officials of these Associations attend and take an active part at meetings of the Trade Union Congress and the Labour Party.No. one watching the march of events could say that the present situation was satisfactory or free from danger. The practice of employing whole-time officials who are not Civil Servants is wrong; and it is deplorable that Associations of Civil Servants should become attached to any political party. But whilst it is easy enough to criticise the present state of things, it is much less easy to find a remedy that would not be more dangerous than the disease. No one at this time of day would think of denying to Civil Servants the right to organise themselves in Associations for the protection and furtherance of their own interests: and it is no doubt better that they should form Associations of their own, even though staffed by persons who are not themselves Civil Servants and affiliated to a particular political party, than that they should join general labour unions. It is not the habit in this country to put clocks back, and however undesirable the present state of things may be, it could hardly be radically altered at this time; it would indeed seem impracticable to do more that insist on strict observance of the existing rule forbidding individual Civil Servants to take any active part in politics.Whatever else may be said about the growth of trade unionism in the Civil Service, it cannot be said that it has so far led to any general feeling among Civil Servants in favour of the &quot; strike weapon.&quot; It may be confidently asserted that Civil Servants in general are absolutely set against strikes in the Civil Service.   Strike funds do not exist: indeed,
when the executive of the Uuion of Postal Workers proposed to start a 546 strike fund a few years ago, the scheme was rejected by an overwhelming majority of the rank and file. In the established Civil Service strikes have hardly ever occurred. There was a strike of 450 London postmen in 1890: two established moulders joined the Moulders&apos; strike in 19t20: and there was a strike, also in 1920, of postal officials in Ireland, many of whom no doubt joined in because they were afraid of being murdered if they refused to do so.It is not so certain, however, that extremists who are out to cause trouble will not sooner or later be making serious attempts to develop a strike policy for the Civil Service. According to a recent article by the Labour Correspondent of the &quot; Westminster Gazette,&quot; Mi-. W. J. Brown, the Secretary of the Civil Service Clerical Association, is said to be negotiating an alliance -with the Industrial Unions, the effect of which would be that &quot; the members of the Civil Service Clerical Association would come under the sway of a small body which could call on them to cease work in support of the miners, transport workers, engineers or shipbuilders.&quot; In view of possible developments in the near future, it may be expedient to take an early opportunity (possibly by way of reply to a question in Parliament) of making clear to all concerned the incom-patibility of a strike policy with the position held by Civil Servants as employees of the Crown.The question of the right to strike was raised in 1920 by the trade union side of the Shipbuilding Trades Joint Council; and, under directions from the Cabinet, the following statement was made to the Council by the official side : &quot; There is no statutory prohibition of strikes by Civil Servants. Such a prohibition has not hitherto been found necessary, for Civil Servants have recognised that the fact that they are Servants of the State and the conditions of establishment with pension on retire-ment, impose special obligations upon them and differentiate their case from that of the employees of any private trader for profit.&quot; But the principle upon which Parliament has proceeded in giving legal sanction to the award of pensions to Civil Servants is that they should have rendered faithful and satisfactory service, and this primary condition cannot be held to have been satisfied in the case of servants of the State who by striking have endangered or prevented the carrying on of the public service for which Government is responsible to Parliament and the community.&quot;If any public declaration is now to be made, it might well follow the lines of this statement.

</content>
</cab>
