<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/62 images: 652-655</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT--&quot;-:        292Printed for the War Cabinet. May 1945. -SECRET. i Copy No.W.P. (45) 312.17th May, 1945.WAR CABINET.PROGRAMMES OF THE SERVICE DEPARTMENTS IN RELATIONTO TOWN AND COUNTRY PLANNING.Memorandum by the Minister of Town and Country Planning.THE Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairsregarding the possible retention by the War Office of the Isle of Purbeck(W.P. (45) 244) raises questions of great moment to my Department, and I desirestrongly to support the views he expresses with regard to the need for a closescrutiny of projects of the Service Departments involving the acquisition orcontinued use of large tracts of land.The war-time holdings of the three Service Departments show the impact of war-time requirements on land use. In the Second Report of the SelectCommittee on National Expenditure, Session 1944-45, the Admiralty were shownas having requisitioned 28,000 acres of land, the War Office 600,000 acres ofland (actually 470,000 at the time of the Report), and the Air Ministry253,000 acres. In addition, at that time the Air Ministry owned 120,000 acres and the War Office 340,000 acres. The present area held by Service deparment is likely to be substantially reduced, but not to anything like pre-war dimensions.It must be expected that there will be a large permanent land holding, and inorder that Service requirements may be fitted in with other important demands on the limited area of land available in this country, the declaration and close examination of a programme are matters of urgency.The issues arising relate not only to the amenity of many areas of greatnatural beauty, historical association and recreational value, but. as the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs points out, on occasions to the whole way of life of communities and to the future of many districts.2. In my memorandum to the Reconstruction Committee (R (45) 21) I drew attention, in the case of airfields, to the material bearing on the future planning of a district of a decision one way or the other on the retention of an airfield.The Prime Minister, in a note of the 23rd February, 1945 (W.P. (45) 110), hasalready directed that the Chiefs of Staff should submit a broad appreciation ofmilitary requirements for airfields, and that an ad hoc Cabinet Committee should then be appointed to assess the airfield requirements of civil aviation and aircraft production, and to see how far these can be dovetailed in with military needs.The decision on projects in contemplation by the other Service Departments may also have important consequences. It may often be the case that the project ofthe Service Department will have to go on, but it is impossible to plan until the project is known and taken into account in deciding on the future developmentof the locality affected.   I will give one or two examples : A War Office military camp has been established on the south side of theCity of&apos; Gloucester. The City Council are unable to plan this side of the cityuntil it is decided whether, as is in contemplation, this camp must remain aftertiie war.Similarly, the whole basis of the redevelopment proposals for Plymouthdepended on the future proposals for the Dockyard; whether there should beextensions, and the extent of them, has a fundamental bearing on the futureof the town. The proposals involve the resettlement of a substantial proportionof the population and the shift of one of the more important shopping centres.In this case the proposals of the Admiralty are definite and have been made known to the City Council, but the case illustrates the point.[29918]
3. Moreover, knowledge of the future of Government developments under-taken during the war is necessary not only in order that Local Authorities panplan the future development of their districts, but in order that an appropriatechoice can be made between post-war Government projects where, as sometimeshappens, they are in conflict. In illustration of this point I would refer to theestablishment of the Aeronautical Research Station at Bedford, involving an ultimate increase of the population of the area by some 10,000 people, to which my Department agreed without knowledge of the fact that it was also proposedto transfer some 2^.000 civil servants to the same town, giving a further potentialincrease of four or five thousand in the population, one result being, for an indefinite period, a strain on the housing resources of the town. Moreover, theadditional population may have to be accommodated by an extension of the town,on a scale which, is on various grounds undesirable, in particular that it meansundue inroads on good agricultural land.-i. One further matter should be mentioned which is arising in many partsof the country in connection with Service Department projects. This is the useof considerable stretches of the coast for such purposes as bombing ranges, tank-firing ranges and battle training schools. In view of the demand which is alreadyarising (and will be clamant now that the war in Europe is over), for holidayfacilities and free access to the coast, this is a most important matter; and anyproposal to devote the coast permanently to such military purposes plainly needsthe closest scrutiny from this point of view.5. What is necessary is that all the Service Departments should as a matterof urgency consider their positive programmes as a comprehensive whole andthat the Minister of Town and Country Planning should be fully consulted on them at an early stage. It is the Ministers duty under statute to see that thebest choice is made between competing uses of land, and when that choice ismade Local Authorities must be informed as soon as possible in view of theimportance of that knowledge to the discharge of their duty&apos; in planning properlyfor the&apos; future of their districts.Certain major projects have had to be parried out during the war on sitesthe use of which for the purpose would in peace-time be objectionable on generalplanning grounds. In such cases the onus should be on the Service departments to justify any proposed permanent retention.6. In one respect only do I differ from the suggestions made by theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs. In my opinion the most importantobjects which he has in mind should be settled not by the reference of proposals to an impartial Commission but by full consultation between the Service Depart-ments and my Ministry and others affected.7. I appreciate that it may well be the case in some instances that whatever may be the effect on the locality, the needs of defence may be overriding. It is,however, apparent that the detriment to a wide area of such a project as abombing range may be very serious; and accordingly it would appear to be worth considering whether at least some of the peace-time training establishments couldnot, by consent of the Governments concerned, be located in the Dominions.W. S. M.Ministry of Town and Country Planning,32 St. James&apos;s Square. S.W. 1,17th May, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
