<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/99/0 images: 126-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fc&apos;&apos;7&apos;-730-   TJl 7 His Bri&apos;) &quot;)S i ?&apos; 0&apos;f? Document^ j.....^tannic lvw3ty&apos;s Government.      jqgcJ&apos;(rlUJ^THE PRESENT CAUSE OF HIGH PRICES.?    .  The fundamental causes of high prices continue to be:-(a) An actual world shortage of most essential commodities. &amp;(This may be illustrated in food stuffs by Sffljar; pre-war production, 18,700,000.tons.  present production, 15,700,000 tons - )(b) A continued expansion of the currency in the principal countries. Both these causes must be removed before the prices can fall to their former level.The first cause, the shortage of supplies, is the fundamental cause; if this alone were removed it would tre possible to substantially relieve the inconvenience by an adjustment .of wages..      Subsidiary and local causes of nigh prices are:- ,(a) increased costs of production..(b) adverse exchanges.(c) increased consumption, e.g. Japan is now consuming wheat, and the , working classes in various countries are striving after a higher standard of living.(d) dislocation of the mearis of distribution, high freights, increased cost of transport.(e) uncontrolled competition by purchasers (f), profiteering.PROSPECTS:There is no apparent prospect of world supplies meeting the world&apos;s effective demands for some years to come. Dislocation of the productive machinery of Europe brought about by 5 years of war will take some years to repair.   There is at least a possibility that the effective demands of Europe., may increase more rapidly than the restoration of European production.   For example -any credit facilities given  to Austria would lead to an increased demand upon the world supplies of food and raw materials, with no immediate prospect of any corresponding ex-ports, in the case of Russia the opening of trade facilities, while alleviating the world position as regards wheat and flax, would in the absence of control probably lead to further severe rises in the price of woollens hardware- and other commodities required, in exchange.EFFECTS ,pricegPerhaps tho most important aspect of the problem is, the effect of rising/upon industrial and political stability in the various count-ries.   According to the nineteenth century economists the present high prices should naturally lead to an increase of production, and so ultim-ately lower prices. But this leaves out of account political factors. High prices today in the absence of any manifest efforts to protect the consumer are   more likely to lead to strikes, Industrial unrest, lessened production, and so to a still higher level of prices.REMEDIES:(a) Radical:The only permanent solution lies in an increase of production in nearly all essential commodities, and the prime factor in&apos; securing increased production must be the--romoval of resentment and dis-content among the working classes.(b) Palliatives:The radtcal cure demands time for its accom-plishment. In the meantime the symptoms created by discontent - economic disorder, industrial unrest, diweoptent and resentment of all classes -may be dealt with by appropriate remedies. For that purpose it is essential that each Government shall satisfy its own people that all possible steps are being taken to check profiteering and to reduce the burden of high prices which makes life dear and difficult for all.For this reason methods of control, even if economically ineffective and imperfect; may politically bo of tho greatest utility, until:-
e 7109(1) world supplies approximate to world demands. and (2) the altered levels of wages are satisfactorily adjusted to, the new levels of prices which will ultimately emerge from the present economic confusion..CONCLUSION;Numerous conferences with the leaders of various important industries in the last six months convince me that in this country manufacturers generally would welcome an opportunity to co-operate with the Government to reduce a level of prices which, -while temper-arily profitable, exposes them to public odium and to a perpetual rc-currence of demands for higher wages on the part of their em ployees.If the consumer is to be really protected the methods to be adopted must vary in the case of different commodities. A severe world shortage can only be dealt with effectively by limiting competition among purchasers - in other words, by a centralised buying, , coupled with some equitable system of distribution among all classes of con-.sumers. Generally, it will be unnecessary to retain anything like a rigid system of war-time controls. The essential features of a systom of control which will neither harass manufacturers nor interfere with export trade are the so:-(1) full and complete information as to present costs of production in the case of all essential commodities at every stage of production and distribution.(2) the power where necessary to impose maximum prices   at any stage.With this knowledge in the possession of a Government Department,, and with these powers in reserve, it will in nearly all cases be possi-ble without compulsion to arrange with the trades themselves to voluntary-arily limit profits, to what tho public will accept as fair and reason-able. This method of control has been the subject of trial with satisfactory results by the Ministry of Pood during the last twelve months, notably in the case of Oils and  Fats.    The general policy of trade combinations and associations In this country in recent years has been, not to unreasonably increase prices but to secure definite and fixed prices and to eliminate competition.   If. in future such prices were subject to criticism and, if necessary to modification by a Government Department, control might be exercised with no sub-stantial interference to the workings of industry, and to the benefit of the manufacturers as well as of the consumer.25th February 1920.CHARLES A. McCURDY. &apos;, -   MINISTRY OF FOOD.

</content>
</cab>
