<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/99/0 images: 214-220</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document- is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government,confidential.I.Political Intelligence Department, Foreign Office.Russia/030.. BOLSHEVIK AIMS IN THE WEST AND IN THE EAST.THE following memorandum contains extracts from Russian papers which have only recently reached the Department. They are circulated because of the interest which they have as throwing light on the avowed policy of Lenin and the situation in Russia.&quot; It goes without saying that the revolutionary movement among the peoples of the East can now receive a successful development by close contact with the revolu-tionary struggle of our Soviet Republic against international Imperialism.....I think that the achievements of the Red Army will be of gigantic, world-wide importance to all the peoples of the East. It will show them that, however weak they are, in spite of all the wonders of technique and military art possessed by the European oppressors, a revolutionary war waged by oppressed peoples may bring about so many marvels that it has become quite a practical policy to liberate the peoples of the East.&quot; We see in Western Europe how Imperialism is falling to pieces. We see how German Imperialism has fallen to pieces, how it has led not only to a republican but a Socialist revolution. You know that at the present time in Germany the class struggle has become more acute and civil war is coming nearer, the struggle of the German proletariat against the German Imperialists who have decked themselves in republican colours, but have remained just the same. Everyone knows that the social revolution is maturing also in Western Europe; everyone knows what is taking place in America and in England. Everyone saw that the Peace of Versailles was a hundred times more rapacious than that of Brest and that the Peace of Versailles is the greatest blow which the capitalists of the victorious countries could have inflicted upon themselves. We can say with confidence that this peace is only an apparent victory for its authors; in reality it means the collapse of the whole imperialist world and the dissociation of the working masses from those Socialists who, during the war, allied themselves with the representatives of a rotten imperialism.&quot;After speaking of the economic chaos in Europe, Lenin explains how completely the efforts of the Entente against Soviet Russia have failed, and how high stands the prestige of the Soviets .in the world at the present moment.Let me now explain the position which has arisen for the nationalities of the East. If the Russian Bolsheviks have succeeded in opening a breach in the old Imperialism and creating new ways for revolution, you, who represent the toiling masses of the East, have a still greater task before you. The social revolution which is approaching for the whole world will not merely consist of the victory of the proletariat in every country over its bourgeoisie. This would be possible if the revolution passes easily and quickly. We know that the Imperialists will not permit this, that all countries are armed against their internal Bolshevism and that they think only of the best way of conquering Bolshevism at home. Thus the social revolution will not only be a struggle of the revolutionary proletariats : it will be a struggle of all oppressed colonies and all dependent countries against international Imperialism. In the programme of our party which was adopted in March of last year we said that the civil war of the workers against the Imperialists and exploiters in all the leading countries will begin by uniting itself with the national war against the international Imperialists. This is confirmed by the course of the revolution, and will be still further confirmed. It will be the same thing in the East. We know that the masses of the East are rising to create a new life because millions of theLenin&apos;s Speech to Moslem Communists, November 22, 1919.-(&quot; Izvestiya Kommunisticheskoi part II,&quot; December 20.)[2388]BL
population belong to dependent nations without full rights, which hitherto have been mere pawns in the game of international politics. When they talk of giving mandates for colonies we know very well that mandates are given for the purposes of robbery. The majority of the population which hitherto has stood outside the stream of historical progress, because it could not supply an independent revolu-tionary force, ceased at the beginning of the twentieth century to play a merely passive role. The Imperialist war has roused the East and brought its peoples into international politics. England and France armed their colonial peoples and helped them to become acquainted with military technique. We shall use this science against the Imperialist masters.&quot; I believe that you are on the threshold of a world revolution which, judging by its beginnings, will last many years and will entail great labour in the revolu-tionary struggle, so that in the revolutionary movement you will join hands with us in the struggle against international Imperialism. The majority of the Eastern peoples are in a worse position than Russia the most backward country in Europe  but we have succeeded in uniting the workers and peasants against the remnants of feudalism and against capitalism. We are like you. because the majority of the population in the East consists not of workmen, who have passed through the school of the Imperialist factories, but of peasants who suffer from oppression similar to that of the Middle Ages.&quot; Our Soviet Republic must group round it all the scattered peoples of the East in order that together with them we may wage the struggle against international Imperialism. Your task is to base yourselves on communist theory and practice, but to adapt it to conditions which are different from those in Europe, as your task is not to fight against capital but against the remains of the Middle Ages. Your task is a difficult one, but it is not a thankless one, as the masses, which have hitherto not taken part in the struggle, are going over to your side, and, moreover, you have organised Centres of Communism in the East which can be closely linked up with the Third International. You must discover the best way of uniting the leading proletariats of the whole world with the exploited masses of the East which live in conditions resembling those of the Middle Ages.&quot; We, Russians, will strengthen the English, Trench and German proletariats, but we see that they will not conquer without the help of all the toiling masses, of all the colonial, oppressed peoples, and particularly the peoples of the East. We must realise that the advance guard cannot realise the transition to Communism. We must arouse the revolutionary activity of the toiling masses no matter on, what level they stand, and must translate the true Communist teaching into the language of every people.&quot;II.  BOLSHEVIK ATTITUDE TOWARDS NATIONAL QUESTIONS. (a.) Lenin&apos;s Letter to the Workmen and Peasants of the Ukraine. (&quot; Petrogradskaya Pravda,&quot; January 6, 1920.)&quot; The supremacy of Denikin in the Ukraine was just as grievous an experience as the supremacy of Kolchak in Siberia. There is no doubt that the lesson gained by this experience will bring the Ukrainian workmen and peasants to a clearer under-standing of the tasks of the Soviet Government and to a firmer defence of it. In Great Russia private property in land has been completely destroyed. In the Ukraine the same thing must be done, and the Soviet Government of the Ukrainian workmen and peasants must see to the complete coni&amp;scation of the landowners&apos; properties, Besides this task there are other tasks which lie before the Great Russian and Ukrainian working masses. There are special tasks for the Soviet Government in the Ukraine. One of these special tasks deserves particular attention at the present time. This is the national question, or the question whether the Ukraine is to be an independent Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic linked in a union or&apos; federation with the Russian Soviet Republic, or whether the Ukraine is to be amalgamated with Russia in a Ukrainian Soviet Republic. All Bolsheviks, all intelligent workmen and peasants must give particular attention to this question.&quot; The independence in the Ukraine was recognised by the Central Executive Committee of the Soviets and by the Russian Communist&apos; Party.  It is therefore
obvious that in the Ukraine workmen and peasants themselves, at their All-Ukrainian Congress of Soviets, can decide whether the Ukraine is to be amalgamated with Eussia or whether an independent Ukrainian Eepublic is to be set up, and in the latter case what federal bond is to be established between this Eepublic and Eussia, This question must be decided from the point of view of the interest of the workers. In the first place the interests of Labour demand the most complete confidence and the closest union between the workers of different countries and different nations. The supporters of the landowners, capitalists and bourgeoisie attempt to disunite the workmen and strengthen national differences and hostilities in order to weaken the workmen and to strengthen the power of capital. Capital is an international force. In order to conquer it the international union of the workers is necessary. We are opponents of national hostilities, national differences and national peculiarities. We are internationalists. We aim at a close union between the workmen and peasants of all nations of the world so that they may be united in a single world-wide Soviet Eepublic.&quot; In the second place the workers must not forget that capitalism has divided nations into a small number of great imperialist powers and a large majority of oppressed, dependent and half-dependent nations with unequal rights. The most criminal and reactionary war of 1914-18 strengthened still further this division and made hatred between different nations more acute. Lack of confidence between dependent nations such as the Ukraine, and oppressing nations such as Great Eussia has been accumulating for centuries. We wish for a voluntary alliance between nations, such an alliance as would not permit any violence of one nation over another.&quot; It is impossible to realise such a union at once; it is necessary to work for it with the greatest patience and caution in order not to create distrust which has been caused for centuries by landowners and capitalists. We must therefore be patient and conciliatory towards what survives of national distrust, but we must be firm and irreconcilable towards everything which concerns the fundamental interests of Labour, towards the struggle for liberation from the yoke of capitalism. The question of State frontiers is now coming to the front. As we aim at the complete annihilation of frontiers between States this is not a fundamental question, but one of secondary importance. We must approach this question very slowly, for national distrust amongst the masses of the peasants and small property owners is very strong, and by lack of confidence this distrust may be increased.&quot; The experience of the workers&apos; and peasants&apos; revolution in Eussia in November 1917, and the experience of two years of a successful fight against Eussian and inter-national capitalists has clearly shown that the capitalists have been able for a time to play upon the national distrust of the Polish, Lettish, Esthonian and Finnish peasants and the Eussian small proprietors. Experience has shown that this distrust only disappears very gradually. For that reason the more patience the Great russians show the more surely will this distrust disappear.&quot; By the recognition of the independence of the States of Poland, Latvia, Lithuania, Esthonia and Finland we have gradually been winning the confidence of the working masses in these countries which have for a long time been deceived by the capitalists. We shall gradually bring them to trust us completely so that they may unite with us in an international Soviet Eepublic. For the time being the Ukraine is not entirely freed from Denikin, and meanwhile until an All-Ukrainian Congress of Soviets can meet the Ukrainian revolutionary committees must be considered the Ukrainian Government. In these revolutionary committees, together with Ukrainian Communists there are working as members of the Government Ukrainian borotbisti [Ukrainian for &apos; struggle &apos;]. The latter differ from the Bolsheviks in that they stand for the unconditional independence of the Ukraine.&quot; The Bolsheviks see in this no cause for separation. They do not consider that this interferes with friendly proletarian work. They can unite in the struggle against capital in defence of the dictatorship of the proletariat and they should not separate on the question of national frontiers and whether the union between the States is to be federalcr one of a different character. Amongst the Bolsheviks there are some who support the complete independence of the Ukraine; there are others who support a more or less close federal union; while there are others who support the complete amalgamation of the Ukraine with Eussia. These questions must be decided by the All-LFkrainian Congress of Soviets. If a Great Eussian Communist supports the amalgamation of the Ukraine with Eussia, the Ukrainian may easily suspect him of defending such a policy not for the sake of the union of proletariats in the struggle [23881 B 2
with capital, but owing to prejudices caused by the old Great Eussian nationalism and imperialism.&quot; Such distrust is natural and to a certain extent inevitable,. for during many centuries the Great Russians have been under the yoke of landlords and capitalists If a Ukrainian Communist stands for the unconditional independence of his State one may suspect that he is defending such a policy not from the point of view of the temporary interests of the Ukrainian workers and peasants in the struggle against capital, but owing to petty bourgeois national prejudices, for experience has shown us a hundred times how the petty bourgeois Socialists of different countries, such as the Polish, Lettish, Lithuanian and Georgian Mensheviks, S. R.&apos;s and others, have pretended to support the proletariat with the sole object of deception, and carrying out a policy of compromise with their national bourgeoisie against the revolutionary workers. We saw this during the time of Kerensky in Russia from March to November 191.7, and we see it at present in every country. It is thus very easy for mutual distrust between the Great Russian and Ukrainian Communists to arise. The best way of overcoming this distrust is to work together for the dictator-ship of the proletariat against the landowners and capitalists of all countries, and against the attempts to establish their supremacy. Such a common struggle will, in practice, clearly show that in deciding the question of State independence or frontiers between Great Russia and the Ukraine, the workers of both countries must closely unite in a military and economic alliance, otherwise the capitalists of the Entente, i.e., a union of the richest capitalist countries, England, France, America, Japan and Italy, will crush us both alike.&quot; Therefore we Great Russian Communists must put down with the greatest -severity the smallest trace of Great Russian nationalism, for any trace of nationalism is treachery to Communism and -will cause the greatest damage by disuniting us with our Ukrainian comrades, and playing into the hands of Denikin and his followers. Thus we Great Russian Communists must be conciliatory in our differences with the Ukrainian Communists and the &apos; borotbisti &apos; if any differences arise about State independence and the form of union of the Ukraine with Russia. At the same time both Great Russian and Ukrainian Communists must be quite irreconcilable on the fundamental question of the proletarian struggle and the proletarian dictatorship. On this question there can be no compromise with the bourgeoisie.&quot;(b.) The Soviet Government and Small Nationalities. (Zhizn Natsionalnostei,&quot; December 7, 1919.)&quot;It is necessary to give particular attention to the consideration of all that is called up by the word nationalism. Marxists must understand that&apos; every phenomenon is progressive or retrogressive according to the circumstances of time and place. A Great Russian nationalists an Englishman is an Imperialist, as he still dreams of supremacy. The same cannot be said of the nationalism of a Votyak, a Buryat, a Bashkir, a Yakut, &amp;c. There are many peoples who have not under-gone their proper national evolution and with whom this period is only in its initial stages. It is difficult for them to pass at one bound to full internationalism, as they have not yet got the necessary foundations for it, having neither a working class developed in a proletarian sense nor a capitalist system of production. For such races nationalism is an inevitable stage in their transition to socialism.&apos;(I know very well that to a certain extent nationalism, whatever its origin! may be, must generally end in the same way as in the case of English nationalism. We see this at the present moment in the case of Jewish nationalism, which, in the person of the Zionists, now dreams of enslaving the Arabs who comprise the majority of the population of Palestine. But this is the case with historic peoples, while those we have in view are such as are only now beginning to write the first pages of their history, who hitherto have not made their mark in the world.&quot;If we believe that the hour has struck for a socialistic revolution, we may be sure that the nationalism of small groups living in an oasis surrounded by socialist microbes or in close association with revolutionary people will be short-lived, ,The time has passed for nationalism to flourish.   This was possible at the first
appearance of capitalism a century ago, at the time of the French Eevolution, but it is not possible in the time of the great proletarian revolution.&quot; We Communists must not, of course, undertake the task of cultivating the nationalism of small peoples, but on the other hand must avoid the tragic fate of the ass in iEsop&apos;s fables, who found himself between two identical stacks of hay and could not decide which one he ought to begin upon, as there was no point in giving preference to one stack over the other, and, as the ass perished from hunger owing to his failure to make up his mind, we can easily draw the moral from this fable in deciding the national question, if we do not adopt a definite criterion from a narrow point of view.&quot;We say definitely to the small nations which are beginning to develop that we shall help them in their present conditions to develop the Buryat, the Votyak, &amp;c, language and culture, for by&apos;this means they will more quickly share in the general culture of humanity, in the revolution, and in communism. In proportion as they develop they will convince themselves by their own experience how their nationalism and their national language obstruct them on the path of their develop-ment. These things are harmful not only to themselves but to .the whole of humanity to which they belong.&quot;Different nationalities have not fallen from the sky fully developed as we see them at present before us, but are the product of a whole complicated chain of historic causes which have played a great role in the development of each of them. Thanks to their geographic, climatic and economic conditions, nationalities have come to differ one from the other, and have received different kinds of development which have divided them into different races and nations. Now at a time when the old causes are disappearing, when man has learnt to fight against nature, geographic and climatic conditions as well as economic differences between people are changing their character, and the difference of class relations is disappearing with the realisa-tion of the ideas of socialism. The possibility of uniting all peoples is greatly increasing. Peculiarities of different nationalities will not disappear completely without leaving a trace, but will be like salt and sugar mixed together in the same dish. One nation will not be swallowed up by any other nation, but from their union one with another they will be transformed into something new.&quot;If the road which the small nationalities will take is clear to us, we know what line, to adopt and whither it will lead us. If the movement against their former masters assumes with small nationalities, instead of a purely revolutionary, character, a tinge of nationalism, then we must not be disturbed. It is true that when this movement&apos; assumes a purely aggressive character we must reply to it in the same way. We see this in the case of the Poles. What moral factors act upon the workmen and peasants in Pilsudski&apos;s army which is now operating against us? Undoubtedly the chief factor is that of nationalism.&quot;Hatred of the Great russians during the time of the Autocracy was very strong amongst the Poles, and this was quite natural, as they considered them their oppressors. The Polish workmen are now being persuaded that the Communists are the same Great Eussian Imperialists who are endeavouring to seize Poland. These lies, unfortunately, have produced an effect, and we are compelled to defend ourselves against them by armed force. But a change is already beginning. Many factors in the dislocation of Pilsudski&apos;s army witness to this change. With our present national policy, hatred of us, which is based only on national feelings, cannot be dangerous to us for long.&quot; Our chief enemy consists of the capitalist interests of our opponents, who cannot reconcile themselves to the foundations of our new form of government. Among many freely developed nationalities, elements which are near to our Eussian &quot;middle&quot; peasants are in the ascendant. The dictatorship of the bourgeoisie cannot under any conditions defend their interests better than the proletariat at the present critical time when the small property owner is in want of the products of labour. For a long time to come he is guaranteed against competition with our industries which have been ruined by the war.&quot; We see this in practice amongst the nationalities that live within the boun-daries of Soviet Eussia. Moslem armies are being built ufj to defend Soviet Eussia. They are devoted to it and are dying heroically in defence-of their interests which are in common with ours. Many of these small nationalities which underwent the occupation of the Whites remained faithful to us, and, during the whole time, caused great alarm to those in occupation. We must admit that on the part of some Soviet workers, who did not properly understand the national policy of Soviet Eussia, some
unjust complaints were made against these oppressed nationalities. They knew, for example, that Ukrainian separatism was harmful from the point of view of Socialism, and they took all appearances of national signs of life as separatism, and for that reason they opposed them. This internationalism of certain of our comrades caused us considerable harm by lessening the sympathies of these unfortunate Allogenes towards us. This is now being corrected by Lenin&apos;s appeals and by legislative acts.&quot; Many comrades are frightened by the idea that we are organising something which is dangerous to ourselves in going to meet the national tendencies of different nationalities. Will not this be used against us, they ask, when we have helped them to be independent? Will they not turn &quot;from us and go over to the side of our opponents ? Such doubts very often spoil our relations with these peoples and lead to suspicions which interfere with our successes. *&quot; We must win the small nationalities for the revolution, for Communism. We must send amongst the poor of these nationalities our Communist missionaries&apos;. They will not act in the same way as the agents of the Orthodox Church who tried to introduce Slavism amongst the Kirghizes, Kalmuks, &amp;c, acting in such a way as to make the Allogenes believe that in adopting Christianity they were losing their own nationality and becoming Russians. If we act wisely and translate our Communist doctrines into different languages and explain to them their own manner of life, we shall undoubtedly meet with a great response amongst them. We have already taken the fiist steps in this direction. Everywhere there are the beginnings of Communist organisations which are the outposts against attempts from any side. We must double and treble this kind of work.&quot; Some people will say that Communism amongst these peoples is only in its infancy, and that independence has been given to them without any proper guarantees. To this we reply that we know very well that there are no aggressive intentions amongst any of us. Our real interests coincide. Moreover, in economic respects these nationalities cannot in any way be independent. They are linked with us and dependent upon us. For strategic reasons the Autocracy transplanted Russian Communists amongst these peoples in order that they might not constitute a danger to Russia. It is possible that in time we shall be able to correct this criminal policy of Russification, but it is clear from this that at present there are no real reasons for being alarmed in this connection.&quot;Liberated Russia is attracting the sympathies of the nations which are still enslaved. They are turning to us for moral support. They see in us the much-desired symbol of a country where all peoples can live together freely. The Koreans inform us that the Japanese bourgeoisie no longer sit so firmly on their thrones. The Japanese workers are being educated. The Japanese workers are thinking of following our example. The oppressed Korean workers, who are raising their national standard of revolt, are at the same time adopting revolutionary Socialist mottces, which are quickly being caught up by the Japanese proletariat.&apos;&apos;(c.) Bolshevik Propaganda among Nomadic Peoples.(&quot;Zhizn Natsionalnostei,&quot; Organ of the People&apos;s Commissariat for NationalitiesDecember 14, 1919.)&quot;Within Soviet Russia (including Turkestan) there lives a nomadic population of not less than 15,000,000, as, for example, the Kirghizes, some of the Bashkirs, the Turcomans, &amp;c. Hitherto, Communist work among the nomads has been conducted on wrong lines. The same methods have been adopted as in the case of the Russian population, and Russian Communist literature has been translated. Experience has shown that this has been unsuccessful.&quot;The nomads have not passed through a capitalist state of society, and capitalist relations are strange to them. Communist agitation in favour of the class struggle between the proletariat and the bourgeoisie was quite incomprehensible to the masses, and those genuine Bashkir or Kirghiz Communists who had been educated in this agitation found that they, had lost touch with the masses of the population and had become &quot;Russian &quot; Communists.. &quot;Amongst the nomads, it is true, the proletariat is small,&apos;but the number of poor is very large. These poor are not lost for Communism. Propaganda is easier amongst them than amongst the Russian middle peasants [srednyak]. The idea of private property is deeply engrained in the srednyak, but has as yet no deep roots.
among the nomads. The latter still preserve what is left of primitive Communism. If the Mensheviks were to do propaganda amongst them, they would argue that Socialism is only possible when Communism has fallen to pieces, and that the nomads must first pass through capitalist relations.&quot; It is not our object to implant Capitalism where it does not yet exist. &quot;We must find a way to bring the nomads from their present state to Communism.&quot;The nomads will soon pass to a settled way of life. The Soviet Government must see that during the transition stage to settled modes of life they do not become land proprietors. We must find some method of sharing the land in common for the nomads which will bring them near to Communism. Our propaganda, therefore, must be conducted on these lines, and we must create a new literature suited to the conditions of the nomads. For this purpose we require all those Communists who know the life of the nomads and can help in creating this Communist literature.&quot;February 19,1920.o

</content>
</cab>
