<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/99/0 images: 224-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT 13 THE&apos; PRO  Eft T!^ OffHI3 -BRITABfltO MAJESTY1 S&apos; GO&apos;vT&apos;?J?MElJJ) *j SECRET, Copy No,O.P.y-7Bdi CAB HEBOUNDARIES OF THE ARMENIAN SME,Decisions of Council of Foreign Secretaries and Ambassadorson 1-etrus.ry^/tnT^^^TCopies of letters from Sir M* Hankey to Mar3halFooh and MroMallrinc(Circulated for information).1 i- I.&apos; LONDON. 8th February, 1920.Mpnsieur le MarSohal,I am dirooted by Mr, Lloyd teeorge to enclose a oopy of a letter I have addressed to the Drawing Committee conveying the provisional decision? of the Council&quot; of Foreign v&amp;ntBterz $nd Ambassadors on the aubjeot of the boundaries of the Armenian State.&apos; It is thought that this information may be useful to&apos;the Commission under your presidency&apos;which is studying the military, naval and air clauses for the Treaty of Peace with Turkey.-I have the honour to be, Monsieur le Marshal, Your obedient Servantt (Signed)   M*P.a.HAN EY. M, le Mrechal. Foch, G*C* *II.LONDON. 28th February, 1920.Sir&quot;,I am directed by Mr. lloyd George to inform you, for tbje-information of the Drafting Committee, that the Conference of Foreign Secretaries and Ambassadors, on February 27th, had under consideration the report and proposals of the Commission for the
delimitation of the boundaries of Armenia, of Tahioh 1 ^joclceecopy, and took the following provisional decisions.(1) That Erzinjan and Srebizond should not be includedI in the boundaries of Armenia^(2) That the boundary between Armenia and the FreeState of Batun should be determined on the spot by an inter-Allied Commission, the smaller zone being preferred, . (3)&apos; That a decision with regard to the boundariesbetween the States of Armenia, Georgia and Azerbaijan should bo postponed until the results of the,agreement&apos; between the three Republics were knownj and that an inter-Allied Commission should subsequently be appointed to . demarcate the linoo(4) That an autonomous State of lasistan should be oreatedunder the. nominal suzerainty of Armenia as suggested by the Commission-for tho Delimitation: of the boundaries of Armenia.(5) That in the hinterland of Irebizbnd between Tereboli andKemakl the Turks should not be entitled either to maintain troops or to keep stores of munitions *(6) That the Council of the League of Nations should beinvited at a later date to oonsiderthO supply to Armenia of the material and&apos; funds necessary for the creation of a National Army, ana\ if necessary, the raising of volunteers among the Allied and Associated Powers for the service of the new States.I am&apos;  . Sir,Your obedient Servant, (Signed)    M.P,A-HAMEY.p,H.W. Malkin, Esq.,v &apos; Drafting Committee.

</content>
</cab>
