<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/99/0 images: 247-252</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
m. C. LUNCHURST,        2()5THIS J)0CulO3JT, Ig THi&apos;3. PROPERTY OP, IJIS,,3RITA1TOQ UAJ23T *Q QOMI^t, GOHPIMTI^. 0 A B,I It. E ,T.O.P.763i KSaOS   WITH   RUSSIA. ^Copy of letter from lir, G.LI,Young, late Financial Adviser to the North Russian Government, to the Private Secretary to the prime Ministerj covering a Memorial.National Emission Caisse (North Russia), 20, Cockspur Street, London, S,W.l.21st Peb.,1920.ily dear Davie3,kI should he most grateful if you would put the accompanying memorial before the Prime Liinistor as early as possible.     I think it speaks for itself but if he wished to hear the signatories they would of couse be happy to wait on him.May I ask you also to add one point which does, not come within the scope of the armorial but which some of the   signatories have very much at heart.     I mean the position of the North Russian Government and people.     Created by the Allies for their own purposes, that Government ha el shown a tenacity of life which puts it in a diffe^j^t; class from the governments of Judenich and Kolchak.     What is more it has shown itself able to rally its people and hold them together even after the evacuation.       It is truo they have not been seriously attacked, but it is wonderful that they have not collapsed from internal strain,.     How much of their unexpected vigour is due to the constant pressure and example of tho English command, it is not easy to say:     personally having lived with them for more than a year I am inclined to put a great deal to that account, and in particular to the credit of Ironside and Hoare.     However, this may be I am afraid that only an early peace eon save them now, and if a Government of our creation is destroyed before the final settlement is made we shall incur much loss (material as well as moral) and it will bo remembered
against us for a long while in the North of Europe.Yours sincerely, 1(Signed)   G. M, YOUNG.It may he worth adding Jjhot Llr,Lambert,. Mr.Sponc^r -Smith, . and Mr0 Spring Rice aro partners respectively in the City firms--of Higgs Whishaw, H, Lefevre and Alexanders^
MEMORIAL.The under signed who have &quot;been at varaous--^times in the last two years engaged in official duties in Russia thinir-that a state-ment of the views which they unanim-oualy hold may at this^uncinrre be of interest to IP.M. Government,The signatories do not consider that ^the crimes committed &quot;by the Russian Government in the past should be regarded as s bar to its recognition now.     They do not believe that the non-Bolshevik governments of Siberia and the South have shown themselves superior to their enemies in humanity, while in energy, union ana. resource they have shown themselves inferior.     If the western powers are influenced by fear of revolutionary propaganda and of the precedent set for direct action by the success of the Soviet government, the signatories would suggest that no protective measures would be so effectual as the reopening of Russia to commerce, intercourse and observation.     The forces of moderation in Russia would be con-solidated, the fundamental differences of character, education and economic structures between Russia and Europe wtmld be displayed, and the misery.to which great territories have been reduced would, if once disclosed, &apos; be the mo3t impressive of warnings against precipitate and violent social changes.     In any oase the Russian question can no longer be isolated from the larger European problem,. It Ls becoming clearer every day that the stability of Europe de-pends mainly on the Central European states being adequately pro-visioned during the coming year, and it is impossible to see froiin what source they can be provisioned except from Russia,,     As the Russian grain moves westward, the danger ,of famina and its con-sequences will disappear.But without b general peace the resources of Russia cannot bo made available.     Until the civil war is ended, there will be no transport to move the grain, and the peasant will neither disclosehis
hia stocks nor work for a larger harvest than he can con.aume&quot;him-self,     It appears to us that the plan of trading through the Go-operatives exclusively will for this&quot; reason alone he found to bo ineffectual even if their resources were otherwise adequate to the task.Without the co-operation of the Russian Government and a largs   j concentration of foreign capital there can be no movement of produce on a scale at all proportioned to the needs of Europe,     Mor does it seem either equitable or politic that.one organization should have free entry into the Russian market while other traders including the great business houses which have done so much for the prosperity of Russia in the past are kept waiting on political developments,Moreover, the co-operative project affords no relief to pre-war ,: bondholders and gives them no incentive to take part in the re-jconstruction of Russia.     Yet it is reported that the Russian Govern-ment is prepared, when once relations are resumed to consider their claims and it is evident that no class in the community has a greater interest in reviving Russian production,-If the Russian supplies are hot made available and there is in consequence famine in any region east of the Rhine, there will cer-tainly be disorder and probably outbreaks of the kind which marked the early phases ,of Bolshevism in Russia,     Once started they might spread beyond the area of their origin,     That the Russian Government,., if still at war with the world would overlook so fair an opportunity of extending its principles is hardly to be supposed,     Its natural policy would be to intervene on the side of the revolution everywhere: with a victorious and seasoned army at its command it could intervene effectively, bringing food as it advanced,In face of these alternatives we believe that peace with Russia is necessary both on economic and on political grounds to save tho continent of Europe from catastrophe.     But if peace is to come at all it must come soon, before famine has made itself felt, and if itis
209is to come soon it must come from England..     Being as a nation loss exposed than tho Continental powers to roroCyjrtdon^ry ini^&amp;o-^i/m, -rpe con think with less passion:     having an equal concern with them in the welfare of Europe and. a special concern in the peace of Asia, we speak with more authority,.-   Even on the narrowest1 ground of natlonal interest the restoration of Russia is a vital concern to us,      Tne-mov populous empire in the world in our neighbour;   the most. .produc-W.Te area in the world is our debtor,     But the longer peace is delated, th-more certain it becomes that the German influence will be. T^ws^iah^JLsh, in Russia, and that Russian policy, both economical and diplomatic, will in consequence take on a character of antagonism to this country.     At a time when we shall be at once searching for new markets and.loading India and the Middle Eas.t through a most difficult period of transiAlor. we cannot afford to see a rival installed in a privileged position and working to make every point.of contact hetweenJUngland and Russia a point of friction as well.  -(3d.)   H. P. GOUGH,it-General. .19,2,20,(Sd.)   P,Lambert.14, Copthall Avenue 3.,. C, Late British Supply Contriver 6c apolitical Officer at Murmansk:.^(Sd.)   Hi Spencer Smith16, Bishopsgate, E,0. Late $..A.&amp;North Russia Expeditionary Force Murmansk;(Sd.)   Domini^ Spring Rice, 24, Lombard St, ,13,0, Late Financial Adviser, British . j.i i s 3 i on 10 Rus &amp;a a ,(Sd.)   P.G,LiOrsh, Lt-Colwiol,(Sd,)   ft,;.. Harvey,a11 en , H a r v ey &amp; R ess, (Late Financial Advisor, North Russia, and to the High , Commissioner of the Rhine),(Sd.)   G ,11,1 ifoung,La t e F i n an p i a 1 A d v i s e r, jorth Russian Government,
210Further letter from Mr. G.M. Young to Mr. J.T.Davies.National Emission Caisse (North Russia), 20, Cockspur Street, London, S.VJ.1.My dear Davies,The Prime Minister said he would circulate the memorial to the Cabinet.     Ttould you be good enough to add the names of :-x Lt.-Col. F.G. Marsh, C.M.G.x E.M. Harvey.(Allen, Harvey and Ross:   late Financial Advisers North Russia and to the High Commissioner of the Rhine).We had a most successful audience and were exceedingly grateful to you for your intervention.Yours sincerely,(Signed). G.M.YOUNG.x    Name inserted in reproducing Memorial.

</content>
</cab>
