<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/99/0 images: 319-334</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,, &quot;secret J (Home Office)Heporb No. 44 Scotland Rouse, S.W.1.4th March, 1920REPORT OK REVOLUTIONARY ORGANISATIONS IN THE UNITED KINGDOM(Circulated by the Home Secretary)NATIONALISATION OP THE COAL MINES...................... Page 1PROFITEERING AND HIGH PRICES........................... &quot; 2PEELING AMONGST EX-SERVICE hon......................... &quot; 3PROHIBITION MEETING AT LIVERPOOL.................... * 4SHEFFIELD AND TEE SPECIAL CONSTABULARY................. &quot; 4THE COMMUNIST PARTY.................................... &quot; 5THE INDEPENDENT LABOUR PARTY........................... &quot; 6THE &quot;HANDS OPP RUSSIA&quot; M0VSL1ENT........................ &quot; 6THE INTERNATIONAL UNION OP EX-SERVICE MEN.............. &quot; 7THE &quot;DAILY HERALD1&apos;..................................... &quot; mr. GEORGE LANS BURY.................................... &quot; 8LIEUTENANT COLONEL MALONE. LLP......................... &quot; 8SYLVIA PANKHURST AND PHILIPS PRICE ..................... w 9TOM MANN............................................... &quot; 10SINN PBIN IN GREAT BRITAIN ........................... &quot; 10IRELAND................................................ &quot; 18S U M MARYThe high oost of living and the feeling about profiteering are still paramount and demands for considerably increased wages may ce expeoted.A general strike for nationalisation of the coal-mines does not appear provable, but the miners may strike for inoreased wages in the near future.The disoontent at the discharges from the Arsenal led to a disorderly prooesslon to Westminster on March 1st.   There was a collision with the Police, which the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; describes as &quot;Westminsterloo&quot;. but only two casualties were reported from St. Thomas&quot;s Hospital.The extremists who are aiming at a United Communist Party in England have not yet settled their differences.Mr. Holmes, of the &quot;Dally Herald&quot;, stated that the paper was In debt to the extent of about  400,000.Albert/
Albert Inkpin, of the British Socialist Party, has state that he has a promise from Litvinoff to employ him at the Russian Embassy at a salary of  1.000 a year as soon as dipl relations are established with the Soviet Government.The &quot;Hands off Russia&quot; Meeting at the Albert Hall on th 28th February was financed by Theodore Rothstein, Lenin1s sec agent, who is credibly reported to have sent money to Paris assist in promoting the recent railway strike.There are growing rumours among Sinn Feiners in Great Britain of a rising known as &quot;Red Day&quot;, which is to take plac on April 5th.
HAT IOSALliti IPS OF TBS GOAL MIMES        - ..?\  .,,    ,  In the agenda for the Spooial Trade Union Congress on. March. 11th, the Parliamentary Committee &quot;suggests&quot; the.  following form of action:-(1)   Trade Union action in the form of a general strike. &quot; . ,,, ,(E)  Political action in the form of an intensive political propaganda in preparation for a general election,     ^ bummn&quot;In the event of Ko. (1) being carried the necessary stepswill &quot;be taken to give &quot;effect to it in accordance with theconstitution efeaoh union.&quot;Alarming though this sounds, it is really a death.sentence on direct action for nationalisation;because, the vote oein&amp; on the &quot;blbok&quot; system, there must he an individualballot in most of the unions and in an individual ballotdirect action will he rejected.   It is by no meanei certainthat the Congress itself will vote for a general strike;the more powerful unions will favour constitutional action.The National Federation of General Workers, with over amillion members, will probably be guided by Mr. W, Thorne,M.P., who has declared that a strike would be a &quot;foolish       Iand suioidal policy&quot;.   The railwaymen, numbering half amillion, have their own reasons for not desiring any strike   1just now, while the Textile unions, with a membership of   ;  I600,000, are quite indifferent to the affaire of the miners. IThe attitude of the Engineers is less certain, since theinfluence of Tom Mann cannot be gauged,, but the mouldershave exhausted their finances and the Scottish brancheshave already votod against direct action.   the probabilityis, therefore, against a vote for a general strike, but       there is always the possibility in the Congress that the delegates, who are elected by a noisy extremist minorityand claim to represent over six million British workers,may/
may wantonly force the issue.The Miners1 Federation will hold a conference on the day following the Congress, and it is said that if the votd goes against direct action the miners will demand from the Coal Controller the surplus after the guaranteed profit has been paid to the owners, in order to meet the increased cost of living.   The claim for higher wages will almost certainly be baoked by a threat to strike, and the miners will respond to an official call to strike either for nationalisation or for higher wages.If a strike be not averted, everything will depend upon the stocks of ooal, not only for vital services but for industries.   In Cornwall for example there is reported to be wily a few days&apos; reserve,, and if the, tin mines are flooded above a certain level it is reported that they will be permanently out of work.PROFITEERING AND HIGH prices the tide of resentment against high prices is stillflowing.   My Newcastle correspondent writes&quot;The price of living is the cause of all the discontent... Every person with whom I come into contact impresses on me that the only way to counteract the extremists&apos; programme is for the Government to concentrate on bringing down prices and to take action against those Trusts which are monopolising commodities.&quot;The Lancashire workers declare that they are being &quot;robbed right and left&quot;, and suggest &quot;general control and severe limitation of prices&quot; as a remedy.At Redruth Market  butter was seized and given away or sold at a moderate price;, eggs and other produce, vh ich the owners would not sell at the miners&apos; price, were forcibly taken and in some cases thrown away.- The Bedwellty Profiteering Committee has decided to close/
close down as it is considered &quot;useless to tinker with trivial cases, while the huge profiteering of Combines cannot be stopped at the source.&quot;In London, anti-profiteering demonstrations are to be held in the Winter Garden Theatre and in Trafalgar Square on March 9th and 13th respectively.   There is ill-feeling about the increase In the price of London coal; the working class contends that the recent increase given to carters and loaders works out at only 5d to 6d per ton and that the increase cannot, therefore, be justified.There can be no doubt that if it were possible to submit increases in price of commodities controlled by a Trust or Combine to a Tribunal &quot;before the increases were sanctioned, much of the distrust would be allayed.ffSKLING AMONGST gX-SMICg ism   -The ex-Service men at Woolwich, who have been drifting for some time into extremist hands, attempted to reaoh Westminster on March 1st in procession.   Their leader was W&apos;, B. Livingstone, who, in June 1918, was arrested in Glasgow on a charge of failing to maintain his wife and child at Aberdeen and with being an absentee. In accordance with the law, the procession was stopped on the South sido of Westminster Bridge, where some rioting took place.   The !?Daily Herald&quot; calls the incident &quot;Westmlnsterloo&quot;, and the men are demanding an enquiry, alleging injuries inflioted by the Police, but enquiries show that only two casualties were admitted into hospital: one man was thrown down and trampled on by the mob, sustaining a fractured jaw and another had a return of shell-shook owing to excitement.My/
My ccrrespondent at Glasgow reports that the &quot;Old Contemptibles&quot; Association of Ex-Service Men, with head-quarters at 38, York Street,.Glasgow, has a membership of about 2,200 and is growing.   Its policy is patriotic and if more funds were forthcoming it might be a set-off to the extremist unions.   The National Federation claims to have a membership of over a million and between 800 and 1,000 branches.. The National Union of Ex-Service Men, which claims a membership of 200,000, began a national campaign.for back pay on March 1st.   According to the &quot;New World&quot;, over 100 branches have passed the resolution to take any action, however strong and drastic it may be, which may be called for by the Executive in the case of (1) the recall of Class z\ (2) an attempt to involve the country in another war, or (3) the occurrence of a grave social and industrial crisis.PROHIBITION MEETING AT LIVERPOOLThe way of the English prohibitionists is not smooth. At a meeting in a Wesleyan Mission Hall at Liverpool on February 27th, the Chairman, Alderman Richardson of the Labour Party, was not allowed to say more than one sentence, and when a woman on the platform asked, &quot;What would you sooner give your children, bread or beer?&quot; she was answered with a roar of &quot;been &quot; from all parts of the Hall.   Anti-prohibitionists then mounted the platform and passed a resolution strongly protesting against &quot;the hordes of Americar .. agitators who wculd deprive the British working man of his national beverage.&quot; SHEEPIELD AND (MB gpBCIAL CONSTABULARYThe Sheffield Trades and Labour Council has taken upthe/
the question of the Special Constabulary end has v/ritten to the Lord Mayor to ask why the Watch Committee is enrolling men.   It was suggested at a recent meeting that all the delegates should enrol, &quot;Then we should be able to assure Socialist meetings being held at any time and place.&quot; It the same meeting, the Executive moved that the Press be excluded from all future meetings; after a heated debate, the recommendation from the Executive was defeated.   It is reported that the question of refusing the Press admission to meetings is being discussed by many of the Trades and Labour Councils.   The Independent Labour Party, which makes a great point of &quot;Secret Diplomacy&quot;, runs these Cou&amp;eils in almost every instance.THE COMMUNIST PARTYThe extremists are still quarrelling about the formation of a Communist Party in England.   There is a dispute between the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation and the British Socialist Party as to which of their respective organs should represent the Party, and there is the further difficulty that Miss Sylvia Pankhurst wants her own way and that if she does not get it she will break away       form an organisation of her own.   She has already quarrelled with the Workers1 Committee though it is recognised by Lenin.   Miss Pankhurst has dealt at considerable length in the &quot;Dreadnought&quot; with her forecast of the ultimate form of British Labour.   It contains nothing but the obvious.Albert Inkpin, of the British Socialist Party, has informed his friends that Litvinoff has promised him  1,000 a year salary at the Russian Embassy in London when diplomatic relations are resumed between British and Soviet Governments.THE/
IMS INDEPENDENT LABOUR PARTYThe campaign conducted against the Peace Treaty by this party is still in progress and it claims to have held 800 meetings within a short period.During the week, Gallacher and John McLean addressed Independent Labour Party meetings at Barrow at which 250-300 people were present.   Both advocated the overthrow of the Constitution.   Gallacher said:   &quot;They ash you to protect the Constitution which they made to protect their own robbery.   You h&amp;ve got to smash the Constitution.   You have got to organise and become strong.&quot;  McLean was equally emphatic:   &quot;The Government, are responsible for the Irish murders, not the Sinn Feiners, and Britain is responsible for the hell in Austria just now.   The capitalist system must be overthrown and the only salvatio is Bolshevism.&quot;.The West Riding has been visited by Messrs. Joseph   i Zing, ex-M.P., Roden Burton and J.W. Kneeshaw, who spoke on the usual lines of the Union of Democratic Control. Tom liyers, M.P.,,is very active in this district during   j week-ends; he devotes himself to explanation of proceeding in the House of Commons.THE &quot;BANDS OFF RUSSIA&quot; MOVEMENTThere was a large proportion of, aliens in the Albert Hall meeting on February 28th.   The resolution was proposi by Colonel Malone and seconded by Mr. Zangwill; other speakers were Tom Mann,-W. T. Goode, Robert Williams, Commander Grenfell and Mrs. Connolly.   No new points were! . made, in fact the speeches made by the pro-Bolshevik laadl are monotonous in their similarity.   At the request of Eoj Williams, a &quot;message of greeting&quot; *ae sent to the Frenoh 1railway/
railway strikers.   It is reported that the literature sales amounted to about  50, and the collection in the Hall yielded over  110.   A book on Bolshevism found a ready sale and the entire stock of Lenin&apos;s photographs, which were sold at 9d. each, was disposed of.The demonstration   cost Theodore Rothstein about  500 for fees to speakers and the rent of the Hall.   The money passed through the British Socialist Party and the go-between was Rothstein&apos;s son, who is a Brackenbury Scholar at Balliol, There is trustworthy information that during the last two months Rothstein has sent 25,000 francs to Loriot, in Paris, for organising the strike of raiiLwaymen on the occasion of the. Caillaux Trial,   Rothstein is of opinionthat France is about to &quot;crack&quot; at an early date.In the provinces the &quot;Hands off Russia&quot; campaign is still in progress; Colonel Halone has recently visited Reading, Mardy, Swansea and Llanelly.   A conference at Plymouth is said to have been attended by 50 delegates, including representatives of the Amalgamated Society of &quot;Engineers, Electrical Trades Union, Carpenters and Joiners, Dockers, National Union of Railwaymen, Coppersmiths, Workers&apos; Union, Boilermakers, National League of the Blind, Independent Labour Party and British Socialist Party.5?RE INTERNATIONAL UNION Off EX-SERVICE MBNThis Union is important only in respect of the violence of its views.   It has now opened a head office at 95,Minories, 3.0*, but as the East London Branch has a membership of only seventeen, of whom -twelve are ex-service men, and the funds on February 21st were under&apos;  5, it is not a very serious menace.&apos;    TEE/
TH3 &quot;DAILY HERALD&quot;On February 29th, Mr. Walter Holmes of the &quot;Daily Herald&quot;   addro&amp;sed a meeting of the Streatiiam Labour Party on &quot;Labour and the Pross&quot;.   He complained bitterly of the support given to the &quot;Daily Mail&quot; and the &quot;Svening Hews&quot; by &quot;so-called trade unionists?  who neglected the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; because it cannot afford to print more than eight pages.   He said that unfortunately the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; is not as successful as it deserves to be and at present is in debt to the extent of about  400,000.   Mr. Holmes added, with more optimism than truth, that the money is nevertheless forthcoming, &quot;from trade union funds and by the campaign which is about to be undertaken to increase the sales of the paper.&quot;   He said that sales are about 320,000 copies daily, 120,000 of which are-sent to the Worth of England.MB. GEORGE MMSBUKg . &apos;When passing through Helsingfors on his way to Russia Mr. Lansbury appeared very anxious to convince people of his impartiality.   He promised to do his utmost to obtain Keeling&apos;s release and to use him as an interpreter with the Russian workmen,as he feared above all things being &quot;spoon-fed&quot; by the Bolsheviks.   Those who have read his articles in the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; may judge his sincerity.   Though the Socialist reporters attempted to draw him on the question of the Third International, he parried all their questions. It is true that the &quot;Politiken&quot; claimed him a3 a &quot;comrade&quot; and there was a local newspaper feud as to whether he was of Bolshevik sympathies or not. LIEUTENANT COLONEL MALOMB. M.P.Lieutenant Colonel Halone seems desirous of occupying the/
- 9 -271the European stage if he can master a few French idioms.In a letter written to Albert Inkpin, the Seoretary to theBritish Socialist Party, and dated February 13th, he says;-&quot;I am not sure whether it is still much use to hold meetings in France.   It first occurred to me two or three months ago when, as you know, France was the chief obstruction to peace,.and I thought that a mass meeting or two in Paris or other industrial centres would be beneficial,&quot;Whether it will still be useful is perhaps a matter for the Local Authority and I suggest therefore that you? might disouss the matter with Longuet or other people an! see what they think.&quot;X have discussed it with Goods and he said he woulf be prepared to come too.   Naturally we should require a good deal of notice owing to bur dates being booked up until the end of March, and the need for preparation of ? a few, French Idioms.&quot;I presume that you will raise the question of international hands offRussia action at the Straeburg Conferenoe.*;SYLVIA PAflKHURST AND PHILIPS PRICE -During her recent visit to the Continent, Sylvia Penkhurst met Philips Price; the following ejctraots from9a letter which she wrote him on her return are notuninteresting:&quot;People here think that peace (with Russia) is about to come and are very jubilant.   They do not fully realise what trading with capitalists must mean to Soviet Russia:   compromise and the eating away of the Communist fabric   They do not realise how the Government here will try to put a wedge between the Co-operatives and the Soviets and incite them to private trading again.&quot;How I wish one could really know conditions in Russia;   I sometimes think that peace may be more dangerous to them than war - but. of course, war must be a horrible strain.   But in any case, everyone thinks it means peace, whereas there is so much reason to believe it is only a blind.&quot;I wish you could give your information very widely.   Of oourse, you get a good public in the &quot;Herald&quot;, but often your news is put in small type and people do not read the newspapers thoroughly every day.   Could you not write to some other papers besides the &quot;Herald&quot;?   I am not suggesting our own merely but for instance &quot;The New Statesman&quot;; &quot;The Labour Leader*; &quot;Common Sense&quot;; &quot;The Nation&quot;?   &quot;The Nation&quot; is very important:   our Socialists are such snobs:   they take their views largely from it.&quot;I was pleased to meet you, and hope that you will keep me as fully informed of all important matters as possible.&quot;TOM/
TOM MilThe General Secretary of the Amalgamate^. Society of engineers,, who supports direct action at any:time and forany purpose, discussed the question.of nationalisationin the February issue of the &quot;Amalgamated Engineers MonthlyReport and Journal.,:&quot;) Jfhile admitting Wat some trade unionists will declare, for constitutional action, he writes:,      &quot;There are others, of whom I am one, who hold ;     -that the,, only action likelyiito be-^-effective isIndustrial action.   Concerted action; over the entire induBtriai field:of ^activities,&apos; the&apos; organised workers..... deciding, exactly what5 services: should be rendered,whose interests should be catered for, -and who should have the privilege of looking after themselves.   This * is the plan to. follow. \  ;      v .   ; v&quot;It is to be hoped that the,Amalgamated Society of JSngineers&apos; delegates will be prepared to support a vigorous militant policy consistent with votes already given, and that not only will unanimity of v.ot4e be.; given, but thoroughgoing solidarity on the industrial field also.&quot;SOT ffjSIN, IN GREAT BRITAINThe Irish in,London are devoting much attention to the forthcoming Gaelic League Festival on St. Patrick&apos;s ^&apos;  Day.   -There is reported to be an &quot; onormous&quot; - numb er of &apos; applicants for tickets and the organisers are threatening to take action for breach, of contract, as the duoen^s Hall authorities failed to- supply.the tickets by the stipulated . .: time.&apos;   -   vLid, %:(Ur$&apos;z :&quot; &apos; &apos;v.-.&quot;;,fIt is reported that at the London; Sinnv^ein Convention &apos; on February 23rd, it was decided to make a determined attempt : as soon as practicable, to release the Sinn Fein prisoners &apos; at Wormwood/Scrubs; Councillor Kelly:of Liverpool was appointed to make.the necessary arrangements.  &apos;Several Finn Fein branches in this country are said to have discussed the possibility of a &quot;persecution&quot; of police officers/
officers who &quot;exceed their nominti duties and interest themselves in Finn Fein matters.&quot; . It is however thought that at present the scheme is not feasible.   The Sinn Feiners have decided to confine their &quot;important secrets&quot; to Irish born people and will adhere to this ruling even in South Wales where many branch officials are of mixed descent.The new branoh of the Irish Self-Determination League at Cardiff, to which I referred in my last report, has now been formed and is known as St. Albans No. 3. Thirty-three members have been enrolled.A demonstration of about 5000 Irish people was held at Glasgow, under the auspices of the United Irish League, on February 29th.   My correspondent reports that the majority of the audience consisted of men and women who adhere to constitutional methods.   Certain Sinn Fein hooligans were, however, present and the meeting terminated in uproar; Councillor Docherty was not allowed to speak, but my correspondent thinks this was due to the fact that he was particularly active on recruiting plat-forms until the Conscription Act was passed, when he fled to Ireland to avoid being called up.   The chief interrupter was a blind Sinn Feinerwho was not ejected on account of his disability.Consequent upon the split in the Irish Labour Party, to which I-referred in my last report, the Springburn, North Western and Duntooher branches have decided to secede and form a now body, &quot;The Irish Workers&apos; Republic&quot;, under the presidency of Sean McLoughlin.   This man is now generally recognised as a revolutionary adventurer.My/
My correspondent reports grov;ing rumours of a rising on April 5th, now known as the &quot;Red Day.&quot;   One young volunteer states that he has already been issued with a revolver, rifle and ammunition.   About 120 delegates areteported to have attended the second conference of the Irish volunteers at Coatbridge on February 26th,   It was then said that 2000 volunteers between the age of zo and 35 years were armed, had plenty of ammunition and sufficient, money and were willing to fight.   This statement is probably quite at variance with the facts.IRELAND   ;There was little improvement in the state of the country during the past week.. The total number of outrages, as far as known at present, does not appear to have been quite so large, nor were the outrages themselves quite so serious, perhaps, as during the preceding week, but the state of Liunster in particular and of Connaught and Leinster in a lesser degree remains most unsatisfactory.   Over thirty of the outrages reported have been raids for arms.Sinn Fein now openly professes to be carrying on a .   species of guerilla warfare against the forces of the Crown, particularly the police, and it is to be feared that in the absence of more widespread military assistance a further concentration of the police to enable them- to protect their barracks may become necessary. \Information is still being received that the Irish Republican Army has definitely decided on a policy of intermittent raids on Police barracks, so that unless these desperadoes receive a severe check when engaged in one of theii enterprises such attempts are likely to continue.The raids for arms and numerous cases of intimidationare/
are the work of gangs of Irish Volunteers, or companies of the Irish Republican Army, as they now style themselves.The next open activity is likely to be concentrated on the County and Rural District County elections in June in pursuance of the plan to obtain control of. the Local Government of the country.The current issue of &quot;Old Ireland&quot; is seditious and contains a very objectionable article by Andrew Maione. entitled &quot;Nothing of Importance&quot;, comparing the present state of the country with despatches during the late War.There is also a most unreliable article on Ulster by W. Forbes Patterson, the Australian Protestant convertedaSinn Feiner, who is out for what he can earn from Sinn Fein.   Government has directed this issue of &quot;Old Ireland&quot; to be Beized also wherever found.This week&apos;s number of the &quot;Watchword of Labour&quot; deals principally with the report of the recent English Labour delegates to Ireland.   It is entirely dissatisfied with the report and deolares that &quot;English Labour fails on Self-Determination for Ireland.&quot;   The editorial dealing with the same question adds. &quot;Evidently English Labour oan no more think of parting with the ill-gotten gains of empire than oan Liberal or Tory and it has failed to learn that the people of Ireland no more want to share in the responsibility of the Stapire than they do in its wars.&quot; This issue of the paper is now also to be seized for the tenth time.Agrarian trouble is still rather-rife in Galway and Clare.   In both counties there have been several outrages to force the surrender of sub-division of farms.Labour/
Labour matters remain fairly quiet though the Irish Transport and General. Workers Union is still active in fomenting local disputes and there is a .general tendency to force up wages to keep pace with the continual rise in the cost of living.   The latter is causing considerable privation and discontent in the towns.No inflammatory speeches have been recently delivered nor have any revolutionary pamphlets come under the notice of the police, though such are no doubt in circulation secretly amongst the small coterie of Socialists.   There is no real tendency to Bolshevism as such apart from the lawless and unsatisfactory state into which a large part of the country has fallen.A correspondent reports that there will be a lull in the militancy of certain Sinn Feiners in Ireland on account of the manner in which certain of the Irish Bishops condemn crime, from a religious standpoint, in their Lenten Pastorals.

</content>
</cab>
