<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/213/0 images: 532-542</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BMTANHIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1930.Copy  No.   30CABINET.RELIEF  OF  THE  ABLE-BODIED  UNEMPLOYED.                 MEMORANDUM BY THE  MINISTER OF LABOUR.    1.   AT the meeting on the 2nd July, 1930 (Cabinet  35  (30), Conclusion 4), theCabinet asked for a  memorandum &quot; giving the figures and facts  in  regard totransitional benefit,  including the benefits paid to married  women, with a view tofurther consideration of the subject.&quot;  A statement with regard to married womenis being prepared separately.  In order to put the question in its  proper perspective,this memorandum sets out the present position, the problem, and the alternativepolicies.   These  questions had in the meantime been under examination by theCommittee entrusted by the Cabinet with the duty of considering proposals in regardto the able-bodied unemployed not covered by the normal Unemployment Insurancescheme, but no decisions have been reached.                            I. PRESENT POSITION.    2.   There are now three forms of aid for the able-bodied unemployed :         (1)  unemployment  insurance;        (2)  transitional benefit;        (3)  public assistance (Poor Law).Unemployment Insurance.    3.   Persons who are able to show that they have paid at least 30 contributions in the last two years qualify for unemployment benefit.  So long as this condition-is satisfied, there is no limit to the period for which benefit can be drawn.  The ratefor a married man with two children is 30/- per week.   The scheme covers 12 millionout of about 17-J- million employed persons.    4.   The main classes not covered  by the scheme are  agriculture  (1,100,000),private  domestic service (1,335,000), persons under 16 and over 65 years  of age,railwaymen and other persons excepted under certificates of exception, Civil servants and persons  engaged  in non-manual  work earning more than  250 per annum.    5.   On a present live register of 1,890,000, the number of persons fully qualified for unemployment benefit is  1,450,000. While these are, in the main, regular workerssuffering from  intermittence of employment through  no fault of their own, about30 per cent, have been unemployed for more than 6 months in the year. On the otherhand, over half of them have been unemployed for less than  a month.Transitional Benefit.    6.   Persons who have not paid  30 contributions in the  last two years may stillqualify  for benefit, at the same rate and substantially under the same conditions asthe regular contributors, if they can show that they have paid at least 8 contributions in the last two years or 30 since entry into insurance, which  may go back to 1920 or,in some trades, to 1911.  This does not necessarily mean 8 weeks&apos; employment intwo years; it means merely some work in each of eight weeks.      [21368]                                                        BSECRET.CP. 235 (30).
     7.  Since last February the number of persons in receipt of transitional benefithas increased from 140,000 to over 300,000.  Of this increase 50,000 have come fromthe Poor Law.  The others are  for the most part persons who were not in receipt ofbenefit or of poor relief, either because they were disqualified or because they hadnot applied for it. Thus, in transferring 50,000 persons from the Poor Law to Statemaintenance, a much  larger number, 110,000, have been attracted in addition.  The300,000 persons in receipt of transitional benefit are not a homogeneous group.  Atone end of the scale there are the men still of good employment value who have beendisplaced and have little chance of obtaining employment in industries which  arecontracting; at the other end there are those persons who are only just able to satisfy the relaxed conditions for  the  receipt of transitional benefit.   The persons in this group are not very  different from persons outside the insurance  scheme  who, ifunemployed, either maintain themselves  or become claimants for public assistance.But, as the group has been created over several  years, it represents broadly  those with least competitive value in  the employment market.Public Assistance.    8.  A person who  is not  qualified  for  unemployment benefit or transitional benefit may be relieved by  the Public Assistance Authorities  according to  need.These Authorities at present provide the  following services :     (1) the provision of relief in money or in kind, or in both;    (2) the provision in kind of necessaries, e.g., teeth, boots, bedding, in addition           to (or  independently of) maintenance;    (3) the provision of medical attention, hospital treatment, or any other matter           or thing required as a result of physical or mental infirmity.    9.  There are 5J million persons  employed in industry who are not covered bythe insurance  scheme.  The average number of  heads of families  in  receipt of out-door relief (item  (1) above)  during 1929 was 120,000.II. THE  FINANCE OF THE THREE PRESENT SCHEMES.Unemployment Insurance.    10.  The payments of unemployment benefit are paid out of the UnemploymentFund,  which derives its income from contributions paid in practically equal  partsby the  employer, the worker and the Exchequer, in respect of workers while they arein employment.    11.  With the  reduction of the total amount of employment represented by theLive Register of 1,890,000, the total  income of the Unemployment Fund  derivedfrom  contributions amounts to   45,000,000 per  annum.   This  is  made up asfollows :                                                                  Contributed by workpeople   ...       ...    14,000,000             Contributed by employers    ...       ...    16,000,000             Contributed by the Exchequer...       ...    15,000,000    12.  On the other side of the account, the benefit paid to persons fully qualified(30 contributions in the last two years), together with the cost of administration,will amount in the course of a year to approximately  68,000,000, to which mustbe  added  over   2,000,000 for interest on the  debt, making  a  total of  over 70,000,000.  The  deficiency of  25,000,000 for the year  will have  to be met by borrowing.   Under  existing  legislation  there is  authority  to  borrow up  to 50,000,000, and the Cabinet has authorised a Bill to increase this to  60,000,000.This figure has been reached by the  following stages : 1921 Act   ...1921 (No. 2) Act1922 Act   ...1928 Act   ...1930 Act   ...1930 Bill   ...   millions.    10    20    30    40    50    60The  income and  expenditure  of  the  Unemployment Fund would balance, at thepresent,rates of benefit and contributions, with a live register in the neighbourhood
of 1,250,000.  Until the number on the register falls  to this figure,  the debt willsteadily increase.  The deficit is already beyond reasonable prospect of repayment atthe present rates of contributions and benefits.Transitional  Benefit.    13.  One of the provisions of the 1930 Act transferred to the Exchequer thecost of transitional benefit.  The result was to transfer temporarily to the Exchequer(at a present annual cost of nearly  20,000,000, which is borne on the Ministry ofLabour estimates) the burden of 300,000 of the able-bodied unemployed.  When theBill was  introduced the  estimated  cost  of transferring  these  persons  to  theExchequer was   8,500,000.  The  Bill was  modified, and the best estimates that could  be made suggested that the cost would be increased to  10,500,000,  without allowing for  payments to married women,  seasonal workers, &amp;o, which could notbe estimated.  Experience shows that, partly due to the phenomenal  live register,the cost may be  nearly  20,000,000.  This is expenditure upon a non-contributory basis in relief of the able-bodied unemployed, in addition to the State contributionto the Unemployment Fund.Public Assistance.    14.  The average number of heads of families in  receipt of outdoor relief in1929 was about 120,000.  The amount paid out in  1929 in this  respect was 5,700,000.   Since the operation of the 1930 Act the numbers of heads of familiesreceiving payment has fallen; the number  on the  latest date available was about72,000 in May 1930.    15.  The financial position of  the  three forms  of public relief is,  therefore,  asfollows :     Unemployment Insurance         Debt (which must be liquidated by the three parties or  by             the Exchequer) :   50,000,000  (possibly  increasing  to              70,000,000)    Contributions      .                                             Paid bv workpeople        ...       ...      ...     14,000,000 per  annum        Paid bv employers        ...       ...      ...     16,000,000  ,,        Paid by the Exchequer     ...       ...      ...     15,000,000  ,,   Ordinary  Benefit         Paid out  of  the Fund     ...       ...      ...     70,000,000  ,,    Transitional Benefit         Paid by the Exchequer     ...       ...      ...     20,000,000  ,,    Public Assistance 1        Paid by the Public Assistance Authorities   ...     5,725,000 (in  1929)        Estimated payment  likely to be made in the             financial year 1930     ...       ...       ...   2/3,000,000 per  annum            III. PROBLEMS ARISING OUT OF THE PRESENT POSITION.Unemployment Insurance.    16.  We are  still gaining experience of the effects of the  change  made by the1930 Act, but it  is clear that the Unemployment  Insurance  Scheme needs close examination. Conditions of industry are changing,  and the incidence and distribu-tion of unemployment among the various classes of  workers is  different from what it was in 1920 when the main scheme was introduced.  The scheme is being askedto meet situations  for which it was never designed. Apart from this wider question,it is for consideration how far the present scheme is appropriate to certain classes       [21368]                                                       B 2
of  workers; for  example, married  women,  casual  workers,  seasonal  workers,short-time workers, and elderly workers with little prospect of re-employment but with several years to go before they  are eligible for Old Age Pensions.   Even ifthere were no other reason, it is obviously impossible to continue without amendmenta scheme which  has  a debt that has mounted in six years from  5,000,000 to 50,000,000.     17.   The fact that a large section have come to regard benefit as a right withoutcontributions and on the same terms and rates as the  contributors makes  it all themore difficult to  deal  with the  proper contributory scheme  and to introduce anyimprovements into it.  The difficulty  would  be  intensified  and  perhaps  madeinsuperable if  the present  transitional  benefit scheme  were made permanent on anything like its present basis.Transitional Benefit.     18.   The situation that is developing cannot be attributed to the changes  madeby the 1930 Act;  it is of longer growth.  The transitional benefit provisions are, infact,  a continuation  of the various  extensions of  the  Unemployment InsuranceScheme since 1920, introduced in the  first place to meet the needs of newly-insuredcontributors who  found themselves out of work and had not paid, and could not pay,the contributions required to qualify them for benefit. The grant of this extendedform of benefit which began by being discretionary was originally for  a limited period  in individual cases,  with some  regard to  needs.   It  was  intended  as atemporary provision for those  persons who could be expected, - with the  return of improved trade conditions, to obtain regular insurable employment.  The  extensionwas treated  as  a temporary  &quot;over-draft&quot;  on the permanent insurance scheme.Circumstances have made it necessary to continue the  extension from time to  time,but on each occasion there has been agreement to the view that the expedient shouldbe regarded as a temporary one, to be brought to an end as soon as circumstances permit.     19.   The rates of benefit paid to  persons covered by  the extension are the sameas those paid to the ordinary insured contributor, irrespective of his actual earningswhen in employment.   The rate for a married man with two children is 30/- a week.This is, of course, higher than the net earnings of many miners working four shiftsa week;  it represents  75  per  cent,  of the  labourers&apos;  rate in the  engineering,shipbuilding and many other trades, and is equal to the agricultural workers rateover a considerable part of England and Wales.  The  corresponding rate  of benefit in 1921 was 22/- per week.  In the same  period (1921 to 1930), while the rate ofbenefit has increased, the cost of living figure has fallen from  128  in May 1921 to55 in May 1930.     20.   Following upon the 1930 Act a large number of persons have been admitted to transitional benefit who are not likely, even with improved industrial conditions,to obtain regular insurable employment.  It  is, therefore,  true to  say that to an appreciable extent transitional benefit, which is paid for entirely by the Exchequer,has ceased to be merely an extension of the Unemployment Insurance Scheme.  It isin fact a maintenance allowance outside the Public Assistance Scheme paid withoutthe tests attaching either to a contributory insurance scheme or  to the Poor Law.     21.   The 300,000 persons in receipt of transitional benefit must to a considerable extent be considered  therefore not as persons  who may reasonably be expected tobecome regular contributors to  the Unemployment Fund, but as persons outside theinsurance scheme for one cause or another for some  of whom  some form of main-tenance must be provided.     22.  So far as a claim for help from public funds is concerned, there is indeedlitCle to distinguish between the person in receipt of traditional benefit, who hasmerely paid 30 contributions since 1920, and the uninsured person.  That being so,and bearing in mind the view that an unemployed person in one trade may have asmuch need of help from public funds as an unemployed person in another  trade, thequestion at once arises, can (or ought) the scheme, whereby non-contributors are paid at the same rates as the contributors, to be.confined to those now represented by a group of 300,000 persons.     23.  This  position involves two especial . problems (1) that  those who arecontributing to the Unemployment Insurance Scheme may demand to!be relieved of
their liability to contribute,  and (2) that those who are at present not covered by insurance at all, e.g., those employed in agriculture and private domestic service, mayclaim payment of benefit at the cost of the Exchequer at the same rates as are givento insurable persons with less than thirty contributions.   In fact we are driftingtowards a position in which the responsibility for all the able-bodied unemployed will tend to become a charge upon the Exchequer without the check of local adminis-tration and local responsibility.Public Assistance.    24.  Exact information as to the effect of the present arrangements for paymentof transitional benefit upon poor law administration is not available to the Ministryof Labour (except in regard to the numbers that have been transferred from the poorlaw to the Employment Exchange)  but the  transitional benefit arrangements must obviously affect the general standard and development of poor law administration.Summary of the Present Position.    25.  The  present position may be  summarised as follows:-:    (1) The unemployment insurance  scheme itself is in  danger administratively           because  the interests of  the great majority of  the twelve  million           contributors are prejudiced in order to meet the special circumstances of           a much  smaller group, which was  140,000 in  February, but has been           increased to 300,000 since;    (2) a class has been artificially created between the insurance scheme and public           assistance, which tends to become permanent;    (3) this class is in receipt of benefit on a non-contributory basis, at the same           rates as contributors;    (4) other  groups  of  workers with  similar claims  to consideration have no         .  recourse except to the Public Assistance Authorities.                         IV. ALTERNATIVE POLICIES.    26.  The  immediate question to be decided is the position after April 1931 ofpersons at present in  receipt of transitional benefit.   The following alternative courses are open :     (A) to continue the transitional  period for another year  (with  or without          amended conditions designed to  go some way towards confining benefit          to those appropriately regarded as.&quot; still in the insurance field &quot;);    (B) to admit the impossibility of confining the benefit of the transitional scheme          to those now covered by it, and to make it available to all the able-bodied          unemployed  at the cost  of the Exchequer, i.e., a dual system of con-          tributory unemployment  insurance for normal insured workers,  and          Exchequer maintenance for others;    (C) to retain and develop the contributory insurance scheme for normal insured          workers, and to transfer to the Public Assistance Authorities,  for relief          according to need, those who have lost or have  never had  rights to          unemployment insurance benefit.    It is  assumed throughout this  memorandum that the Cabinet will desire thefullest practicable provision of remedial treatment (training, &amp;c), whatever scheme may be decided upon for maintenance,  and therefore no special reference is made toit under any of the alternatives.    Alternative A          A further transitional period.    27.  The  existing arrangements and the difficulties of the position have alreadybeen explained.    Their continuance can be regarded as a temporary expedient for adoption only if other courses fail.
    Alternative B          To make the transitional scheme available to all the able-bodied unemployed,             not entitled to ordinary benefit, at the cost of the Exchequer.    28.  Under this alternative,  all able-bodied unemployed persons not entitled to ordinary benefit, would receive State maintenance at the  cost  of  the  Exchequerthrough  a  central administration.   The local administration, including decisionsupon claims for assistance, could be entrusted either to     (1) the Employment Exchanges,  when  those  applying  for maintenance would           attend the Exchanges along Avith regular contributors to the  Unemploy-           ment Fund, the  inevitable tendency being to merge them in one group;  or    (2) the local Public Assistance Committee, operating from, say, the Town Hall,           Avith co-operation by the Employment Exchanges in work-finding;  or    (3) a neAv local body (Local  Employment Authority), including representation           of the  Public  Assistance  Authority  and  the  Local  Employment           Committee,  combining  the experience  and  knowledge  of  the local           authority and of the  Employment Exchanges, in selecting the persons           Avho are to receive maintenance or treatment.    If the local administration is in the hands of the Employment Exchanges, therecan, of course,  be central control, upon lines determined on national grounds.  If,however, local  administration  (at Exchequer cost) is in the charge of either fEePublic Assistance Committee or some new joint body, important questions arise as tothe extent  to Avhich there can be  central control of the administration.  Conflict isto be expected between the central government and  the local authority, both  on general questions and  individual cases, as well  as in  regard to the administrative costs of the local work.    29.  There  are certain services at present performed by the Public AssistanceCommittees which could not be assumed by a central  authority,  e.g., the provisionof medical  services. In any case public assistance would have to remain as the basicprovision for persons Avho fail to pass any conditions which might be attached to a secondary scheme.   Certain questions at once arise Avhich call for  determination if ascheme of this kind is to be considered; for  example :     (1) Who should be included ?         Experience of the  1930 Act shows how difficult it is to estimate the number    of new  claimants that  may be  attracted  by any particular  change  in  the    conditions.  The number, however, is likely to  be large, and any extension of the    present provision  is therefore likely to admit an unknown number of persons    who at present are not  qualified for benefit,  and are not in receipt of  public    assistance, and, indeed, are not in need of assistance, but will claim it if it is    available.    (2) Should there be a needs test ?         If so, rules defining precisely AArhat is meant by need would have to be laid    down.   Are the Exchanges suited to the administration of  a scheme based  on    need?   The Employment  Exchange  machinery would  require a great deal of    adaptation  and extension for these new purposes.         If there is to be no needs test, what other conditions are to be applied ?    (3) On what scale  should relief or maintenance be given?         At present, persons receiving transitional benefit  on a non-contributory    basis receive the same  rates of benefit as the regular contributors.   Should the    payments continue to  be at  this  rate?   If  so, is  there any  justification for a    separate insurance scheme  Avith stricter conditions as regards contributions ?         Public Assistance Authorities adjust  their  standards  of  relief, broadly    speaking, to the actual cost of living in the particular locality,  at any rate, as    between urban and rural areas.  Is  a  national standard possible for this    purpose ?
(4) A t what stage should a person cease to be qualified for unemployment benefit        or State maintenance, and therefore fall to be dealt with by the Public        Assistance Authority?    (5)  Is there to be a readjustment of the new system of grants to Local Authorities             under the de-rating scheme ?        The present distribution of these grants is to some extent influenced by the    estimated burden of relieving the unemployed, and presumably, therefore, would    have to be reconsidered if the Local Authorities are relieved of the burden.Finance.    30.  For reasons  given in paragraph  29 (1)  above, it is  impossible even  toestimate the annual cost to the  Exchequer of  transferring the whole  burden  ofmaintaining  the  able-bodied  unemployed.    It would, however,  run into many millions.    Alternative C         Transfer to Public Assistance of persons not in the insurable field.    31.  The next alternative is to relegate to Public Assistance Authorities allpersons who are not strictly qualified for unemployment benefit under the Insurancescheme, while retaining that scheme for  those, and those only, who are qualified  by contributions.  This course clearly separates the Unemployment Insurance Schemefor the regular contributors from other forms of maintenance.   Taking a long view,is it not in the interests of 12,000,000 regular  insured workers (or a greater numberif insurance is extended), that they should be distinguishable from the much smaller number not covered by the insurance scheme ?  Whatever may have to be done in theimmediate  future,  to carry those who are  in difficulties owing to the  sharp andsevere post-war depression, should there not be, in a permanent scheme, some induce-ment  to a man to remain in the  insurance field, and some incentive to rejoin  it  toa man who may have fallen out of it ?    32.  Most of the persons who are not regular contributors to the UnemploymentFund need remedial treatment, varying according to individual needs, and the flat-rate insurance system is not suitable for them.  The body which has knowledge  oflocal economic conditions and has local responsibility is probably in  a better positionto administer to those needs.    33.  Such a  separation,  by relieving the Unemployment Insurance Scheme  ofits association with a scheme of Exchequer grants, would  enable  the Ministry  ofLabour to adjust  and adapt the scheme to meet changing industrial conditions, and,no doubt, with improved trade, to increase the measure of protection and benefits which the scheme can afford.    34.  One consequence of a proposal to transfer to Public Assistance committees the relief of persons outside insurance,  is that  considerable public opposition willbe aroused  by the  suggestion (particularly in the case of the older men who have spentthe greater part  of their lives in the insured trade, but, owing to the unfortunatecircumstances of  recent years, are not  qualified  for unemployment benefit), that theresponsibility for their future maintenance rested not With the State, but with theLocal Authorities.    In this connection reference may be made to the statement of policy in &quot; Labourand  the Nation,&quot; an extract  from which is given  in  the Appendix, together  withExtracts from recent speeches by leaders of the Opposition parties.    35.  Finance. The main difficulty, however, would be  that, while  the  total numbers and the cost would be widely distributed, in  some  areas Public assistance authorities would find a difficulty in meeting the extra cost.  This objection might
b. met by providing that the Public Assistance Authorities should administer thescheme with Exchequer assistance.  Difficult questions would, of course, arise as tothe proportion of the charge to be borne by each of the two parties:  In former timesa grant in aid of local relief as high as 50 per cent, was regarded as a very dangerousfinancial expedient, because the expenditure was not controllable.  It is considered desirable that  if  Local Authorities  are to  have a  substantial  share  in  theadministration  of whatever  scheme is  decided upon  for  the  class of person inquestion, .they should pay a sufficiently large proportion of the  total charge  to give them an  interest in the proper administration on their part.                     V. MAJOR QUESTIONS FOR  DECISION.     36.  Before details of any  scheme can be worked out, the  Cabinet must reach decisions on the following points :      (1) Is the  contributory unemployment insurance scheme to be maintained and           developed for the regular worker on the present tripartite arrangement,           under which employers, the workers and the State are all interested in           and  concerned with  the administration of the scheme, its progress, its           development and its improvement?     (2) As  regards persons now  in  receipt  of transitional  benefit, should  the           transitional period be extended temporarily (either on the present basis,           or with amended  conditions designed to go some way towards confining           it to those appropriately regarded as &quot; still in the insurable field &apos;&apos;) ?     (3) If  a  permanent  scheme  is  to  be  devised,  there  are the  following           alternatives :             1. to make the transitional benefit scheme available to all the able-bodied                 unemployed not entitled to benefit, at the cost of the Exchequer.                 The cost of this to the Exchequer  at present is nearly  20,000,000;                 its cost on an extended basis cannot be calculated; or           2. to retain  and  develop  the contributory  scheme for normal  insured                 workers and transfer  to  the  Public  Assistance Authorities,  for                 relief according to need,  those who have lost or have never had                 rights to unemployment insurance benefit.     37.  If  either of the two latter alternatives (1  or  2)  is  adopted,  certainsubsidiary  but  important  questions call  for decision, of which the most importantare: Under the first alternative        (i)  are the  persons in question to be given in general the  same benefits and             subject to the same conditions as those applicable to persons possessing             the contributory qualification,  or are they to  be different?      (ii)  is there to be a means test ?     (iii)  should the administration be by the Employment  Exchanges or by  the             Public Assistance Authorities, or by a new Local Body,, combining the             experience of both, if a satisfactory body can be devised?      (iv)  if  the Local Authorities are relieved of the cost of meeting the needs of             the unemployed, is a readjustment of grants to be made under  the             derating scheme?Under the second alternative       (v) is the Exchequer to share the cost and in what proportions?                                                   (Initialled)       M.  G. B.Ministry of Labour,    July 9, 1930.
                  EXTRACTS FROM &quot; LABOUR AND THE NATION.&quot;     THE reorganisation of Local Government contemplated by the Cabinet is slap- dash and amateurish to an almost ludicrous degree.  It leaves the Poor Law System, in all essentials, intact, though official investigations have repeatedly condemned it. It refuses  to remove the  maintenance of the unemployed from  the overburdened shoulders of local authorities,  though it is the cost of unemployment which  has created the present crisis in Local Government finance.         ******     It will treat unemployment as what it is a national, and not a local, issue  and  will transfer the present responsibility for unemployment from the local rates to a  national scheme.         *     ... *          *           *           *          *     In accordance with the recommendations long accepted by all  familiar with the problem, a Labour Government would transfer the maintenance of  unemployed workers from the local rates to  a national authority,  would break  up the Poor Law and  assign the care of the different classes of persons concerned to the  appropriate committees of the county or borough councils, and would thus at once relieve the mostnecessitous districts of a substantial part of the financial charges that at present  fall upon them, and secure that more effective provision is made for those in distress.APPENDIX II.                           EXTRACTS FROM  HANSARD. Hansard, 21st November, 1929.                    UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (NO. 2) BILL.     MR. LOCKER-LAMPSON: The criticism which  I  make against the Bill  is- that there is no definite relation in it between contributions and benefits.  The next step after the Act of 1927 ought to have been to revert to the Act of 1920, where a definite relation between contributions and benefits was laid down.  The Government ought to have taken the uninsurable class  out of insurance altogether and handed them over to the local authorities and the machinery of the new Local Government Act.  [Hon.  Members:  &quot;Oh!&quot;]  I was afraid that hon. Gentlemen opposite  would not  agree with me  on that point,  but until that  is  done, every  unemployment insurance scheme will be  actuarially unsound and vicious in principle.  It is now generally recognised, as it was recognised in the Blanesburgh Report, that there must always  be a large number of people chronically unemployed.  These ought not to be dealt with in  an insurance scheme at all.  The  problem of the chronically unemployed is a totally different one and, to my mind,  should be dealt with  under a special scheme.  The old  local authorities that dealt with destitution and with grants for relieving that destitution having now been  unified, there  was a great opportunity to establish an  insurance scheme, on the one hand, actuarially sound, for those who in normal  times can get work and are therefore insurable, and,  on[the other hand, a scheme under the new Local Government Act for those who must be regarded,  I am sorry to  say, as chronically unemployed  and  who have to faceIminsurable unemployment.   But the  Bill before  the  House has failed to do that.Kt has  tried to include both categories, the insurable and  the  uninsurable, andtherefore it can only be regarded as merely a transitional Measure until somethingItetter can be thought out.      [21368]                                                         e
Hansard, 21st November, 1929.                    UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (NO. 2) BILL.    MR. G. LOCKER-LAMPSON : They do not form part of the unemploymentinsurance scheme at all.  They ought to be dealt with  by special schemes arranged by the local authorities with an Exchequer grant certainly not on the rates.Hansard, 25th November, 1929.                    UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (No. 2) BILL.    MR. STANLEY :  Does not that give certain opportunities \  An hon. Memberopposite made great play with the suggestion of my right hon. Friend with regardto local authorities.  Was that suggestion really  quite as ridiculous as  the  hon.Member tried to make out ?  Is it not conceivable that the Ministry of Labour, going through these people for whom this relief is designed, may see a certain number whothrough age or health or other causes are, in fact,  unemployed, and never likely tobe employed again or become part of an unemployment  insurance scheme.  Is it notpossible that they may say that the amount of this Fund applicable to that portionis much better administered through local authorities with all their local resources ?Is it not possible to take out the class of the young men  with no dependents and saythat the amount of the  Fund applicable to these young men will be better paid out as part payment of wages on some national scheme than  it would be in simple relief 1Is it  not possible that in the case of the more technical unemployed the  Ministrymight feel that their chances of  finding employment would be greater through thecraftsmen&apos;s union, that the union will be able to keep an  eye upon them and see whether the skill they still possess entitled them to be classed as such craftsmen, anddelegate the work of their relief to the union ?  It is also conceivable that you mightcapitalise part of this Fund  and use it for grants  in your afforestation  settlementsand upon the land.  I  do not say that all these suggestions are practicable, but Ithink we are  entitled to ask the right  hon.  Lady whether such matters have  beenconsidered and, if not,  we are entitled to an explanation as to why none of these suggestions have been put before  us.  Do not let us forget  that  this is  a  very fineopportunity.  When you administer these  new principles  under the old methodsyou will have  less opportunity, and if you want to do something of that kind in thefuture it may be a great deal more difficult.Hansard, 25th November, 1929.                   UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (NO. 2) BILL.    MR. ORMSBY-GORE :  I believe it is essential to  bring the administration ofthe whole of the chronic class out  of association with the insurance fund altogetherfor good and all.  The only way to deal with that class is in association with the newcentral  authorities.Hansard, 25th November, 1929.                   UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (NO. 2) BILL.     MR. ORMSBY-GORE :  The essential  thing is to  take over the restoration ofthese people by one organisation.   The present position is  ridiculous.  You  have65,000 people unemployed, wholly maintained out of the rates,  to which  the centralGovernment does not contribute one penny, and you  are going to have 120,000 similarpeople paid wholly from the  central Government, and not out of the rates.  On top of that you are to have two similar organisations,  the organisation of the new PoorLaw  authorities, dealing with one category, and the Employment Exchanges (whichare to-day ceasing altogether to fulfil their functions of  Employment Exchanges and are becoming a new relieving inquisitorial order)  examining  into the lives of thepeople, to deal with the other category.     The only essential  thing is to bring those two categories together, and to dealwith them in  a partnership between the State and  the local authorities by relievingthose people in a more scientific way not based on a flat rate.   An hon. Member says : &quot;More on the rates.&quot;  I wish to emphasise not on the rates.
     If a proposition to deal scientifically with those people not on a flat rate or on the rates. in a way which will meet the needs of the very poorest class of the unemployed, can  be  examined,  not in relation  to  the  stability  or  finance of an insurance fund from which half the contributors have drawn no benefit, if the State will face up to the problem of the submerged tenth and of how to deal with them in a humane way, then you will find your solution.   The whole problem is to combine together the necessary deterrent and the necessary incentive, the necessary preventive side with the essential restorative side, in dealing with that appalling isolated mass in getting it back into industry.  That is where your internal migration schemes, your adult training schemes  and your various scales of relief will help.-  Then vou will have isolated the great shifting mass of insured people  who can be covered by Insurance, the bulk of whom are in and out of employment, and whom the Fund can help during the  temporary periods of unemployment.   That is  the  only type of unemployed that an insurance scheme can  really help. Hansard, 4:th April, 1930.                    UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE  (NO. 3)  BILL. SIR A. STEEL-MAITLAND :          *           *****     Take our present  unemployment system.  It is a fact that there is no one satisfied with it as it exists.  That is true of those  who sit on both sides of the House.   I am not going to discuss the rights and wrongs of the Blanesburgh recommendations or the previous Acts dealing with this subject and more particularly the Act which was passed early this year,  but no one is satisfied with the results, and the reason  that they are dissatisfied is because those Acts mix up pure insurance with what you may call  State assistance,  maintenance, or relief.  It is  the mixture of the two things that causes the trouble, because either of them, taken separately, can be administered all right, but when you mix up the two the results are disastrous.  The labour  that is immobile is not the labour that would receive benefits under  a real insurance system.  From that  point of  view, cannot  something be  done to  improve the situation 1  Everybody  is agreed that the two things ought  to be separated.   The hon. Member  for  Leith (Mr. E. Brown)  suggested the setting up of  a Cabinet Committee  to go  into this question and  thoroughly overhaul it.   I  do not know whether that Committee is likely to reach the conclusion of its labours  very soon; in fact, I am not quite  sure whether it has ever met.  Of course, I would not refer to a Cabinet Committee if Members of the Government had not referred to it on several occasions.    MR. THOMAS : I publicly announced that meetings of the Committee had been held.    SIR A.  STEEL-MAITLAND : That is so much to the good.   Here you have a system which is admittedly not perfect, and I think it ought to be changed.  The fact that the system is so imperfect is increasing the amount of unemployment.  This is obviously a controversial matter, but I would ask the Lord Privy Seal and the House to consider the fact that the field of controversy, although acute, is not really as wide as it seems at the first  glance.   In my view, if all the differences on this subject were stated, I do not think it would be found that there is any  real difference on thepure insurance side of the question.  If we were left to settle the pure insuranceside, I  do not imagine that  there  would  be  much difficulty about coming to anagreement as to a workable  system.

</content>
</cab>
