<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/213/0 images: 545-548</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
s document is ihe property of His Britannic Majesty&apos; s Government) 0ET.                    CAB I I)T E T .237(30).          STOWAWAYS FROM AROHAHGEL.                  3  4            Memorandum by the Home Secretary.      I desire to obtain, as a matter of urgency, the advice ofray colleagues on a very difficult question which has arisen inregard to the disposal of certain stowaways from Archangel who,.on arrival here, have claimed to be escaped political prisoners.      On the 10th June last a Russian stowaway arrived at liverpool on the s.s. Langleeridge from Archangel and claimed&apos;to be a political refugee who had escaped from a party  ofsome 1,200 convicts employed by the Soviet Government inloading and unloading ships at Archangel.      Since then further stowaways have arrived as follows:-                     On 17th June     1                        20th   &quot;      3                        28th   &quot;      3                         1st July     1                         5th  &quot;       1All claim to be political prisoners and ask not to be sent backto Archangel, stating that they would certainly be shot on arrival.   One has said that he would sooner commit suicidethan return to Russia.      The normal course is for a stowaway to be refused leave to land in this country and to require the master of the vesselon which he arrived to remove him.  If these stowaways had come from any other country than the Union of Socialist SovietRepublics there would be no difficulty.      Having regard, however, to the  fate which they state,no doubt correctly^ awaits them if they are returned to SovietRussia, the Immigration Officers have endeavoured, in the earliercases, to arrange with the responsible Steamship Companies for
tho removal of the stowaways on one of their boats sailingto some other foreign destination.      As regards the three men  -who arrived at Aberdeen onthe 28th June on the s.s. Hopedene, it has not been possibleto arrange for their shipment to a non-Russian Port because theowners, Messrs. Arthur Stott of Kewcastle, fear that, if theirship returns to Archangel without the etowaways, &quot;the master,and perhaps the ship, will be exposed to proceedings by theSoviet Government, which in the case of the master might involve very serious consequences.  Their apprehension is increased by the fact that the s.s. Hopedene is on time charter to the Soviet Government and they state that, ifthe ship is required by the British authorities to returnto Archangel without the stowaways, they - will look with.M. Government to afford full protection both to the ship and to the master,  Failing such an assurance, they have urgedthat they ought to be allowed to take the stowaways back inthe ship, which sails direct for Archangel on Saturday the12th instanto      I understand the Foreign Office, who?&apos; I have consulted,feel that it is not possible to give any satisfactory guarantee in the sense desired by the owners and that, if the master were dealt with on his return to Archangel on a charge of counterrevoluntionary activities (the penalty for which is death), it&apos;would be very difficult, to represent that he was not being dealt with according to Soviet lav/, or indeed to take any effective action for his protection.      There appear to be only two alternatives:  either togrant the stowaways leave to land and allow them (subject tocondition if necessary) to enter this country or to maintainthe refusal of leave to land and require them to return toRussia o
      The first alternative is open to trie objections that itwould tend to encourage the Soviet prisoners at Archangel toattempt to escape to this country in increasing numbers and thatit would provide an obvious channel by which the Soviet government might introduce secret agents into the United Kingdom.  Furtherif anything untoward happened to the master as a result of th**otowaways not being returned to Archangel it might well lead to an even greater agitation than the return of the stowaways themselves,and might precipitate a demand for the breaking off of diplomaticrelationships.  The second alternative would no doubt lead to criticism on humanitarian grounds both by the advocates of the&quot;right of asylum&quot; and by others who are more concerned to attack the methods of the Soviet Government -      The choice between these two alternatives is a verydifficult one.  On the one hand, I feel that in all quarters ofthe Houss strong resentment would be felt if these men were sentbaok to Russia and it would be represented that the Governmenthad sent them to certain death,,  Sir Alfred Xnox had given noticeof a Question to ask me  whether the men were to be sent back buthe took his question off the paper at my request pending furtherconsideration of the whole matter.  On the other hand to allow the stowaways to remain here may be exposing the master of theship, who is a British subject, to similar perils and it may be argued that our first duty is to safeguard the  interests of ourown nationals,      The considerations involved are not purely departmentaland I should be glad to have the considered view of my colleagues.Personally 1 am inclined to the view that we .should not requirethe stowaways to return to Archangel on Saturday but should grantthem leave to land temporarily pending investigation.  If thiscourse were approved, the circumstances should be explained to theSoviet Authorities and they should be informed to the effect thatthses stowaways claimed to be political refugees.  In view of the traditional policy of this country to give consideration to anyplea of this kind His Majesty1s Government could not refuse
11.7.30their appeal offhand in the absence of  full  knowledge  of  thefacts, and as there was no time to ascertain the  facts,  theGovernment felt that they had no alternative but  to  grant tothese stowaways leave to land temporarily.   His majesty&apos;s government would however be prepared,  on being informed  of thefacts, to consider any representations  which the  SovietGovernment might wish to make.  An official  letter should also  besent, before the ship sails, to the owners of the ship in terms which would make it clear that the master wished  to  remove thestowaways but that His Majesty&apos;s Government  had decided  to.grantthem leave to land temporarily pending investigation of  their claims.                                          Jo R. Go

</content>
</cab>
