<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/213/0 images: 632-640</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.CP.242(30).                                                   Copy  No                   ROUND  TABLE  CONFERENCE.         Composition of the British Delegation:   Question of                    three-Party co-operation.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.          Up to the 12th May last the position, as stated in public utterances, was that &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government would meet both representatives of British India and representativesof the States for the purpose of seeking the greatest possible measure of agreement for the final proposals Talica it wouldlater be the duty of His Majesty&apos;s Government to submit toParliament&apos;&apos;.  Those are the words used in Sir John Simon&apos;sletter of the 15th October last to the Prime Minister, whichis the first public suggestion of the Conference.  These or similar words were used to describe the general purpose of theConference, in the Prime Minister&apos;s reply and in the Viceroy&apos;declaration of the 1st November, and again in the Viceroy&apos;sAddress to the Indian Legislature on the 25th January.  TheConference was to be between representatives of India on theone side and of His Majesty&apos;s Government j?n.the^j?her.          More recently language has been used of a widermeaning.  In his Statement of the 12th May, the Viceroy,speaking principally about other matters, referred to theConference in the following terms - &quot;in order thatGreat Britain and India might collaborate together in finding a solution of our present difficulties.&apos;&apos;   Again Lord Irwinon the 9&apos;th July said &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government simultaneouslyannounced their intention to convene a Conference as widely                                            representative
representative in character as possible, in order t oat,after the submission of the Statutory Commission1s Report,the spokesmen of Great Britain and India might take furthercounsel together upon tlx  measures which His LEa.iesty&apos;s Governmentwould later present to ParliamentLater in the same Speechhe said - &quot;It is the belief of His Majesty&apos;s Government that,by way of the Conferences it should be possible to reachsolutions that both countries and all parties and interests in them can honourably accept, and any such agreement at whichthe Conference is able to arrive will form the basis of proposals which His Majesty&apos;s Government will later submit toParliament.  From such a definition of the scope of theConference it is clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government conceive ofit, not as a mere meeting for discussion and debate, but as ajoint assembly of representatives of. hot^^opjantri^es..on whoseagreement precise proposals to Parliament may be founded&quot;.          These latest utterances afford an opening for thesuggestion which has been made that the Opposition Parties inthis country should be represented at the Conference.   I do not suggest that Lord Irwin&apos;s words formed the occasion for thissuggestion;   indeed ever since the publication of the secondVolume of the Indian Statutory Commission&apos;s Reports the ideahas been promoted in the Press that the Conference should beon a three-Party basis.    The connection between the report and the desire of the Opposition Parties to participate in theConference is clear.  The Opposition Leaders in conversationrecently have made it plain that one, if not the main, objectof their presence at the Conference would be to ensure that,when discussion takes place upon various proposals that might come before the Conference, all points mentioned in the Report                                                          of
                                                            Q2 D                                                           3.of  the  Indian Statutory Commission should b:e brought out in debate.         It is generally admitted on the one hand that, indealing with high questions of Indian policy, it is desirablethat there should be free consultation between the Governmentof  the  day and the Opposition.   On the other hand, sole responsibility for decisions must and always has rested withthe Government.   This general proposition is generally accepted and has been pursued in practice for the last tenyears at least.  The outstanding example of three-Party co-operation is to be found in the composition of the IndianStatutory Commission, &quot;where all Parties of this country co-operated in the great task of that body.  But it must beremembered that the task of that Commission, in which all three Parties co-operated, was no more than consultative.Different considerations have to be borne in mind when weconsider the generally accepted proposition of the desirabilityof  three-Party co-operation, in relation to a Conference whichis  to have a decisive character in so far as upon agreement reached at it the legislative proposals of the Government areto be foundedo          By the Viceroy&apos;s Speech of the 9th July which was approved by His Majesty&apos;s Government, the latter are now pledged to regard the Conference as an assembly of representatives onwhose agreement precise proposals to Parliament may be founded;that is  to say, His Majesty&apos;s Government are pledged to take asthe basis for the legislative proposals which they will beresponsible for placing before Parliament such agreement onall or any of the phases of the Indian constitutional problem as may be reached by the  Conference.          Agreement between whom?  Between the indian representatives on the one side and His Majesty&apos;s Governmenton the other?  Or between &quot;both countries and all Parties                                                    and
 and  interests  in them?&quot;  To this question I think the answer lies  in  the phrase which I have advisedly used in the preceding paragraph  of His Majesty&apos;s Government being responsible for laying the proposals before Parliament.  However well accepted may be the practice of three-Party consultation in Indian affairs, the responsibility for taking action must lie with  the Executive Government of the day;  and therefore I submit that the agreement upon which legislative proposals are to be based noed be agreement between the Indian representatives and His Majesty&apos;s Government only.          But  though His Majesty&apos;s Government would, in my opinion, be evading their responsibility and failing to carry out the  pledge which they have now given through the mouth of the Viceroy if they did not submit to Parliament proposals based on agreement reached between themselves and the Indian representatives, irrespective of the views of other Parties, this  is not to say that there might not be advantages in having representatives of the Opposition Partiesat the Conference;   and this is the more evident when we lookbeyond the Conference stage to the Parliamentary stage which isto follow.    For it i;0 evident that,  if on any particular point,His Majesty&apos;s Government have with difficulty reached agreement with the Indian representatives,  their task in implementing their promise  to endeavour to  carry throughlegislation on such point will be  made very much easier ifrepresentatives of the  Opposition  Parties have been convincedin the course  of the Conference of the  reasonableness of theagreement so  reached.   This,  it appears to  me,  is the obviouspositive advantage  to  India  of the  presence of the  opposition parties  at  the  Conference.          Conversely,  again looking forward to  the  Parliamentarystage, there  is a great disadvantage  to be  seen in leaving  the                                                    Opposition
 Opposition  Parties cut of the Conference. To make this point  clear,  it will help to attempt to give a cursory forecast of  the course  of  the discussions  in the Conference.  On many matters, given a  reasonable amount of goodwill on both sides, adjustment  of  the respective points of view will no doubt be possible.   The real difficulty willbe reached when the Conference  comes  to consider the  constitution of the Indian Central Government.   Setting aside discussion of the precise meaning of such phrases as &quot;Dominion Status&quot; Or &quot;Dominion Status with safeguards&quot; it may be anticipated that, broadly speaking, the  representatives of British India will stand out for a  Central  Executive Government responsible to the Legislature even  though the responsibility of that Governmentmay temporarily be limited in certain branches of administration. As  is well  known  tlx  Statutory Commission has rejected this demand  in a most  uncompromising fashion.          Let  us  suppose that, in a conference in which the Opposition  Parties in this country did not participate. HisMajesty&apos;s Government1s representatives were brought tc the opinion that the  Indian demand on this point ought to beadmitted wholly or in part,  and that, fulfilling its recentpledge, it  undertook to present proposals to Parliament onthis agreed basis.  The Indian representatives would return fromthe Conference flushed with victory in the consciousness ofwhich the extreme  elements in India would be quiet.   But laterif tlx-  Government&apos;s proposals on this point &quot;were rejected byParliament,  the consequences would be disastrous.  For the indians would foel,  not unreasonably,  that they had beentricked.    The extreme  elements would regain their ascendancyand disturbances  even more serious than those  that wereexperienced in 1921  and again at the  present time would                                                 inedtably
 inevitably  result.   If, however,  the Conference contained representatives  of  the  Opposition Parties as well as of His Majesty&apos;s  Groveriiaent, an!  if, as night be expected, the Opposition  representatives wade  it plain at tho Conference that, in regard to the constitution  of  the Indian Central Government, they  stood  by  the Statutory Commission&apos;s Report and did not accept  the  Indian claim, no room would  be left for in is under stand - ing on  ths  Indian side.  If His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s representatives  were convinced by the Indian case they would formulate their  legislative proposals in accordance with their promise;  but  they would do so with the full knowledge of the responsibility which they undertook;  and the Indian representatives would have no excuse for failing to realise that the agreement which had been reached with His Majesty&apos;s Government  at  tho Conference was not the last word but might very well be rejected by Parliament at  the next stage.          fhis,  it appears to me, is the negative advantage in having  the  Opposition Parties in the Conference, or perhaps no should  say,  the positive disadvantage of leaving them out.          A third advantage of having them in tho Conference lies in the opportunity which their presence would afford to educate them as to the intensity of  Indian feeling: in regard  to the  Indian constitutional problem.  In private letters to me.  Lord Irwin has again and again stressed, notmerely  the intensity of this feeling,, but the degree to which it pervades all classes and creeds in India who have any capacity for political  thought at all.    And in recent lettershe has been no  less emphatic an to the  desperate ignorance of this fooling which is displayed by the  Opposition Leaders in this country air1  by the Press which publishes their speeches and their letters.   From this point of view,  therefore,  it                                                        seems
                                                          7. seems  to me  that  a positive advantage would he gained by bringing  into  direct  contact with the exponents of Indian political thought tho Opposition Leaders  in this country on whose  attitude largely depends the  spirit and temper in which the  legislative stage v/ill be taken in parliament hereafter.          In the  telegram, of which I have circulated a copy (C.P.242(al)(30))  I endeavoured on the 11th instant to put the pros and cons  to  Lord Irwin as briefly as misht be.  I have 1* . ..                                    J   ^ ... .1 ....... circulated,  with  my telegram, Lord  Irwin&apos;s reply dated 14-th July.   In general, it will be seen  that he is in favour of the  Oppositions being associated with the Conference in some capacity or  other;  but he is anxious as to the effect on Indian  opinion of any announcement  that the Opposition parties would be represented  at the Conference;   indeed he regards any announcement to this  effect at the  present time as positivelydangerous.   In an earlier telegram,  two months ago, he went so far  as  to say that he thought the inclusion of representatives of the  Opposition Parties (or an announcement as to the intentionto include them)  would have the effect of leading Indians tothird: that this was a device to obstruct their ambitions bypresenting an obstinate all-Party front to Indian hopes.  Tothis opinion the  greatest weight must be attached.          The Indians&apos; fear, of which Lord Irwin is soapprehensive, no  doubt is that, if  it is now announced thatthe&apos;Opposition Parties are to be represented at the Conference, it will be implied that agreement with them has to beachieved as well  as agreement with the representatives of Hismajesty&apos;s Government, before legislative proposals arisingout of the discussions in the Conference can be formulated;and they will be well aware that on many of the  points onwhich they set the greatest store agreement with certain individual Opposition Leaders will be almost hopeless of                                               atta innent.
attainment.  And this fear, if not assuaged, may deterthem from coming to the Conference.          This, broadly, is the great danger of nowannouncing the intention to include Opposition Leaders inthe Conference.          Lord In/in&apos;s argument might be met by the followingsuggestion, which of course would have to be submitted to him for his views.    The plan would be that correspondenceshould be published for the information of Indian opinion to the effect that Opposition Members          (i) were invited to attend the Conference on the    understanding that,  though they would be free to    engage in all discussions, and though their agreement    would be sought, His Majesty&apos;s Government would not    regard it as an essential pre-condition for formulating    their legislative proposals;  that,  in fact,  as Lord    Irwin points out that Indians anticipate,  the agreement    on which His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s  proposals ars  to    be formulated is agreement between Indian representatives    ana His Majesty&apos;s Government with whom the responsibility    rests.         (ii) were accepting the invitation on the    und erst a ncl i ng               (a)  that  they would attend with a  genuine        purpose of co-operating and not,  as some  Indian leaders        are likely to apprehend, for the  purpose  of wrecking        the Conference in advance.  (Obviously the fulfilment        of  any ouch promise depends very  largely  on the        personality of the representatives selected who would        have to be approved persons);               (b)  that  they would support in Parliament any        proposals to implement points  on  which their                                         r e pr e s e nt a t i v e s
         representatives at the Conference were in agreement         with liis Majesty&apos;s government&apos;s and the Indian         delegates.          I should wish also that in accepting the invitationthe Opposition would give an undertaking to accept ths Viceroy&apos;announcement of the 1st November last as to Dominion Statusbeina&apos; the natural issue oi  India&apos;s constitutional progress.This may be too much to expect but it might at least bepossible to induce them themselves to refrain and privatelyrestrain their followers, till the Conference is assembled,from any further attacks on that Declaration - from thesubstance of which they have never dissented.  The Governmentof course would be free to  announce that its policy was asod on those two Declarations made on its behalf.          If the plan outlined above is favourably viewed theViceroy should be consulted immediately as to whetherit would prove dangerous to tho success of the Conference orworsen the situation in India, which shows signs of slightimprovement.                               TT &quot;P                               ii o .15th July 1930.

</content>
</cab>
