<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/213/0 images: 707-710</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS B0CUM23FT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS  ERITAHITIG majesty&apos;J3  GOYEPJMKKT) ._J.GR E T..P. 250  (30) .GOPY HO . j^- SA B I K         AGRICULTURAL POLICY.       The Government have before them two documents,the Minister of AgricultureTs paper on Agricultural Policy,a collection of miscellaneous proposals several, of whichhave been put forward from tine to time during the last3&apos;ear by his predecessor, and the report of the economic advisory Council Committee presided over by Mr. S.D.Simon,M*P,       The contrast between these two papers indicatesso clearly the choice of policj&apos;&quot; .which lies before theGovernment that it is worth while putting the main pointsvery briefly in parallel columnsi-The Minister of Agriculture.(Paper Ifo,CP- 34 (50) )(l) Land to be more freely availablefor cultivation with security of tenure on fair terms.    This means Small Holdings schemescarried out centrally at Stateexpense, including an emergencyscheme for the unemployed for whom theState would have to find workingcapitals  It involves the super-session of local authorities and thepayment by the Exchequer of the wholeloss. 1 million (to begin with) is tobe invested by a Corporation composedof nominees of the Minister  inexperimental large scale farming,equipping farms and small holdings and in advances and credit facilities to tenants and small holders.          Simon Committee.    (Paper No,  0.P.244(50)).   The Committee point out that apart from the fact that part ofthe capital cost is irrecover-able, small holdings do not add to productiveness of landsuffering from low world prices,or increase employment to any marked extent.   They do not provide a remedy for thedepression prevailing in the distressed areas-   The social value of familyfarms is great.(This seems to  Imply that theservice is not  an economicproposition.)   Government should continuethe help which it is alreadygiving so effectively alongmany lines, e.g. research,education etc:   particularly important is economic research into methods of farm manage-cent.-1-
The Minister of-Agriculture.Q iW   Producer to bo emancipated&quot;&apos;Tom present desolatingncertainty as to price both in the hone market and iniompetition, particularly withouhty-fed imports.   For this purpose he is toe given &quot;much needed security&quot;)j all or ;aiy of the following;ethods:-Countervailing; duties..on&quot;  anty-fed.....i^Dorts (if not  iiaxy barredj report Boards (to be put before   Imperial Conference asvolley of the Government)guaranteed Home Market,, for^ereals.-^quota for Tsheat and kaltingBarley and tariff protectionor &quot;staining&quot; for Oats) (5)  Organisation to be developed,n a self-supporting basis,, , Add!son revives the Marketing ill which authorises the reation of subsidised producers&apos;trusts with power to coerceainorlties and to prohibitIndependent trading in specified-ommodities (Milk, Potatoes, troops, Wool, CO 3)reals and Choose)    Simon Committee.    Committee find that morethan half the industry is in asatisfactory condition and a severe depression only affectsabout one-tenth of the whole*There has been no decline inthe total volume of output.    Zl.Jt^MLi*.....aa2ial.j2]^yl.onbe eg cardinal; principle of                         it .isthe .f,5vrso...busineospf. e^Jjiagerto , make, his,, farm&quot;pay in, theSaMMlsoiMtltei.....iOisiamarkets, and measures adoptedby the &quot;State should promote andhot retard economic progress infarming.  There should be nosubsidies or guaranteed prices:any assistance given should bedirected to furthering theadoption of improved methods ofproduction and distribution.Committee  ire divided on thequestion whether any emergencyrelief for certain districts(to he given with last mention-ed object) is now justified,hutthey are agreed that agricul- ture has no better (and no worse) claim to State assistancethan other basic industries.    Organised marketing is ofthe first importance.  large scale  organisations may dovaluable work and in this fieldState help and guidance isparticularly valuable. Someof the Committee think that itmay sometimes he accessary tocoerce a minority but the power should be used sparingly.  TheCommittee clearly attach more importance to reform of farmingmethods than to marketingdevices,,         Tho foregoing comparison makes it clear, I think,that the Minister&apos;s policy is to &apos;offor agriculture, in one form or another, subsidies and protection.   Mr. Simon&apos;sCommittee would adhere to free trade principles for agriculture so long as protection is not given to otherb a si c i ndu strifes;.In
          In addition the Minister proposes that a Billfor the application of unemployment insurance to agricultural workers on special terms should he introduced as soon as possible.   This proposal has never been approved Toy the Cabinet which only authorised theMinister of Labour to discuss the question informallywith employers and employed without communicating any official memorandum and without making it known that thequestion had been considered by the Cabinet,    The scheme would add to the farmer&apos;s costs of production,  and inparticular increase the difficulties of arable  farming inwhich, as the Simon Committee point out, wages  are 40 percent of the cost, and which, they state, &quot;has sufferedmore than any other types of farming by reason  of the risein wages at a time when prices were falling&quot;.   It wouldalso add about another  1 million per annum to  theexisting Exchequer liabilities for unemployment insurance.In view of the present state of public feeling  about theUnemployment&quot; Insurance sjrstem I am sure that it would bea political mistake to embark upon a wide extension of itat this moment.          The remainder of the Minister&apos;s proposals are estimated to cost approximately  1 million in 1931 andover  if millions a year in 1932 and later years, plus 2 millions capital expenditure spread over 1931 and thenext few years,          I would point out that we are already spendingnearly  10 millions a year on Agricultural services(Including Sugar Beet and Forestry) which is an increaseof some.  2 millions on the last estimates of the late government.          While the Economic Advisory Council committee recommend the continuance of State-expenditure  on
research and experiment on the existing scale,  theirreport does not suggest that the remedy for the present difficulties of agriculture is to he found in lavishincreases of Exchequer grants any more than in subsidiesaxid protection.          It would he a mistake to concentrate on thewheat question which is the smallest part of theagricultural problem.   In view of the mast importationof dairy produce, eggs etc., which could be produced at home, it would be far better for the farmer to turn his attention to this aspect of agricultural production.          The question of Import Boards ought to beconsidered on its merits and not merely as a means ofsubsidising the producer..   Ve have not yet had thearguments fully before us and I think that the whole subject should be examined by a special committee of officials who should formulate the material issues sothat the Cabinet may reach a decision.                           (Intd.) P.S.Treasury Chambers,

</content>
</cab>
